<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>solar on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/solar/</link><description>Recent content in solar on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 22:05:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/solar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #239: Embarrassing finitude</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 22:05:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</guid><description> This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.
Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay.
House gets more energy reserves In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three
weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Fiery sunset in Betty&rsquo;s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="house-gets-more-energy-reserves">House gets more energy reserves</h2>
<p>In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium
ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of
the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</p>
<p>The complete stack looks as follows, with the new UP5000 on top, and the two
&ldquo;old&rdquo; US3000 units (3.5kWh each) under it:</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A cluster of lithium ion house batteries." width="400px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A cluster of lithium ion house batteries.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I can already see the positive effect of this on the daily line chart of solar
energy stored: Where previously there were gaps, because the battery was full,
the hot water geysers were either already hot or had not come on yet (in our
house, these act as water batteries on fixed charge times) and we were not
drawing much load, the gaps are smoothed out and the area under the curve is
consistently higher.</p>
<h2 id="dot-dot-dot-while-human-has-to-make-peace-with-limited-energy-reserves">&hellip; while human has to make peace with limited energy reserves</h2>
<p>As a human, you have to deal with a limited amount of energy every day, as if
the fact that your total time on earth was embarrassingly finite was not
challenging enough.</p>
<p>In other words, during one&rsquo;s waking hours, of which one gets a limited number,
one can&rsquo;t rely on operating at the highest energy output all of the time.</p>
<p>As far as I can surmise, one can increase one&rsquo;s daily energy through the
consistent and continuous application of positive lifestyle choices.</p>
<p>This can be hard work, and due to the infernal complexity of organics (have you
looked at a <a href="http://biochemical-pathways.com/">map of metabolic pathways recently</a>? &ndash; you should really go take a
look, it&rsquo;s complicated but also really interesting) and the effects of aging
maybe even an intractable problem, and as if that&rsquo;s not enough, the right
lifestyle can be extremely boring (to those around you).</p>
<p>My mornings usually start pretty nicely, but by the middle of the afternoon my
brain starts disassembling itself anywhere from just after lunch to later in
the afternoon.</p>
<p>What I have recently started noticing, is that when I enjoy one of those highly
productive days with focus straying sharp until late in the afternoon, I pretty
much have to tone it down a bit the next day.</p>
<p>I can still do good work, but I do need to approach the day in a slightly more
relaxed fashion in order to make it through the whole thing in one piece, and
to increase the chances of having a highly productive day after the toned down
one.</p>
<h2 id="the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">The rickety raft of life directions and priorities</h2>
<p>Staying on the theme of limited energy, but taking many steps back from the
cyclical alternate day grinding effect, I&rsquo;ve had to make peace with another
phenomenon:</p>
<p>Again thanks to embarrassingly limited energy, one can only focus on a subset
of one&rsquo;s life directions and priorities at any one time.</p>
<p>For example, when your children are younger, it&rsquo;s normal to dedicate a
substantial chunk of your time to them.</p>
<p>Between that and the necessary parts of work, not much time is left for one&rsquo;s
own hobbies, like Trying To Be a Better Human, or for other worthy goals, like
writing that novel(la) (short story, err or maybe just a nice haiku).</p>
<p>Conversely, when you&rsquo;re training for an important cycle race (not me, a
friend), some of those other dimensions by definition spend time on the
dimensional back burner.</p>
<p>So while you probably have a longer list of priorities which are all very
important to you, you have no choice but to make peace with the fact that at
any one point in time, you can only deal with a fairly narrow subset.</p>
<p>To me it looks the most important to make peace with this fact, and to treat it
as a deliberate and honest choice.</p>
<p>Oh and don&rsquo;t flip flop too much. (that&rsquo;s meant for me)</p>
<h2 id="young-human-wise-beyond-her-years">Young human wise beyond her years</h2>
<p><a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU#1</a> and I were chatting in the car, on way back from one of her social
commitments.</p>
<p>We talked about sleep. (Had she gotten enough?)</p>
<p>She mentioned people that get by on six hours per night and seem to get more
done&hellip;</p>
<p>As I was preparing to attempt commenting Socratically about this, she
pre-empted me by volunteering that when she sleeps well, and for much longer
than six hours, she experiences that she is better with other humans, and that
she feels emotions more intensely.</p>
<p>Goodness!</p>
<h2 id="two-pages-per-week">Two pages per week</h2>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. on the topic of GOU #1 and how best to spend my puny energy:</p>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/#gou-1-reveals-her-plans-and-makes-us-think--more">WHV #194</a> when GOU #1 revealed her cunning plan for
completing a PhD, part of which was writing only 136 words a day for a year,
leaving the two sandwich years for respectively planning and proofreading,
leading to a perfect thesis.</p>
<p>In the recent <a href="https://lexfridman.com/tim-urban/">Lex Fridman podcast #264 with Tim Urban</a>, he of <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/">Wait but why</a> fame,
they start <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Jd7fJgFkPU&amp;t=7166s">talking in-depth about procrastination at the 2 hour mark</a>. (relax,
you can listen to it later. <strong>&lt;ba dum tiss!&gt;</strong>)</p>
<p>(Urban considers himself a procrastinator, but he is a deep thinker, and so this
is a pretty interesting bit of conversation.)</p>
<p>He starts off with the example of a writer who is able to commit to producing
only two pages <em>per week</em>, and by consistently hitting this pretty modest
sounding goal, is able to prepare a book per year.</p>
<p>Glossing over the fact that 200 pages is perhaps not a very <em>impressive</em> book, at
least in terms of girth, publishing one every two years would be frankly
amazing.</p>
<p>He then talks about this idea of being able to attain something substantial and
worthwile by consistently chipping away.</p>
<p>He is clearly searching for the right word,
<a href="https://youtu.be/0Jd7fJgFkPU?t=7203">but then comes up with <em>compiling</em></a>.</p>
<p>I would really like to think that he was in fact searching for our old friend
<a href="/tags/compounding"><em>compounding</em></a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #201: Sunny anniversary</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 10:12:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/</guid><description> I could feel this one almost slipping through to the two week group, but then I thought to myself: It feels like I have nothing to write about, but future me will probably still want to know what sort of nothing exactly happened in that week.
The 201st edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the week from Moday July 20 to Sunday July 26, 2020, which since last week I&amp;rsquo;m calling Cray-cray 20.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="la_mountain_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/la_mountain_pano_huf95566e1297f83153e178c9a2f08e1bb_1060884_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/la_mountain_pano_huf95566e1297f83153e178c9a2f08e1bb_1060884_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/la_mountain_pano_huf95566e1297f83153e178c9a2f08e1bb_1060884_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/la_mountain_pano_huf95566e1297f83153e178c9a2f08e1bb_1060884_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/la_mountain_pano_huf95566e1297f83153e178c9a2f08e1bb_1060884_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I could feel this one almost slipping through to the two week group, but then I
thought to myself: It feels like I have nothing to write about, but future me
will probably still want to know what <em>sort</em> of nothing exactly happened in
that week.</p>
<p>The 201st edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the week from Moday
July 20 to Sunday July 26, 2020, which since last week I&rsquo;m calling
Cray-cray 20.</p>
<h2 id="solar-power-birthday">Solar Power Birthday</h2>
<p>You might recall that we <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">solar powered our house at the end of June last year</a>,
but that there were still some teething problems (read: almost bricked the
inverter) which <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/#bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">we had solved by July 25</a>, almost exactly a year ago!</p>
<p>That means&hellip;</p>
<p><em>HAPPY BIRTHDAY DEAR SOLAR POWER AT MY HOUSE HAPPY BIRTHDAY TO YOU WE LOVE YOU!</em></p>








<figure><a href="goodwe_sems_sample_20200728.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/goodwe_sems_sample_20200728_hu35d0223f8e68ff6d32894f184e2e6abf_38291_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/goodwe_sems_sample_20200728.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Solar production today (2020-07-18, a sunny winter&amp;rsquo;s day) was 24.4kWh and total production since commissioning just under 8MWh. Cost saving is an estimate." width="300"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Solar production today (2020-07-18, a sunny winter&rsquo;s day) was 24.4kWh and total production since commissioning just under 8MWh. Cost saving is an estimate.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The app reports that since commissioning we have generated and used almost 8
MWh of solar power, which makes me happy.</p>
<p>What makes me even happier, is that the whole system has been essentially
maintenance free this whole time.</p>
<p>The only action I perform, is to switch the inverter to back-up mode when we&rsquo;re
in load-shedding season, which means that it prioritises keeping the lithium
ion batteries full.</p>
<p>When we&rsquo;re not load-shedding seasion, it&rsquo;s in normal mode, meaning it
prioritises using as little grid power as possible, which in the summer months
is quite close to nothing.</p>
<p>P.S. For our viewing pleasure, I just looked up the monthly generation for the
past 12 months, in order to be able to see the seasonal variation. It looks
like this:</p>








<figure><a href="goodwe_monthly_generation_202007.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/goodwe_monthly_generation_202007_huc6f7a551d8f2e84dcd203e589430f9b5_118019_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/goodwe_monthly_generation_202007_huc6f7a551d8f2e84dcd203e589430f9b5_118019_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/goodwe_monthly_generation_202007_huc6f7a551d8f2e84dcd203e589430f9b5_118019_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/goodwe_monthly_generation_202007_huc6f7a551d8f2e84dcd203e589430f9b5_118019_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/29/weekly-head-voices-201-sunny-anniversary/goodwe_monthly_generation_202007_huc6f7a551d8f2e84dcd203e589430f9b5_118019_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>While July has been <strong>really</strong> good sun-wise (thanks Cape winter, you&rsquo;re a
star!), we will probably be entering the 600kWh+/month zone soon.</p>
<p>That dip last December is probably because we were away from home for a
while. The February dip is of course because it&rsquo;s a few days shorter than most
months, which in February can easily amount to 30kWh per day.</p>
<h2 id="nerdy-posts-over-on-vxlabs">Nerdy posts over on vxlabs</h2>
<p>Whilst working with the brand new Microsoft Pylance Python language server for
Visual Studio Code, I figured out how to make some red squiggly lines yellow
and wrote a whole blog post about it: <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/07/23/vscode-pylance-type-mismatch-warning/">Set severity override of Visual Studio
Code Pylance type mismatches for better visual distinction</a></p>
<p>Besides the subject of the post, it was interesting to check how low the
barrier between my internal notes and publishing a blog post had become since I
started using ox-hugo.</p>
<p>The screenshots in the post meant I had to do some manual <code>attachment:</code>
link-wrangling, and so I wrote an Emacs function to fix that.</p>
<p>In a slightly meta fashion, I then pushed my notes about that new function to
another blog post titled: <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/07/25/emacs-lisp-function-convert-attachment-to-file/">An Emacs Lisp function to convert attachment: links
to file: links for ox-hugo exports</a></p>
<p>Ironically, that blog post itself did not contain a single screenshot.</p>
<p>Somewhere in-between I tweaked the fonts on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>It surprised me what a difference such a small change can make.</li>
<li>With the new <a href="https://gohugo.io/hugo-pipes/">Hugo pipes</a> it has become straight-forward to modify source SCSS
(for example) and then have the hugo build server automatically rebuild the
resultant CSS while you work. Kudos to the authors!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="microsoft-helps-to-break-nvidia-s-stranglehold-on-deep-learning-hardware">Microsoft helps to break NVIDIA&rsquo;s stranglehold on deep learning hardware</h2>
<p>What I realised only the other day, is that Microsoft&rsquo;s recent work on <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/directx/directx-heart-linux/">porting
TensorFlow to run on their DirectML stack</a> has magically enabled AMD and even
Intel GPUs to be used to accelerate deep learning training and inference.</p>
<p>If you look at this <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/DirectML/issues/21">DirectML github issue</a>, you&rsquo;ll see that it&rsquo;s still early
days as performance is not what it should be, but peeps are almost routinely
accelerating their deep learning workloads using AMD GPUs, something which up
to now has been almost impossibly impractical.</p>
<p>To reiterate: Microsoft has made it straight-forward for any GPU manufacturer
to support deep learning, by simply implementing DirectML support. NVIDIA on
the other hand was really happy with their fully proprietary CUDA platform and
its dominance in the deep learning world.</p>
<p>What a strange world we live in.</p>
<p>The Microsoft of 2020 has built up a track record over the past years of doing
truly positive stuff.</p>
<p>I approve.</p>
<h2 id="living-in-the-future">Living in the future</h2>
<p>Thanks to the internet, I was just able to find the source of a remembered adage.</p>
<p>The source is <a href="http://paulgraham.com/startupideas.html">Paul Graham&rsquo;s essay How to Get Startup Ideas</a>, and the adage is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Live in the future, then build what&rsquo;s missing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It&rsquo;s going quite well with the company. We have products, we have (slowly)
growing traction in the market, and we have a great team.</p>
<p>However, just like any other company, we have to work hard at getting more traction.</p>
<p>There are direct ways to increase traction (SELL MORE WIDGETS!), but as an
engineer I also tend to look at the product side.</p>
<p>We have started work on a really exciting new feature, which is a natural
extension of what <a href="https://www.telesensi.com/">TeleSensi</a> already does and which there is already a market
for, that in my mind also falls squarely into the class of things that people
in the future (5 year horizon) are going to need a whole lot more of.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s my inner engineer talking.</p>
<p>My inner scientist has pointedly asked to &ldquo;show him the data&rdquo;.</p>
<p>How does one solve this conundrum?</p>
<p>To build a truly successful product, it seems you have to take a chance on an
idea that&rsquo;s going to be huge in the future.</p>
<p>By definition, we can&rsquo;t measure there.</p>
<p>You can only measure now, then lick and hold up your finger to determine the
current wind direction, and finally muster up all of your cognitive biases to
make that call.</p>
<p>And then&hellip;</p>
<p><em>You&rsquo;ve got to ask yourself one question: &ldquo;Do I feel lucky?&rdquo;</em></p>
<p><em>Well, do you, punk?</em></p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #186: Helderberg 20.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 16:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/</guid><description> Friends, it is with great pleasure that I welcome you back here to the Weekly Head Voices!
The passing of time usually seems to be quite a theoretical affair, but at this moment I can really feel the year taking its last few breaths.
(People even seem to think of this as the last year of the decade, which makes it all the more dramatic, but not everyone is convinced. If the first day of the first year was January 1, year 1, the end of the first year was December 31, year 1, and the end of that first decade was on December 31, year 10.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Friends, it is with great pleasure that I welcome you back here to the Weekly
Head Voices!</p>
<p>The passing of time usually seems to be quite a theoretical affair, but at this
moment I can really feel the year taking its last few breaths.</p>
<p>(People even seem to think of this as the last year of the decade, which makes
it all the more dramatic, but <a href="https://www.withum.com/resources/end-of-the-decade/">not everyone is
convinced</a>. If the first
day of the first year was January 1, year 1, the end of the first year was
December 31, year 1, and the end of that first decade was on December 31,
year 10. By this reasoning, the end of the current decade is still more than a
year away, on December 31, 2020. Yes, the calendar has changed drastically over the years, but the principle of when decades start and end is the same.)</p>
<p>Anyways, one thing I am only slightly more sure about is that this edition of
the WHV Monday looks back on the days from Monday December 9 to Sunday December
15, 2019!</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
<p>There&rsquo;s a buck (a sort of goat), probably of the duiker variety, really showing
off its camouflage on one of the ledges in this photo taken along the West Peak
/ Woody&rsquo;s Walk route on Helderberg mountain. See if you can find it!</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="we-are-load-shedding-again">We are load shedding again.</h2>
<p>So yeah, there&rsquo;s that.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re load shedding again.</p>
<p>Everything I wrote &ldquo;<a href="/2019/03/24/weekly-head-voices-166-morgan-bay/#on-being-powerless">on being
powerless</a>&rdquo;
in March of this year is again happening, down to me spending more time on
Twitter again (DANG IT) searching for voices that might indicate justice
eventually being served.</p>
<p>In spite of the fact that our home is now more or less load-shedding-proof due
to it being for the largest part <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">solar
powered</a> this time
around, the rotating power outages (we had a week or two of stage 4, i.e. 3 x
2.5 hour outages per day, and one evening of escalation to stage 6) are an
upsetting reminder of the decades-long and now continuing incompetence and
corruption of the country&rsquo;s leadership.</p>
<p>Apart from the numerous mental cycles this phenomenon has been <em>stealing</em> (see
what I did there) from my work focus, it is hard not to notice how businesses,
colleagues and friends are being hit by this.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s perhaps new this time, is that <a href="https://www.timeslive.co.za/politics/2019-10-29-eskom-board-member-slams-interference-says-there-should-be-load-shedding/">it has been confirmed by an Eskom board
member</a>
that the same politicians who have caused this mess, are <em>still</em> meddling in
technical affairs they have no idea about, for all of the wrong reasons.</p>
<p>To put it quite bluntly, instead of trying to address the almost insurmountable
technical problems at the electricity supplier, it seems that the ruling party
(the ANC of course) for example insisted that the electricity be kept on at all
costs during the elections.</p>
<p>Numerous incidences of this sort of interference helped them to save face over
the years, at the cost of further debilitating the already fragile South
African economy.</p>
<p>At this moment, as large parts of industry are shutting down for the Christmas
period, we are enjoying a respite from load shedding.</p>
<p>We will see what happens in the new year.</p>
<p>The board member quoted above stated that if meddling had not been such a
concern, and they could face the technical problems head-on, we were looking at
at least 8 months of load shedding.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m sure that the people would be able to deal with it if those cards were
simply laid on the table, without all of the political meddling and backroom
dealings.</p>
<p>As was the case the previous time, I do remain hopeful that the number of
spines in power grows, and that the electricity provider is able to focus all
of its energy on addressing the significant problems that it faces.</p>
<h2 id="time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">Time-restricted Eating (TRE) with Black Coffee please.</h2>
<p>I think it was Reader K who introduced me to the idea of time-restricted
eating, or TRE, a year or two ago.</p>
<p>(Together we tried to figure out on which medium this happened, because under
normal circumstances I would have wanted to look up the exact time and contents
of the messages.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, we discovered that it must have been via Facebook Messenger, and
somewhere between then and now Reader K had expunged their whole Facebook
history.</p>
<p>I think there&rsquo;s a lesson in here somewhere, but we have to forge ahead, so
we&rsquo;re going to have to side-step it.)</p>
<p>Time-restricted eating, or TRE, is a sort of intermittent fasting where the
eating window is deliberately limited to an as short as possible duration
during the daytime.</p>
<p>The theory behind it is that our metabolism is in fact also ruled by the
all-powerful circadian clock.</p>
<p>During our long evolution, we would have been foraging and feeding during
daylight, and resting during the night.</p>
<p>With artificial light and the ubiquitousness of food of modern times, we easily
fall into the habit of starting to eat when we wake up, and having the last
snack shortly before going to sleep, hours after sunset.</p>
<p>In short, we really do eat too much, and to make it even worse, we eat at all
the wrong times.</p>
<p>With research around TRE, science, as is its wont, is showing us the way back
to redemption.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s starting to look like limiting one&rsquo;s feeding window to a few hours during
daylight could have a number of health advantages.</p>
<p>See for example:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4255155/">Time-restricted feeding is a preventative and therapeutic intervention
against diverse nutritional
challenges</a> - a 2014
Cell Biology study with mice.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/12/191205141731.htm">Clinical study finds eating within 10-hour window may help stave off
diabetes, heart
disease</a> - a 2019 Science Daily summary.</li>
<li><a href="https://m2performancenutrition.com/blog/can-time-restricted-feeding-make-you-fitter">Can time restricted feeding make you
fitter</a> -
a reasonable overview.</li>
</ul>
<p>After a debate with friend LM about whether black sugarless coffee constituted
a break of the TRE fast (I thought that it did due to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m6KClPkotxM">this conversation
between Rhonda Patrick and Joe
Rogan</a>, friend LM did not, so I
initially did not even try TRE because I am unable to operate without black
coffee in the mornings), I have been dipping my toes in the TRE pool.</p>
<p>I have never been a breakfast person (&ldquo;Breakfast is the most important meal of
the day&rdquo; ??! TRUST NO ONE.), so sticking to black coffee in the mornings until
as late as possible, which is in many cases lunch, and not eating anything
after dark, has subjectively worked out pretty well so far.</p>
<p>Sometimes, shortly before lunch, there seems to be a slight delusional quality
to my seemingly enhanced mental clarity, but let&rsquo;s keep that between you and
me.</p>
<h2 id="anniversary-walk-up-the-mountain">Anniversary walk up the mountain.</h2>
<p>Recently, my life partner and I celebrated two decades of official
togetherness by walking up the Helderberg mountain.</p>
<p>We did not quite make West Peak, and we were pretty bushed by the end, but
that&rsquo;s ok. The scenery was epic, and getting back home was brilliant.</p>
<p>We will try again in 2029.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
<p>All by itself, Google&rsquo;s AI stitched together a bunch of my photos of the
Helderberg hike to make this lovely panorama. It&rsquo;s better than the panorama I
made by myself, so I&rsquo;m giving you this one. Click for higher resolution.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #181: The Slow Ones.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 19:47:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/</guid><description> Welcome back everyone!
This edition of the WHV, #181, looks back at the period of time from Monday October 7 to Sunday October 13, 2019.
Compulsory running shot: Looking at Gordon's Bay from the Strand. This was on Thursday. I squeezed in another short run on Friday, which my legs definitely did not appreciate. Note to self: Laziness earlier in the week leads to skipped rest days and sore legs later.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>This edition of the WHV, #181, looks back at the period of time from Monday
October 7 to Sunday October 13, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_2256592_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_2256592_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_2256592_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_2256592_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_2256592_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Compulsory running shot: Looking at Gordon's Bay from the Strand. This was on
Thursday. I squeezed in another short run on Friday, which my legs definitely
did not appreciate. Note to self: Laziness earlier in the week leads to skipped
rest days and sore legs later. (cf. "A stitch in time saves nine." Also
cf. Always Be Compounding.)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="alternative-whv-notification-modalities">Alternative WHV notification modalities.</h2>
<p>Shortly after publishing WHV #180, I decided (bolstered by the advice of my,
err, advisor) to return to announcing new WHVs on Facebook and perhaps even on
Twitter, in spite of
<a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#twifraf-progress-report">TwiFRaF-YT</a>.</p>
<p>For the past months, the only place where you could opt in to be notified of
new WHVs was on the mailing list. (Well, that and RSS, which seems to be
becoming more niche with every passing day.)</p>
<p>Although the mailing list works for a number of people, I am interested in
adding other options that would make sense for WHV readers.</p>
<p>Readers, where else would be a good place to keep you up to date about new WHV
posts, should you like to be kept up to date?</p>
<h2 id="what-i-did-in-week-41">What I did in week 41.</h2>
<p>This was a great week for social events.</p>
<p>It was not the best week for avoiding amazing craft beer and even more amazing
wine.</p>
<p>(I knew what I was getting into when the week started. I committed to it.)</p>
<p>On Tuesday evening, I really enjoyed our local Helderberg business and nerdery
meetup.</p>
<p>Two &ldquo;lightning&rdquo; talks were given: The first on getting your podcasting game on
(microphones, syndication, oh my!), and the second on personal knowledge
management, based on the recently published <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">note-taking post on this
blog</a>.</p>
<p>Craft beer was enjoyed.</p>
<p>The next day, at a regular(ish) Top Secret Business Meeting (at the Thirsty
Scarecrow), I made use of the opportunity to drink my favourite IPA of all time
(so far), a beer which goes by the name of WARLORD, and a beer that has been
<a href="/2018/03/18/weekly-head-voices-136-slightly-more-than-nothing-much/#new-beer-warlord">documented before on these
pages</a>.</p>
<p>As the tasting ceremony started, I was greeted by this portentous sign:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu8547bac2bf22040485a698e616ed2557_2139205_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu8547bac2bf22040485a698e616ed2557_2139205_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu8547bac2bf22040485a698e616ed2557_2139205_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu8547bac2bf22040485a698e616ed2557_2139205_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu8547bac2bf22040485a698e616ed2557_2139205_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The name is BONECRUSHER, WARLORD BONECRUSHER.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Coincidence? I think not.</p>
<p>On Friday, we had lunch with friends from the Netherlands at the newly
re-opened Long Table restaurant at Haskell Winery.</p>
<p>The view from one&rsquo;s lunch table looked something like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_4319041_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_4319041_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_4319041_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_4319041_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu75e13b317c3046d4c0a670365b52da6d_4319041_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
For a whole while before the guests arrived and before I took this photo I just
sat there drinking in the view with my own eyes, like a crazy person.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>As if that was not enough, we had the exquisite pleasure of making the
acquaintance of the Haskell Anvil 2018, probably the best Chardonnay I have
ever tasted.</p>
<h3 id="running-with-fluids-and-fuel-1210-going-to-do-again">Running with fluids and fuel. 12/10 going to do again.</h3>
<p>On Sunday, I went out on a long run, partly to atone for my sins but mostly just
because I really like going on long runs.</p>
<p>What was special about this run, is that I took along extra fluids for the
first time ever.</p>
<p>Weekend runs these days are mostly longer than an hour.</p>
<p>After an hour of running on a sunny day down here, one loses quite an amount of
moisture. If this moisture is not replenished, one&rsquo;s running equipment starts
to malfunction.</p>
<p>To prevent this situation, I recently acquired a <a href="https://runnerclick.com/camelbak-circuit-vest-review/">Camelbak Circuit 1.5l
Hydration vest</a>.</p>
<p>On Sunday, I took this vest out for its maiden voyage. It had about a litre of
Game (local cheap isotonic drink) in the bladder, and two bananas stuffed in
the front pockets.</p>
<p>Subjectively, the run went better than usual and I was able to increase my
distance by a little, but gratifying, bit.</p>
<p>However, next time I&rsquo;m filling that bladder to capacity.</p>
<p>The angst-inducing sound which that thing makes when you suck out the last few
drops of drink with some distance still left to go is not something I want to
hear again soon.</p>
<h2 id="solar">Solar</h2>
<p>For the first time since <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">our house was
solarized</a>, this
thing happened on Saturday morning at 7:18:</p>
<figure style="width: 400px;">














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24.png">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24_huc0e0be8262e3fdc02622910aa5b89973_156000_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w
  
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24.png"
  

   />

</a>

</figure>
<p>The house&rsquo;s batteries were still at 24%, but the sun was already high enough to
meet our modest energy demands at that point.</p>
<p>In other words, for the first time, we had stored enough solar power the
previous day to get us 100% through the night and back into solar, without us
having to dip into the grid.</p>
<p>(The inverter is programmed not to let the lithium batteries discharge below
20%, in order to further increase their lifespan. When there&rsquo;s a real power
outage, it will go down to 10%.)</p>
<p>This should happen more often now that the days are getting longer.</p>
<p>I derive a <em>substantial</em> amount of pleasure from every single kilowatt-hour of
sunbeam-powered electricity that we generate and use.</p>
<h2 id="first-rule-of-blogging-you-dont-blog-about-blogging">First rule of blogging: You don&rsquo;t blog about blogging.</h2>
<p>According to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/oct/12/blogging-twenty-five-years-old-all-grown-up">this Guardian
article</a>,
blogging turned 25 on Monday, October 7, 2019.</p>
<p>They define the start of blogging as the birth of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Winer">Dave
Winer&rsquo;s</a> first blog post in 1994. It
turns out that Winer has posted to his blog on every single day since that very
first year.</p>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/QFKtHSlaMVI">RESTECP!</a></p>
<p>I like how the Guardian article juxtaposes blogging with modern social media.</p>
<p>Of course the truth is more complicated, but generally blogging is more about
the content, and the reasoning, albeit just as opinionated, behind it, whereas
social media is all about emotion-driven <em>engagement</em> and extremely short-term
gratification-analogues of some kind or another.</p>
<h2 id="the-slow-ones">The Slow Ones.</h2>
<p>Complementing <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">ABC</a>, I
feel another (old) theme brewing amongst the voices&hellip;</p>
<p>Deliberate, deep and slow thinking and doing, is an additional antidote to the
all-encompassing AI-optimised immediate gratification information environment
that we live in, and to humankind&rsquo;s concomitant addiction to all that is
instant.</p>
<p>In a science fiction world, we&rsquo;re going to end up with yet another
schism between humans.</p>
<p>There will be those who will hold conversations with ten others at the same
time, data streams coming in from twenty more sources in the background,
processing-processing-processing.</p>
<p>There will be a far smaller group of folks who still command the almost
forgotten art of focusing intently on a single thing for hours on end, without
swiping in any direction.</p>
<p>Communication between the two groups will become increasingly difficult.</p>
<p>Will this remain the stuff of fiction?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #174: Row row row your boat.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2019 08:33:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/</guid><description> The view through one of the old windows of Cucina di Giovanni in Paarl on a brilliant winter afternoon. The symbolism of this will hopefully shine through soon. Hello friends.
Although these Weekly Head Voices look back at the week from Monday July 15 to Sunday July 21, it is already Wednesday, July 24, as I write this.
As is usually the case this time of the year, I access the below visualization perhaps a tad too often:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="view_from_giovannis_paarl.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
The view through one of the old windows of Cucina di Giovanni in Paarl on a brilliant winter afternoon. The symbolism of this will hopefully shine through soon.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Hello friends.</p>
<p>Although these Weekly Head Voices look back at the week from Monday July 15 to
Sunday July 21, it is already Wednesday, July 24, as I write this.</p>
<p>As is usually the case this time of the year, I access the below visualization
perhaps a tad too often:</p>
<a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-africa/cape-town?month=7&year=2019">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu7b457eb91d598aa5b697ea92f5e0f54b_43837_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu7b457eb91d598aa5b697ea92f5e0f54b_43837_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu7b457eb91d598aa5b697ea92f5e0f54b_43837_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu7b457eb91d598aa5b697ea92f5e0f54b_43837_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
  

   />



</a>
<p>Although it&rsquo;s grey and cold and rainy down here at the moment, I console myself
with the fact that the days are slowly but surely getting longer again, minute
by minute.</p>
<p>Starting from the depths of the Winter Solstice on June 21, when there were 9
hours and 53 minutes of daylight, today that had already stretched to a period
of 10 hours and 16 minutes.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re slowly making our way to 14 hours and 25 minutes of daylight on December
22, the Summer Solstice.</p>
<p>Although I do try to savour every moment, I can&rsquo;t help but look forward to the
warmth.</p>
<p>Anyways, the rest of this post exploded into a solid dollop of backyard
philosophy, which I hope you enjoy.</p>
<h2 id="bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Bullet List of Miscellany (BLoM).</h2>
<p>Before we dig in to the promised solid dollop, let&rsquo;s warm up with a BLoM.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Last week I
reported</a>
that we had half-bricked the solar inverter with a firmware upgrade. Shortly
after that, with some help from local support, we reflashed everything from
scratch (note: Although the manual says NOT to use EzFlash for GW5048-ES
inverters shipped after March, you in fact have to use EzFlash in this case)
and, lo and behold, the inverter was resurrected!
<ul>
<li>With BMS (battery management system) communication online, the system works
like a charm. Record solar consumption so far is 24.1 kWh, which is great for
winter!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>My favourite (and only) TPN (Tall Philosophical Neighbour) alerted me to the
fact that images were positively ginormous in the email version of this
blog. I&rsquo;ve fine-tuned the Hugo image-resizing shortcode to do a better job.</li>
<li>After a discussion with a friend from work about kindness, I came across this
post I wrote five (5) years ago: <a href="/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/">Weekly Head Voices #81 - Middle-aged
zen</a>. For me it was worth
reading again. (Also, the person who wrote that seems to be more advanced
than I currently am. Life is circles.)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="life-is-but-a-dream">Life is but a dream.</h2>
<p>I would like to take you on a little trip.</p>
<p>Please imagine an extremely dark room.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;re stuck in this room.</p>
<p>Fortunately there are two really small holes in the thick black walls through
which light shines in. If you get up and peak out through the holes, you can
make out what&rsquo;s going on outside of the room.</p>
<p>There are two more holes through which you can hear sounds from the outside
world, if you put your ears up to them.</p>
<p>Every day, someone shoves food in through yet another small hole.</p>
<p>At least you won&rsquo;t go hungry.</p>
<p>However, if you have to be honest, this room, your jail, is still really
dark and really lonely.</p>
<p>After some time, you discover, behind a really heavy floor tile, a number of
levers.</p>
<p>Using these levers, you are able to make the room rock to and fro.</p>
<p>After some months of practice, you learn how to rock the room more
consistently, and move it in a certain direction.</p>
<p>When you do this, the rays of light coming in through the two pinprick holes
change in interesting ways.</p>
<p>Very slowly, over a period of years, you start figuring out that the rays of
light coming in through the two holes, and the sounds coming in through the
other holes, are often caused by other prisoners, all trapped in cells similar
to yours.</p>
<p>You start making <em>contact</em>.</p>
<h3 id="real-time-reality-synthesis">Real-time reality synthesis.</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to tell this story without giving it away of course.</p>
<p>Your brain is in fact trapped in a bony cage.</p>
<p>It has two slimy nerve bundles slithering out through two holes in your
skull. The ends of those nerve bundles are sensitive to photons falling on them
(light), and send electrical signals back along their bodies when this happens.</p>
<p>Your brain has more slimy nerve bundles connected to your ears.</p>
<p>Sound waves hitting your eardrums via a chain of contact end up as vibrations
in the fluid inside your cochleae, where another set of nerve endings are
stimulated and send more electrical signals back along their bodies.</p>
<p>Your whole body is criss-crossed by more of these bundles of super long
neurons.</p>
<p>Trapped in its terribly dark bony cage, your brain is a slimy mass that absorbs
all of the electrical signals coming back from your eyes, your ears, and the
rest of your nervous system.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s really not that much coming in folks.</p>
<p>However, somehow, somewhere inside of that slimy mass, &ldquo;you&rdquo; experience all of
this as a multi-coloured, high definition, surround-sound, smell-&lsquo;o-vision,
multi-million dollar 3D Hollywood movie.</p>
<p>When I look at the imbalance between the real-time sensory data coming in on
the one hand, and the incredible richness of the experience on the other, and
bolstered slightly by what I know about the human sensory system, I come to the
conclusion that the multi-million dollar experience is a result of an almost
perpetual hallucination.</p>
<p>In other words, the reality that we experience while awake is <em>seeded</em> by our
senses, but a large part of its verdant richness is synthesised, in real-time,
by our amazing brains.</p>
<p>Thinking about it this way, it is not so surprising that we are apparently able
to synthesise whole realities while we dream, including people, environments,
conversations, relationships and experiences, all in apparent real-time.</p>
<h3 id="ps-its-the-music">P.S. It&rsquo;s the music.</h3>
<p>This whole story came up in a conversation I recently had with my partner.</p>
<p>I was trying to explain that I easily get lost in thought with the right
music.</p>
<p>Heck, when I go running (for realz), I sometimes get utterly lost in my
imagination, and it&rsquo;s quite a visual, even multi-sensory affair.</p>
<p>During that conversation, I had the insight that when this happens (i.e. I get
lost in thought), it&rsquo;s only some of the lower bandwidth sensory feeds that are
suppressed and/or slightly disrupted, for example by the right music, enabling
the super deluxe reality synthesis equipment in my brain to do what it normally
does, only slightly less constrained by outside stimuli.</p>
<p>Taking this one step further, although one might be permanently hallucinating,
one does have some control over the balance between incoming feeds and internal
simulation.</p>
<p>In <a href="/2018/02/04/weekly-head-voices-130-2-direct-experience-dopamine/#your-brain-at-work-part-2-dopamine-and-more-mindfulness">direct experience
mode</a>,
one shifts more bandwidth to the incoming feeds.</p>
<p>(Internal simulation still has to fill in the multitude of blanks.)</p>
<p>Then, when one&rsquo;s imagination takes flight, incoming feeds are turned down
somewhat, enabling internal simulation to take over.</p>
<h2 id="row-row-row-your-boat">Row, row, row your boat.</h2>
<p>I wish you an amazing week, and I look forward to when we meet again.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #173: I know.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</guid><description> Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm still quite bad. Let&amp;rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:
Well hello there folks!
A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not have much to report on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="helderberg_protea.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By
the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm
still quite bad.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:</p>
<p>Well hello there folks!</p>
<p>A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not
have much to report on.</p>
<p>However, it&rsquo;s funny how these things go. One week nothing&hellip; Then it&rsquo;s just a
single week later and there&rsquo;s almost a bit too much that I would like to talk
about.</p>
<p>It seems to have been a mix of more writing, but also just more doing.</p>
<p>So, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 1 to Sunday July 14, 2019, I
would like to present the following notes.</p>
<h2 id="bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Bullet List of Miscellany (BLoM).</h2>
<ul>
<li>GOU#1, age 13, is on a week-long school trip in a different time zone
(GMT+8). I am super happy that she can have this experience, but durnit, one
misses one&rsquo;s genetic offspring units dearly!</li>
<li>Remember that I told you about our <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">solar inverter not talking to the
battery&rsquo;s BMS</a>?
Well, one small recommended firmware upgrade later, from 151507 to 151508,
and the whole system is completely down. Please cross your fingers, because
we&rsquo;ve tried <strong>everything</strong> else.</li>
<li>I regularly get accosted by off-leash dogs whilst running. There are
incredibly clear by-laws down here which absolutely forbid any dog ever being
off-leash in any public space which is not a designated off-leash zone. I
recently made the mistake (twice) of trying to explain this to the relevant
dog-owners. Well, dog-owners seem to be quite sadly under-endowed in the area
of introspective capability, but at least I&rsquo;m getting a lot better at
unprepared debates in public spaces. (Psychologists in the audience, help me
out here with any tips please!)</li>
<li>I really enjoyed <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/162-medical-intelligence/">this Sam Harris podcast with Eric
Topol</a>. <a href="https://www.scripps.edu/faculty/topol/">Eric
Topol</a> is a cardiologist and the
founder and director of the Scripps Research Translational Institute in the
US. Apart from the main topic of the discussion, namely Topol&rsquo;s
well-developed and articulated view of AI in medicine (well, his books on
this topic are quite influential, so there&rsquo;s that), I was struck and inspired
by the humble gentleness of this impressive intellect. Furthermore, although
we are not supposed to use twitter anymore (in some circles, it has been
dubbed &ldquo;road rage of the internet&rdquo;), <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Prof Topol&rsquo;s tweet
stream</a> is a shining example of how twitter
could be used more constructively.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email">Would you like some more Emacs with that Email?</h2>
<p>During the past two weeks I published two blog posts on my nerd blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/03/send-queued-mails-in-background-with-mu4e/">Sending queued mails in the background with
mu4e.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/05/mbsync-vs-offlineimap-speed/">Is mbsync really faster than offlineimap? A
measurement.</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Based on these, you might come to the conclusion that I&rsquo;m processing email
inside of Emacs
<a href="/2014/05/24/weekly-head-voices-71-vote-for-the-future/">again</a>.</p>
<p>I can confirm that this is indeed the case.</p>
<p>Probably for a large part due to the popularity of google&rsquo;s gmail, the growth
of the rest of the email ecosystem seems to have been stunted to a significant
degree.</p>
<p>In this specific case, I am referring to the dearth of really good email
clients for Windows.</p>
<p>(By the way, Thunderbird, still my fallback, usually makes the top of any
Windows email client lists. However, if it weren&rsquo;t for GMail, Thunderbird
would probably also be miles better than it is today.)</p>
<p>After losing more hours than I could afford trying to find that perfect email
client (I would have settled for &ldquo;still has all of its own teeth&rdquo;), I realised
that I would just have to buckle down and get <a href="/tags/mu4e/">mu4e</a>, my favourite
Emacs email client, working well enough on Windows, which I currently <em>prefer</em>
(DID I JUST SAY THAT?!) due to my <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1E
baby</a>.</p>
<p>That was of course a whole different wormhole to get sucked into.</p>
<p>Well, more of those precious hours later, I have a Frankensteined concoction
consisting of Emacs running on the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL),
displaying to the Windows desktop via <a href="https://token2shell.com/x410/">X410</a>,
and opening email and orgmode attachments, and dired files, using the native
Windows handlers via an
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Xdg-utils#xdg-open">xdg-open</a> work-alike
I coded up in Python.</p>
<p>(I am planning to release my xdg-open clone along with a more detailed howto
blog post. Let me know if you would like advanced access.)</p>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. after all of that effort I am now back more or less to where I
started in 2014.</p>
<p>(To be honest, Emacs is near the top of my list of compounding activities. The
fact that it&rsquo;s back in my email workflow, combined with five years of
compounded Emacs skills, has resulted in further increased efficiency.)</p>
<h3 id="sticking-it-to-the-man-gmail-with-fastmail">Sticking it to the Man (GMail) with FastMail.</h3>
<p>Wrapping up that email workflow reconfiguration frenzy, I did spend some
minutes doing a quick survey of fastmail alternatives which might have email
servers somewhat closer to the Southern tip of Africa and hence shave off a few
seconds of latency.</p>
<p>I found nothing that came close in terms of features and price. Except for one
outage, <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">I&rsquo;ve been a really happy fastmail camper for the last three
years</a>.</p>
<p>All of that, together with the fact that gmail&rsquo;s continued dominance is
unhealthy for the world of email, convinced me to stick with fastmail for the
conceivable future.</p>
<h2 id="stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">Stone Three Healthcare is now a thing.</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.stonethree.com/healthcare/">Stone Three Healthcare</a>, until recently
a business unit within Stone Three Venture Technology, has now been officially
spun out.</p>
<p>In other words, S3HC is now a more-or-less independent company that will
henceforth have to create its own success.</p>
<p>As some of you know, this project has been cooking for a few years now.</p>
<p>We have a really great team, products with customers and a market, and a
respectable patch of runway.</p>
<p>There are worse ways for a startup to start up.</p>
<p>P.S. if you have any golden tips for startup dummies, I (and probably others)
would be super grateful if you could let &rsquo;em loose in the comments!</p>
<h2 id="always-be-compounding-the-side-project-edition">Always Be Compounding: The side-project edition.</h2>
<p>In the previous WHV, I <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">started going on about the principle of ABC, or Always Be
Compounding</a>.</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been spending a great deal of mental cycles on finding more
ways to ABC.</p>
<p>Besides the more general examples I mentioned there, another method is to
design some long-running project that can function as a container for all of
the work that you&rsquo;ll have to do in any case.</p>
<p>A perhaps slightly flawed personal example is DeVIDE, an open source
visualization and image processing tool that started life somewhere in 2001,
<a href="/2003/12/19/the-visualisation-and-image-processing-platform-formerly-known-as-dscas3/">was renamed to DeVIDE at the end of
2003</a>,
open-sourced in 2007 and had its last release in 2012.</p>
<p>Although it did see some use after that, the project went into hibernation
(weeeelll&hellip;.) when I left academia.</p>
<p>My point is that, for about 10 years, I had a single technical <em>artifact</em> with
a name that became slowly better known (even if it was often by its alias &ldquo;Not
Responding&rdquo;), into which I could integrate all the other new work I was doing.</p>
<p>This enabled me to enjoy some of the advantages of compounding effort, in the
shape of DeVIDE, even although the work I was doing over the years necessarily
had to change.</p>
<p>(A really nice additional benefit was that some students sometimes found the
software useful! I do wish that that part could have continued for a little
longer.)</p>
<p>Setting aside my
<a href="/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/#a-strange-thing-happened-this-weekend">DeVIDE-nostalgia</a>
(and a bit of sadness) for a moment, I would like to apply some of this
learning to my current (and perhaps your) situation.</p>
<p>My idea would be to define a new side-project that can act as the slightly
longer-lived container for some of the smaller side-projects and learnings I
sometimes manage to spend time on.</p>
<p>It would have to be a technology / thematic fit for many of my other
side-projects. It would of course constitute a double-whammy if this
side-project had commercial potential.</p>
<p>Well, SURPRISE!</p>
<p>I do have at least one side-project that ticks a number of these boxes, and
could <em>potentially</em> serve as such a vehicle.</p>
<h3 id="aikno">AIKNO</h3>
<p>The side-project in question is called AIKNO, which is pronounced &ldquo;I know&rdquo;, but
which somehow expands to <em>AI organizational knowledge base</em>. Magic!</p>
<p>It eats all of your organization&rsquo;s emails for breakfast, and then uses
different methods, both algorithmic and crowd/team-sourced, to sort and
organize those emails and all of their attachments, and then makes those easily
and attractively (hey, data visualization!) accessible by that organization.</p>
<p>Think of it as an almost zero-effort always-up-to-date organizational knowledge
base.</p>
<p>Besides having slots for various machine learning and visualization techniques,
it fits nicely into my overgrown knowledge management hobby.</p>
<p>The first commit in the AIKNO repo was in November of 2017. Oof. The prototype
is able to import emails and attachments into its structured database, and
already does funky stuff with similarity searches and whatnot.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, it has also suffered from my regular technology stack
changes, and it&rsquo;s currently languishing while I write blog posts.</p>
<p>My previous failed side-project was called <em>TableTops</em>, or <em>Paradigm Desktop</em> by
the same people who dubbed DeVIDE &ldquo;Not Responding&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It was a free-form canvas / whiteboard tool for the free-form storage and
linking of <em>anything</em>. For example, it had relational data structures for
linking specific coordinates or regions in photos to centralised concepts, and
other interesting things that will probably never see the light of day.</p>
<p>It went through seven tech-stack-change-induced rewrites before being obsoleted
by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">my growing Emacs Orgmode powers</a>. (first
commit October 2013, last commit August 2017, now on the backest back
burner. the one that&rsquo;s not burning.)</p>
<p>I did learn a <em>tremendous</em> amount.</p>
<p>Maybe <em>that</em> is the real reason for doing these things?</p>
<h2 id="always-be-learning">Always Be Learning.</h2>
<p>Thanks for joining me on that trip folks.</p>
<p>I hope to see you soon. Until then, make an amazing time!</p>
<figure>
<a href="coffee_company_belgian_brownie.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
100% amazing Belgian brownie and delectable flat white at the
Coffee Company on Lourensford this past weekend.
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #172: ABC.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 20:17:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/</guid><description> YARRRRGGGHHHH it&amp;rsquo;s now more than a month after the previous WHV saw the light of day.
This draft, intially intended to see the light of day not much more than a week after 171, has been languishing in a cold jail of electrons up in the cloud somewhere for the past weeks, while life was doing its thing, you know, inexorably marching ahead.
Whatever the case may be, I&amp;rsquo;m happy that we are here now.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="reflection_strand_beach.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu40e4562709a994338e239aee0aa31b03_2470891_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu40e4562709a994338e239aee0aa31b03_2470891_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu40e4562709a994338e239aee0aa31b03_2470891_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu40e4562709a994338e239aee0aa31b03_2470891_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu40e4562709a994338e239aee0aa31b03_2470891_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>YARRRRGGGHHHH it&rsquo;s now more than a month after the previous WHV saw the light
of day.</p>
<p>This draft, intially intended to see the light of day not much more than a week
after 171, has been languishing in a cold jail of electrons up in the cloud
somewhere for the past weeks, while life was doing its thing, you know,
inexorably marching ahead.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I&rsquo;m happy that we are here now.</p>
<h2 id="the-dark-forest">The Dark Forest.</h2>
<p>I just searched this blog to check: To my surprise, I have somehow not gushed
about the Dark Forest trilogy by Cixin Liu before.</p>
<p>I read Ken Liu&rsquo;s translation of <em>The Three-Body Problem</em> in 2014, and it blew
my mind.</p>
<p>It could be that I deliberately reserved gushing until finishing the rest of
the trilogy.</p>
<p>During the past weeks I finished <em>The Dark Forest</em> and finally <em>Death&rsquo;s End</em>.</p>
<p>This is hardcore science fiction, with enough mind-bending physics ideas to,
well, bend your mind, and an insightful peek into at least one Chinese world
view through the eyes of the author.</p>
<p>Most haunting, however, is this work&rsquo;s dark answer to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermi_paradox">the Fermi
paradox</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-books-will-stop-working">The books will stop working.</h2>
<p>I bought The Dark Forest trilogy as Kindle ebooks from Amazon, adding to quite
a stack of previous Kindle ebook purchases.</p>
<p>As you might have heard, Microsoft are shutting off their DRM servers, and have
<a href="https://boingboing.net/2019/06/28/jun-17-2004.html">warned their customers that &ldquo;The books will stop
working&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>Stfan <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2016/08/21/amazon-owns-your-ebooks/">has also warned about
this</a> in the
context of Amazon.</p>
<p>Today I saw that Charlie Stross, a super successful author himself, as a rule
<a href="https://twitter.com/cstross/status/1144336012015034368">breaks the DRM on any ebooks that he
buys</a>.</p>
<p>I find all of this a bit chilling.</p>
<h2 id="circadian-brevity">Circadian brevity.</h2>
<p>We have been privy to some of those magical sunny winter days that this part of
the world is renowned for.</p>
<p>However, the days are significantly shorter, and this does tend to have a sort
of narrowing effect on one&rsquo;s days.</p>
<p>More concretely, for these past few weeks (excluding the KNP break mentioned
below) it really felt like each work day consisted exclusively of waking up,
preparing for school and work, leaving for school and work, doing work and/or
school, getting back home for dinner and bath-time, and then going to bed.</p>
<p>Somehow, there&rsquo;s almost no time for anything else.</p>
<p>The optimist in me notes that this is probably really just the shorter days. In
a few months, spring will bring longer days, and longer days have the potential
of bearing much more variety.</p>
<p>The cynic on the other hand is making the scary case that this could just be
one of the many new and irreversible artefacts of inexorably approaching old
age.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the stakes are even higher than normal for
maintaining focus throughout the day.</p>
<h2 id="knp">KNP</h2>
<p>Our (almost) <a href="/tags/knp/">yearly break under the reassuring sun in the Kruger National
Park</a> was just what the doctors ordered to remedy some of all that
darkness.</p>
<p>The sun and the soft winter warmth were amazing as always.</p>
<p>However, I had significant troubles (all of them in my head of course. Wait,
what isn&rsquo;t? HA HA) <a href="/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/#you-are-turning-into-a-cyborg">disconnecting from
work</a>.</p>
<p>&hellip; only to realise the day <em>after</em> bestie PK&rsquo;s birthday that I&rsquo;d forgotten to
call due to being <em>half</em> disconnected. (Correction: I was reminded by said
bestie. I think in the Book of Etiquette my faux pas is thus at least a -3 on a
scale of 1 to 10.)</p>
<p>Dang it. I&rsquo;m not very good at this.</p>
<p>However, word on the street is that &ldquo;grit&rdquo; is hip again, so I kept at it. (I&rsquo;m
also stubborn.)</p>
<p>By the last day of our break, I think I finally managed to reach the desired
state of disconnectedness.</p>
<p>On this day, we arrived at <a href="http://www.krugerpark.co.za/Kruger_National_Park_Bush_Lodges_&amp;_Camps-travel/shimuwini-camp.html">the Shimuwini
camp</a>,
where a troupe of elephants decided to join us for dinner on the bank of the
Letaba river, about 50 metres from our front porch.</p>
<p>Magical.</p>
<video controls>
  <source src="elephants_grazing_shimuwini.mp4" type="video/mp4">
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
<h2 id="solar-powerrrrrrrr">Solar powerrrrrrrr</h2>
<p>Well well well well well.</p>
<p>At one point I was starting to think that it would forever be all talk and no
solar action around here.</p>
<p>However, thanks to <a href="http://redengineering.co.za/">RED Engineering</a>, the
brilliant and well-organized installer (#4 on my list&hellip;) who was also patient
enough to field my never-ending stream of questions, this post and hopefully
many more in the future are 100% solar powered.</p>
<p>(I just checked on the dashboard. Very much overcast today, but plant is
generating enough to power the house.)</p>
<p>When the final bits and bobs have been sorted (most important remaining
challenge is getting the GoodWe GW5048D-ES to successfully talk to the
PylonTech US3000 battery cluster BMS), I&rsquo;ll write a post with more details
about the system and its performance.</p>
<p>Until then, these are the specifications:</p>
<ul>
<li>Panels: 18 x <a href="./canadian_solar_cs3u_specs.pdf">Canadian Solar KuMax high efficiency polycrystalline CS3U
355Wp</a></li>
<li>Inverter: <a href="https://www.goodwe.com/Products/index_spec/id/22.html">GoodWe
GW5048D-ES</a></li>
<li>Batteries: 2 x <a href="http://www.pylontech.com.cn/pro_detail.aspx?id=121&amp;cid=23">PylonTech US3000 lithium iron phosphate
batteries</a> for a
total of 7kWh of storage.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="always-be-compounding">Always Be Compounding!</h2>
<p>I think it was during <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/155-mental-models/">a recent podcast with Shane
Parrish</a> where I heard about
the idea of applying compounding to aspects of one&rsquo;s life.</p>
<p>In short, if <a href="https://fs.blog/2016/03/five-percent-better/">you can become 5% wiser and better every year, you&rsquo;ll be about
twice as wise as you are now in a mere 15
years</a>.</p>
<p>The fundamental principle is one of modest, incremental progress, but, and this
is the secret sauce, <em>consistently</em> applied, without letting up.</p>
<p>If you can write a blog post every week (ahem..) you&rsquo;ll have hundreds of blog
posts in a few years, and something significant to look back on.</p>
<p>(If you&rsquo;re able to write on a specific topic, that&rsquo;s even better. Stfan
recently Signalled me this very relevant post titled <a href="https://matthewrocklin.com/blog/work/2019/06/25/write-short-blogposts">&ldquo;Write Short
Blogposts&rdquo;</a>.)</p>
<p>If you can write a book chapter every month, you&rsquo;ll have written a book when
the year is over.</p>
<p>If you are able to pick a worthwhile activity or topic, and then to <em>keep on</em>
making incremental contributions to that activity or topic, you&rsquo;ll become
<em>the</em> expert on that topic before you know it.</p>
<p>I think you get the idea.</p>
<p>I find this such a powerful concept, so much so that I&rsquo;ve resolved to integrate
it with my daily checklist.</p>
<p>For me, step one is to have a list of worthwhile directions available, and step
two is to execute, just a little bit, on any of them as regularly as possible.</p>
<h2 id="gou2-tells-it-like-it-is">GOU#2 tells it like it is.</h2>
<p>Recently, GOU#2 (age 9) and her classmates compiled a father&rsquo;s day book, where
each child had to draw a picture illustrating what makes their dad special.</p>
<p>My heart melted when I finally reached her page:</p>
<figure>
<a href="sylvia_kunswerk_blog.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hub952abb093da398011bffe4b97536905_181331_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hub952abb093da398011bffe4b97536905_181331_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hub952abb093da398011bffe4b97536905_181331_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hub952abb093da398011bffe4b97536905_181331_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hub952abb093da398011bffe4b97536905_181331_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<p>Because the meta is strong down here, I could not resist posting this artwork
as well.</p>
<p>Folks, have an excellent week. I wish you happiness, health and compounding.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #164: Its what future you would want.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 14:53:44 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/</guid><description> Pre-work not-too-shabby running route.
Welcome back friends! This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday February 18 to Sunday March 3, 2019. I was planning to release the edition of the WHV on time, but my need for a break was greater.
Because Ive given up on ever mastering the art of the bullet-list form of the weekly(ish) status update, I am going to double-down on the old-fashioned sectioned prose form that you see before you.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/strand_running_route_2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/strand_running_route_2-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Pre-work not-too-shabby running route."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pre-work not-too-shabby running route.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome back friends! This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday February 18 to Sunday March 3, 2019. I was planning to release the edition of the WHV on time, but my need for a break was greater.</p>
<p>Because Ive given up on ever mastering the art of the bullet-list form of the weekly(ish) status update, I am going to double-down on the old-fashioned sectioned prose form that you see before you.</p>
<p>Also, this post has again evolved into a long ramble. (Its now Saturday March 9, time to start working on the next edition. Im curious what form it will take.)</p>
<h2 id="gou1-is-2">GOU#1 is #2</h2>
<p>It feels like through these posts youve pretty much seen <a href="/2010/07/26/island-style-weekly-head-voices-27/">GOU#1 grow up before your eyes</a>, so Ive given myself permission to mention this moment of parental pride, hopefully quite briefly though (I write this blog not only for you, but also for me in 20 years time!):</p>
<p>GOU #1 has been elected as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Head_girl_and_head_boy">deputy head girl</a> of her 1600+ pupil primary school!</p>
<p>She was really mature, also before the time, about this possible outcome of taking the #2 position. She seems to have made up her mind before the time that this would in fact be, for her, the best configuration.</p>
<p>This thoughtfulness of hers might have made me even more proud than the achievement itself.</p>
<h2 id="dreams-of-clean-solar-electricity-wafting-ineffectually-against-the-greasy-gears-of-government">Dreams of clean solar electricity wafting ineffectually against the greasy gears of government.</h2>
<p>Way back in December of last year <a href="/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/#extreme-solar">I mentioned</a> that we were working on getting the house upgraded with a photovoltaic solar power system.</p>
<p>Some of you have asked me via various communication pathways how it was going.</p>
<p>Thanks to legislation, or rather the lack of communication around this legislation, the amount of physical progress we have made so far is close to zero. Oh, just make that zero.</p>
<p>My shopping list now looks as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Unchanged: 3.6kW GoodWe EM hybrid inverter: Although a larger inverter would have been preferable, uncertainty caused by above-mentioned lack of communication motivates me to play it safe with this unit which is in the 2017 column of the approved list.</li>
<li>Unchanged: 2 x PylonTech US3000b lithium ion batteries.</li>
<li>CHANGED: 16 x Canadian Solar CS3U 350Wp or 355Wp solar panels.</li>
</ul>
<p>It used to be common knowledge that monocrystalline panel power output suffered less due to high temperature than that of the cheaper polycrystalline panels. This is quite relevant, because just sitting there on your roof the whole day, these things can get really hot!</p>
<p>Well, I finally went and looked up the temperature coefficient of these current generation Canadian Solar panels, namely the CS3U range, <a href="https://www.canadiansolar.com/upload/521adedf1d5fecb9/e5ba81805bf70380.pdf">which is -0.37% Pmax / </a>. This is in fact slightly better than the -0.39% of the monocrystalline panels I had on my list.</p>
<p>I am currently on the lookout for what is going to be my fourth candidate solar installer, although at this stage I would be quite happy with a talented electrician who is not afraid of heights.</p>
<p>(My second installer had difficulty keeping up with all of their work (probably thanks to load-shedding and also to the substantial price increases expected from our embattled electricity monopoly) and my third installer has decided to focus on commercial installations.)</p>
<h2 id="my-big-and-stupid-misstep-into-google-drive">My big and stupid misstep into Google Drive.</h2>
<p>Somewhere during the past two weeks, I lost, forever and ever, at least three evenings.</p>
<p>Tipped off by a colleague at work, encouraged by my familys mobile photos investment in Google Photos, and further tempted by the significant price difference and the family storage sharing option, I convinced myself that it was time to migrate my little empire of useless files (dropbox reports that I currently have just over 500000 (five hundred thousand) of them) out of Dropbox and into Google Drive.</p>
<p>This is how it looked on paper, i.e. in my head and in my Emacs notes:</p>
<ul>
<li>I have about 70GB of photos taken with various family cameras of kids growing up, vacations everywhere and so on. These photos are currently not easily accessible by said family. If they were on Google Drive, they could be automatically exposed to Google Photos, which my family is already using!</li>
<li>My 237G of Google Drive space, sufficient for everything, costs R39 / month (thats about $2.75), whereas my Dropbox subscription costs $10 / month.</li>
<li>The cheap subscription of Drive already enables one to do content searches. E.g. I could find scans of documents instantly by typing OCRd words that occur in the documents. If you want the same with Dropbox, you have to go Pro (not Plus), and pay double, that is $19.99 per month.</li>
<li>Drive has a built-in facility to backup folders outside of the main sync folder.</li>
<li>Theres a great tool called <a href="https://rclone.org/">rclone</a> with which nerds can sync files to Google Drive from the command-line!</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="four-lessons-learned-uploading-500k-files-to-google-drive">Four lessons learned uploading 500k files to Google Drive</h3>
<ol>
<li>Google has servers down here in South Africa: With larger files, the upload could easily max out my 50Mbit/s upload.</li>
<li>However, in spite of allocating and configuring my own <a href="https://rclone.org/drive/#making-your-own-client-id"><code>client_id</code></a>, I could not upload faster than about 3 files per second. Based on various threads on the rclone forums, this is a known issue.</li>
<li>Google Drives selective sync functionality does NOT (easily) allow you to maintain a local version of an excluded directory in the same way that Dropbox does. This is <em>especially</em> annoying for those already quite annoying <code>node_modules</code> folders.</li>
<li>Google Drive and its API support identically named files and directories, located in the same parent directory.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="how-did-the-wheels-fall-off-then">How did the wheels fall off then?</h3>
<p>I was alternating between the official Google Backup &amp; Sync client and <code>rclone sync</code>. I did this to check if rclone with a private <code>client_id</code> would be able to upload faster (it couldnt) and because rclone showed sync progress more clearly with an estimated time of completion (all of this turned out to be wildly incorrect and variable due to all of those small files).</p>
<p>My logic was that as long as the two tools were not running in parallel, sync logic and checksums should prevail right?!</p>
<p>Well, that turned out to be a very sad assumption</p>
<p>rclone, which I still believe is a great tool for bulk uploads and downloads, should probably not be used for syncing in situations like this.</p>
<p>Unbeknownst to me, it had created hundreds of identically-named directories everywhere. (See lesson #4 above.)</p>
<p>At about halfway through this multi-day upload project, I switched back to the official Google tool, which finally, FINALLY managed to sync everything after about 5 days I would guess.</p>
<p>I was briefly <em>quite</em> happy with Googles arrow-in-cloud you-are-fully-synced icon in the menubar.</p>
<p>However, because happiness is so inherently fleeting anyways, I decided that it was time for the next phase of the project: Add the first Linux workstation to the little sync family.</p>
<p>Google Drive does NOT have a native client for Linux, although theyve promised this since the start, and so I decided to try <a href="https://www.insynchq.com">Insync</a>, which seems to be one of the best of the third party clients.</p>
<p>I pre-seeded the sync directory on said Linux machine using rsync and then started the insync client. This is a use case which was often enough mentioned on the forums as being supported.</p>
<p>Initially, everything seemed to be going swimmingly!</p>
<p>However, soon I saw whole directory hierarchies with thousands of files disappearing simultaneously from both my local disc and google drive.</p>
<p>STAAAAAAAAHP!!! JUST STAHP.</p>
<p>A second, stubborn attempt, after having recovered files and synced everything up with Googles tool, yielded similarly frustrating results.</p>
<p>Granted, the duplicate folders on Google Drive are a far from ideal test case, but deleting directories like that on both client and server is not defensible.</p>
<p>Defeated, I retreated to the expensive, but safe, embrace of Dropbox.</p>
<h3 id="more-lessons-learned">More lessons learned:</h3>
<ul>
<li>The lack of an official Google Drive client on Linux is debilitating to my workflow.</li>
<li>Handle the third-party Insync client with extreme caution.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://www.behavioraleconomics.com/resources/mini-encyclopedia-of-be/sunk-cost-fallacy/">sunk cost fallacy</a> is a real danger in cases like these.</li>
<li>The hours I lost are probably worth at least a year or two of Dropbox.</li>
<li>Having reliable incremental backups outside of your cloud syncing service remains important.</li>
</ul>
<p>On that last point: Juggling my 500k files between Dropbox, Google Drive, then going live on Google Drive with real work before jumping into the shady world of badly implemented sync clients made me realise (again) the importance of a separate set of incremental backups.</p>
<p>Before my macOS phase (which started on May 6, 2015 when my employer bought me my first MacBook Pro and I wrote in my diary: Bought 13.3 retina MacBook Pro early 2015, 128 GB SSD. I am doomed.) I used to maintain a <a href="http://dirvish.org">dirvish</a> backup.</p>
<p>(Dirvish is an amazing tool by the way.)</p>
<p>The truly stupid and frustrating adventure I write about here, did at least lead to some learning, and to me hooking up a <a href="https://www.storagereview.com/seagate_4tb_backup_plus_portable_drive_review">Seagate 4TB external drive</a> to my desk at work. Now when I connect my MacBook, Time Machine performs incremental backups the whole day long.</p>
<p>The next time I have one of these moments of irrationality again, I will at least have the possibility of returning my files to sanity as soon as I do.</p>
<h2 id="thinking-of-future-you">Thinking of future you.</h2>
<p>There was one more learning I wanted to share.</p>
<p>I have mentioned before <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#three">on this blog</a> the well-known productivity trick of writing down, during your morning planning, the two to three really important tasks for the day.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/143-keys-mind/">the Sam Harris podcast where he interviews Derren Brown</a>, they briefly mention a really interesting take or perspective on the tip above.</p>
<p><em>When writing those tasks down, try to predict the two to three tasks the completion of which will satisfy future you the most at the end of the day.</em></p>
<p>It sounds like a small tweak, but this is a great way to encourage deeper (almost meta-)consideration of tasks that will really matter.</p>
<p>Additionally and more straight-forward than that, with this exercise you increase the chances that you end the day with that great feeling of closure that comes with getting important stuff done.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #160: Write stuff down.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 17:10:31 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/</guid><description> In the foreground, the mortar and pestle I used to mash together garlic, ginger, a serenade chilli, green cardamom pods, a whole cinnamon quill, one bay leaf, some curry powder for even more oomf, turmeric, coriander, salt and a few cloves. This paste ended up in that blurry red cast iron pot on the coals to result, a few hours later, in a delectable chicken curry potjie.
Welcome to the first WHV of the year 2019 folks!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/chicken_potjie_no2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/chicken_potjie_no2-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="In the foreground, the mortar and pestle I used to mash together garlic, ginger, a serenade chilli, green cardamom pods, a whole cinnamon quill, one bay leaf, some curry powder for even more oomf, turmeric, coriander, salt and a few cloves. This paste ended up in that blurry red cast iron pot on the coals to result, a few hours later, in a delectable chicken curry potjie."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>In the foreground, the mortar and pestle I used to mash together garlic, ginger, a serenade chilli, green cardamom pods, a whole cinnamon quill, one bay leaf, some curry powder for even more oomf, turmeric, coriander, salt and a few cloves. This paste ended up in that blurry red cast iron pot on the coals to result, a few hours later, in a delectable chicken curry potjie.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to the first WHV of the year 2019 folks!</p>
<p>In what is hopefully just a minor incident and not a portent of calamitous events to come, we have already skipped the first two weeks of the year, which means this WHV looks back at the three weeks from Monday January 7 to Saturday January 26.</p>
<p>I guess this would not be the WHV if we did not start off with some sort of awkwardness or miscellaneous embarrassment, so: CHECK!</p>
<p>Because you are probably thirsty for your WHV now, I tried to write you a long and rambly edition, with pictures! (Because its so long and rambly, and because markdown, I have liberally sprinkled with headings and sub-headings, so that those of you with lives outside of blog reading can hop, skip and jump through like the professionals you are.)</p>
<h2 id="the-future-is-here-long-form-blog-posts-on-the-ipad">The future is here: Long-form blog posts on the iPad.</h2>
<p>This also would not be the WHV if we did not have some little digital trick to reveal: Todays attempt is that this post is being written, for the largest part, on a 2018 iPad (the cheapest one) with an old (also very cheap) bluetooth keyboard.</p>
<p>Because I really dont like the new block-based WordPress 5.0 editor, named in an entirely non-hubristic fashion Gutenberg, but it does fortunately support importing markdown formatted blog posts (just make sure you dont hard-wrap anything), and because I like trying new things, I am typing this on the iPad using the iOS version of <a href="https://www.textasticapp.com/">Textastic</a>.</p>
<p>A few hours ago, it looked like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/img_0005.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/img_0005-1024x768.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>
</p>
<p>In contrast to the direct <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2014/05/25/emacs-24-with-prelude-org2blog-and-wordpress/">orgmode to wordpress Emacs workflow</a> I normally use, this workflow enables me to copy and paste sections of markdown text into WordPress. Each pasted section is automatically imported as WordPress blocks, based on the markdown structure.</p>
<p>This means I can position and edit images using the WordPress interface, but author the text using Markdown. With <a href="https://github.com/org2blog/org2blog">org2blog</a> the whole post, including images, has to go through life as an orgmode file, which is brilliant for my more technical posts, but not so much for prose-heavy blog posts such as this one.</p>
<h3 id="btw-1-why-i-dont-yet-like-the-new-wordpress-editor">BTW 1: Why I dont (yet) like the new WordPress editor.</h3>
<p>The old WordPress editor enabled me to focus on the content and just write.</p>
<p>The new <a href="https://wordpress.org/gutenberg/">Gutenberg editor</a> now wants me to create a bunch of blocks, e.g. paragraph, image, paragraph, bullet list, etc., and then work with those blocks.</p>
<p>Thats really great if youre building a site, but not so much when you would just like to get down and write that blog post.</p>
<p>Although this is now the standard editor in WordPress, there are still bugs, such as the fact that my cursor keeps on jumping to the start of the block while Im typing, which is not irritating at all, and the not unimportant observation that none of the mobile apps support Gutenberg yet.</p>
<p>WordPress-using readers, what do you think?</p>
<p>(P.S. Another just-discovered issue: In Gutenberg, your biggest heading is H2. H1 is not available in the UI normally. When pasting in markdown, H1s do display, but do not show in the type-UI as anything. Here is <a href="https://github.com/WordPress/gutenberg/issues/4234">a confusing Gutenberg bug report</a>.)</p>
<h3 id="btw-2-why-textastic-aka-at-least-it-will-syntax-highlight-your-orgmode">BTW 2: Why Textastic? (AKA At least it will syntax highlight your Orgmode.)</h3>
<p>The main reason I found and purchased Textastic, was that I ran into <a href="https://github.com/jezcope/Org.tmbundle">Jez Copes github repo</a> with a TextMate Bundle (thats an editor configuration) that was made for Textastic to support editing Emacs orgmode files.</p>
<p>As is the age-old open source way, there were a few small bugs which I <a href="https://github.com/jezcope/Org.tmbundle/pull/5">fixed in my fork</a>, which you should definitely get if you are in the same I-want-to-edit-Orgmode-on-my-iOS boat as I am. Its not a very large boat, but its super fun!</p>
<p>(There is no Emacs on iOS. This is in my view the greatest downside of iOS. It turns out that Apple generally does not allow apps with embedded interpreters on the app store. However, I am still trying to find out why there are no iOS-capable Emacs source code forks available.)</p>
<h3 id="btw-3-the-ipad-with-keyboard-is-a-shockingly-good-laptop-replacement">BTW 3: The iPad with keyboard is a shockingly good laptop replacement.</h3>
<p>I recently recommended to a privacy-conscious reader who was searching for an affordable Linux-running laptop in South Africa, that she instead consider buying an iPad with bluetooth keyboard.</p>
<p>Down here a brand new 2018 iPad costs R5999. A cheap keyboard cover (e.g. Body Glove) can be had for about R860.</p>
<p>If you compare this to any new laptop of R6900 (about EUR 444) which will probably be sold with Windows included, you get a computing device with a fantastic quality multi-touch screen, great battery life, best-in-class security, almost no maintenance, and a fantastic app ecosystem. To seal the deal, the iPads resale value is proportionally probably also much better than that entry-level laptop.</p>
<p><em>After</em> I sent that email, I started with this iPad + cheap bluetooth keyboard experiment to try it for myself. I have to say that the experience has been way better than I expected.</p>
<p>For a large subset of laptop users, and for a large subset of workflows and tasks, this is a really great solution.</p>
<p>Please dont worry (too much) yet, I am not planning one of those I switched to an iPad as my main computing device blog posts. I would not be able to survive without my development tools, and I would especially not be able to survive without my Emacs.</p>
<h2 id="pv-solar-installation-progress">PV Solar installation progress</h2>
<p>As I excitedly <a href="/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/#extreme-solar">announced in WHV #159</a> (slightly more than a month ago), we had decided that it was time to get a photovoltaic solar power system installed at the house.</p>
<p>I found a local installer with the required PVGreenCard accreditation and started the consultation process.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the installer did not seem to be prepared for a customer that would not stop asking questions. The customer even went so far as to pose questions that challenged the installers brand loyalty!</p>
<p>I really do understand that Im probably not the easiest end-user, but I dont think that an experts brand loyalty should get in the way of reason, and far more importantly in the way of basic physics.</p>
<p>To make a long story short, I ended up getting fired by the installer.</p>
<p>This was probably for the better: He can now continue doing well-practised installs for other clients who dont ask (so many) questions, and I suddenly had the opportunity to find a new, more engineer-friendly installer, and to continue learning.</p>
<p>Following are two noteworthy learnings:</p>
<h3 id="learning-1-you-should-almost-always-try-to-oversize-the-photovoltaic-array">Learning 1: You should almost always try to oversize the photovoltaic array</h3>
<p>If the equipment states for example 4600kVA, then you are usually quite safe installing from 25% up to 30% more kWp of solar panels.</p>
<p>Oversizing will mean that on very sunny days youll get peaks higher than the maximum rated PV, which can be handled for short periods by the solar equipment, but more importantly, youll be able to generate more electricity when there is less sun, which is most of the time.</p>
<p>In other words, you increase the area under the curve of kW generated per hour.</p>
<p>By the way, I emailed GoodWe (they make the hybrid inverters I have my eye on) who confirmed that their EM range supports 27.8% oversizing. The ES range advertise 30% PV oversizing on the box.</p>
<p>It is of course an interesting question what exactly is meant by oversizing. Do they support pumping 30% more power into the inverter for 5 minutes, or for 2 hours?</p>
<h3 id="learning-2-powerforumcoza-is-a-great-source-of-information">Learning 2: powerforum.co.za is a great source of information.</h3>
<p><a href="https://powerforum.co.za/">This forum</a> has a surprisingly high signal to noise ratio.</p>
<p>There are a number of experts hanging around, including one of Victrons super helpful and knowledgeable R&amp;D engineers, and the archive posts are invaluable as you try to navigate <a href="https://powerforum.co.za/topic/2791-experience-getting-city-of-cape-town-to-sign-off-a-zero-feed-in-system-with-inverter-maximum-output-greater-than-35kva/">the quagmire</a> of often conflicting information.</p>
<h2 id="avocado-baby-progress-very-much-touch-and-go">Avocado baby progress: Very much touch and go.</h2>
<p>The baby avocado tree, in spite of being being watered almost every day (thank you rainwater harvest!) does not seem to be doing too well.</p>
<p>Because the summer sun down here can be quite vicious, the tree has its own little pink umbrella.</p>
<p>The current plan is to feed it more compost, and, if that fails, to try to transplant it out of the big, wild garden and into a pot with softer, kinder earth.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-explain-complicated-topics">How to explain complicated topics</h2>
<p>The international and yearly <a href="https://mlssafrica.com">Machine Learning Summer School took place in Stellenbosch this year</a>, from Monday, January 7 to Friday, January 18.</p>
<p>As you can see from the programme, there were a bunch of heavy hitting speakers present both physically and virtually, including the super resourceful (failed super resolution pun, su(p)e(r) me) Dr Stefan van der Walt, who gave a talk on good scientific software.</p>
<p>Anyways, because I am currently in a more commercial configuration, I could not justify taking two weeks out, and instead opted for a day visit at the start of the congress.</p>
<p>It is a testament to the current prominence of the field that the list of international sponsors included Microsoft, Apple, SAP, Uber <em>and</em> Amazon.</p>
<p>It was gratifying to experience a sampling of such a well-organized international gathering here in my neck of the woods.</p>
<p>On the first day, we had a high throughput introduction to causality, probabilistic thinking, and variational inference. All the presenters were clearly good speakers, but they werent all equally experienced in teaching such complex material.</p>
<p>(At one point one of the statisticians I was chatting to in break admitted having difficulty keeping up with the math. I did not feel <strong>that</strong> stupid anymore.)</p>
<p>What is the difference between being a good speaker and an experienced teacher?, you might now ask.</p>
<p>Great question, I would then say, grateful for the opportunity to explain.</p>
<p>What I was missing in the one specific case I do not want to be too specific about, was that the presenter did a great job of talking about each of a long list of concepts relevant to his topic, but somehow forgot that one of the most important parts of teaching is communicating the conceptual framework into which all of those concepts fit.</p>
<p>Conceptual frameworks are also one of those multi-scalar things: Each group of factoids can be gratifyingly embedded into a slightly higher level component, groups of which can be slotted into the overarching big idea, or another level of compnonent. (Its turtles all the way down.)</p>
<p>As great lecturers talk, they keep on bringing their narrative back up to the higher-level embedding construct.</p>
<p>It looks something like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/teach_complicated_things.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/teach_complicated_things-1024x576.png"
        
            alt="Yes, I did make this especially for this post, especially for you. No, I am not sure exactly why."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Yes, I did make this especially for this post, especially for you. No, I am not sure exactly why.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>By repeatedly diving deeper into the details, and then following the conceptual link back up to the higher-level constructs and especially your big idea, your listeners will start to see the beautiful fractal of understanding that you are guiding them through.</p>
<h2 id="what-will-i-be-working-on-this-year">What will I be working on this year?</h2>
<p>At this moment, 2019 is shaping up to be pretty exciting work-wise.</p>
<p>We just heard that we will be able to continue for some months more working on the X-Ray based surgical planning project we worked on last year.</p>
<p>Partly thanks to the great deep learning work of two summer interns (note: Southern Hemisphere means summer interns over December and January, which might be weird if youre from the Northern Hemisphere) we are in great shape for all of the deep neural network-based image understanding plans we need to execute on.</p>
<p>This year I will also be spending more time on <a href="https://www.telesensi.com">TeleSensi, our FDA-certified tele-auscultation product</a>. This is less rocket-sciencey than the surgical planning project, but super interesting to work on, as it has many more users on the open market.</p>
<p>(That being said, we do have plans to increase the level of rocket science significantly. I am not called the science officer for nothing (well, that and also the fact that I got to choose my own title, and so I chose the same as Spock on the USS Enterprise).)</p>
<h2 id="do-you-write-stuff-down">Do you write stuff down?</h2>
<p>You might remember from WHV #155 <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">my trick of starting the day with a checklist</a>.</p>
<p>A part of that checklist is a checklist of habits which I try to form and maintain, called The HabitFormer(tm). Every item that I sufficiently address gets a super satisfying little <code>[X]</code> mark, which feels a whole lot better than the sadly empty <code>[ ]</code> construct.</p>
<p>Here is the current list:</p>
<ul>
<li>did you write stuff down?</li>
<li>are you satisfied with number of pomodori?</li>
<li>7.5 hrs sleep last night</li>
<li>meditate &lt; (WHV <em>hidden</em> pro-tip: Get the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up</a> app by Sam Harris. Thanks LM for the fantastic recommendation.)</li>
<li>stand at desk</li>
<li>do valuable things</li>
<li>fruit &amp; veg</li>
<li>reading</li>
<li>thinking</li>
<li>running or other exercise</li>
</ul>
<p>Ironically enough, the first item is brand new on the list.</p>
<p>I somehow forgot my habit of writing, during the day, a little done list / random thoughts lists. After bringing this habit back I noticed what difference it made.</p>
<p>At regular intervals during the day, I will spend a minute or three writing down what I had completed, or what I was thinking. This moment of introspection would either result in a pleasant bit of satisfaction with some small task taken care of, or, more often, it would reel me back in from a spot of less than deliberate action and enable me to bring back my attention to the point of focus.</p>
<p>Im filing this under 101 tricks to get your <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/">rider back on your elephant</a>.</p>
<p>Alright friends, thank you very much for joining me on this part of my journey. I am looking forward to our next interaction!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #159: Extreme.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 21:16:49 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/</guid><description> The view from Waterkloof Restaurants balcony, on a fairly perfect evening.
In theory, this edition should cover the period of time from Monday November 19 to today, Wednesday December 19, 2018.
I am very late with this post, because down here we were first busy winding down the year with all of the completion-madness that that entails, and then the vacation started starting.
It hasnt yet stopped being busy starting.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/waterkloof_perfect_evening.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/waterkloof_perfect_evening-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from Waterkloof Restaurants balcony, on a fairly perfect evening."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from Waterkloof Restaurants balcony, on a fairly perfect evening.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In theory, this edition should cover the period of time from Monday November 19 to today, Wednesday December 19, 2018.</p>
<p>I am very late with this post, because down here we were first busy winding down the year with all of the completion-madness that that entails, and then the vacation started starting.</p>
<p>It hasnt yet stopped being busy starting.</p>
<p>We are now entering what the Dutch call <a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komkommertijd">komkommertijd</a>, and, as Ive just learned, the Germans <em>Sauregurkenzeit</em>, referring to the period when everyone has left and theres not really anything news-worthy happening.</p>
<h2 id="extreme-dining">Extreme dining</h2>
<p>To celebrate the occasion of the official partnership between my partner and me adding another year to its growing collection, and due to my partners impeccable timing and ingenuity, we spent an amazing evening at what is currently South Africas best restaurant, at least according to <a href="https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/lifestyle/food/2018-11-20-this-eatery-in-the-western-cape-has-been-named-sas-best-restaurant/">the 2018 Eat Out Mercedes-Benz Restaurant Awards</a>.</p>
<p>I would like to share three observations:</p>
<ol>
<li>The Waterkloof experience is a superbly balanced combination of location (see the photo above), architecture and interior design, art and ambience, all acting as context for the almost other-worldly culinary adventure, itself consisting of pairings of wine and perfect little dishes, the latter again artfully manipulating appearance and taste, space and time.</li>
<li>South Africa is a country of extremes. Just the previous night, close family had been the victims in a violent but fortunately non-fatal home invasion.</li>
<li>If you ever manage to find yourself at Waterkloof, take this advice to heart: The <em>small</em> dgustation menu with wine pairing is most probably more than enough. (We selected the <em>normal</em>. By what felt like the 15th course, we were dealing with the dilemma of having to abstain from eye-wateringly beautiful culinary creations.)</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="extreme-solar">Extreme Solar</h2>
<p>For many good reasons, we are currently seriously evaluating upgrading the house with a photovoltaic solar power system.</p>
<p>It turns out, as I should have expected, that theres a whole universe of new toys and gadgets to evaluate.</p>
<p>We are currently looking at the following main components:</p>
<ul>
<li>2 x <a href="http://www.pylontech.com.cn/pro_detail.aspx?id=121&amp;cid=23">PylonTech US3000B</a> LithiumIon batteries for a total of about 7 kWh of stored electricity.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.goodwe.co.uk/Products/index_em.html">GoodWeGW3648-EM Hybrid inverter</a>: This coordinates everything between the PV Solar panels, the grid and the batteries. When the sun is shining, it charges the batteries, and powers as much as possible of the house, only using the grid when theres no other option. During the evening, it powers the house using the batteries, again only using the grid when absolutely required. Due to strict rules down here in Cape Town, we are limited to inverters with a maximum output of 3.6 kW, even when no feed-in (to the grid) is planned.</li>
<li>The PV Solar Panels: I am still considering options here. I would prefer monocrystalline, and as close as possible to the 4.6 kWp maximum supported by the GoodWe inverter to maximise the amount of sun in our power diet.</li>
</ul>
<p>As a first step, today we had a number of intelligent geyser controllers installed. These devices enable me to keep the geysers (we heat all of our water electrically down here) off for most of the day, only switching them on an hour or two before hot water is usually required.</p>
<p>They look like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/geyserwise_tse.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/geyserwise_tse-888x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="GeyserWise TSE geyser controller. I should have done this ages ago. Who came up with the idea that a water geyser needs to maintain its high temperature 24/7?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>GeyserWise TSE geyser controller. I should have done this ages ago. Who came up with the idea that a water geyser needs to maintain its high temperature 24/7?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The rest of this exercise will be considerably more expensive, but am really looking forward to being able to harvest most of our electricity from the lovely African sun!</p>
<p>I have one final bit of nerd-news, and it comes in the form of a</p>
<p>WHV pro-tip #23972847376: If you are doing data science(tm), or machine learning, or visualization, or any other dataset-oriented work, I can highly recommend <a href="https://dvc.org/">DVC, or DataVersionControl</a>. We have started using this on one of our projects to manage different collections of DICOM images, and it works incredibly well.</p>
<h2 id="extreme-health">Extreme health</h2>
<p>In conclusion, I would like to mention arecent and very <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2707428?resultClick=3">impressive study by the Cleveland Clinic about the correlation between cardiorespiratory fitness and all-cause mortality</a>.</p>
<p>Ill start with this quote:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>
    In this cohort study of 122007 consecutive patients undergoing exercise treadmill testing, cardiorespiratory fitness was inversely associated with all-cause mortality without an observed upper limit of benefit.
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Lets unpack that, as they say.</p>
<p>The researchers spent about 23 years measuring the cardiorespiratory fitness of just over 122 thousand subjects as they were running on a treadmill.</p>
<p>Measuring that many people gives your conclusions quite some statistical power. Also, the treadmill doesnt lie, as people will often do, inadvertently or not, when self-reporting their fitness level.</p>
<p>Whats also interesting to me is that they didnt observe any upper limit to the positive effect of fitness. Every additional amount of cardiorespiratory fitness, up to crazy levels, correlated with longer life.</p>
<p>The upshot of all of this is that theres really no excuse. That one most important thing we can do to live long and prosper is to exercise.</p>
<p>Its what Spock would have wanted.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/bettys_gravel_running.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/bettys_gravel_running-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Running on a dirt road in Bettys Bay. I love running on dirt roads, although on this particular morning I was already tired before I started. The tiredness unfortunately did not decrease. I think there might still have been some virus involved, or, more probably, just standard bad vacation habits involving craft beer in the evening."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Running on a dirt road in Bettys Bay. I love running on dirt roads, although on this particular morning I was already tired before I started. The tiredness unfortunately did not decrease. I think there might still have been some virus involved, or, more probably, just standard bad vacation habits involving craft beer in the evening.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>