<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Peter Hamilton on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/peter-hamilton/</link><description>Recent content in Peter Hamilton on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2014 12:40:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/peter-hamilton/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #83: Fallen Dragon</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/10/04/weekly-head-voices-83-fallen-dragon/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2014 12:40:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/10/04/weekly-head-voices-83-fallen-dragon/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m still trying to find my way home out of wild deadline country (WDC), so I hope you don&amp;rsquo;t mind (again) that I crunch together two weeks of weekly head voices during these few days of recharging. Because the post ended up being quite long, I&amp;rsquo;ve inserted headings. Feel free to read any, all or none of the parts!
Software babies out in the real world It&amp;rsquo;s great when that software system you&amp;rsquo;ve been designing gets used by real people in the real world. Check out this press release by the National Health Laboratory Service (NHLS): Together with the Council for Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR) they are building a national digital pathology database to improve pathology education nation-wide. Cool eh?!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I&rsquo;m still trying to find my way home out of wild deadline country (WDC), so I hope you don&rsquo;t mind (again) that I crunch together two weeks of weekly head voices during these few days of recharging. Because the post ended up being quite long, I&rsquo;ve inserted headings. Feel free to read any, all or none of the parts!</p>
<h2 id="software-babies-out-in-the-real-world">Software babies out in the real world</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s great when that software system you&rsquo;ve been designing gets used by real
people in the real world. Check out <a href="http://www.nhls.ac.za/?page=news&amp;id=4&amp;rid=398">this press
release</a> by the <a href="http://www.nhls.ac.za/">National Health Laboratory
Service (NHLS)</a>: Together with the <a href="http://www.csir.co.za/">Council
for Scientific and Industrial Research (CSIR)</a> they are building a national
digital pathology database to improve pathology education nation-wide. Cool
eh?!</p>
<p>See the screenshot at the bottom of the press release:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wpid-nhls_digital_morphology.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/wpid-nhls_digital_morphology.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>It&rsquo;s highly probable that the software you see running on the tablet and on the
screen behind it was programmed by the very fingers typing this blog post, and
their owner is stoked! I built it in very close collaboration with scientists
(friends in the meantime) at the CSIR (who work closely with the NHLS) and at
Stone Three. It&rsquo;s a whole suite of applications which I hope I can say more
about soon. (By the way, PYTHON. :)</p>
<h2 id="two-science-fiction-recommendations">Two science fiction recommendations</h2>
<p>I finished Peter Hamilton&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fallen_Dragon">Fallen Dragon</a>. I&rsquo;m a
sucker for space opera, and I thought that I&rsquo;d already read everything that
Hamilton wrote, but <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2014/08/07/weekly-head-voices-80-there-can-be-only-one/#comment-148198">regular
commenter and old friend R brought this one to my attention</a>. Some dollars
exchanged hands (well, actually I authorized a credit card transaction to pay
Amazon, but dollars changing hands sounds better) and I was off. It&rsquo;s a
stupendously enjoyable space opera where the human race finally goes next level
due to accidental contact with a sentient artefact of the most advanced space
race ever. Hamilton is sneaky, because between all of the interstellar
corporate &ldquo;asset realisation&rdquo;, and the plotting and scheming of
untouchable CEOs and the fighting of bionic soldiers, he manages to build a
&ldquo;boy meets girl boy loses girl forever but boy creates wormhole time loop
and against all odds finds his true love again at the end and gets to keep the
space ship&rdquo; story, by the end of which I had a slight eye-moisture
problem to contend with. Highly recommended!</p>
<p>Based on a random recommendation by <a href="http://twitter.com/xsyn">@xsyn</a>
on FB, I picked up and absolutely could not put down <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blindsight_(Watts_novel)">Blindsight</a> by
Peter Watts. Hard science fiction is awesome. I found this one intriguing
initiallly due to the promised plot of a mysterious alien incursion, then the
crazy mix of characters (narrator-protagonist with no emotion (more or less)
due to childhood brain surgery, a linguist with 4 cooperating split
personalities, a biologist with lab equipment wired directly into his
sensorium, an augmented soldier, and a vampire as a captain; in this book&rsquo;s
universe, vampires are a hyper-intelligent human sub-species who indeed used to
hunt humans), then aliens that are probbably ever more out there in terms of
weirdness than that of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solaris_(novel)">Solaris</a> by Stanislaw
Lem, and finally a mind-bending discussion on the very nature of consciousness
and sentience vs intelligence. The only little nitpick, is that at one point
Chernoff faces are employed as a serious visualization technique, an episode
during which I had to employ slightly more suspension of disbelief than usual.</p>
<h2 id="mark-shuttleworth-sticks-it-to-the-man">Mark Shuttleworth sticks it to the man!</h2>
<p>On October 1, 2014 the South African Supreme Court of Appeal found in favour of
Mark Shuttleworth in his case against the South African Reserve Bank (SARB). To
summarise: Mark Shuttleworth is a South African billionaire who made the first
big chunk of his wealth when he sold Thawte Consulting (for a large part the
product of his ingenuity and hard work) to Verisign.</p>
<p>In &lsquo;99, Shuttleworth had to emigrate, because SARB&rsquo;s archaic regulations were
making it unncessarily complicated to run an international business from within
SA. He then had to pay SARB more than R250 (about $25 million) in levies.</p>
<p>The court has just determined that this levy was unconstitutional and has
ordered SARB to pay it back with interest. Shuttleworth has announced that
he&rsquo;ll put this money in a trust, and that it will be used to uphold the
constitutional rights of citizens in court against the state, in South Africa
and in the rest of Africa.</p>
<p>In <a href="http://www.markshuttleworth.com/archives/1409">the statement on his blog</a>, he writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Banks profit from exchange controls, but our economy is stifled, and the most
vulnerable suffer most of all. Everything you buy is more expensive, South
Africans are less globally competitive, and cross-border labourers, already
vulnerable, pay the highest price of all – a shame we should work to address.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&hellip; and then further down:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The World Bank found that ‘remittance fees punish poor Africans&rsquo;. South
Africa scores worst of all, and according to the Payments Association of South
Africa and the Reserve Bank, this is ‘..mostly related to the regulations
that South African financial institutions needed to comply with, such as the
Financial Intelligence Centre Act (Fica) and exchange-control regulations.&rsquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In a very limited fashion I&rsquo;ve had to deal with the completely misguided
regulations of the SARB. Just receiving international payment (which should be
as smooth as possible!) is an unnecessarily painful process.</p>
<p>The most poignant bit from Shuttleworth&rsquo;s post was this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This case also has a very strong personal element for me, because it is
exchange controls which make it impossible for me to pursue the work I am most
interested in from within South Africa and which thus forced me to emigrate
years ago. I pursue this case in the hope that the next generation of South
Africans who want to build small but global operations will be able to do so
without leaving the country. In our modern, connected world, and our modern
connected country, that is the right outcome for all South Africans.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>SA has a great constitution. This gentleman is personally taking on the state
(and in this case specifically the SARB) to ensure that the regulations are in
line with the constitution, and South Africans are empowered to play their role
in international business. He deserves all the support we can give.</p>
<p>Thanks for listening peeps, and have a brilliant week!!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>