<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Advent of Code on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/advent-of-code/</link><description>Recent content in Advent of Code on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 17:57:35 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/advent-of-code/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #257: Untitled49.ipynb</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/12/08/weekly-head-voices-257-untitled49-ipynb/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2024 17:57:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/12/08/weekly-head-voices-257-untitled49-ipynb/</guid><description>This, the 257th edition of the WHV, covers the period of time from Monday November 25 to Sunday December 8, 2024.
The view right from our lunch table at Stellenbosch Reserve, Haskell Vineyard
Haskell vineyard has made previous appearances on this blog in WHV #99 in 2015, in WHV #181 in 2019 and perhaps in other posts. I strongly suspect that some of the good friends mentioned there were the same good friends we were so fortunate to spend this Sunday lunch with!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 257th edition of the WHV, covers the period of time from Monday November 25 to Sunday December 8, 2024.</p>








    


<figure><a href="stellenbosch_reserve_view_from_table.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/12/08/weekly-head-voices-257-untitled49-ipynb/stellenbosch_reserve_view_from_table_hu_628aabaa4fc4deb1.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/12/08/weekly-head-voices-257-untitled49-ipynb/stellenbosch_reserve_view_from_table_hu_26e1903f953321e3.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/12/08/weekly-head-voices-257-untitled49-ipynb/stellenbosch_reserve_view_from_table_hu_fba80af0d08785ec.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/12/08/weekly-head-voices-257-untitled49-ipynb/stellenbosch_reserve_view_from_table_hu_cdf93c7de6ffbf4b.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/12/08/weekly-head-voices-257-untitled49-ipynb/stellenbosch_reserve_view_from_table_hu_26e1903f953321e3.webp"
            

        
            alt="The view right from our lunch table at Stellenbosch Reserve, Haskell Vineyard"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view right from our lunch table at Stellenbosch Reserve, Haskell Vineyard</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Haskell vineyard has made previous appearances on this blog in <a href="/2015/08/23/weekly-head-voices-99-no-lands/">WHV #99 in 2015</a>, in <a href="/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/">WHV #181 in 2019</a> and perhaps in other posts. I strongly suspect that some of the good friends mentioned there were the same good friends we were so fortunate to spend this Sunday lunch with!</p>
<h2 id="why-im-definitely-not-taking-part-in-advent-of-code-2024">Why I&rsquo;m definitely not taking part in Advent of Code 2024</h2>
<p>I tried to <a href="/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/#advent-of-code-2020">explain The Advent of Code in WHV #211</a>, back in December of 2020 when I took part for the first time.</p>
<p>An extract from that explanation pertinent to this discussion is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To my non-programmer friends: Solving puzzles is like concentrated cat nip to programmers. In the case of AoC, you get unadulterated puzzle solving, and none of the other complications of writing production software.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The dark side of that property is that as the puzzles get more difficult and take up increasing amounts of time, the cat nip enjoyer can get locked in and have great difficulty even noticing that they are spending hours every day writing computer programmes when at first other people are working and later, down here, they are outside enjoying their summer vacation.</p>
<p>In 2020, I think it was on day 21 that I noticed after more than four hours on that day&rsquo;s puzzle that it was probably time to put down the keyboard.</p>
<p>Since then I have been carefully enjoying the first few days of each year&rsquo;s AoC, taking care to walk away when the cat nip becomes too strong.</p>
<p>This year I had resolved not to take part at all, as there are a number of important work projects and personal obligations to take care of.</p>
<p>However, my resolve broke on the first day when I thought &ldquo;What could be the harm in just taking a little peek?&rdquo;. That little peek led to a little solution, and then another, and then another day, and so on.</p>
<p>Anyways, as you can see from my <a href="https://bsky.app/hashtag/AdventOfCode?author=charlbotha.com">#AdventOfCode tagged posts on Bluesky</a>, I am not officially taking part, I&rsquo;m just submitting solutions every day.</p>
<p>On a more serious note: I am happy not to miss out on the AoC loads of fun, especially the banter and comparisons and learning on various chat groups, but I am really trying to keep a critical eye on the daily time expense. If it gets out of hand, I will walk away from the programmer cat nip.</p>
<p>P.S. Today was particularly fun, precisely because I managed to squeeze the puzzle in between more important activities. The little rush when I submitted part 2&rsquo;s solution minutes before we had to leave for lunch was exquisite.</p>
<blockquote class="bluesky-embed" data-bluesky-uri="at://did:plc:oy5vmr2vnff6yxs65hwgk5xq/app.bsky.feed.post/3lcsengeop22r" data-bluesky-cid="bafyreic3sip7ko7ice6gssjd5e57i7l7mbzkghwzp6dy24bee3m2texiza"><p lang="en">Today I was planning on extra vigorously NOT taking part in AoC because it&#x27;s Sunday: planning a long run followed by lunch with some of our best friends.
<p>Plans all happened, but in between I completed &quot;Resonant Collinearity&quot; - Day 8 - Advent of Code 2024 #AdventOfCode adventofcode.com/2024/day/8<br><br><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/did:plc:oy5vmr2vnff6yxs65hwgk5xq/post/3lcsengeop22r?ref_src=embed">[image or embed]</a></p>— Charl P. Botha | code, data-*, Emacs, running, humans (<a href="https://bsky.app/profile/did:plc:oy5vmr2vnff6yxs65hwgk5xq?ref_src=embed">@charlbotha.com</a>) <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/did:plc:oy5vmr2vnff6yxs65hwgk5xq/post/3lcsengeop22r?ref_src=embed">December 8, 2024 at 3:59 PM</a></blockquote><script async src="https://embed.bsky.app/static/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>
<h2 id="webp-ftw">WebP FTW</h2>
<p>Back in 2020, friend <a href="https://mentat.za.net/">Stéfan</a> and I <a href="/2020/05/02/drop-in-replacement-for-hugo-figure-shortcode-with-responsive-img-srcset/">hacked and slashed together a Hugo shortcode to render srcset images</a>.</p>
<p>In short, this adds multiple resolutions of each image in such a way that users download only what makes sense on their displays, often leading to faster page loading.</p>
<p>Fast forward 4 years as I try out <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebP">WebP</a> format images on this website (always for faster loading!) and run into a disappointingly long-standing bug in the Go standard library&hellip;</p>
<p>Another long story short, our <a href="https://gist.github.com/cpbotha/deb310eed14308fe26f7b7d0fabeb34d?permalink_comment_id=5299293">figure shortcode can now work around this bug</a> by displaying webp, but using png/jpg behind the scenes for all conversions, meaning most images should load faster for you.</p>
<p>The photo at the top of this post should have the WebP format, and thanks to srcset it should download lower resolution versions if you are on a smaller display.</p>
<h2 id="why-im-starting-to-write-these-more-regularly-in-hugo-vs-orgmode">Why I&rsquo;m starting to write these more regularly in Hugo vs Orgmode</h2>
<p>This is just a quick note to me, and perhaps others who occupy this same nanoscopic technical niche.</p>
<p>For the past few years, <a href="/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/#fantastic-blogging-tools-and-where-to-find-them">since May of 2020</a>, I&rsquo;ve been writing most of the WHV posts, and posts for my other blogs, in Emacs Orgmode, exporting them with the wonderful ox-hugo tool.</p>
<p>It made a great deal of sense to me (and it still does!) that my WHV entries were just entries in my monthly orgmode file.</p>
<p>However, sometimes when I go back to update a post from a few years back, some evolution in my orgmode configuration over the years complicates the orgmode to Hugo markdown process, and I&rsquo;m relegated to debugging the issue before I can get down to the actual update.</p>
<p>A year or two back, to lessen the impact of this problem, I started creating standalone org files for the WHVs. Whilst this certainly reduces the error surface, it&rsquo;s not as robust as editing the markdown directly, which I&rsquo;m doing right now.</p>
<p>Thanks for coming to my TED talk.</p>
<h2 id="on-waiting">On waiting</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>There&rsquo;s no such thing as waiting &ndash; only unexpected extra time to practice being present. &ndash; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Chozen_Bays">Jan Chozen Bays</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>P.S. In American English, practice is used both as verb and as noun, unlike British English which uses practice as a noun, and practise as the verb. Dr Bays is American, so I&rsquo;m keeping the spelling.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #212: Use it, or lose it</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 10:57:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/</guid><description>Well hello there folks, and welcome to the 212th edition of the Weekly Head Voices!
This one covers the two weeks from Monday December 7 to Sunday December 20, 2020. My end-of-year vacation started at some point during the period under investigation, so there&amp;rsquo;s not all that much to report here, except perhaps for a small philosophy message brought to you by the world of science.
Figure 1: View of the bridge over the mouth of the Steenbras River, taken from our anniversary hike up Steenbras Gorge to the Crystal Pools and back.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well hello there folks, and welcome to the 212th edition of the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This one covers the two weeks from Monday December 7 to Sunday December
20, 2020. My end-of-year vacation started at some point during the period under
investigation, so there&rsquo;s not all that much to report here, except perhaps for
a small philosophy message brought to you by the world of science.</p>










<figure><a href="bridge_steenbras_gorge.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu_cec6c22716d1ca02.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu_de962cb6c2cc6a35.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu_3d14cfb4d25829cc.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu_f056774007f40f97.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu_de962cb6c2cc6a35.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View of the bridge over the mouth of the Steenbras River, taken from our anniversary hike up Steenbras Gorge to the Crystal Pools and back."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View of the bridge over the mouth of the Steenbras River, taken from our anniversary hike up Steenbras Gorge to the Crystal Pools and back.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="my-advent-of-code-comes-to-an-end">My Advent of Code comes to an end</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/#advent-of-code-2020">WHV #211 that I was really enjoying the Advent of Code 2020</a>.</p>
<p>As I hinted there, I was happy to reach my modest goal of the double digits (i.e. day 10).</p>
<p>On day 20 however (which is of course December 20), the puzzle took up so much
of my time that I decided, with significant difficulty (remember these puzzles
are like cat nip for nerds), to drop out.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s been great fun, and I learned so much <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a> in such a short period, but at
some point one has to make the call whether the time cost is justified by the
fun and the learning.</p>
<p>P.S. It took about two days to finally let go. :)</p>
<h2 id="use-it-or-lose-it">Use it, or lose it</h2>
<p>I am currently reading the fascinating book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/51778153-livewired"><em>Livewired: The Inside Story of the
Ever-Changing Brain</em></a> by neuro-scientist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%5FEagleman">David Eagleman</a>.</p>
<p>As you can probably deduce from the title, this book is about how the brain
never stops rewiring itself.</p>
<p>Even now as you&rsquo;re reading these words, your brain is making and breaking
connections, and changing chemical balances, as it crunches through and
sometimes integrates the ideas that are invoked by this weird trick we humans
do, called <em>speech</em>, and the even weirder trick, called <em>writing</em>.</p>
<p>(Writing: Your retinae count the photons coming from the screen on which you&rsquo;re
reading this, construct patterns of darkness and light, convert those patterns
to words, and then string together those words into living, breathing
simulations of reality in your giant neural network.)</p>
<p>Besides functioning as an awe-inspiring exploration of the inner workings of
the brain and the nervous system, also for me with a little bit of existing
background, the book explains the phenomenon that inside the brain there is a
never-ending struggle between brain regions, between neurons and between the
thoughts that they store.</p>
<p>If you are blindfolded for a few days, your audio cortex will start annexing
parts of your visual cortex. If you&rsquo;re blindfolded for long enough (don&rsquo;t do
this), your visual cortex could be repurposed completely.</p>
<p>Neurons compete for incoming data, memories compete for neurons; it&rsquo;s a
continual fight for existence.</p>
<p>When a new, more important or more stressful memory arrives, it can push out,
into eternal oblivion, an older, less interesting memory.</p>
<p>If an input data stream like sight or hearing stops, another strong input
stream will take over those neurons. When you stop practising long division, or
algebraic simplification, you&rsquo;ll first start to get slower, and then later lose
that ability.</p>
<p>Those neurons have been repurposed.</p>
<p>(The book posits a really interesting hypothesis for why humans dream so
visually: Your eyes are closed for a large part of the day. Your visual cortex
would take a beating every night, i.e. be taken over by other parts of your
brain, if you didn&rsquo;t use it so actively during dreaming every night.)</p>
<p>You can probably see where this is going.</p>
<p>In the brain, just like in the rest of your human physiology, efficiency is
everything.</p>
<p>The moment you stop practising a certain function, like math, or absorbing
technical documents, or programming, or driving, or running, or being kind,
your system will start to try to repurpose as much as possible of the required
subsystems for other functions that you <em>are</em> actively deploying.</p>
<p>In short: <em>Use it, or lose it.</em></p>
<p>You&rsquo;re going to have to keep on practising all of the things you find important
until the day all of it stops for the last time.</p>
<p>This may seem quite harsh, but man, does it keep us honest.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #211: Table Mountain Run(ish)</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 15:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/</guid><description>Welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices friends!
These ones, the two hundred and eleventh (haha, remember at school you always wondered if anyone would ever really need to be able to write out numbers&amp;hellip; IT WAS ALL FOR ME) edition, will hopefully be talking more or less coherently about events that took place during the two weeks from Monday November 23 to Sunday December 6 of the year 2020.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices friends!</p>
<p>These ones, the two hundred and eleventh (haha, remember at school you always
wondered if anyone would ever really need to be able to write out numbers&hellip; IT
WAS ALL FOR ME) edition, will hopefully be talking more or less coherently
about events that took place during the two weeks from Monday November 23 to
Sunday December 6 of the year 2020.</p>










<figure><a href="table-mountain-20201204-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_hu_7c197f2c59cafb5f.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_hu_dd32fb0a8fcbc122.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_hu_2361eb185a117dda.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_hu_a4e9cd4fbee15845.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_hu_dd32fb0a8fcbc122.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Not the worst spot to eat one&rsquo;s peanut butter sandwiches"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Not the worst spot to eat one&rsquo;s peanut butter sandwiches</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">Wetware checklist to bootstrap your software checklist</h2>
<p>My <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">daily review</a> routine has been taking quite a beating.</p>
<p>The busier it gets, the more easily I somehow skip my whole daily review in the
morning thinking that I can better invest that time into just jumping on the
most urgent things first.</p>
<p>This is of course one of the stupidest things I can do at that point.</p>
<p>It doesn&rsquo;t help that the daily review contains quite a number of points I have
to take care of every morning.</p>
<p>So, what does one do to help sticking to your morning daily review habit?</p>
<p>Logically, one creates yet another, but this time smaller and hopefully more
robust, habit that triggers the larger habit!</p>
<p>(In the end, it&rsquo;s turtles all the way down in any case.)</p>
<p>The one redeeming factor in my morning routine has been the increasing
regularity of meditation exercise. (Thanks PK for putting me back on that
horse, or should I say <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/#shorter-focus-blocks-work-better">elephant</a>, and thanks to Sam Harris and his Waking Up
app.)</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;ve now added to my system is a smaller checklist with three items on it:</p>
<ol>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> meditation</li>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> deep reading</li>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> planning: review + task setting</li>
</ol>
<p>The difference is that this checkpoint now lives in my brain, and is much
harder to side-step. Also, because of the firmly embedded meditation kernel,
there&rsquo;s a bit of momentum to help me move on to items 2 and 3.</p>
<p>I sneaked in item 2, because reading is basically cheap but really powerful
cybernetic upgrades for normal humans, and I found that it nicely completes
this 30 minutes (or so) of quiet time in the morning before I start with work.</p>
<p>So far, this small addition to my firmware has made quite a positive impact,
although I have to admit that AoC (see further down) is temporarily interfering
with items 2 and/or 3.</p>
<p>Oh well, one just has to keep on keeping on.</p>
<h2 id="someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet-part-972387">Someone is wrong on the internet, part 972387</h2>
<p>Some of you (does 2 out of my total of 5 readers qualify as &ldquo;some of you&rdquo;,
relatively speaking?) will remember that I sometimes have a fraught
relationship with people being wrong on the internet, or you could just look up
<a href="/2014/07/01/weekly-head-voices-76-someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet/">WHV #76 to read about a previous episode</a>.</p>
<p>Most recently, I was again trying spectacularly unsuccessfully to avoid
twitter, when I ran into a thread where people were arguing about wearing
facemasks or not in these times.</p>
<p>My plan was to pull myself away from my phone, then throw the phone into the
fire, and then start the BBQ, but unfortunately one of the persons who was
arguing on the wrong side carries the same name as I do.</p>
<p>Although I am the <strong>one true Charl Botha</strong>, as is confirmed by the world&rsquo;s
premier reference on everything Charl Botha, namely the website <a href="https://charlbotha.com/">charlbotha.com</a>,
I was still worried that someone somewhere might confuse me with the third-rate
Charl Botha who was putting his lack of humanity on display.</p>
<p>My initial reaction was to go in there with all of my verbal guns blazing in
order to correct the poor sod, and to ensure that people would see there were
more Charls, some of which were not <em>as</em> bad, but fortunately some of the
psychology I have been absorbing from the literature kicked in on time and I
managed to limit my reply tweet to the fact that 1) I was in fact the real
Charl Botha (the one with a brain), and 2) that I thought one should wear a
mask because it&rsquo;s kind to other humans.</p>
<p>This made me think about the observation that mask deniers would always believe
that there were holes in the science of mask-wearing, when the most important
consideration comes down to the fact that even if mask-wearing helped your
fellow humans possibly only a little bit, it&rsquo;s already the kind thing to do.</p>
<p>After that, I made the following tweet to summarise my thinking on this topic:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Folks, remember that
of the 14 mask types tested in <a
href="https://t.co/BrQ6cpCnkk">https://t.co/BrQ6cpCnkk</a> (sensitive to
droplet size all the way down to 0.5um), 13 of them reduced droplet
transmission relative to no mask. SO: Be kind. Wear a multi-layer mask, reduce
droplets, help your fellow humans. <a
href="https://t.co/COyrdksV9K">pic.twitter.com/COyrdksV9K</a></p>&mdash; Charl
Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a
href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1332014932481732608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November
26, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>What I learned from this would-be altercation, is that it&rsquo;s better for me to
focus my someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet rage into something that&rsquo;s more
constructive:</p>
<p>Strip the issue down as far as you can. Inject information. Combine that with
the desire that many humans share for a society where we can all just get
along.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s probably still not going to work, but just maybe, it&rsquo;ll cause less trouble
and result in a little bit more goodwill, and who knows where that may lead?</p>
<p>P.S. On the topic of mask-wearing: Even if there were no COVID-19, don&rsquo;t you
think we&rsquo;d all be a little better of if the wearing of good masks became the
norm?</p>
<p>There are indications that <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/flu-season-never-came-to-the-southern-hemisphere1/">mask-wearing and physical distancing basically
stopped flu season in the Southern Hemisphere</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Never in my 40-year career have we ever seen rates &hellip; so low</p>
<p>&ndash; Greg Poland, influenza expert at the Mayo Clinic</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="advent-of-code-2020">Advent of Code 2020</h2>
<p>Thanks to this tweet by <a href="https://twitter.com/RameezKhanSA">@RameezKhanSA</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My pledge this year is
to do the <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/AdventOfCode?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#AdventOfCode</a>
in <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Clojure?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Clojure</a>. Looking
forward to it. Already started doing some of last years challenges. Want to
keep it simple. No Leiningen just a plain deps.edn.</p>&mdash; Rameez
(@RameezKhanSA) <a
href="https://twitter.com/RameezKhanSA/status/1332692669190074370?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November
28, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; I am taking part, for the first time, in <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">the Advent of Code</a>!</p>
<p>Nerds from the world over get a new two-part programming puzzle every day at 5
AM UTC, from December 1 to December 25, for a total of 50 puzzles.</p>
<p>The idea is that said nerds use any programming language, or combination of
programming languages, to solve the puzzles and enter the answers on the AoC
website.</p>
<p>The quickest nerds, the ones who manage to solve these puzzles in an amazing
minute or three, earn a highly-coveted place on the <a href="https://adventofcode.com/2020/leaderboard">leaderboard</a>.</p>
<p>Just like Rameez, I wanted to use the AoC to get to know a programming language
better, although in my case that language is Nim.</p>
<p>So far, this has been a great deal of fun!</p>
<p>To my non-programmer friends: Solving puzzles is like concentrated cat nip to
programmers. In the case of AoC, you get unadulterated puzzle solving, and none
of the other complications of writing production software.</p>
<p>Besides the fun, Nim <em>really</em> shines at this. As I mentioned in <a href="/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/#save-image-from-clipboard">the previous
WHV</a>, Nim somehow manages to combine the expressivity and development velocity
of Python, with a great dollop of Python&rsquo;s famed batteries-included, with close
to the metal performance.</p>
<p>(My brain is currently spending background cycles figuring out if I could
somehow use this in a product.)</p>
<p>I am sort of expecting to drop out eventually, because, based on past years,
it&rsquo;s going to take up an increasing amount of time.</p>
<p>However, although I&rsquo;m already happy with what I have (day 6&rsquo;s puzzles completed
on Sunday December 6, ostensibly the end of this WHV&rsquo;s window of reality), I
would be really chuffed reaching the double digits!</p>
<p><em>Narrator: He ended up reaching the double digits.</em></p>
<h2 id="table-mountain-run--ish--2020">Table Mountain Run(ish) 2020</h2>
<p>We thought we were going to do a trail run up Skeleton Gorge.</p>
<p>Well, if one is us, one does not simply run up Skeleton Gorge. Instead, one
huffs and one puffs, for about a kilometre of ascent. It is a substantial
amount of huffing and puffing.</p>
<p>We did get to run on top of the mountain, from the beach at the top of Skeleton
Gorge (yes, there&rsquo;s a beach), to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maclear%27s%5FBeacon">Maclear&rsquo;s Beacon</a>, which I&rsquo;ve now learned was
used in the calculation of the curvature of he Earth, to the old cable station,
past the reservoirs to end up walking really slowly back down Nursery Gorge.</p>
<p>It was an interesting observation that although I found parts of the route hard
and sometimes maybe even a little unpleasant (coming down Nursery Gorge&hellip;)
whilst in the thick of things, the whole memory of the experience started
transmogrifying into <em>wonderful</em> verging on <em>magical</em> extremely soon after we
had reached the finish.</p>
<p>12/10 would do again, but next time a more gradual descent please!</p>
<h2 id="hi-mom">Hi mom</h2>
<p>My mom has now seen three quarters of a century.</p>
<p>I am happy to report that she is as fit as a fiddle. Genetics and some really
great habits are a really solid combination.</p>
<p>Importantly, we are truly fortunate to count her as an integral part of our
household.</p>
<p>(Them is some big words for: We have so much fun together! Our GOUs, who are
also her GOUs, will probably never forget these stories with their Oma.)</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s to the next quarter century!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve convinced her of the great business opportunity of publishing a book at
100 with tips and tricks for other (aspirant) centenarians, so she really needs
to remain as sharp and as fit as she is today!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>