<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Priorities on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/priorities/</link><description>Recent content in Priorities on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2022 14:32:13 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/priorities/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #243: Part-time role-model</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 22:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/</guid><description>Welcome back friends, welcome back me!
This WHV covers the multiple weeks from Monday May 23 to Sunday June 19, 2022.
It is this late, because it has been super busy at work (and at home), and by the time that I get any sort of opportunity to write, I am often too tired to focus.
I hope to say something about that a bit further down.
Whatever the case may be, I am happy to be here now, focusing on this post draft right here.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends, welcome back me!</p>
<p>This WHV covers the <em>multiple</em> weeks from Monday May 23 to Sunday June 19, 2022.</p>
<p>It is this late, because it has been super busy at work (and at home), and by
the time that I get any sort of opportunity to write, I am often too tired to
focus.</p>
<p>I hope to say something about that a bit further down.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am happy to be here now, focusing on this post
draft right here.</p>










<figure><a href="20220616-bettys-walk-famjam.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_hu_156b08f26b3223f1.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_hu_167c5cca0f87788c.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_hu_4baf08f736812d13.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_hu_8f58b8ddbbfae8a2.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_hu_167c5cca0f87788c.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a walk in Betty&rsquo;s Bay with the fam-jam."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Scene from a walk in Betty&rsquo;s Bay with the fam-jam.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="a-drop-in-the-bucket-is-a-drop-in-the-bucket">A drop in the bucket is a drop in the bucket</h2>
<p>After taking a critical look at my discord subscription (I&rsquo;m too old for
animated emojis anyways), I decided to cancel that, and rather switch to
(small) monthly subscriptions to two services I find really important: <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">Signal</a>
(the private messaging app; I activated the sub via Apple) and <a href="https://donate.wikimedia.org/wiki/Ways_to_Give">Wikipedia</a>.</p>
<p>#feelsgoodman</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not that I have piles of cash to give away every month (come back in 6
months, hopefully that mythical ship will have come in), but I learned at a
recent course on the topic that it is possible, and even prudent, to review
critically and design with intent one&rsquo;s strategy of giving.</p>
<p>What do you find important, and which organizations appear to be applying their
resources effectively towards the furthering of their (and your) principles?</p>
<p>In that same vein, I subscribe (at the cheapest tier until ship comes in, see
above) to one of the <a href="https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/">better local news sources</a>, although their articles are
available for free online. We live in a society&hellip; where functional and honest
journalism is crucially important.</p>
<h2 id="tip-the-tailscale">tip the tailscale</h2>
<p>Some time back, a friend from work suggested tailscale as a tool to connect
computers and devices, separated by firewalls, into a virtual private network</p>
<p>My brain helpfully surfaced this information about three weeks back when I
wondered if there was a less painful way to connect to my home network from
work via the OpenVPN server on my home router.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that there&rsquo;s a <em>delightfully smooth</em> way to connect the
devices that you own together into a secure network, no matter behind which
firewalls they might be hiding.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s called <a href="https://tailscale.com/">tailscale</a>.</p>
<p>Within five minutes (literally) I had five of my devices hooked up, and
suddenly I was able to make point-to-point wireguard connections from anywhere
to anywhere, often via two firewalls, without having to click any buttons.</p>
<p>Each device is automatically assigned a &ldquo;static&rdquo; <code>100.*.*.*</code> IP number, and
hostnames can even be setup via tailscale MagicDNS, which is currently the
switching of a single toggle.</p>
<h2 id="typescript-with-emacs-and-tree-sitter">TypeScript with Emacs and tree-sitter</h2>
<p>In spite of the fact that I mostly use Visual Studio Code for my programming
these days (Emacs is for everything else), a question on reddit&rsquo;s <code>/r/emacs</code>
caused me to go down the Emacs-TypeScript-and-tree-sitter rabbit-hole.</p>
<p>I wrote up most of the results of this adventure a vxlabs post titled
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/06/12/typescript-development-with-emacs-tree-sitter-and-lsp-in-2022/">TypeScript development with Emacs, tree-sitter and LSP in 2022</a>.</p>
<p>After years of hearing its name mentioned, this was my first real contact with
tree-sitter, which turns out to be a fascinating recent development in
interactive source code parsing.</p>
<p>Thanks to tree-sitter, which was developed by the Atom editor team at GitHub,
and the combination of LSP and Microsoft&rsquo;s typescript compiler, Emacs (just
like other open source editors), gets access to state-of-the-art code
intelligence.</p>
<h2 id="when-the-going-gets-tough-double-down-on-the-side-projects">When the going gets tough, double-down on the side-projects</h2>
<p>If anything, this is a note to myself, but maybe also to you.</p>
<p>As evidenced by the lateness of this post and the one before it, the weekly
head voices had to take a backseat to other priorities.</p>
<p>However, writing posts on this here blog is one of <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#learning-at-the-burning">my &ldquo;show up to every day&rdquo;
things</a>, and so the fact that my frequency is currently reduced probably has
nothing to do with <a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">the general rickety raft of shifting life directions and
priorities</a>, but is indeed due to more urgent work sneakily taking precedence.</p>
<p>I have deliberately chosen the word &ldquo;sneakily&rdquo;, because when I start actually
paying attention (an activity the frequency of which is ironically also reduced
due to above-mentioned business), I realise that under these circumstances it
becomes even more important to buckle down and make time for the side-projects.</p>
<p>I could waste time on YouTube and reddit, or I could apply some intent and
create something interesting that is deliberately outside the broad umbrella of
work.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not that I don&rsquo;t like work (I love it), but rather spending that
carved-out time on side-projects is invigorating, and boosts creativity.</p>
<p>P.S. I like YouTube too, but it&rsquo;s time:leisure ratio (I recently coined that
term in a discussion with GOU#1 about her instagram usage) is not great.</p>
<h2 id="part-time--role--model">Part-time (role-)model</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve discussed the following with a small number of friends (some of them my
mentors; haha who am I kidding, they&rsquo;re all my mentors) over the years, so it
must be correct.</p>
<p>What I have learned over time, is that all of us are role models for fellow
humans at various (hopefully high) points in time, but we won&rsquo;t know when and
we often won&rsquo;t know for whom.</p>
<p>This knowledge has more than one important implication.</p>
<p>Firstly, we can never stop trying to be good humans, because we don&rsquo;t know who
might be depending on us at that moment.</p>
<p>This is reminiscent <a href="/2008/11/17/what-i-did-this-err-summer/">one of my favourite quotes, this one by Plato</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Be kind, for everyone you meet is fighting a hard battle.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Secondly, we will always have those ups and those downs, and often it will feel
like the ratio is hopelessly in the wrong direction.</p>
<p>I have explained to my children (my most important mentees, also the ones that
seem to pay the least attention) that athough I often fail, I will always keep
on trying.</p>
<p>Finally, even my own amazing mentors are humans who have ups and downs.</p>
<p>I love them for who they are, but I remember them at their best.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>