<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Ox-Pandoc on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/ox-pandoc/</link><description>Recent content in Ox-Pandoc on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 11:19:21 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/ox-pandoc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Sunday 2023-12-24</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/31/daily-head-voices-on-sunday-2023-12-24/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 11:19:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/31/daily-head-voices-on-sunday-2023-12-24/</guid><description> Christmas Eve everyone! Just realized that my trick of setting default-dir does work for the temporary org file and output html file that ox-pandoc creates, but of course all image links will break, as they are relative to the actual location of the source org files. 😭 (this means I will have to redo everything via the temporary buffer after all) A simply brilliant late afternoon at the beach with the whole family, and even squeezed in a short barefoot run on the beach. Car battery was so much on the edge that a phone forgotten on the USB charge cable managed to push it over said edge, and so car refused to start. A minute or two before a friend arrived with jumper leads, a random kind stranger with a truck and jumper leads offered to help and did! I do need to emphasise what a sublime day this was. So much joy!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Christmas Eve everyone!</li>
<li>Just realized that my trick of setting <code>default-dir</code> does work for the temporary org file and output html file that <code>ox-pandoc</code> creates, but of course all image links will break, as they are relative to the actual location of the source org files. 😭 (this means I will have to redo everything via the temporary buffer after all)</li>
<li>A simply brilliant late afternoon at the beach with the whole family, and even squeezed in a short barefoot run on the beach.</li>
<li>Car battery was so much on the edge that a phone forgotten on the USB charge cable managed to push it over said edge, and so car refused to start. A minute or two before a friend arrived with jumper leads, a random kind stranger with a truck and jumper leads offered to help and did!</li>
<li>I do need to emphasise what a sublime day this was. So much joy!</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>