<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>barefoot on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/barefoot/</link><description>Recent content in barefoot on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 07:01:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/barefoot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #161: Email Equilibrium.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 07:01:08 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/</guid><description> Welcome to the one hundred and sixty first edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looking back at the week from Sunday January 27 to Sunday February 3, 2018.
I am writing this draft in a markdown file, using good old Emacs, during an early morning session (more about that later), because I am still not really loving the Gutenberg block-based editor experience in WordPress 5.0.
Today, I have three stories:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/screenshot_2019-01-31_06-16-47.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/screenshot_2019-01-31_06-16-47.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to the one hundred and sixty first edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looking back at the week from Sunday January 27 to Sunday February 3, 2018.</p>
<p>I am writing this draft in a markdown file, using good old Emacs, during an early morning session (more about that later), because I am still <a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/#btw-1-why-i-dont-yet-like-the-new-wordpress-editor">not really loving the Gutenberg block-based editor experience in WordPress 5.0</a>.</p>
<p>Today, I have three stories:</p>
<h2 id="running-inspiration">Running inspiration</h2>
<p>After a <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#running">month-long normal-shoe-person hiatus</a> at the end of last year which again led to tender ankles, I realised (I’m a slow realiser, ok?) that it’s not the shoes but the person in the shoes.</p>
<p>Because it seemed that the shoes initially offered some relief, I reflexively started increasing distance and speed until my ankles started complaining again.</p>
<p>Durnit!</p>
<p>I then chatted with an erstwhile collaborator who is now, besides still being a successful tech entrepreneur, a successful sandal-wearing ultra runner and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leadville_Trail_100">Leadville Trail 100 mile finisher</a>.</p>
<p>He gave great advice, especially with regard to continuously training complementary muscle groups so that they can better contribute to the whole running mechanism.</p>
<p>Perhaps more importantly (to me) than that, was simply knowing that someone with a history, mechanism and control system not too dissimilar from mine, including the flat feet, runs so far with much joy.</p>
<p>Shortly after the chat, friend LM sent me <a href="https://runrepeat.com/arch-support-study">this highly interesting Run Repeat survey of 150+ studies about arch support</a>.</p>
<p>Amongst other things, it again confirmed what we know about barefoot and minimalist runners running with less impact and more efficiency, two ideas that I really like.</p>
<p>All of this led to me getting back on my Lunas, and my Xeros, and my bare feet.</p>
<p>I have been keeping the distances shorter, and my pace lower.</p>
<p>Initial results are encouraging.</p>
<p>P.S. Of course that survey does not come with a simple answer. However, the quote at the end by itself is worth the price of admission:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>
    If you don’t need an arch support, you probably shouldn’t use one. It is the equivalent of wearing a cast when you don’t have a stress fracture or broken bone. Why would you do that? The best forms of injury prevention are make sure your body is balanced in strength, mobility and flexibility, you are training smart and getting good sleep and nutrition. An arch support affects only one aspect of the body. Don’t forget the big picture.
  </p>
<p>
    A FAR cheaper and more long term solution? Work on you arch, foot and hip strength!!! That is where you are supposed to get “arch support” from. Not some shoe insert. Work on your posterior tibialis, fibularis longus, single leg balance, proprioception, gluteal strength, core strength, body alignment, etc.
  </p>
<p>
<cite>﻿<a href="http://www.doctorsofrunning.com/">Dr Mathew Klein</a></cite>
</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="earlyish-morning-sessions">Early(ish) morning sessions</h2>
<p>It usually takes us until about 20:30 and often up to about 21:00 when all of our GOUs are finally in their beds. There’s a spread of 10 years between the oldest and the youngest, so there’s a wide range of themes and activities keeping us busy until that hour.</p>
<p>In my younger days (ack!) I used to be able to switch my work brain back on at that time, and work quite productively for a few hours.</p>
<p>(It is of course also possible that I just don’t remember this too well. Who knows what’s real anymore?!)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, it seems that I wrote blog posts, did some more reading and learning, and was generally productive.</p>
<p>More recently however, I’ve noticed that my work brain simply refuses to come back online at nine.</p>
<p>In order to work around this issue, my awake brain devised a plan, during the daylight hours of course.</p>
<p>Instead of trying to force poor work-brain to continue working, I go to bed at 22:00 and set my alarm for 5:30 (the optimal amount of sleep these days is 7.5 hours <em>exactly</em>). It does not seem like much, but I have an extra 50 minutes to an hour of <em>crystal clear</em> time in the mornings before the rest of the family wakes up to start the day.</p>
<p>(I also used to do this in 2012 when we were finishing The Visual Computing in Medicine Book. In Dutchie-land, the kids go to school much later, so I had even more time in the mornings.)</p>
<p>I usually start the morning with a little mindfulness exercise from the Waking Up course (extremely high-stress double-project-lead duties in 2013 were the catalyst that got me into mindfulness and early morning practices in the first place!), then I do <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">the day planner</a>, and <em>then</em> I take care of one or two important activities, the selection of which is usually clear after the day planning.</p>
<p>(It has not escaped me that this whole exercise is quite reminiscent of HN’s <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4166183">startup founder daily routine parody</a>. :).</p>
<p>This morning, I get to write the words you are currently reading, with a clear(ish) mind to boot.</p>
<p>Whether this is just novelty, I don’t know yet, but it currently does seem as if starting the day with a bit of quiet and focus increases the probability the rest of my day at the office also starts more productively.</p>
<h2 id="inbox-under-control-what-is-happening">Inbox under control. WHAT IS HAPPENING?!</h2>
<p>In the old days, I used to be a fan of <a href="/tag/inbox-zero/">inbox zero</a>.</p>
<p>However, due to life stubbornly not adhering to <a href="https://lifehacker.com/merlin-mann-presents-inbox-zero-282544">Merlin Mann’s view of email</a> (quite poetically, it seems that the <a href="http://inboxzero.com">inboxzero.com website</a> is currently down), I eventually ended up with 1000+ unread emails in my inbox. (I know people with multiples of that…)</p>
<p>The term <em>email bankruptcy</em> (shudder) had even come up once or twice in conversations with friends.</p>
<p>Whoops.</p>
<p>I wrote <a href="/2014/04/29/weekly-head-voices-69-no-sugar-added/">back in WHV #69</a> that there seemed to be an inverse correlation between my creativity and inbox-zero.</p>
<p>I still think there is something to be said for that observation.</p>
<p>One can definitely get sucked into busy-work, a prime example of which is the grooming of one’s email, wasting time and energy that could far better be invested in creative pursuits.</p>
<p>However, could it be possible in some situations that one’s email landscape has changed in such a way that it has suddenly become tractable to maintain inbox-zero with a creativity-friendly and entirely affordable amount of energy?</p>
<p>Could it be that because one has let email slip so long, people don’t send as much email anymore, and now one paradoxically has the opportunity to reclaim inbox zero?</p>
<p>It seems it can be.</p>
<p>On January 31, at the tail end of that day’s early morning session, I was staring incredulously at the words:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-default">
<p>
    This Folder is Empty.
  </p>
<p>
<cite>my inbox</cite>
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t want to call this inbox zero, because it’s not 2007 anymore Dorothy.</p>
<p>Let’s go for Email Equilibrium Startup Founder Parody instead.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Friends, thank you for reading this.</p>
<p>I am looking forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #148: Data stylist.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 07:22:30 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/</guid><description> Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)
This post covers the week from Monday July 9 to Sunday July 15.
The business part of my week was unfairly dominated by far too much after-work obsessing over programming languages, with which I seem to have an unhealthy (or perhaps not) obsession.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/drakenstein_trail.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/drakenstein_trail-1024x241.jpg"
        
            alt="Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This post covers the week from Monday July 9 to Sunday July 15.</p>
<p>The business part of my week was unfairly dominated by far too much after-work obsessing over programming languages, with which I seem to have an unhealthy (or perhaps not) obsession.</p>
<p>I will externalise some of these thoughts further down in this post.</p>
<p>I’m starting with a weekend / running update, which should be reasonably safe for non-nerds to read. However, after that, the nerd dial will go up to 11 with stuff about tools and programming languages right up to the end of the post.</p>
<p>I would have wanted to use the adjective “face-melting”, but I’m not sure if any intensity of nerdery could ever reach that level.</p>
<p>We can dream.</p>
<h1 id="weekend-running-update">Weekend running update</h1>
<p>Most fortunately the weekend had other plans and supplied us with at least 2.5 parties, the first of which even culminated in a <em>ridiculously</em> fun trail run in the mountains on the winter morning after.</p>
<p>The winter morning sun was just perfect, the company was great, and I had forgotten all forms of performance tracking devices at home.</p>
<p>Readers with bionic eyes might notice the Lunas on my feet.</p>
<p>I have now ran just over 260km in them, but, in a surprise twist to the regular readers of this blog, my biological equipment has still not yet completely adjusted to the new style of locomotion.</p>
<p>The latest victim seems to be one of Tom, Dick and Harry, the tendons running under the medial <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malleolus">malleolus</a> of my left foot, also known as that big knob on your inside ankle. Tom (the primary suspect in this case according to Trail Friend #1 who is knowledgable with regard to these matters, being a running foot surgeon and all), Dick and Harry <a href="https://radiopaedia.org/articles/posterior-ankle-tendons-mnemonic">are also known as the *T*ibialis posterior, flexor *D*igitorum longus and the flexor *H*allucis longus</a>.</p>
<p>They currently have to work extra hard to stabilise my feet while running, because, you know, no shoes.</p>
<p>Because doing this thing was not hard enough already, and because the Lunas are perhaps still a bit too cushiony, and because my friend the Very Flat Cat forgot that I’m very suggestible after 11:00 in the morning when my prefrontal cortex takes the rest of the day off, I am now also the very shy owner of a pair of <a href="https://xeroshoes.com/shop/genesis/genesis-men/">Xero Genesis running sandals</a>:</p>
<p><img src="https://xeroshoes.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/Genesis_Limeade-3-4-770x500.jpg" alt="Image result for xero genesis"></p>
<p>The soles are only 5mm thick, and quite hard, being <a href="https://xeroshoes.com/warranty/">rated for a few thousand miles</a> and all. The upshot of this is that one’s feet have to work even harder than in the Lunas.</p>
<p>My first run in these was amazing: I could feel my feet reacting to every little pebble, and my running style having to adapt even more to the terrain.</p>
<p>However, there was a price to pay for all of that additional terrain feel (and the fact that I took a much longer maiden run than I should have): The next day, the tendons in my feet felt even more (ab)used than usual.</p>
<p>WITH GREAT POWER COMES GREAT RESPONSIBILITY, it seems.</p>
<p>Due to these shoes being so powerful, I have had to resign to introducing Xero running far more gradually than I had initially thought.</p>
<h1 id="vacation-based-thinking-driven-tool-sharpening-aka-the-wvv-2018-data-science-toolboxtm">Vacation-based-thinking-driven tool sharpening aka The WVV 2018 Data Science Toolbox(tm).</h1>
<p>During the <a href="/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/">previously blogged-about</a> Mpumalanga vacation, the lack of alarms, devices, and other work accoutrements, resulted in there being ample time for staring-into-space-grade thinking sessions.</p>
<p>During one of these thinking sessions, I realised that I had somehow neglected my data science toolbox for a while.</p>
<p>At some point a few years back, I was so into ipython notebooks (what has now become jupyter) that I used them as my main work lab notes modality.</p>
<p>However, in the meantime I had fallen slightly out of love with the computational notebook style of data programming, because I had begun to develop doubts about their role in the analysis pipeline.</p>
<p><strong>interlude 1:</strong> <em>jupyter notebooks are nice for initial data exploration, and they’re especially useful for remote computation with embedded graphics. However, that initial momentum of discovery risks devolving into an unwieldy monolith of code snippets, data transformations and experiments. There’s a fine line to be walked between flexible experimentation on the one hand, and version-controlled, time-stamped, permutational and scientific rigour on the other.</em></p>
<p><strong>interlude 2:</strong> <em>I have to apologise for using the term “data science” in a non-comedic context. In spite of the inherent humour, it has turned into a usable blanket term for computational data understanding.</em></p>
<p>Due to my growing doubts in the order of Jupyter, and due to being occupied with less traditionally data sciencey work projects, I had unfortunately let my data science toolbox gather perhaps a bit too much dust.</p>
<p>Slightly more worrying than falling out of love with the Jupyter Notebooks (I still like them, I’m just not that madly in love anymore), was the more specific issue that I’d even let the datavis parts get a bit dusty.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Although I should probably write a more complete post about this, here is the list of ingredients of the official <em><strong>2018 WHV Data Science Toolbox(tm)</strong></em>:</p>
<h2 id="programming-language-and-library-ecosystem-python">Programming language and library ecosystem: Python.</h2>
<p>This language, in spite of its shortcomings, <em>dominates</em> the data science / machine learning world thanks to its STELLAR ecosystem.</p>
<p>numpy, pandas, scipy, scikit-*, tensorflow, pytorch, keras, cython… this snowball has turned into a pretty sizeable planet.</p>
<p>For this reason, it would be hard to justify any other choice for data science.</p>
<p>However, since I’ve been seeing more of Lisp and the rest of the ever-expanding programming language landscape, I can see (Python’s shortcomings as a programming language) clearly now.</p>
<p>In terms of interactive programming, Python beats the majority of practical programming languages, with Common Lisp being one notable exception.</p>
<p>However, it’s not functional enough, which engenders unnecessarily imperative, side-effecting code.  More specifically, it’s not expression-oriented.</p>
<p>More about this slightly further down. Maybe.</p>
<h2 id="datavis-anything-as-long-as-its-vega-or-vega-lite">Datavis: Anything, as long as it’s Vega or Vega-Lite.</h2>
<p>I spent a few years of my life wrangling <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a>, down to INNARD-LEVEL.</p>
<p>Mike Bostock’s idea of <a href="https://bost.ocks.org/mike/join/">data-element-joins</a> is genius, and internalising it was intellectually satisfying.</p>
<p>I thought that these d3 skillz would serve me well for decades (that’s WEEKS in javascript-time), but it turns out that there’s a new, even smarter kid in town.</p>
<p>(if it’s any consolation, the new kid can be considered the grand-child of d3.js.)</p>
<p><a href="https://vega.github.io/">vega and vega-lite</a> are so-called visualization grammars, or visualization DSLs (domain specific languages).</p>
<p>The upshot is that one codes up a chart, or a whole set of linked charts and their interactive behaviour, using a language that was designed for this purpose.</p>
<p>This chart code can be easily shared, or converted into interactive visual representations that can be embedded in applications, online or in print quality documents.</p>
<p>Genius!</p>
<p>With <a href="https://altair-viz.github.io/">Altair</a>, you can even send your pandas dataframes to vega and vega-lite charts all from the comfort of your slightly defective Python armchair.</p>
<h2 id="development-environment-pycharm">Development Environment: PyCharm.</h2>
<p>You knew it was not going to be Jupyter Notebooks, but you probably expected it to be <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tag/emacs/">Emacs</a>.</p>
<p>Well it’s not. Surprise!</p>
<p>The remote interpreter support in PyCharm enables me to connect to a Python virtual environment anywhere on the planet, which I often do.</p>
<p>The JetBrains wizards have optimised the remote communication of code intelligence, so completion, documentation and general code understanding is almost indistinguishable from that on a completely local project.</p>
<p>Being able to step through a <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/12/08/variational-autoencoder-in-pytorch-commented-and-annotated/"><em>remote</em> PyTorch neural network training iteration with the PyCharm debugger</a> or any other remote Python algorithmics is insightful.</p>
<p>Two notable drawbacks are visualization and long-running jobs.</p>
<p>For the long-running jobs I do tend to use Jupyter Notebooks or when at all possible <a href="https://mosh.org/">mosh</a>, which is amazing. However, because the primary modality is not the notebook, my code is versioned and organised into separate libraries which I can call into from notebook or mosh.</p>
<p>For visualization, it’s either connecting to the altair chart server via SSH pipe, dumping the chart to the unison-synced project, and/or a Jupyter Notebook.</p>
<h2 id="the-rest">The rest.</h2>
<p>Of course you use Postgres on an SSD for your data, and of course you know enough SQL to make short work of most of the heavy-weight transformations often required at the start your data crunching pipeline.</p>
<p>For all of my lab notes, reports, books, papers and blog posts, I use <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tag/orgmode/">Emacs Org mode</a>.</p>
<p>LaTeX math with live preview, live code snippets, SVG graphics, bibtex references, export to anything. This is one of the best ways to document your science.</p>
<h1 id="programming-language-addiction-update">Programming language addiction update.</h1>
<p>I spend far too much obsessing over programming languages, old and new.</p>
<p>For the past two weeks, I wasted even more precious time than usual reading up about programming languages.</p>
<p>Because I would really like to spend more of my time on other, perhaps more valuable activities, I’ve been trying to better define what it is I’m actually looking for.</p>
<p>Of course there is no single best programming language, but a whole set of good languages that map in intricate ways to different problem domains.</p>
<p>In spite of this, I have been pining for a language with, in order of importance:</p>
<ol>
<li>A Functional Programming DNA, with which I’m referring to a) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expression-oriented_programming_language">expression-orientedness</a>, b) a preference for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pure_function">pure functions</a>, and at a higher level, c) the modelling of reality as more or less explicit dataflows.</li>
<li>Interactive programming, with Common Lisp being the textbook example of this.</li>
<li>Great tooling and IDEs, meaning first-class support by something from JetBrains, Microsoft or Emacs.</li>
<li>Great concurrency and parallelism stories.</li>
<li>A great library ecosystem.</li>
<li>Modest memory use.</li>
</ol>
<p>Having just explicitly written this down for the first time (!! – it was consuming so much glucose just being kept amorphously swirling around in my brain) I can now mentally map some of my most recent language dalliances to these points.</p>
<h2 id="go">go</h2>
<p>This language is far too simple for my taste, but probably really great for teams.</p>
<p>I did recently take a more serious look when <a href="https://tutorials.botsfloor.com/develop-your-own-telegram-bot-with-golang-and-tbot-de726883b83c">setting up a telegram bot using tbot</a> and being amazed at how simple it was building web services like these using goroutines and channels.</p>
<p>Go satisfies points 3 to 6 from the list above. Makes sense that I decided to file this experiment away under “check when you need to put a webservice together REALLY QUICKLY”.</p>
<h2 id="rust">rust</h2>
<p>When I saw up that rust, surprisingly, is an expression-oriented language, I flew through the O’Reilly Programming Rust book I had bought previously as part of a bundle.</p>
<p>Evaluating rust by the list above, we award it a fractional 1 because expression-oriented, 3 due to jetbrains plugin amongst others, 4(ish) – great memory safety, but compared to clojure, concurrency and parallelism stories still have much room to grow, a solid 5 thanks to cargo and a very strong 6.</p>
<p>I filed this one away under “re-evaluate whenever you reach for your trusty C++”. (also, <a href="https://github.com/actix/actix-web">actix-web</a> looks amazing for super high performance microservices.)</p>
<h2 id="f">f#</h2>
<p>You didn’t see this one coming, did you?</p>
<p>Very strong 1 to 5 and a solid 6.</p>
<p>WAT?!</p>
<p>I’m currently working my way through <a href="https://pragprog.com/book/swdddf/domain-modeling-made-functional">Domain Modeling Made Functional</a> by Scott Wlaschin, who is also the author of the brilliant <a href="https://fsharpforfunandprofit.com/">f# for fun and profit</a> website.</p>
<p>In addition to f# hitting all 6 of my 2018 PL-requirements above, I’m slowly starting to see the advantages of having a real type system under the hood.</p>
<p>f# is a member of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ML_(programming_language)">ML-family</a> of functional languages, which have their origin in Lisp (some very naughty person removed all of the lovely parentheses I’m afraid…).</p>
<p>I hope that at some point I’ll have the opportunity to use f# in anger, at which point I’ll be able to report more concretely as to its suitability.</p>
<h1 id="the-end">The End</h1>
<p>Let me know in the comments what you think about any of this, or anything else.</p>
<p>I hope to meet you again in a few days, here or elsewhere.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #146: You too can learn Kung Fu.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/06/18/weekly-head-voices-146-you-too-can-learn-kung-fu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2018 21:24:40 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/06/18/weekly-head-voices-146-you-too-can-learn-kung-fu/</guid><description> This post covers the period Monday June 11 to Sunday June 17. Read it to become rich, yawn at Lisp and Emacs, yearn to run free on the wide open plains and to learn Kung Fu. Not ambitious at all. Front door nearby De Waal Park, in Cape Town. Photo taken on Sunday by GOU#1, age 12.
Social Democracy FTW It turns out that your chances of becoming rich are the greatest if you had the good fortune to have been born in one of the Nordic social democracies, such as Norway, Sweden or Denmark.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>This post covers the period Monday June 11 to Sunday June 17. Read it to become rich, yawn at Lisp and Emacs, yearn to run free on the wide open plains and to learn Kung Fu. Not ambitious at all.</em>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/IMG_2004.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/IMG_2004-768x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Front door nearby De Waal Park, in Cape Town. Photo taken on Sunday by GOU#1, age 12."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Front door nearby De Waal Park, in Cape Town. Photo taken on Sunday by GOU#1, age 12.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<h1 id="social-democracy-ftw">Social Democracy FTW</h1>
<p>It turns out that your chances of becoming rich are the greatest if you had the good fortune to have been born in one of the Nordic social democracies, such as Norway, Sweden or Denmark.</p>
<p>The US trails these countries, at position 13, in terms of per capita individuals with net worth over $30 million.</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/A9UmdY0E8hU?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Being a proponent of social democracy as the most humane form of currently practical human government, and often infuriating conservatives   by pointing out that many crucial aspects of social democracies can be described as socialistic, I really enjoyed the linked TEDx talk by Norwegian <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harald_Eia">Harald Eia</a>.</p>
<p>This material will serve me well as the source of future mischief.</p>
<h1 id="paradigms-of-ai-programming-in-common-lisp">Paradigms of AI Programming in Common Lisp</h1>
<p>I am currently working my way through <a href="https://github.com/norvig/paip-lisp">“Paradigms of Artificial Intelligence Programming: Case Studies in Common Lisp”</a>, Peter Norvig’s famous 1992 book an artificial intelligence. Although modern AI has been transformed almost unrecognisably since then (THANKS DEEP LEARNING! <a href="http://norvig.com/Lisp-retro.html">Norvig’s PAIP retrospective</a>) the way in which Norvig uses Lisp to model and solve real-world problems is inspiring and quite foundational.</p>
<p>It’s not only that though.</p>
<p>My inconvenient but uncontrollable infatuation with Common Lisp also seems to be pulling the strings. I should study a real language which is not 60 years old, like Rust or something.</p>
<p>What attracts me about Common Lisp is the liberated and pragmatic way in which it enables one to mix functional, object-oriented and procedural programming, and, perhaps most importantly, how it was designed from the ground up for iterative and interactive programming.</p>
<p>Tweak the defun, eval the defun, watch the system adapt. This is what I always imagined programming would be like. Except for the Lisps, it really turned out perhaps a bit more boring than it really needs to be.</p>
<h2 id="interleave-mode-for-working-through-pdf-books">interleave-mode for working through PDF books</h2>
<p>For the fellow Emacs users, I also wanted to mention the utility of <a href="https://github.com/rudolfochrist/interleave">interleave-mode</a> for working through such a programming book, if you can find it in PDF format.</p>
<p>In my Emacs I have the PDF on the left, and my interleave-mode-linked orgfile on the right. On any page of the PDF I hit the i-button to add a note in the orgfile, where I can of course insert and execute live code snippets.</p>
<p>The sections in the orgfile remain linked to the correct pages of the PDF.</p>
<p>For programming books this is an amazing combination. For studying other books, having your orgfile notes linked will probably also be quite useful.</p>
<p>On the topic of note-taking: This past week, on Friday June 15 (I made a note of that), I was able to help a colleague solve a technical problem by searching for and retrieving an org-file note, including detailed configuration settings, that I made on May 13, 2014.</p>
<h1 id="ether-as-currency">Ether as currency</h1>
<p>Although I acquired a small amount of the Ether cryptocurrency for the first time in July of 2016, I’ve never had the opportunity to actually transact with it.</p>
<p>Up to now, it has functioned solely as a pretty volatile store of value.</p>
<p>On Saturday, I used some ether for the first time to straight-up buy something on the internet, which was a pretty exciting but in practice an uneventful procedure, fortunately.</p>
<p>The vendor used a payment processor which presented me with an address and corresponding QR code. I scanned the QR code with the relevant mobile app (Luno in this case), paid the requested amount, and waited for a few minutes for it to be multiply confirmed by the blockchain. The sending fee was about 0.04% of the transaction.</p>
<h1 id="barefoot-style-running-update">Barefoot-style running update</h1>
<p>On Sunday I went for a long(ish) run, bringing my total on the Luna sandals to just over 200km.</p>
<p>My feet, ankles and calves are much stronger than they used to be, but the barefoot conversion is clearly still has some ways to go. I have to take at the very least two rest days (instead of one) between runs to give my feet some extra time to recover.</p>
<p>What I have recently started doing, is that instead of trying to micro-manage my form (put your foot down like this, bend your ankle like that, let your achilles tendon shoot back like this, and so on), I am following the advice of some <em>new</em> random person on <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/BarefootRunning/">reddit/r/BarefootRunning</a> who gave the advice, often echoed elsewhere by barefoot-runners, to try and maintain a cadence (steps-per-minute) of at least 180.</p>
<p>That sounds pretty high for a normal person like me, but it turns out that when I do that, and I try at the same time to run as silently as possible (I often just APPEAR right beside someone, hehe), my legs and feet figure out their elastic bio-kinematics all by themselves.</p>
<p>As yet another random reddit expert (I wish I could find the post) quipped:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You can’t overthink proprioception.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(that’s a running nerd joke)</p>
<h1 id="i-know-kung-fu">I know Kung Fu</h1>
<p>Do you remember this scene from The Matrix (1999)?</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/V8ZdGmgj0PQ?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>The other day at the <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#reunion">Old People Reunion</a>, friend T. Monster, a highly capable pragmatist but also backyard theoretician, talked about how often it happened these days that you had to deal with some DIY issue, tapped or spoke the question into youtube, watched a video or two, and then fixed the issue like a pro.</p>
<p>This, along with my recent pseudo-expert repair of a number of stripped cabinet hinge screw holes with tooth picks and cold glue (this works, I kid you not), made me think that, although The Matrix version was perhaps far more spectacular, we in fact now find ourselves in a <em>real, shared reality</em> where a large subset of skills can be acquired <em>a la carte</em>.</p>
<p>Some may take longer than a few minutes, but it still is pretty amazing how far YouTube has managed to democratise so many different forms of modern Kung Fu.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #138: Born to run.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/04/02/weekly-head-voices-138-born-to-run/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 08:13:12 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/04/02/weekly-head-voices-138-born-to-run/</guid><description> I am currently in a place with no to extremely little internet. Just getting the photo above uploaded was an adventure.
I briefly debated breaking my current WHV posting streak due to exceptional circumstances, but decided against it, at least for now.
Anyways, I might have no internet, but the scenery here is phenomenal.
(It later turned out that just getting this blog post uploaded on Sunday evening was not going to happen.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/mystery_place.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/mystery_place-1024x575.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I am currently in a place with no to extremely little internet. Just getting the photo above uploaded was an adventure.</p>
<p>I briefly debated breaking my current WHV posting streak due to exceptional circumstances, but decided against it, at least for now.</p>
<p>Anyways, I might have no internet, but the scenery here is phenomenal.</p>
<p>(It later turned out that just getting this blog post uploaded on Sunday evening was not going to happen.)</p>
<h1 id="sometimes-focus-falls-and-slips-into-emacs">Sometimes focus falls and slips into Emacs</h1>
<p>During the past week I had a fairly difficult technical puzzle to deal with. It’s one of those puzzles that can only be solved with multiple days of research and concerted focus.</p>
<p>It’s funny how my mind manages to sort of slip away when faced with these sorts of puzzles where the solution, if it even exists (this is probably the main reason for the continual slippage), seems to be weeks away, instead of a few hours or days.</p>
<p>It’s like a usually sharp(ish) knife which simply refuses to bite into the thing that I so desperately want to cut with it.</p>
<p>In my specific case, especially later in the afternoons when prefrontal cortex is long-gone, mindlessly drinking its beer while staring into space somewhere, or even later in the evenings when everyone else is also drinking beer while staring into space, I wake up to find myself working on some obscure Emacs hack.</p>
<p>This week, primary thought slippage resulted in:</p>
<ul>
<li>Hooking up my emacs, via <a href="http://pragmaticemacs.com/emacs/find-and-open-files-from-anywhere-with-helm-for-files/">helm-for-files</a> with mdfind (the command-line interface to spotlight) on macOS and the tracker file indexer on Linux. This means that with a simple press of the <code>C-x c o</code> keys, I can instantly open any file in Emacs which is already open somewhere, which I’ve recently worked on, whose filename faintly resembles what I’m typing, whose contents (or tags) faintly resembles what I’m typing, no matter where that file is hiding in the hundreds of gigabytes on my SSD.</li>
<li>My efforts getting the above working for Linux are <a href="https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm/pull/2005">now part of helm</a>, via the wonderful system of github pull requests.</li>
<li>Setting up <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/emacs/Dired.html">Emacs dired</a> to do rsync-based network copying in the background, which culminated in <a href="https://github.com/tmtxt/tmtxt-dired-async/pull/6">a github contribution</a> which will hopefully also find its way into the main repository soon. (I do most of my <strong>serious</strong> file management in Emacs dired. You should try it.)</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="the-running-people">The Running People</h1>
<p>I finally bought <a href="http://www.chrismcdougall.com/born-to-run/">Born to Run by Christopher McDougall</a>.</p>
<p>In between travelling and other activities, I was not able put this book down.</p>
<p>As I was reading the final pages on Sunday morning, I had trouble keeping my eyes dry. I had connected with the story and all of its nested stories on so many levels.</p>
<p>One strand of the story makes the case that humans, or more specifically homo sapiens, had evolved to run its prey down on the savannah.</p>
<p>We are able to cool ourselves down during running thanks to being mostly hairless and sweaty, whereas an antelope is not able to pant while galloping, and has no choice but to stop.</p>
<p>So the trick is simple: We can run fast enough to keep a galloping antelope in sight. Eventually it will lose the battle, overheat and collapse.</p>
<p>This is what homo sapiens did for millions of years for food. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neanderthal"><em>Homo neanderthalensis</em></a>, our intelligent and stronger competition who used to dominate during colder times, had no chance.</p>
<p>McDougall connects with a number of scientists and sports trainers to flesh out this part of the story. Below is an interesting (and related) video about Prof Daniel Liebermann and his work on the evolutionary biology and biomechanics of barefoot running:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7jrnj-7YKZE?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>(Being internet-deprived, I’m not currently able to find one of the cited Nature papers discussing other elements of our biology underlining our running heritage. Remind me in the comments so I can update this later.)</p>
<p>Another strand of the story is about the [Tarahumara of Mexico, also</p>
<p>known as Rarámuri]<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rar%C3%A1muri">7</a>, or The Running People, a legendary tribe of natural super athletes who are masters of avoiding other humans (due to past persecution and other shenanigans) and of running 30 miles in the mountains, in sandals.</p>
<p><em>Even more intriguing than their home-made sandals, is that they run throughout their healthy lives with joy and exuberance.</em></p>
<p>The final strand I want to mention here, is McDougall’s personal journey from injury-prone runner all the way to finally taking part in the very first edition of a gruelling 50 mile trail race (the centre-piece of the story I would argue), together with the world’s best ultra marathoners and the Taramuhara in the Copper Canyons of Mexico.</p>
<p>For a large part of this journey, he and a number of other key actors are propelled along by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Micah_True">Caballo Blanco</a>, the White Horse, a supernaturally gifted runner who lived off the land in the Copper Canyons, and one of the few foreigners who seemed to be completely accepted by the Taramuhara.</p>
<p>Caballo is the one who managed to bring together, for the first time, the Taramuhara and the best ultra-marathoners in the small town of Urque for this humanity-affirming 50 mile trail run. He did so from his stone hut in the middle of nowhere, from where he would have to run for 30 miles to the closest settlement that had a telephone line that he could use.</p>
<p>Often that line was down.</p>
<p>Caballo passed away in 2012, shortly after the first Copper Canyon race. Shortly after, the race was officially dubbed the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ultramaraton_Caballo_Blanco">Ultramaraton Caballo Blanco.</a></p>
<p>Right after I put the book down, I put on my shoes and went for a run</p>
<p>up the mountain-side and in the valley over here. On the balls of my feet as they landed right under me, really small steps, straight back, trying my best to float over the earth, just like the running people in the book.</p>
<p>I could not help but smile for most of the way.</p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>