<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>101 mind-tricks on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/101-mind-tricks/</link><description>Recent content in 101 mind-tricks on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 22:15:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/101-mind-tricks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #227: Reality bending security blanket</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 22:15:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.
This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.
Groundhog Lockdown On the above-mentioned Sunday, president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4, one level more serious from where we were.
For us this means that schools are closing a week earlier for the July vacation, and hence will have to open a week earlier, and hence will have a severe effect on the breakaway we had planned, an effect of the cancellation variety.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="backyard_walk_s_and_i.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from
Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.</p>
<h2 id="groundhog-lockdown">Groundhog Lockdown</h2>
<p>On the above-mentioned Sunday, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/level-4-lockdown-for-south-africa-for-14-days-2021-6">president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4</a>,
one level more serious from where we were.</p>
<p>For us this means that schools are closing a week earlier for the July
vacation, and hence will have to open a week earlier, and hence will have a
severe effect on the breakaway we had planned, an effect of the
<em>cancellation</em> variety.</p>
<p>Although frustrating (some of us really need that precious time away to keep
calm and carry on afterwards), we don&rsquo;t really have anything to complain about
if that is our biggest problem.</p>
<p>Gauteng province has been hit really hard by the third wave of COVID, and
specifically this new Delta variant.</p>
<p>This modified lockdown level 4 explicitly prohibits travel into and out of the
province in order to help stem the disease&rsquo;s spread.</p>
<p>In other news, our vaccination is making progress, albeit at a slower pace than
most people had hoped.</p>
<p>In a few days they are going to start with the over 50s. No, this does not
include me yet, although I am close.</p>
<h2 id="amazon-document-culture">Amazon document culture</h2>
<p>Last week, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=27545331">Hacker News discussed</a> a really interesting <a href="https://www.justingarrison.com/blog/2021-03-15-the-document-culture-of-amazon/">blog post by an Amazon
employee about Amazon&rsquo;s document culture</a>.</p>
<p>In short, at Amazon, a meeting can only happen if a document has been written
detailing what is to be discussed during the meeting.</p>
<p>At the start of the meeting, everyone gets from 10 minutes to half an hour,
depending on what makes sense for the document under discussion, to read the
document, and only then the meeting starts.</p>
<p>This approach has many advantages, discussed in the blog post.</p>
<p>What I personally like about doing it this way, is that the convenor of the
meeting has to pay a price for that meeting, namely sitting down and spending
time to structure their thoughts on paper well enough so it will satisfy the
expectations of the participants.</p>
<p>Furthermore, by dedicating quiet time to reading the document, one has a
slightly better guarantee that everyone is up to date with the background, and,
more interesting to me, is that it sets a more deliberate and thoughtful mood
for the whole meeting.</p>
<p>Of course I tried this out at the first high-level meeting that I could, where
I had to present a plan to the participants.</p>
<p>It felt a bit strange initiating this silent reading at the start, but my
perception is that it contributed to a higher quality discussion afterwards.</p>
<p>In this case it was easy, because the goal of the meeting was to present a plan
that was already a document. However, this is something I will definitely want
to repeat.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, the document will be all that is required.</p>
<h2 id="your-choice">Your choice</h2>
<p>In <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">WHV #226</a> I wrote that I had chosen to be in the situation that was causing
stress due to its new challenges.</p>
<p>Friend SvdW (jokingly? chidingly?) commented via private communications
channels that that &ldquo;choice&rdquo; had surprised him, seeing that <a href="https://philosophybreak.com/articles/free-will-illusion-sam-harris/">we have no free
will</a>.</p>
<p>He is right of course, but in this case it <em>is</em> in fact all about the illusion,
about being subjectively convinced that one is the agent and the author of
one&rsquo;s current situation.</p>
<p>This did remind me something I wrote in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#productivity-system-tuneup">WHV #185</a> about how this same framing
can be effective against procrastination:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have chosen to
take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having decided
to commit, i.e. active.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the cases where you believe that you <em>are</em> probably the agent of your
situation, it can really help to verbalise that to yourself in the way
described above.</p>
<p>This can sometimes be tricky, because so much of it has to do with potentially
subjective-reality-bending framing, which could get in the way of addressing
problems external to oneself.</p>
<p>If you apply This One Trick, and you do a great job, how real were those
external problems in the first place?</p>
<p>On days like these, I get a feeling, albeit an extremely faint one, for why
Descartes constructed the mental security blanket of <em>cogito ergo sum</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2020 to 2021 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 15:19:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Welcome to the year 2021 friends.
Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.
You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to the &ldquo;transition&rdquo; tag page.
If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition.
This transition tradition started at the end of 2009, which coincidentally is also the year that the Weekly Head Voices was born.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2021 friends.</p>
<p>Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.</p>
<p>You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to <a href="/tags/transition/">the &ldquo;transition&rdquo;
tag page</a>.</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/">last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition</a>.</p>
<p>This transition tradition <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">started at the end of 2009</a>, which coincidentally is
also the year that <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">the Weekly Head Voices was born</a>.</p>
<p>The goal of the transition post is to do a really spotty year review, and then
to gaze unsuccessfully into the future.</p>








<figure><a href="leopards_kloof.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&amp;rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>More seriously, the ever-evolving network of posts on this website (there are
now literally hundreds of them), along with the ever-evolving but also fading
network of neurons in my head (probably at least a few hundred of them too!),
benefit from an occasional higher-level connecting of some of the dots.</p>
<p>In the introduction of the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/">2018 to 2019 transition post</a>, I ramble on slightly
more about the multiscalar nature of my subjective experience, and how that is
reflected in my notes database, of which this blog is one aspect.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s get on with it!</p>
<h2 id="noteworthy-snippets-through-the-lens-of-this-blog">Noteworthy snippets through the lens of this blog</h2>
<h3 id="covid-19">COVID-19</h3>
<p>One of the biggest issues for most people last year and still at this moment is
COVID-19.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested, you could take a look at the Weekly Head Voices posts
that had something to say about <a href="/tags/covid19/">COVID-19</a>, but you don&rsquo;t really have to.</p>
<p>Fortunately, world-wide vaccination has commenced. However, we have to keep our
fingers crossed that:</p>
<ol>
<li>The world succeeds in getting the vaccine to a sufficient number of humans
on time.</li>
<li>A vaccine-resistant strain does not happen. It could, because math, and
because evolution (selection pressure due to the vaccine, doh),</li>
</ol>
<p>Whether the above outcomes realise or not, I do also hope that we retain as
many as possible of the lessons we have been learning thanks to the pandemic.</p>
<ul>
<li>Mask-wearing and generally improved hygeine with the major goal of protecting
our fellow humans are great habits.</li>
<li>We have made great strides towards the future of work, where many workers (by
far not all, but it&rsquo;s a good meaningful chunk) are able to commute less,
pollute less, better organize the interaction of their work and family lives
and, importantly, their work is measured by its value and not by the number
of hours it takes place in.</li>
<li>We humans are in this (today pandemic, tomorrow something else!) together.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="lazar-focus-the-side-project-that-got-released">Lazar Focus: The side-project that got released</h3>
<p>Around these parts we have a rich tradition of starting but then never
finishing side-projects, and the concomitant giant side-project graveyard to
show for it.</p>
<p>This year, I did manage to ship the little distraction blocker tool I wrote,
called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a>. The <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">first WHV mentioning was #196</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the fact that this little tool has ended up helping me to rescue
many aspirant unproductive days, it has sold more than 10 copies, which was my
life goal for this project.</p>
<h3 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion effect</h3>
<p>From Adam Grant&rsquo;s book Give and Take, I learned about the <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#the-pygmalion-effect">Pygmalion effect</a>,
where a teacher&rsquo;s <em>belief</em> in the intrinsic capabilities of a student, whether
those were justified or not at the time, had a significant and enduring
positive, one could say potentially life-changing, effect on that student&rsquo;s
performance.</p>
<p>Besides the bit about the Pygmalion effect, <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/">that post (WHV #201)</a> contains a
micro-summary of the Shape Up book by Basecamp, which is also worth a look.</p>
<h3 id="take-the-day-off-to-go-run-in-the-mountain">Take the day off to go run in the mountain</h3>
<p>During the year, for example in <a href="/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/#life-progress-update">WHV #203</a> when I took my birthday off to go
running in the mountains, I learned that taking days off on the birthdays of you
and your loved ones to go do stuff outdoors is a Great Idea(tm).</p>
<p>(I also learned that sometimes you don&rsquo;t even need an excuse. Just take the day
off and go run in the mountains.)</p>
<h3 id="use-it-or-lose-it">Use it or lose it</h3>
<p>The human system is amazingly adaptable.</p>
<p>The price that we pay for that flexibility is that each and every one of our
learned capabilities requires continuous practice in order to be maintained.</p>
<p>In short humans, <a href="/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/#use-it-or-lose-it">use it, or lose it</a>.</p>
<h3 id="fool-your-mind">Fool your mind</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m making peace with the fact that I apparently need to apply, continuously,
various silly tricks to keep <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">the slippery eel that is my mind</a> on the
straight-and-narrow.</p>
<p>As a shining example, <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">the refocus reminder</a>, a bell that reminds you at hourly
intervals to focus, indeed sounds a bit silly but adds a great deal of value.</p>
<p>My favourite example from last year however is creating yet more (but smaller!)
habits to kickstart my bigger habits, in this case a <a href="/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/#wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">3-item morning checklist
to kickstart the more daunting full day checklist</a>.</p>
<p>The morning bootstrap checklist is, at the risk of sounding like a startup-bro:</p>
<ol>
<li>meditation,</li>
<li>deep reading and</li>
<li>planning.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="blogging-stats">Blogging stats</h2>
<p>Since February 17 of 2020 when I <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">migrated everything to a small Hetzner VPS</a>,
the server log files tell me that cpbotha.net saw just over 157000 unique
visitors, which is 492 per day on average.</p>
<p>I wrote 30 posts on cpbotha.net during 2020, of which 25 were editions of the
Weekly Head Voices.</p>
<p>Thanks to the shiny new archive page I put together today, you can now finally
<a href="/archive/#2020">see all of 2020&rsquo;s posts in one place</a>, or of any other year, should you be more
into the older stuff.</p>
<p>In addition to the cpbotha.net posts, I also published 11 posts over on
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the regular WHV posts, I&rsquo;m happy to have published what will
hopefully be only the first in a whole collection of book notes posts, namely
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Creativity, Inc.&rdquo; by Ed Catmull with Amy Wallace</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s chunky at just over 7000 words, but it will give you a pretty good idea of
the contents of the much more substantial book it is based on!</p>
<h3 id="details-for-nerds">Details for nerds</h3>
<p>This is the invocation I used to generate reports from the nginx log files
using the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess</a> tool:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>zcat -f -- /var/log/nginx/cpbotha.net.access.log.*.gz |<span style="color:#2aa198">\
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198"></span>    goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>In 2020 I seem to have run just 100 metres shy of 1100km. (Typical&hellip;)</p>
<p>More would have been good, but I&rsquo;m happy with this.</p>
<p>Exercise did take a bit of a hit due to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/#exercise">lockdown</a>, although I could definitely
have squeezed more in.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the aggregated amount of enjoyment and satisfaction
was astronomical.</p>
<p>A personal highlight was <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#random-notes-on-the-kogelberg-trail-adventure">running the 24km(ish) Kogelberg trail with a tiny
crew that included two of my Dutch family members</a>.</p>
<p>(These blog retrospectives are strange, because they are also life
retrospectives, but they shouldn&rsquo;t get too personal. I would be remiss however
if I did not mention that having these specific Dutch peeps here in 2020 was
magical. I am going to miss them terribly.)</p>
<p>Also thanks to said peeps, I did more trail running this year than ever before.</p>
<p>It turns out that I am surrounded by beautiful trails. WHO KNEW?!</p>
<p>The other highlight I want to mention was <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations">GOU#1</a> running her first race, the
distributed <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#running-and-reading">CTM 10km in Jonkershoek</a>. Here&rsquo;s to many more GOU kilometres!</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>Thanks to some strict words by friend PK during the year, I got solidly back on
the daily meditation train, which ended up being the start of a streak of
(workday) morning meditation longer than anything I&rsquo;ve been able to maintain up
to now.</p>
<p>(The bootstrap checklist in <a href="#fool-your-mind">Fool Your Mind</a> above might also have contributed to
this.)</p>
<p>The Waking Up course by Sam Harris has been amazing for more than two years
now, and even more so when trying to build and keep up a daily meditation
habit.</p>
<p>What I especially like about Waking Up is its focus on the explicit practice of
the experience of consciousness and the role (or non-role) of the self within
that. (for a tiny example, see <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#find-a-place-in-the-universe-that-is-your-consciousness">WHV #207</a>)</p>
<p>Practising this daily has been an experience that I can only recommend in the
strongest terms.</p>
<p>(Please let me know if you&rsquo;d like to try a month for free. As a subscriber, I
get to give these out to as many peeps as I want to.)</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV approach to life, the universe and everything (also known as &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo;,
but you have to over-emphasize the terribly soft &ldquo;W&rdquo;) has been evolving for a
few years now, but it was most recently summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.</p>
<p>At the basis of this approach we find the two formidable pillars of</p>
<ol>
<li><em>love</em> and</li>
<li><em>science</em>,</li>
</ol>
<p>and in that order. On top of these pillars rest <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">The WHV&rsquo;s Two no Three Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</a>.</p>
<p>The two no three rules are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be useful.</li>
<li>Be likable.</li>
<li>Evolve.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the previous transition post, I talked about <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">six personal daily life
directions</a>, the continuous reformulation of which I had integrated into my
morning routine.</p>
<p>It was a good start, but the life directions were a bit too specific, and six
separate things is too many to keep at the core of your thoughts.</p>
<p>Motivated by this, and also by <a href="https://lexfridman.com/chris-lattner-2/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Chris Lattner</a>
wherein Lattner, an amazing engineer, but more importantly such a kind human
being, underlined the importance to him of always continuing to grow and learn,
I mashed together everything I had to come up with two clusters of daily life
directions:</p>
<ol>
<li>Grow, learn, build, enjoy. (motion)</li>
<li>Be useful. Be likeable. Be kind. (self-checks)</li>
</ol>
<p>In the stupid-dimensional universe that is my mind, I know that these
directions are obviously in the spirit of WALUE, but I can&rsquo;t yet articulate
clearly how they relate to the pillars and the rules of WALUE.</p>
<p>Maybe they&rsquo;re just a neat little pile on top, or a little bit to the side,
leaning against the WALUE building?</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, they have been part of my daily checklist for a few
months now, and they seem to work in the sense of being practical, checkable
and tiny enough to keep in mind always.</p>
<h2 id="plans--for-tomorrow-at-least">Plans (for tomorrow, at least)</h2>
<p>This bit is quite scary.</p>
<p>I hardly know what&rsquo;s going to happen tomorrow, and here I wanted to talk about
plans for the whole year!</p>
<p>So, to be clear, what I&rsquo;ve listed below is limited to the concrete items that I
can see before me right now.</p>
<h3 id="the-absolute-basics">The absolute basics</h3>
<ul>
<li>Attempt to apply <a href="#life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</a> all of the time.</li>
<li>Practise mindfulness every day.</li>
<li>If I&rsquo;m wondering whether I should go run, the answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="comms-upgrade">Comms upgrade</h3>
<p>I would like to level up my communication game.</p>
<p>Work from home is here to stay, and that&rsquo;s a good thing, but it has muffled my
face-to-face communication modality, something that has had a profound impact
on my full communication suite.</p>
<p>Most of the clever folks now agree that <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">the correct answer is asynchronous
communication</a>. Future-facing companies like Basecamp and <a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/">Doist have been
preaching this long before COVID-19</a>.</p>
<p>To be more specific, I need to figure out first how to do asynchronous
communication in my daily work, and then to become really good at it.</p>
<h3 id="write-more-about-good-books">Write more about good books</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to publish more focused book notes like the recently appeared
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Creativity, Inc. post</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s great reading these books, but I&rsquo;ve noticed that if I&rsquo;m planning to
publish book notes, I read more intently, I take better notes, and the extra
processing stage before starting to put together a blog post really helps me to
integrate the knowledge contained in the book.</p>
<p>Every good book one is able to integrate is in fact a cheap, but possibly
game-changing firmware upgrade&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2021-for-you">Wishes for 2021, for you</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this. I am grateful that you&rsquo;re here.</p>
<p>I wish you and everyone you hold dear the best 2021 possible.</p>
<p>Quite concretely, we can all help to make this happen by being as kind as we
possibly can to as many fellow humans as we possibly can.</p>
<p>In the words of a fellow traveller: SMÃ‰AGOL OUT!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #206: Mount Ceder</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 13:10:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/</guid><description> Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder.
Welcome, dear readers, to the 206th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the two weeks from Monday September 21 to Sunday October 4, 2020.
Mount Ceder beauty The weather prediction for the September 25 long weekend did not look good at all.
Temperatures in the low single digits, and rain.
We were unable to reschedule our reservation, and so, with significant trepidation, we packed our things for the weekend and made the drive to Mount Ceder.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="mount_ceder_4873_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome, dear readers, to the 206th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering
the two weeks from Monday September 21 to Sunday October 4, 2020.</p>
<h2 id="mount-ceder-beauty">Mount Ceder beauty</h2>
<p>The weather prediction for the September 25 long weekend did not look good at
all.</p>
<p>Temperatures in the low single digits, and rain.</p>
<p>We were unable to reschedule our reservation, and so, with significant
trepidation, we packed our things for the weekend and made the drive to Mount
Ceder.</p>
<p>As we entered the valley right before arriving at our destination, the rugged
and wonderful beauty of the surroundings quickly started dispelling our puny
expectations.</p>
<p>The weather did turn out almost exactly as was predicted, but our time there
ended up being the brilliant opposite of what we had feared.</p>
<p>In between spells of rain, there was plenty of fresh sunshine outside, with a
super effective little closed combustion fireplace inside the house to keep it
toasty.</p>








<figure><a href="mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a hike up the mountain with the whole fam-jam."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: View from a hike up the mountain with the whole fam-jam.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The outside jacuzzi which we discovered late on the Saturday afternoon might
also have played a role in the amount of fun that was had.</p>
<p>It does also need to be said that the fact that there&rsquo;s no telephone reception
is a massive perk for us visitors.</p>
<p>The older I get, the more I enjoy disconnecting.</p>
<h2 id="vcbm-2020-virtually">VCBM 2020, virtually</h2>
<p>Thanks to the modern miracle that is virtual conferences, I was able to attend
a large part of the <a href="https://www.gcpr-vmv-vcbm-2020.uni-tuebingen.de/">Visual Computing in Biology and Medicine (VCBM) 2020
conference</a>.</p>
<p>Although I am super interested in the themes and people of this conference, it
is <em>usually</em> not possible for me to fly around the globe to take part in this
or any other relevant academic gathering.</p>
<p>However, the current pandemic has brought with it a whole host of changes, not
least of which is the concept of being able to participate, as a first class
citizen, in an international conference.</p>
<p>It was really great, although slightly nostalgic, connecting with friends and
colleagues from years ago.</p>
<p>Just being able to join in on the post-talk question sessions, and in the
surreal social rooms on discord where you find yourself in a grid of talking
heads, was super enjoyable.</p>
<p>(It has to be noted here that the technical aspects of VCBM 2020 were also
top-class. Everything, from the interactive block-based conference programme
with downloadable papers, to the youtube streams for each session, to the
discord channels for real-time discussion and the discord channels for social
video conferencing, was simply top notch!)</p>
<h3 id="multi-tasking-virtual-meetings-quo-vadis">Multi-tasking virtual meetings: Quo vadis?</h3>
<p>What was also interesting to hear, was a possibly less positive aspect of
virtual conferencing, specifically that academic peeps were now in the
situation where they often had to multi-task whilst taking part in the
conference.</p>
<p>In the old days, pre-COVID, it could definitely happen that folks had to take
care of a few emails or perhaps even a video meeting, but the majority of the
day would be spent conferencing.</p>
<p>That is, people from potentially right around the globe would be chatting
face-to-face about anything and everything, an activity which is truly
important for collaboration, and friendship.</p>
<p>Now it seems that this ratio has changed, where most of the time folks are
expected to be available online for additional tasks and interactions, while
conferencing in parallel.</p>
<p>In my day job I&rsquo;ve noticed a similar phenomenon, where one can often notice
that people taking part in a meeting are only partially present.</p>
<p>Whilst this is perhaps a good thing for a number of meetings that are by their
nature not that efficient, I think that it&rsquo;s a dangerous habit to
cultivate.</p>
<p>Imagine that by default, every meeting means your poor cognition trying to keep
up with multiple streams of information at the same time. Looking at it from a
different perspective, now you have even less confidence that your
collaborators are paying attention to what is being discussed.</p>
<p>This might be yet another reason to <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">favour asynchronous offline communication</a>,
that is, writing long-form messages on message boards, with synchronous
face-time being reserved more and more for purely social reasons.</p>
<h2 id="on-thursday-october-1-too-much-distraction-was-too-much">On Thursday October 1, too much distraction was too much</h2>
<p>Seguing right on from the synchronous communication point above, On October 1 I
unfortunately needed to be jacked-in to Teams, WhatsApp <em>and</em> Discord for the
whole day, for various good reasons.</p>
<p>It was only around 16:20 that I was able to snap out of all of this and jack
out again, with <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a> helping to bring a bit of welcome rest and,
surprise(!), focus.</p>
<p>Before that, anxiety about possibly missing something kept me from plugging out
for even short bursts to be able to do work.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s funny how the expectations, real or perhaps more often just perceived, of
one&rsquo;s surroundings make it extremely difficult to disconnect, which leads to
more time lost to these various forms of distraction, which leads to further
anxiety, which further complicates just taking those few steps back and pulling
the plug.</p>
<p>I wish I had a trick to manage all of this better.</p>
<h2 id="that-time-i-nuked-all-of-my-computers-with-a-partition-resize-and-move-that-should-have-taken-no-more-than-5-minutes">That time I nuked all of my computers with a partition resize and move that should have taken no more than 5 minutes</h2>
<p><em>Massive nerd warning: If you don&rsquo;t want to know about filesystems, feel free</em>
<em>to skip this section. Before you do however, take this advice from me: Avoid</em>
<em>AOMEI.</em></p>
<p>My goal was simple: Move the newly appeared recovery partition (in addition to
the one at the start of the disk) to its end, so that I can grow my main system
partition to fill the available space on the drive.</p>
<p>Some years ago I had used EaseUs for something similar, but they wanted payment
for this task, and current reviews were pointing quite convincingly in the
direction of AOMEI.</p>
<p>Narrator: <em>The reviews were all tragically wrong.</em></p>
<p>My specific use case is even documented exactly on the AOMEI website, see <a href="https://www.diskpart.com/windows-10/windows-10-move-recovery-partition-4348.html">this
page</a>.</p>
<p>I followed those steps exactly.</p>
<p>My computer rebooted twice in order to perform the two actions:</p>
<ol>
<li>move recovery partition, and</li>
<li>resize system partition&hellip;</li>
</ol>
<p>&hellip; to conclude finally by leaving my laptop in a 100% unusable state.</p>
<p>No boot, no nothing.</p>
<p>I tried various combinations of booting into safe mode, which worked at first
but showed me the full drive&rsquo;s space available, meaning that the filesystem had
probably been damaged.</p>
<p>Hard.</p>
<p>I later booted with Windows installation media, from where I launched various
rescue attempts, including the stalwart <code>bootrec /rebuildbcd</code> and all of its
friends.</p>
<p>Nothing.</p>
<p>AOMEI had done a pretty great job in completely destroying my partition table
and filesystem.</p>
<p>Narrator: <em>He got what he paid for!</em></p>
<p>I ended up installing Windows 10 twice, the second time with the
soon-to-be-released 20H2 install media, because installing the old 1909 and
then upgrading was taking far too long.</p>
<p>The whole exercise, or should I say &ldquo;lesson&rdquo;, cost me about a day.</p>
<p>Stoic narrator: <em>Fortunately, the situation afterwards was better than it was before.</em></p>
<ul>
<li>My main WSL2 ubuntu 20.04 image, where most of my development work happens,
remained untouched on the second SSD and was up and running pretty quickly
after the Windows re-install.</li>
<li>My backups demonstrably work, although Windows File History is truly klunky
compared to Apple&rsquo;s Time Machine.</li>
<li>In the chaos of trying to get my work environment back up and running, I also
had to upgrade my deep learning Linux desktop machine to Ubuntu 20.04. (It
started as a Murphy&rsquo;s law situation, where both my laptop <em>and</em> the desktop
were unusable, the latter due to a stupid Ubuntu bug manifesting as a
non-working keyboard)</li>
<li>A fresh install of Windows feels really fresh.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">My mind is a slippery eel</h2>
<p>Recently I had to work on a chunk of software system design.</p>
<p>It starts with nothing laid down, just a general idea of what this pretty
significant feature should be able to do.</p>
<p>Pulling yourself up by your bootstraps, you have to start laying down the
bottom-most levels of the design that will eventually be able to make those
high-level desired features a reality.</p>
<p>This whole growing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rube%5FGoldberg%5Fmachine">Rube Goldberg machine</a> has to stay in your mind for a large
part of the day, as you&rsquo;re mentally twisting, turning and replacing bits here
and there.</p>
<p>Most of these days, getting my brain to stay focused felt a lot like trying to
hold on to a really slippery eel, and, if that wasn&rsquo;t tricky enough, trying to
aim the sporadically working laser, badly mounted on its slippery head, to try
and carve something recognisable from a block of slowly melting ice.</p>
<p>By the end of most days, it would mostly not feel like it had been very
productive.</p>
<p>I tried to make peace with the fact that some sorts of work, coupled with all
of the usual emotional interactions, would often result in this sort of
feeling.</p>
<p>In that moment, this did also help me to get back into the habit of daily
meditation practice. Fortunately there&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.wakingup.com/">the Waking Up app by Sam Harris</a> which
is perfect for this. Using this, I am usually able to squeeze in a 10 minute
practice before work starts, which subjectively seems to bring a little more
equanimity into each day.</p>
<p>Looking back at this experience now, it also seems like a strong vote for
paying more attention to the daily &ldquo;done&rdquo; list.</p>
<p>Although I mostly remember to journal every day, I often forget to look at it
also from the perspective of compactly listing the little tasks that have been
completed.</p>
<p>This could be tricky when working on an amorphous project like &ldquo;design this
vague thing&rdquo;, but I think that it&rsquo;s more about the ritual of formulating and
then reviewing a small but plausible thing that is now apparently done.</p>
<p>This seems to fool the anxious parts of one&rsquo;s brain into a semblance of
temporary calm, enabling some of the other parts to get back to work.</p>
<p>This too I shall file this under <a href="/tags/101-mind-tricks">&ldquo;101 stupid but effective tricks to fool your
mind into being more useful&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. I just discovered that some part of <a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/#do-you-write-stuff-down">January-2019-Charl already did</a>.</p>
<p>P.P.S. &ldquo;Fool your mind&rdquo;, although it sounds much less awesome than &ldquo;free your
mind&rdquo;, seems to be a recurring aspect of effectively operating the human
machine.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #203: Spiritual</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 10:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</guid><description> Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&amp;rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&amp;rsquo;s magic.
Dear friends,
It brings me joy to meet you here again.
Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10 to Sunday September 6, 2020.
If I were in your shoes, I would hop skip and jump selectively over the hopefully not too unhelpfully titled headings.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="jonkershoek_magic_20200901.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&amp;rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&amp;rsquo;s magic."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&rsquo;s magic.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>It brings me joy to meet you here again.</p>
<p>Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will
attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10
to Sunday September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>If I were in your shoes, I would hop skip and jump selectively over the
hopefully not too unhelpfully titled headings.</p>
<p>In order to reduce this wall of text somewhat, I have pre-emptively moved a
sub-section or two to the next edition of the WHV.</p>
<p><em>Dear Charl of the Future,</em></p>
<p><em>You have no choice. (also no free will haha) I am writing this for you, so you
better read every last bit.</em></p>
<p><em>I am watching you.</em> ðŸ‘€</p>
<h2 id="i-m-sorry-but-it-really-is-just-quite-complicated">I&rsquo;m sorry, but it really is just quite complicated</h2>
<p>I would like to kick this off with the following cartoon by Wiley Miller, which
entered my information field of view via dr topol&rsquo;s tweet stream. (don&rsquo;t worry,
this came in via my rss reader. i have not returned to twitter.)</p>








<figure><a href="science_vs_everything_else.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It is ironic that the people who get it, already got it, but that the people who
really should get it, won&rsquo;t get it.</p>
<p>As is the case with many of these efforts, i guess that the best we can hope
for is that some of those on the borders between the aforementioned two groups
might be gently encouraged to gravitate towards the light.</p>
<h3 id="the-giant-band-aid-phenomenon">the giant band-aid phenomenon</h3>
<p>Related to the cartoon above, it is quite interesting to me how often
well-meaning people desire to come up with a giant band-aid for any current
problem.</p>
<p>Climate change? Inequality? Surely if we just find a band-aid big
enough we can make the problem go away!</p>
<p>There really is no band-aid.</p>
<h2 id="on-the-minimum-unit-of-focus">On the minimum unit of focus</h2>
<p>Somewhere in week 34 i was struggling to wrap up a piece of programming work
that i had been struggling with for a few days, in-between meetings and a whole
smorgasbord of other modern interruptions.</p>
<p>Finally i decided to bust out the little focus tool that i shall not name here,
because that&rsquo;s not the point.</p>
<p>The point is rather that i created an interruption-free block of time and then
wrapped up the stupid programming problem decisively, there and then.</p>
<p>Relieved that it was finally done, I did feel stupid that it had taken me that
long to just shut off those damn interruptions.</p>
<p>The experience did remind me of the following cartoon by <a href="https://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/">the slightly
disgruntled scientist</a>. It describes <strong>extremely</strong> well how a single little
interruption can derail a whole constellation of mental models in an instant.</p>
<p>Click or tap to zoom in, or skip past if you know this:</p>








<figure><a href="ProgrammerInterrupted.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted_hu3267a53534c5d7f823d13c1b76e71025_414884_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted.png"
            

         width="30%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>I have found that the absolute minimum block of distraction-free time i need to
do reliably something worthwhile is about an hour.</p>
<p>A large part of my job is indeed handling the information that arrives via all
of the those pesky interruptions, but sometimes i wonder if there&rsquo;s not a
better way to reconcile these two facets.</p>
<p>Very much related to this phenomenon, is falling into the morning distraction
trap, something which is probably familiar to a number of you. (future charl,
you don&rsquo;t count.)</p>
<p>It goes like this: i arrive at work (or these days, i walk a few metres on from
the kitchen into the guest bedroom / home office), and then i start the day
with meetings, microsoft teams chats, and emails.</p>
<p>If I&rsquo;m not careful, I get stuck in this reactive mode, forgetting until far too
late in the day to eject from the reactive-jet for some of them juicy focus
hours.</p>
<p>#feelsbadman</p>
<p>Just this past week, I decided on Thursday and Friday to start work directly on
my main project, ignoring emails and chats and any other distractions until the
first stand-up meeting at 9:00.</p>
<p>Just priming my mind like this for slightly more than an hour was enough to
give the whole day a flavour of focus and intentionality.</p>
<p>It feels like I forget this lesson every other day.</p>
<p>How do you manage this?</p>
<h2 id="on-the-opposite-of-focus">On the opposite of focus</h2>
<p>Sort of inspired by <a href="https://youtu.be/0m3hGZvD-0s">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s deliberate scheduling of a shallow work
session</a> after the day&rsquo;s deep work, I was pleasantly surprised during a past few
evening sessions where I combined an entertaining DJ Set on the second screen
with some actual programming work on the main.</p>
<p>Somehow the fully intentional addition of distracting entertainment, and
importantly the <em>acceptance</em> that the work would necessarily be approached with
a leisurely attitude, I got a surprising amount of extra work done, and
experienced the whole session as relaxing.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to file this under &ldquo;101 stupid but effective tricks to fool your mind
into being more useful&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Let me know if you try this, or if you knew this all along and <em>that&rsquo;s</em> how you
manage everything so well!</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://lexfridman.com/podcast/">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s podcasts</a> are edifying and humanity-affirming. Try them if
you haven&rsquo;t yet.</p>
<h2 id="on-divide-and-conquer-for-the-email">On divide and conquer for the email</h2>
<p>Spontaneously in the night somewhere during the past weeks, I had the idea that
it was time to split my <a href="https://www.stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> work email account from the rest of my
email empire (which is partially also work, because vxlabs, but not my main
job).</p>
<p>I did this because the account I use to manage everything, the <a href="/tags/fastmail/">fastmail one</a>,
was becoming far too chaotic.</p>
<p>(Back in the TU Delft days, an adventure that ended now almost 7 years ago, I
also used to sport an e-mail split.)</p>
<p>My perception now is that I&rsquo;m working against the idea of the whole being
greater than the sum of the parts, i.e. the whole chaos is perhaps worse than
the two smaller chaos explosions by themselves.</p>
<p>(That&rsquo;s a pretty convoluted way to think about &ldquo;divide and conquer&rdquo;, isn&rsquo;t it?)</p>
<p>Also, the dream of being able to search through all of my email and actually
finding stuff is not being realised.</p>
<p>Email searching these days is usually a last resort, because I have a pretty
good <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">personal knowledge management system</a>. It could also be that fastmail
search is not as clever as gmail search.</p>
<p>In the weeks since I did this split (my notes tell me this happened on Friday,
August 21, 2020 at around 8:30 in the morning), I have noticed that my Stone
Three email is now under control, while my personal email is slightly out of
control, which is an improvement.</p>
<p>I have noticed that I do in fact apply a whole different mode of cognition and
context to the handling of work email than I do to personal/work-ish email.</p>
<p>A further advantage is that I can now focus on mastering the way of life that
is called Outlook. The first artifact I have to show for this is a pretty
complicated blog post in the drafts folder that shows how you can link to
arbitrary outlook items (in the latest outlook) from anywhere, in my case of
course Emacs.</p>
<h2 id="life-progress-update">Life progress update</h2>
<p>During the past several weeks, I passed a birthday.</p>
<p>As one bestie remarked, I am now just past the halfway mark, at least by one
pretty optimistic estimate of the total duration of me.</p>
<p>Anyways, moving on&hellip;</p>
<p>I took the largest part of the day off to go run the in the mountains here in my
backyard.</p>
<p>The route that I took for the first time, and which caused a considerable
amount of enjoyment, could be described by Watsonia, Baboon traverse, Leopard
Loop, Caracal, Protea, Sugarbird.</p>
<p>Making time for outdoorsy activities on your birthday: Two WHV thumbs up, would
do again.</p>
<p>Thanks to the <a href="http://www.workoutdoors.net/">WorkOutDoors Apple Watch app</a>, which I bought two years ago but
have never used, I did not get lost like I usually do when attempting trail
runs.</p>
<p>The app displays brilliant vector maps on your watch, optionally overlaid with
GPX routes supplied by generous friends.</p>
<p>After the birthday run, I use it again on more trails (see photo at start of
post) to run almost like someone who actually possesses a sense of
direction.</p>
<p>Technological augmentation FTW!</p>
<h2 id="here-s-to-a-more-regular-return">Here&rsquo;s to a more regular return</h2>
<p>Thank you for working through this mishmash with me!</p>
<p>We are now caught up until Sunday, September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>At this stage, I would have preferred to post more coherent little posts more
often, but I seem to find myself in a loop of slightly too much busyness (and
other issues), which ironically is contributing to my need to write more, but
which is taking up so much time and so many mental cycles that blog-writing
opportunities are hard to create and make use of.</p>
<p>Anyways&hellip; at least the overfull post-pipeline fence has now been cleared.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you equanimity, kindness and health.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next connection.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #160: Write stuff down.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 17:10:31 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/</guid><description> In the foreground, the mortar and pestle I used to mash together garlic, ginger, a serenade chilli, green cardamom pods, a whole cinnamon quill, one bay leaf, some curry powder for even more oomf, turmeric, coriander, salt and a few cloves. This paste ended up in that blurry red cast iron pot on the coals to result, a few hours later, in a delectable chicken curry potjie.
Welcome to the first WHV of the year 2019 folks!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/chicken_potjie_no2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/chicken_potjie_no2-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="In the foreground, the mortar and pestle I used to mash together garlic, ginger, a serenade chilli, green cardamom pods, a whole cinnamon quill, one bay leaf, some curry powder for even more oomf, turmeric, coriander, salt and a few cloves. This paste ended up in that blurry red cast iron pot on the coals to result, a few hours later, in a delectable chicken curry potjie."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>In the foreground, the mortar and pestle I used to mash together garlic, ginger, a serenade chilli, green cardamom pods, a whole cinnamon quill, one bay leaf, some curry powder for even more oomf, turmeric, coriander, salt and a few cloves. This paste ended up in that blurry red cast iron pot on the coals to result, a few hours later, in a delectable chicken curry potjie.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to the first WHV of the year 2019 folks!</p>
<p>In what is hopefully just a minor incident and not a portent of calamitous events to come, we have already skipped the first two weeks of the year, which means this WHV looks back at the three weeks from Monday January 7 to Saturday January 26.</p>
<p>I guess this would not be the WHV if we did not start off with some sort of awkwardness or miscellaneous embarrassment, so: CHECK!</p>
<p>Because you are probably thirsty for your WHV now, I tried to write you a long and rambly edition, with pictures! (Because itâ€™s so long and rambly, and because markdown, I have liberally sprinkled with headings and sub-headings, so that those of you with lives outside of blog reading can hop, skip and jump through like the professionals you are.)</p>
<h2 id="the-future-is-here-long-form-blog-posts-on-the-ipad">The future is here: Long-form blog posts on the iPad.</h2>
<p>This also would not be the WHV if we did not have some little digital trick to reveal: Todayâ€™s attempt is that this post is being written, for the largest part, on a 2018 iPad (the cheapest one) with an old (also very cheap) bluetooth keyboard.</p>
<p>Because I really donâ€™t like the new block-based WordPress 5.0 editor, named in an entirely non-hubristic fashion â€œGutenbergâ€, but it does fortunately support importing markdown formatted blog posts (just make sure you donâ€™t hard-wrap anything), and because I like trying new things, I am typing this on the iPad using the iOS version of <a href="https://www.textasticapp.com/">Textastic</a>.</p>
<p>A few hours ago, it looked like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/img_0005.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/img_0005-1024x768.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>
</p>
<p>In contrast to the direct <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2014/05/25/emacs-24-with-prelude-org2blog-and-wordpress/">orgmode to wordpress Emacs workflow</a> I normally use, this workflow enables me to copy and paste sections of markdown text into WordPress. Each pasted section is automatically imported as WordPress blocks, based on the markdown structure.</p>
<p>This means I can position and edit images using the WordPress interface, but author the text using Markdown. With <a href="https://github.com/org2blog/org2blog">org2blog</a> the whole post, including images, has to go through life as an orgmode file, which is brilliant for my more technical posts, but not so much for prose-heavy blog posts such as this one.</p>
<h3 id="btw-1-why-i-dont-yet-like-the-new-wordpress-editor">BTW 1: Why I donâ€™t (yet) like the new WordPress editor.</h3>
<p>The old WordPress editor enabled me to focus on the content and just write.</p>
<p>The new <a href="https://wordpress.org/gutenberg/">Gutenberg editor</a> now wants me to create a bunch of blocks, e.g. paragraph, image, paragraph, bullet list, etc., and then work with those blocks.</p>
<p>Thatâ€™s really great if youâ€™re building a site, but not so much when you would just like to get down and write that blog post.</p>
<p>Although this is now the standard editor in WordPress, there are still bugs, such as the fact that my cursor keeps on jumping to the start of the block while Iâ€™m typing, which is not irritating at all, and the not unimportant observation that none of the mobile apps support Gutenberg yet.</p>
<p>WordPress-using readers, what do you think?</p>
<p>(P.S. Another just-discovered issue: In Gutenberg, your biggest heading is H2. H1 is not available in the UI normally. When pasting in markdown, H1s do display, but do not show in the type-UI as anything. Here is <a href="https://github.com/WordPress/gutenberg/issues/4234">a confusing Gutenberg bug report</a>.)</p>
<h3 id="btw-2-why-textastic-aka-at-least-it-will-syntax-highlight-your-orgmode">BTW 2: Why Textastic? (AKA At least it will syntax highlight your Orgmode.)</h3>
<p>The main reason I found and purchased Textastic, was that I ran into <a href="https://github.com/jezcope/Org.tmbundle">Jez Copeâ€™s github repo</a> with a TextMate Bundle (thatâ€™s an editor configuration) that was made for Textastic to support editing Emacs orgmode files.</p>
<p>As is the age-old open source way, there were a few small bugs which I <a href="https://github.com/jezcope/Org.tmbundle/pull/5">fixed in my fork</a>, which you should definitely get if you are in the same I-want-to-edit-Orgmode-on-my-iOS boat as I am. Itâ€™s not a very large boat, but itâ€™s super fun!</p>
<p>(There is no Emacs on iOS. This is in my view the greatest downside of iOS. It turns out that Apple generally does not allow apps with embedded interpreters on the app store. However, I am still trying to find out why there are no iOS-capable Emacs source code forks available.)</p>
<h3 id="btw-3-the-ipad-with-keyboard-is-a-shockingly-good-laptop-replacement">BTW 3: The iPad with keyboard is a shockingly good laptop replacement.</h3>
<p>I recently recommended to a privacy-conscious reader who was searching for an affordable Linux-running laptop in South Africa, that she instead consider buying an iPad with bluetooth keyboard.</p>
<p>Down here a brand new 2018 iPad costs R5999. A cheap keyboard cover (e.g. Body Glove) can be had for about R860.</p>
<p>If you compare this to any new laptop of R6900 (about EUR 444) which will probably be sold with Windows included, you get a computing device with a fantastic quality multi-touch screen, great battery life, best-in-class security, almost no maintenance, and a fantastic app ecosystem. To seal the deal, the iPadâ€™s resale value is proportionally probably also much better than that entry-level laptop.</p>
<p><em>After</em> I sent that email, I started with this iPad + cheap bluetooth keyboard experiment to try it for myself. I have to say that the experience has been way better than I expected.</p>
<p>For a large subset of laptop users, and for a large subset of workflows and tasks, this is a really great solution.</p>
<p>Please donâ€™t worry (too much) yet, I am not planning one of those â€œI switched to an iPad as my main computing deviceâ€ blog posts. I would not be able to survive without my development tools, and I would especially not be able to survive without my Emacs.</p>
<h2 id="pv-solar-installation-progress">PV Solar installation progress</h2>
<p>As I excitedly <a href="/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/#extreme-solar">announced in WHV #159</a> (slightly more than a month ago), we had decided that it was time to get a photovoltaic solar power system installed at the house.</p>
<p>I found a local installer with the required PVGreenCard accreditation and started the consultation process.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the installer did not seem to be prepared for a customer that would not stop asking questions. The customer even went so far as to pose questions that challenged the installerâ€™s brand loyalty!</p>
<p>I really do understand that Iâ€™m probably not the easiest end-user, but I donâ€™t think that an expertâ€™s brand loyalty should get in the way of reason, and far more importantly in the way of basic physics.</p>
<p>To make a long story short, I ended up getting fired by the installer.</p>
<p>This was probably for the better: He can now continue doing well-practised installs for other clients who donâ€™t ask (so many) questions, and I suddenly had the opportunity to find a new, more engineer-friendly installer, and to continue learning.</p>
<p>Following are two noteworthy learnings:</p>
<h3 id="learning-1-you-should-almost-always-try-to-oversize-the-photovoltaic-array">Learning 1: You should almost always try to oversize the photovoltaic array</h3>
<p>If the equipment states for example 4600kVA, then you are usually quite safe installing from 25% up to 30% more kWp of solar panels.</p>
<p>Oversizing will mean that on very sunny days youâ€™ll get peaks higher than the maximum rated PV, which can be handled for short periods by the solar equipment, but more importantly, youâ€™ll be able to generate more electricity when there is less sun, which is most of the time.</p>
<p>In other words, you increase the area under the curve of kW generated per hour.</p>
<p>By the way, I emailed GoodWe (they make the hybrid inverters I have my eye on) who confirmed that their EM range supports 27.8% oversizing. The ES range advertise 30% PV oversizing on the box.</p>
<p>It is of course an interesting question what exactly is meant by oversizing. Do they support pumping 30% more power into the inverter for 5 minutes, or for 2 hours?</p>
<h3 id="learning-2-powerforumcoza-is-a-great-source-of-information">Learning 2: powerforum.co.za is a great source of information.</h3>
<p><a href="https://powerforum.co.za/">This forum</a> has a surprisingly high signal to noise ratio.</p>
<p>There are a number of experts hanging around, including one of Victronâ€™s super helpful and knowledgeable R&amp;D engineers, and the archive posts are invaluable as you try to navigate <a href="https://powerforum.co.za/topic/2791-experience-getting-city-of-cape-town-to-sign-off-a-zero-feed-in-system-with-inverter-maximum-output-greater-than-35kva/">the quagmire</a> of often conflicting information.</p>
<h2 id="avocado-baby-progress-very-much-touch-and-go">Avocado baby progress: Very much touch and go.</h2>
<p>The baby avocado tree, in spite of being being watered almost every day (thank you rainwater harvest!) does not seem to be doing too well.</p>
<p>Because the summer sun down here can be quite vicious, the tree has its own little pink umbrella.</p>
<p>The current plan is to feed it more compost, and, if that fails, to try to transplant it out of the big, wild garden and into a pot with softer, kinder earth.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-explain-complicated-topics">How to explain complicated topics</h2>
<p>The international and yearly <a href="https://mlssafrica.com">Machine Learning Summer School took place in Stellenbosch this year</a>, from Monday, January 7 to Friday, January 18.</p>
<p>As you can see from the programme, there were a bunch of heavy hitting speakers present both physically and virtually, including the super resourceful (failed super resolution pun, su(p)e(r) me) Dr Stefan van der Walt, who gave a talk on good scientific software.</p>
<p>Anyways, because I am currently in a more commercial configuration, I could not justify taking two weeks out, and instead opted for a day visit at the start of the congress.</p>
<p>It is a testament to the current prominence of the field that the list of international sponsors included Microsoft, Apple, SAP, Uber <em>and</em> Amazon.</p>
<p>It was gratifying to experience a sampling of such a well-organized international gathering here in my neck of the woods.</p>
<p>On the first day, we had a high throughput introduction to causality, probabilistic thinking, and variational inference. All the presenters were clearly good speakers, but they werenâ€™t all equally experienced in teaching such complex material.</p>
<p>(At one point one of the statisticians I was chatting to in break admitted having difficulty keeping up with the math. I did not feel <strong>that</strong> stupid anymore.)</p>
<p>â€œWhat is the difference between being a good speaker and an experienced teacher?â€, you might now ask.</p>
<p>Great question, I would then say, grateful for the opportunity to explain.</p>
<p>What I was missing in the one specific case I do not want to be too specific about, was that the presenter did a great job of talking about each of a long list of concepts relevant to his topic, but somehow forgot that one of the most important parts of teaching is communicating the conceptual framework into which all of those concepts fit.</p>
<p>Conceptual frameworks are also one of those multi-scalar things: Each group of factoids can be gratifyingly embedded into a slightly higher level component, groups of which can be slotted into the overarching â€œbig ideaâ€, or another level of compnonent. (Itâ€™s turtles all the way down.)</p>
<p>As great lecturers talk, they keep on bringing their narrative back up to the higher-level embedding construct.</p>
<p>It looks something like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/teach_complicated_things.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/teach_complicated_things-1024x576.png"
        
            alt="Yes, I did make this especially for this post, especially for you. No, I am not sure exactly why."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Yes, I did make this especially for this post, especially for you. No, I am not sure exactly why.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>By repeatedly diving deeper into the details, and then following the conceptual link back up to the higher-level constructs and especially your big idea, your listeners will start to see the beautiful fractal of understanding that you are guiding them through.</p>
<h2 id="what-will-i-be-working-on-this-year">What will I be working on this year?</h2>
<p>At this moment, 2019 is shaping up to be pretty exciting work-wise.</p>
<p>We just heard that we will be able to continue for some months more working on the X-Ray based surgical planning project we worked on last year.</p>
<p>Partly thanks to the great deep learning work of two summer interns (note: Southern Hemisphere means summer interns over December and January, which might be weird if youâ€™re from the Northern Hemisphere) we are in great shape for all of the deep neural network-based image understanding plans we need to execute on.</p>
<p>This year I will also be spending more time on <a href="https://www.telesensi.com">TeleSensi, our FDA-certified tele-auscultation product</a>. This is less rocket-sciencey than the surgical planning project, but super interesting to work on, as it has many more users on the open market.</p>
<p>(That being said, we do have plans to increase the level of rocket science significantly. I am not called the science officer for nothingâ€¦ (well, that and also the fact that I got to choose my own title, and so I chose the same as Spock on the USS Enterprise).)</p>
<h2 id="do-you-write-stuff-down">Do you write stuff down?</h2>
<p>You might remember from WHV #155 <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">my trick of starting the day with a checklist</a>.</p>
<p>A part of that checklist is a checklist of habits which I try to form and maintain, called The HabitFormer(tm). Every item that I sufficiently address gets a super satisfying little <code>[X]</code> mark, which feels a whole lot better than the sadly empty <code>[ ]</code> construct.</p>
<p>Here is the current list:</p>
<ul>
<li>did you write stuff down?</li>
<li>are you satisfied with number of pomodori?</li>
<li>7.5 hrs sleep last night</li>
<li>meditate &lt;â€“ (WHV <em>hidden</em> pro-tip: Get the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up</a> app by Sam Harris. Thanks LM for the fantastic recommendation.)</li>
<li>stand at desk</li>
<li>do valuable things</li>
<li>fruit &amp; veg</li>
<li>reading</li>
<li>thinking</li>
<li>running or other exercise</li>
</ul>
<p>Ironically enough, the first item is brand new on the list.</p>
<p>I somehow forgot my habit of writing, during the day, a little done list / random thoughts lists. After bringing this habit back I noticed what difference it made.</p>
<p>At regular intervals during the day, I will spend a minute or three writing down what I had completed, or what I was thinking. This moment of introspection would either result in a pleasant bit of satisfaction with some small task taken care of, or, more often, it would reel me back in from a spot of less than deliberate action and enable me to bring back my attention to the point of focus.</p>
<p>Iâ€™m filing this under â€œ101 tricks to get your <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/">rider back on your elephant</a>â€œ.</p>
<p>Alright friends, thank you very much for joining me on this part of my journey. I am looking forward to our next interaction!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>