<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>orgmode on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/orgmode/</link><description>Recent content in orgmode on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 21:06:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/orgmode/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #240: I am just a copy of a copy of a copy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 21:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</guid><description> Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three weeks instead of one.
I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking
back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of
the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three
weeks instead of one.</p>
<p>I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about
alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more
resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough
time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</p>
<p>(Some more famous bloggers that I follow manage to put out a paragraph or two
every single day. It would be interesting to try an experiment like that.)</p>
<p>Anyways, switching out of meta mode back to the mishmash of on-topics for edition
240:</p>
<h2 id="blood-flowers">Blood flowers</h2>
<p>During a recent karma-restoring family beach walk, we came across the following
pretty striking flowers:</p>








<figure><a href="blood-flowers.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Blood flowers in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Blood flowers in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The <a href="http://pza.sanbi.org/haemanthus-coccineus">PlantZAfrica website tells us</a> that these are examples of <em>Haemanthus
coccineus</em>, also known as &ldquo;March flower&rdquo; (no idea why) or &ldquo;blood flower&rdquo;, the
latter which is more in line with the meaning of its Greek genus (haima =
blood, anthos = flower), and its Latin species.</p>
<p>We are not the first or only people to find it quite striking:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It was probably the first flower to be collected from Table Mountain and,
probably also the first illustration of a South African flower to appearin a
European publication. The illustration was by the Flemish botanis de L&rsquo;Obel
in 1605. &ndash; PlantZAfrica</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, as if the name &ldquo;Blood Flower&rdquo; is not metal enough, it turns out
<em>Haemanthus coccineus</em> lives fully underground in the form of a large bulb for
the dry summer months, only revealing its brilliant red flower when the rainy
season is about to start.</p>
<h2 id="fantastic-karma-and-how-to-destroy-it">Fantastic karma and how to destroy it</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s Friday evening. We&rsquo;ve just had a brilliant edition of our Friday evening
family braai tradition, and everyone starts retiring to their various
individual relaxation activities.</p>
<p>I decide that it&rsquo;s a great idea to forge ahead with the <a href="https://github.com/vega/react-vega/tree/master/packages/react-vega">react-vega</a> and <a href="https://redux-toolkit.js.org/rtk-query/overview">RTK
Query</a> visualization functionality I had ended my work week with.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d successfully worked with a previous version of the former, and my
confidence in RTKQ&rsquo;s quality was trending upwards due to recent experience in
one of our products.</p>
<p>I had already made a start with this new instance, and surely my first fully
backend-data-driven visualization was only an hour or two away, giving me a
final Friday evening boost.</p>
<p>Well friends, in hindsight I should have stopped right there and then.</p>
<p>Sure, it was the sort of gamble that had often paid off in the past &ndash; who does
not like to start their weekend with the dopamine rush that comes with the
solving of a little technical puzzle, especially one that results in pretty
pictures?! &ndash; but in this case it was doomed to failure.</p>
<p>The later it got, the less able I was to debug the issue, and the less
emotional control I was able to exert over my growing frustration.</p>
<p>(I am still less than happy with the new react-vega&rsquo;s limited documentation,
error handling and examples.)</p>
<p>I went to bed far later than normal, frustrated, and with no solution in sight.</p>
<p>All of this continued to affect my Saturday (grumpy with capital G&hellip; no wait,
all capitals&hellip;), until I finally made the conscious decision to disconnect
from the technical problem completely.</p>
<p>Anyways, I&rsquo;m writing this down as a reminder to me to be really, really careful
with the work-to-weekend transition.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-1-make-my-home-smart-but-do-it-really-slowly">Techno interlude #1: Make my home smart, but do it really slowly</h2>
<p>I finally got around to hooking up one (1) of the <a href="https://shelly.cloud/products/shelly-1-smart-home-automation-relay/">Shelly 1 smart relays</a> I
bought at the end of 2020.</p>
<p>My whole family is now able to open the main yard gate using&hellip; THEIR PHONES.</p>
<p>Noteworthy here is how easily the Shelly switches can be flashed, over the air
(OTA) no less, with the third party <a href="https://github.com/mongoose-os-apps/shelly-homekit">shelly-homekit firmware</a> to make them
natively Apple homekit compatible.</p>
<p>You can read about the how and the what in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/03/05/connecting-the-shelly-1-to-an-et-systems-gate-motor-for-apple-homekit-control/">this vxlabs post</a>.</p>
<p>Shortly after that post appeared, we held a <a href="https://fb.me/e/30MWR7Rq3">&ldquo;home automation&rdquo;-themed Helderberg
Software Developers and Entrepreneurs meetup</a>. Thanks to current interest in the
topic, and the three absolutely brilliant speakers who were willing to take us
along on their HA adventure, it was the biggest and most active we&rsquo;ve had in
years, by far!</p>
<p>In another probably surprising move, we are currently moving the meetup group
away from meetup.com and onto facebook as a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/helderberg.swdev.entrep.meetups/">group</a> (join if you&rsquo;re on fb!) from
where we can easily setup events.</p>
<p>Since 2019, meetup.com has been charging a pretty ridiculous $50 / 6-months fee
for a 100% free meetup with 0 commercial intent. In return for that, they
handle attendance (ish, we ofen had &gt;50% no-shows) and supply a bit of
discoverability.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, we now fortunately also have a snazzy website at
<a href="https://helderberg.dev/">https://helderberg.dev/</a> where you&rsquo;ll always be able to find the meetup, no
matter the events platform <em>du jour</em>.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-2-make-emacs-more-prettier">Techno interlude #2: Make Emacs More Prettier</h2>
<p>In spite of general business, I did have to make time for some <code>init.el</code>
wrangling, as is the privilege and sworn duty of every Emacs user.</p>
<p>This time, I refined my font and specifically <code>variable-pitch</code> setup.</p>
<p>I settled on the <a href="https://www.figma.com/blog/the-birth-of-inter/">Inter font</a> because I liked the look of <a href="https://obsidian.md/">obsidian.md</a>, where it&rsquo;s
the default. Then I discovered that it was designed (based on the Roboto font)
by Figma designer Rasmus Andersson as &ldquo;a font meant to make it easier to read
text on computer screens&rdquo; (hey, that&rsquo;s exactly what I need!), and is now also
the default on github, mozilla, and notion. Pretty good typographic company
right there.</p>
<p>The other small change I made which was much more satisfying than I expected,
was setting the default font size based on the estimated pixel density of the
current screen.</p>
<p>This means that my Emacs will render its default fonts at sizes that make sense
on whichever display I&rsquo;m using it.</p>
<p>Yes, I know that we should have been able to specify <a href="https://github.com/kickingvegas/12pt-should-be-the-same-everywhere/blob/master/absoluteMeasurementDPI.md">resolution invariant font
sizes by now</a>, but until that future arrives, my Emacs config will just have to
compensate.</p>
<p>The screenshot below shows an example of variable-pitch rendering on the left
(org-roam entry at the bottom, automatic topic backlinks at the top) and in the
centre (a slightly earlier draft of this post) and fixed-pitch on the right,
the relevant parts of my <code>init.el</code> showing the font and (<a href="https://github.com/humanoid-colors/emacs-humanoid-themes">humanoid</a>) theme setup.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Emacs screenshot. No, I don&amp;rsquo;t like dark themes."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Emacs screenshot. No, <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">I don&rsquo;t like dark themes</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="permutation-city">Permutation City</h2>
<p>When I saw a recommendation for <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156784.Permutation_City">Permutation City, a 1994 sci-fi novel by the
Australian author Greg Egan</a>, I was hesitant.</p>
<p>Would a novel, written more than 25 years ago, about uploading digital copies
of humans to virtual reality (I wrote a bit about that in <a href="/2020/07/01/weekly-head-voices-199-a-bit-stubborn/#a-totally-unexpected-ramble-on-cycles-patterns-and-teleportation">WHV #199</a> back in
2020), still be up to date with the latest ideas on the topic, seeing that
several adjacent fields of research have been advancing at a break-neck pace in
recent decades?</p>
<p>Weeeeell&hellip;.</p>
<p>It turns out great sci-fi has no problem reaching ahead through a quarter
century of modern technological development and then blowing my mind several
times.</p>
<p>With Permutation City, Egan has written the book I would have wanted to write,
in my wildest fantasies of course, about humans, and copies of humans, and the
philosophically indistinguishable self-awareness and consciousness of the
copies, and of their copies, and so on, literally ad infinitum.</p>
<p>Fortunately this is my first Egan novel, and even more fortunately it turns out
that he has produced a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/32699.Greg_Egan">considerable collection of stories</a> which I now have the
privilege to proceed to assimilate!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2021 to 2022 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</guid><description> Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.
I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to 2014 (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and 2015 (no real excuse).
Much later, on Sunday January 23: It could very well still win the Most Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&amp;rsquo;s done.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition
post</a>!</p>








<figure><a href="20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to
<a href="/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/">2014</a> (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and <a href="/2015/01/21/weekly-head-voices-88-just-be-yourself-they-said/">2015</a> (no real
excuse).</p>
<p><em>Much later, on Sunday January 23:</em> It could very well still win the Most
Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Emacs and <code>M-x count-words</code> (on a temporary buffer copied over from <a href="/archive/#2021">the 2021
blog post archive</a>) tells me that I published 28 posts on this blog, and 8
technical posts over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>Just like with the running below, but for different reasons, I lost a lot of
steam during the last few months of the year.</p>
<p>In a truly surprise twist, in 2022 I will again attempt to write regularly, and
to write more, and to keep it up until the end.</p>
<h3 id="stats-addendum">Stats addendum</h3>
<p>Applying the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess log analyzer</a> to this blog&rsquo;s log files with the following
invocation:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#859900">for</span> i in {2..13..1}; <span style="color:#859900">do</span> <span style="color:#cb4b16">echo</span> cpbotha.net.access.log.<span style="color:#268bd2">$i</span>.gz; <span style="color:#859900">done</span>) | xargs zcat -f -- | goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; tells me that in 2021 cpbotha.net welcomed over 115000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>The same tool reports that <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a> clocked in at just under 165000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>Even if the real number of actual human visits is a quarter of what the tool is
reporting, I am ecstatic!</p>
<p>The three most popular cpbotha.net posts based on hits during 2021 were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">Dear USA, my data has left your building</a></li>
<li><a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">Note-taking strategy 2019</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>Thanks to Strava&rsquo;s handy training calendar shown below, we can see that I spent
125 hours last year (mostly, about 4 hours was spent on hiking just over 20km)
running a bit over 1300km.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can also see quite clearly that I lost steam in November and especially in
December.</p>
<p>This was initially due to work getting quite busy, and then later in December a
bout with Omicron (highly probably) and also less than run-friendly weather in
St. Francis.</p>
<p>I am always happy when I manage to average 100km or more per month, and I&rsquo;ll
probably try to do that again in 2022.</p>
<h3 id="possibly-tmi-read-on-at-your-own-risk">Possibly TMI, read on at your own risk</h3>
<p>Those of you who know me, will also know about my giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunion">bunion</a>, or hallux
valgus as it prefers to be called.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&amp;rsquo;s complicated." width="240px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyways, Mr Valgus is unfortunately playing an increasingly frequent role in my
attempts at running, often starting to complain at N kilometres where N is
fortunately still higher than most of my attempts, but still affecting a
worrying number of them.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to push on, until Mr Valgus overstays its welcome, at which point
it will be time to explore invasive corrective procedures.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Probably my most redeeming habit of them all, is reading books every night in
bed until I fall asleep.</p>
<p>Even if the day has been less than satisfactory, ending it with an entirely
deliberate and focused reading session tends to make up for quite a lot.</p>
<p>Although I was planning to do more book summaries in 2021, I managed to
complete only one. At least it was a good one, namely <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Seven
and a Half Lessons About the Brain&rdquo; by Lisa Feldman Barrett</a>, which I can
strongly recommend if you have not checked it out yet.</p>
<p>Thanks to strong contenders like the one above, the competition was fierce, but
in the end the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em> could go to nothing other
than Oliver Burkeman&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08FGV64B1/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</em></a>.</p>
<p>Burkeman, he of the <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">importance of being able to put <em>down</em> your work</a> and of <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">more
appearances on this blog</a>, has created a beautifully written ode to our terribly
limited lifespans (4000 weeks if you&rsquo;re lucky, you can almost hear them ticking
away&hellip;), and to our terribly limited capacity to make the most of the time
that we do get, and to really just giving up the fight to <em>get everything done</em>,
because we will never ever win the battle against the law of perpetually
filling inboxes of various kinds, and because it&rsquo;s so much better to simply
<em>disconnect</em> from the firehose (which we can&rsquo;t get rid of completely) in order to
spend time on no-excuses leisure, and especially on our loved ones.</p>
<p>My favourite fiction book by far was <em>The Anomaly</em> by Hervé le Tellier, as
translated by Adriana Hunter.</p>
<p>After having just grudgingly finished Elizabeth Bear&rsquo;s Ancestral Night (first
novel in the White Space series; some interesting ideas, but just too pulpy,
clumsy and exposition-rich for my taste, in spite of space opera being a guilty
pleasure&hellip;), the light literariness and French cynicism of The Anomaly was a
<em>delightful</em> and refreshing breeze that I was unable to put down until it was
done.</p>
<p>In 2022, I&rsquo;m planning to read more than in 2021, and publish more of those
summaries.</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#mindfulness">daily meditation streak that started in 2020</a> continued for most of 2021,
until the end-of-year school vacation started. I am not yet sure how I&rsquo;ll be
able to fit this into my new 2022 work-routine.</p>
<h2 id="worst-habit-of-2021">Worst habit of 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV Award for Worst Habit of 2021 By Far goes, without a doubt, to my old
friend TwiFRaF-Yo, although this time around the main culprits were Twitter,
Reddit and YouTube.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know exactly when I fell out of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">the previous social media fast</a>, but I
fell out with a vengeance.</p>
<p>Although I subscribe almost entirely to technical communities on reddit (Emacs,
Orgmode, Org-roam, keyboards, etc.), there are enough of them to keep a person
busy.</p>
<p>If you add to that my twitter feed, where I&rsquo;ve also taken care to remove the
noise, subscribing largerly to high-signal science-, technology- , and
engineering-related feeds, there&rsquo;s a great deal of valuable-seeming information
that one feels compelled to get through every day&hellip;</p>
<p>(It feels like I&rsquo;ve told this story before&hellip;)</p>
<p>Anyways, every time I manage to disconnect (it&rsquo;s been a few weeks now, I think
Monday January 3 was the official start date of the current fast), only then am
I able to recognise (where by &ldquo;recognise&rdquo;, I mean that friends say this to me,
and this is when I&rsquo;m able to admit that they&rsquo;re right) that the net value for
me is highly probably negative.</p>
<p>While there is certainly valuable information that enters via those streams, it
costs so much attention and emotional energy that it&rsquo;s not really worth it.</p>
<p>So.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m back on the no-social-media cart until next time.</p>
<p>Just like the previous time, I&rsquo;m limiting myself to the brilliant Inoreader RSS
subscription service (which I pay for) to keep up to date with 99% long-form
blogs, and two Twitter accounts that are worth too much to me to disconnect
from (<a href="https://twitter.com/erictopol">Eric Topol</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/alper">Alper Çuğun-Gscheidel</a>).</p>
<p>Although I sometimes think this makes me slower, because I don&rsquo;t have all of
the current happenings at my fingertips all the time, I&rsquo;m hoping this gives me
more space and time for reading, thinking and writing.</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">Systems and tools for running this human (PKM baby)</h2>
<p>In the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">2018 to 2019 transition post</a> I mentioned the &ldquo;The System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This time, for this section, I would like to limit it to tools for knowledge
management and task management (this is not my favourite term, but I&rsquo;m erring
on the side of familiarity here) .</p>
<p>All of Emacs and Orgmode and Org-roam is still going strong, although I waver
quite a bit sometimes when I see some of the shiny new things, like <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>,
which I would probably be using if it wasn&rsquo;t for Emacs.</p>
<p>However, when I sometimes dive into my notes, I can see the difference it makes
when you stick to a single tool for longer than a few years. The amount of
knowledge keeps on growing, and I am slowly getting better at linking it all
together and&hellip;  sometimes even using it.</p>
<p>The picture below shows the graph created, by the <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> package, of a
sub-section of my notes network:</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Before I got side-tracked by the pretty picture, I was planning to dedicate
this section to a new WHV award, namely the Award for the Most Unexpectedly
Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021.</p>
<p>This year the award goes to&hellip; <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper/guide">Dropbox Paper</a>!</p>
<p>Back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">WHV #233</a> I listed many of the reasons why. In the few months since then
it has become only more useful to me as the go-to mobile tool for checklists
(especially useful when we go on trips), lists of books, movies and music
recommended by people in person, and so on.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualifier features, such as its markdown DNA and its
usability on mobile for idea capturing, the fact that Paper documents show up
in Dropbox searches, which is how I usually search when I <span class="underline">really</span> need to find a
specific file (versus ripgrep searches in Orgmode), is the deal maker.</p>
<p>(My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">strange scheme for continuously converting all org files to docx</a> for
searching and reading on the iPhone is also still going strong.)</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I had a piece written here with more details about what exactly was happening
at work, but I decided to nuke that and instead keep it more personal by
mentioning that thanks to great big dollops of serendipity and people, I find
myself, with a number of levers at my disposal, right in the middle of an
organization which, after a few months of reconfiguration and preparation, has
embarked on a genuinely exciting, and importantly more unified, course.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not mention the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">discomfort and stress</a> I was
experiencing at the start of the current personal phase, most probably due to
trying to adapt quickly to my new circumstances and responsibilities.</p>
<p>In the time since then, my stress levels have returned to more acceptable
levels, but expectations remain high.</p>
<h2 id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<p>One of the most positive changes I made in the past year, was to put more
effort into making regular and active (virtual) contact with friends whom I
don&rsquo;t see in person regularly enough.</p>
<p>THANKS INTERNET YOU DA BEST.</p>
<p>This year, I want to try harder to do more of that.</p>
<p>More generally, I made a note (yes, again, one has to keep doing this until the
end) to celebrate any of my peeps and our relationships whenever there&rsquo;s a
chance.</p>
<p>Secret message for my innner INNER circle: You are my energy and my joy, I am
here to be yours.</p>
<p>Whatever else happens, these precious relationships are all we have.</p>
<h2 id="even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">Even more plans for 2022: Continue trying</h2>
<p>First off, I would really like to get this blog post here done and
published. (it wants to be too much, or rather I want it to be too much, and so
we sit here staring at each other instead of just getting on with it so I can
try again to write a good post for once)</p>
<p>Second, EAZ is back on, since Monday January 10. EAZ means no alcohol until at
least February 10. As has been the case previously, my sleep quality is
subjectively better, and it seems like my energy levels are more consistent
throughout the week.</p>
<p>I just looked back at last year&rsquo;s transition post, and especially at the <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">final
sections, including the neatly documented Life Systems 2021</a>. That guy
(<a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">apparently we share only about 2% of our atoms</a>) really seemed to have his
stuff together, on paper at the very least.</p>
<p>As I write this (22:38 on Saturday, January 22), I have just realised that <em>this</em>
&ldquo;I&rdquo; definitely needs to spend some more time thinking about &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo; (The WHV
approach to life, the universe and everything, the one with the pillars (love
and science, that&rsquo;s the easy and reliable bit) and the rules) and specifically
if and how to revise the daily life direction clusters.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll have it on your desk by Monday.</p>
<p>Until then, the one thing I&rsquo;m sure about, is that I wish you and your loved
ones the best 2022 possible.</p>








<figure><a href="stormsriver-mouth.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Morgan McGuire Markdeep project Management Method: MMMMM.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 21:37:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/</guid><description> This weekend, Morgan McGuire, graphics and game programming god, tweeted a thread about his text journal based method of software development project management.
Here I single out three of the tweets, but you should really read the whole thread:
When coding, I always maintain a journal in the repo (I happen to use Markdeep for this now) with a TODO list.
Tasks are at the level of one hour for &amp;ldquo;today&amp;rdquo; stuff, one day for next week, and then week- or longer level tasks.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This weekend, Morgan McGuire, graphics and game programming god, <a href="https://twitter.com/CasualEffects/status/1241329539902570498">tweeted a
thread about his text journal based method of software development project
management</a>.</p>
<p>Here I single out three of the tweets, but you should really read the whole
thread:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When coding, I always maintain a journal in the repo (I happen to use Markdeep
for this now) with a TODO list.</p>
<p>Tasks are at the level of one hour for &ldquo;today&rdquo; stuff, one day for next week,
and then week- or longer level tasks.</p>
<p>I expand the details for the next week on Friday.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tweet 3:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When I start working on the top, ~1-hour item, on the list, I immediately
expand it recursively until the subtasks are completely braindead to
implement.</p>
<p>I do all of the hard part of programming here, in the TODO list, figuring out
the library calls, designing the APIs, etc.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Tweet 4:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When I get into the actual source code, I&rsquo;m just working from my own
walk-through on the TODO list, and I only need to think about syntax and code
cleanup. I can focus on programming legibly in the small instead of worrying
about the big picture.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He shows the following screenshot as an example:</p>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/mmmmm_example_journal.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/mmmmm_example_journal_hu708b383afffb5b210387c092519a5f71_284523_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/mmmmm_example_journal_hu708b383afffb5b210387c092519a5f71_284523_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/mmmmm_example_journal_hu708b383afffb5b210387c092519a5f71_284523_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/mmmmm_example_journal_hu708b383afffb5b210387c092519a5f71_284523_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/mmmmm_example_journal_hu708b383afffb5b210387c092519a5f71_284523_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<p>This is such a brilliant way of doing the highest level &ldquo;programming&rdquo; in an
outlining tool, and then working one&rsquo;s way down until it&rsquo;s eventually time to
jump into the code.</p>
<p>I can also immediately see how well this would work in a team context.</p>
<p>During the planning session, the outline could be collaboratively fleshed
out. Furthermore, as McGuire states, it can be fleshed out differently
depending on the experience level of the team member.</p>
<p>This makes me wonder how much we as engineers <em>really</em> need the Jiras and the
YouTracks and the DevOpses of the world?</p>
<p>(Just joking folks, I know we need it, but perhaps we could do with a little
more MMMMM in our lives?)</p>
<h2 id="markdeep">Markdeep.</h2>
<p>Almost in passing McGuire mentions markdeep, the system he designed for
extremely agile technical documentation.</p>
<p>A friend from work introduced me to this years ago (thanks HB!), but then I
somehow missed its genius.</p>
<p>One of the core ideas that makes markdeep so interesting and useful, is that
the markdeep plaintext markup (it&rsquo;s like supercharged markdown) is embedded in
an extremely thin layer of HTML which invokes the markdeep.js renderer on
itself.</p>
<p>In other words, you edit the self-contained <code>.md.html</code> file with your favourite
text editor, but when you open this file in your browser, a single line of HTML
at the end pulls in <code>markdeep.min.js</code> from a CDN or from your local disc, and
renders the beautifully typeset version of the document.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, markdeep has extensive support for the SVG rendering
of ascii art.</p>
<p>See the following pages for more information:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://casual-effects.com/markdeep/">The Markdeep website</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://casual-effects.com/markdeep/features.md.html">The extensive Markdeep demo
document</a> - especially
the <a href="https://casual-effects.com/markdeep/features.md.html#diagramexamples">diagram
examples</a>
are impressive!</li>
</ul>
<p>For my own notes I am sticking to <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Orgmode</a> (if you&rsquo;re an
emacs user, it&rsquo;s more powerful), but there will surely be situations where the
self-contained Markdeep makes more sense.</p>
<h2 id="the-graphics-codex">The Graphics Codex.</h2>
<p>Markdeep has been used to author a number of books, but <a href="http://graphicscodex.com/">The Graphics
Codex</a> must be one of the more amazing examples, in
terms of its interactivity and just general prettiness.</p>
<p>The iPhone app version looks like this:</p>
<a href="http://graphicscodex.com/">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/iphone5-large_hu6d6bf869dea808897c5bb056b398e0ba_271138_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/iphone5-large_hu6d6bf869dea808897c5bb056b398e0ba_271138_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/iphone5-large_hu6d6bf869dea808897c5bb056b398e0ba_271138_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/iphone5-large_hu6d6bf869dea808897c5bb056b398e0ba_271138_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/24/the-morgan-mcguire-markdeep-project-management-method-mmmmm/iphone5-large_hu6d6bf869dea808897c5bb056b398e0ba_271138_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
  

   />



</a>
<p>I bought the web version not because I currently need a graphics reference, but
rather because it is a thing of beauty, and because I wanted to be able to see
better how it all works.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Forming and maintaining habits using Orgmode.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 16:48:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/</guid><description> In this post, I explain how to get up and running with Emacs Orgmode habits.
Even if you&amp;rsquo;re not planning to use Emacs for this, it might be interesting context for the development of other ideas for habit tracking tricks and tools.
The importance of habits. If you have some experience being, you know, alive, and perhaps even trying to get just that little bit better at it every day, you will have realised by now that being able to form and maintain good habits is almost a super power.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this post, I explain how to get up and running with Emacs Orgmode habits.</p>
<p>Even if you&rsquo;re not planning to use Emacs for this, it might be interesting
context for the development of other ideas for habit tracking tricks and tools.</p>
<h2 id="the-importance-of-habits">The importance of habits.</h2>
<p>If you have some experience being, you know, alive, and perhaps even trying to
get just that little bit better at it every day, you will have realised by now
that being able to form and maintain good habits is almost a super power.</p>
<p>(Other real-life super powers: Kindness. Peace. Focus. I digress&hellip; haha.)</p>
<p>All of those promises we make to ourselves to read more, to eat better, to
exercise more, to meditate regularly, and so on: The key to making all of these
happen is forming and then maintaining habits.</p>
<p>First the habit has to be created out of nothing, and once it&rsquo;s up and running,
the idea is to keep going at it for as long as possible.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">Streaking</a>,
that is trying to continue for as long as possible without any interruption, is
a fun and effective trick to keep at it.</p>
<p>However, it is just as important being able to restart a new streak once the
previous one has been broken for whatever reason.</p>
<h2 id="what-the-orgmode-habit-tracker-does">What the Orgmode habit tracker does.</h2>
<p>Up to now, I mostly used <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#monthly-journal-files">daily checklists to keep track of healthy
habits</a>, but for
some habits, especially ones with a non-daily frequency, this does not work so
well.</p>
<p>A significant step up from daily checklists, the <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Tracking-your-habits.html">Emacs Orgmode habits
function</a> enables you:</p>
<ul>
<li>to specify any number of habits, each with different, sometimes less regular
frequencies;</li>
<li>to track when you perform a habit and when you should next perform it and finally</li>
<li>to visualize if you are performing according to the specifications you have
set.</li>
</ul>
<p>For example: I would like to run at least three times a week. There should be
at least one rest day after a running day (I&rsquo;m not a spring chicken
anymore). There should be a maximum of three rest days allowed (this usually
happens after a longer weekend run).</p>
<p>Although I enjoy running enough to keep this habit up by myself, I chose it as
a first test of the Orgmode habits function.</p>
<p>So far I have setup two other simpler examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>A core exercise which I call &ldquo;The Wheel&rdquo; (of pain). This has to happen every
second day, usually in between running days.</li>
<li>&ldquo;Deep reading&rdquo;, which is meant to describe a session of focused reading of
long-form, i.e. mostly books. This has to happen every day.</li>
</ul>
<p>Before starting tracking of these latter two habits slightly more than a week
ago, I somehow kept on letting them slip.</p>
<p>This morning, my org-agenda looked like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot.png">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu66c0ac3ba129dae999c7a15c38ad8dc3_53878_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu66c0ac3ba129dae999c7a15c38ad8dc3_53878_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu66c0ac3ba129dae999c7a15c38ad8dc3_53878_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu66c0ac3ba129dae999c7a15c38ad8dc3_53878_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu66c0ac3ba129dae999c7a15c38ad8dc3_53878_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
  

   />

</a>

</figure>
<p>In the figure you can see that today, represented by the exclamation mark <code>!</code>,
I will have to schedule in a session of deep reading (indicated by the yellow
colouring), and a session of &ldquo;the wheel&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The running habit graph  is showing that I still have three days, including
today, on which I do not have to run.</p>
<p>By default it would not have displayed today, because I ran yesterday, as shown
by the asterisk <code>*</code>, and I specified that minimum of one rest day. However, I
temporarily configured it to show today for the sake of this exposition.</p>
<p>To summarise: These habit graphs show up as part of your org-agenda view and
show you at a glance when you should perform which habits, and, quite
importantly, how long you have been streaking a particular habit.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-setup-orgmode-habits">How to setup Orgmode habits.</h2>
<h3 id="global-configuration">Global configuration.</h3>
<p>Firstly, ensure that the <code>org-habit</code> Orgmode extension is activated by adding
the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-elisp" data-lang="elisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#268bd2">add-to-list</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#39;org-modules</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#39;org-habit</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">t</span>)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Whilst your in your <code>init.el</code>, add something like the following to activate
state logging for the task <code>DONE</code> state:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-elisp" data-lang="elisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; each state with ! is recorded as state change</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; in this case I&#39;m logging TODO and DONE states</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#cb4b16">setq</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">org-todo-keywords</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      &#39;((<span style="color:#268bd2">sequence</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;TODO(t!)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;NEXT(n)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;SOMD(s)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;WAFO(w)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;|&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;DONE(d!)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;CANC(c!)&#34;</span>)))
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; I prefer to log TODO creation also</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#cb4b16">setq</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">org-treat-insert-todo-heading-as-state-change</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">t</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; log into LOGBOOK drawer</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#cb4b16">setq</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">org-log-into-drawer</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">t</span>)
</span></span></code></pre></div><h3 id="per-habit-configuration">Per-habit configuration.</h3>
<p>Then, start creating the special habit nodes as explained in the following:</p>
<p>Below is what the &ldquo;running&rdquo; habit currently looks like in my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#monthly-journal-files">current monthly
journal file</a>:</p>
<!-- I used M-x htmlize-region-save-screenshot to get this HTML representation of a real org file onto the clipboard. -->
<pre style="color: #DCDCCC; background-color: #3F3F3F;">
<span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">** </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">TODO</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;"> Running</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">SCHEDULED:</span> <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">&lt;2019-11-03 Sun .+2d/4d&gt;</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:PROPERTIES:</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:STYLE:</span>    habit
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:LAST_REPEAT:</span> <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-11-01 Wed 16:00]</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:END:</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:LOGBOOK:</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-11-01 Wed 16:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-30 Wed 15:41]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-26 Sat 14:14]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-24 Thu 19:11]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-22 Tue 16:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-20 Sun 10:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-18 Fri 16:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-18 Fri 16:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-16 Wed 08:13]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-13 Sun 10:00]</span>
- Created "TODO" <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-23 Wed 09:53]</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:END:</span>
</pre>
<p>The <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Tracking-your-habits.html">orgmode habits
documentation</a> explains
that a habit is a special sort of <code>TODO</code> node with the following additional
properties, which can all be seen in the above example:</p>
<ul>
<li>The node has a <code>:STYLE:</code> property of <code>habit</code>. Configure with =M-x
org-set-property=.</li>
<li>The node has a <code>SCHEDULED</code> date in the future on the next date when this
habit should take place, along with a frequency / time constraint
specification, in this case <code>.+2d/4d</code>, meaning that at the most every second
day, and at the least every fourth day.</li>
</ul>
<p>Furthermore, with <code>DONE</code> state logging configured as explained above, you&rsquo;ll
get the <code>LOGBOOK</code> with the required state changes used by the habit graphs.</p>
<h3 id="in-use">In use.</h3>
<p>Whenever you&rsquo;ve completed a habit, fire up Emacs (I&rsquo;m joking of course: Emacs
is always running) and then toggle the state of the habit to <code>DONE</code>.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;ll see that it briefly toggles to <code>DONE</code>, and then automatically switches
back to <code>TODO</code>.</p>
<p>(There&rsquo;s some philosophical lesson to be learned from that&hellip;)</p>
<p>When this happens, the <code>:LAST_REPEAT:</code> timestamp will be automatically updated
to the current time, and, more importantly, the <code>SCHEDULED</code> date will be
automatically updated to the next earliest date when this habit should be
exercised.</p>
<p>In the case of the running example above, that will be tomorrow, as today is a
rest day.</p>
<p>Whenever you activate org-agenda, you&rsquo;ll see the habit graphs right at the top,
by default only on the days when they are actually scheduled. In the running
example, that habit will not appear on rest days. (This can naturally be
configured, see <code>M-x describe-variable RET org-habit-show-all-today</code>).</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion.</h2>
<ul>
<li>Being able to forming and maintain habits can form an important component of
better living.</li>
<li><em>Habit streaking</em> is a fun psychological trick to keep you going.</li>
<li>However, don&rsquo;t be disheartened by a broken streak. Get back on that horse and
try again.</li>
<li>Emacs Orgmode habit tracking is a great tool for Emacs users to help form and
maintain habits, especially non-daily ones.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Note-taking strategy 2019.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 16:19:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/</guid><description><![CDATA[ At the start of 2016, I published an overview of my note-taking strategy then.
In the intervening three and a half years, my note-taking has further evolved to adapt to my changing environment, and the underlying &ldquo;system&rdquo; has co-evolved to support this.
Although note-taking is at the core of the system, a more accurate description of its current purpose would be personal knowledge management.
What you&rsquo;ll also find in this post, is the culmination of many years of lessons learned trying to &ldquo;keep a lab journal&rdquo;.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>At the start of 2016, I published an <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">overview of my note-taking strategy
then</a>.</p>
<p>In the intervening three and a half years, my note-taking has further evolved
to adapt to my changing environment, and the underlying &ldquo;system&rdquo; has co-evolved
to support this.</p>
<p>Although note-taking is at the core of the system, a more accurate description
of its current purpose would be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_knowledge_management"><em>personal knowledge
management</em></a>.</p>
<p>What you&rsquo;ll also find in this post, is the culmination of many years of lessons
learned trying to <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#three">&ldquo;keep a lab
journal&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<h2 id="highest-level-overview-of-note-taking-system">Highest level overview of note-taking system.</h2>
<p>My approach consists of four main components:</p>
<p>At the core of everything is <a href="https://orgmode.org/"><strong>1. Emacs Org mode</strong></a>.</p>
<p>As you might know, Org mode is infinitely flexible. This is where all of my
projects and tasks are tracked. This is also where I keep my daily personal and
work journals.</p>
<p>I describe the specific directory structure and orgfile setup in the sections
below.</p>
<p>I continually and actively search for and find interesting <strong>2. Web-pages and
Articles</strong>, both academic and less so, which I convert to PDF and store in a
year-stamped directory inside of my
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">JBOP</a>.</p>
<p><strong>3. Academic articles</strong> that I plan to refer to in my own writings graduate into my
Zotero bibliographic database, which is synced together with everything else.</p>
<p>On <strong>4. Mobile</strong> (phone and watch, oh my!), I use the Dropbox app for capturing
and for limited access to my notes database via a small subset of markdown
files, PDFs and exported HTML, and I use the new WatchOS 6 voice notes if I&rsquo;m
not able to use my phone.</p>
<h3 id="other-noteworthy-characteristics">Other noteworthy characteristics.</h3>
<p>Everything mentioned above lives on local drives, synced with Dropbox and also
automatically and continuously backed-up to a removable disk at my office.</p>
<p>The Org mode part of the system has been in use since 2014. I have also
imported a few years of Simplenote text notes into Org mode, so its memory
stretches a bit further back still.</p>
<p>The longer the system lasts, the more valuable it gets.</p>
<p>It has now happened more than once that I could help someone with the same
advice I helped someone else with 4 years ago, simply because the real-time
text search found the relevant snippet of code or attachment in my Org mode
database.</p>
<p>Even if I were ever to change tools, the current single source of truth is a
collection of plaintext org files and PDF files which can easily be further
processed and imported into some new system.</p>
<h2 id="the-components-in-slightly-more-detail">The components in slightly more detail.</h2>
<p>In the following sections, I explain each of the four components in more detail
than in the overview above.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-org-mode">Emacs Org mode.</h3>
<p>The heart of my knowledge management system, let&rsquo;s call it <code>pkb4000</code>, is <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Emacs
Org mode</a>. Org mode, or &ldquo;Your life in plaintext&rdquo;, is a
powerful text-file-based system for managing notes, task lists, projects and
even authoring documents.</p>
<p>Once you get used to the programmable flexibility it offers, you will find it
hard to go back to any conventional system.</p>
<h4 id="monthly-journal-files">Monthly journal files.</h4>
<p>In my main Org mode directory, I have a subdirectory named <code>journals</code>, which
contains a directory for each year.</p>
<p>Each of these year directories contains an <code>.org</code> file for each month, so we would have for example
<code>journals/2019/2019-09-Sep.org</code>.</p>
<p>Each month file follows the structure showed in the following redacted version
of my current journal file:</p>
<!-- I used M-x htmlize-region-save-screenshot to get this HTML representation of a real org file onto the clipboard. -->
<pre style="color: #DCDCCC; background-color: #3F3F3F;">
<span style="color: #b3b3b3;">#+TITLE:</span> <span style="color: #8CD0D3; background-color: #3F3F3F; font-weight: bold;">2019-09 September month journal
</span>
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Vitals</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Focus items</span>
Topics and reminders I would like to spend a few minutes on during every
morning review: High value time, always be compounding, always be in a focus
block, etc.
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tired list</span>
A general list of valuable activities for when I have some time, but brain too
tired to come up with anything.
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Planning / overview / major done list</span>
Check lists with books, courses, etc.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Projects</span>
A list of current major projects, with links to each project's dedicated org
file.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks</span>
A list of Org mode tasks that are not associated with specific projects. This
list is reviewed at the start of every month, as I have to manually copy across
those tasks that are still relevant and important.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019-09 September</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">**</span><span style="color: #7CB8BB; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019-09-19 Thursday (example day)</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">***</span><span style="color: #D0BF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Day planning </span><span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-09-19 Thu 09:17]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Done list / thoughts / diary</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks for today </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[/]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[/]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Focus blocks</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Sleep</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Review </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[3/8]</span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> <span style="color: #D0BF8F; text-decoration: underline;"><a href="*Vitals">Month vitals</a></span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> Calendar
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> Org tasks
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> <span style="color: #D0BF8F; text-decoration: underline;"><a href="file:~/Dropbox/notes/mobile/inbox/">dropbox mobile inbox</a></span>
      - ...

<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Habits / important </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[7/12]</span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> 7.5 hrs sleep last night
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> are you satisfied with number of pomodori? = 0 (v R)
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> did you write stuff down?
      - ...
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">***</span><span style="color: #D0BF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* is dropbox better than evernote for mobile capturing? </span><span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">&lt;2019-09-19 Thu 22:16&gt;</span>

     in ios, with any page in safari, I can do "save to dropbox" and get a PDF
     version of the page for the <span style="color: #b3b3b3;">=notes/mobile/inbox=</span>.
</pre>
<p>As you can see from the example above, the monthly journal file is the main
index to my current high-level goals and focus items, my currently running work
and personal projects, miscellaneous tasks, and my detailed daily journalling
and habit tracking.</p>
<h5 id="daily-review">Daily review.</h5>
<p>When I start the day, I instantiate a new org-capture &ldquo;day planning&rdquo; template
by pressing <code>C-c c p</code>.</p>
<p>This creates the <code>Day planning</code> subsection with all of its subsections and
checklists. As you will see, this guides me through the morning review, which
in turn has me check each of those additional sources of incoming information
and tasks.</p>
<p>New bits of information are filed into their correct place, whilst the task
review shows me a list of tasks, extracted from the month file and the list of
current project files, so that I can decide which ones should be taken on.</p>
<p>I list tasks which should preferably be taken care of today under <code>Tasks for today</code>, whilst any really high-value high-satisfaction tasks go under <code>Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl</code>.</p>
<h5 id="during-the-day">During the day.</h5>
<p>During the rest of the day, I&rsquo;ll write short diary-like notes under <code>Done list / thoughts / diary</code> and log pomodori (focus blocks) under, you guessed it,
<code>Focus blocks</code>, either using the <code>org-pomodoro</code> package, or plain Org mode
clocking in and out functions.</p>
<p>I use additional custom org-capture templates, via keyboard shortcuts, to
create more extensive timestamped journal entries (see the <code>is dropbox better ...</code> example) and to create new timestamped and logged Org mode <code>TODO</code> entries.</p>
<h5 id="kill-your-darlings-during-the-monthly-review">Kill your darlings (during the monthly review).</h5>
<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned this before, but it&rsquo;s just an important aspect of my &ldquo;system&rdquo;
that I would like to mention it again.</p>
<p>When I still used primitive task management systems such as <em>everything else</em>
that&rsquo;s not Org mode, the collection of more mature tasks would soon grow out of
control.</p>
<p>However, because I create a new Org mode file for every month, I have to copy
across manually any tasks that have not been completed yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WHY IS THAT NOT AUTOMATED YET?!&rdquo; you are probably thinking.</p>
<p>Well, the advantage of having to copy each task over manually is that it is the
ideal opportunity to evaluate the task and ask some hard questions as to its
continued relevance&hellip;</p>
<p>When a task gets too old, I will often make the decision to change its status
to <code>CANC</code> (for cancelled), sometimes with the reason for the cancellation
explained in the task body, and then just leave it there in the old month file.</p>
<p>With most of these task systems, regular reviews are of crucial importance. The
monthly start-over is a great, almost enforced, opportunity for review, as is
the morning routine when I instantiate the day planner template.</p>
<h5 id="what-about-email">What about email?!</h5>
<p>An important part of knowledge and task management is one&rsquo;s emails.</p>
<p>Although I currently prefer processing my email using
<a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email"><code>mu4e</code></a>,
an email client which lives inside of Emacs, I have used other tools in the
past, and will probably use new tools in the future.</p>
<p>Also, even at this moment I alternate between <code>mu4e</code> and the
<a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">FastMail</a>
web-interface.</p>
<p>Long story short, I have it setup so that I can easily convert any email in
<code>mu4e</code> into a universal <code>message://message-id</code> link to be integrated with a
new task or note entry.</p>
<p>When I later open that link using a shortcut, I have programmed it so that
<code>mu4e</code> will open the relevant email if it is active, or the <code>FastMail</code> webmail
when it is not. From here I can either review the email to see what the
associated task requires, or respond to it, if the task has been completed.</p>
<p>Some of these <code>message://</code> links were created using macOS mail and they still
work. In future, if I add a new mail client to the mix, I will still be able to
jump to specific old emails, no matter where they find themselves inside of my
FastMail mailboxes.</p>
<h4 id="core-notes-database">Core notes database.</h4>
<p>With <code>database</code> I of course refer to hundreds of org and markdown files, most
of which find themselves in the top-level <code>pkb4000</code> directory, one level up
from the <code>journals</code> directory containing all of the monthly journal files.</p>
<p>There are files on various <code>rsync</code> or <code>ffmpeg</code> invocations, files on
programming languages, software tools, note-taking strategies, personal
information on each of my kids, and much more.</p>
<p>Org mode enables me to combine document structure, math, vector and bitmap
images and executable source code in many different languages.</p>
<p>I have configured my Emacs (where by &ldquo;configured&rdquo; I mean &ldquo;coded up the emacs
lisp for&rdquo;) to invoke ripgrep on different subsets of my notes database, and to
proffer up the results in different ways.</p>
<p>I can usually find anything that went in to this database at any point.</p>
<p>What I really like, is also being able to tell you on which day, and during
which hour, I learned this or that, or experimented with something or the
other.</p>
<h4 id="project-files">Project files.</h4>
<p>Work and personal projects each get their own Org file. Some projects even get
a whole directory to themselves, in cases where the project will have many more
files than just the main Org file.</p>
<p>In all cases, the project org file will live somewhere below a year-stamped
directory, e.g. <code>work/projects/2019/project-name/</code>.</p>
<p>Some projects go over year boundaries, but their files and directories remain
in the year that they started in. The project org also has <code>Tasks</code> and a
datetree section, similar to the month journal.</p>
<p>All current project files, along with my the current month file, are configured
to be part of the <code>org-agenda-files</code> variable.</p>
<p>This means that when I activate the <code>org-agenda</code> view, I see a unified list of
all tasks as extracted from all current project files and the current monthly
journal file.</p>
<p>When a project is completed, it is of course removed from <code>org-agenda-files</code>.</p>
<h3 id="web-pages-and-articles">Web-pages and articles.</h3>
<p>As mentioned in the short system overview, I store all web-pages and articles I
come across as date-stamped PDF files in a set of year-stamped directories.</p>
<p>For more detail, please refer to the
<a href="/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">JBOP</a>
section of WHV#165 on this blog.</p>
<p>In short, I use good ad-blocking and <em>mostly</em> the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/">printfriendly browser
extension</a> in Brave or Chromium to convert any
interesting web-pages to PDF. PDF articles from journals and other reputable
sources obviously don&rsquo;t have to be converted.</p>
<p>I name and save these PDFs into my <code>refs</code> hierarchy, for example
<code>Dropbox/refs/2019/20190518 Measles and Immune Amnesia - asm.pdf</code>.</p>
<p>Usually, to win any argument, I can find the pertinent reference on my phone or
my laptop in 30 seconds or less.</p>
<p>(I used to be a paying Pocket subscriber. However, as you will read in WHV#165
cited above, I was disappointed by the super important search function. The
advantages of having Just a Bunch of PDFs on your (synced) disc are many.)</p>
<h3 id="zotero">Zotero.</h3>
<p>The <code>refs</code> directory hierarchy described above is great for quickly storing an
article in the right place with a suitable name, ready for search-based
retrieval later.</p>
<p>However, in cases where one needs to cite any academics works, having these
articles in a good reference manager is important.</p>
<p>Zotero is in my view one of the best reference managers out there, and it&rsquo;s open
source!</p>
<p>The reasons I prefer zotero are:</p>
<ul>
<li>You can make use of their synchronisation service, or you can do it
yourself. I have about 2.3GB of additional articles in zotero, so this is
great.</li>
<li>Zotero uses your browser to retrieve fulltexts automatically when you import
any web-page with bibliographic information using the browser extension. This
is great when you have access via your institution. Competing cloud services
would historically use <em>their</em> servers to retrieve the fulltext, which would
often not work.</li>
<li>Zotero is open source. To me this is important, <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/zotero/">because on more than one
occasion</a> I have been able to make small
modifications to make it perform peculiar tricks I needed at that point.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="mobile">Mobile.</h3>
<p>This has always been the weakest part of my whole knowledge management system.</p>
<p>Ideally, I would have easy access to my complete org database and any related
files. Ideally, it would be possible to store any interesting tidbits I come
across whilst browsing using my phone.</p>
<p>So far I have invested time in the following apps and ecosystems:</p>
<ul>
<li>iCloud Notes: This was great, until <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/#so-tell-me-why-did-your-somewhat-stylish-macbook-phase-have-to-come-to-an-end">I sold my
MacBook</a>. iCloud
Notes web-access is terribly slow and more or less unusable. Whatever I have
on mobile, needs to interoperate smoothly with desktop.</li>
<li>Google Keep: This worked pretty well on mobile and via the web, but it&rsquo;s a
closed off ecosystem. You can
<a href="https://takeout.google.com/settings/takeout">&ldquo;takeout&rdquo;</a> your data, but you
end up with ginormous HTML files (images are base64-encoded and included)
that are not straight-forward to work with.</li>
<li>OneNote: This has SO MUCH potential (free-form note-taking, drawing with
Apple Pencil, apps for so many platforms, great organization, etc. etc.) but
is just so frustratingly unusable due to syncing issues everywhere, even on
my true-blue Windows 10 laptop with the true-blue official gold star
Microsoft OneNote application. Microsoft is doing fantastic work in some
domains (Visual Studio Code, .net core, WSL, etc. etc.) but in some others
not so much it seems.</li>
<li>Evernote: I recently just gave up and bought a premium subscription for the
year, because Evernote is the industry standard and it had Apple Watch voice
notes even before WatchOS 6 was released. In any case, although initially
promising, Evernote is unfortunately quite slow at unpredictable moments
(sharing web-page with evernote mobile app for storage can sometimes take 20
second or more&hellip;) so I&rsquo;ve had to ditch it. Again.</li>
</ul>
<p>During all of this experimentation, I started storing mobile discoveries in a
new section called &ldquo;inbox&rdquo; in the relevant note-taking app&rsquo;s organizational
structure. During morning review, I go through the relevant inbox, and
re-convert the relevant page into PDF for my more permanent archive.</p>
<p>It dawned on me that this approach could also be applied with just the Dropbox
app! It would be klunky, but at least not disappointing.</p>
<p>So, when I want to store something from the phone, I either print to PDF or
make use of the &ldquo;Save to Dropbox&rdquo; app extension, and then store the resultant
PDF in <code>Dropbox/notes/inbox</code>. During morning review, PDFs in this directory are
re-converted if required, and then stored in their more permanent home.</p>
<p>Using the Dropbox app, I can also create markdown text files in the <code>inbox</code>
directory.</p>
<p>If I have something a little more extensive, I have the option of using the
&ldquo;Voice Memos&rdquo; app, either on the phone, or even via the Apple Watch.</p>
<p>In <code>Dropbox/notes/mobile</code> I keep items I often need to access from the phone:
Think loyalty cards, markdown files with IP numbers and configuration of my
home network, and so on. This directory is marked as &ldquo;available offline&rdquo;, so I
can access its contents even when there&rsquo;s no data connection.</p>
<p>Other than that, I do an export of my whole org database to HTML now and then,
following a procedure similar to the one I used <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">to use for exporting Org mode
to iCloud
Notes</a>. The
HTML versions are searchable on the phone.</p>
<p>What would be better, is if the Dropbox iOS app would start recognising .org
files as plaintext files, much like what it already does for markdown .md
files. As it stands, I keep a small subset of my notes as markdown, instead of
the superior org, for mobile editing.</p>
<h4 id="drawing-with-apple-pencil-on-the-ipad-using-notability">Drawing with Apple Pencil on the iPad using Notability.</h4>
<p>Sometimes one does need to sketch.</p>
<p>This could be a rough UI, an architecture diagram, a data flow chart, or just
doodling.</p>
<p>Since about the end of 2018, I&rsquo;ve been using the <a href="https://apps.apple.com/za/app/notability/id360593530">Notability
app</a> along with an iPad
6th gen (2018 entry-level, the first non-Pro to support the Pencil) to doodle
electronically.</p>
<p>Notability automatically syncs all of these drawings as fully vectorised PDFs
to my Dropbox. All handwritten text is quite smartly OCRd, and the OCRd version
is stored as correctly positioned metadata behind my ugly scribbles.</p>
<p>I would have liked Notability even more if it supported arbitrary canvas sizes
(as it stands, only standard paper size in protrait mode), and had an always
visible overview minimap.</p>
<h4 id="signal-messaging-apps-brilliant-note-to-self-contact">Signal messaging app&rsquo;s brilliant &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo; contact.</h4>
<p>The <a href="https://signal.org/">Signal messaging app</a>, which you should all be using,
has a built-in contact called &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As of late (since about December 2019) this has become my main <em>capturing tool</em>
when I&rsquo;m on the phone.</p>
<p>You can share links, media, photos, voice notes or a plain old text message,
all of which will be securely stored, neatly timestampted to boot, in your
conversation with this silent but very useful &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo; character.</p>
<p>During the morning review, I go through each of the shared items, processing
them, and then add the message &ldquo;DONE =====&gt;&rdquo; to indicate that they have been
completed.</p>
<h2 id="limitations-and-points-for-improvement">Limitations and points for improvement.</h2>
<p>The current system is great for capturing and search-based retrieval of
personal knowledge.</p>
<p>However, I miss functionality for making some of the higher-level patterns and
networks more <em>discoverable</em>.</p>
<p>For example, as I create a new orgmode entry, the system could show me related,
older nodes (that is something I could implement&hellip;).</p>
<p>Furthermore, it would have been great to see some form of visual representation
of the associations between nodes, and of how they fit into higher-level
concepts. This bit is slightly far-fetched.</p>
<p>Interestingly, I just ran into the following paragraph at the end of <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">my 2016
note-taking post</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>However, I think that there might be room for a fourth type of tool that is
more visual, supports rich and graphical linking between data items and even
between sub-components of such items and, perhaps most importantly, enables
us to build note landscapes that are natively as non-linear as our thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let&rsquo;s see what happens over the next few years!</p>
<h2 id="appendix">Appendix</h2>
<h3 id="redacted-emacs-orgmode-capture-template">Redacted Emacs Orgmode capture template</h3>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; normally I construct current-journal-filename using mix of expand-file-name and concat</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#cb4b16">setq</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">current-journal-filename</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;/full/path/to/current/month-journal/&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; %i = selected text, %a org-store-link, %U created timestamp, %? place cursor here</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#cb4b16">setq</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">org-capture-templates</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      &#39;((<span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;t&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;Todo&#34;</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">entry</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">file+headline</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">current-journal-filename</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;Tasks&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;* TODO %?\n:LOGBOOK:\n- Created \&#34;TODO\&#34; %U\n:END:\n%i\n%a\n\n&#34;</span> 
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#cb4b16">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#2aa198;font-weight:bold">1</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        (<span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;j&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;Journal&#34;</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">entry</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">file+olp+datetree</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">current-journal-filename</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;* %? %T\n&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#cb4b16">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#2aa198;font-weight:bold">1</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        (<span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;p&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;Day planning&#34;</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">entry</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">file+olp+datetree</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">current-journal-filename</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;* Day planning %U
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Done list / thoughts / diary
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- %?
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Tasks for today [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Experiment: Articulate your directions / systems.
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Focus blocks
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Review [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] [[*Vitals][Month vitals]]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] Org sub-projects
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] Calendar
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] ...
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Habits / important [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] 7.5 hrs sleep last night
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] are you satisfied with number of pomodori? = 0 (v R)
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] did you write stuff down?
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] ...
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#cb4b16">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#2aa198;font-weight:bold">1</span>)))
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>
<h3 id="sunday-2020-01-12">Sunday 2020-01-12</h3>
<ul>
<li>Add <a href="#redacted-emacs-orgmode-capture-template">example of orgmode capture template
configuration</a> in appendix.</li>
<li>Add <a href="#drawing-with-apple-pencil-on-the-ipad-using-notability">section about iPad, Notability and Apple
Pencil</a>.</li>
<li>Add <a href="#signal-messaging-apps-brilliant-note-to-self-contact">section about Signal&rsquo;s Note to Self
contact</a>.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #177: Streakers.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 22:26:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</guid><description> A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly challenging post-Sunday-lunch run. This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to Sunday September 8, 2019.
On friendship, 25 years later. The birthday mentioned previously, along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends for more than 25 years now.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="lourensriver_at_vergelegen.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly
challenging post-Sunday-lunch run.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to
Sunday September 8, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="on-friendship-25-years-later">On friendship, 25 years later.</h2>
<p>The birthday <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/#celebration">mentioned
previously</a>,
along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two
small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends
for more than 25 years now.</p>
<p>In the bigger scheme of things, it&rsquo;s not <em>that</em> long, but what I would like to
mention here is how much such friendships can grow into the most honest of
human connections.</p>
<p>It is as if with the passing years, one is able to shed all of the unnecessary
baggage one tends to carry around as a beginner human.</p>
<p>What is left, is pure human warmth, unconditional support and, perhaps most
significantly, the effortless loss of self.</p>
<p><em>You</em> fade away, quite happily so, when one of your friends gets up in the
light to tell a story.</p>
<p>For a while at least, one&rsquo;s only representative in the conversation is one&rsquo;s
undivided recognition of and attention to the other.</p>
<p>This is certainly not reserved for 25+ year friendships, although this
pre-requisite seems to facilitate the process to the point of effortlessness.</p>
<h2 id="nested-headings-of-miscellany-nhom-nhom">Nested Headings of Miscellany (NHoM-NHoM).</h2>
<h3 id="org-pdf-tools-for-constructing-unifying-notes">org-pdf-tools for constructing unifying notes.</h3>
<p>Recently, I had to work through a stack of regulatory documents in PDF format.</p>
<p>The challenge was that the documents described different aspects of a single,
complicated procedure, but were severely lacking in overview-engendering
outlines or, even better, diagrams.</p>
<p>I did what I mostly do when faced with any research-related complexity: BUST
OUT SOME MORE OF THAT EMACS!</p>
<p>I found the Emacs package
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/">org-pdftools</a>, which I then
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/pull/4">PRd to work on my newer
Orgmode</a> (github makes
this sort of collaboration so easy!) and then integrated into my workflow.</p>
<p>org-pdftools enables one to link to specific annotated extracts, created
on-demand inside Emacs, from one&rsquo;s orgmode notes.</p>
<p>I used this to synthesise an overview document explaining the whole process,
linking to different parts of multiple PDFs explaining each aspect in more
detail.</p>
<p>Being able to jump effortlessly from a central overview document to specific
positions in reference PDFs is a huge boon to the research process.</p>
<h3 id="escalante">Escalante!</h3>
<p>One friend of work pointed me at an online source of affordable Altras.</p>
<p>I have secretly been pining for a pair of these shoes.</p>
<p>I was planning to use them for the longer runs when I can feel that my feet
need a little more support than my sandals are able to provide.</p>
<p>However, my feet have really gotten used to the wide open spaces of sandals, or
even better, of going barefoot.</p>
<p>Altras are zero-drop shoes, with <em>ginormous</em> toe boxes. Their motto is &ldquo;Embrace
the Space&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It seems like I have found some shoes with the right motto&hellip;</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://altrarunning.com/">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/altra-foot-space.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>Friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation had shoes that were semi-affordable, contrary to my
expectation.</p>
<p>When I pointed friend #2 from work at friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation, he pointed me
at an even <em>more</em> affordable source.</p>
<p>I <em>could</em> have continued with this iterative process, but I was unable to delay
this purchase any longer.</p>
<p>My new pair of Altra Escalante 1.0s arrived the next day.</p>
<p>(Yes, I know, 1.5 and 2.0 are available. However, <a href="https://runrepeat.com/altra-escalante">the stellar reviews of
1.0</a> have not changed, and did I say
&ldquo;affordable&rdquo;?!)</p>
<p>On Friday I broke them in, and on Sunday I made a slightly longer than normal
run (see in-progress photo above) to see how they did.</p>
<p>Anyways, in spite of the rest of me taking quite a beating on the second run, I
can happily report that the shoes did a marvellous job of balancing support
on the one hand and foot-freedom on the other.</p>
<h2 id="life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">Life optimisation tip #73: Streak more.</h2>
<p>As I was scrolling aimlessly through my facebook feed during my last session
before the Great Social Media Fast of September 2019 (see next section), I
quite ironically ran into a truly interesting post by a Swedish visualization
colleague (SVC).</p>
<p>In this post, he talked about his hobby and progress as a <em>run streaker</em>.</p>
<p>It turns out that there are runners with the <em>excellent</em> additional hobby of
<em>streaking</em>, which in <em>this</em> context refers to the act of running every single
day of their lives, and trying to do these daily runs for the longest
continuous streak possible.</p>
<p>The streakers know of each other, almost like Highlander, and are in a friendly
competition, very much unlike Highlander.</p>
<p>SVC now has a single uninterrupted streak, spanning multiple years, of daily
running behind him. He has friends in his city who have also been streaking for
multiple years now.</p>
<p>I find this fantastic, both specifically as a running and fitness feat, and
more generally as a brilliant human optimisation trick.</p>
<p>The longer your streak, the harder it&rsquo;s going to become to break that
streak. Add in the friendly competition element, and you have become an
accomplishment machine.</p>
<p>I see great potential here in the context of
<a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">compounding</a>
more consistently, and for longer.</p>
<p>What else could we streak folks?</p>
<h2 id="the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">The Great Social Media Fast of 2019.</h2>
<p>Twitter, Facebook, Reddit and friends&hellip; hot durnit.</p>
<p>Because I recently re-acquired the habit of checking reddit and twitter
multiple times during the day, I again examined the mechanisms driving this
undesirable behaviour.</p>
<p>The insidiousness, at least for me, lies in the fact that TwiFRaF (twitter,
facebook, reddit and friends) always has something looking like new information
on tap, where with tap, I mean firehose.</p>
<p>At any given moment during the day, when brain desires new input, or is just
tired and would like to take a break, TwiFRaF firehoses are ready to spew
something that appears to be new information but is only a very convincing
analogue.</p>
<p>Brain thinks it&rsquo;s getting what it wanted, plus a tiny and uninspired spurt of
discovery-dopamine here and there, which helps to keep up the illusion.</p>
<p>Any chance of real curiousity taking its natural course is cancelled.</p>
<p>Instead of pondering a question, and then going out on a slow and deliberate
search for information and later enlightenment, the firehose is opened, because
it&rsquo;s easier.</p>
<p>Furthermore, brain is unnecessarily exhausted trawling through a mix of mostly
generic rubbish with, granted, an interesting nugget every blue moon.</p>
<p>Hot durnit.</p>
<p>Fortunately, I like experiments, and Cold Turkey is my middle name!</p>
<p>So, on Saturday I decided to cut out TwiFRaF completely.</p>
<p>Initially I thought it would be an experiment until the end of September, but
now I&rsquo;m thinking that streaking might be an even better option.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;ll see.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #166: Morgan Bay</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/24/weekly-head-voices-166-morgan-bay/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2019 20:29:11 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/24/weekly-head-voices-166-morgan-bay/</guid><description> Amazing view from a rather precariously installed bench on the hills above Morgan Bay.
In this, the 166th edition of the WHV, I attempt to peer back at the two weeks from Sunday March 11 to Sunday March 24, 2019.
If you like, you may imagine that this looks like somewhat like the photo above, although the photo above was in fact just me peering out over the sea, while I generally just sit hunched over some form of keyboard when writing these posts.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/c_looking_out_for_you.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/c_looking_out_for_you-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Amazing view from a rather precariously installed bench on the hills above Morgan Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Amazing view from a rather precariously installed bench on the hills above Morgan Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In this, the 166th edition of the WHV, I attempt to peer back at the two weeks from Sunday March 11 to Sunday March 24, 2019.</p>
<p>If you like, you may imagine that this looks like somewhat like the photo above, although the photo above was in fact just me peering out over the sea, while I generally just sit hunched over some form of keyboard when writing these posts.</p>
<h2 id="blogosphere-housekeeping">Blogosphere housekeeping.</h2>
<p>In my eternal quest to avoid the new Gutenberg editor in WordPress (now at version 5.1.1), this and the previous post were typed up in Orgmode, and then copy-pasted from the Emacs-exported HTML.</p>
<h2 id="on-being-powerless">On being powerless.</h2>
<p>Years of corruption, in most cases made possible by the current ruling party, the ANC, have left our electricity-producing monoply, Eskom, in shambles.</p>
<p>Billions of rands disappeared into the pockets of dishonest types, instead of being invested into the maintenance and upgrades of our power generation and distribution network.</p>
<p>The result of all of this, is that the country currently has to deal with stage 4 load shedding, which means that electricity is completely shut off for 2.5 hours, three times a day.</p>
<p>This has to be done in order to prevent a total grid shutdown, which would result in a two to three week national electricity outage whilst the grid has to be started back up again.</p>
<p>You can read more about the details in <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/6-quick-fixes-that-can-save-south-africa-from-more-load-shedding-2019-3">this Business Insider article</a>.</p>
<p>Anyways, although there are many worse problems than this in the world today, these 7.5 powerless hours every day are a fairly visceral reminder of the utterly disappointing lack of integrity and leadership in our government.</p>
<p>At a more microscopic level, I am again spending far more time than usual on twitter, as this is where news about the electricity crisis plays out first.</p>
<p>Unfortunately Twitter, or <em>Road Rage of the Internet</em> as it has been called, does not contribute positively to one’s karma, which is the exact opposite of what is required here.</p>
<p>On the bright(ish) side, it does seem as if the whole drama is being adequately documented and analysed in the media.</p>
<p>Although there are fundamental issues at Eskom that need to be addressed, such as the fact that a state-owned entity has the monopoly over electricity production, I am optimistic that there are enough capable folks at Eskom, <em>with</em> spines, to band-aid the system back into operation.</p>
<p>I am less optimistic but still hopeful that this will result in deeper rectifications to both our power production strategy and, more acutely, the South African government.</p>
<h2 id="on-finding-oneself-in-the-most-entirely-wrong-place-for-any-sort-of-complaining">On finding oneself in the most entirely wrong place for any sort of complaining.</h2>
<p>GOU #1 left us for a week-long, zero-communication canoeing trip, along with about 60 of her fellow pupils, down the Orange River.</p>
<p>Although quite a challenge for our parental hearts, we did expect that this would be quite a valuable adventure for a 12 year old.</p>
<p>We were not wrong, but it sounds as if above-mentioned teenager experienced the adventure more like a week-long party with canoeing breaks thrown in for good measure.</p>
<p>While she was away, the rest of us spent the week on the East coast, in a beautiful coastal village called Morgan Bay.</p>
<p>To be more specific, we stayed at the Morgan Bay Hotel, a brilliant little family-run hotel at the core of the village.</p>
<p>The view from our room was not too shabby. In fact, it looked a little bit like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/view_from_mbh_room.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/view_from_mbh_room-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Morning runs, on barefoot, often looked like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/morgan_bay_morning_run.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/morgan_bay_morning_run-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>
</p>
<p>… and sometimes the World’s Worst Trail Runner (me), took on trails, in wet sandals, which were perhaps a tad too technical. See the following beaut for example:







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/morgan_bay_run_too_technical.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/morgan_bay_run_too_technical-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>
</p>
<h3 id="experiment-alcohol-zero-2-is-briefly-interrupted">Experiment Alcohol Zero #2 is briefly interrupted.</h3>
<p>Under immense beer peer pressure, and in the presence of locally brewed craft beer on tap, I finally broke my 2.5 month long alcohol fast with an Emerald Vale Amber Ale.</p>
<p>The beer was tasty, and the moment was suitably bittersweet.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/emerald_vale_amber_ale.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/emerald_vale_amber_ale-768x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="This is the pose one strikes when one is having mixed feelings about interrupting a great health streak with a potentially super tasty beverage."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>This is the pose one strikes when one is having mixed feelings about interrupting a great health streak with a potentially super tasty beverage.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I was happy to find after 10 weeks of zero alcohol that I could drink craft beer like a normal person, without any acclimatisation or noticeable ill effects.</p>
<p>However, thanks to consistently great sleep and subjectively more overall acuity, I will probably continue with zero (or very little) alcohol for a while longer.</p>
<p>If you’re interested in this (or anything else), pipe up in the comments!</p>
<h2 id="the-end">The End.</h2>
<p>I am happy that we ended up with family in Betty’s Bay this weekend.</p>
<p>The recent fires have stripped away so much vegetation that I was easily able to reach a spot I had never been able to navigate to before.</p>
<p>I made a panorama in which you can hopefully appreciate some of the devastation caused by the blaze:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/bettys_burnt_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/bettys_burnt_pano-1024x308.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Friends, I wish you a week filled with deep gratification!</p>
<p>As for me, I am planning to start my Monday with some project-related stress, but after that I will attempt to move smoothly into further evolving <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">The System</a>, with the specific goal of counteracting my current anger- and dopamine-driven twitter phase with deeper and longer inputs and thoughts.<figure class="wp-block-embed-youtube wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"></p>
<div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/brZ_WBEzw6E?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #130: TTAGGG.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/28/weekly-head-voices-130-ttaggg/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 20:52:04 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/28/weekly-head-voices-130-ttaggg/</guid><description> Lovely summer’s day. Not much rain.
Water On the water front (I see what I did there): Day Zero, that is the day on which the whole of Cape Town’s municipal water will be cut off, has been brought further forward to to April 12. Citizens will be able to fetch drinking water every day from 200 collection points. Judging by how quickly shelves of bottled water are currently disappearing from the shops and by panicky facebook posts, people are stocking up in advance.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/IMG_3107.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/IMG_3107-1024x576.png"
        
            alt="Lovely summer’s day. Not much rain."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Lovely summer’s day. Not much rain.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h1 id="water">Water</h1>
<p>On the water front (I see what I did there): Day Zero, that is the day on which the whole of Cape Town’s municipal water will be cut off, has been brought further forward to to April 12. Citizens will be able to fetch drinking water every day from 200 collection points. Judging by how quickly shelves of bottled water are currently disappearing from the shops and by panicky facebook posts, people are stocking up in advance.</p>
<h1 id="the-immortality-of-lobsters">The immortality of lobsters</h1>
<p>Continuing with our watery theme, this past week I learned the very surprising fact that lobsters are <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/dont-listen-to-the-buzz-lobsters-arent-actually-immortal-88450872/"><em>sort of</em> biologically immortal</a>. In short, lobsters produce more of the enzyme telomerase than humans and other animals, which rejuvenates their <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telomere">telomeres</a>, which means that their cells can in theory keep on dividing forever.</p>
<p>The telomeres are the genetic bits (feeling quite punny today; nucleotides TTAGGG in vertebrates, apparently) protecting the ends of your chromosomes. Every time cells divide, the child cells have slightly shortened telomeres. At some point, the telomere becomes too short, and that line of cells can’t divide anymore.</p>
<p>This is a large part of how most animals finally die: Our cells can only divide so many times, and then the telomere ends, and then someone switches on the bright lights, and then the whole party is over.</p>
<p>However, the enzyme telomerase is able to repair telomeres, thus extending the lifetime of the organism.</p>
<p>Lobsters naturally produce so much telomerase, that their cells can keep on dividing forever. In practice, lobsters apparently only grow in size, strength and reproductive ability as they age.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, their party also eventually ends. As they grow, they have to molt their suddenly too small exoskeleton. As they get bigger, this process takes more and more energy, until the day comes that they have grown so large (<a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/dont-listen-to-the-buzz-lobsters-arent-actually-immortal-88450872/">12 kg in one instance</a>) so that the attempted molting, due to disease, is a fatal process.</p>
<p>Intriguingly, <a href="https://www.ucsf.edu/news/2013/09/108886/lifestyle-changes-may-lengthen-telomeres-measure-cell-aging">a 2013 study</a> showed that lifestyle changes such as diet, exercise, stress reduction (including meditation) and social support, boosted telomerase activity and significantly increased telomere length in human subjects.</p>
<h1 id="your-brain-not-at-work">Your brain (not) at work</h1>
<p>On the recommendation of a colleague who is most versed in these things, I am currently reading the book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Your-Brain-Work-Strategies-Distraction-ebook/dp/B002Q1YE3K/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1517170057&amp;sr=8-1&amp;keywords=your+brain+at+work">“Your Brain at Work: Strategies for Overcoming Distraction, Regaining Focus, and Working Smarter All Day Long”</a> by David Rock.</p>
<p>While the author clearly has not yet read any books on Coming Up With Shorter Book Titles, he has put together a compelling piece on the extreme limitations of the human <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prefrontal_cortex">prefrontal cortex</a>. These are the bits that we use for important thoughts and for solving tricky technical puzzles.</p>
<p>I thought that I just naturally had the attention span of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Budgerigar">budgie</a> (which I continuously try my best to compensate for by the gnashing of teeth, will power, and <a href="/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">various other tricks</a>), but it turns out it’s a basic human limitation.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/Melopsittacus_undulatus_-Fort_Worth_Zoo-8a-4c.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/Melopsittacus_undulatus_-Fort_Worth_Zoo-8a-4c-1024x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="A pretty budgie which will probably distract you from the contents of this post. FOCUS!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>A pretty budgie which will probably distract you from the contents of this post. FOCUS!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>If all of the neuroscientists he has interviewed can be believed, we are severely limited both in terms of the number of thoughts / ideas we can handle at any one time, and, to me far more frighteningly, in terms of the total time we have available for this sort of complex work.</p>
<p>The prefrontal cortex is relatively-speaking quite inefficient, and gets exhausted really quickly. Remember the last time you spent the evening trying to figure out how to get all of your children to their various activities during the week, and how unexpectedly difficult that was? (if no children, please replace this example with something more familiar to you :) Your prefrontal cortex was probably already exhausted by 15:00 in the afternoon (if not earlier), and you were in effect beating a dead neural horse.</p>
<p>Sometimes you wake up the next morning, and you solve that exact same puzzle in 3 minutes, at which point you might have already exhausted your cognition quota, and might as well stay at home for the rest of the day.</p>
<p>Because the capacity and bandwidth of the prefrontal cortex can’t (yet?) be significantly improved, the book recommends that one carefully monitors oneself, taking breaks when necessary, single-tasking, and practising any often-occurring tasks until they become automatic, at which point the much more efficient <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basal_ganglia">basal ganglia</a> take over.</p>
<p>Apart from this, the prefrontal cortex works at its best when you are slightly stressed, but not too much, and when you are slightly happy (with novelty and dopamine), but not too much. Too stressed, and it freezes up like a deer in the headlights of a rapidly approaching car. Too happy, and it just hangs around enjoying the vibes, not really producing anything.</p>
<p>I still have to finish the book, but it has already motivated me to continue on my quest to automate and script as much of my life and work as possible. For example, for the daily goals list mentioned in <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">pro-tip #1 of WHV #126</a> I have a keyboard shortcut in Emacs which creates the relevant section in the correct part of my journal, correctly timestamped, and pre-filled with one or two habits I am trying to form, ready to accept the rest of the goals for the day. I used to think examples like this were perhaps going a little too far, but I now keep my eyes open for any task or activity that can be partially or fully automated. (Some even refer to <a href="http://irreal.org/blog/?p=6641">Emacs Orgmode</a> as their exocortex.)</p>
<p>On the topic of lists, the book mentions prioritisation as one of the more cognitively taxing activities we can engage in, so it makes even more sense to take care of it first thing in the morning, and to do this as efficiently as possible.</p>
<p>More broadly speaking, I think having <em>instant</em> access to documented and <em>executable</em> conventions for most of one’s tasks and projects would help greatly to free up the precious little prefrontal quality time we are allotted.</p>
<p>Even more broadly speaking, it seems we need to practise how to <em>listen</em> more carefully to our brain so that we are able to guide it through the treacherous waters of exhaustion, stress and happiness.</p>
<h1 id="the-part-where-i-wish-you-a-good-journey">The part where I wish you a good journey</h1>
<p>Thank you very much for reading this post. I hope you have a week filled with learning, challenges surmounted and a solid dose of contentment.</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #126: Fleur-de-lis.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 13:39:32 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/</guid><description> Betty’s Bay’s Crepuscular Rays. An apostrophe in time saves rhyme.
Happy new year everyone, and welcome to the first Weekly (truly?! will this be the year?) Head Voices of 2018! I ended 2017 with a longish (by my standards) run in the morning, followed by a laid-back mini-party and finally by struggling really hard to stay awake until midnight. In contrast, returning to the office on January 2 was a pretty good way to ease gradually into work in 2018.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/bettys_crepuscular_rays-2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/bettys_crepuscular_rays-2-1024x462.jpg"
        
            alt="Betty’s Bay’s Crepuscular Rays. An apostrophe in time saves rhyme."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Betty’s Bay’s Crepuscular Rays. An apostrophe in time saves rhyme.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<ul>
<li>Happy new year everyone, and welcome to the first <em>Weekly</em> (truly?! will this be the year?) Head Voices of 2018!</li>
<li>I ended 2017 with a longish (by my standards) run in the morning, followed by a laid-back mini-party and finally by struggling really hard to stay awake until midnight.</li>
<li>In contrast, returning to the office on January 2 was a pretty good way to ease gradually into work in 2018. Many colleagues were still on vacation, so the week felt a bit like work with training wheels.</li>
<li>Pro-tip #1 for the new year: In the last few weeks of 2017 I started (again…) explicitly making quiet time at the start of the day to think about what I want to take care of. These take the form of a small number of <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Org mode</a> “<code>- [ ] Do this thing</code>” checklist items that are usually related to but separate from my main tasks. I find it amazing to which extent these few minutes are able to shape my day. (In my org mode monthly journal, I also usually start by listing out manually the tasks I want to complete during that month, as well as the ideas / thoughts / principles I want to keep in my sights.)</li>
<li>Pro-tip #2 for the new year: After years of resisting these types of software tools due to my belief that I should simply apply more grit and will power to squeeze out more focus hours, I finally broke down and purchased the <a href="https://heyfocus.com/">macOS app called Focus</a>. You click its pretty icon, and then your computer goes into focus mode: The Mail application and a bunch of other non-focus-related apps all get killed, and a bunch of websites (reddit, youtube, work chat, etc) are blocked for a user-configurable block of time. I rationalised this purchase with the following reasoning: <em>It usually takes a single moment of weakness for a distraction to terminate a valuable block of focus. It takes a single moment of strength for this tool to start a valuable block of focus.</em></li>
<li>Although I’m having fun, I really don’t think I’m supposed to use bullets like this.</li>
<li>Thank you very much for spending time here with me. I wish you a week of value and focus, followed by a visit to the next WHV!

  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/huguenot_monument_franschhoek.jpg">
      <img
          
              
              src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/huguenot_monument_franschhoek-1024x653.jpg"
          
              alt="The Huguenot Monument in Franschhoek, where we found ourselves an hour or two ago. Immediacy FTW."/> </a><figcaption>
              <p>The Huguenot Monument in Franschhoek, where we found ourselves an hour or two ago. Immediacy FTW.</p>
          </figcaption>
  </figure>
</li>
</ul>
<p>P.S. This post was finished during a 30 minute FocusApp block. Background music: <a href="https://www.residentadvisor.net/reviews/5988">Balance 014</a> by Joris Voorn, one of my favourite music creations ever.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #123: A semblance of a cadence.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/06/28/weekly-head-voices-123-a-semblance-of-a-cadence/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 19:29:59 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/06/28/weekly-head-voices-123-a-semblance-of-a-cadence/</guid><description> Yes, we ended up in the mountains again.
In the period from Monday June 12 to Sunday June 25 we were mostly trying to get through the winter, fighting off a virus or three (the kind that invades biological organisms you nerd) and generally nerding out.
One more of my org2blog pull requests was merged in: You can now configure the thumbnail sizes your blog will automatically show of your uploaded images.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/IMG_0321-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/IMG_0321-PANO-1024x598.jpg"
        
            alt="Yes, we ended up in the mountains again."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Yes, we ended up in the mountains again.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In the period from Monday June 12 to Sunday June 25 we were mostly trying to get through the winter, fighting off a virus or three (the kind that invades biological organisms you nerd) and generally nerding out.</p>
<p>One more of my <a href="https://github.com/org2blog/org2blog/pull/226">org2blog pull requests</a> was merged in: You can now configure the thumbnail sizes your blog will automatically show of your uploaded images. Getting my own itch scratches merged merged into open source projects never fails to makes me happy, even although in this case there can’t be more than 5 other people who will ever use this particular functionality.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<h1 id="aspnet-core-surprise">ASP.NET Core SURPRISE!</h1>
<p>For a work project I was <em>encouraged</em> to explore Microsoft’s brand new <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/aspnet/core/">ASP.NET Core</a>. While on the one hand I remain wary of Microsoft (IE6 anyone?), I am an absolute sucker for new technology on the other.</p>
<p>You may colour me impressed.</p>
<p>If I had to describe it in one sentence, I would have to describe ASP.NET Core as Django done in C#. You can develop and deploy this on Windows, Mac or Linux. You model and query your data using Entity Framework Core and LINQ for example, or Dapper if you prefer performance and don’t mind the SQL (I don’t), or both. You write controller classes and view templates using the Razor templating language.</p>
<p>C# 7.0 looks like it could be a high development velocity language. It has modern features such as lambdas with what looks like real closures (unlike C++ variable capturing), as well as the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/language-reference/operators/null-conditional-operator">null coalescing operator (??)</a> and the <a href="http://geekswithblogs.net/BlackRabbitCoder/archive/2015/06/05/c.net-little-wonders-null-conditional-operator-in-c-6.aspx">null conditional operator (?.)</a>, the latter of which looks superbly useful. Between Visual Studio on Windows and the Mac, or the new Intellij Rider IDE (all platforms) or Visual Studio Code (all platforms), the tooling is top notch.</p>
<p>Time will have to tell how it compares to Python with respect to development velocity, a competition that Python traditionally fares extremely well at.</p>
<p>Where ASP.NET Core wins hands down is in the memory usage department: By default you deploy using the Kestrel web server, which runs your C# code using <em>multiple</em> libuv (yeah, of lightning fast node.js event loop fame) event loops, all in threads.</p>
<p>With Django I usually deploy as many processes as I can behind uwsgi, itself behind nginx. The problem is that with Python’s garbage collector, these processes end up sharing very little memory, and so one has to take into account memory limits as well as CPU count on servers when considering concurrency.</p>
<p>The long and the short of this is that one will probably be able to process many more requests in parallel with ASP.NET Core than with Django. With uwsgi and Django I have experimented with gevent in uwsgi and monkey patching, but this does not work as well as it does in ASP.NET Core, which has been designed with this concurrency model in mind from the get go. My first memory usage and performance experiments have shown compelling results.</p>
<p>Hopefully more later!</p>
<h1 id="a-cadence-of-accountability">A cadence of accountability</h1>
<p>Lately my <a href="/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">Deep Work habits</a> have taken a bit of a hit. At first I could not understand how to address this, until I remembered mention of a <em>cadence of accountability</em> in <a href="http://calnewport.com/books/deep-work/">The Book</a><em>.</em></p>
<p>Taking a quick look at <a href="/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">that post</a>, I understood what I had forgotten to integrate with my habits. Besides just doing the deep work, it’s important to “keep a compelling scoreboard” and to “create a cadence of accountability”.</p>
<p>Although I was tracking my deep work time using the <a href="http://orgmode.org/manual/Clocking-commands.html">orgmode clocking commands</a> (when I start “deep working” on anything, I make an orgmode heading for it in my journal and clock in; when I’m done I clock out; orgmode remembers all durations) I was not regularly reviewing my performance.</p>
<p>With orgmode’s <code>org-clock-report</code> command (<code>C-c C-x C-r</code>), I can easily create or update a little table, embedded in my monthly journal orgfile, with all of my deep work clocked time tallied by day. This “compelling scoreboard” gives me instant insight into my weekly and monthly performance, and gives me either a mental kick in the behind or pat on the shoulder, depending on how many deep work hours I’ve been able to squeeze in that day and the days before it.</p>
<p>The moment I started doing this at regular intervals, “creating a cadence of accountability” in other words, I was able to swat distractions out of the way and get my zone back.</p>
<p>This is an interesting similarity with <a href="/tag/gtd/">GTD</a> (which I don’t do so much anymore because focus is far more important to me than taking care of sometimes arbitrary and fragmentary tasks) in that GTD has the <a href="https://zenhabits.net/weekly-review-key-to-gtd-and-achieving/">regular review</a> as a core principle.</p>
<p>Us humans being so dependent on habits to make real progress in life leads me to the conclusion that this is a clever trick to acquire behaviour that is not habitual: Work on an auxiliary behaviour that is habitual, e.g. the regular review, that encourages / reinforces behaviour that is perhaps not habitual, e.g. taking care of randomly scheduled heterogeneous tasks (GTD) or fitting in randomly scheduled focus periods (Deep Work of the journalistic variant).</p>
<p>As an aside, cadence in this context is just a really elegant synonym for habit. I suggest we use it more, especially at cocktail parties.</p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>