<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Kindness on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/kindness/</link><description>Recent content in Kindness on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 19:47:51 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/kindness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #242: Multiplicity of me</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 20:51:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</guid><description>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.
If you like backyard philosophy, you&amp;rsquo;re in the right place.
Even if you only like bullet lists, you&amp;rsquo;re going to be ok.
Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from
Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.</p>
<p>If you like backyard philosophy, you&rsquo;re in the right place.</p>
<p>Even if you only like bullet lists, you&rsquo;re going to be ok.</p>










<figure><a href="afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_41bd9f5429550d06.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_cd29c721e76c2270.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_968c3008cb01b577.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_454f8c3e3a4ec58f.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_cd29c721e76c2270.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo by friend WvdL.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="learning-at-the-burning">Learning at the Burning</h2>
<p>There&rsquo;s an unwritten rule that you should not make any life decisions for at
least three weeks after the (Afrika)Burn.</p>
<p>Apparently people have, inspired by the sometimes weird experiences of the
event, made some major but unfortunately quite regrettable decisions in its
afterglow.</p>
<p>Anyways, I did not come back with anything like that.</p>
<p>Without sounding (too much) like Zaphod eating the fairy cake powering the
Total Perspective Vortex and walking away pretty much unscathed, through the
week&rsquo;s ups (mostly) and downs I learned a bunch, and I did come back with some
internal changes, but they were at their most extreme a strong reminder (kick
in the butt might even be appropriate) of a partially buried perspective or
two.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it is now exactly three weeks after the thing, and although that
dusty afterglow has definitely waned, it feels like I&rsquo;ve just merged back into
reality without any major incidents, just a slight tweak (or gentle kick in the
butt) here and there, for the better.</p>
<p>(Because inquiring minds might want to know, yes, we again brought the
BURNIVERSITY. We&rsquo;re probably one of the smallest theme camps, but we were
intense, and it feels like our interactions were too.)</p>
<p>Anyways, here are some completely random words, some of them loosely based (or
not at all, or something in between) on a recent conversation with friend PK,
and some of them from friend DW:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA</a> is a good framework for your well-being, and that of your loved ones:
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion</li>
<li>Engagement</li>
<li>Relationships</li>
<li>Meaning</li>
<li>Accomplishment</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>That thing you&rsquo;re stressing about is most probably not worth such a high
personal cost, and health-risk.</li>
<li>Just do the work.</li>
<li><a href="https://typesense.org/blog/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-just-showing-up-everyday/">Just showing up every day is a super power</a>. Pick your thing(s), show up to
them every single day, profit.</li>
<li>Chopping onions is the physical manifestation of your love for the people for
whom you are cooking. Give it (chopping onions, making food, loving) your
<em>whole</em> attention, and see what happens. Thank you DW, for this wisdom, and
for the food.
<ul>
<li>(Dear reader, between you and me, man that guy was burning so bright&hellip;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Practice will boost your powers of attention. This will deeply improve you,
and how you interact with others.</li>
<li>Kindness is still the most important super power.</li>
<li>Check up on yourself every day, about all of these completely random words.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="multiplicity-of-you">Multiplicity of you</h2>
<p><a href="/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/#homo-deus">In 2018, I talked about <em>Homo Deus</em></a>, a book by Yuval Harari in which he
discusses several thought-provoking ideas, one of which I highlighted then and
would like to discuss again now:</p>
<p>Your experience of being a single identity, a single <em>I</em>, is most probably an
illusion, as your brain most probably houses more &ldquo;me&quot;s than you would think.</p>
<p>Research by the Nobel prize-winner Daniel Kahneman and his various
collaborators showed that we house at the very least two major selves, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow#Two_selves">namely
the remembering / narrating self and the experiencing self</a>.</p>
<p>The experiencing self is the one who actually does the living and the
<em>experiencing</em> of each moment, while the narrating self is the one who
continuously stitches together your whole story, often bending the truth to fit
its (your) opinions of yourself and those around you.</p>
<p>The narrating self is the one who dominates, for better or for worse.</p>
<p>Kahnemann himself pointed out the irony of this the best:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Odd as it may seem, I am my remembering self, and the experiencing self, who
does my living, is like a stranger to me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(You might have heard of <a href="https://positivepsychology.com/what-is-peak-end-theory/">Peak-End Theory</a>, or the phenomenon that humans tend to
judge an experience based largley on the single peak moment, and on how they
felt at the end. You can thank your remembering self for this, and you can
imagine how this could really complicate your decision making.)</p>
<p>Harari discusses Kahneman&rsquo;s selves, but continues into more research with
people who for various reasons have separated brain hemispheres.</p>
<p>When you show one brain hemisphere one version of reality, and the other
another, it is as if there are multiple narrating selves in the same person who
come up with stories that they are convinced are the truth, although in this
case these stories conflict diametrically with other thanks to the design of
the experiment.</p>
<p>From this and other data, Harari concludes that humans generally house multiple
identities.</p>
<p>What I want to to get at, is that it helps to remember (always) that &ldquo;you&rdquo; are
in fact a collection of sometimes competing &ldquo;you&quot;s.</p>
<p>As if that were not challenging enough, your narrating self takes
responsibility for all of these feelings, and tries to weave it all into a
consistent story, although that is often extremely difficult or even
impossible.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.samharris.org/blog/the-illusion-of-the-self2">an 2012 interview with Sam Harris</a>, Bruce Hood had the following to say about
this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>By rejecting the notion of a core self and considering how we are a multitude
of competing urges and impulses, I think it is easier to understand why we
suddenly go off the rails. It explains why we act, often unconsciously, in a
way that is inconsistent with our self image &ndash; or the image of our self as we
believe others see us.</p>
<p>That said, the self illusion is probably an inescapable experience we need for
interacting with others and the world, and indeed we cannot readily abandon or
ignore its influence, but we should be skeptical that each of us is the
coherent, integrated entity we assume we are.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because this thought has become much more prominent for me in quite a positive
way, I would like to take it even further, by reminding you to practise
reminding yourself of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Although your perception is generally tied to your narrating self (the one
that&rsquo;s going to remember this blog post), the complete &ldquo;you&rdquo; in fact
constitutes the whole playing field, the consciousness and its physical
medium, in which <em>all</em> of these selves live and move around. In the words of
Harris, &ldquo;you can drop back into that&rdquo; and just <em>be</em> the consciousness, <em>be</em> that
which contains it all.</li>
<li>While your own selves truly live in this conciousness, high definition
versions of your surroundings and everyone you interact with are also
running in this same (your) neural network.
<ul>
<li>This means that you have a surprising amount of control of how you
experience life.</li>
<li>When you hear a dog barking, this is really nothing more than clusters of
neurons firing in your brain, but you visualize the dog <em>over there</em>. When
you feel the wind blowing over your skin, there&rsquo;s just another set of
neurons firing not far away from the barking dog. It&rsquo;s all inside your
head, and the borders between &ldquo;inside&rdquo; and &ldquo;outside&rdquo; are far more blurry
than you might think.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>All of your selves are <em>you</em>. Treat them like you would a group of your closest
friends. You can hold them up to the group&rsquo;s standards, but you have to
forgive, and you have to be kind.</li>
</ul>
<p>Folks, I wish you all (and all the yous), and all of your people, peace and
love.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2016 to 2017 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 11:05:01 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/</guid><description>Following the rich tradition over here of year transition posts, having just rounded off a brilliant outdoorsy take-your-mind-off-of-everything vacation with friends, and also inspired by wogan.blog’s nicely personal 2016 review post, I decided that a farewell-2016 how-you-doin’-2017 post was in order.
By the way, by rich tradition I mean that I wrote the grand total of one (1) similarly titled post previously, as the year ticked from 2009 to 2010, and at least one other, disguised as a weekly head voices, as we entered 2012. That last one is worth another read, early 2012 cpbotha had some really good tips. There might be more such posts, this blog has been around for more than 15 years and much of what I’ve written is not available from my short-term memory, which is nice.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Following the rich tradition over here of year transition posts, having just rounded off a brilliant outdoorsy take-your-mind-off-of-everything vacation with friends, and also inspired by <a href="https://wogan.blog/2017/01/01/2016-in-review/">wogan.blog’s nicely personal 2016 review post</a>, I decided that a farewell-2016 how-you-doin’-2017 post was in order.</p>
<p>By the way, by <em>rich tradition</em> I mean that I wrote the grand total of one (1) similarly titled post previously, <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">as the year ticked from 2009 to 2010</a>, and at least one other, disguised as a weekly head voices, <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">as we entered 2012</a>. <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">That last one</a> is worth another read, early 2012 cpbotha had some really good tips. There might be more such posts, <a href="/about/history/">this blog has been around for more than 15 years</a> and much of what I’ve written is not available from my short-term memory, which is nice.</p>
<p><em><strong>Warning:</strong> This post is long (1800 words+), rambly and sometimes even a bit mushy. I hope you enjoy it!</em></p>
<h1 id="2016-the-review">2016: The Review</h1>
<h2 id="the-bad-with-a-hopefully-slightlypositive-outlook-at-the-end">The bad, with a hopefully slightly positive outlook at the end</h2>
<p>Let’s get the bad stuff out of the way as soon as we can…</p>
<p>For me the biggest disappointments of 2016 were the double-whammy of the Brexit followed by the Trumpocalypse.</p>
<p>I really did not expect either of these events to go the way they did.</p>
<p>This is probably because I was, ever the optimist, over-estimating the level of human development of British and US voters.</p>
<p>The exclusionist, nationalist, xenophobic and in many cases even white supremacist thinking associated with Trump’s support in the US and the Leave vote in the UK are truly abhorrent.</p>
<p>I understand that there were many other factors at play. However, these voters were either throwing out the baby with the bath water, or, much much  worse, agreeing with the abhorrent sentiments mentioned above. Especially this second possibility depressed me greatly after the US election.</p>
<p>After such setbacks, one needs to look for solutions.</p>
<p>After Brexit, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/06/brexit-vote-statistics-united-kingdom-european-union/488780/">analysis showed that education level was the strongest indicator of a vote for leave or remain</a>. Higher education was strongly associated with remain, whilst the opposite was the case for leave.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Screen-Shot-2017-01-05-at-12.28.37-PM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Screen-Shot-2017-01-05-at-12.28.37-PM-709x1024.png"
        
            alt="Leave / remain voter analysis by The Atlantic. Click to go to article &#43; interactive version of this graphic."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Leave / remain voter analysis by The Atlantic. Click to go to article + interactive version of this graphic.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>For Trump voters, you probably guessed it, it was more or less the same idea. <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/education-not-income-predicted-who-would-vote-for-trump/">Less educated citizens voted for Trump, more educated citizens for Clinton</a>.</p>
<p>This is yet another strong indication that we should really be pouring every resource we have into the education of our people. (yes, correlation and causation, I know. hence the terms “strong indication”. discuss in the comments if you like.)</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrence_M._Krauss">Lawrence M. Krauss</a>, superstar theoretical physicist and author of the book A Universe from Nothing, <a href="https://twitter.com/LKrauss1/status/814947974203641857">recently tweeted</a> this <a href="http://www.quotationspage.com/quote/26977.html">1920 quote by H.G. Wells</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Human history has become, more and more, a race between education and catastrophe.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The way things are going now, that thought, and movements like #feesmustfall, are more important than ever. There can be absolutely no excuse for neglecting the highest quality and <strong>accessible</strong> education (basic up to tertiary) of future generations of humans whom we expect to further our civilization.</p>
<h2 id="therunning-and-the-mindful">The running and the mindful</h2>
<p>In 2016, I ran 440km.</p>
<p>There are a great deal of people who have run much more than that, but those are <em>my</em> 440 kilometers and somehow they brought me a great deal of deep satisfaction.</p>
<p>During the year, my per-run distance and speed have gradually increased.</p>
<p>Besides fitness gradually increasing, I discovered experimentally that shorter, quicker steps get me further and a higher pace. It took a biomechanical friend to explain to me that this was about muscles operating within the more efficient middle of their full extension/contraction ranges. I could probably just have read this somewhere, but doing it the hard way and then having a friend explain it on top of Table Mountain definitely added something to the experience.</p>
<p>For the last 200 kilometres or so, I have listened to the exact same album: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skin_(Flume_album)">Skin by Flume</a>. Every single run, I start that exact same album with the exact same sequence of tracks. As I learned from <a href="https://www.swimgeek.com/blog/2016/11/16/quick-update-445/">the SwimGeek’s blog</a>, <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/2113776/question-everything-tim-ferriss-fitness"><em>finding your soundtrack and putting it on repeat</em> whilst exercising is apparently a thing</a>.</p>
<p>With the surroundings over here being what they are, it does not take much to slip into a state of mindfulness.</p>
<p>No doing, no planning; just absorbing all of the surroundings, physical and mental, the music, and feeling how the meat-based machine that houses me propels us forward.</p>
<p>On the topic of mindfulness, for the last few months I added a repeat event to my todoist, helping me to spend five minutes every morning before work doing the breathing exercise. More recently I do this without any voice track, but previously Prof. Mark Williams at one point would say (original quote is due to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon_Kabat-Zinn">Jon Kabat-Zinn, PhD</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Each breath a new beginning; each out-breath a letting go.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There’s a whole lot in there. I have spent quite some time with it and I am far from done.</p>
<h3 id="the-blog">The blog</h3>
<p>The first rule of blogging: You don’t blog about blogging.</p>
<p>However, I hope you don’t mind me breaking that rule to mention that in 2016, this blog was viewed 133 thousand times. I already get happy when one other person reads a post. You can imagine how happy it makes me to know that there are even slightly more people who have come here to consume some of the words I have written, and even some who have taken the time to leave behind comments!</p>
<p>The lion’s share of those views were due to focused posts that got picked up by some of the more popular nerd sites. I have to admit that I derived the most enjoyment from the more personal posts that were only read by friends.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, this has to be my most satisfying hobby. Thank you for the crucial role that you who read play in it!</p>
<h3 id="the-new-life">The new life</h3>
<p>In early(ish) 2016, our third daughter, affectionately known as Genetic Offspring Unit #3 (GOU#3 for short) around these parts, <a href="/2016/05/05/weekly-head-voices-106-ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/">was born</a>.</p>
<p>This wonderful little cellular mega-cluster is currently making noises that have the primary purpose of being immensely cute, but are also slowly starting to make sense. Her ambulation capabilities have increased immensely, and she is on the verge of standing up by herself and so we will probably have to re-arrange our interior. Again.</p>
<p>Long ago, <a href="/2011/08/28/the-lowlands-tooth-fairy-37-weekly-head-voices-55/">I wrote here about my unexpected new role as someone else’s Tooth Fairy</a>. In the meantime, working as a part-time tooth fairy and a full-time papa to three little humans has turned out to be a more fulfilling career than I ever could have imagined.</p>
<h1 id="2017-not-much-planned-yet-you">2017: Not much planned yet, you?</h1>
<p>I prefer making resolutions in secret, then carrying them out or not, and only then reporting on them. However, that would mean that I would have to wrap up this post right now, and for that I’m not quite ready yet.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-alcohol-zero">Experiment Alcohol Zero</h2>
<p>One resolution that I am already executing on, is performing an interesting little experiment. After reading about <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/the-running-blog/2014/apr/23/how-does-alcohol-affect-athletic-performance">the effects of alcohol on one’s (running) performance and general energy levels</a>, I have decided to go for 30 days without a drop of alcohol to try and get a subjective idea of its potential impact.</p>
<p>Those of you who have spent more than 8 seconds in my or my blog’s vicinity know that I absolutely adore craft <a href="/tag/beer/">beer</a> (this includes local, but also special beers of the Belgian type) and local wines, both of which are regularly consumed by me and “business partners” during “business lunches” in the not-unattractive local surroundings.</p>
<p>This decision was not taken lightly.</p>
<p>It is mid-morning of day 2 of Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) as I write this. With the air full of smoke due to <a href="/2017/01/04/massive-fires-around-here-thanks-to-firefighters-my-neighbourhood-escaped/">local vegetation fires</a>, I have not been able to go running yet, but I am imagining that my energy lasted later last night, and I got up easier this morning. I have 29 more days to investigate.</p>
<h2 id="reminders-for-a-hopefully-better-life">Reminders for a hopefully better life</h2>
<p>Every day, I remind myself <a href="/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/">to be the kindest I can possibly be to everyone I come into contact with</a>. We have infinite amounts of kindness to spread.</p>
<p>I also remind myself to <a href="/2014/11/03/weekly-head-voices-84-on-being-grateful/">be grateful</a>. It takes continuous practice to identify the many things one can be grateful for every day, but it is definitely worth it.</p>
<p>I often remind GOU#1 (#2 and #3 are not old enough yet for this lesson) that, besides the guidelines above, we have to keep on working on two more related characteristics: being useful, and being likable.</p>
<p>Being useful means continuously developing and refining skills that enable one to contribute value to one’s surroundings. Being likable means understanding and appreciating how we humans stick together. Kindness, see above, is an important component of this.</p>
<p>In 2017, I would like to write more (on this blog probably), and read more.</p>
<h1 id="rapidly-morphing-goalpostsjumping-randomly-through-even-more-randomly-pulsating-hyperspace-with-a-slightly-positive-outlook-at-the-end">Rapidly morphing goalposts jumping randomly through even more randomly pulsating hyperspace, with a slightly positive outlook at the end</h1>
<p>Yes folks, this is going to be my parting thought.</p>
<p>When I was much younger, I used to believe that one’s life could be “cracked”. That is, if you searched, and you worked really hard at understanding yourself, your people and your surroundings, you could come up with some kind of answer with which you would be able to attain contentment.</p>
<p>In the meantime I’ve come to the realisation that that Much Younger Me, although quite dashing, was of course utterly wrong.</p>
<p>Life is utterly dynamic. You Now are a different person from You Last Year. The same goes for people around you, and the same goes for everything around you.</p>
<p>The goal posts are not just moving all the time, they are an illusion flashing in and out of an hallucinogenic and especially dynamic perception.</p>
<p>One trick to help one deal with this, is to stop thinking about goals in the first place, and instead <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">consider the directions of your movement</a>.</p>
<p>Also keep in mind that <a href="/2016/02/02/weekly-head-voices-103-chips/">there are no answers, only choices</a>. You work to make the best ones you can with the means at your disposal at that moment.</p>
<p>Importantly, in this restless environment, some peace can be found by realising that a large part of the restlessness originates from within you. Fortunately, you have slightly more say in you than you have in your surroundings.</p>
<p>What one can do then, is nicely summarised by Prof. Mark Williams in the audio accompanying <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mindfulness-Eight-Week-Finding-Peace-Frantic/dp/1609618955">his mindfulness book</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The deep stillness we seek does not arise because the world is still or the mind is quiet. Stillness is nourished when we allow things to be just as they are for now, in this moment, moment by moment and breath by breath.</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="the-end-for-now">The End (for now)</h1>
<p>Alright friends, that was it from me, for now. I hope that you have the best 2017 possible. I hope especially that your kindness and that of those around you flows deeply and freely.</p>
<p>As a parting gift, here is the high-resolution panoroma I made from the top of Table Mountain, after hiking up Platteklip Gorge with friends:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama-1024x325.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net. Click for high-res."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net. Click for high-res.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #81: Middle-aged zen.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 20:21:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/</guid><description>(Warning: This post has an extremely high backyard philosophy content. Will probably greatly offend any real philosophers, and a bunch of other people I probably have not even thought about.)
I recently became middle-aged. As part of the thank you I wrote for the many kind words people posted to my facebook wall, I made a short summary of the things I had learned over the past N years. I hope you don’t mind that I post them here as well:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(Warning: This post has an extremely high backyard philosophy content. Will probably greatly offend any real philosophers, and a bunch of other people I probably have not even thought about.)</em></p>
<p>I recently became middle-aged. As part of the thank you I wrote for the many kind words people posted to my facebook wall, I made a short summary of the things I had learned over the past N years. I hope you don’t mind that I post them here as well:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>… here’s what I’ve picked up over the past decades (only two things, I’m a slow learner):</p>
<ol>
<li>Relationships – the most important thing (and maybe even the only thing) in the world.</li>
<li>Kindness – it really looks like we have unlimited quantities of this to give, but somehow there’s not as much of it going around as there could be. Let’s fix this!</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Since that note (I’ve skipped a number of weekly posts here as you might have noticed; really really busy) I have also been thinking about the relationship between one’s happiness, one’s circumstances, and the plasticity of one’s self.</p>
<p>I’ll start this little story with me during a coffee-induced zen moment:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/wpid-cpbotha_at_coffee_roasting_co.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/wpid-cpbotha_at_coffee_roasting_co.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Zen is a real thing that you can read about on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen">wikipedia</a>, in a billion blogs and also in <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://youtu.be/MOXQo7nURs0">BookBooks</a>. I don’t think that I’m deviating <strong>too</strong> far from the real deal when I use zen to describe any form of personal enlightenment, or that elevated state of self I should be striving for every moment of every day, but mostly forget to do because I get caught up in life as, ironically, I am not yet zen enough.</p>
<p>Sometimes, I find myself in a perfect little moment of warmth and humanity with close friends or family (and/or with a perfect coffee) and I am somehow able to observe and appreciate the moment in real-time from a spot somewhere outside of the conversation, for example while I’m walking to school with my daughter on a spring morning and realise that life in these simple moments is even greater than I thought. Sometimes I am briefly able to distance myself from some perceived life complexity, a distance from which everything actually looks pretty fine and then turns out to be exactly that. Was it that way to start with, did it change, or did I change?</p>
<p>I think being able to take a few (or a thousand) steps back in order to better see yourself and your situation is related to one of the few fundamental zen principles: Enlightenment through growing self-knowledge. I also somehow had in my mind that there was some connection between zen and the principle of mind like water, or <em>mizo no kokoro</em> if you prefer its prettier ring. In searching for this link, I stumbled onto <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/quotes/163198-you-must-be-shapeless-formless-like-water-when-you-pour">this Bruce Lee quote</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You must be shapeless, formless, like water. When you pour water in a cup, it becomes the cup. When you pour water in a bottle, it becomes the bottle. When you pour water in a teapot, it becomes the teapot. Water can drip and it can crash. Become like water my friend.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>During those occasional and coincidental flashes of increased perception I mentioned above the quote, when I was both in the experience and outside, at a good distance, I was able to look inwards and see how I could best change <em>me</em> to suit the situation better. The better I suit the situation, the more it agrees with me. Harmony.</p>
<p>Let me restate that: Most often I am not able to change my environment. However, I am apparently able to train my ability to change <em>me</em>, which in many cases can lead to the same desired harmonious outcome.</p>
<p>So, sort of in addition to the things I’ve learned over the past years, here are the things I strive to have cultivated when I grow up:</p>
<ul>
<li>Mindfulness, of me, the human beings I am fortunate to be surrounded with and all of the interactions between us. This includes the ability to take a thousand steps back, and to see clearly.</li>
<li>A mind like water, not to do kung fu fighting, but to be able to change and flow continuously to contribute more to harmony and happiness.</li>
</ul>
<p>Because I’m not sure how else to do this, I’m ending this story with a photo of a beer that I took during a really sunny zen moment:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-radison_jack_black.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-radison_jack_black.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Have a beautiful and harmonious week fellow humans!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>