<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Medical Visualization on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/medical-visualization/</link><description>Recent content in Medical Visualization on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2013 12:28:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/medical-visualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The new MedVis Book is out!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2013/12/24/the-new-medvis-book-is-out/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2013 12:28:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2013/12/24/the-new-medvis-book-is-out/</guid><description>For the past 2.5 years, I have been helping my friend Prof. Bernhard Preim to write the new Medical Visualization textbook. A crazy number of hours of studying scientific literature (a quick count in the bbl file yields 1880 cited references!!), trying to fit everything into a coherent conceptual framework and then trying to write all of it down as a more or less readable story has finally led to more than 1000 pages of Medical Visualization reading pleasure.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>For the past 2.5 years, I have been helping my friend <a href="http://isgwww.cs.uni-magdeburg.de/~bernhard/" title="bernhard's website">Prof. Bernhard Preim</a> to write the new Medical Visualization textbook. A crazy number of hours of studying scientific literature (a quick count in the bbl file yields 1880 cited references!!), trying to fit everything into a coherent conceptual framework and then trying to write all of it down as a more or less readable story has finally led to more than 1000 pages of Medical Visualization reading pleasure.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>
<p><a href="http://medvisbook.com/"><img alt="" class="alignnone" height="922" src="http://medvisbook.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/cover_full_20130729.jpg" width="1650"/></a></p>
<p>The title has been changed to <em>Visual Computing for Medicine</em> to reflect the significant rework, and also the broader treatment of the field. The book itself is 836 pages with hundreds of colour figures. Five chapters (190+ pages) are <a href="http://medvisbook.com/online-chapters/" title="medvisbook online chapters">available exclusively online</a>, free to download.</p>
<p>Go to <a href="http://medvisbook.com/" title="medvisbook website">the book website</a> (run by us) to read more <a href="http://medvisbook.com/about/" title="about the book">about the contents</a> of the book, and to find out <a href="http://medvisbook.com/where-to-buy/" title="where to buy">where you can get your very own copy</a>!</p>
<p>P.S. It was a huge pleasure working on the book together with Bernhard. (We’ve been collaborating quite intensively since the end of 2007 somewhere, when we started setting up the <a href="http://www.vcbm.org/" title="VCBM website">Eurographics Workshops on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine</a>, which have since then been held in 2008, 2010, 2012 and will be held again in 2014 in Vienna.) Just for the record, he definitely put a great deal more work into the book than I did. The exact ratio will remain our secret.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>GOUMEs [weekly head voices #47]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/05/10/goumes-weekly-head-voices-47/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 21:25:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/05/10/goumes-weekly-head-voices-47/</guid><description>As you all would have guessed by now (ALL my readers are insanely astute, of course), GOUMEs stands for Genetic Offspring Unit Maturation Events. You see, the first week of May has the fantastic privilege of hosting the birth dates of both of my Genetic Offspring Units. One of them is too young to appreciate the significance of this event, the other is now at the stage where one tends to over-estimate said significance. In any case, more on this in a bullet or two. The Nemo in Amsterdam. Pinball Machine of Science.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>As you all would have guessed by now (ALL my readers are insanely astute, of course), GOUMEs stands for Genetic Offspring Unit Maturation Events. You see, the first week of May has the fantastic privilege of hosting the birth dates of both of my Genetic Offspring Units. One of them is too young to appreciate the significance of this event, the other is now at the stage where one tends to over-estimate said significance. In any case, more on this in a bullet or two.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/nemo-1024.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/nemo-1024.jpg"
        
            alt="The Nemo in Amsterdam. Pinball Machine of Science."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Nemo in Amsterdam. Pinball Machine of Science.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="Weekly Head Voices Abbreviations">TPN</a> and I were brave (or stupid) enough to take two of the GOUs to the <a href="http://www.e-nemo.nl/" title="Nemo Science Centre website">Nemo Science Centre</a> in Amsterdam on one sunny Monday. The Nemo is 5 floors packed chock-full of fun and interactive science exhibits. This is really cool, except perhaps for the fact that kids of around <em>that</em> age have a maximum attention span of about 5 seconds, in which case the Nemo could also be considered as 5 floors packed chock-full of irresistible distractions. The end result is 5 floors of hyper-active kids bouncing around from exhibit to exhibit, much like a pinball machine that has for some or other reason been filled with zillions of balls and is being operated by an octopus on speed.</li>
<li>After a long discussion with the book publisher Morgan Kaufmann, filled with book proposals, proposal reviews and proposal review rebuttals, my good friend and colleague Prof. Bernhard Preim and I have received the green light and will soon start writing the second edition of the “Visualization in Medicine” textbook.  The working title of the new book is “Visual Computing in Medicine”. Whatever the case may be, this is <em>the</em> textbook defining my research field, and it’s quite an honour being able to participate in its writing. This does mean that until about March 2013 I have another excuse to be permanently over-busy, and hence grumpy. You have been warned.</li>
<li>On the eve of her very first birthday, my GOU #2 ate her first BBQ spare rib, right from the bone. Now that’s a significant event.</li>
<li>GOU #1 wanted a princess-themed party, and so it came to be. After an intensive few hours surrounded by little girls dressed up as princesses, flying unicorns, pink fairies and other types of sugar and spice and all things nice, I believe that my DNA might be permanently damaged. I will have to spend significantly more time with my <a href="/2010/03/29/weekly-head-voices-19-the-time-travellers-bbq/" title="black time machine">black time machine</a> to counter these effects.</li>
</ul>
<p>This weekend,  Maarten Keulemans, the new Volkskrant science editor, concluded his current stint as columnist for the same paper with a collection of thought-provoking factoids and propositions. In order to give you some backyard philosophy to think about, I’d like to conclude with a translation of one of the factoids that really struck me:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s bizarre that humankind spends eleven times more on killing people than it spends on saving lives through scientific research.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Humankind</em> does sometimes disappoint, doesn’t it? Have a great week kids, and be really good to one another.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>VCBM 2010 [Weekly Head Voices #26]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/07/08/vcbm-2010-weekly-head-voices-26/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 09:58:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/07/08/vcbm-2010-weekly-head-voices-26/</guid><description>(This post is a slightly longer than average report detailing our trip to the EG VCBM 2010 conference. It’s of course super-entertaining, but if you still do wish to skim through it, I’ve bolded the per-paragraph themes. If you’re not sure what these danged conferences are about, see my recent EuroVis 2010 post for a general introduction.)
Last week, I accompanied Peter Schaafsma (he of the orbital fat mobility paper), Bastijn Vissers and André van Dixhoorn (they of the resting state fMRI brain connectivity paper) to Leipzig, where they had been selected to present their work at the second Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine (VCBM). Pretty VCBM logo.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This post is a slightly longer than average report detailing our trip to the EG VCBM 2010 conference. It’s of course super-entertaining, but if you still do wish to skim through it, I’ve bolded the per-paragraph themes. If you’re not sure what these danged conferences are about, see my <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/" title="my EuroVis 2010, with general introduction to scientific conferences">recent EuroVis 2010 post</a></em> <em>for a general introduction.)</em></p>
<p>Last week, I accompanied Peter Schaafsma (he of the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Schaafsma2010" title="orbital fat mobility paper">orbital fat mobility paper</a>), <a href="http://www.bastijn.nl/" title="Bastijn Visser's website">Bastijn Vissers</a> and André van Dixhoorn (they of the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Dixhoorn2010" title="rs-fMRI connectivity paper">resting state fMRI brain connectivity paper</a>) to Leipzig, where they had been selected to present their work at the <a href="http://vcbm.org/2010/" title="VCBM 2010 website">second Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine (VCBM)</a>.










<figure><a href="http://vcbm.org/2010/">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/newlogo-270x150.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty VCBM logo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty VCBM logo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Things got off to a great start when, as we were travelling there by speeding bullet (okay, it was just a brand-new rental Opel, but the Autobahn turns any car into a Speeding Bullet!), we managed to <strong>strike, at high speed, a high-quality German plastic bucket that had suddenly appeared right in the middle of the road</strong>. After a few more kilometres of noticing that our speeding bullet was not able to pass the very slowly accelerating bullet stage and was making strange disconcerting noises to boot (excuse the automotive pun), we stopped to investigate, noticing to our shock that the bucket, having been very badly burnt, <a href="http://www.moviedeaths.com/austin_powers:_international_man_of_mystery/mustafa/" title="Mustafa?">Mustafa-style</a>, was still lodged under the car.</p>
<p>After carefully dislodging the remaining half of the bucket, we were even more shocked to notice that the car was dripping concerning amounts of liquid more or less from the spot where the bucket had been stuck. Further on-site and online investigation by the crew brought to light the following observations: 1) The liquid was not hot, and so probably did not come from the engine. 2) The liquid was tasteless (don’t ask). 3) The air-conditioner had been running all the time, and certainly would have to get rid of water condensate from the cooled air. This latter observation was to us not immediately obvious, but now is, and hopefully to you as well: <strong>Automobile air-conditioners often get rid of condensed water through outlets under the car.</strong> Phew.</p>
<p>Our speeding bullet tore through the remaining 200 kilometres in record time, where <a href="http://simvis.at/" title="Link to SimVis, Helmut's company.">my man Helmut from Vienna</a> <em>and</em> these <strong>wonderful brain-boosters</strong> were waiting for us on the <a href="http://maps.google.nl/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=Nikolaikirchhof,+Leipzig,+Deutschland&amp;sll=51.34071,12.378302&amp;sspn=0.000678,0.001742&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=Nikolaikirchhof,+04109+Leipzig,+Germany%E2%89%AA=51.340525,12.378309&amp;spn=0.001356,0.003484&amp;t=h&amp;z=19" title="Google Maps link to Nikolaikirchhof">Nikolaikirchhof</a>:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/leipzig_4x1l.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/leipzig_4x1l.jpg"
        
            alt="Leipzig&#39;s famous 1 litre brain boosters. Image deliberately deFaced. The arms in the photo might or might not belong to anyone that you know."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Leipzig's famous 1 litre brain boosters. Image deliberately deFaced. The arms in the photo might or might not belong to anyone that you know.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  The conference kicked off the next morning bright and early with a <strong>brilliant keynote by </strong><strong><a href="http://webstaff.itn.liu.se/~andyn/ITN/Home.html" title="website prof. Anders Ynnerman">Prof. Anders Ynnerman</a></strong>.  This was related to the great talk he gave in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/06/28/sometimes-being-in-academia-rules-weekly-head-voices-25/" title="blog post including Prof. Ynnerman's talk in Delft">Delft the week before</a>, but even better, as, amongst other things, he had had the Virtual Autopsy multi-touch table shipped all the way to Leipzig to be able to demo live during his presentation. He even managed to undo the evil our projector in Delft had wrought on his laptop’s colour profiles and finally showed his visualisations in their full glory on the projector in the <a href="http://www.mediencampus-villa-ida.de/" title="link to Mediencampus Villa Ida website">Mediencampus Villa Ida</a>.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  The <strong>second keynote, given by <a href="http://rsl.stanford.edu/bammer/" title="homepage Dr Roland Bammer">Dr Roland Bammer</a></strong><strong>, focused on their work on eliminating motion artefacts in brain MRI</strong>, both by image post-processing but also, and this is the really cool bit, by mounting a special marker on the forehead of the subject that allows real-time 3D motion tracking and linked real-time low-level correction of the MRI acquisition process. They are currently working hard on getting their tech into users’ hands. Help them by bugging your local Radiology Department about this! :)
</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/virtual_autopsy_at_vcbm2010.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/virtual_autopsy_at_vcbm2010.jpg"
        
            alt="The multi-touch virtual autopsy table was available throughout the conference to try out. Two observations: 1. Sometimes the glass surface of the multitouch.fi table is harder to work with than the MS Surface&#39;s matt finish. 2. It&#39;s hard to use the table in environments with too much lighting."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The multi-touch virtual autopsy table was available throughout the conference to try out. Two observations: 1. Sometimes the glass surface of the multitouch.fi table is harder to work with than the MS Surface's matt finish. 2. It's hard to use the table in environments with too much lighting.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
 
<p>The rest of the scientific program was perfectly varied, consisting of paper presentations, an invited talks session and a posters session, including a plenary fast-forward where each poster author was given three minutes to promote their work.  What really shone throughout the two days, was the <strong>superb organisation in Leipzig</strong>: Thanks to <a href="http://www.cbs.mpg.de/staff/wiebel-11088" title="website Dr Alex Wiebel">Dr Alex Wiebel</a> and colleagues, the conference was a text-book example of conference organisation, with each event occurring at exactly the right time, not a moment too soon or a moment too late.  The <a href="http://www.mediencampus-villa-ida.de/" title="Mediencampus Villa Ida website">Mediencampus Ida Villa</a> was the ideal location for the conference, not in the least due to its air-conditioned auditorium shielding us from the more than 30 degrees Celsius outside temperatures. Another important manifestation of the superb organisation were the magical coffee breaks, always taking place exactly when <em>you</em> needed them, with copious amounts of cookies to boot!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  Erik Pernod and Herve Delingette won the <strong>VCBM 2010 Best Paper award</strong> with their paper titled <em>Interactive real time simulation of cardiac radio-frequency ablation</em>, really great work combining elements of simulation, visualisation and a clear clinical application.  The best paper committee had a relatively easy choice, as the reviews (3 to 4 per submission) were also unanimous about this paper’s ranking. As an added bonus, the work is available within the open-source <a href="http://www.sofa-framework.org/" title="SOFA framework website">SOFA framework</a>.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  My personal and completely biased <strong>Head Voices VCBM 2010 Best Talk Award</strong> however, goes to the invited talk by <a href="http://www.icg.tu-graz.ac.at/Members/streit" title="website Marc Streit">Marc Streit</a> and <a href="http://www.icg.tugraz.at/Members/alex" title="website Alexander Lex">Alexander Lex</a> on <em>Caleydo: Visual Analysis of Biomolecular Data</em>. The presentation was an extremely entertaining show by two skilled speakers, striking just the right balance between focus and variety as they demonstrated several aspects of their Caleydo visual analysis software.  At several points, for example the explicit visual linking of different heterogeneous data sources (paper <a href="http://www.caleydo.org/publication/2010_GI_VisualLinksAcrossApplications.pdf" title="caleydo: linking different applications paper">here</a>, youtube video <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4uXvxAeb5xA" title="Caleydo: Linking different applications video.">here</a>, see <a href="http://www.caleydo.org/publications.html" title="All Caleydo publications">here</a> for other publications.), I had the typical reaction to good scientific contributions: Now why didn’t I think of that?!
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  Three to four of the VCBM 2010 papers (this includes the best paper of course) will soon be selected to submit an extended version to the <strong>forthcoming special issue in the Computers and Graphics journal on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine</strong>.  Very importantly: <em>Everyone is welcome to submit an aptly themed paper to this special issue!</em> See the <a href="http://vcbm.org/2010/cagissue/" title="C&amp;G special issue on VCBM call for papers">C&amp;G special issue on VCBM call for papers</a> for more information.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  On a more personal note: This was the second VCBM workshop, with the first having been held in Delft in 2008, organised by yours truly. It was really great in Leipzig experiencing the growing community around this event and especially connecting with some of my favourite people. I’m greatly looking forward to future VCBM workshops, which makes it doubly cool that  VCBM 2012 will be hosted by Prof. Anders Ynnerman in Linköping (Sweden) and that after that, it will become a yearly phenomenon.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  Will you join us?
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #9: Windows 7 Geek-o-Rama.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2009 20:35:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/</guid><description>I’ve unfortunately not been involved in any quantum entanglement accidents recently — teaching duties are mostly to be blamed for my two-week silence. Besides spending at least a whole work-day every week on our Data Visualisation practical, I’ve been lecturing and also been preparing a new lecture block on information visualisation with a dash of visual data analysis. Due to my not secretly being an infovis expert, this latter activity has taken up quite a chunk of my time and effort. On the other hand, the exercise has forced me to acquire a significant amount of new infovis brain juice which I’ll probably soon be applying to impressive effect.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve unfortunately not been involved in any quantum entanglement accidents recently — teaching duties are mostly to be blamed for my two-week silence.  Besides spending at least a whole work-day every week on our <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4086p" title="datavis practical website">Data Visualisation practical</a>, I’ve been lecturing and also been preparing a new lecture block on information visualisation with a dash of visual data analysis.  Due to my not secretly being an infovis expert, this latter activity has taken up quite a chunk of my time and effort.  On the other hand, the exercise has forced me to acquire a significant amount of new infovis brain juice which I’ll probably soon be applying to <em>impressive</em> effect.</p>
<p>In any case.</p>
<p>On the geek front, I have to say that I’m <strong>really liking Windows 7</strong>.  Partly eye-candy, partly the SuperBar, partly the revamped file manager: I’m a happy camper both on the NetBook (just installed 4GB of SDHC especially for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ReadyBoost" title="wikipedia page on readyboost">ReadyBoost</a>) and on the quad core workstation.  Feel free to discuss this in the comments, even, or especially, my black turtleneck-wearing friends! :)  Unrelated to the big 7, it turns out that if you use large removable (USB) drives between computers with different operating systems, NTFS is your best bet.  Even more unrelated, I’ve also discovered that one can implement complete independent Windows applications using <a href="http://www.autohotkey.com/" title="AutoHotkey website">AutoHotkey</a>.  Before I knew what I was doing, I had re-implemented most of my <a href="http://cpbotha.net/software/envedit/" title="envedit website">envedit</a> application in AutoHotKey, with GUI and all (you can find my efforts in <a href="http://code.google.com/p/envedit/source/browse/trunk/ahk/envedit.ahk" title="source of envedit.ahk">SVN</a>, AHK’s a strange little language).  The resultant stand-alone app is 400k, which compares favourably to the 4MB envedit installation.  To conclude this week’s edition of I Really Like Geeking Out, I broke down and bought 20G of extra Google storage for slightly less than EUR 5 per year.  I’m not using it (yet), but I somehow get a kick from seeing this at the bottom of my GMail interface (click the image for a slightly larger version):</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png" title=""><img alt="gmail_storage_screenie" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-701" data-attachment-id="701" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":""}' data-image-title="gmail_storage_screenie" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie-300x88.png" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png" data-orig-size="533,158" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/gmail_storage_screenie/" height="88" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie-300x88.png" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie-300x88.png 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png 533w" title="gmail_storage_screenie" width="300"/></a>
</p>
<p>With regard to research, things have been going just swimmingly.  There are a number of really cool articles being lovingly incubated as we speak.  Some mathematical visualization and some time-varying VDA will go to Eurovis, whilst one other submission is already being carefully groomed for the Vis deadline in March next year.</p>
<p>In other news that absolutely made my day on Monday, November 9, 2009: After being in the oven for almost two years, our pathological shoulder segmentation article should soon appear at a news-stand near you:</p>
<div>
<blockquote>
<p>
      Peter R Krekel, Edward R Valstar, Frits H Post, Piet M Rozing, and Charl P Botha. 2009. <em><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Krekel2010" title="Link to paper website.">Combined Surface and Volume Processing for Fused Joint Segmentation</a>.</em> The International Journal for Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery.
    </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
<strong>Mr Cricket, that was just marvelous!</strong>
</p>
<p>
    Finally, I’m ecstatic to report that due to an unfair dose of serendipity, not in the least brought about by the involvement of <a href="http://gpsgek.nl/" title="website of said extremely resourceful individual">one extremely resourceful individual</a>, <strong>Longitudinal Medical Visualisation</strong> (google should take you to the right place) looks like it might be getting off the ground in a Really Big Way soon.  Stay tuned kids, stay tuned.
  </p>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>I have an official course code!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2008/05/01/i-have-an-official-course-code/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2008 09:34:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2008/05/01/i-have-an-official-course-code/</guid><description>I am currently designing a new master-level course at the TU Delft, creatively named Medical Visualization, and it’s just been assigned an official course code: IN4307. Whooo!
Keep an eye out for IN4307: This 5 ECTS course will run in the 3d period (February to April) of the 2008/2009 academic year and it’s going to rule. I’m integrating more modern educational techniques (thank you TU Delft BKO for the inspiration) in that the whole course will be run as an interactive workshop (I lecture, you immediately try it out on your computer machine), and assessment will be based on weekly practice exercises as well as a more extensive project that will have to be orally defended at the end. In other words, there will be no written exam.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I am currently designing a new master-level course at the TU Delft, creatively named <em>Medical Visualization</em>, and it’s just been assigned an official course code: IN4307. Whooo!</p>
<p>Keep an eye out for IN4307: This 5 ECTS course will run in the 3d period (February to April) of the 2008/2009 academic year and <strong>it’s going to rule</strong>. I’m integrating more modern educational techniques (thank you <a href="http://bko.tudelft.nl/" title="Link to TU Delft BKO">TU Delft BKO</a> for the inspiration) in that the whole course will be run as an interactive workshop (I lecture, you immediately try it out on your computer machine), and assessment will be based on weekly practice exercises as well as a more extensive project that will have to be orally defended at the end. In other words, <strong>there will be no written exam</strong>.</p>
<p>My goal is to produce <strong>frikking medical visualisation ninjas</strong> that will hit the ground running when deployed in any academic or industrial projects. I have the technology to make you <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://youtube.com/watch?v=oGECJP3phyY" title="Link to Daft Punk live performance">harder, better, faster, stronger</a>, and I’m not afraid to use it.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>