<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Habits on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/habits/</link><description>Recent content in Habits on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 09:55:44 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/habits/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2022 to 2023 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 16:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2023 everyone, and to the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis
I wish all of you all of the best for this shiny new year twenty-twenty-three!
(By the way, this, the first day of the year, is the earliest that the yearly transition post has ever appeared!)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2023 everyone, and to the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="20221220-cape-st-francis-walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_9aeb90d9d01a11e9.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_8678af152961e9a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_d62854548d79e21e.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_4e0ce1b965a24760.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_8678af152961e9a.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I wish all of you all of the best for this shiny new year twenty-twenty-three!</p>
<p>(By the way, this, the first day of the year, is the earliest that the
yearly transition post has ever appeared!)</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Over the past year, I published fifteen posts on this blog, 14 of which were
&ldquo;weekly&rdquo; head voices posts (#237 to #250), and one <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/">the 2022 transition post</a>.</p>
<p>In an ideal world where I get to divide up my time between family and friends,
blogging, running and Emacs, I might be able to get close to the mythical 52
WHVs per year.</p>
<p>However, for me 2022 was definitely The Year of a Whole Lot of Work.</p>
<p>You might remember <a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">WHV #239 Embarrassing finitude</a>, in which I observed that you
only get to choose a really small number (probably only two: family and
friends, and one additional project) of significant priorities that you can
effectively contribute to over any given stretch of time.</p>
<p>I mostly remember that I&rsquo;ve made peace with this limitation, and I am realising
that (good) Work might be a crucial and substantial component of a long and
good life.</p>
<h3 id="some-stats">Some stats</h3>
<p>Invoking the goaccess log analysis tool using the incantation below reports that
this site was visited by just over 126 thousand unique visitor IP numbers in
the year up to December 27.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#6639ba">export</span> <span style="color:#953800">DOMAIN</span><span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>cpbotha.net
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0550ae">(</span><span style="color:#cf222e">for</span> i in <span style="color:#0550ae">{</span>1..11<span style="color:#0550ae">}</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">do</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> <span style="color:#953800">$DOMAIN</span>.access.log.<span style="color:#953800">$i</span>.gz<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">done</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> <span style="color:#953800">$DOMAIN</span>.access.log<span style="color:#0550ae">)</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> xargs zcat -f -- <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format<span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The most popular posts also over 2022 were the very old <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">2013 usa my data has
left your building</a>, the still quite relevant <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">2016 migrating from gmail to
fastmail</a> and my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">2019 note-taking strategy post</a>.</p>
<p>From this it&rsquo;s clear that I really have to get around to completing that
started-month-ago-but-languishing 202x note-taking strategy update, as my
system has evolved quite substantially.</p>
<p>I did also publish five posts on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>, this site&rsquo;s nerdy sibling, which
in its turn attracted just over 147 thousand unique visitor IPs over the year.</p>
<p>The most popular posts from vxlabs were the following, in descending order:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/06/12/typescript-development-with-emacs-tree-sitter-and-lsp-in-2022/">TypeScript development with Emacs, tree-sitter and LSP in 2022</a> - with
tree-sitter having been merged with Emacs core in the meantime, this post
also needs a substantial update. Emacs is developing faster than ever!</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/12/06/wsl2-io-measurements/">Comparing WSL1 and WSL2 filesystem I/O performance on local and host files</a> &ndash;
still reasonably accurate, still relevant.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/11/21/using-kubernetes-for-development-containers/">Using Kubernetes for development containers</a> - I&rsquo;m surprised that this is
relatively popular. I thought that it would be super niche.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="selected-learnings-from-2022">Selected learnings from 2022</h3>
<p>I went through all of 2022&rsquo;s WHVs to make an <em>extremely critical</em> (haha)
selection of learnings that bear mention in this yearly overview.</p>
<p>Because I think all of them are worthy of a retrospection, they are
chronologically ordered.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237 Don&rsquo;t step over the thing</a> &ndash; <em>We’re constantly stepping over the thing that
we think we’re seeking in the act of seeking it.</em> &hellip; <em>You can’t actually
become happy. You can only be happy.</em>
<ul>
<li>Related: <a href="/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/#take-a-picture-with-your-mind">WHV #247 Take a picture with your mind</a> &ndash; Your narrating self, the
one that needs to take all of those photos, can also take you out of the
thing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">WHV #239 Embarrassing finitude</a> &ndash; I&rsquo;m going to summarise that post section
here with &ldquo;pick your battles&rdquo;, or for the more poetically inclined readers
&ldquo;choose your f*cks&rdquo;. Our time is extremely limited - it is best to make
extremely deliberate and economical choices about the things that we spend
our time and energy on at any point.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/">WHV #242 Multiplicity of me</a> &ndash; If you skip everything else, read this
one. It&rsquo;s like &ldquo;happiness for dummies, in 24 hours&rdquo;.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/#part-time--role--model">WHV #243 Part-time role model</a> &ndash; Some motivation to never stop trying to be the
best you, also when, inevitably, you&rsquo;ll only have occasional success.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">WHV #246 Call up your friends</a> &ndash; Do call up that friend you&rsquo;re thinking
up. Write thank-you notes. Send birthday messages. Make the connection!</li>
<li><a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#self-discipline">WHV #249 Self-discipline</a> &ndash; Take care of this personal engine and it will
take you places.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/#happiness-is-a-joke">WHV #250 Durable, blissful contentment</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="quo-vadis-2023">Quo vadis 2023</h3>
<p>Writing on this here blog, and specifically the WHVs, is important to me for
the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>They enable learning, through retro- and introspection.</li>
<li>Each successful post is an exercise in applied and externalised self-discipline.</li>
<li>I enjoy practising the dying art of writing.</li>
<li>They help to form a connection with other humans, both friends and strangers.</li>
</ul>
<p>The reason for this retro-retrospection here, is that I am evaluating the
(smouldering) results and implications of the tension between post regularity
on the one hand, and self-perceived post substance on the other, over the past
year.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve erred on the side of post substance, when regularity might have been the
better option.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not that I was able to control it that deftly; what we have here is merely
the result of trying to publish posts of a reasonable quality at a reasonable
cadence.</p>
<p>My current feeling is that I would like to increase regularity, in spite of
past performance.</p>
<p>To make this happen, I have to learn to be satisfied with somewhat less, and
more importantly, I have to come up with improvements to my blogging workflow
that enable a more predictable flow of material.</p>
<p>A new year won&rsquo;t be a true new year without overly ambitious resolutions, now
will it?</p>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>This year, I averaged 20km of running per week for a total of 1044km (118 runs,
just under 99 hours) over the whole year.</p>
<p>Last year I did 25km per week, which is what I would have liked for this year
as well, but this is fine. <em>Any</em> kilometres are better than no kilometres!</p>










<figure>
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_51b4310156cb6775.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_9b2d56329fea834b.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_44ff53ded7296414.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_b6f0d925e5348190.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_9b2d56329fea834b.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Random drop-outs in graph below. At least finished strong in last week of year."/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Random drop-outs in graph below. At least finished strong in last week of year.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I did three quick spot checks in my daily journals to see if I could determine
any specific reasons for the low / no-exercise weeks, but nothing jumped out.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to have to blame work for this one too.</p>
<p>Anyways, what I <em>can</em> say, without any hesitation, is that running made a massive
positive contribution to my physical and mental well-being this year.</p>
<p>The effects can generally be immediately felt (that beautiful bit when it feels
like all one&rsquo;s limbs are finally working together, rhythmically even, is
exhilarating), and usually signal another start of a cascade of positive
physiological and life-style factors.</p>
<p>Running resolutions for 2023: 0) Much enjoy. 1) Don&rsquo;t get injured. 2) Try <em>again</em> for the 25km/w average.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>I really enjoyed the following books:</p>
<h3 id="fiction">Fiction</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/54906250-project-hail-mary">Project Hail Mary by Andy Weir</a> - feel good edge of seat stranded in space but
have to save the earth human-alien-buddy movie -book. Great for engineers who
know how to suspend disbelief.
<ul>
<li>I could not remember that I had ever bought this book, but enjoyed the
living daylights out of it. Only later discovered that it was GOU #1 (who
shares my Kindle account)! 🥰 we enjoyed the same book!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57357418-termination-shock">Termination Shock by Neal Stephenson</a> - this is such a disciplined, detailed,
diligent piece of science fiction by someone who clearly has <em>practised</em> this
art and honed their craft to perfection. I enjoyed the story (it does require
some reader stamina) and appreciated the massive skills of the artist.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/#permutation-city">Permutation City by Greg Egan</a> - click on the link to the left to go to my
mini-review in WHV #240.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="non-fiction">Non-fiction</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/#projections">Projections: A Story of Human Emotions by Karl Deisseroth</a> - click on the link
to the left to go to my mini-review in WHV #244.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59516276-the-unseen-body">The Unseen
Body: A Doctor&rsquo;s Journey Through the Hidden Wonders of Human Anatomy by
Jonathan Reisman</a> - Join the doctor on a fascinating journey through each
and every organ in the human body, robustly spiced by his stories of travels
to some of the most remote corners of the globe, and of his experience
various medical emergencies.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="resolutions">Resolutions</h3>
<p>Somewhere in the second half of 2022, I somehow lost my <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#reading">reading-before-sleep
habit</a>.</p>
<p>I plan to reinstate this habit, and to install the new habit of reading more
books on my phone (vs being limited to my Kindle, which is not always with me).</p>
<p>Armed with these two life-hacks, I hope to finish reading 20 books in 2023.</p>
<p>Please send me your recommendations in the comments below!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human">Systems and tools for running this human</h2>
<p>As per tradition, I quote from previous transition posts my explanation of &ldquo;The
System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Similar to <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">last year</a>, Emacs, Orgmode and Org-roam are still going very strong,
and constitute the lion&rsquo;s share of my personal knowledge management system.</p>
<p>In fact, with the imminent Emacs 29 release, a recent build of which I&rsquo;m typing
this draft into (English is hard folks&hellip;), Emacs has only become <em>more</em>
compelling.</p>
<p>Amongst <a href="https://blog.phundrak.com/emacs-29-what-can-we-expect">many other improvements</a>, tree-sitter, eglot and use-package are now all
part of core.</p>
<h3 id="byeeeeee-dropbox">Byeeeeee Dropbox!</h3>
<p>However&hellip;</p>
<p>The time has finally come for me to drop (again) Dropbox.</p>
<p>Although I have been a paying customer for many years (see <a href="/2010/02/28/weekly-head-voices-15-auto-tune-my-cloud/">WHV #15</a> from
February of 2010 for a report close to the start of our commercial
relationship), in the end it was their intransigence and inscrutability around
the Dropbox Paper 2020 migration that broke the camel&rsquo;s back.</p>
<p>They have been promising since before 2020 that they would migrate all existing
users to the new 2020 edition of Dropbox Paper.</p>
<p>However, now all you can find about this are frustrated forum posts from
long-time customers. My direct support request to be migrated was promptly
answered, and then closed with the following message:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As much as I would like to help, currently, the latest version of Paper release
is available to new users only.</p>
<p>Our team is currently in the process of working on this new feature in order to
build the best Paper experience for all our users.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I still really love that tool (winner of the WHV Award for the Most
Unexpectedly Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021!), but the interaction above
only served as a reminder of the pitfalls of a relationship like this.</p>
<p>During the writing of my yet-to-appear 202x note-taking approach blog post, it
bugged me that I had to come up with a good explanation for why I allowed
Dropbox Paper to break my rule of everything-needs-to-be-a-file-I-could-sync.</p>
<p>Although my yearly Dropbox Paper subscription is only up for renewal in June of
&lsquo;23, I decided to bite the bullet and <a href="/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/#hell-freezes-over--again">migrate everything out to an extremely
frightening mix of OneDrive, syncthing and unison</a>.</p>
<p>As I write this, it&rsquo;s been just over two months with nary a hiccup.</p>
<p>In June, I&rsquo;ll let that Dropbox subscription lapse.</p>
<p>Dropbox Paper, RIP.</p>
<p>(With <a href="https://1writerapp.com/">1writer</a> and also <a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> on the iPhone, and <a href="https://syncthing.net/">syncthing</a> on my main desktop
at home, plus Apple Notes for the truly ephemeral stuff, I have a pretty
capable mobile response to Paper.)</p>
<h3 id="resolutions">Resolutions</h3>
<ol>
<li>I would really like to publish a blog post titled <em>Note-taking approach
2023</em>. Ideally, it should be full of information about my current PKM system.</li>
<li>Write more notes, including both journals and <a href="/tags/zettelkasten/">Zettelkasten-style</a> notes.</li>
<li>Stretch goal: Maybe get another useful patch into Emacs.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>2022 was my first year back in employment, after <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">eight years of freelancing</a>.</p>
<p>In this year, I have only become more deeply involved and invested in the
current <a href="https://stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> adventure.</p>
<p>As I mentioned previously, I have the privilege of working closely together
with extremely capable folks, in a high-trust setting.</p>
<p>Many of my colleagues are smarter than I am in their respective fields. Due to
that, and the fact that we are both growing and innovating, I am constantly
learning.</p>
<p>My personal responsibilities span the spectrum from programming, through
mentor- and leadership to management and org-level technical decisions. On the
other dimension, I am exposed to everything from software plumbing to data
science, engineering and visualization. (This is what&rsquo;s known as a
PiM-situation. PiM = pig in mud)</p>
<p>The work is hard, but it&rsquo;s varied, it&rsquo;s challenging, it&rsquo;s together with a group
of humans I like, and it feels meaningful.</p>
<p>I have written all these words to try and explain that although it&rsquo;s clear from
this post that Work(tm) took up significantly more time and space this year, it
has contributed substantially to my well-being.</p>
<p>Freelancing was less stressful &ndash; I could focus on the engineering tasks at
hand and usually deliver. Now I have more responsibility, which brings
substantially more stress but also more satisfaction.</p>
<p>Furthermore, in terms of maintaining the plasticity of my neural network,
something I do have to pay more and more attention to thanks to the advancing
years, the variation and challenges of my current work setting are great.</p>
<p>That being said, I definitely have to get better at controlling stress.</p>
<h2 id="things-i-would-like-to-work-on-in-2023">Things I would like to work on in 2023</h2>
<p>In addition to the blogging, running, reading and systems resolutions mentioned
above, I would like to work on the following bigger themes in 2023:</p>
<ol>
<li>Work(tm).</li>
<li>Self-discipline, <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#self-discipline">as featured in WHV #249</a>. I will implement this by writing
really stern messages to me in my diary.</li>
<li>Creating, restoring and maintaining good habits that <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a>: Reading,
writing, running, mindfulness practice.</li>
</ol>
<p>&hellip; and then finally, my central theme for 2023 will be:</p>
<h3 id="4-dot-expansiveness">4. Expansiveness</h3>
<p>Sometimes, most probably when you&rsquo;re out in nature, you experience your senses
really opening up.</p>
<p>It is as if the usually clearly defined borders between you and your
surroundings start to fade away.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve talked about this phenomenon before, in <a href="/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/#the-strange-continuum-of-consciousness">WHV #217&rsquo;s The Strange Continuum
of Consciousness</a> and in other places.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a great feeling, and it usually happens when you are fully present in that
moment.</p>
<p>For a while, you can get pleasantly lost in the infinite and fractal detail in
the moment and its participants.</p>
<p>For a while, you can truly appreciate the beauty of your surroundings, of the food
and drink you might be enjoying, and of the humans in your company.</p>
<p>In 2023, let us be expansive!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #194: 136 words a day</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 23:19:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/</guid><description> Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&amp;rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&amp;rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="afrikaburn2017-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_375a1371e2dd1a54.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_fdd86842f9ddcde0.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_7249dd9600e79b87.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_48c0abab619b5985.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_fdd86842f9ddcde0.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This post quite compactly gazes back at the week from Monday May 4 to Sunday
May 10.</p>
<p>It starts with a short summary of my work week, followed by a story which you
will hopefully enjoy.</p>
<h2 id="how-was-your-week-honey">How was your week honey?</h2>
<p>I hacked on and fixed iPad microphone support in our direct-to-patient
TeleMedicine app.</p>
<p>If you are a programmer, or you have programmers in your life, you&rsquo;ll hopefully
understand the absolute catnip of technical rabbit holes that suck you in for
hours on end, only to eject you on a beautiful but extremely short-lived
dopamine deluge of discovery.</p>
<p>We integrated <a href="https://casual-effects.com/markdeep/">markdeep</a> into the performance tracking component of one of our
medical image processing pipelines.</p>
<p>Having a format, namely .md.html, which is this easy to generate
programmatically from some computational pipeline, yet results in such
attractive output documents is a great boon.</p>
<h2 id="gou-1-reveals-her-plans-and-makes-us-think--more">GOU #1 reveals her plans and makes us think (more)</h2>
<p><a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> turned another year older.</p>
<p>At the dinner table on the big day, we were having a conversation about further
education in general and about postgraduate studies and PhDs in particular.</p>
<p>(She is now in high school, so these conversations are happening more often.)</p>
<p>I said that she will have to get a PhD in Physics or Math, but that I would
probably be able to make peace with a PhD in Engineering also.</p>
<p>She asked us how the PhD works, and so we explained the background as well as
we could.</p>
<p>We spent quite some time on the observation that the most important part of a
successful PhD is just never giving up.</p>
<p>Although never giving up is a chronic aspect, many PhD-veterans will tell you
that this adventure often includes a fairly acute existential crisis, mostly at
about the halfway mark.</p>
<p>This is when the candidate asks pertinent questions like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Why, oh why did I ever think this was a good idea?</li>
<li>Is this work really worth <em>anything</em>?</li>
<li>Does anyone really care about this?</li>
<li>I wonder what the non-academic job market is like at this moment?!</li>
</ul>
<p>Fortunately in many cases, the candidate gets through this process and emerges
from the other side of the ordeal ever so slightly stronger and wiser.</p>
<p>(For those of you who have been paying attention, this crisis is like the super
deluxe version of the <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">5-stage Creative Process</a>.)</p>
<p>I digress&hellip;</p>
<p>Talking more about the mechanics, GOU #1 asked how long a PhD thesis usually
is.</p>
<p>Off the top of my head I said: &ldquo;Around 50 thousand words, but there is of
course huge variation&rdquo;.</p>
<p>At that point she got out her phone (well, it&rsquo;s actually never not out) and
made a quick calculation, after which she quipped: &ldquo;Well, that&rsquo;s
straight-forward then. I&rsquo;ll spend one year planning, then I&rsquo;ll spend the year
after that writing only 136 words per day, and the year after that revising
everything to make it perfect.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was a simply lovely and humorous conversation to have at that moment, but
what a great point she made: If you can manage to write 136 words per day for a
year, you&rsquo;ll have 50000 words.</p>
<h3 id="the-slightly-modified-136-word-plan">The slightly modified 136 word plan</h3>
<p>136 words is really not that much if you look at it in isolation. The text
above, from right after &ldquo;I digress&hellip;&rdquo; until right before the heading above, is
exactly 136 words (if Emacs can be trusted).</p>
<p>To me the <a href="/tags/compounding/">compounding</a> nature of this act of writing such a paltry number of
words every day, but simply keeping at it for months and years, is quite
amazing.</p>
<p>So, thanks to my daughter&rsquo;s inspiration, I added a daily item to <a href="/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/">my habit
tracker</a> that says <em>Write 100 words towards publication</em>.</p>
<p>I hope she won&rsquo;t mind that I changed the limit to 100, simply because I would
like to increase my chances of being consistent and maintaining those <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">streaks</a>.</p>
<p>I have added the explicit qualifier that the 100 words I write should be
towards publication: This means that my intention should be for them to end up
either in a blog post, or perhaps a future book project, or any other form of
publication that is intended for public consumption.</p>
<p>Wish me luck folks! Even better, why not join me on this journey?!</p>
<h2 id="friendly-wishes">Friendly wishes</h2>
<p>Thank you friends for meeting me here.</p>
<p>I wish you all health and kindness and contentment.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Forming and maintaining habits using Orgmode.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 16:48:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/</guid><description>In this post, I explain how to get up and running with Emacs Orgmode habits.
Even if you&amp;rsquo;re not planning to use Emacs for this, it might be interesting context for the development of other ideas for habit tracking tricks and tools.
The importance of habits. If you have some experience being, you know, alive, and perhaps even trying to get just that little bit better at it every day, you will have realised by now that being able to form and maintain good habits is almost a super power.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this post, I explain how to get up and running with Emacs Orgmode habits.</p>
<p>Even if you&rsquo;re not planning to use Emacs for this, it might be interesting
context for the development of other ideas for habit tracking tricks and tools.</p>
<h2 id="the-importance-of-habits">The importance of habits.</h2>
<p>If you have some experience being, you know, alive, and perhaps even trying to
get just that little bit better at it every day, you will have realised by now
that being able to form and maintain good habits is almost a super power.</p>
<p>(Other real-life super powers: Kindness. Peace. Focus. I digress&hellip; haha.)</p>
<p>All of those promises we make to ourselves to read more, to eat better, to
exercise more, to meditate regularly, and so on: The key to making all of these
happen is forming and then maintaining habits.</p>
<p>First the habit has to be created out of nothing, and once it&rsquo;s up and running,
the idea is to keep going at it for as long as possible.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">Streaking</a>,
that is trying to continue for as long as possible without any interruption, is
a fun and effective trick to keep at it.</p>
<p>However, it is just as important being able to restart a new streak once the
previous one has been broken for whatever reason.</p>
<h2 id="what-the-orgmode-habit-tracker-does">What the Orgmode habit tracker does.</h2>
<p>Up to now, I mostly used <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#monthly-journal-files">daily checklists to keep track of healthy
habits</a>, but for
some habits, especially ones with a non-daily frequency, this does not work so
well.</p>
<p>A significant step up from daily checklists, the <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Tracking-your-habits.html">Emacs Orgmode habits
function</a> enables you:</p>
<ul>
<li>to specify any number of habits, each with different, sometimes less regular
frequencies;</li>
<li>to track when you perform a habit and when you should next perform it and finally</li>
<li>to visualize if you are performing according to the specifications you have
set.</li>
</ul>
<p>For example: I would like to run at least three times a week. There should be
at least one rest day after a running day (I&rsquo;m not a spring chicken
anymore). There should be a maximum of three rest days allowed (this usually
happens after a longer weekend run).</p>
<p>Although I enjoy running enough to keep this habit up by myself, I chose it as
a first test of the Orgmode habits function.</p>
<p>So far I have setup two other simpler examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>A core exercise which I call &ldquo;The Wheel&rdquo; (of pain). This has to happen every
second day, usually in between running days.</li>
<li>&ldquo;Deep reading&rdquo;, which is meant to describe a session of focused reading of
long-form, i.e. mostly books. This has to happen every day.</li>
</ul>
<p>Before starting tracking of these latter two habits slightly more than a week
ago, I somehow kept on letting them slip.</p>
<p>This morning, my org-agenda looked like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot.png">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu_f5ebe94babcb0c44.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu_a9cc921388380294.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu_678f29c39cc0d732.png 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu_8cbade739c4c6438.png 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/org-habits-screenshot_hu_a9cc921388380294.png"
  

   />

</a>

</figure>
<p>In the figure you can see that today, represented by the exclamation mark <code>!</code>,
I will have to schedule in a session of deep reading (indicated by the yellow
colouring), and a session of &ldquo;the wheel&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The running habit graph  is showing that I still have three days, including
today, on which I do not have to run.</p>
<p>By default it would not have displayed today, because I ran yesterday, as shown
by the asterisk <code>*</code>, and I specified that minimum of one rest day. However, I
temporarily configured it to show today for the sake of this exposition.</p>
<p>To summarise: These habit graphs show up as part of your org-agenda view and
show you at a glance when you should perform which habits, and, quite
importantly, how long you have been streaking a particular habit.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-setup-orgmode-habits">How to setup Orgmode habits.</h2>
<h3 id="global-configuration">Global configuration.</h3>
<p>Firstly, ensure that the <code>org-habit</code> Orgmode extension is activated by adding
the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-elisp" data-lang="elisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">add-to-list</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;org-modules</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;org-habit</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">t</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Whilst your in your <code>init.el</code>, add something like the following to activate
state logging for the task <code>DONE</code> state:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-elisp" data-lang="elisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; each state with ! is recorded as state change</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; in this case I&#39;m logging TODO and DONE states</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">setq</span> <span style="color:#953800">org-todo-keywords</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#0550ae">&#39;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">((</span><span style="color:#953800">sequence</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;TODO(t!)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;NEXT(n)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;SOMD(s)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;WAFO(w)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;|&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;DONE(d!)&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;CANC(c!)&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)))</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; I prefer to log TODO creation also</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">setq</span> <span style="color:#953800">org-treat-insert-todo-heading-as-state-change</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">t</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; log into LOGBOOK drawer</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">setq</span> <span style="color:#953800">org-log-into-drawer</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">t</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><h3 id="per-habit-configuration">Per-habit configuration.</h3>
<p>Then, start creating the special habit nodes as explained in the following:</p>
<p>Below is what the &ldquo;running&rdquo; habit currently looks like in my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#monthly-journal-files">current monthly
journal file</a>:</p>
<!-- I used M-x htmlize-region-save-screenshot to get this HTML representation of a real org file onto the clipboard. -->
<pre style="color: #DCDCCC; background-color: #3F3F3F;">
<span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">** </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">TODO</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;"> Running</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">SCHEDULED:</span> <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">&lt;2019-11-03 Sun .+2d/4d&gt;</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:PROPERTIES:</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:STYLE:</span>    habit
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:LAST_REPEAT:</span> <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-11-01 Wed 16:00]</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:END:</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:LOGBOOK:</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-11-01 Wed 16:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-30 Wed 15:41]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-26 Sat 14:14]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-24 Thu 19:11]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-22 Tue 16:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-20 Sun 10:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-18 Fri 16:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-18 Fri 16:00]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-16 Wed 08:13]</span>
- State "DONE"       from "TODO"       <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-13 Sun 10:00]</span>
- Created "TODO" <span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-10-23 Wed 09:53]</span>
<span style="color: #7F9F7F;">:END:</span>
</pre>
<p>The <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Tracking-your-habits.html">orgmode habits
documentation</a> explains
that a habit is a special sort of <code>TODO</code> node with the following additional
properties, which can all be seen in the above example:</p>
<ul>
<li>The node has a <code>:STYLE:</code> property of <code>habit</code>. Configure with =M-x
org-set-property=.</li>
<li>The node has a <code>SCHEDULED</code> date in the future on the next date when this
habit should take place, along with a frequency / time constraint
specification, in this case <code>.+2d/4d</code>, meaning that at the most every second
day, and at the least every fourth day.</li>
</ul>
<p>Furthermore, with <code>DONE</code> state logging configured as explained above, you&rsquo;ll
get the <code>LOGBOOK</code> with the required state changes used by the habit graphs.</p>
<h3 id="in-use">In use.</h3>
<p>Whenever you&rsquo;ve completed a habit, fire up Emacs (I&rsquo;m joking of course: Emacs
is always running) and then toggle the state of the habit to <code>DONE</code>.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;ll see that it briefly toggles to <code>DONE</code>, and then automatically switches
back to <code>TODO</code>.</p>
<p>(There&rsquo;s some philosophical lesson to be learned from that&hellip;)</p>
<p>When this happens, the <code>:LAST_REPEAT:</code> timestamp will be automatically updated
to the current time, and, more importantly, the <code>SCHEDULED</code> date will be
automatically updated to the next earliest date when this habit should be
exercised.</p>
<p>In the case of the running example above, that will be tomorrow, as today is a
rest day.</p>
<p>Whenever you activate org-agenda, you&rsquo;ll see the habit graphs right at the top,
by default only on the days when they are actually scheduled. In the running
example, that habit will not appear on rest days. (This can naturally be
configured, see <code>M-x describe-variable RET org-habit-show-all-today</code>).</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion.</h2>
<ul>
<li>Being able to forming and maintain habits can form an important component of
better living.</li>
<li><em>Habit streaking</em> is a fun psychological trick to keep you going.</li>
<li>However, don&rsquo;t be disheartened by a broken streak. Get back on that horse and
try again.</li>
<li>Emacs Orgmode habit tracking is a great tool for Emacs users to help form and
maintain habits, especially non-daily ones.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #123: A semblance of a cadence.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/06/28/weekly-head-voices-123-a-semblance-of-a-cadence/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 19:29:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/06/28/weekly-head-voices-123-a-semblance-of-a-cadence/</guid><description> Yes, we ended up in the mountains again.
In the period from Monday June 12 to Sunday June 25 we were mostly trying to get through the winter, fighting off a virus or three (the kind that invades biological organisms you nerd) and generally nerding out.
One more of my org2blog pull requests was merged in: You can now configure the thumbnail sizes your blog will automatically show of your uploaded images. Getting my own itch scratches merged merged into open source projects never fails to makes me happy, even although in this case there can’t be more than 5 other people who will ever use this particular functionality.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/IMG_0321-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/IMG_0321-PANO-1024x598.jpg"
        
            alt="Yes, we ended up in the mountains again."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Yes, we ended up in the mountains again.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In the period from Monday June 12 to Sunday June 25 we were mostly trying to get through the winter, fighting off a virus or three (the kind that invades biological organisms you nerd) and generally nerding out.</p>
<p>One more of my <a href="https://github.com/org2blog/org2blog/pull/226">org2blog pull requests</a> was merged in: You can now configure the thumbnail sizes your blog will automatically show of your uploaded images. Getting my own itch scratches merged merged into open source projects never fails to makes me happy, even although in this case there can’t be more than 5 other people who will ever use this particular functionality.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<h1 id="aspnet-core-surprise">ASP.NET Core SURPRISE!</h1>
<p>For a work project I was <em>encouraged</em> to explore Microsoft’s brand new <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/aspnet/core/">ASP.NET Core</a>. While on the one hand I remain wary of Microsoft (IE6 anyone?), I am an absolute sucker for new technology on the other.</p>
<p>You may colour me impressed.</p>
<p>If I had to describe it in one sentence, I would have to describe ASP.NET Core as Django done in C#. You can develop and deploy this on Windows, Mac or Linux. You model and query your data using Entity Framework Core and LINQ for example, or Dapper if you prefer performance and don’t mind the SQL (I don’t), or both. You write controller classes and view templates using the Razor templating language.</p>
<p>C# 7.0 looks like it could be a high development velocity language. It has modern features such as lambdas with what looks like real closures (unlike C++ variable capturing), as well as the <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/csharp/language-reference/operators/null-conditional-operator">null coalescing operator (??)</a> and the <a href="http://geekswithblogs.net/BlackRabbitCoder/archive/2015/06/05/c.net-little-wonders-null-conditional-operator-in-c-6.aspx">null conditional operator (?.)</a>, the latter of which looks superbly useful. Between Visual Studio on Windows and the Mac, or the new Intellij Rider IDE (all platforms) or Visual Studio Code (all platforms), the tooling is top notch.</p>
<p>Time will have to tell how it compares to Python with respect to development velocity, a competition that Python traditionally fares extremely well at.</p>
<p>Where ASP.NET Core wins hands down is in the memory usage department: By default you deploy using the Kestrel web server, which runs your C# code using <em>multiple</em> libuv (yeah, of lightning fast node.js event loop fame) event loops, all in threads.</p>
<p>With Django I usually deploy as many processes as I can behind uwsgi, itself behind nginx. The problem is that with Python’s garbage collector, these processes end up sharing very little memory, and so one has to take into account memory limits as well as CPU count on servers when considering concurrency.</p>
<p>The long and the short of this is that one will probably be able to process many more requests in parallel with ASP.NET Core than with Django. With uwsgi and Django I have experimented with gevent in uwsgi and monkey patching, but this does not work as well as it does in ASP.NET Core, which has been designed with this concurrency model in mind from the get go. My first memory usage and performance experiments have shown compelling results.</p>
<p>Hopefully more later!</p>
<h1 id="a-cadence-of-accountability">A cadence of accountability</h1>
<p>Lately my <a href="/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">Deep Work habits</a> have taken a bit of a hit. At first I could not understand how to address this, until I remembered mention of a <em>cadence of accountability</em> in <a href="http://calnewport.com/books/deep-work/">The Book</a><em>.</em></p>
<p>Taking a quick look at <a href="/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">that post</a>, I understood what I had forgotten to integrate with my habits. Besides just doing the deep work, it’s important to “keep a compelling scoreboard” and to “create a cadence of accountability”.</p>
<p>Although I was tracking my deep work time using the <a href="http://orgmode.org/manual/Clocking-commands.html">orgmode clocking commands</a> (when I start “deep working” on anything, I make an orgmode heading for it in my journal and clock in; when I’m done I clock out; orgmode remembers all durations) I was not regularly reviewing my performance.</p>
<p>With orgmode’s <code>org-clock-report</code> command (<code>C-c C-x C-r</code>), I can easily create or update a little table, embedded in my monthly journal orgfile, with all of my deep work clocked time tallied by day. This “compelling scoreboard” gives me instant insight into my weekly and monthly performance, and gives me either a mental kick in the behind or pat on the shoulder, depending on how many deep work hours I’ve been able to squeeze in that day and the days before it.</p>
<p>The moment I started doing this at regular intervals, “creating a cadence of accountability” in other words, I was able to swat distractions out of the way and get my zone back.</p>
<p>This is an interesting similarity with <a href="/tag/gtd/">GTD</a> (which I don’t do so much anymore because focus is far more important to me than taking care of sometimes arbitrary and fragmentary tasks) in that GTD has the <a href="https://zenhabits.net/weekly-review-key-to-gtd-and-achieving/">regular review</a> as a core principle.</p>
<p>Us humans being so dependent on habits to make real progress in life leads me to the conclusion that this is a clever trick to acquire behaviour that is not habitual: Work on an auxiliary behaviour that is habitual, e.g. the regular review, that encourages / reinforces behaviour that is perhaps not habitual, e.g. taking care of randomly scheduled heterogeneous tasks (GTD) or fitting in randomly scheduled focus periods (Deep Work of the journalistic variant).</p>
<p>As an aside, cadence in this context is just a really elegant synonym for habit. I suggest we use it more, especially at cocktail parties.</p>
<p> </p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #119: Snowcrash.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/03/26/weekly-head-voices-119-snowcrash/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2017 20:55:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/03/26/weekly-head-voices-119-snowcrash/</guid><description>This edition of the not-quite-Weekly Head Voices covers the period of time from Monday March 6 to Sunday March 26, 2017.
As is becoming sort of a tradition around these parts, I get to show you a photo or two of our over-nerding antidote trips into the wild.
This is the path to the Koppie Alleen beach in the De Hoop Nature Reserve. Paths and photos of paths make me all pensive:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the not-quite-Weekly Head Voices covers the period of time from Monday March 6 to Sunday March 26, 2017.</p>
<p>As is becoming sort of a tradition around these parts, I get to show you a photo or two of our over-nerding antidote trips into the wild.</p>
<p>This is the path to the Koppie Alleen beach in the <a href="http://www.capenature.co.za/reserves/de-hoop-nature-reserve/">De Hoop Nature Reserve</a>. Paths and photos of paths make me all pensive:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/IMG_20170318_1613225.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/IMG_20170318_1613225-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The following impression is of the De Hoopvlei. The short hiking trail along the vlei turned my morning run into an epic one.</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/IMG_20170318_1044208-1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/IMG_20170318_1044208-1-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The weekend before the De Hoop one, I spent at least half an hour sitting on the sofa just thinking.</p>
<p>Two things are noteworthy about this event.</p>
<ol>
<li>I had half an hour of pure, uncut, interruption-free idle time.</li>
<li>During this time, I resisted the urge to flip out or open any information consumption device, instead electing to have my thoughts explore my internal landscape, like people used to do in the old days.</li>
</ol>
<p>I was trying to come up with better ways to keep track of this landscape. The <a href="/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">Deep Work</a> phase I’m going through currently applies to work time (doh), but somehow not to free time, where I’m very much prone to latch on securely to the internet firehose for a mind-blasting gulp-athon.</p>
<p>Coincidentally, and perhaps even slightly ironically, the firehose deposited this insightful Scientific American article titled <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/warning-your-new-digital-world-is-highly-addictive/"><em>Warning: Your New Digital World Is Highly Addictive</em></a>.</p>
<p>Psychology and marketing professor Adam Alter argues that the companies behind the apps and the media that we consume are naturally applying various advanced tools to ensure that we remain engaged for as long as possible.</p>
<p>In short, you spend so much time in Facebook (<a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="https://youtu.be/md4kM9AKjHs">I don’t anymore haha</a>) because Facebook employs really clever people who build systems that run continuous experiments on your viewing behaviour and figure out what to show you so that your eyeballs remain glued to that little display.</p>
<p>This makes absolute sense of course.</p>
<p>If your company’s life blood was advertising revenue, and/or user engagement was important to your company’s bottom line for some or other reason, of course you would analyse and A/B test the living daylights out of your users in order to keep them in your app / media stream for that much longer.</p>
<p>The following day, the firehose of faux-wisdom gave me this: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2017/mar/11/tim-berners-lee-web-inventor-save-internet"><em>Tim Berners-Lee: I invented the web. Here are three things we need to change to save it</em></a>.</p>
<p>Sir Berners-Lee is arguing that we’ve lost control of our data (“your” data belongs to Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, <em>&lt;insert your thing here&gt;</em>, you should blog more it’s better) and, more importantly, that we’re being manipulated by less than benevolent actors (pronounce with melodramatic accent on the “tors”) who, again based on advanced analytics tools, manufacture and modify news in order to sway public opinion. (Read my other recent post <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2017/03/25/fake-news-is-just-the-beginning/">Fake News is Just the Beginning</a> if your tin foil hat is just getting warmed up.)</p>
<p>In <a href="/2011/03/19/drown-in-the-now-weekly-head-voices-42/">2011</a>, <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">2012</a> and <a href="/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/">2014</a>, I wrote briefly about our innate weakness for anything new. Social media is almost the perfect poison in that respect. You keep on scrolling down, because what if, what if there’s something <em>new</em> that’s going to answer that question you have not even formulated yet.</p>
<p>Putting all of this together: The internet is a beautiful thing. However, we have evolved parts of it to target an insidious psychological weakness in ourselves. Furthermore, there is a massive commercial incentive to keep on tweaking the distractions so that they become even more addictive, negating many of the information-related advantages they might have offered.</p>
<p>As if that was not sufficient, there is political and commercial incentive to develop techniques that essentially subvert our cognition, thereby fairly effectively misleading us to make decisions that satisfy somebody else’s agenda.</p>
<p>All is not lost.</p>
<p>Making time to think is great. Set aside as much as you can. Stare into space. Resist the urge to check the little magic window.</p>
<p>Personally, I like to form habits as much as possible.</p>
<p><a href="/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">Deep Work</a> has become a habit for me. I am going to bring in old-school glassy-eyed staring-into-space thinking as a habit also. Complementary to that, and as an answer to my search for ways of keeping track of my mental landscape, I have resolved to write / draw as much of that mental landscape as I can, at regular intervals.</p>
<p>More generally, I wonder if, and how, we as humankind are going to address the issue of news and opinion manipulation.</p>
<p>Do we have to resign ourselves to this future? Is it going to become a question of which side employs the most expensive analytics and data science, and can hence out-manipulate its opponents? Or are we humans somehow going to develop systemic immunity?</p>
<p>In any case, I wish you all great success and happiness staring into space!</p>
<p>P.S. I nominated <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexandra_Elbakyan">Alexandra Elbakyan</a> for the brand-new <a href="https://www.media.mit.edu/disobedience/?ref=3c57421c098068c80298fd5fd3e18c74">MIT Media Lab Disobedience Prize</a>. If you have some time, and you feel that publically funded research results should be available to the public, please <a href="https://www.media.mit.edu/disobedience/?ref=3c57421c098068c80298fd5fd3e18c74">add your nomination</a>.</p>
<p> </p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>