<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>pomodoro on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/pomodoro/</link><description>Recent content in pomodoro on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 11:09:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/pomodoro/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #192: COVID-19 part 2.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 11:09:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/</guid><description> A scene from Stilbaai, my number one favourite new vacation destination, taken on the morning after the lockdown had been announced. We were extremely fortunate to spend our last day of freedom in a place like this. Greetings, fellow humans!
It&amp;rsquo;s 16:15 (UTC+2) on Sunday afternoon as I sit here writing this.
The post seems to be mostly planned out, with fragments of text strewn around the editor window right below this sentence.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
A scene from Stilbaai, my number one favourite new vacation destination, taken
on the morning after the lockdown had been announced. We were extremely
fortunate to spend our last day of freedom in a place like this.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Greetings, fellow humans!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s 16:15 (UTC+2) on Sunday afternoon as I sit here writing this.</p>
<p>The post seems to be mostly planned out, with fragments of text strewn around
the editor window right below this sentence.</p>
<p>With sheer luck, I&rsquo;ve managed to find music that interacts well with my current
mood trajectory (finding <em>the right music</em> seems like a truly hard problem),
and at this moment I&rsquo;m still hopeful that I might also have found <a href="/tags/pomodoro/">one whole
pomodoro</a> to work with here.</p>
<p>We are living through some of the most surrealistic times I have ever
experienced.</p>
<p>For friends, for other curious observers and for posterity I think it&rsquo;s now an
even better idea than usual to write down at least some of my observations.</p>
<p>On that note, the older I get, the more clearly I see how the idea of a unified
&ldquo;I&rdquo; going through life is nothing more than an illusion, albeit seemingly
well-made.</p>
<p>In 2014 I <a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">wrote about us being patterns continuously shifting in the sands of
the universe</a>.</p>
<p>Back then, at least if I can go by my writing, it was a dawning
realisation. Now it has become Captain Obvious territory.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS</p>
<p>In this post, I look back at the period of time from Wednesday March 25 to
Sunday April 11.</p>
<h2 id="lockdown-extension">Lockdown extension.</h2>
<p>The South African national lockdown started at midnhight on Thursday, March 26
and would continue for three weeks until April 16.</p>
<p>Of course this virus wasn&rsquo;t magically going to give up and go home after
exactly three weeks.</p>
<p>Just like everyone else, we were only buying time, and I&rsquo;m super happy that we
started when we did.</p>
<p>We know <em>much</em> more now than we knew then. In three weeks more, we&rsquo;ll know even
more.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I&rsquo;ve never before seen the whole of South Africa work
together this well.</p>
<p>There is certaintly some dissent, but by and large the measures seem to be
working, and the curve looks like it is flattening for us.</p>
<p>(There will <em>of course</em> be those, as there always are, who will claim that it
was all much ado about nothing&hellip;)</p>
<p>Although we sort of saw it coming, it was still quite something hearing on
Friday evening, April 10, that the national lockdown would be extended to April
30.</p>
<h2 id="masks4all">#Masks4All</h2>
<p>On March 30, I &ldquo;joined&rdquo; the twitter #masks4all campaign by doing my little bit
to try and convince people everywhere that if <strong>all</strong> of us started wearing
home-made (the good stuff is for the healthcare workers yo!) masks as a rule,
it would contribute substantially to preventing the virus from spreading.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">South Africans, how do
we get our leaders and their advisors to look into <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Masks4All?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Masks4All</a>
as a way to end this lockdown *safely* and get the economy back into action
again? See e.g. <a href="https://t.co/iCMNAwAJhr">https://t.co/iCMNAwAJhr</a>
for a summary. <a
href="https://twitter.com/DrZweliMkhize?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@DrZweliMkhize</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/PresidencyZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@PresidencyZA</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/nicd_sa?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nicd_sa</a></p>&mdash;
Charl Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a
href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1244511197921185792?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March
30, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>I find this extra important, because it could play a really important role,
together with physical distancing, hand-washing and more, in how we end the
lockdown safely and get our already-less-than-robust economy back up and
running.</p>
<p>At the start it felt like no-one was listening, and I was getting anxious.</p>
<p>SOMEONE WAS WRONG ON THE INTERNET, AND THIS TIME IT WAS SERIOUS!</p>
<p>It really did not help that the <a href="https://www.westerncape.gov.za/gc-news/147/54065">official line of the Western Cape Health
Department on March 29 was warning <em>against</em> masks and
gloves</a>. (I&rsquo;ve archived the
statement in case anyone loses it.)</p>
<p>The point that many people were utterly missing at that point but that is
hopefully now embarrassingly obvious, is that the mask is not there to protect
the wearer, it&rsquo;s there to help protect <em>everyone else</em> from being infected by the
wearer.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a week or so (an eternity in COVID-19 time) to April 10, and South
Africa&rsquo;s very own and very respected health minister Dr Zweli Mkhize started
tweeting the new official line that the department of health now also
recommends that everyone wears cloth masks:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Cloth face mask
recommendations: <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MasksCOVID19?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#MasksCOVID19</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ClothFaceMask?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ClothFaceMask</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/COVID_19_ZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@COVID_19_ZA</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/HealthZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@HealthZA</a> <a
href="https://t.co/ptNsa4oUFl">pic.twitter.com/ptNsa4oUFl</a></p>&mdash; Dr
Zweli Mkhize (@DrZweliMkhize) <a
href="https://twitter.com/DrZweliMkhize/status/1248613456934129667?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April
10, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>See the great <a href="https://masks4all.co/">#masks4all.co</a> for more information.</p>
<p>My (microscopic little) work here is done.</p>
<h2 id="work-exercise-and-the-future-in-captivity">Work, exercise and the future, in captivity.</h2>
<h3 id="remote-work">Remote work.</h3>
<p>In <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#outlook">the previous
WHV</a>, I might have
mentioned remote work once or twice.</p>
<p>Well, since then it feels like I&rsquo;ve spent at least three and a half years
working remotely, hard.</p>
<p>I underestimated the amount of automatic, implicit, in-person communication
that happens when you&rsquo;re at the office.</p>
<p>All of that currently has to happen via various video meetings, instant
messenging, emails, and then many more instant messages during the rest of the
day.</p>
<p>In its new form, all of this communication takes quite an amount of time and
energy. It feels like I can only bunker down late morning to start on the
actual work.</p>
<p>(Microsoft Teams is our tool for all of this. Whilst it&rsquo;s not perfect, it has
been serving us quite well.)</p>
<p>In spite of the feeling that communication is taking up significantly more time
and energy, my perception is that, over-all, we engineers get a lot more done
in this new configuration.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I am hopeful that continued practice will reduce the perceived
additional communication effort.</p>
<h3 id="exercise">Exercise.</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s not allowed to leave the house even for exercise, and so my running has
taken quite a hit.</p>
<p>I have had to resort to running circles around the house for half an hour at a
time, which, in spite of me usually really enjoying the monotony of
road-running, is quite a challenge.</p>
<p>On the other hand, there are people who are stuck in apartments and <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/mar/21/man-runs-marathon-on-7-metre-balcony-during-french-lockdown">then run
42km on the
balcony</a>,
and there&rsquo;s even the South African <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/southafrica/comments/fzvtak/south_african_runner_from_george_runs_100_miles/">Eddie Mouton who ran 160km in his
yard</a>.</p>
<p>The elliptical trainer which we bought on July 31 of 2007 (it&rsquo;s the FINNLO
crosstrainer 3252), and for the almost 13 years since then has been nothing
more than an overpriced clothing and towel hanger, has seen more actual
exercise use in the past weeks than during its whole lifetime up to now.</p>
<p>One great upshot of all of this is that we more often train together, or at
least close enough for a high-five now and then.</p>
<h3 id="the-future">The future.</h3>
<p>As I alluded to in the previous <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#outlook">WHV
#191</a>, and
especially as the lockdown has now been extended, giving us even more time to
practise and build habits, I would really like to know how much of what we
learn and experience now is going to stick in the post-covid-19-era?</p>
<p>Noticing how we have to pay much more attention to how exactly we communicate,
realising how much work can actually be fit into a day without too many
interruptions, and seeing how quickly nature uses this time to recover from our
normally incessant onslaught, all lead me to think that we should not stop
analysing and discussing the changes that COVID-19 has brought.</p>
<p>Do you think we&rsquo;ll just flip back to the old normal as soon as we (hopefully)
get through this, or do you think we can look forward to a slightly upgraded
humanity?</p>
<h2 id="thats-all-folks">That&rsquo;s all folks!</h2>
<p>Because this post had already grown substantially larger than I had intended, I
just removed two whole subsections, the beefiest one about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niklas_Luhmann">Niklas
Luhmann</a> and <a href="https://writingcooperative.com/zettelkasten-how-one-german-scholar-was-so-freakishly-productive-997e4e0ca125">his amazing
Zettelkästen / external
brain</a>.</p>
<p>Do not fear, they&rsquo;ll probably make an appearance in a subsequent WHV, or
perhaps even separate posts.</p>
<p>As some of you might have read previously on this blog, the struggle in my head
between these longer form mish-mash-life-snapshot WHV posts on the one hand and
more topic-focused shorter posts on the other has been going on for years, and
will hopefully continue for years more.</p>
<p>(I say hopefully, because that means I might still be posting as well.)</p>
<p>This specific thought is still developing, but I might be starting an
experiment where I do try to write some shorter, more focused posts.</p>
<p>I will keep you up to date!</p>
<p>Ok reader, whoever and wherever you are, I wish you the very best that humanity
has to offer!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #185: Starship GOU #1.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 22:35:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</guid><description> Welcome back friends!
It&amp;rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.
Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file two weeks ago, but then I didn&amp;rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).
In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more
precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.</p>
<p>Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file
two weeks ago, but then I didn&rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then
everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).</p>
<p>In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time
right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look
back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view from a Friday afternoon arrival run along the Langebaan Lagoon in the West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="lecturing-old-school">Lecturing, old school.</h2>
<p>On Thursday, November 21, I gave a two hour lecture titled &ldquo;IoMT in Healthcare
Innovation&rdquo; at the <a href="https://www.usb.ac.za/">University of Stellenbosch Business
School</a>.</p>
<p>IoMT expands to the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/bernardmarr/2018/01/25/why-the-internet-of-medical-things-iomt-will-start-to-transform-healthcare-in-2018/#46f18c694a3c">&ldquo;Internet of Medical
Things&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>My knowledge of IoT is spotty, and before giving this lecture I didn&rsquo;t even
know that the term &ldquo;IoMT&rdquo; existed.</p>
<p>Fortunately, it turns out that a lot of what we&rsquo;re currently doing at Stone
Three Healthcare (connecting patients with specialist care through
diagnostic-grade streaming of auscultation (and soon other modalities) device
data) can in fact be classified as IoMT.</p>
<p>Phew.</p>
<p>I would like to make the following observations based on this experience:</p>
<ol>
<li>I still really love getting up in front of a group of people to present
something. There are so many things that could go wrong, but when they go
right, the experience is great.</li>
<li>A two hour lecture is quite long, for both the students, even when they&rsquo;re
as advanced as this, <em>and</em> for the lecturer, especially when he is as out of
practice as this.
<ul>
<li>If there&rsquo;s a next time, I will either insert my own 15 minute break, or I
will get the class to break out into some sort of topic-strengthening
activity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I had somehow forgotten how much time lecture preparation could take up,
even when you just had to present your own day-to-day reality.
<ul>
<li>BIG UP TO THE LECTURERS IN THE WHV AUDIENCE!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="productivity-system-tuneup">Productivity system tuneup.</h2>
<p>Last Sunday morning, as the family took a last swim at Kraalbaai before we had
to return home, I tried to apply some serious thinking (well, I did this by
stringing together a series of normal thinking moments) to the problem of
increasing my efficiency and focus at work.</p>
<p>At that moment, the scenery outside looked like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view of the Preekstoel from Kraalbaai beach, West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Regular readers will know that coming up with new ways to increase and maintain
focus is a life-long endeavour, which my subconscious self enjoys inventing
interesting new ways to subvert.</p>
<p>Conscious me has made peace with the fact that it has no choice but to keep on
working at its end of the bargain, until the very end.</p>
<p>With the opposing forces involved, my focus seems to oscillate with varying
frequencies between terrible and not too bad.</p>
<p>Anyways, having had a few days of fresh air and majestic scenery to jog the
neural circuitry, I applied myself, again, to the problem at hand.</p>
<p>I thought that sketching could help, so I was scribbling using a rather
impressive electronic pencil-analogue on a glass screen.</p>
<p>After several focused minutes (SEVERAL MINUTES, I TELL YOU!), I had a mindmap
with &ldquo;increase efficiency&rdquo; in a little oval at the center, arrows pointing
outwards into three terribly familiar habits, each in a rectangle <em>this</em> time,
and finally more connecting lines to lists of pretty plausible sounding reasons
for the three well-known habits.</p>
<p>The three rectangles were:</p>
<ol>
<li>Morning planning.</li>
<li>Inbox 0.</li>
<li>Pomodoro always.</li>
</ol>
<p>Over the years, these three items have made pretty regular appearances, in
various different forms, on this blog.</p>
<p>(I laughed when I just looked up <a href="/2010/09/20/an-indecent-proposal-weekly-head-voices-31/">this old 2010
post</a> and found a
pretty effective focus technique in the comments.)</p>
<p>Anyways, although the little thinking and drawing session documented here
seemingly did not result in any new revelations, the act of going through the
whole thought process, and documenting the results (again), seemed to have
contributed to a pretty great week in terms of focus.</p>
<p>I wrote down a little mantra for myself (definitely not fit for publication),
weaving together the three points above and the reasoning behind them, almost
like the affirmation in Wreckit Ralph&rsquo;s bad guy support group:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m bad, and that&rsquo;s good. I will never be good, and that&rsquo;s not bad. There&rsquo;s
no one I&rsquo;d rather be than me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have <em>chosen</em>
to take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having <em>decided</em>
to <em>commit</em>, i.e. active.</p>
<p>My humble focus mantra is following in this tradition.</p>
<p>(I really hope that my subversive sub-conscious is not paying attention right
now&hellip;)</p>
<h2 id="starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">Starship GOU #1, taxiing on the runway.</h2>
<p>Wednesday, December 4, was officially <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU
#1&rsquo;s</a> last day of primary school.</p>
<p>Although she seemed to navigate this emotional event with her customary
even-keeled demeanour, some of the moments were really just too big to let go by
without a good cry or two.</p>
<p>I was also happy to observe the level of retrospection and sunny candour she
applied to her informal post hoc analyses of above-mentioned crying moments.</p>
<p>I really hope that she strengthens and maintains this important human ability.</p>
<p>From our perspective as parents, it feels like the stakes are being raised
quite significantly.</p>
<p>The thing is, our oldest is now quite obviously becoming an adult.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like that scene at the end of the brilliant 2015 movie <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2096673/">Inside
Out</a>, where the protagonist&rsquo;s brain
console is suddenly upgraded to one with at least 9000 new knobs and dials.</p>
<p>Up to now, we (the parents) were GOU #1&rsquo;s only control system.</p>
<p>Now it is becoming quite clear that she is increasingly forming her own
opinions, and making her own decisions.</p>
<p>In most cases, the physical constraints of a 13 year old living in her parent&rsquo;s
house still afford us some level of control.</p>
<p>However, relying on that would be missing the point entirely.</p>
<p>You see, we find ourselves in the moment of truth, when the past 13 years of
mostly gentle programming has to start executing all by itself.</p>
<p>Our little GOU #1, our first co-created human intelligence, is preparing to go
out into the world.</p>
<p>She has not taken off yet, so we do our best to apply the final touches to her
already promising software.</p>
<p>We exhort her regularly: <em>Be useful. Use your (rational) brain. Be kind. Find
the kindness in others.</em></p>
<p>In the darkness, when we are at our weakest, stripped down to our core, we do
what all parents do:</p>
<p>We worry, and we hope with a passion, the intensity of which it is difficult to
describe, that our offspring units do manage to <a href="/2012/03/04/rhythm-of-the-night-weekly-head-voices-66/#life-philosophy-that-works">generate their own motivation,
to manufacture meaning, and to create
love</a>.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
This could be a runway, but it is the entrance to Vergelegen Wine Estate. At
this point, I was in fact running on this way.
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2018 to 2019 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 15:39:34 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</guid><description> The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house-1024x646.jpg"
        
            alt="The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to this, the most recent (as of this writing) instance of the venerable WHV year transition post tradition!</p>
<p>You can find previous editions here:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 to 2018</a> – short post, can be summarised as: “Sorry I stopped blogging for a while, I did run a bit, I’m going to blog more.”</li>
<li><a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">2016 to 2017</a> – substantial post (1800 words) with: “education will improve stupid politics; running, blogging, meditation; we made a new baby!!; kindness and gratefulness; life changes the whole time, deal with it.”</li>
<li><a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">2011 to 2012</a> – transition post disguised as WHV with: “stop doing life goals, disconnect more, list of miscellaneous life tips, because in 2011 I am not-even-40-yet Mr Wisdom”.</li>
<li><a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">2009 to 2010</a> – super short but sweet, I am clearly still new at this.</li>
</ul>
<p>Putting that list together just reminded me of an interesting observation: The more I try to take notes and document everything I see, the more I notice the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiscale_modeling">multiscalar</a> nature of my subjective experience being exposed.</p>
<p>I make detailed daily notes, all of them grouped in monthly text files.</p>
<p>At a slightly higher scale, the frequency of these WHV blog posts is somewhere between a post per week down to a post every three weeks.</p>
<p>When I write each blog post, I look back through the previous weeks, at a daily scale, and perform an extremely lossy summarisation.</p>
<p>When I write the year transitions, I perform an extremely lossy summarisation of the weekly-scale WHV posts.</p>
<p>The list above links together the various yearly transition posts, thus creating a lovely ball of multi-scalar confusion, which should not be confused with a lemur ball, shown below:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball-1024x682.jpg"
        
            alt="At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>WARNING: This post has grown into a long ramble over the past few days. I hope that you enjoy reading the ramble as much as I did thinking of you while writing it.</p>
<h2 id="focus-quantity-and-quality">Focus: Quantity and Quality.</h2>
<p>This post has been taking a while.</p>
<p>I am now back here at the start, after having been almost at the end, because I did not want you to have the idea that my 2018 did not have aspects I am not that happy with, or that I don’t use multiple negations in confusing ways often enough.</p>
<p><em>(As an aside, a friend and I have been exchanging photos of the less glamorous but entirely normal aspects of our vacations via WhatsApp: Plastic on the beach, the washing line, filthy toilets, truly terrible interior decor, and so on. What started as a joke has turned into an unintended but interesting psychological experiment in</em> <strong><em>reverse image crafting</em></strong><em>, strongly underlining the effect that this sort of communication can have.)</em></p>
<p>Back to my main story: During retrospection, I have the tendency to focus (sorry, couldn’t resist) on the good parts, because this is what I remember the best.</p>
<p>However, for the purpose of this post, I did want to spend some words on one of the (multiple!) issues that I struggled with in 2018.</p>
<p>Either I am getting worse at focusing, or I am getting better at noticing when I lose focus, or a combination of both.</p>
<p>At the very least <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">five of the posts I wrote in 2018 dealt in some way with</a> <em><a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">focus</a></em>.</p>
<p>The mentioned posts specifically and my thinking generally take the form of some analysis but mostly tools and tricks to try and improve the frequency, intensity and length of periods of focus.</p>
<p>(What you don’t read in the posts because of above-mentioned memory bias, is that there is usually a significant amount of inwardly-directed regret and disappointment involved.)</p>
<p>Even more subtle is the problem of selecting That One Most Suitable Thing to focus on. What’s going to have the most impact? What do I have capacity for at the moment? Can I trust my own subjective assessment of my current capacity, or is Lazy-Me being sneaky?</p>
<p>By the time I have made a decision, it’s probably wrong. <em>Sometimes</em> it’s a good decision, but by then the little block of time I had has flown away or has been blown to smithereens by the latest interruption, and so the quality of the decision is moot.</p>
<p>I would have expected that at this advanced age focus would come naturally and easily, and that I would know exactly what to do. However, I have had to accept that <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#slippery-slippery-focus">focus will probably remain this slippery</a> and require constant attention (haha I see what I did there) until the very end.</p>
<p>Besides eating well, sleeping well, exercising regularly and taking time to meditate (just in case!), our old friend <a href="https://cpbotha.net/?s=pomodoro">the pomodoro technique</a> is still the best tool in the box.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging.</h2>
<p>During 2018, 36 blog posts were published here, most of which were Weekly Head Voices. Those of you who have a math degree or two will not need much time to calculate that the “W” in “WHV” is at the moment mostly a little inside joke.</p>
<p>However, I did publish 14 more posts than I did in 2017, so there is hope for this year!</p>
<p>The wordpress.com statistics plugin reports just over 19000 visitors (unique IP numbers) who were responsible for just over 26000 page views for the whole year.</p>
<p>Because many people use some form of ad and/or tracking blocking these days, their visits won’t be counted, as the wordpress.com statistics relies on a tiny image which is hosted by wordpress.com, access to which is (rightfully) blocked by many blocker plugins.</p>
<p>In order to get a better idea of how many ad-blocker people read my stuff, I installed the <a href="https://wp-statistics.com/">wp-statistics</a> plugin, which locally tallies up all visits and hence is not blocked by blockers, at the start of March. For the period from March 2018 until the end of the year, it is reporting just over 74000 visitors and somewhere north of 390000 page hits.</p>
<p>Although to me this seems on the high side, I do think we can safely say that there were somewhere between 19000 and 74000 unique hosts, which to me is a very pleasant surprise.</p>
<p>However, I am by far the happiest due to all of the interactions I had with friends, mostly old and some new, on this blog. Most recently, the comments section of <a href="/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/">WHV #156</a> blew up in such a brilliant way!</p>
<p>More generally speaking, even when there are no comments, I know that throughout the year I am connecting with various subsets of my peeps through the posts on this blog. This acts as tremendous motivation to keep on writing. If even a single friend reads, it has been more than worth it.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, there is now a</em> <a href="https://t.me/headvoices"><em>telegram group, quite surprisingly called “headvoices”</em></a><em>, that you can join to receive a summary whenever a new post is published, and for general chitchat. Although so far only two of my most avant-garde friends have joined, this new form of blog-related communication excites me!)</em></p>
<h3 id="looking-forward">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>Surprisingly, I again will aim to write one WHV post per week.</p>
<p>I will probably fail again, but I believe that this is one of those cases of “aim for the stars, reach the moon”.</p>
<p>As mentioned above, writing these letters and writing them regularly is really important to me.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, I should probably have declared <strong>email bankruptcy</strong> years ago. I am</em> <strong><em>just</em></strong> <em>managing to keep head above water, but writing letters to friends like we used to do in the old days is becoming increasingly difficult. What is your feeling currently re email and how it has changed over the past few years?)</em></p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>Strava says I ran 1286km in 2018.</p>
<p>Seeing that I had set myself a private goal of 1000km for 2018 (2016 was 440km and <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 was 880km</a>), I am quite happy with this.</p>
<p>(As an aside, I spent 119 hours running, spread out over a total of 149 runs, which means 2.86 runs every week of the year.)</p>
<p>I did 770 of those 1286 kilometres in sandals, and a further 35km on barefoot.</p>
<p>More importantly, I had to learn the humbling lesson that no amount of stubborn, brute-force exercise could work around the fact I am flat footed (arch-challenged?), resulting in easily overworked posterior tibial tendons.</p>
<p>As I pushed my weekly distance up, my feet complained more loudly, until I was forced to go back to normal-person-running-shoes.</p>
<p>After a few weeks eating humble pie in running shoes, things are going much better, and I recently did my first short and careful run in sandals.</p>
<p>(Similar to the observation confirmed by <a href="https://veronikach.com/progress-reports/my-goals-for-2018-final-progress-report/">the pattern recognition heroine veronikach in her end-of-2018 post</a>, I too ran slower this year in order to run better. I did this for the largest part due to my temporarily busted ankles, but also because more experienced athletes at work recommended heart rate training. For the past few hundreds of kilometres, I have regulated my running speed to try and keep my heart rate within the 75% to 85% of maximum range, mostly ending up closer to 85% than 80%. This has increased the occurrence of those addictive perfect runs, and it has helped to keep my ankles out of trouble.)</p>
<h3 id="looking-forward-1">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>In 2019, I would be happy to <em>maintain</em> my 2018 monthly running quota, to remain injury-free, and to maximise my running zen.</p>
<p>(“Running slow” explained above can contribute substantially to the latter two goals.)</p>
<p>I do have an additional concrete (but very humble) running-related resolution for 2019, but I have decided to keep that quiet until it’s in the pocket. :)</p>
<h2 id="other-plans-for-2019">Other plans for 2019.</h2>
<h3 id="experiment-alcohol-zero">Experiment Alcohol Zero #2.</h3>
<p>Yesterday, which at the time of writing is January 4, 2019, was the first day of EAZ #2.</p>
<p>It has been two years since <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#experiment-alcohol-zero">the previous EAZ in 2016</a>. The previous experiment coincided with a significant jump in my running performance, the effects of which did not fade away after the end of the experiment.</p>
<p>This time around, the plan is to run EAZ for at least as long as in 2016, but hopefully a few days or weeks longer.</p>
<p>(I should probably call this EA&lt;0.5, as that is what my current favourite “alcohol-free” beer, Devil’s Peak Zero to Hero, claims.)</p>
<h3 id="ship-more-side-projects">Ship more side-projects.</h3>
<p>Most nerds I know have <em>side-projects</em>.</p>
<p>These are the technical artifacts, systems and machines one builds, because one can’t stop building stuff, even after work ends.</p>
<p>Like most nerds, I have a number of these that started with high momentum (new programming language, new tools, new problem, EXCITING! … 3 hours later … NOVELTY COMPLETELY WORN OFF doh.) and are now lying around gathering dust.</p>
<p>Inspired by a colleague who managed to ship <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/656740/Cosmonator/">a brilliant shooter game side-project on Steam</a> last year, I made myself the promise to ship more side-projects.</p>
<p>After that, I managed to ship two side-projects, one small and the other quite tiny.</p>
<p>This was a satisfying experience that I would like to continue in 2019.</p>
<p>(P.S. the problem with shipping side-projects, is that you now have more things that you actually have to look after. Next year I’ll think up a resolution for unmaintained shipped side-projects.)</p>
<h3 id="mindful-more">Mindful more.</h3>
<p>This is a simple one.</p>
<p>I used to spend a few minutes every second morning before work doing simple mindfulness breathing and focus exercises.</p>
<p>It was worth the modest time investment many times over, in terms of focus, and especially in terms of seeing life in perspective.</p>
<p>In the second half of 2018 I let this habit slip for some or other reason. I think it’s because I convinced myself that running time could also count as meditation time.</p>
<p>In 2019, I’m going to #bringbackthemeditation.</p>
<h3 id="learn-more">Learn more.</h3>
<p>During 2018, I started taking a more structured approach to the books I wanted to read, and the courses I wanted to follow, by tracking these in my <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">sneaky longer term goals which form part of my daily planning routine</a>.</p>
<p>More structure meant more books read to completion, and more courses followed, resulting in an Ever So Slightly Improved Me.</p>
<p>I am planning to continue and extend this practice in 2019.</p>
<h3 id="evolve-the-system">Evolve The System.</h3>
<p>The System.</p>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
<p>One step, and then another, and then another, until the lights finally go out.</p>
<h3 id="try-to-grow-a-tree">Try to grow a tree.</h3>
<p>I grew up with a fuerte avocado tree that gave us hundreds of the divine fruit every season.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 40 odd years, and my mom (HI MOM!) gave us a beautiful baby fuerte avocado tree for Christmas!







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree-805x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>We are currently trying to nurture it through its first few weeks of life in our garden.</p>
<p>With the summer sun, and the new environment, it’s a bit touch and go at the moment, but we’re really rooting for that baby tree! (bad pun quota exhausted now?!)</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This is it my friends.</p>
<p>You have made it to the end, an endeavour for which I am truly grateful.</p>
<p>I wish you a 2019 filled with growth, health and happiness.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #157: Melodramatic.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/11/06/weekly-head-voices-157-melodramatic/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 20:45:10 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/11/06/weekly-head-voices-157-melodramatic/</guid><description> Vergelegen, an important node on my Rome Glen – Vergelegen – Lourensford – Land en Zeezicht route.
It&amp;rsquo;s Monday evening around 22:31.
The track “Still on Fire” by Trentemøller is making my neurons fire in highly pleasant patterns while I try to gaze back through time at the days from Monday October 22 to Sunday November 4, and to gather my thoughts.
I have come to a decision:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/vergelegen_entrance.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/vergelegen_entrance-1024x542.jpg"
        
            alt="Vergelegen, an important node on my Rome Glen – Vergelegen – Lourensford – Land en Zeezicht route."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Vergelegen, an important node on my Rome Glen – Vergelegen – Lourensford – Land en Zeezicht route.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It&rsquo;s Monday evening around 22:31.</p>
<p>The track <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="https://youtu.be/liHjofQBAeM">“Still on Fire” by Trentemøller</a> is making my neurons fire in highly pleasant patterns while I try to gaze back through time at the days from Monday October 22 to Sunday November 4, and to gather my thoughts.</p>
<p>I have come to a decision:</p>
<p>The rest of this blog will be less melodramatic. Instead, I shall focus my efforts on puns.</p>
<p>(You should still listen to the track.)</p>
<h2 id="productivity-and-focus">Productivity and Focus</h2>
<h3 id="vitamin-r--tomatoes-for-apples">Vitamin-R – tomatoes for apples!</h3>
<p>As a <a href="https://cpbotha.net/?s=mytomatoes">quick search will tell you</a>, we here at the WHV headquarters are big fans of <a href="http://mytomatoes.com/">mytomatoes.com</a>, an online pomodoro timer that keeps track of your pomodori in a truly low friction fashion.</p>
<p>Bonus factoid: mytomatoes was built and is maintained by <a href="https://twitter.com/magnars?lang=en">Magnar Sveen</a>, who is revered, at least in my circles, as a young Emacs god. Take a gander at his <a href="http://emacsrocks.com/">jaw-dropping dexterity and raw nerd power</a>. The <a data-rel="lightbox-video-1" href="https://youtu.be/jNa3axo40qM">one where he uses Emacs to calculate the number of hours his videos have wasted</a> around the world is especially good.</p>
<p>I digress.</p>
<p>Some of us need a constant reminder that we&rsquo;re trapped inside a tomato with absolutely no way to get out.</p>
<p>mytomatoes lives in a browser window, and can easily disappear under the thousands of distractions trying to snatch victory from your ambitious little hands.</p>
<p>No friends. Nothing less than a permanent reminder on the main OSX menubar will do!</p>
<p>I initially made a small misstep with Be Focused Pro. This does satisfy the requirement of displaying a timer in the menubar, but also tries, unfortunately quite badly, to be a task manager, and to connect each pomodoro to a task that you have to create. (As an <a href="https://orgmode.org/">orgmode</a> user, I have infinitely high expectations of any task manager.)</p>
<p>I digress. Again.</p>
<p>After 30 minutes of searching, I fortunately landed on <a href="http://www.publicspace.net/Vitamin-R/">Vitamin-R</a> (the new version 3) on October 29. Since then, it has helped me to churn successfully through an impressive number of pomodori.</p>
<p>Why I&rsquo;m probably going to buy this after the evaluation period:</p>
<ul>
<li>Vitamin-R is exactly configurable enough. I could get it to work exactly like I wanted, without having to wade through an overly complex UI.</li>
<li>I get to log what work I plan to do during each pomodoro, and I get to edit this afterwards, but it&rsquo;s incredibly low friction, i.e. no task creation and so on.</li>
<li>It has a number of simple but useful charts that help me to do better each day.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="multiple-desktops-seem-to-have-been-detrimental-to-my-focus">Multiple-desktops seem to have been detrimental to my focus.</h3>
<p>Back in the early 90s, I started using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_desktop">multiple virtual desktops</a> on my humble Linux 0.99pl13 computer. Because the year of the Linux Desktop was never really to be, we had to console (nerd pun, sorry) ourselves with obscure features like this.</p>
<p>Fast forward a few years, and Ctrl-Alt-SOMENUMBER is deeply ingrained into my muscle memory. 1 is work, 2 is more work, 3 is Emacs (all hail her greatness) and related admin tools, 4 is email and other communication, 5 is browsing and 6 is utility browsing.</p>
<p>This means that a single neuron misfiring leads to my number 5 finger (index) lashing upwards, like some sort of digital (Latin pun intended, work with me here people) cobra, with thumb and pinkie deftly dance-dance-revolutioning over to respectively alt and control, which switches me away from my work (usually 1 or 3) to browsing, all of this in about 3 milliseconds.</p>
<p>This visual shock routinely causes <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/">the rider on my mental elephant</a> to keel over backwards and fall from the large pachyderm.</p>
<p>Hours of web-browsing ensue, during which my already extensive knowledge of useless trivia is expanded, but no to absolutely no work is done.</p>
<p>This stage is usually followed by the guilt, and the crying to sleep, and the renewed chasing of deadlines the next day.</p>
<p>In my feeble but eternal endeavour to increase my focus, I recently tried to mitigate the effects of these misfiring neurons by disabling multiple desktops.</p>
<p>Yes readers, like many of you have wisely been doing all along, I am now limited to a single desktop.</p>
<p>Desktop One: I can&rsquo;t switch there, because I am already here, right now.</p>
<p>Before I started this experiment, I searched for any relevant scientific literature, but came up quite empty. It could be because it&rsquo;s a complicated thing to measure. People are very different, and the computing they do is very different.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, my experience the past two weeks has been positive.</p>
<p>In spite of neurons misfiring and muscle memory invoking key combinations, I have been staring quite dutifully at Desktop One all this time.</p>
<h2 id="two-other-blog-posts-that-you-might-find-interesting-i-dont-know-let-me-know-in-the-comments-or-dont">Two other blog posts that you might find interesting I don&rsquo;t know let me know in the comments or don&rsquo;t.</h2>
<p>Between this and the previous WHV, I wrote two other blog posts that I know of:</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">Importing all of your orgmode notes into Apple Notes for mobile access</a> – This used to be a huge weakness of my otherwise amazing orgmode-based note-taking: I could not access any of my Orgmode notes from my phone. In the end, all I needed to do was to use Orgmode&rsquo;s built-in HTML site publishing function to get hundreds of org files, including images, math, source code and other wisdom, into my Apple Notes, ready to search and access on the phone.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/11/04/pytorch-1-0-preview-nov-4-2018-packages-with-full-cuda-10-support-for-your-ubuntu-18-04-x86_64-systems/">PyTorch 1.0 preview (Nov 4, 2018) packages with full CUDA 10 support for your Ubuntu 18.04 x86_64 systems</a> – The title says it all. The backstory (not in that post) is that I now have a private RTX 2070 With TensorCores(tm) !!!1!! at my disposal, with which I plan to do my part in bringing about the AI-pocalypse. (Actually, I just want the AIs to take away all of our driving licenses. Humans are truly crappy drivers.)</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="gou2-discovers-parts-of-buddhism-in-the-car-on-the-way-to-school">GOU#2 discovers parts of Buddhism in the car on the way to school.</h2>
<p>On Monday, October 23, as we were on our way to school, GOU#2, age 8, explained something she had come to realise.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s about really wanting that certain brilliant and <em>clearly</em> amazing toy.</p>
<p>You want it so much, but you have to wait so long for it.</p>
<p>When you finally do get it, you play with it for a while, but you soon realise that it&rsquo;s really not making you as happy as you thought it would.</p>
<p>I listened carefully to her story.</p>
<p>As far as I could establish, it did sound like a general lesson she had extracted, that is, not just about that one specific dud toy.</p>
<p>I explained to her and GOU#1 that that was a core learning from Buddhism.</p>
<p>We humans desire things, and we go to great lengths to acquire them, and once we have them, we usually realise that the happiness they bring is fleeting at best.</p>
<p>If we are clever, we see this pattern, and so we stop desiring things, instead finding happiness wherever we are right now.</p>
<p>Me?</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m on <em>Desktop One</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Ubik on the beach, please. [Weekly Head Voices #54]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/17/ubik-on-the-beach-please-weekly-head-voices-54/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 21:36:45 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/17/ubik-on-the-beach-please-weekly-head-voices-54/</guid><description> At least part of this post was conceived right on this balcony over here: One day, I wish to own such a balcony.
Yes friends, that there right in front of us is the beach, and right in front of that the North Sea, and right over that the beautiful setting sun. We will definitely be going back there, it’s just that awesome spending a few days right on the sand.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>At least part of this post was conceived right on this balcony over here:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/julianadorp_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/julianadorp_view-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="One day, I wish to own such a balcony."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>One day, I wish to own such a balcony.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Yes friends, that there right in front of us is the beach, and right in front of that the North Sea, and right over that the beautiful setting sun. We will definitely be going back there, it’s just that awesome spending a few days right on the sand.</p>
<p>During my vacation, I had time to to spend some of it with one of my favourite authors, the late but fantastically great <strong>Philip K. Dick</strong>. Those of you with some culture will immediately think of VALIS, a masterpiece that he wrote after becoming more or less psychotic in 1974. The rest will go Ah! when I explain that Bladerunner, Total Recall , Minority Report and many more movies are based on his work. This time I visited Ubik, a book he wrote in 1969, chock-full of precogs, telepaths, anti-psis and the whole idea that your current reality might not be the only or even the most authentic reality. After reading this with great enjoyment, I’ve come to the conclusion that Dick might have been functionally psychotic for a longer time, but somehow was able to channel this masterfully into his truly psychedelic writing.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Ubik drops you back in the thick of things fast. Taken as directed, Ubik speeds relief to head and stomach. Remember: Ubik is only seconds away. Avoid prolonged use.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In other extremely significant happenings, <strong>genetic offspring #2 spontaneously started walking independently on Monday, August 8, 2011</strong>. Just to prove a point, she started doing dance moves during walking on the same day. Picture this: Little person, head and eyes disproportionately big and hence super cute, walking like a beginner across the room and then stopping halfway to do a little swinging-hips-jig. My cuteness-appreciation gland just about burst.</p>
<p>We’ve now also acquired the pinnacle of human transportation technology:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/ultimate_form_of_transportation.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/ultimate_form_of_transportation-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Say hello to your transportation future, humankind!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Say hello to your transportation future, humankind!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Yes people not from Holland, that’s a really weird three-wheeled bicycle with a huge wooden container on the front. Here it’s called a <strong>BAKFIETS</strong>. You fill the wooden container with kids (I’ve tested up to 4, works like a charm) or crates of beer (I’m soon going to test), fit the tent if it’s raining, and then cycle anywhere. It’s silent and does infinite miles to the gallon! I did get some funny looks when I cycled the 15 kilometres from Bergschenhoek, where we bought this baby, to Delft, but that might have been the fact that it was pitch dark at a time, and I had that crazy I-just-bought-a-bakfiets-and-I-will-cycle-her-home-come-hell-or-high-water look in my eye. Whatever the case may be, I can only very highly recommend this form of transport.</p>
<p>Alright kids, that’s it for now. I’m <a href="http://mytomatoes.com/" title="mytomatoes - great pomodoro app!">doing pomodori left and right</a>, but <em>The Man</em> keeps on piling on more work. It’s especially funny how just about every research grant programme worth its salt has its deadline right about now. One day I’m going to stick it to <em>The Man</em> I tell you!</p>
<p>P.S. This weekend, I’ll <strong>not</strong> be working on research grant proposals at a <a href="http://lowlands.nl/" title="lowlands baby!">truly wonderful event</a> with some suitably wonderful people.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Time does wait for electronic true love [Weekly Head Voices #30]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/12/time-does-wait-for-electronic-true-love-weekly-head-voices-30/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 15:06:55 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/12/time-does-wait-for-electronic-true-love-weekly-head-voices-30/</guid><description> I probably shouldn’t be spending deadline-chasing time writing this post, but I can’t not, you know? I do have some Sunday pomodoros behind me, so the FNSF (and other involved parties) will probably not mind too much. Also, to shave off a few more seconds, I’ll temporarily switch to the Swimgeek Quick Update-style bullet list.
Before the first bullet however, you really have to see the DTV Shredder in action, the vehicle I’ve decided to equip my evil footsoldiers with, right after I manage to purchase a suitable volcanic island and install my evil lair:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I probably shouldn’t be spending deadline-chasing time writing this post, but I can’t not, you know? I do have some Sunday <a href="http://www.pomodorotechnique.com/" title="Pomodoro Technique website">pomodoros</a> behind me, so the <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviation page">FNSF</a> (and other involved parties) will probably not mind too much. Also, to shave off a few more seconds, I’ll temporarily switch to the <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/" title="SwimGeek's blog">Swimgeek Quick Update-style</a> bullet list.</p>
<p>Before the first bullet however, you really have to see the DTV Shredder in action, the vehicle I’ve decided to equip my evil footsoldiers with, right after I manage to purchase a suitable volcanic island and install my evil lair:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ws8zIHW6Ghk?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>(found via <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2010/09/12/what-happens-when-you-leave-a-skateboard-and-a-tank-alone-in-a-d/" title="engadget post on the DTV Shredder">engadget</a>.)</p>
<p>Here come the bullets:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Due to the completion of the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/TI1100A" title="TI 1100-a website">TI 1100-a project</a> by the end of the previous week, I was expecting this week to be of the more relaxed persuasion. I couldn’t have been more wrong. It turns out that a number of deadlines were simply in stealth mode, waiting for the right moment to pounce. Colour me surprised.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="Link to WHV abbreviations page">extremely resourceful  / capable individual (ERCI)</a> mentioned in <a href="/2009/09/13/weekly-head-voices-3-powerless-meat-zen-xi-leaves-nfbi-motek/" title="Weekly Head Voices #3">WHV #3</a> and <a href="/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/" title="Weekly Head Voices #9">#9</a> completed his M.Sc. under the entertaining supervision of the <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">FSNF</a> and myself, defended his thesis (title: <em>Integrated Visual Analysis for Heterogeneous Datasets in Cohort Studies — Application to Neuropsychiatric SLE</em>) this past week, and managed to acquire his whole degree <em>Cum Laude</em>. Congratulations Ir. ERCI, we hope to see much more of you during the coming years *wink wink*!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It turns out that combining a Goretex raincoat, a <a href="http://www.senzumbrellas.com/" title="Senz Umbrellas website">Senz aerodynamic storm-proof umbrella</a> (truly awesome tech, designed by a TU Delft spinoff) and a set of <a href="http://rainlegs.com/" title="RainLegs website">RainLegs</a> (you look like the missing fifth member of the <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CS9OO0S5w2k" title="YMCA original by the Village People">Village People</a>, but your legs remain dry) results in a pretty effective counter-measure against the soul-demolishing Dutch Autumn rain, if one is able to live with wet feet. A Facebook friend with some serious tropical storm experience also recommended a pair of those big Timberland boots, a suggestion that for some or other reason resonated with me, and not only because it would solve my wet feet problem. He meant these really pretty yellow boots with the macho-looking soles:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg"
        
            alt="These are the Timberland boots you were looking for."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>These are the Timberland boots you were looking for.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>On Thursday, my <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kindle-DX-Wireless-Reader-3G-Global/dp/B002GYWHSQ/" title="website Kindle DX graphite">Kindle DX Graphite</a> was delivered by the friendly UPS dude. It was love at first sight (with the Kindle and not the UPS dude), and since then my feelings have only deepened. You see, the Kindle DX embodies the fusion of two of my greatest fetishes: Reading and high-tech gadgets. Ostensibly I bought it to try paperlessify my academic review work (papers, student theses, proposals, all printed out numerous times and finally thrown out for recycling) and as soon as firmware 3.0 has been released for the KDX Graphite and I get some time I’ll write a critical blog post concerning its performance in this role, but for now I’m just euphoric with the thing as general reading platform. <a href="http://calibre-ebook.com/" title="Calibre website">Calibre</a>, once you get used to its idiosyncrasies, is fantastic as a cross-platform library manager.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Specific events of the past week, as well as interesting conversations with the FSNF and others, have again pointed out that terminal over-booking might be necessarily associated with a post-Ph.D. academic career. During your Ph.D., you have the exquisite luxury of focusing on one (perhaps three) important things for extended periods of time. Thereafter, right after the defence-afterglow has subsided, if you decide to stay in academia, your calendar and task-manager explode in a messy deluge of meetings, administration and forced work during the evenings and weekends, because this is the only way to get more than half of your stuff done. I have it from trustworthy sources that this only gets worse the further along you get in your career. As I’ve invested heavily in optimising my own time utilisation and efficiency, and now have a strategy that, although there’s significant room for improvement, doesn’t work <em>too</em> badly, I’m planning to put together <em>The Great Academic Time Management Post</em>. If you already disagree with this or with what you think the contents of the post might turn out to be, please vent in the comments!</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it for this episode. My big red pomodoro timer is looking at me in a decidedly unfriendly way… The rest of you have a great week!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>