<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Iphone on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/iphone/</link><description>Recent content in Iphone on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 14:41:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/iphone/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #263: High Dynamic Life</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/12/25/weekly-head-voices-263-high-dynamic-life/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 14:41:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/12/25/weekly-head-voices-263-high-dynamic-life/</guid><description>Well will you look at that date&amp;hellip; Merry Christmas everyone!
I would also like to welcome you to the 263d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, a surprise even to me that it managed to get this far!
26th wedding anniversary hike, this time a forbidden route starting from Rooi Els
I was partially inspired by Martin Fowler&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;writing fragments&amp;rdquo; to just get this post out there. In his post, he makes the case that social media comes and goes, something I&amp;rsquo;ve seen happen more than once during the 25 year existence of this blog, and so he just plonks together a bunch of things that he found interesting and publishes that as a blog post.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well will you look at that date&hellip; Merry Christmas everyone!</p>
<p>I would also like to welcome you to the 263d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, a surprise even to me that it managed to get this far!</p>
<figure><a href="rooi_els_anniversary_hike_5996.jpg"><img src="/2025/12/25/weekly-head-voices-263-high-dynamic-life/rooi_els_anniversary_hike_5996_1280.jpg"
    alt="26th wedding anniversary hike, this time a forbidden route starting from Rooi Els"></a><figcaption>
      <p>26th wedding anniversary hike, this time a forbidden route starting from Rooi Els</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I was partially inspired by Martin Fowler&rsquo;s <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/writing-fragments.html">&ldquo;writing fragments&rdquo;</a> to just get this post out there. In his post, he makes the case that social media comes and goes, something I&rsquo;ve seen happen more than once during the 25 year existence of this blog, and so he just plonks together a bunch of things that he found interesting and publishes that as a blog post.</p>
<p>Plonking together a bunch of things and calling it a post sounds like a robust approach to me, and so I&rsquo;m adopting it as of now.</p>
<p>I also thought that it would feel good publishing one more normal WHV for 2025 before the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional year transition post</a> which will hopefully also happen on time(ish).</p>
<h2 id="boox-go-6-e-ink-reader-micro-review">Boox Go 6 e-ink reader micro review</h2>
<p>My fourth Kindle e-reader, a 2018 Paperwhite, has this irritating issue where it will hard crash after some amount of reading, at which point one has to hard reboot, a process that takes some number of minutes.</p>
<p>This is of course not great when you&rsquo;re reading in bed, in the dark, before going to sleep. I tried all of the recommended remedies, including the factor reset, all to no avail. (see <a href="https://www.amazon.com/review/RRA4LVNPHE0TE/ref=cm_cr_srp_d_rdp_perm?ie=UTF8">my Amazon review</a>)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s too late to return this unit, and so I decided to invest in the Boox Go 6 e-ink reader, a more generic Android device that is able to run the official Android apps of all the retailers, including Kindle, Kobo and more.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve now been using this for about four months (it arrived on August 21) and I can say that it&rsquo;s a keeper.</p>
<p>Here are some observations, but please let me know in the comments if you would like to know anything else:</p>
<ul>
<li>I bought my unit through <a href="https://www.dynamiccom.co.za/products/boox-go-6-e-ink-reader/1123586000024646701">DynamicCom</a>, the local distributor, who were super helpful and send regular emails to inform me of shipment progress. Down here the unit is slightly more expensive than the equivalent Kindle. I also bought the Boox magnetic cover, highly recommended!</li>
<li>By default, the power setting on this device does a full shutdown after 15 minutes! This was super irritating, because I had to wait for it to boot up every time. Fortunately, by changing <code>settings -&gt; power -&gt; power-off timeout</code> from 15 minutes to 2 days, I now have instant on, returning to the page I was reading.</li>
<li>It is indeed great that I can now buy and read books from Kobo as well. I&rsquo;m currently binging <a href="https://adriantchaikovsky.com/">Adrian Tchaikovsy</a>, and the two most recent books I bought were substantially cheaper on Kobo than on Amazon.</li>
<li>The Kobo app&rsquo;s maximum font size is not big enough so that I can read without my spectacles at night. This is only an issue if you are &gt;50 (welcome to the club!) or have other vision challenges. I have submitted a support request with Kobo. In the meantime, I am reading the DRM-free epubs that Kobo supplied with my purchase in the Boox&rsquo;s built-in e-reader.</li>
<li>Battery life, even with my 2 day power off timeout, is practically a week or more. The unit charges with USB-C which is great.</li>
<li>As far as I can see, the Boox uses the Carta 1300 e-ink screen. It is a pleasure to read from. The backlight brightness and colour temperature can be adjusted to your liking.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="hugo-0153-with-libwebp-via-wasm">Hugo 0.153 with libwebp via wasm</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2024/12/08/weekly-head-voices-257-untitled49-ipynb/#webp-ftw">WHV #257</a> about the long-standing Golang bug that darkens webp images, which I worked around by using an auxiliary non-webp image as the source.</p>
<p>Thanks to github notifications on <a href="https://github.com/gohugoio/hugo/issues/8879">the relevant Hugo bug</a>, I saw that bep (Bjørn Erik Pedersen, the amazing creator of Hugo) had just merged a <a href="https://github.com/gohugoio/hugo/pull/14234">PR switching to libwebp via WASM</a> (!!) instead of the built-in Go libraries.</p>
<p>This update uses libwebp, a C-library, compiled to wasm via the wazero.io pure-go runtime.</p>
<p>Based on what I read, in the <a href="https://github.com/gohugoio/hugo/issues/12843">relevant github issue</a> and elsewhere, this is a really neat trick for Hugo to have pure Go builds that can use native libraries because they&rsquo;ve been compiled to wasm! In this specific case, it means that in hugo 0.153, I can webp all the things without the work-around I am using at the moment.</p>
<p>I was really excited by this update, and thus also reloading the <a href="https://github.com/gohugoio/hugo/milestone/349">hugo 0.153 release milestone</a> multiple times per day, until the release of 0.153 and 0.153.1 shortly after on December 20.</p>
<p>The Hugo release was the additional fuel needed to get this post off the ground, but alas, my enthusiasm for WebP was just about snuffed out when I discovered that it has 0 (zero) support for HDR&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="the-surprising-trickiness-of-hdr-photos-on-this-blog">The surprising trickiness of HDR photos on this blog</h2>
<p>As I was putting this post together, I selected a number of candidate photos, as I usually do.</p>
<p>However, this time I could not help but notice the HDR (high dynamic range) adding some extra brightness to the highlights: In this particular case, brighter parts in sunny photos, and night lights in night photos.</p>
<p>As is often the case with my brain, multiple multi-hour research sessions ensued, some of the notes of which you can see <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Convert-iPhone-HDR-.heic-photos-to-web-compatible-HDR-images">at my TiL site</a>.</p>
<p>Long story short, many iPhones and Androids can add HDR information to their photos when the scene requires it. Apple does it in their .HEIC images (mostly extra HDR gainmap, but could also be in a single image), and Google adds the HDR gainmap as part of the JPG metadata, a format dubbed <a href="https://github.com/google/libultrahdr">Ultra HDR</a>.</p>
<p>You can see some <a href="https://gregbenzphotography.com/hdr-gain-map-gallery/">examples of web-compatible HDR photos</a> at Greg Benz&rsquo;s site. (If you dig into this, you&rsquo;ll run into Greg Benz in many places &ndash; he has been working hard campaigning for web-compatible gainmap-based HDR image support in various places.)</p>
<p>Currently most of the main browsers support <em>subsets of</em> Ultra HDR (you have to know which subset!), and hopefully in the slightly further future, we&rsquo;ll be able to use <a href="https://caniuse.com/?search=avif">AVIF</a> for HDR and also all other web-facing images.</p>
<p><em>Note: WebP has no support for HDR. My new hope for the future is AVIF.</em></p>
<p>In my case, I had to figure out how to convert my iPhone&rsquo;s .HEIC images into UltraHDR JPGs. After more hours of failed experiments (no, none of Gimp, ImageMagick, libvips, Affinity Photo, GraphicConverter 12 do this correctly), I landed on a rather obscure bit of macOS / Swift open-source called <a href="https://github.com/chemharuka/toGainMapHDR">toGainMapHDR</a> which is able to convert HDR .HEIC files to Ultra HDR with the particular Apple gainmap format (<code>-g</code>) currently supported by Edge and Chrome on macOS.</p>
<p>Alernatively, Graphic Converter 12 can convert from HDR .HEIC images to single image HDR AVIF, which are substantially smaller than the corresponding Ultra HDR JPG files. The problem is that these AVIFs have no built-in fallback to standard SDR like Ultra HDR has by design. Soon there will be more support for HDR AVIF via included gainmap, which will have similar fallback behaviour to Ultra HDR.</p>
<p>So after all that, the Ultra HDR photos in this post should show up with HDR highlights if your display system and browser (Chrome, Edge, Safari do, Firefox not yet) support it, and gracefully fall back to the non HDR versions if they do not!</p>
<p>Because neither Hugo or Golang support processing the HDR metadata in these images correctly, I have to manually resize them, instead of using <a href="/2020/05/02/drop-in-replacement-for-hugo-figure-shortcode-with-responsive-img-srcset/">my otherwise convenient srcsets figure shortcode</a> that automatically creates all the scaled versions.</p>
<h3 id="ps-a-taste-of-the-avif-future">P.S. A taste of the AVIF future</h3>
<p>Below I have embedded the same photo as the Ultra HDR (JPG) shown in the next section, but here as a high(er)-bitdepth single image HDR AVIF.</p>
<figure><a href="cape_town_from_overseers_5775.avif"><img src="/2025/12/25/weekly-head-voices-263-high-dynamic-life/cape_town_from_overseers_5775_640.avif"></a>
</figure>

<p>You should see the AVIF image above these words, and your browser should show the full resolution version if you click on the image. If you don&rsquo;t, please let me know in the comments below, or via any other means, along with details of your web-browser.</p>
<p>For interest&rsquo;s sake, here are the file sizes:</p>
<ul>
<li>original .heic 4032x2268: 1 MB</li>
<li>Ultra HDR JPG 85% quality: 2 MB</li>
<li>HDR AVIF 12-bit depth 85% quality: 422 kB</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="significant-life-events">Significant life events</h2>
<p>My SO completed a significant but undisclosed number of orbits around the sun. We celebrated with friends by spending the night at the Overseers Cottage on top of Table Mountain, which felt like a pretty spectacular way to celebrate this special birthday. The party fully lived up to this standard (and then some).</p>
<figure><a href="cape_town_from_overseers_5775.jpg"><img src="/2025/12/25/weekly-head-voices-263-high-dynamic-life/cape_town_from_overseers_5775_1280.jpg"
    alt="Cape Town at night as seen from the overseers cottage on top of Table Mountain"></a><figcaption>
      <p>Cape Town at night as seen from the overseers cottage on top of Table Mountain</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Somewhat later, we celebrated my mom&rsquo;s 80th at home, with a great group of her close friends. It was such a beautiful day to celebrate such a beautiful human&rsquo;s vitality. In addition to being in great shape in spite of her limits and to being mentally sharp (did your 80 year old figure out Apple Pay by herself?!), my mom is an example to us all of how to celebrate life, and how to celebrate one&rsquo;s people.</p>
<p>(Hi Mom!)</p>
<p>Somewhat later than that, above-mentioned SO and I celebrated our 26th year of marriage with our traditional anniversary hike, this time on a forbidden route (no jokes) starting from Rooi Els.</p>
<p>The hike was absolutely brilliant, even although we both had more than one near-faceplant coming back down the mountain on loose rocks. This is what happens when you get a bit tired, and you need to work extra hard to focus on the footwork. In Rooi Els, there were some ice-cold Stellas waiting, after which we had an early celebratory dinner with the family.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a lot more that I&rsquo;m not going to talk about here, but I do need to mention that these past few weeks I&rsquo;ve really been experiencing those moments of <a href="/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/#happiness-is-a-joke">durable, blissful contentment</a> with my family and my friends, and it&rsquo;s brilliant.</p>
<p>Thank you for reading this fellow human! I hope to see you soon, either here, or on the road somewhere&hellip;</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There is no way to happiness, happiness is the way. There is no way to peace, peace is the way. There is no way to enlightenment, enlightenment is the way.</p>
<p>&ndash; Thich Nhat Hanh</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #122: Thanks Pythagoras.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/06/11/weekly-head-voices-122/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 13:14:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/06/11/weekly-head-voices-122/</guid><description> Pink sunset, as they do here in my backyard.
Welcome back everyone!
During a brilliant breakfast chat with friends who are visiting from afar, friend S (now 16.67% name-dropped) admitted that the WHV, strange unfocused mishmash of thoughts that it is, contributed positively to his information diet.
In spite of this admission adding to my already considerable posting anxiety, I am enormously grateful for the encouragement. I often worry about this mishmash, as I also aspire to enter the fabled halls of A-list bloggers one day.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/swest_pink_sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/swest_pink_sunset-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Pink sunset, as they do here in my backyard."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pink sunset, as they do here in my backyard.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>During a brilliant breakfast chat with friends who are visiting from afar, friend S (now 16.67% name-dropped) admitted that the WHV, strange unfocused mishmash of thoughts that it is, contributed positively to his information diet.</p>
<p>In spite of this admission adding to my already considerable posting anxiety, I am enormously grateful for the encouragement. I often worry about this mishmash, as I also aspire to enter the fabled halls of A-list bloggers one day.</p>
<p>Perhaps I should just embrace the mishmash. Again.</p>
<p>In this edition of the mishmash, I extremely sparsely review the weeks from Monday May 8 to Sunday June 11.</p>
<p>During our weekly extra math, science and philosophy lessons, GOU#1 (now 11 years old) and I arrived through serendipity at the topic of Pythagoras. Her mind almost visibly expanded when she discovered the relationship between the 9, 16 and 25 square adjacent squares I drew for her on the 3-4-5 example triangle. Her eyes went wide when I explained that this works for <em>any</em> right-angled triangle.</p>
<p>She was soon happily squaring, adding (long-form on paper of course) and square-rooting away on geometry problems.</p>
<p>Seeing your own child discover the beauty that is math is brilliant.</p>
<p>After complaining about <a href="/2016/11/27/android-security-in-2016-is-a-mess/">subpar android security</a> and <a href="/2017/02/12/android-vs-iphone-performance-a-quick-note/">dismal android performance</a> on this blog, I finally decided to bite the bullet and acquired a second-hand iPhone 6S 64GB on May 10, 2017. The phone is in mint condition, and the price was excellent.</p>
<p>So far, the performance is substantially better than any of my previous Androids. In fact, so far I’ve never had to wait for anything on this phone, which was my main issue with the Androids. (Google Maps anyone?!) Besides that, when Apple pushes a software update, all phones immediately get that update, without interference from any third parties, including carriers.</p>
<p>(A word to the wise: There is no official way to transfer your complete WhatsApp message history from Android to iPhone, which was a huge disappointment. There are unofficial, closed-sourced, solutions that require one to connect one’s Android phone in USB debugging mode to the PC. That risk is a bit too great for me.)</p>
<p>After a period of rest, <a href="http://visible-orbit.org/">the Visible Orbit website</a>, including the <a href="http://visible-orbit.org/the-collection/high-res-section-stacks/">high-resolution microscopic slice data and viewer</a>, is online again! It was quite satisfying getting all of the backed-up data back on the interwebs again.</p>
<p>Since the previous WHV (well actually mainly during the last week), I’ve published five posts on my nerd blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/03/bitcoin-and-the-blockchain-in-10-minutes/">Bitcoin and the blockchain in 10 minutes</a> – I extracted this from <a href="/2016/07/25/weekly-head-voices-110-satoshi/">WHV #110</a>, because I’ve been spending way too much time on various blockchains (read: cryptocurrencies) and was planning more nerdy blog posts over here.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/03/querying-restful-webservices-into-emacs-orgmode-tables/">Querying RESTful webservices into Emacs orgmode tables</a> – Here I combined two of my obsessions, one old (Emacs) and the other new (cryptocurrencies) to show how you could pull live ticker data (prices) into your Emacs.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/06/setting-up-fastcgi-apps-on-webfaction/">Setting up FastCGI apps on WebFaction</a> – I love it when work leads to spin-off blog posts! In this case, to get the visible-orbit high-res slice viewer working on WebFaction, I had to jump some hoops. This post shows you how to jump them too.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/07/adding-page-sidebar-to-wordpress-twenty-seventeen-theme/">Adding page sidebar to WordPress Twenty Seventeen theme</a> – Intellectually the least interesting, but still a visible-orbit spin-off that might help at least one other person. I’m crossing my fingers.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/10/extracting-the-jaxx-12-word-wallet-backup-phrase/">Extracting the Jaxx 12-word wallet backup phrase</a> – After a few hours of analysis on Saturday (yesterday), I discovered a serious vulnerability in a popular multi-cryptocurrency wallet. The post has been picked up by a number of other blogs, and has caused good discussion on the various social media outlets.</li>
</ul>
<p>Three of those five posts have to do with cryptocurrency, which is to a certain extent a reflection of my free-time mental cycles at the moment. Looking at how technology such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethereum">Ethereum</a> and its Smart Contracts (a Smart Contract blog post is currently forming in the back of my head…) seem to be breaking through, I can’t help but be reminded of stories such as those by Charlie Stross in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accelerando">Accelerando</a> (at least the first bits).</p>
<p>Do we find ourselves at the start of something truly significant, or is this just an extremely elegant and high-tech dead-end?</p>
<p>What a time to be alive!</p>
<p>P.S. Here, have another outdoorsy photo on the house!










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/IMG_0109.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/IMG_0109-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="I tricked GOU#1 and GOU#2 to join me on a sneakily long mountain walk. They did a sterling job."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>I tricked GOU#1 and GOU#2 to join me on a sneakily long mountain walk. They did a sterling job.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Android vs iPhone performance: A quick note.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/02/12/android-vs-iphone-performance-a-quick-note/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 13:40:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/02/12/android-vs-iphone-performance-a-quick-note/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending some time doing research on the relative (perceived) performance of flagship Android phones compared to iPhones. I will probably not write the extended post I was planning to, as it seems that it&amp;rsquo;s hard to answer this question scientifically, and, perhaps more importantly, it makes people Very Very Angry.
I would still like to leave you with some interesting reading material. Hence this quick note.
From this discussion post (December 2016) by CodingHorror, aka Jeff Atwood, one of the two founders of the whole StackOverflow empire, where he measures the relative performance of his discourse web-app, the following choice quote:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I&rsquo;ve been spending some time doing research on the relative (perceived) performance of flagship Android phones compared to iPhones. I will probably not write the extended post I was planning to, as it seems that it&rsquo;s hard to answer this question scientifically, and, perhaps more importantly, it makes people Very Very Angry.</p>
<p>I would still like to leave you with some interesting reading material. Hence this quick note.</p>
<p>From <a href="https://discuss.emberjs.com/t/why-is-ember-3x-5x-slower-on-android/6577/60">this discussion post</a> (December 2016) by CodingHorror, aka Jeff Atwood, one of the two founders of the whole StackOverflow empire, where he measures the relative performance of his discourse web-app, the following choice quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Some Android users report up to about 29 score on very new late 2016 Android
devices, depending on the vagaries of the browser used. Still below the 2013
iPhone 5s which can be purchased used for about $150 these days.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That&rsquo;s pretty amazing: Based on the <a href="http://browserbench.org/Speedometer/">browserbench speedtest</a>, which is supposed to reflect quite realistically real-world web-browsing performance, <strong>the 2013 iPhone 5s outperforms 2016 Android flagships</strong>. Ouch.</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/snapdragon808-browserbench.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/snapdragon808-browserbench-1024x823.png"
        
            alt="My Snapdragon 808 does a measly 14.7 on browserbench. The iPhone 5s which is a year or two older does more than double that."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>My Snapdragon 808 does a measly 14.7 on browserbench. The iPhone 5s which is a year or two older does more than double that.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>There are more sites where this discussion / flamewar is being continued. Google is your friend.</p>
<p>The core argument is that Apple long ago made the call that fewer, more high performance CPU cores would give the best <strong>subjective</strong> performance. In other words, to a user the phone would feel more responsive.</p>
<p>This does make sense: As a user, when I tap a button, I would like to see an instantaneous response. A single really fast core is going to help more with this than a higher number of slower cores.</p>
<p>Furthermore, programming single-threaded apps is significantly easier than programming robust and efficient multi-threaded apps. You can guess what the apps in the various stores look like in this regard.</p>
<p>The iPhone 6s had only two cores, whereas most mid- to high-range Androids had 6 or more cores when the 6s was released.</p>
<p>The iPhone 7 A10 chip has finally made the jump to 4 cores, two of which are lower power cores. Still, it turns out this chip again <a href="http://bgr.com/2016/10/21/iphone-7-specs-a10-fusion-processor/">crushes all of its Android (read: Qualcomm) competition</a>.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s another <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="https://youtu.be/k_PK_6F_Bhk">relevant demo on YouTube </a>where the same set of apps are started up in the same sequence, which is repeated, on both the iPhone 7 and the Samsung S7. All in all, the iPhone manages to get through the exercise more than twice as fast as the S7. This is definitely some indication of how users will perceive the responsivity of these devices.</p>
<p>The argument that multi-core was not a good choice for Android is weakened to an extent by <a href="http://www.anandtech.com/show/9518/the-mobile-cpu-corecount-debate">this recent AnandTech analysis</a> showing that these phones are actually pretty good at utilising all of their cores:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In the end what we should take away from this analysis is that Android
devices can make much better use of multi-threading than initially
expected. There&rsquo;s very solid evidence that not only are 4.4 big.LITTLE
designs validated, but we also find practical benefits of using 8-core
&ldquo;little&rdquo; designs over similar single-cluster 4-core SoCs.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>My personal experience with the Snapdragon 808 (6 core big.LITTLE) in my <a href="http://www.gsmarena.com/blackberry_priv-7587.php">BlackBerry PRIV</a> (late 2015 flagship) has been less than stellar. I love the phone for its screen, physical keyboard and other little idiosyncrasies, but the fact that I often have to wait more than a second after tapping an icon or a button before it responds, combined with <a href="/2016/11/27/android-security-in-2016-is-a-mess/">the terrible Android security story</a> (where the PRIV paradoxically does quite well), makes me wonder about the future smartphone landscape for Android enthusiasts.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>