<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>twifraf on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/twifraf/</link><description>Recent content in twifraf on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 22:16:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/twifraf/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #202: I don't even have to miss Dr Topol!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 22:16:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/</guid><description> Welcome everyone to this, the two hundred and second edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 27 to Sunday August 9 of the year of our simulation-running overlords 2020.
Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1.
Shape Up: Stop Running in Circles and Ship Work that Matters After it having spent a few quality months in my to-do list, I finally got around to reading the Shape Up book by Ryan Singer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome everyone to this, the two hundred and second edition of the Weekly Head
Voices, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 27 to Sunday August 9 of
the year of our simulation-running overlords 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="closeup_prot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="shape-up-stop-running-in-circles-and-ship-work-that-matters">Shape Up: Stop Running in Circles and Ship Work that Matters</h2>
<p>After it having spent a few quality months in my to-do list, I finally got
around to reading <a href="https://basecamp.com/shapeup">the Shape Up book by Ryan Singer</a>.</p>
<p>(You can too, by clicking on that link, it&rsquo;s free!)</p>
<p>This book documents the development methodology that the folks over at
37signals, also the original makers of <a href="https://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a>, <a href="https://basecamp.com/">Basecamp</a>, and most
recently the new email re-imagining <a href="https://hey.com/">HEY</a>, have evolved over the years.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not currently using any of those artifacts, but RoR has made (and is
probably still making) a significant impact on the technology landscape, and
the other products are truly impressive in their own right.</p>
<p>My point is, the 37signals company ships high-impact products like it&rsquo;s
nobody&rsquo;s business, so one should probably pay attention if they are willing to
explain to the rest of us how they are able to perform this feat so
consistently.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re involved in software development, or are interested, then this
compact book is worth your time.</p>
<p>However, until you can get around to it, I present to you the book&rsquo;s own
bullet-list summary (you&rsquo;ll find it in the conclusions chapter), where I&rsquo;ve
embellished each bullet with my from-memory explanation.</p>
<dl>
<dt>Shaped versus unshaped work</dt>
<dd>In Shape Up, each project is a user-visible
feature that can be done in 6 weeks or less. Senior devs in the company
<em>shape</em> the work, which means that they derisk and write down enough to
delineate the work, to specify the parameters, but not so much that it has
been pinned down. The team that gets the project assigned is given free reign
as to <em>how</em> exactly they fill in the space delineated by the shaping.</dd>
<dt>Setting appetites instead of estimates</dt>
<dd>Instead of specifying a feature,
and then estimating how much time it will take (feature first, number
second), Shape Up suggests rather determining at management level how much
appetite / motivation there is for a feature, up to a maximum of 6 weeks,
knowing that the feature will be <em>hammered</em> down to fit into the appetite for
it (number first, feature second).</dd>
<dt>Designing at the right level of abstraction</dt>
<dd>As mentioned above, the
shaping process has to reach the Goldilocks level somewhere between abstract
and concrete. Enough detail so there are no surprises that could risk the
success of the project, but little enough so that the team has the freedom to
construct a solution independently and in a more data-driven fashion.</dd>
<dt>Concepting with breadboards and fat marker sketches</dt>
<dd>These are practical
tricks to keep the detail level under control. For example, during shaping, a
<strong>fat marker</strong> is used to draw UI ideas to prevent the shapers from inking in
too much detail.</dd>
<dt>Making bets with a capped downside (the circuit breaker) and honoring uninterrupted time</dt>
<dd>This
is pretty hardcore. If a project runs over its time (e.g. 6 weeks), it is
cancelled, that is, moth-balled. End of story. As a corollary, teams are not
to be interrupted during their project cycle.</dd>
<dt>Choosing the right cycle length (six weeks)</dt>
<dd>Six weeks is the maximum time
a team will get to finish a feature. This seems to be the sweet spot for
features that are significant enough to be interesting, but don&rsquo;t get too big
to manage.</dd>
<dt>A cool-down period between cycles</dt>
<dd>After every six week cycle, all teams
get two weeks of cool-down time. This is to be used for fixing bugs, writing
tests, doing spikes, and just generally recovering from the feature
development cycle.</dd>
<dt>Breaking projects apart into scopes</dt>
<dd>As a team works on a certain feature,
the sub-tasks that they formulate as they work, can be naturally grouped into
thematic scopes. It&rsquo;s important that these emergent groupings are closely
monitored and updated. They are useful for understanding the feature, and for
reporting on progress.</dd>
<dt>Downhill versus uphill work and communicating about unknowns</dt>
<dd>The team
gives <em>asynchronous</em> feedback on project progress by plotting each scope on a
<a href="https://basecamp.com/features/hill-charts">hill chart</a>. To me this is yet another interesting and useful concept from the
book. If a scope is somewhere on the uphill part, there are still unknowns
that have to be investigated. Once the team thinks there are no more
unknowns, a scope can be moved past the top and somewhere onto the downhill
section.</dd>
<dt>Scope hammering to separate must-haves from nice-to-haves</dt>
<dd>In this case,
scope is used in the more traditional software development sense, and scope
hammering refers to the action of whittling down features until a project
fits into the time allotted to it.</dd>
</dl>
<p>At work, we are currently experimenting with elements of this methodology for a
new product we&rsquo;re working on. I&rsquo;m curious to see how much of this will work in
our setup. It sure looks good on paper!</p>
<p>(The book impressed me further with its chapter containing practical advice on
how to implement various levels of Shape Up in organizations of various types
and sizes. Super pragmatic!)</p>
<h2 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion Effect</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently reading the organizational psychologist Adam Grant&rsquo;s book <a href="https://www.adamgrant.net/give-and-take">Give
and Take</a>.</p>
<p>In this book he describes the classic study led by Harvard psychologist Robert
Rosenthal, where he told the teachers of 18 different classrooms that 20
percent of their children had scored high on a Harvard aptitude test, when in
fact they had been randomly chosen.</p>
<p>In spite of being <em>randomly chosen</em>, those children showed consistently higher
performance than their peers, even when they were measured years later.</p>
<p>From Grant&rsquo;s book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Harvard test was discerning: when the students took the cognitive ability
test a year later, the bloomers [the randomly selected kids, ed.] improved more
than the rest of the students. The bloomers gained an average of twelve IQ
points, compared with average gains of only eight points for their
classmates. The bloomers outgained their peers by roughly fifteen IQ points in
first grade and ten IQ points in second grade. Two years later, the bloomers
were still outgaining their classmates. The intelligence test was successful in
identifying high-potential students: the bloomers got smarter &ndash; and at a faster
rate than their classmates</p>
</blockquote>
<p>and then a paragraph or two later:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Teachers' beliefs created self-fulfilling prophecies. When teachers believed
their students were bloomers, they set high expectations for their success. As
a result, the teachers engaged in more supportive behaviors that boosted the
students' confidence and enhanced their learning and development. Teachers
communicated more warmly to the bloomers, gave them more challenging
assignments, called on them more often, and provided them with more
feedback. Many experiments have replicated these effects, showing that teacher
expectations are especially important for improving the grades and intelligence
test scores of low-achieving students and members of stigmatized minority
groups.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just to reiterate: These kids were randomly selected, but just because their
teachers <em>thought</em> that they had scored higher on an aptitude test and hence
treated them differently, they started and then kept out-performing their peers
for years.</p>
<p>Grant writes that similar experiments have been successfully performed in different
learning contexts, and the results were always the same.</p>
<p>This really blows my mind folks. I hope I can keep this knowledge close.</p>
<h2 id="yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">Yet another social media fast because you have to keep on doing them</h2>
<p><a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">The Great Social Media Fast of 2019</a> really was great when it started, but it
unfortunately fizzled out a few months later, probably when the end-of-the-year
vacation started.</p>
<p>When COVID-19 hit, I had such a need for up-to-the-minute news that my phone
soon had twitter almost permanently on position #1 of the app suggestions you
get when you swipe down.</p>
<p>Fast-forward another few months, and I was again stuck in TwiFRaF-Yo like it
was nobody&rsquo;s business.</p>
<p>Anyways, this weekend I had some serious discussions with myself, during which
I <em>again</em> had to convince myself that the select few jewels of Twitter (Dr
Topol, I salute you) and the rest of TwiFRaF-Yo did not even come close to
justifying the amount of mental cycles I was spending.</p>
<p>Fortunately I won that debate, and so now I&rsquo;m again officially on a social
media fast, during which I have resolved to read more books, blogs and other
long-form content, and to write more notes and blogs.</p>
<p>My brain already feels substantially more roomy and relaxed than it did a mere
day ago.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I didn&rsquo;t mention one of my favourite College Humor skits
in this context:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315"
src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/md4kM9AKjHs" frameborder="0"
allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
allowfullscreen></iframe>
<h3 id="a-not-quite-satisfactory-solution-for-not-having-to-miss-dr-topol">A not quite satisfactory solution for not having to miss Dr Topol</h3>
<p>Dr Topol did briefly complicate my temporary exit.</p>
<p>How was I going to keep up to date with his twitter stream without using the
twitter app and getting sucked in?</p>
<p>Unfortunately, my inoreader &ldquo;supporter&rdquo; subscription does not include its
social media subscription function that does exactly what I need, and the
upgrade is $50 per year instead of my current $20.</p>
<p>While I think about this, I&rsquo;ve activated <a href="https://ifttt.com/applets/xcHFiVvR-get-an-email-when-there-s-a-new-tweet-from-a-specific-username">the IFTTT twitter to email thingy</a>.</p>
<p>This sends me an email for <em>each</em> tweet, which constitutes a whole new problem
in itself.</p>
<h3 id="inoreader-satisfaction-with-a-side-of-retail-therapy">Inoreader satisfaction with a side of retail therapy</h3>
<p><em>&hellip; 8 hours pass after this post was published &hellip;</em></p>
<p>Narrator: <em>It became a whole new problem in itself.</em></p>
<p>Dr Topol can&rsquo;t stop tweeting admittedly truly interesting health- and
covid-related research, but the format of one email per tweet is indeed not
going to cut it.</p>
<p>I have deactivated that IFTTT thingy, and upgraded my inoreader subscription to
pro.</p>
<p>This is where I read all my blog subscriptions when I make time for that, so
having Dr Topol&rsquo;s feed there as well makes a great deal more sense.</p>
<h2 id="an-ai-to-fall-in-love--with">An AI to fall in love (with)</h2>
<p><a href="https://lexfridman.com/">Lex Fridman</a> is another of the internet&rsquo;s jewels, who is fortunately accessible
via long-form podcast.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://lexfridman.com/matt-botvinick/">episode #106</a>, he talks with <a href="https://hai.stanford.edu/people/matthew-botvinick">Prof. Matt Botvinick</a>, a brilliant
neuro-scientist who also employs AI in his research, and clearly likes to think
deeply about deep questions.</p>
<p>One of the things I (and apparently many of his interviewees) love about Dr
Fridman, is the left-field questions he often poses.</p>
<p>He does this with Botvinick:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But let me ask the over-romanticized question: Do you think we&rsquo;ll ever engineer
an AGI system that we humans would be able to love and that would love us back?
So have that level and depth of connection?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Goodness, so many layers.</p>
<p>What do you think?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #180: EnsembleYou and The Describers.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 22:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/</guid><description> Dear friends,
Welcome to this, the 180th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I perform retrospection on the week from Monday September 30 to Sunday October 6, 2019.
To be more specific, this is mostly indirect retrospection, meaning that I think about and attempt to describe the thoughts I had about topics and events that might or might not have occurred in the period of time that this post is ostensibly looking back on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="vergelegen_running_shot.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu6b4d272f392b4315b9f56c90756220eb_1916909_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu6b4d272f392b4315b9f56c90756220eb_1916909_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu6b4d272f392b4315b9f56c90756220eb_1916909_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu6b4d272f392b4315b9f56c90756220eb_1916909_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu6b4d272f392b4315b9f56c90756220eb_1916909_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>Welcome to this, the 180th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I
perform retrospection on the week from Monday September 30 to Sunday October 6,
2019.</p>
<p>To be more specific, this is mostly indirect retrospection, meaning that I
think about and attempt to describe the thoughts I had about topics and events
that might or might not have occurred in the period of time that this post is
ostensibly looking back on.</p>
<h2 id="twifraf-progress-report">TwiFRaF progress report.</h2>
<p>Almost a month ago, all the way back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">WHV
#177</a>,
I announced that I would be cutting out TwiFRaF (Twitter, Facebook, Reddit and
Friends) from my information diet.</p>
<p>This has been going quite well.</p>
<p>Subjectively, I&rsquo;ve been spending substantially more time on more constructive
activities. Also important, my work-day focus has improved; there seems to be
more of it to go around.</p>
<p>However&hellip; A part of the vacuum left by TwiFRaF was being sneakily filled by
YouTube recommender riding.</p>
<p>You know, load the YouTube main page, SEE ALL THOSE SUPER INTERESTING RANDOM
CLIPS WHICH THE YOUTUBE AI <em>KNOWS</em> WILL GET YOU (in my case movie trailers,
movie reviews and analyses, comics, <a href="https://youtu.be/T_rDA-7E_ys">running</a>,
HOW TO GET CHISELED (no idea how that got in there), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/SaturdayNightLive">Saturday Night Live
clips</a>, running really terribly
far, some programming or computer thing) and middle-click on about five of &lsquo;em.</p>
<p>Watch the clips, reload the main page, repeat!</p>
<p>As entertaining as this was, most of it couldn&rsquo;t really count as a constructive
use of my time, and so, at the start of October, TwiFraF was summarily upgraded
to TwiFraF-Yo.</p>
<p>For the past week, I have observed a further uptick in the quantity and quality
of my focus.</p>
<h2 id="the-describers">The Describers.</h2>
<p>Thanks to an <em>excellent</em> recommendation by friend PK (he of <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/">the introducing of
the rider and the
elephant</a>, I&rsquo;m
currently reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stumbling_on_Happiness"><em>Stumbling on
Happiness</em></a> by the
Harvard psychologist Daniel Gilbert.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m only about a third of the way through, but so far this tome is filled to
the brim with knowledge about the thinking and feeling parts of the human
machine.</p>
<p>(As an aside, the topic of <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/#life-is-but-a-dream">the story I wrote in WHV #174 which no-one
noticed</a>,
you know the one about your experience of reality being mostly synthesised and
hallucinated in real-time, was discussed at length by Gilbert (the topic, not
my story of course). According to Gilbert, this is what the philosopher
Immanuel Kant introduced into the world under the label <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transcendental_idealism">(Transcendental)
Idealism</a>. Knowing this,
I feel like slightly less of a barbarian now.)</p>
<p>What I would like to focus on here though, is <em>The Describers</em>.</p>
<p>Gilbert talks about their research on <em>focalism</em>, the human tendency to place
too much weight on one piece of information when making a prediction or a
decision.</p>
<p>In <a href="http://people.virginia.edu/~tdw/wilson,focalism.pdf">their 2000 paper</a>,
they discuss an experiment where they compared two groups of college students
(psychology research, also the important parts, is positively riddled with
experiments on college students) with regard to their ability to predict the
future emotional impact of a negative event, in this case, losing some
important (just run with it, please) football match to some rival college.</p>
<p>The difference between the two groups is that they asked the one group, which
they named <em>The Describers</em> (capitals and emphasis mine, I like all of the
story-telling possibilities), to describe the events of a typical day (see p823
in the paper, this was a structured questionnaire), <em>before</em> predicting the
impact of that future negative event.</p>
<p>In the end, the non-describers over-estimated the impact of the loss on their
happiness, whilst the describers predicted much more accurately.</p>
<p>Although the main reason I&rsquo;m writing about this here is that I&rsquo;ve really taken
a liking to the name <em>The Describers</em>, it will not have escaped you, astute
readers, that this is yet another convoluted reason <a href="/tags/note-taking/"><em>to write stuff
down</em></a>.</p>
<p>If the research above can be believed, and here I have to divulge that my life
(debating) partner is still highly sceptical, journalling could contribute
positively to the quality of your prediction and decision-making.</p>
<p>At the very least, the hypothesis that taking the time to re-process and
document one&rsquo;s thoughts, observations and reasoning could contribute positively
to one&rsquo;s judgement seems eminently plausible to me.</p>
<h2 id="ensembleyoutm">EnsembleYou(tm).</h2>
<p>In machine learning, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ensemble_learning">ensemble
methods</a> combine multiple
different classifiers or algorithms, which in many cases comes down to simply
averaging their output predictions, in order to obtain better accuracy than any
of the constituent classifiers.</p>
<p>As I was chatting with a mathematical friend from work the other day, I rambled
on and on (sorry mathematical friend) right into the idea of EnsembleYou(tm).</p>
<p>It was actualy the unsurprising admission that the in-the-moment me is really
not very good at predictions, decisions or anything else.</p>
<p>However, continuously writing everything down is one practical way of averaging
out the observations and decisions of a whole bunch of instantaneous mes, or
yous.</p>
<p>(More specifically, this was about the fact that the &ldquo;Vitals&rdquo; section of <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#monthly-journal-files">my
monthly journal
files</a>,
containing lists of reminders for a good life, is copied from month to month,
evolving slowly as I add, remove and incrementally improve its contents.)</p>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through
time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less
faulty entity.</p>
<p>I am calling this specific composite entity EnsembleCharl, but because I would
like to give the <em>idea</em> to you, <em>that</em> will go through life as EnsembleYou(tm)!</p>
<h2 id="friendly-wishes">Friendly Wishes.</h2>
<p>Friends(es), I wish you effortless connectivity, and great wisdom in your
multiplicity.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>