<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Twifraf on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/twifraf/</link><description>Recent content in Twifraf on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 16:25:48 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/twifraf/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2021 to 2022 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.
I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to 2014 (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and 2015 (no real excuse).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition
post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_43b7cf87c31b21c0.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_fc6e5e937f90c6a9.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_12a18d122cde4000.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_5b0c7558e9575.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_fc6e5e937f90c6a9.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to
<a href="/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/">2014</a> (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and <a href="/2015/01/21/weekly-head-voices-88-just-be-yourself-they-said/">2015</a> (no real
excuse).</p>
<p><em>Much later, on Sunday January 23:</em> It could very well still win the Most
Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Emacs and <code>M-x count-words</code> (on a temporary buffer copied over from <a href="/archive/#2021">the 2021
blog post archive</a>) tells me that I published 28 posts on this blog, and 8
technical posts over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>Just like with the running below, but for different reasons, I lost a lot of
steam during the last few months of the year.</p>
<p>In a truly surprise twist, in 2022 I will again attempt to write regularly, and
to write more, and to keep it up until the end.</p>
<h3 id="stats-addendum">Stats addendum</h3>
<p>Applying the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess log analyzer</a> to this blog&rsquo;s log files with the following
invocation:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0550ae">(</span><span style="color:#cf222e">for</span> i in <span style="color:#0550ae">{</span>2..13..1<span style="color:#0550ae">}</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">do</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> cpbotha.net.access.log.<span style="color:#953800">$i</span>.gz<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">done</span><span style="color:#0550ae">)</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> xargs zcat -f -- <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format<span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; tells me that in 2021 cpbotha.net welcomed over 115000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>The same tool reports that <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a> clocked in at just under 165000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>Even if the real number of actual human visits is a quarter of what the tool is
reporting, I am ecstatic!</p>
<p>The three most popular cpbotha.net posts based on hits during 2021 were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">Dear USA, my data has left your building</a></li>
<li><a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">Note-taking strategy 2019</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>Thanks to Strava&rsquo;s handy training calendar shown below, we can see that I spent
125 hours last year (mostly, about 4 hours was spent on hiking just over 20km)
running a bit over 1300km.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_d8797d3ae69f2074.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_bcb23928a764c751.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_71b26fe22f2669f7.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_fd426be487962b7e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_bcb23928a764c751.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can also see quite clearly that I lost steam in November and especially in
December.</p>
<p>This was initially due to work getting quite busy, and then later in December a
bout with Omicron (highly probably) and also less than run-friendly weather in
St. Francis.</p>
<p>I am always happy when I manage to average 100km or more per month, and I&rsquo;ll
probably try to do that again in 2022.</p>
<h3 id="possibly-tmi-read-on-at-your-own-risk">Possibly TMI, read on at your own risk</h3>
<p>Those of you who know me, will also know about my giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunion">bunion</a>, or hallux
valgus as it prefers to be called.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated." width="240px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyways, Mr Valgus is unfortunately playing an increasingly frequent role in my
attempts at running, often starting to complain at N kilometres where N is
fortunately still higher than most of my attempts, but still affecting a
worrying number of them.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to push on, until Mr Valgus overstays its welcome, at which point
it will be time to explore invasive corrective procedures.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Probably my most redeeming habit of them all, is reading books every night in
bed until I fall asleep.</p>
<p>Even if the day has been less than satisfactory, ending it with an entirely
deliberate and focused reading session tends to make up for quite a lot.</p>
<p>Although I was planning to do more book summaries in 2021, I managed to
complete only one. At least it was a good one, namely <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Seven
and a Half Lessons About the Brain&rdquo; by Lisa Feldman Barrett</a>, which I can
strongly recommend if you have not checked it out yet.</p>
<p>Thanks to strong contenders like the one above, the competition was fierce, but
in the end the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em> could go to nothing other
than Oliver Burkeman&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08FGV64B1/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</em></a>.</p>
<p>Burkeman, he of the <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">importance of being able to put <em>down</em> your work</a> and of <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">more
appearances on this blog</a>, has created a beautifully written ode to our terribly
limited lifespans (4000 weeks if you&rsquo;re lucky, you can almost hear them ticking
away&hellip;), and to our terribly limited capacity to make the most of the time
that we do get, and to really just giving up the fight to <em>get everything done</em>,
because we will never ever win the battle against the law of perpetually
filling inboxes of various kinds, and because it&rsquo;s so much better to simply
<em>disconnect</em> from the firehose (which we can&rsquo;t get rid of completely) in order to
spend time on no-excuses leisure, and especially on our loved ones.</p>
<p>My favourite fiction book by far was <em>The Anomaly</em> by Hervé le Tellier, as
translated by Adriana Hunter.</p>
<p>After having just grudgingly finished Elizabeth Bear&rsquo;s Ancestral Night (first
novel in the White Space series; some interesting ideas, but just too pulpy,
clumsy and exposition-rich for my taste, in spite of space opera being a guilty
pleasure&hellip;), the light literariness and French cynicism of The Anomaly was a
<em>delightful</em> and refreshing breeze that I was unable to put down until it was
done.</p>
<p>In 2022, I&rsquo;m planning to read more than in 2021, and publish more of those
summaries.</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#mindfulness">daily meditation streak that started in 2020</a> continued for most of 2021,
until the end-of-year school vacation started. I am not yet sure how I&rsquo;ll be
able to fit this into my new 2022 work-routine.</p>
<h2 id="worst-habit-of-2021">Worst habit of 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV Award for Worst Habit of 2021 By Far goes, without a doubt, to my old
friend TwiFRaF-Yo, although this time around the main culprits were Twitter,
Reddit and YouTube.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know exactly when I fell out of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">the previous social media fast</a>, but I
fell out with a vengeance.</p>
<p>Although I subscribe almost entirely to technical communities on reddit (Emacs,
Orgmode, Org-roam, keyboards, etc.), there are enough of them to keep a person
busy.</p>
<p>If you add to that my twitter feed, where I&rsquo;ve also taken care to remove the
noise, subscribing largerly to high-signal science-, technology- , and
engineering-related feeds, there&rsquo;s a great deal of valuable-seeming information
that one feels compelled to get through every day&hellip;</p>
<p>(It feels like I&rsquo;ve told this story before&hellip;)</p>
<p>Anyways, every time I manage to disconnect (it&rsquo;s been a few weeks now, I think
Monday January 3 was the official start date of the current fast), only then am
I able to recognise (where by &ldquo;recognise&rdquo;, I mean that friends say this to me,
and this is when I&rsquo;m able to admit that they&rsquo;re right) that the net value for
me is highly probably negative.</p>
<p>While there is certainly valuable information that enters via those streams, it
costs so much attention and emotional energy that it&rsquo;s not really worth it.</p>
<p>So.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m back on the no-social-media cart until next time.</p>
<p>Just like the previous time, I&rsquo;m limiting myself to the brilliant Inoreader RSS
subscription service (which I pay for) to keep up to date with 99% long-form
blogs, and two Twitter accounts that are worth too much to me to disconnect
from (<a href="https://twitter.com/erictopol">Eric Topol</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/alper">Alper Çuğun-Gscheidel</a>).</p>
<p>Although I sometimes think this makes me slower, because I don&rsquo;t have all of
the current happenings at my fingertips all the time, I&rsquo;m hoping this gives me
more space and time for reading, thinking and writing.</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">Systems and tools for running this human (PKM baby)</h2>
<p>In the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">2018 to 2019 transition post</a> I mentioned the &ldquo;The System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This time, for this section, I would like to limit it to tools for knowledge
management and task management (this is not my favourite term, but I&rsquo;m erring
on the side of familiarity here) .</p>
<p>All of Emacs and Orgmode and Org-roam is still going strong, although I waver
quite a bit sometimes when I see some of the shiny new things, like <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>,
which I would probably be using if it wasn&rsquo;t for Emacs.</p>
<p>However, when I sometimes dive into my notes, I can see the difference it makes
when you stick to a single tool for longer than a few years. The amount of
knowledge keeps on growing, and I am slowly getting better at linking it all
together and&hellip;  sometimes even using it.</p>
<p>The picture below shows the graph created, by the <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> package, of a
sub-section of my notes network:</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_d1209fe41888514f.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_31ce23bcfd961e9f.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_950ec103a8bb11b5.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_df618e90e2d265e3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_31ce23bcfd961e9f.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Before I got side-tracked by the pretty picture, I was planning to dedicate
this section to a new WHV award, namely the Award for the Most Unexpectedly
Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021.</p>
<p>This year the award goes to&hellip; <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper/guide">Dropbox Paper</a>!</p>
<p>Back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">WHV #233</a> I listed many of the reasons why. In the few months since then
it has become only more useful to me as the go-to mobile tool for checklists
(especially useful when we go on trips), lists of books, movies and music
recommended by people in person, and so on.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualifier features, such as its markdown DNA and its
usability on mobile for idea capturing, the fact that Paper documents show up
in Dropbox searches, which is how I usually search when I <span class="underline">really</span> need to find a
specific file (versus ripgrep searches in Orgmode), is the deal maker.</p>
<p>(My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">strange scheme for continuously converting all org files to docx</a> for
searching and reading on the iPhone is also still going strong.)</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I had a piece written here with more details about what exactly was happening
at work, but I decided to nuke that and instead keep it more personal by
mentioning that thanks to great big dollops of serendipity and people, I find
myself, with a number of levers at my disposal, right in the middle of an
organization which, after a few months of reconfiguration and preparation, has
embarked on a genuinely exciting, and importantly more unified, course.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not mention the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">discomfort and stress</a> I was
experiencing at the start of the current personal phase, most probably due to
trying to adapt quickly to my new circumstances and responsibilities.</p>
<p>In the time since then, my stress levels have returned to more acceptable
levels, but expectations remain high.</p>
<h2 id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<p>One of the most positive changes I made in the past year, was to put more
effort into making regular and active (virtual) contact with friends whom I
don&rsquo;t see in person regularly enough.</p>
<p>THANKS INTERNET YOU DA BEST.</p>
<p>This year, I want to try harder to do more of that.</p>
<p>More generally, I made a note (yes, again, one has to keep doing this until the
end) to celebrate any of my peeps and our relationships whenever there&rsquo;s a
chance.</p>
<p>Secret message for my innner INNER circle: You are my energy and my joy, I am
here to be yours.</p>
<p>Whatever else happens, these precious relationships are all we have.</p>
<h2 id="even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">Even more plans for 2022: Continue trying</h2>
<p>First off, I would really like to get this blog post here done and
published. (it wants to be too much, or rather I want it to be too much, and so
we sit here staring at each other instead of just getting on with it so I can
try again to write a good post for once)</p>
<p>Second, EAZ is back on, since Monday January 10. EAZ means no alcohol until at
least February 10. As has been the case previously, my sleep quality is
subjectively better, and it seems like my energy levels are more consistent
throughout the week.</p>
<p>I just looked back at last year&rsquo;s transition post, and especially at the <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">final
sections, including the neatly documented Life Systems 2021</a>. That guy
(<a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">apparently we share only about 2% of our atoms</a>) really seemed to have his
stuff together, on paper at the very least.</p>
<p>As I write this (22:38 on Saturday, January 22), I have just realised that <em>this</em>
&ldquo;I&rdquo; definitely needs to spend some more time thinking about &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo; (The WHV
approach to life, the universe and everything, the one with the pillars (love
and science, that&rsquo;s the easy and reliable bit) and the rules) and specifically
if and how to revise the daily life direction clusters.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll have it on your desk by Monday.</p>
<p>Until then, the one thing I&rsquo;m sure about, is that I wish you and your loved
ones the best 2022 possible.</p>










<figure><a href="stormsriver-mouth.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_9489d85cd70e5f2e.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_ebadf81992f9fe5e.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_f4dbd9f895343922.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_cfb4aaba0c7a1dbd.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_ebadf81992f9fe5e.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #202: I don't even have to miss Dr Topol!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 22:16:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/</guid><description>Welcome everyone to this, the two hundred and second edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 27 to Sunday August 9 of the year of our simulation-running overlords 2020.
Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome everyone to this, the two hundred and second edition of the Weekly Head
Voices, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 27 to Sunday August 9 of
the year of our simulation-running overlords 2020.</p>










<figure><a href="closeup_prot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_d89573766f676725.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_993a91b5290b8eed.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_464ae933d5fcdd43.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_3e99996eb6e88668.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_993a91b5290b8eed.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="shape-up-stop-running-in-circles-and-ship-work-that-matters">Shape Up: Stop Running in Circles and Ship Work that Matters</h2>
<p>After it having spent a few quality months in my to-do list, I finally got
around to reading <a href="https://basecamp.com/shapeup">the Shape Up book by Ryan Singer</a>.</p>
<p>(You can too, by clicking on that link, it&rsquo;s free!)</p>
<p>This book documents the development methodology that the folks over at
37signals, also the original makers of <a href="https://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a>, <a href="https://basecamp.com/">Basecamp</a>, and most
recently the new email re-imagining <a href="https://hey.com/">HEY</a>, have evolved over the years.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not currently using any of those artifacts, but RoR has made (and is
probably still making) a significant impact on the technology landscape, and
the other products are truly impressive in their own right.</p>
<p>My point is, the 37signals company ships high-impact products like it&rsquo;s
nobody&rsquo;s business, so one should probably pay attention if they are willing to
explain to the rest of us how they are able to perform this feat so
consistently.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re involved in software development, or are interested, then this
compact book is worth your time.</p>
<p>However, until you can get around to it, I present to you the book&rsquo;s own
bullet-list summary (you&rsquo;ll find it in the conclusions chapter), where I&rsquo;ve
embellished each bullet with my from-memory explanation.</p>
<dl>
<dt>Shaped versus unshaped work</dt>
<dd>In Shape Up, each project is a user-visible
feature that can be done in 6 weeks or less. Senior devs in the company
<em>shape</em> the work, which means that they derisk and write down enough to
delineate the work, to specify the parameters, but not so much that it has
been pinned down. The team that gets the project assigned is given free reign
as to <em>how</em> exactly they fill in the space delineated by the shaping.</dd>
<dt>Setting appetites instead of estimates</dt>
<dd>Instead of specifying a feature,
and then estimating how much time it will take (feature first, number
second), Shape Up suggests rather determining at management level how much
appetite / motivation there is for a feature, up to a maximum of 6 weeks,
knowing that the feature will be <em>hammered</em> down to fit into the appetite for
it (number first, feature second).</dd>
<dt>Designing at the right level of abstraction</dt>
<dd>As mentioned above, the
shaping process has to reach the Goldilocks level somewhere between abstract
and concrete. Enough detail so there are no surprises that could risk the
success of the project, but little enough so that the team has the freedom to
construct a solution independently and in a more data-driven fashion.</dd>
<dt>Concepting with breadboards and fat marker sketches</dt>
<dd>These are practical
tricks to keep the detail level under control. For example, during shaping, a
<strong>fat marker</strong> is used to draw UI ideas to prevent the shapers from inking in
too much detail.</dd>
<dt>Making bets with a capped downside (the circuit breaker) and honoring uninterrupted time</dt>
<dd>This
is pretty hardcore. If a project runs over its time (e.g. 6 weeks), it is
cancelled, that is, moth-balled. End of story. As a corollary, teams are not
to be interrupted during their project cycle.</dd>
<dt>Choosing the right cycle length (six weeks)</dt>
<dd>Six weeks is the maximum time
a team will get to finish a feature. This seems to be the sweet spot for
features that are significant enough to be interesting, but don&rsquo;t get too big
to manage.</dd>
<dt>A cool-down period between cycles</dt>
<dd>After every six week cycle, all teams
get two weeks of cool-down time. This is to be used for fixing bugs, writing
tests, doing spikes, and just generally recovering from the feature
development cycle.</dd>
<dt>Breaking projects apart into scopes</dt>
<dd>As a team works on a certain feature,
the sub-tasks that they formulate as they work, can be naturally grouped into
thematic scopes. It&rsquo;s important that these emergent groupings are closely
monitored and updated. They are useful for understanding the feature, and for
reporting on progress.</dd>
<dt>Downhill versus uphill work and communicating about unknowns</dt>
<dd>The team
gives <em>asynchronous</em> feedback on project progress by plotting each scope on a
<a href="https://basecamp.com/features/hill-charts">hill chart</a>. To me this is yet another interesting and useful concept from the
book. If a scope is somewhere on the uphill part, there are still unknowns
that have to be investigated. Once the team thinks there are no more
unknowns, a scope can be moved past the top and somewhere onto the downhill
section.</dd>
<dt>Scope hammering to separate must-haves from nice-to-haves</dt>
<dd>In this case,
scope is used in the more traditional software development sense, and scope
hammering refers to the action of whittling down features until a project
fits into the time allotted to it.</dd>
</dl>
<p>At work, we are currently experimenting with elements of this methodology for a
new product we&rsquo;re working on. I&rsquo;m curious to see how much of this will work in
our setup. It sure looks good on paper!</p>
<p>(The book impressed me further with its chapter containing practical advice on
how to implement various levels of Shape Up in organizations of various types
and sizes. Super pragmatic!)</p>
<h2 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion Effect</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently reading the organizational psychologist Adam Grant&rsquo;s book <a href="https://www.adamgrant.net/give-and-take">Give
and Take</a>.</p>
<p>In this book he describes the classic study led by Harvard psychologist Robert
Rosenthal, where he told the teachers of 18 different classrooms that 20
percent of their children had scored high on a Harvard aptitude test, when in
fact they had been randomly chosen.</p>
<p>In spite of being <em>randomly chosen</em>, those children showed consistently higher
performance than their peers, even when they were measured years later.</p>
<p>From Grant&rsquo;s book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Harvard test was discerning: when the students took the cognitive ability
test a year later, the bloomers [the randomly selected kids, ed.] improved more
than the rest of the students. The bloomers gained an average of twelve IQ
points, compared with average gains of only eight points for their
classmates. The bloomers outgained their peers by roughly fifteen IQ points in
first grade and ten IQ points in second grade. Two years later, the bloomers
were still outgaining their classmates. The intelligence test was successful in
identifying high-potential students: the bloomers got smarter &ndash; and at a faster
rate than their classmates</p>
</blockquote>
<p>and then a paragraph or two later:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Teachers&rsquo; beliefs created self-fulfilling prophecies. When teachers believed
their students were bloomers, they set high expectations for their success. As
a result, the teachers engaged in more supportive behaviors that boosted the
students&rsquo; confidence and enhanced their learning and development. Teachers
communicated more warmly to the bloomers, gave them more challenging
assignments, called on them more often, and provided them with more
feedback. Many experiments have replicated these effects, showing that teacher
expectations are especially important for improving the grades and intelligence
test scores of low-achieving students and members of stigmatized minority
groups.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just to reiterate: These kids were randomly selected, but just because their
teachers <em>thought</em> that they had scored higher on an aptitude test and hence
treated them differently, they started and then kept out-performing their peers
for years.</p>
<p>Grant writes that similar experiments have been successfully performed in different
learning contexts, and the results were always the same.</p>
<p>This really blows my mind folks. I hope I can keep this knowledge close.</p>
<h2 id="yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">Yet another social media fast because you have to keep on doing them</h2>
<p><a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">The Great Social Media Fast of 2019</a> really was great when it started, but it
unfortunately fizzled out a few months later, probably when the end-of-the-year
vacation started.</p>
<p>When COVID-19 hit, I had such a need for up-to-the-minute news that my phone
soon had twitter almost permanently on position #1 of the app suggestions you
get when you swipe down.</p>
<p>Fast-forward another few months, and I was again stuck in TwiFRaF-Yo like it
was nobody&rsquo;s business.</p>
<p>Anyways, this weekend I had some serious discussions with myself, during which
I <em>again</em> had to convince myself that the select few jewels of Twitter (Dr
Topol, I salute you) and the rest of TwiFRaF-Yo did not even come close to
justifying the amount of mental cycles I was spending.</p>
<p>Fortunately I won that debate, and so now I&rsquo;m again officially on a social
media fast, during which I have resolved to read more books, blogs and other
long-form content, and to write more notes and blogs.</p>
<p>My brain already feels substantially more roomy and relaxed than it did a mere
day ago.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I didn&rsquo;t mention one of my favourite College Humor skits
in this context:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315"
src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/md4kM9AKjHs" frameborder="0"
allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
allowfullscreen></iframe>
<h3 id="a-not-quite-satisfactory-solution-for-not-having-to-miss-dr-topol">A not quite satisfactory solution for not having to miss Dr Topol</h3>
<p>Dr Topol did briefly complicate my temporary exit.</p>
<p>How was I going to keep up to date with his twitter stream without using the
twitter app and getting sucked in?</p>
<p>Unfortunately, my inoreader &ldquo;supporter&rdquo; subscription does not include its
social media subscription function that does exactly what I need, and the
upgrade is $50 per year instead of my current $20.</p>
<p>While I think about this, I&rsquo;ve activated <a href="https://ifttt.com/applets/xcHFiVvR-get-an-email-when-there-s-a-new-tweet-from-a-specific-username">the IFTTT twitter to email thingy</a>.</p>
<p>This sends me an email for <em>each</em> tweet, which constitutes a whole new problem
in itself.</p>
<h3 id="inoreader-satisfaction-with-a-side-of-retail-therapy">Inoreader satisfaction with a side of retail therapy</h3>
<p><em>&hellip; 8 hours pass after this post was published &hellip;</em></p>
<p>Narrator: <em>It became a whole new problem in itself.</em></p>
<p>Dr Topol can&rsquo;t stop tweeting admittedly truly interesting health- and
covid-related research, but the format of one email per tweet is indeed not
going to cut it.</p>
<p>I have deactivated that IFTTT thingy, and upgraded my inoreader subscription to
pro.</p>
<p>This is where I read all my blog subscriptions when I make time for that, so
having Dr Topol&rsquo;s feed there as well makes a great deal more sense.</p>
<h2 id="an-ai-to-fall-in-love--with">An AI to fall in love (with)</h2>
<p><a href="https://lexfridman.com/">Lex Fridman</a> is another of the internet&rsquo;s jewels, who is fortunately accessible
via long-form podcast.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://lexfridman.com/matt-botvinick/">episode #106</a>, he talks with <a href="https://hai.stanford.edu/people/matthew-botvinick">Prof. Matt Botvinick</a>, a brilliant
neuro-scientist who also employs AI in his research, and clearly likes to think
deeply about deep questions.</p>
<p>One of the things I (and apparently many of his interviewees) love about Dr
Fridman, is the left-field questions he often poses.</p>
<p>He does this with Botvinick:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But let me ask the over-romanticized question: Do you think we&rsquo;ll ever engineer
an AGI system that we humans would be able to love and that would love us back?
So have that level and depth of connection?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Goodness, so many layers.</p>
<p>What do you think?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #180: EnsembleYou and The Describers.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 22:08:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/</guid><description> Dear friends,
Welcome to this, the 180th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I perform retrospection on the week from Monday September 30 to Sunday October 6, 2019.
To be more specific, this is mostly indirect retrospection, meaning that I think about and attempt to describe the thoughts I had about topics and events that might or might not have occurred in the period of time that this post is ostensibly looking back on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="vergelegen_running_shot.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_5bcfc02c2265e1df.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_4c46c4ed0b003324.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_b5c11d35c063a837.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_9f8c2d4bb52b3f6.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_4c46c4ed0b003324.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>Welcome to this, the 180th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I
perform retrospection on the week from Monday September 30 to Sunday October 6,
2019.</p>
<p>To be more specific, this is mostly indirect retrospection, meaning that I
think about and attempt to describe the thoughts I had about topics and events
that might or might not have occurred in the period of time that this post is
ostensibly looking back on.</p>
<h2 id="twifraf-progress-report">TwiFRaF progress report.</h2>
<p>Almost a month ago, all the way back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">WHV
#177</a>,
I announced that I would be cutting out TwiFRaF (Twitter, Facebook, Reddit and
Friends) from my information diet.</p>
<p>This has been going quite well.</p>
<p>Subjectively, I&rsquo;ve been spending substantially more time on more constructive
activities. Also important, my work-day focus has improved; there seems to be
more of it to go around.</p>
<p>However&hellip; A part of the vacuum left by TwiFRaF was being sneakily filled by
YouTube recommender riding.</p>
<p>You know, load the YouTube main page, SEE ALL THOSE SUPER INTERESTING RANDOM
CLIPS WHICH THE YOUTUBE AI <em>KNOWS</em> WILL GET YOU (in my case movie trailers,
movie reviews and analyses, comics, <a href="https://youtu.be/T_rDA-7E_ys">running</a>,
HOW TO GET CHISELED (no idea how that got in there), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/SaturdayNightLive">Saturday Night Live
clips</a>, running really terribly
far, some programming or computer thing) and middle-click on about five of &rsquo;em.</p>
<p>Watch the clips, reload the main page, repeat!</p>
<p>As entertaining as this was, most of it couldn&rsquo;t really count as a constructive
use of my time, and so, at the start of October, TwiFraF was summarily upgraded
to TwiFraF-Yo.</p>
<p>For the past week, I have observed a further uptick in the quantity and quality
of my focus.</p>
<h2 id="the-describers">The Describers.</h2>
<p>Thanks to an <em>excellent</em> recommendation by friend PK (he of <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/">the introducing of
the rider and the
elephant</a>, I&rsquo;m
currently reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stumbling_on_Happiness"><em>Stumbling on
Happiness</em></a> by the
Harvard psychologist Daniel Gilbert.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m only about a third of the way through, but so far this tome is filled to
the brim with knowledge about the thinking and feeling parts of the human
machine.</p>
<p>(As an aside, the topic of <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/#life-is-but-a-dream">the story I wrote in WHV #174 which no-one
noticed</a>,
you know the one about your experience of reality being mostly synthesised and
hallucinated in real-time, was discussed at length by Gilbert (the topic, not
my story of course). According to Gilbert, this is what the philosopher
Immanuel Kant introduced into the world under the label <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transcendental_idealism">(Transcendental)
Idealism</a>. Knowing this,
I feel like slightly less of a barbarian now.)</p>
<p>What I would like to focus on here though, is <em>The Describers</em>.</p>
<p>Gilbert talks about their research on <em>focalism</em>, the human tendency to place
too much weight on one piece of information when making a prediction or a
decision.</p>
<p>In <a href="http://people.virginia.edu/~tdw/wilson,focalism.pdf">their 2000 paper</a>,
they discuss an experiment where they compared two groups of college students
(psychology research, also the important parts, is positively riddled with
experiments on college students) with regard to their ability to predict the
future emotional impact of a negative event, in this case, losing some
important (just run with it, please) football match to some rival college.</p>
<p>The difference between the two groups is that they asked the one group, which
they named <em>The Describers</em> (capitals and emphasis mine, I like all of the
story-telling possibilities), to describe the events of a typical day (see p823
in the paper, this was a structured questionnaire), <em>before</em> predicting the
impact of that future negative event.</p>
<p>In the end, the non-describers over-estimated the impact of the loss on their
happiness, whilst the describers predicted much more accurately.</p>
<p>Although the main reason I&rsquo;m writing about this here is that I&rsquo;ve really taken
a liking to the name <em>The Describers</em>, it will not have escaped you, astute
readers, that this is yet another convoluted reason <a href="/tags/note-taking/"><em>to write stuff
down</em></a>.</p>
<p>If the research above can be believed, and here I have to divulge that my life
(debating) partner is still highly sceptical, journalling could contribute
positively to the quality of your prediction and decision-making.</p>
<p>At the very least, the hypothesis that taking the time to re-process and
document one&rsquo;s thoughts, observations and reasoning could contribute positively
to one&rsquo;s judgement seems eminently plausible to me.</p>
<h2 id="ensembleyoutm">EnsembleYou(tm).</h2>
<p>In machine learning, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ensemble_learning">ensemble
methods</a> combine multiple
different classifiers or algorithms, which in many cases comes down to simply
averaging their output predictions, in order to obtain better accuracy than any
of the constituent classifiers.</p>
<p>As I was chatting with a mathematical friend from work the other day, I rambled
on and on (sorry mathematical friend) right into the idea of EnsembleYou(tm).</p>
<p>It was actualy the unsurprising admission that the in-the-moment me is really
not very good at predictions, decisions or anything else.</p>
<p>However, continuously writing everything down is one practical way of averaging
out the observations and decisions of a whole bunch of instantaneous mes, or
yous.</p>
<p>(More specifically, this was about the fact that the &ldquo;Vitals&rdquo; section of <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#monthly-journal-files">my
monthly journal
files</a>,
containing lists of reminders for a good life, is copied from month to month,
evolving slowly as I add, remove and incrementally improve its contents.)</p>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through
time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less
faulty entity.</p>
<p>I am calling this specific composite entity EnsembleCharl, but because I would
like to give the <em>idea</em> to you, <em>that</em> will go through life as EnsembleYou(tm)!</p>
<h2 id="friendly-wishes">Friendly Wishes.</h2>
<p>Friends(es), I wish you effortless connectivity, and great wisdom in your
multiplicity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>