<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>review on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/categories/review/</link><description>Recent content in review on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 08:31:25 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/categories/review/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Deep Work: A welcome kick in the butt.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 08:31:25 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Based on this tweet by Enrico Bertini:
Little project I developed during the break looking back at 2016: &quot;Quantifying and Visualizing “Deep Work”&quot; https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q
&mdash; Enrico Bertini (@FILWD) January 3, 2017  &hellip; after having been successfully primed by this one some weeks ago (because locals!):
I also recommend https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf. I was skeptical, but it’s surprisingly good.
&mdash; Rian van der Merwe (@RianVDM) December 22, 2016 &hellip; I bought and then devoured Deep Work by Cal Newport in two to three sessions.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Based on this tweet by <a href="http://enrico.bertini.io/">Enrico Bertini</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Little project I developed during the break looking back at 2016: &quot;Quantifying and Visualizing “Deep Work”&quot; <a href="https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q">https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q</a></p>&mdash; Enrico Bertini (@FILWD) <a href="https://twitter.com/FILWD/status/816374094212067328?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 3, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; after having been successfully primed by this one some weeks ago (because locals!):</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I also recommend <a href="https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf">https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf</a>. I was skeptical, but it’s surprisingly good.</p>&mdash; Rian van der Merwe (@RianVDM) <a href="https://twitter.com/RianVDM/status/811955081201319936?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 22, 2016</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script
<p>&hellip; I bought and then devoured <a href="http://calnewport.com/books/deep-work/">Deep Work by Cal Newport</a> in two to three sessions.</p>
<p>As I munched through the book, I could almost physically sense the impact it was making on my thought patterns. I have since spent another Deep Work Pomodoro scanning through its pages again to make sure I did not miss anything.</p>
<p>Deep Work is at its heart Cal Newport&rsquo;s passionate argument for Deep Work in this extremely fragmented and highly connected information age. He defines Deep Work as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Professional activities performed in a state of distraction-free concentration that push your cognitive capabilities to their limit. These efforts create new value, improve your skill, and are hard to replicate.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Armed with a whole book full of stories and examples, he makes the case for eschewing <em>network tools</em> such as email, twitter, facebook, reddit, slack, whatsapp and so forth, instead dedicating as much of your time as possible to specific valuable outcomes. Yes, even after work, he makes the case for structuring your leisure activities in a similar fashion.</p>
<p>Although the book cites a number of studies, storytelling is its main persuasive tool. Whatever the case may be, I am utterly convinced.</p>
<p>I have resolved to put in a massive effort to get my Deep Work muscles back in top form.</p>
<p>I <em>knew</em> all of this stuff before. Heck, I&rsquo;ve even written on this blog about <a href="/2010/09/28/slow-e-mail-weekly-head-voices-32/">deprioritising communication to make room for important things</a>, <a href="/2010/08/08/workin-9-to-5-weekly-head-voices-28/">minimising interruptions and maximising concentration</a> and more (use the search Luke).</p>
<p>Somehow, maybe because of my transition to business, I&rsquo;ve slipped back into the illusion that you have to be connected all the time. On an average workday, I have email, two instances of slack, one instance of mattermost and whatsapp all open on my desktop, just in case I need to be reached. (To be clear, there&rsquo;s a great deal of messages that go through them every day, so it&rsquo;s not just me sitting there waiting in vain for someone, anyone, to please send me a message.)</p>
<p>Contrary to what I&rsquo;ve convinced myself of, these tools all detract significantly from my value production, both in terms of quality and throughput.</p>
<h2 id="structure-and-summary-of-the-book">Structure and summary of the book</h2>
<p>In Part 1, Newport tries to convince you of the value and necessity of Deep Work. The take-home message is that in order to excel at learning and at doing especially in the current interruption and distraction filled information age, we need unfragmented periods of distraction-free concentration, during which we push our cognition to the limit.</p>
<p>When I say it like that, it seems pretty obvious, doesn&rsquo;t it?</p>
<p>Phrased differently, the great fallacy of current times is that one can perform at one&rsquo;s best whilst being hyper-connected.</p>
<p>One can&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>Even worse, if we continue doing it this way, we&rsquo;ll start losing our ability to focus.</p>
<p>In Part 2, Newport gives high-level advice towards implementing Deep Work, packaged as the four rules of Deep Work:</p>
<ol>
<li>Work deeply: More about this further down.</li>
<li>Embrace boredom: Avoid busywork. That is, when you have a few minutes waiting in line somewhere, use the time to think instead of reaching for your smartphone.</li>
<li>Quit social media: EEEKE! Don&rsquo;t worry, it&rsquo;s slightly more complicated, but “manage social media” would not have had the same impact.)</li>
<li>Drain the shallows: Squeeze out as much as possible shallow work from your schedule. Focus work should be the default, distractions (shallow work) the exception.</li>
</ol>
<p>In terms of scheduling, rule #1 can be implemented in at least four different ways: monastic (isolate yourself almost permanently), bimodal (isolate yourself some of the time, but for significant periods, e.g. a month sabbatical), rhythmic (integrate into your schedule at set times during the day every day), journalistic (cultivate the ability to work deeply whenever you get a moment).</p>
<p>Of these, the rhythmic philosophy is probably the most practical for me and for most of the readers of this blog.</p>
<p>More practically, rule #1 (“Work Deeply”, remember?!) can be implemented using the following four disciplines:</p>
<ol>
<li>Focus on the wildly important: Make sure that you always know what the absolute most valuable thing is to work on.</li>
<li>Act on lead measures: Track your deep work by metrics that can be calculated <em>before</em> the output realises and not after, for example track your daily number of hours during which you were able to work deeply.</li>
<li>Keep a compelling scoreboard: Create some modality with which you can see clearly your daily deep work performance.</li>
<li>Create a cadence of accountability: Your daily or weekly routine should ensure that you review your work, and your deep work performance via the scoreboard for example.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="how-im-planning-to-apply-deep-work">How I&rsquo;m planning to apply Deep Work</h2>
<p>In the book Newport reiterates an important observation: We humans have limited stores of will power. These can and will get depleted through the day if we&rsquo;re not careful.</p>
<p>If it takes too much conscious effort to avoid distractions and to stay focused on the mentally taxing task at hand, our will power is depleted at some point and then our defences crumble.</p>
<p>Before you know it, you&rsquo;re stuck in that super satisfying (not) email, twitter, facebook, reddit, email, twitter, whatsapp, slack loop again.</p>
<p>An effective remedy for this is ritualization.</p>
<p>This does not mean that you have to get out the old Ouija board. Rather, it means that you should develop “routines and rituals to your working life designed to minimize the amount of your limited willpower necessary to transition into and maintain a state of unbroken concentration”.</p>
<p>Fortunately, because of a choice I made in 2013, my work already involves spending longer periods reading, thinking and programming. Now I only need to ensure that these periods are as deep as possible, which means eliminating distractions and practising as intensively as possible focusing on that One Really Important Thing.</p>
<p>I will eliminate distractions by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Using the pomodoro method (as I&rsquo;ve been doing all this time, just badly).</li>
<li>Extending the length of the 25 minute pomodoro. If I&rsquo;m in the deep work flow, I&rsquo;ll continue past the 25 minute alarm. A longer break can be taken later.</li>
<li>Activating my phone&rsquo;s no distraction mode during pomodori. Only phone calls get through, nothing else.</li>
<li>Killing my email app and all browser tabs that have to do with real-time communication (slack, mattermost, whatsapp, and so on).</li>
<li>Just in case, pasting a list of time-wasting site hostnames into my uBlock Origin&rsquo;s “My Filters” list.</li>
</ul>
<p>Besides that, I am recording deep work by prepending one of D0, D1, … D5 to the mytomatoes.com pomodoro description, corresponding to the spectrum from shallow to most deep work.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="http://www.veronikach.com/">veronikach.com</a>, I am using <a href="https://www.focusatwill.com/">focus@will</a> which helps tremendously with my concentration in the sometimes busy office.</p>
<p>Newport explains that most people can manage a maximum of four hours per day of truly deep work. Furthermore, for many people, it is most effective to schedule creative and deep work for the morning, and shallow work (email, admin, meetings etc.) for the afternoon. For a longer time I have been following the guideline of scheduling meetings for the afternoon, so now I&rsquo;ll strengthen that by trying to get my deep work done in the morning, leaving shallow work for the afternoon as far as possible.</p>
<p>Finally, I think that probably the most important advice here is to practise, practise and then practise some more.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This could very well be due to my own bias, but if I had to describe Deep Work as compactly as possible, I would have to say that it comes down to “mindful action”.</p>
<p>It might sound like a contradiction in terms (mindfulness is the practice of being, amongst other things), but I am referring to the practice of being fully connected to and focused on the current moment.</p>
<p>With Deep Work, one practises connecting fully to and focusing on the current endeavour, thus greatly enriching that experience and the output that it generates.</p>
<p>Thank you, Cal Newport, for this very welcome kick in the butt.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Review: Awei A990-BL Wireless Sport Bluetooth Earphones – Avoid!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/12/20/review-awei-a990-bl-wireless-sport-bluetooth-earphones-avoid/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 11:33:19 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/12/20/review-awei-a990-bl-wireless-sport-bluetooth-earphones-avoid/</guid><description> Due to my terrible running addiction, my recent acquisition of the Samsung Gear Fit 2 sports tracker watch, and the mechanical incompatibility of the Bluedio Ci3 earphones with my ears, I was again in the market for a new set of bluetooth earphones. (The earphones are not only to listen to MP3s on the watch, but more importantly, to hear the pacing information communicated by the watch’s terrible synthesised voice.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Due to my terrible running addiction, my recent acquisition of the Samsung Gear Fit 2 sports tracker watch, and the mechanical <a href="/2016/11/15/the-bluedio-ci3-bluetooth-earphones-will-probably-not-fit-your-ears-either/">incompatibility of the Bluedio Ci3 earphones with my ears</a>, I was again in the market for a new set of bluetooth earphones. (The earphones are not only to listen to MP3s on the watch, but more importantly, to hear the pacing information communicated by the watch’s terrible synthesised voice.)</p>
<p>After some scratching around on <a href="http://www.takealot.com/">Takealot.com</a>, our otherwise wonderful local Amazon-analogue, I settled on the Awei A990-BL Wireless Sport Bluetooth Earphones.</p>
<p>After just under a month of real-world testing of these earphones (that is, running with them a few times a week, they are “sport” earphones after all), punctuated by disappointing performance and some mechanical breakage, and culminating in complete hardware failure, I can make only this very simple recommendation:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>DO NOT under any circumstances buy the Awei A990-BL Wireless Sport Bluetooth Earphones. They have attained the rarely awarded “cpbotha.net THREE (3) thumbs down, avoid at all costs” review.</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="a-complete-set-of-accessories">A complete set of accessories</h1>
<p>I was pretty happy when the the earphones arrived on November 15, right on time, and with a pretty complete set of accessories:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/20161116_095902.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/20161116_095902-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>None of the three sets of silicone earbuds were large enough for my ears, an issue that was easily solved by using a set of my old Sennheiser buds. My last Skullkandy earphones had the same issue, so I’m ascribing it to my anatomy and not to Awei.</p>
<h1 id="ear-clips-break-easily">Ear clips break easily</h1>
<p>During the first run with these earphones in the wind (when one also really notices how the control unit, a few centimetres from one’s right ear, can really flop around), I realised that the curved ear hooks were definitely necessary. For the next few runs, I had them clipped onto the earphones and they made a huge difference keeping music in my ears.</p>
<p>However, at the start of another run, I slight re-adjustment of the hooks relative to the earphones caused both of the earbud attachment bits to break clean off, rendering these accessories completely useless. I used a reasonable amount of force, and have to conclude that these clips are just not well made:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/IMG_20161204_0809504.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/IMG_20161204_0809504-768x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<h1 id="bluetooth-transmission-hiccups">Bluetooth transmission hiccups</h1>
<p>Besides the breakage, I also noticed from the start regular little breaks in the music transmission from the Gear Fit 2 to my ears. It’s possible that these were somehow caused by the unit’s movement during my exercise. I take this opportunity to remind the reader of the “sport” classification of this Awei product.</p>
<p>It could also be that the Gear Fit 2’s bluetooth implementation is sub-par, but, unlike the Awei, it’s an a-list product. In the following weeks I will be able to test this hypothesis with alternative hardware.</p>
<h1 id="complete-hardware-failure">Complete hardware failure</h1>
<p>About 25 calendar days after purchase, the unit spontaneously died during a run, a disappointment in itself. At first I thought that it was simply the battery that was exhausted. However, no amount of charging back home could revive the earphones.</p>
<p>My Awei A990-BL earphones remain completely dead to this day.</p>
<h1 id="quo-vadis-emptor">Quo vadis emptor?</h1>
<p>After two failed attempts, first with the Bluedio Ci3 and then with these Awei headphones, I have decided to go a different route with the <a href="http://www.androidcentral.com/hands-samsung-level-link-wireless-adapter">Samsung Level Link bluetooth adapter</a>.</p>
<p>I’ll be able to use any wired earphones (at a much better price-performance ratio, and also much easier to replace) and just plug them into the Samsung Level Link, which will connect wirelessly to the Gear Fit 2.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Bluedio Ci3 bluetooth earphones will probably not fit your ears either.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/15/the-bluedio-ci3-bluetooth-earphones-will-probably-not-fit-your-ears-either/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 12:14:45 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/15/the-bluedio-ci3-bluetooth-earphones-will-probably-not-fit-your-ears-either/</guid><description> This is just a quick warning to anyone else considering buying the Bluedio Ci3 bluetooth in-ear earphones:
Due to their size and design, the Bluedio Ci3 bluetooth in-ear earphones will probably not fit your ears.
If you’re considering to buy them, make sure that you are either able to return them if they don’t fit, or that you’re able to test them out beforehand.
To illustrate the problem, here is a photo of the the right earphone, along with the supplied silicone cover and t-light tip (the large version), with a Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboard as the background so that you can get a feeling for the size of the earphone: The Bluedio Ci3 earphones are quite big.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This is just a quick warning to anyone else considering buying the Bluedio Ci3 bluetooth in-ear earphones:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Due to their size and design, the Bluedio Ci3 bluetooth in-ear earphones will probably not fit your ears.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you’re considering to buy them, make sure that you are either able to return them if they don’t fit, or that you’re able to test them out beforehand.</p>
<p>To illustrate the problem, here is a photo of the the right earphone, along with the supplied silicone cover and t-light tip (the large version), with a Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboard as the background so that you can get a feeling for the size of the earphone:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/bluedio_ci3_earbud_size.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/bluedio_ci3_earbud_size-1024x596.jpg"
        
            alt="The Bluedio Ci3 earphones are quite big. They rely on the t-light tips to stay in your ears."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Bluedio Ci3 earphones are quite big. They rely on the t-light tips to stay in your ears.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The idea behind this design is that the so-called <em>t-light tip</em> (the wing-like bit of the silicone cover) anchors the whole mechanism in your ear, so that the spout-shaped bit in the silicone cover guides the sound into your ear-canal.</p>
<p>However, I tried all three the supplied cover sizes, but the earphones keep falling out. I am able to fit the t-light tip correctly into my ear, but the driver part is so far from my ear-canal that the music loses all form of bass and sounds incredibly tinny. Even worse, the whole earphone eventually starts to fall out due to its heaviness. (I am 1.9m, that is 6’3″, with ears to match.)</p>
<p>Looking at the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Bluedio-Ci3-Bluetooth-Headphones-Sweatproof/product-reviews/B016C1WP26/ref=cm_cr_dp_see_all_btm?ie=UTF8&amp;reviewerType=avp_only_reviews&amp;showViewpoints=1&amp;sortBy=recent">Amazon customer reviews of the Bluedio Ci3</a>, it seems I am not the only one with this problem. Let me know in the comments what your experience was.</p>
<p>(Compliments to <a href="http://www.takealot.com/">takealot.com</a> down here in South Africa, who are doing an absolutely fantastic job both with delivering goodies to your doorstop, but also with handling the odd return now and then.)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2016 20:22:04 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/</guid><description> In 2013, when it became clear, primarily through Edward Snowden&amp;rsquo;s heroic actions, that the level of snooping by the US and other governments was far greater than any of us would have thought, I moved all of my data out of the US and of course blogged about it (that blog post has been read almost 70000 times; I think for many people this is an important issue).
This included migrating 60000 emails away from my beloved GMail (I got my GMail invite from The Vogon Poet on August 24, 2004.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In 2013, when it became clear, primarily through Edward Snowden&rsquo;s heroic actions, that the level of snooping by the US and other governments was far greater than any of us would have thought, I moved all of my data out of the US and of course <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">blogged about it</a> (that blog post has been read almost 70000 times; I think for many people this is an important issue).</p>
<p>This included migrating 60000 emails away from my beloved GMail (I got my GMail invite from <a href="https://twitter.com/vogonpoet">The Vogon Poet</a> on August 24, 2004. At that time, you could only get GMail by invitation. It was pretty exciting! (I have emails from before 2004, back to &lsquo;93 or &lsquo;94, but those are in a backup archive somewhere.)) to the little <a href="https://www.engadget.com/products/synology/ds213j/">Synology DS213j</a> standing next to my desk at the time.  This was all well and good behind the stable Dutch 100 Mbit/s <em>down</em> / 10 Mbit/s <em>up</em> cable connection I had, but when we decided to move back to South Africa, where home internet is a few years behind The Netherlands, I ended up having to pay for a virtual private server in Cape Town (to keep latency between me and my mail server manageable) and having to admin my own dovecot IMAP and postfix SMTP server.</p>
<p>Initially this was workable, until the Nth time that I had to interrupt my real job (which has nothing to do with mail servers) to apply a security patch or get the VPS booting again after a botched kernel upgrade. Besides that, I had to deal with keeping my server out of over-enthusiastic spam blacklists and whatnot. Also, inspite of <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2014/06/06/configuring-emacs-mu4e-with-nullmailer-offlineimap-and-multiple-identities/">mu4e</a>, I did end up missing the fast graphical GMail web interface.</p>
<p>So, it was with a great deal of tail between my legs that on June 10, 2015 (<a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">I have a lab journal, remember</a>) I went right back back to GMail. My mail setup, although pleasingly decentralised, was costing me too much time and hence actual money.</p>
<p>Fast forward to July 15, 2016 (there&rsquo;s that lab journal again…) when, after receiving an email from Google asking me to indicate how exactly I would like them to use my data to customise adverts around the web, and after thinking for a bit about what kind of machine learning tricks I would be able to pull on you with 12 years of your email, I decided that I really had to make alternative plans for my little email empire.</p>
<p>Somehow FastMail came up and in one of those impulsive LET&rsquo;S WASTE SOME TIME manoeuvres, I pressed the big red MIGRATE button!</p>
<p>The rest of this post is my mini-review of the FastMail service after almost 3 weeks of intensive use.</p>
<h2 id="importing-mail-from-gmail">Importing mail from GMail</h2>
<p>







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-10.50.45-AM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-10.50.45-AM-1024x594.png"
        
            alt="The main import &amp;amp; export window"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The main import &amp; export window</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-11.01.46-AM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-11.01.46-AM.png"
        
            alt="IMAP migration configuration dialog"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>IMAP migration configuration dialog</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The <strong>Settings | Import &amp; Export</strong> option in FastMail was easy to setup. It knows how to authenticate with GMail, even when you make use of two-factor authentication, like I do and you probably should.</p>
<p>The import takes place via the GMail IMAP interface. It&rsquo;s important to remember that via the IMAP client, an email tagged in GMail with both <em>important</em> and <em>info</em> will appear in two different folders. Because of this, I did check the <strong>no duplicates</strong> checkbox, but still I noticed that my 15 GB FastMail evaluation mailbox was filling up more quickly than I would have expected.</p>
<p>After a support request which was responded to within minutes (bonus), I discovered the <strong>Quota Usage</strong> screen and could see that the duplicate detection did indeed not seem to work correctly during the import. Based on more tips from the support tech, I made use of the <strong>Mass delete or remove duplicates</strong> module (Settings | Folders | Scroll all the way to the bottom of the page) to delete thousands of duplicate emails during the import. This was indeed because of emails appearing in multiple IMAP folders due to their GMail tags. <em><strong>Note:</strong> Friend and reader <a href="https://twitter.com/stefanvdwalt">stefanvdwalt</a> reported the exact same mail duplication during import issue which in his case did go over quota, so do keep an eye on this!</em></p>
<p>After a day or so (during which I could email more or less normally) I received an import report from FastMail claiming that the import had been successful, except for this error:</p>
<pre>Log: Fri Jul 15 17:49:17 2016; cpbotha/imap.gmail.com; Migrating folder Inbox -&gt; Inbox
Log: Fri Jul 15 17:49:17 2016; cpbotha/imap.gmail.com; Creating local folder Inbox
Log: Fri Jul 15 17:49:17 2016; cpbotha/imap.gmail.com; Error migrating remote folder Inbox: Failed to create Inbox. IMAP Command : 'create' failed. Response was : no - Mailbox already exists</pre>
<p>The import had managed to figure out that GMail Sent should map to FastMail Sent for example, but Inbox was probably too special to map in the same way. I fixed this by firing up my trusty Thunderbird, and using IMAP to drag and drop emails from my GMail Inbox to my shiny new FastMail Inbox.</p>
<p>In retrospect, I should have selected <strong>Create under new sub-folder</strong> in the IMAP migration configuration instead of <strong>Merge into existing folders</strong>. I discovered later that <strong>moving thousands of emails to a different folder is near instantaneous</strong> in the FastMail web-app.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-like">What I like</h2>
<h3 id="webmail-speed">Webmail speed</h3>
<p>I live more or less at the southern tip of the African continent. My lowest latency connection with the rest of the internet is via undersea optic cable to Europe (about 140ms ping).</p>
<p>The FastMail web servers are in the USA, which is, as the ping flies, much further away. I was not expecting much from the webmail, but colour me surprised when I discovered that this felt subjectively <em>faster</em> than GMail (who have servers everywhere, even down here). Things remained snappy, even with all 50000 of my conversations imported.</p>
<p>As far as I can figure out, it seems that much of this is due to FastMail&rsquo;s self-designed but open source IMAP-replacement called <a href="http://jmap.io/">JMAP</a>. JMAP has been designed for low latency, and for improved battery life. What it does differently, is batch requests together, and it also has optimisations specifically for interactive webmail.</p>
<p>The web-app has full support for keyboard shortcuts, which increases the subjective perception of speed.</p>
<h3 id="webmail-search">Webmail search</h3>
<p>For my purposes, search in FastMail is on par with that of GMail. I can dig up any of my emails, back up to 2004, in seconds.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-11.18.06-AM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-11.18.06-AM.png"
        
            alt="FastMail advanced search interface"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>FastMail advanced search interface</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s also very useful, is that you can turn any search into a virtual folder.</p>
<h3 id="tech-support">Tech support</h3>
<p>This is one area where Google really can&rsquo;t hold a candle to FastMail. If something goes wrong with your gmail account (this hardly ever happens, but it&rsquo;s possible) it&rsquo;s almost impossible to get hold of any kind of official tech support. Here&rsquo;s <a href="https://medium.com/@xdvl/stop-using-gmail-com-for-things-you-care-about-14af40e43a88#.h5ljyewg7">a recent story</a> where a GMail user&rsquo;s account was summarily terminated. There <em>was</em> probably some kind of ToS infringment, but the user has no idea what or why, and has lost all access to their emails and contacts database.</p>
<p>So far I&rsquo;ve contacted FastMail tech support twice: Once during my email migration, and once to confirm the absence of the “quote selected text in reply” feature (discussed below). In both cases, I was helped by real humans who responded very quickly and courteously to my support requests.</p>
<h3 id="email-and-contacts-and-calendar-out-of-googles-view">Email and contacts (and calendar) out of Google&rsquo;s view</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m still of the opinion that Google makes fantastic and valuable products. However, with all of their data mining know-how and resources, one has to decide how much of one&rsquo;s personal information one is willing to trade in for the use of these fantastic products.</p>
<p>With FastMail, I have been able to extricate my significant email archive (2004 to 2016, 50000 conversations) as well as my contacts database. I&rsquo;m still making use of Google Calendar, because of bunches of sharing going on with family members, but I have the option of moving that out also.</p>
<p>By the way, the FastMail Calendar web interface is more than capable (and pretty enough) to replace Google&rsquo;s version.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-dont-like">What I don&rsquo;t like</h2>
<h3 id="missing-integrations-todoist">Missing integrations: Todoist</h3>
<p>GMail, being as popular as it is, has tonnes of integrations with other apps. In my case, I will really miss the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/todoist-for-gmail/clgenfnodoocmhnlnpknojdbjjnmecff">Todoist for Gmail extension</a>. With this, I had a mini-todoist window inside my GMail, and I could turn any email into a task at the click of a button (or the press of a shortcut).</p>
<p>Because FastMail email URLs seem to be persistent, I use the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/todoist-to-do-list-and-ta/jldhpllghnbhlbpcmnajkpdmadaolakh">Todoist Chrome extension&rsquo;s</a> “Add to Todoist” context menu action to add the URL and email subject as a task. This not as nice as the gmail-specific extension (the task goes immediately into the todoist inbox, without the possibility to edit metadata such as due date and tags).</p>
<h3 id="missing-feature-quote-selection-in-reply">Missing feature: Quote selection in reply</h3>
<p>In Gmail and in Thunderbird, if you select text in an incoming email and then reply, that selected text is quoted in the reply email. Unfortunately, this feature is not available in the FastMail web-app, and they have no plans to implement it.</p>
<p>I use both the FastMail web-interface as well as Thunderbird, because of its great PGP email encryption and signature support (hey, <a href="https://keybase.io/cpbotha">find me on keybase</a>, send me encrypted email!), so this issue is somewhat ameliorated. Still, it would have been nice.</p>
<h3 id="android-app-lag">Android app lag</h3>
<p>I do have <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.fastmail.app">FastMail&rsquo;s Android app</a> on my telephone. The app is a Cordova / PhoneGap / CrossWalk style unit with real-time email push and notification via Google Cloud Messaging (this is a relatively energy-efficient way for android phones to get push notification and is natively supported by FastMail).</p>
<p>However, there is a few second lag when I open the inbox, so I prefer using the pro version of <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.kman.AquaMail">AquaMail, a great Android IMAP mail client</a>. I have this set to 15 minute polling for new email, as IMAP IDLE (push, in other words) is not as battery efficient as GCM or Apple&rsquo;s email push. Opening any folder or email in AquaMail is of course instantaneous, as the emails live on the phone.</p>
<p>That being said, I use the FastMail app for searching, which is just as fast and as effective as the web-app.</p>
<p>THAT being said, FastMail really needs to implement some sort of caching in the Android app for lightning <em>fast</em> folder and email access. (The FastMail app is quite attractive, I would prefer using it more.)







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fastmail_calendar_google_play.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fastmail_calendar_google_play-1024x580.png"
        
            alt="FastMail Android app Calendar screen, from the Google Play page."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>FastMail Android app Calendar screen, from the Google Play page.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<h3 id="niggle-creating-an-email-alias--incoming-route-automatically-creates-a-new-sending-identity">Niggle: Creating an email alias / incoming route automatically creates a new sending identity</h3>
<p>FastMail can manage the DNS for any of the custom domains that you assign to it, which is super useful if you don&rsquo;t already have a DNS service.</p>
<p>I already make use of webfaction&rsquo;s DNS for all of my domains, so I chose to add DNS records to designate fastmail as the official MX for those domains. (All of this is explained clearly in the FastMail help.)</p>
<p>When you do this, you have to create an email alias for each incoming address you would like to receive mail for (you can also create a catchall, but this could result in more spam arriving in your inbox). For each and every alias, <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/help/receive/alias-catchall.html">FastMail automatically creates an outgoing (from address) identity</a>. While this is usually quite convenient, I have quite a number of incoming addresses, but I only ever send from a subset of these addresses, so the drop-down list with sending identities became quite unwieldy.</p>
<p>I deleted all of the unnecessary identities. What would help, would be if FastMail were to implement most-used-at-the-top sorting for that drop-down.</p>
<h2 id="other-noteworthy-points">Other noteworthy points</h2>
<h3 id="domain-setup">Domain setup</h3>
<p>For my most important domains, I have set FastMail to be the MX. I have also performed the necessary <a href="https://blog.fastmail.com/2014/12/09/email-authentication/">SPF and DKIM</a> setup: FastMail gives super useful feedback in its configuration screens to help you with this. For these domains, I send mail directly via the FastMail SMTP servers, and mail is delivered directly to FastMail servers. Nice and simple.







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-9.46.01-PM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-9.46.01-PM-1024x623.png"
        
            alt="Domain setup feedback screen."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Domain setup feedback screen.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>For some other email accounts I have with clients, FastMail supports POP fetch from and SMTP send via foreign servers.</p>
<h3 id="ios-push-support">iOS Push support</h3>
<p>If you use any Apple iOS devices to read your mail, you&rsquo;ll be pleased to know that FastMail, with help from the big A, <a href="https://blog.fastmail.com/2015/07/17/push-email-now-available-in-ios-mail/">fully supports iOS push</a>. This means battery efficient real-time incoming emails to make it even more difficult for you to focus on That One Really Important Thing.</p>
<h3 id="android-contact-syncing-with-carddav">Android contact syncing with CardDAV</h3>
<p>With google contacts, syncing on Android just works, and it works really well. To sync my contacts with FastMail&rsquo;s Address Book instead, I bought the pro version of the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.dmfs.carddav.Sync">CardDAV android app</a> for 24 South African Ront (that&rsquo;s about EUR 1.5). This works as a sync provider, so once setup, the process is also pretty much transparent.</p>
<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>So there you have it: A hopefully helpful story, with included mini-review, about my move from GMail to the FastMail service.</p>
<p>So far, my conclusion is that this is a service that is technically more than capable of replacing GMail, even for power users. Furthermore, FastMail&rsquo;s primary (and in fact only) business model is to charge you money for making sure that you can keep on emailing like a boss. Together, this makes for an offer that I could not refuse.</p>
<p><em>P.S. Let me know in the comments if you would like me to add anything else to this post.</em></p>
<p><em>P.P.S. You can also join the lively <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12247401">Hacker News discussion of this post</a>!</em></p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Z Launcher: A breath of fresh air in the world of Android.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/04/z-launcher-a-breath-of-fresh-air-in-the-world-of-android/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2016 12:42:43 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/04/z-launcher-a-breath-of-fresh-air-in-the-world-of-android/</guid><description> Most Android launchers are small variations on the same concept: One or more screens of widgets and icons (sometimes grouped) which can be used to start various different apps. It’s usually up to the user to place these icons on the screen, much like we’ve been doing for ages on our computer desktops.
If you too are in the mood for a more innovative take on the launcher, you could do much worse than installing Nokia’s (yes, they live!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Most Android launchers are  small variations on the same concept: One or more screens of widgets and icons (sometimes grouped) which can be used to start various different apps. It’s usually up to the user to place these icons on the screen, much like we’ve been doing for ages on our computer desktops.</p>
<p>If you too are in the mood for a more innovative take on the launcher, you could do much worse than installing Nokia’s (yes, they live!) free <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.nokia.z">Z Launcher app</a>.</p>
<p>It looks and works like this:</p>
<div class="gallery galleryid-2296 gallery-columns-3 gallery-size-medium" data-carousel-extra='{"blog_id":1,"permalink":"https:\/\/cpbotha.net\/2016\/01\/04\/z-launcher-a-breath-of-fresh-air-in-the-world-of-android\/"}' id="gallery-2">
<figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon portrait">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-2" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_start_screenie.jpg" title=""><img alt="" class="attachment-medium size-medium" data-attachment-id="2297" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":"","orientation":"1"}' data-image-title="zlauncher_start_screenie" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_start_screenie-576x1024.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_start_screenie-169x300.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_start_screenie.jpg" data-orig-size="720,1280" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/04/z-launcher-a-breath-of-fresh-air-in-the-world-of-android/zlauncher_start_screenie/" height="300" sizes="(max-width: 169px) 85vw, 169px" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_start_screenie-169x300.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_start_screenie-169x300.jpg 169w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_start_screenie-576x1024.jpg 576w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_start_screenie.jpg 720w" width="169"/></a>
</div></figure><figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon portrait">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-2" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_scribble.jpg" title=""><img alt="" class="attachment-medium size-medium" data-attachment-id="2299" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":"","orientation":"0"}' data-image-title="zlauncher_scribble" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_scribble.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_scribble-166x300.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_scribble.jpg" data-orig-size="322,583" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/04/z-launcher-a-breath-of-fresh-air-in-the-world-of-android/zlauncher_scribble/" height="300" sizes="(max-width: 166px) 85vw, 166px" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_scribble-166x300.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_scribble-166x300.jpg 166w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_scribble.jpg 322w" width="166"/></a>
</div></figure><figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon portrait">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-2" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_refine_screenie.jpg" title=""><img alt="" class="attachment-medium size-medium" data-attachment-id="2298" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":"","orientation":"1"}' data-image-title="zlauncher_refine_screenie" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_refine_screenie-576x1024.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_refine_screenie-169x300.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_refine_screenie.jpg" data-orig-size="720,1280" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/04/z-launcher-a-breath-of-fresh-air-in-the-world-of-android/zlauncher_refine_screenie/" height="300" sizes="(max-width: 169px) 85vw, 169px" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_refine_screenie-169x300.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_refine_screenie-169x300.jpg 169w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_refine_screenie-576x1024.jpg 576w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/zlauncher_refine_screenie.jpg 720w" width="169"/></a>
</div></figure>
</div>
<p>On the left is the default start screen. It shows a list of the apps I’ve most recently started, with the most used ones at the top (you can see that I was quite busy <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">using Signal</a> at that point).</p>
<p>If you would like to start some other app which is not on the current short list, or view or call a contact, simply scribble the first letter of the app or contact on the screen! In my case, I scribbled a “g” (the “p” screenshot is from the Z Launcher play store page, because I was not able to screenshot it on my own phone), at which point it listed apps and contacts with the letter “g”. Again all of the “g” apps are listed in order of how much I’d interacted with them at that point.</p>
<p>Swiping to the right gives you a traditional widget area (here I have a weather (<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=no.nrk.yr">yr.no</a> is the best, even here in South Africa) and a calendar widget), and swiping to the right gives you a traditional searchable list of all of your apps.</p>
<p>Z Launcher continuously learns about the apps and other items you interact with the most, and will always show you the ones that you interact with the most at the top. Over the past week of testing, this has saved me a significant amount of time finding and starting the phone functions I was looking for.</p>
<p>For saving me time, and doing it in an aesthetically pleasing way: <strong>5 stars for you Z Launcher!</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Nerd-alert: Ubuntu Linux 12.04 on my NVIDIA Optimus Samsung NP300V3A laptop</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/05/02/nerd-alert-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-my-nvidia-optimus-samsung-np300v3a-laptop/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 08:01:14 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/05/02/nerd-alert-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-my-nvidia-optimus-samsung-np300v3a-laptop/</guid><description> When I acquired my pre-ultrabook-era but still pretty Samsung NP300V3A laptop some nine months ago, I lamented that I’d probably never be able to put Linux on there due to the NVIDIA Optimus graphics switching thingamagoo.
Well, yesterday I ate my hat.
If you have nerdy tendencies, head on over to VXLabs, my nerd blog, to read all about it.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>When I acquired my pre-ultrabook-era but still pretty <a href="/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/" title="samsung np300v3a welcome post">Samsung NP300V3A laptop some nine months ago</a>, I lamented that I’d probably never be able to put Linux on there due to the NVIDIA Optimus graphics switching thingamagoo.</p>
<p>Well, yesterday I ate my hat.</p>
<p>If you have nerdy tendencies, head on over to VXLabs, my nerd blog, to <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2012/05/01/review-of-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-the-samsung-np300v3a-core-i5-nvidia-optimus-laptop/" title="ubuntu 12.04 on Samsung NP300V3A post on VXLabs">read all about it</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Google Drive: Not reliable yet, but potential.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/04/27/google-drive-not-reliable-yet-but-potential/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2012 20:47:56 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/04/27/google-drive-not-reliable-yet-but-potential/</guid><description> I’ve been a Dropbox Pro (50G) user for more than two years now, and in this time it has never let me down, not even by a little bit. Still, when Google announced its new Google Drive syncing service, I had to take it for a spin.
For those of you with short attention spans, my conclusion is: Google Drive has great promise due to its price-point, Google’s great infrastructure and the integration with Google Docs, but you shouldn’t yet trust this service with your critical files.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve been a Dropbox Pro (50G) user for <a href="/2010/03/29/weekly-head-voices-19-the-time-travellers-bbq/" title="me gets a dropbox pro account">more than two years now</a>, and in this time it has never let me down, not even by a little bit. Still, when Google <a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2012/04/introducing-google-drive-yes-really.html" title="google drive announcement">announced its new Google Drive syncing service</a>, I had to take it for a spin.</p>
<p>For those of you with short attention spans, my conclusion is: <em>Google Drive has great promise due to its price-point, Google’s great infrastructure and the integration with Google Docs, but you shouldn’t yet trust this service with your critical files.</em></p>
<p>To summarise: Google Drive is Google’s answer to Dropbox (and 50 other inferior syncing services). You install a small app on your Windows or Mac (no Linux yet, although <a href="http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/254488/google_drive_for_linux_is_on_the_way.html" title="Google Drive for Linux should come">it has been promised</a>), and then it’ll keep a folder of your choosing in sync with Google Drive in the cloud. You can access your files via the website <a href="http://drive.google.com/" title="google drive website">drive.google.com</a> (google docs, but slightly updated), any computer with the Google Drive software, or via the Google Drive mobile apps.  You can also share files through authorizing the relevant google accounts, or via URL. Google Drive has a number of built-in viewers, meaning that users will not have to install PowerPoint to view your PowerPoint presentation for example.</p>
<p>Things start to deviate from Dropbox when we look at the storage plans and prices the big G is offering:</p>
<p><a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_storage_plans.jpg" title=""><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-1654" data-attachment-id="1654" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":""}' data-image-title="gdrive_storage_plans" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_storage_plans.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_storage_plans-300x86.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_storage_plans.jpg" data-orig-size="744,215" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2012/04/27/google-drive-not-reliable-yet-but-potential/gdrive_storage_plans/" height="86" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_storage_plans-300x86.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_storage_plans-300x86.jpg 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_storage_plans.jpg 744w" title="gdrive_storage_plans" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>You get 5G for free. For a measly $2.49 per month, you get 25G of storage, and 30G of GMail storage as a bonus, and for $5 per month you get 100G! Compare this with the $10 / month Dropbox wants for 50G. This, together with the fact that you <em>could</em> go up to 16 TERABYTES if you would want to, makes you at least think for a bit.</p>
<p>I installed the client on this Windows laptop. For you screenshot-freaks, here’s the context menu for the systray icon:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_systray_menu.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_systray_menu.jpg"
        
            alt="Google Drive systray context menu."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Google Drive systray context menu.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Note that because I pay a measly $5 / year for 25G of extra GMail space, I’ve been <em>grandfathered</em> into 25G of Google Drive space. Heh, I also only just learnt the term grandfathered. It means I could get this because of my previous price plan that doesn’t exist anymore.</p>
<p>Here’s the preferences dialog, nothing special really, unless you have a screenshot fetish:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_prefs.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_prefs.jpg"
        
            alt="Google Drive preferences dialog."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Google Drive preferences dialog.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>For me also an important functionality: You can easily recover deleted files. If you delete a file on your client computer, it gets synced to the trash folder on the google drive website, from where undeletion is an easy click on the “Recover” button away. Under the File | Manage Revisions you can retrieve file versions up to 30 days ago, or 100 revisions, whichever comes earlier.</p>
<p>Another important difference is that Google Drive, as far as I could find out, does not do something similar to Dropbox’s LAN sync, a pretty cool function that will grab files from the computers on the local LAN if they’re available, instead of from the cloud.</p>
<p>So I set out to do some tests. Before I could really get started, I ran into the first problems. I created a text file in my Google Drive folder with Vim (yes, I use Vim. deal.), as I wanted to test the file revisions. As you know, when Vim saves a file, it first writes to a temporary file, then deletes the original file and finally renames the new file to the original file. This confused Google Drive to no end. For each save, Google Drive created a new file with exactly the same name in the web interface, whilst on the client side, there was only one file.</p>
<p>I then proceeded to delete the text file on the client, leaving me with the following situation, even after Google Drive was done syncing:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_sync_huh.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_sync_huh.jpg"
        
            alt="Huh?! You call this syncing?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Huh?! You call this syncing?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>As you can see, on the server is my text file, on the client nothing. I expect of a syncing solution to actually, uhm, synchronise my files. I did notice a sync error message in the systray context menu. After clicking, I got this dialog:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_sync_error.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/04/gdrive_sync_error.jpg"
        
            alt="Informative error message. NOT."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Informative error message. NOT.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Yes, thank you Google Drive, you have an unknown issue. That’s just great.</p>
<p>So, in spite of the really attractive offering, this type of wonkiness (multiple files due to stupid create-new-rename saves, sync errors soon after), even after a few minutes of playing around, does not instil confidence or trust. If there’s one thing a good sync service should do, it’s instil confidence and trust. Dropbox has never failed me, and I’ve thrown some pretty strange things at it. Until Google Drive is able to do the same, I’ll continue coughing up 10 bucks a month for Dropbox.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>a critical look at ubuntu feisty beta on an hp nc8430 laptop</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2007/04/10/a-critical-look-at-ubuntu-feisty-beta-on-an-hp-nc8430-laptop/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2007 14:37:41 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2007/04/10/a-critical-look-at-ubuntu-feisty-beta-on-an-hp-nc8430-laptop/</guid><description> I’ve been running Linux since 1993 (kernel 0.99-pl13 if I remember correctly) on most of my workstations and servers. I’ve had my idiot-zealot phase (“nothing but Linux is good enough”), but fortunately have left that far behind me. Now I like teasing idiot-zealots with comments about that shareware Loonix thing.
So for the past few laptops, I’ve been running Windows XP, mostly because this Just Works(tm) on modern laptop hardware. Linux really didn’t cut it when compared to XP: yes, you could install it without too much trouble, but getting 100% out of your laptop (suspend/resume, good power management, full support for modern GPUs, etc) is a different story.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve been running Linux since 1993 (kernel 0.99-pl13 if I remember correctly) on most of my workstations and servers. I’ve had my idiot-zealot phase (“nothing but Linux is good enough”), but fortunately have left that far behind me. Now I like teasing idiot-zealots with comments about that shareware Loonix thing.</p>
<p>So for the past few laptops, I’ve been running Windows XP, mostly because this Just Works(tm) on modern laptop hardware. Linux really didn’t cut it when compared to XP: yes, you could install it without too much trouble, but getting 100% out of your laptop (suspend/resume, <strong>good</strong> power management, full support for modern GPUs, etc) is a different story.</p>
<p>Because XP is getting more scary by the day (WGA things, licensing issues) and Vista promises to be even more scary (binding itself to your motherboard) and because I’ve been hearing many good things about Ubuntu Feisty (the soon-to-be-released 7.04), I decided to give this a shot on my HP NC8430 laptop (Core Duo 2GHz, ATI X1600, 2G RAM, etc.). Initially I was determined to do this like a “normal” user, i.e. no tweaking config files and especially no script writing. I wanted to see how far your average user could get with a state of the art Linux installation on a laptop.</p>
<p><strong>Installation</strong></p>
<p>This was quite impressive: I defragmented my NTFS filesystem, booted from the Ubuntu Feisty live CD and did the install. Without getting all cocky about it, the installer resized my NTFS partition, created a new EXT3 partition and installed itself. Colour me impressed.</p>
<p><strong>General configuration</strong></p>
<p>After the first boot, I was greeted with a VESA-driven x.org and an incorrect resolution. My laptop screen supports 1680 x 1050. The Gnome Preferences | Screen Resolution applet couldn’t go higher than 1280 x 1024. I had to break my first rule and edit the x.org configuration file to add the higher resolution. Why is this still necessary? A novice user shouldn’t need to have to do this!</p>
<p>I also installed the Ubuntu packaged fglrx ATI drivers with the Synaptic package management software, as I depend on good 3D graphics support for my work. The new Restricted Driver Manager helps one to complete this configuration in a user-friendly fashion.</p>
<p>By running “aticonfig –set-powerstate 1”, the GPU can be set to a lower-power mode, leading to a cooler-running laptop, meaning the fans don’t spin up as often. This command can be added to the gnome startup by adding it to System | Preferences | Sessions. With “aticonfig –lsp” one can query the available powerstates. One can only change the powerstate if a single display is active.</p>
<p>I removed “quiet” (but left “splash”) from the GRUB config for the default kernel in order to be able to see boot-up messages. These are helpful, especially when things take longer than they should.</p>
<p><strong>Wireless networking support</strong></p>
<p>This is the part that really impressed me: With Ubuntu 6.10 (Edgy Eft), I had to jump through all kinds of very user-unfriendly hoops to connect to my WPA wireless network. Feisty Beta simply popped up a pretty dialog box showing me the detected wireless networks and prompted me for the network key when I selected my WPA access point. I was online… colour me even more impressed!</p>
<p><strong>Power management</strong></p>
<p>This is when my jaw dropped ever so slightly (I’ll get to the “critical” part of this look a bit later): I selected suspend to RAM, which the laptop promptly did. When I pressed the power button to resume, I expected the typical black-screen-crashed-laptop syndrome. Instead, my desktop came back and I could continue working. This is a quantum leap in user-friendly Linux!</p>
<p>However, I soon saw that at every third resume (on average) all my <em>keyboards would be dead</em>.</p>
<p>It turns out something similar to <a href="https://launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/linux-source-2.6.20/+bug/23497" title="link to ubuntu feisty bug where keyboard is dead after resume">this bug</a> applies to my laptop. By adding the necessary suspend/resume hooks as documented in the bug report (so that the i8042 module is removed before suspend and re-installed after resume), the problem seems to have been solved.</p>
<p>Often after resume, my laptop gets stuck in the text console. I have to switch manually to X with Alt-F7. Another suspend/resume glitch is that the CPU Frequency Scaling Monitor gnome applet is stuck on 2GHz for my second core, although the core is running at half that most of the time. In general, things get a bit flaky after resume; often I need to restart X to get back to normal. I could potentially deal with this.</p>
<p>Another disappointing issue is the terrible battery life under Ubuntu Feisty. On Windows, I get more than 4 hours of battery life with average use (wireless network, web browsing, text editing). With Feisty, even after enabling LAPTOP_MODE in /etc/default/acpi-support and putting the GPU in low-power mode as explained above, I get only 2 hours and 40 minutes. This is almost a show stopper.</p>
<p>Out of the box ACPI monitoring support is well-done. With just a few clicks, I could various temperatures and fan speeds on my panel. See the panel at the top of the screen in the screenshot below:</p>
<p> </p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/cpbotha/Screenshots/photo#5051808151758926946"><img alt="" src="http://lh6.google.com/image/cpbotha/Rhugv5cDdGI/AAAAAAAAAc0/mT09SLVTKkA/s288/cpb_ubuntu_feisty_beta_20070408.jpg"/></a>
</p>
<p>This also shows the Deskbar applet in action.</p>
<p><strong>Dynamic multi-monitor support SUCKS</strong></p>
<p>My laptop has a docking station with an external LCD monitor, resolution 1280 x 1024. The laptop is 1680 x 1050, as I’ve mentioned. With Windows, (hot) docking / undocking always Just Works. It automatically activates the correct resolution without me having to configure anything. So whenever I resume, I have a working display.</p>
<p>Feisty does not quite get this yet. In fact, Feisty needs some serious clue-bat-based attention… When I dock or undock and then resume, I have no display, and no way of getting my display back, besides power-cycling the laptop at every dock / undock. I ended up writing <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/~cpbotha/thingies/aticonfig_switch.py" title="Python script to switch to NEXT display with aticonfig">this Python script</a> and binding it to Alt-F5 (for example) so that I would always have a way of activating the <em>next</em> display in the list of connected displays. Oh jeez, even assigning an arbitrary shell command to a global hot key in Gnome is not straight-forward. You have to use gconf as explained on <a href="http://www.captain.at/howto-gnome-custom-hotkey-keyboard-shortcut.php" title="binding arbitrary shell commands to global hotkeys in Gnome">this page</a>. You can query connected and enabled displays with “aticonfig –query-monitor” and activate any subset with “aticonfig –enable-monitor=name1,name2,…,nameN”.</p>
<p><strong>Desktop effects with XGL and Beryl</strong></p>
<p>Wobbly Windows, you know, these are immensely useful and result in a more productive computing experience. NOT!</p>
<p>They are really very nice though. Most of the desktop effects are more nice to look at than actually useful, except for one: The ExposÃ©-like functionality, called “Scale” by Beryl, scales and fits all windows on the current screen so that one can select the window that one wants to select easily.</p>
<p>Because fglrx doesn’t support the XComposite extension, I could not install AIGLX (Ubuntu default) and had to go for XGL and Beryl. After following <a href="http://lhansen.blogspot.com/2006/10/3d-desktop-beryl-and-xgl-on-ubuntu-edgy.html" title="beryl + xgl on ubuntu and fglrx">this guide</a> and making sure to use the external Beryl package repository as explained <a href="http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=393678" title="More tips on beryl + xgl">here</a> (the Ubuntu packages won’t work in this case, they don’t have XGL support), I got the whole shebang to work. MAN this is pretty! Check out the screenshot below for Scale in action (there are non-desktop-effect ways of doing this, e.g. kompose or skippy, but none of them are as slick as the desktop effects version):</p>
<p> </p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/cpbotha/Screenshots/photo#5051808151758926962"><img alt="" src="http://lh6.google.com/image/cpbotha/Rhugv5cDdHI/AAAAAAAAAc8/DMNDclhbAyk/s288/cpb_ubuntu_feisty_beta_scale_20070410b.jpg"/></a>
</p>
<p>As with most other things in Ubuntu, this functionality is not without its caveats. This is even more flaky with suspending and resuming: after resuming, logging out and in will give you a garbled display. I have to restart X at the GDM login screen to get XGL to work again. There are also some focus issues, especially with the Gnome Deskbar (very useful utility, by the way): pressing the hotkey activates the deskbar, but you can’t begin to type, as the current window still has the focus. I managed to fix this by setting the Beryl “Level of Focus Stealing Prevention” (under general settings) to None. Changing to a higher resolution with the “Display Resolution” applet whilst running XGL+Beryl, results in only part of the screen being usable.</p>
<p><strong>Miscellaneous issues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Palm Pilot synchronisation seems to work out of the box with my Tungsten C, but hangs forever on ToDo synchronisation. Seems it’s due to <a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/gnome-pilot-conduits/+bug/81170" title="feisty pilot todo syncing bug">this bug</a>.</li>
<li>The built-in Texas Instruments SD card reader works out of the box, but does not automount like other removable media. This is either due to the fact that it’s not seen as removable, or that the driver forgets to assign its parent bus. See <a href="http://www.nabble.com/SD-card-automounting-t2870318.html" title="mail thread wrt SD card not automounting">this mail thread</a>. I ended up applying <a href="http://www.dau-sicher.de/pmwiki/Main/CardreaderWithUdev" title="workaround for SD card thingy">this workaround</a>, involving adding rules to the udev system to pmount the SD card.</li>
<li>Gimp doesn’t understand SMB: URIs, whereas the Gnome Image Viewer does, and gthumb pretends to but doesn’t.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<p>All in all, I’m positive but not quite convinced yet. The Ubuntu people have done a marvellous job, but Feisty Beta (up to date as of 2007-04-10) doesn’t quite Just Work(tm) on the HP NC8430. I had to break my rule of editing config files or writing scripts more than once to get it to work to my satisfaction, and still there are problems that would make it difficult to work in Ubuntu full-time: the miserable battery life, the flaky suspend/resume and the really bad dynamic multi-monitor support. That being said, things like the user-friendly WPA support and the flawless install on an NTFS partition are going in the right direction.</p>
<p><strong>Updates</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>This post has been linked by OSNews! You can also follow some of the discussion <a href="http://osnews.com/comment.php?news_id=17663" title="Link to this post at OSNews.com.">over there</a>.</li>
<li>It’s also on digg (should I say that it’s been dugg?).Â  See <a href="http://digg.com/linux_unix/A_critical_look_at_Ubuntu_Feisty_beta" title="digg dugg">here</a>.</li>
<li>Fixed aticonfig lsp/lsb typo, thanks lampshade!</li>
<li>My domain has been migrated to a more stable server, some comments may have been lost in the process. If your comment has not appeared yet, <em>please</em> re-submit it.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>PS</strong></p>
<p>Please comment away, but keep it civilised. I’ll update the post as we go along, and give credit where credit’s due.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>