<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Beach on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/beach/</link><description>Recent content in Beach on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 11:19:21 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/beach/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Sunday 2023-12-24</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/31/daily-head-voices-on-sunday-2023-12-24/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 11:19:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/31/daily-head-voices-on-sunday-2023-12-24/</guid><description> Christmas Eve everyone! Just realized that my trick of setting default-dir does work for the temporary org file and output html file that ox-pandoc creates, but of course all image links will break, as they are relative to the actual location of the source org files. 😭 (this means I will have to redo everything via the temporary buffer after all) A simply brilliant late afternoon at the beach with the whole family, and even squeezed in a short barefoot run on the beach. Car battery was so much on the edge that a phone forgotten on the USB charge cable managed to push it over said edge, and so car refused to start. A minute or two before a friend arrived with jumper leads, a random kind stranger with a truck and jumper leads offered to help and did! I do need to emphasise what a sublime day this was. So much joy!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Christmas Eve everyone!</li>
<li>Just realized that my trick of setting <code>default-dir</code> does work for the temporary org file and output html file that <code>ox-pandoc</code> creates, but of course all image links will break, as they are relative to the actual location of the source org files. 😭 (this means I will have to redo everything via the temporary buffer after all)</li>
<li>A simply brilliant late afternoon at the beach with the whole family, and even squeezed in a short barefoot run on the beach.</li>
<li>Car battery was so much on the edge that a phone forgotten on the USB charge cable managed to push it over said edge, and so car refused to start. A minute or two before a friend arrived with jumper leads, a random kind stranger with a truck and jumper leads offered to help and did!</li>
<li>I do need to emphasise what a sublime day this was. So much joy!</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #163: Ons wereldjie raak baie klein.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/02/23/weekly-head-voices-163-ons-wereldjie-raak-baie-klein/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2019 11:37:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/02/23/weekly-head-voices-163-ons-wereldjie-raak-baie-klein/</guid><description> The view from a Sunday run in Onrus.
This WHV looks back at the week stretching from Monday February 11 to Sunday February 17, 2019.
I would like to share the following life bits with you:
Work: Plumbing and running. I converted our one telemedicine product from virtualenv and requirements files to pipenv. Much has been said about pipenv, also in various dramatic contexts, but there is not much competition when it comes to reproducible builds of Python applications.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/onrust_run_20190217.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/onrust_run_20190217-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from a Sunday run in Onrus."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from a Sunday run in Onrus.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This WHV looks back at the week stretching from Monday February 11 to Sunday February 17, 2019.</p>
<p>I would like to share the following life bits with you:</p>
<h2 id="work-plumbing-and-running">Work: Plumbing and running.</h2>
<p>I converted our one telemedicine product from virtualenv and requirements files to <a href="https://pipenv.readthedocs.io/en/latest/">pipenv</a>. Much has been said about pipenv, also in various dramatic contexts, but there is not much competition when it comes to reproducible builds of Python applications.</p>
<p>It’s interesting how wrapping up something relatively straight-forward like this (it’s the carpentry or plumbing parts of software engineering, one could say) can result in a fairly high level of satisfaction by the end of the work day.</p>
<p>Friday’s barefoot run on the beach was nothing short of epically enjoyable. Just a slight breeze, sun out but not too warm, goldilocks sand to run on and a ripe banana, entered into the system just before the run, contributing what felt like bundles of energy until the very end.</p>
<h2 id="weekend-reunion-in-vermont">Weekend-reunion in Vermont.</h2>
<p>On Saturday, GOU#2 and I (middle-children UNITE!) joined friends in Vermont (coastal village right next to Onrus, another coastal village) where I prepared for everyone present <a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/">version 3.0 of “my” curry potjie</a>.</p>
<p>There’s something very special to the ritual of slowly (in this case three hours and a bit) but very deliberately preparing food for your friends. The fact that a large chunk of it happens on a wood fire adds even more flavour to the experience.</p>
<p>Sunday started with a run on the coastal path from Vermont to Onrus, under perfect blue skies (see photo above).</p>
<p>Later that morning, we spent some time at the Onrus lagoon, in and around which I spent a large number of happy hours growing up. It was amazing being able to show GOU#2 around, and then seeing her playing in the same waters.</p>
<h2 id="mindful-elder-superheroes">Mindful Elder Superheroes.</h2>
<p>All packed up and on our way home, we decided to visit M and A, one of two aunt-uncle pairs who live in Onrus.</p>
<p>GOU#2, age 9, did an amazing job of focusing on the stories my aunt had to tell, and reciprocating with curiosity and questions. (I told her afterwards that I was proud of her, also for this.)</p>
<p>At one point, my aunt explained, almost apologetically, that their <em>world had become really small</em>.</p>
<p>They were able to go down to the beach and spend hours looking at the sea and at the people walking by.</p>
<p>I thought that this was such a humble way for them to articulate their growing perceptual ability to sense the whole universes of experience hiding away in all of the seemingly small moments making up the average day.</p>
<h2 id="pro-tip-google-photoscan-for-your-pre-digital-photos">Pro-tip: Google PhotoScan for your pre-digital photos.</h2>
<p>This was yet another great tip from LM: If you need to digitise and old photo or two, try the <a href="https://www.google.com/photos/scan/">Google PhotoScan</a> app.</p>
<p>Using your smartphone, you start by making one overview photo of your old print, and then the app guides you with four white filled discs to make four rapid shots of the corners.</p>
<p>A whole bunch of Google image processing magic ensues, and out pops a glare-corrected perfectly cropped version of the photo!</p>
<p>Below you can see a test with a photo taken in 1993. The flash glare on the door was real.</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/cpbotha_programming_93.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/cpbotha_programming_93-1024x683.jpg"
        
            alt="Main container and conduit of the weekly head voices, 25 years ago. If memory serves correctly, I was making (in [x86 assembly language][4]) a software tool to play [Amiga Mod Music][5] files. My implementation was one of the fastest on the block, as I was prone to 1) counting and minimising the clock cycles in my routines and 2) employing self-modifying code in order to shave off even more unnecessary conditionals. (I overwrote memory areas with the specific sound rendering implementation for the selected output device. Modern caching architectures would probably not like this very much.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Main container and conduit of the weekly head voices, 25 years ago. If memory serves correctly, I was making (in [x86 assembly language][4]) a software tool to play [Amiga Mod Music][5] files. My implementation was one of the fastest on the block, as I was prone to 1) counting and minimising the clock cycles in my routines and 2) employing self-modifying code in order to shave off even more unnecessary conditionals. (I overwrote memory areas with the specific sound rendering implementation for the selected output device. Modern caching architectures would probably not like this very much.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts.</h2>
<p>It’s already Saturday February 23 as I write these hopefully almost final words of this post.</p>
<p>The plan was to make a super humble and compact bullet-list WHV, but then the week got super busy, and then I realised (again…) that I am truly terrible at bullet lists. (Please remind me when you see me again.)</p>
<p>What I <em>am</em> happy about, is that it’s now here for you to read.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Ubik on the beach, please. [Weekly Head Voices #54]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/17/ubik-on-the-beach-please-weekly-head-voices-54/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2011 21:36:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/17/ubik-on-the-beach-please-weekly-head-voices-54/</guid><description>At least part of this post was conceived right on this balcony over here: One day, I wish to own such a balcony.
Yes friends, that there right in front of us is the beach, and right in front of that the North Sea, and right over that the beautiful setting sun. We will definitely be going back there, it’s just that awesome spending a few days right on the sand.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>At least part of this post was conceived right on this balcony over here:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/julianadorp_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/julianadorp_view-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="One day, I wish to own such a balcony."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>One day, I wish to own such a balcony.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Yes friends, that there right in front of us is the beach, and right in front of that the North Sea, and right over that the beautiful setting sun. We will definitely be going back there, it’s just that awesome spending a few days right on the sand.</p>
<p>During my vacation, I had time to to spend some of it with one of my favourite authors, the late but fantastically great <strong>Philip K. Dick</strong>. Those of you with some culture will immediately think of VALIS, a masterpiece that he wrote after becoming more or less psychotic in 1974. The rest will go Ah! when I explain that Bladerunner, Total Recall , Minority Report and many more movies are based on his work. This time I visited Ubik, a book he wrote in 1969, chock-full of precogs, telepaths, anti-psis and the whole idea that your current reality might not be the only or even the most authentic reality. After reading this with great enjoyment, I’ve come to the conclusion that Dick might have been functionally psychotic for a longer time, but somehow was able to channel this masterfully into his truly psychedelic writing.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Ubik drops you back in the thick of things fast. Taken as directed, Ubik speeds relief to head and stomach. Remember: Ubik is only seconds away. Avoid prolonged use.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In other extremely significant happenings, <strong>genetic offspring #2 spontaneously started walking independently on Monday, August 8, 2011</strong>. Just to prove a point, she started doing dance moves during walking on the same day. Picture this: Little person, head and eyes disproportionately big and hence super cute, walking like a beginner across the room and then stopping halfway to do a little swinging-hips-jig. My cuteness-appreciation gland just about burst.</p>
<p>We’ve now also acquired the pinnacle of human transportation technology:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/ultimate_form_of_transportation.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/ultimate_form_of_transportation-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Say hello to your transportation future, humankind!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Say hello to your transportation future, humankind!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Yes people not from Holland, that’s a really weird three-wheeled bicycle with a huge wooden container on the front. Here it’s called a <strong>BAKFIETS</strong>. You fill the wooden container with kids (I’ve tested up to 4, works like a charm) or crates of beer (I’m soon going to test), fit the tent if it’s raining, and then cycle anywhere. It’s silent and does infinite miles to the gallon! I did get some funny looks when I cycled the 15 kilometres from Bergschenhoek, where we bought this baby, to Delft, but that might have been the fact that it was pitch dark at a time, and I had that crazy I-just-bought-a-bakfiets-and-I-will-cycle-her-home-come-hell-or-high-water look in my eye. Whatever the case may be, I can only very highly recommend this form of transport.</p>
<p>Alright kids, that’s it for now. I’m <a href="http://mytomatoes.com/" title="mytomatoes - great pomodoro app!">doing pomodori left and right</a>, but <em>The Man</em> keeps on piling on more work. It’s especially funny how just about every research grant programme worth its salt has its deadline right about now. One day I’m going to stick it to <em>The Man</em> I tell you!</p>
<p>P.S. This weekend, I’ll <strong>not</strong> be working on research grant proposals at a <a href="http://lowlands.nl/" title="lowlands baby!">truly wonderful event</a> with some suitably wonderful people.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>