<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>St Francis on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/st-francis/</link><description>Recent content in St Francis on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/st-francis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2024 to 2025 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to the year 2025!
We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this traditional yearly transition blog post here to keep you busy in the meantime.
The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2025!</p>
<p>We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this <a href="/tags/transition">traditional yearly transition blog post</a> here to keep you busy in the meantime.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20241228-st-francis-light-house.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a7c8fad0a4fb3336.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_c471bba5b301f4e3.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_7e36ecc6dd88d868.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp"
            

        
            alt="The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For those of you who are new here, 1) welcome! and 2) the traditional yearly transition post is where I both ramble semi-coherently on about the year that is closest to its conclusion and also speculate a bit about the year that is closest to its inception.</p>
<p>The main audience for this post is me &ndash; writing this up and the concomitant thinking and formulating bits form an important part of my maintenance process &ndash; but to anyone else who is reading this, there is hopefully something of value (or just a bit of entertainment) for you in these words. In any case, I am super happy that you&rsquo;re here!</p>
<h2 id="life-events">Life events</h2>
<p>In 2024, <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#i-turned-50">I turned 50</a> while <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#gou-1-turned-18">GOU#1 turned 18</a>, finished high school and is now on her way to university.</p>
<p>I mention these two in the same breath, because looking back it feels like the 5 years of her high school, a substantial chunk of time in terms of her development, went by in a flash.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s almost like we blinked <a href="/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">when she was still our little girl going to high school</a> and now suddenly she is an adult, and we finally feel like actual adults (aka old people) ourselves.</p>
<p>Although these have been amazing years for us, this experience of a whole period of life flashing by, through the lense of our children&rsquo;s development into adults, is a stark reminder to strive even harder to experience the living daylights out of every single moment that we are blessed with.</p>
<p>If all goes according to plan, we will have two more blink-blink-another-high-school-journey-is-complete experiences (GOU#2 is now in her second year of that journey, GOU#3 has a few years to go before she can start) so we should probably try to blink far less often.</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>After the dip both this blog and I went through in 2023 (total of 3 WHV posts&hellip;) and a very slow blogging start in 2024, it does feel like I might slowly be getting my WHV groove back, which seems to be evidenced by 66% more WHV posting in 2024, i.e. a whole 5 WHV posts! (Contrast this with the historic average of one post every two weeks.)</p>
<p>In the introduction to <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/">WHV #255 You lift me up</a> I speculate a bit about the reasons for my hiatus (I didn&rsquo;t mention there that maybe 2023 was actually just a real downer for me) and the current potential revival.</p>
<p>In addition to the posts here, I published <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">12 technical posts over on at the vxlabs</a> and a whole bunch of short howtos / recipes in the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">brand new TiL section of my other-OTHER website</a>. WHV #255 <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">explains the motivation behind the TiL section</a>.</p>
<p>I am also quite happy about the fact that I wrote a daily entry in my private diary for a large part of 2024, and this is something that I would like to continue, hopefully for an even larger part of 2025.</p>
<p>Spending some time every day to review that day, where the review is enriched by the deliberate activitity of trying to formulate everything into a story that I can write down, helps me to make sense of everything.</p>
<p>Writing in general seems to modulate positively my experience of reality.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a lot about this idea in various posts on this blog, but allow me to surface <a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#the-describers">two relevant sections from WHV 180</a>, and especially the quote below (but you should go read those two sections):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less faulty entity.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>My secret running goal for 2024 was to do 25km of running every week. In my head this was auto-simplified to 1200km for the year (you know, the way one often calculates a month as 4 weeks), but of course we&rsquo;re talking 1300km.</p>
<p>Well, I failed at all of these goals!</p>
<p>However, I did manage to run a total of 1149.7km over the year, which comes to an average of 22.1km per week, which I am pretty OK with. I had over 100 hours of fun (I truly enjoy running) and no injuries that I can remember.</p>
<p>The training calendar below shows that August was my laziest month, but that&rsquo;s because August has the worst weather, and because I was away for a week visiting my Dutch family and getting many tens of thousands of dancing steps instead. The calendar also shows how I made a last ditch effort in December to close the gap with my goal as much as possible.</p>










<figure><a href="20250101-strava-training-calendar.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_e13adc1c4101c63a.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_2caa5fcc1a219359.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_57229ed99a10234e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You might remember <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">my three metrics-focused goals from last year&rsquo;s post</a>, namely 50 consecutive push-ups, VO<sub>2</sub> Max of at least 50 and a resting state heart rate of 50 or under&hellip;</p>
<p>Well, 50 consecutive push-ups was not that hard, Apple Health reports my average resting state heart rate for 2024 as 48 BPM (this would be mostly via my Garmin Forerunner 245 and more recently 265) but my VO<sub>2</sub> briefly peaked at 49 (some time after I turned 50) before settling back on 48. I  would have loved that 50, but <a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/blog/fitness/whats-a-good-vo2-max-for-me/">48 is not the worst for a man of my age</a>.</p>
<p>My real goal for the coming year is the same as last year: I want to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>The older I get and the more I learn, the more I understand that with exercise, the more hours I can spend every week doing it, of course maintaining balance with the rest of my life (see life systems further down), the better my meat-coated skeleton will work, and the happier the ghost driving it will be.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’re a ghost driving a meat-coated skeleton made from stardust; what do you have to be scared of?</p>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2022/10/13/ghost-stardust/">@rat_sandwich on twitter, January 31, 2013</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>P.S. of course I will again go for 25km of running per week. I think logging substantially more than 120 hours of activities in Strava will be good. I might even give that VO<sub>2</sub> Max goal another shot.</p>
<p>P.P.S. I read <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/outlive/">Peter Attia&rsquo;s book Outlive</a> a few months ago. This is a detailed and practical manual for healthy living. There&rsquo;s a lot in there, but at the core he wants you, while you still have any say in the matter, to become as fit (measured by our friend VO<sub>2</sub> Max) and as strong (measured by grip strength) as you possibly can. You see, from middle age we&rsquo;re all on a downward curve, and there&rsquo;s not much we can do about it, except ensuring that we start as high as possible.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. It&rsquo;s funny; back in school, I thought little of athleticism, because it was a jock thing, and the jocks were generally not very kind to nerd-kind (my people). Now that I&rsquo;m older and quite ironically due to my nerdy lifelong learning habits, I strive for us much athleticism as I can &ldquo;fit&rdquo; in (jock joke harr harr).</p>
<h3 id="diet">Diet</h3>
<p>During this post&rsquo;s generously long incubation, I thought it worth adding here my approach to eating.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been practising 16-8 time-restricted eating (intermittent fasting in some circles) about 95% of the time since somewhere in 2019. I first <a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">wrote about it in WHV 186</a>, and then in <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#i-really-don-t-like-breakfast">WHV 221 I came out and stated the beef I have with breakfast</a> (that pun might be too heavy for this post).</p>
<p>Anyways, while I still believe that breakfast is bad for most people, I know that the scientific world has not yet reached consensus on time-restricted eating for healthy folks.</p>
<p>However, there is considerably more consensus that lowering daily caloric intake is good for most people.</p>
<p>For me, 16-8 TRE, where I simply don&rsquo;t ingest anything besides water and black coffee from about 7 in the evening until about noon the next day, is an extremely practical and especially low-effort way to reduce caloric intake.</p>
<p>When I do eat, the portions are modest, I try to stick to natural and unprocessed where I can and I keep an eye on protein.</p>
<p>When I do break these rules, I do so with deliberation. Great food, great wine, great beer and the company of friends and family, especially when combined, constitute a perfect reason to break all of these rules.</p>
<p>In short, reduce caloric intake, increase per-calorie value and/or enjoyment!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and Tools</h2>
<p>This is the place where I summarise (read: ramble on about) the current state of my digital tools and systems. If you&rsquo;re going to skip a (nerdy) section, this is the one! You can dive back in at <a href="#life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</a>.</p>
<p>I am one of those people who <em>regularly</em> finds and uses information from notes that I made.</p>
<p>If I have the note, and I often do because I make an effort to write stuff down with the lowest possible friction but the highest possible chance of being found again, this is generally miles faster than finding the information online, even with tools like the <a href="https://kagi.com/">premium search engine Kagi</a> which I have been using regularly for a few weeks now.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-and-obsidian">Emacs and Obsidian</h3>
<p>A year ago I <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#systems-and-tools">experienced a bit of a crisis of (Emacs) faith</a>.</p>
<p>Whilst that was more of a clash between the either-or poles of Emacs and Obsidian, I am now at a place where I&rsquo;m finding increasing uses for Obisidian as an <em>additional</em> note-taking tool, working on the same collection of hundreds of org-mode and a growing number of markdown files.</p>
<p>Emacs and org-roam treat <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">markdown files as if they are native org-roam nodes</a>. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/BBazard/obsidian-orgmode-cm6">Benoit Bazard&rsquo;s fantastic new CodeMirror 6 org-mode plugin for Obsidian</a> and my <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Monitor-rclone-cron-job-with-Home-Assistant">rclone + syncthing syncing setup for iPhone</a>, I have semi-usable org database support on my phone.</p>
<p><a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> and since recently <a href="https://orgro.org/">Orgro</a> are great for editing org files in the iPhone, but they are missing the searching and discovery, let&rsquo;s call it <em>note management</em>, aspects of a tool like Obsidian.</p>
<p>Long but quite important-to-me story short, it looks like for the time being I&rsquo;ll continue to use both Emacs and Obsidian for note-taking. Because interoperability is not perfect, there will be some natural gravitational pull towards the one or the other which I have decided to explore.</p>
<p>At the moment, it looks like I might be writing more of my atomic notes as markdown files, whilst using org for the lab journal / logbook and project management type of notes.</p>
<p>On a deeper note, the Obsidian team is doing fantastic work.</p>
<p>Apart from their <a href="https://stephango.com/file-over-app"><em>file over app</em> philosophy</a>, Obsidian is <em>programmable</em> as can be witnessed by the thriving extension ecosystem.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?id=ai-chat-as-md">written a modest extension</a> to test this out from the inside. The programmability is not as extensive as that of Emacs, but it runs everywhere, even on mobile devices, and it might be extensive enough for the note-taking platform that Obsidian has become.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Emacs on and off since the late 90s, but for the past 10 years it has become an always-running and integral part of my life. It feels really strange, disconcerting if I&rsquo;m being honest, that it seems to be losing its core spot.</p>
<p>I console myself in these moments with the observation that science must trump dogma, always.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m writing this post in Emacs.</p>
<h4 id="til">TiL</h4>
<p>Thanks to Obsidian, my other, OTHER website <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">now has a &ldquo;today I learned&rdquo; (TIL) section</a> at <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">charlbotha.com/til</a>, published directly from a sub-directory of my main notes directory.</p>
<p>The benefit is that there is even less friction than usual and, perhaps more importantly, the psychological friction has also been reduced because I have convinced myself that the posts there are just notes and not true blog posts.</p>
<h3 id="honorable-tool-mentions-zotero-and-quarto">Honorable tool mentions: Zotero and Quarto</h3>
<p>After <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#omnivore-is-no-more">my distastrous recommendation of Omnivore turned into a disaster</a>, it is with some emotional trepidation but intellectual confidence (thanks to file over app and its staunchly open source nature) that I can re-recommend Zotero as a reference (of all kinds!) management tool for the long term.</p>
<p>After I last mentioned it on my blog, I have been using it quite intensively, and <a href="https://bsky.app/hashtag/zotero?author=charlbotha.com">I keep on running into delightful features</a>, like the built-in PDF reader&rsquo;s pop-up visualization of citations and image references.</p>
<p>A more recent but high power entry into my toolbelt is <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, which I will contend strikes a fantastic usability-power balance in the world of technical document and presentation authoring. I&rsquo;ve now used it, in anger, to write a fairly extensive technical document, along with the afore-mentioned Zotero and <a href="https://retorque.re/zotero-better-bibtex/">Better BibTeX</a> for reference management, and the experience was magically smooth. To seal the deal, by the end I used Quarto to generate an attractive-looking docx for interoperability with the other stakeholders, but my contact time with Word was mercifully minimised.</p>
<h3 id="my-micro-blogging-history-2008---2025">My micro-blogging history 2008 - 2025</h3>
<p>Twitter says I created my account there in December of 2008. However, <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">this blog here says I only started using it in April of 2009</a>. (Twitter first launched in July of 2006.)</p>
<p>Some years later in 2016, coincidentally right before the previous Trumpocalypse, I wrote a post naively suggesting that we should <a href="/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/">replace twitter with something better (blogs&hellip;)</a> due to the risk of Twitter possibly going bad (ahem) and to the observation then that it was (then already) doing a crappy job keeping out abusive users (AHEM).</p>
<p>That post <a href="/2016/11/20/look-mom-hacker-news-front-page/">reached the front page of Hacker News</a>, and was thus read and discussed over there (and probably in the comments here) by tens of thousands of nerds, and a surprisingly small share of the usual &ldquo;Ackchyually&rdquo;-Bros.</p>
<p>(Please allow me this little tangent: A mental model that will really ease your time on sites like HN and reddit, is that the person on the other side, especially when they come across as super confident and assertive, is probably <strong>not</strong> an expert, not even by a long shot, on the topic that they are so confidently mansplaining. In fact, they are probably the least qualified to say anything. ChatGPT avant le lettre one might say. Ok back to your regular programming&hellip;)</p>
<p>Needless to say, my specific idea of replacing twitter with&hellip; blogs and rss was not implemented by the internet, at least not at that point&hellip;</p>
<p>When Musk acquired Twitter in October of 2022, the writing started appearing on the wall, at first vaguely, but with more and more definition as the months went on. I started looking for micro-blogging alternatives that were not twitter.</p>
<p>At first Mastodon looked too complicated, but then someone setup a <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#emacs-mastodon-server-was-irresistible">mastodon server dedicated to Emacs and I was immediately sold</a>.</p>
<p>However, Mastodon indeed turned out to be too complex and fundamentally quite fragile (all but the larger instances have a just a volunteer human or two behind them), leading to the owner of my favourite instance bascially being harassed to such an extent that it was better for him to get out of this business and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@cpbotha/113340325817581254">shut the Emacs mastodon server down</a>.</p>
<p>When I saw this announcement, I was disheartened.</p>
<p>When I read that Mastodon supports message export, but not message import, meaning that my posts would languish in a sad archive file somewhere, I was convinced that I had to try something out that was not Mastodon.</p>
<p>In parallel to my Mastodon efforts, I did also try Threads and was quite enthusiastic about its scale, and the speed with which Meta managed to build it, but I didn&rsquo;t manage to get any sort of interaction there. I think that it might be more geared for the Instagram model of influencers broadcasting to large groups of followers, in contrast to a more collaborative setup. (Urgh, the recent news about Meta&rsquo;s new &ldquo;free speech&rdquo; overhaul is additional motivation for me to spend even less energy there.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, it turns out that the newer and shinier microblogging service Bluesky was conceived in 2019 with the goal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluesky">&ldquo;to find or develop an open and decentralized standard for social media that would give users more control over their data and experience&rdquo;</a>, precisely the sort of thing that has suddenly become even more painfully relevant with the advent of the Trumpocalypse part deux, now with more Musk-power.</p>
<p>Long story short, in a very short time, Bluesky has proven to be almost exactly the microblogging platform that I enjoy participating in. Lots of human interaction, no ads, many different user-contributed algorithms to choose from, including just seeing the stuff your people post, in the order that they post it &ndash; it really feels like the thing was put together with semi-normal human interaction as the central concern.</p>
<p>Up to now, it also feels like <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#bluesky-is-my-new-micro-blogging-thing-of-choice">many folks on there prefer being decent to each other</a>, something I militantly (haha) support.</p>
<p>Some mastodon folks are downright unhappy with bluesky, because they feel that it&rsquo;s not truly decentralized like mastodon.</p>
<p>Thing is, Bluesky has chosen a different spot on the usability - decentralization spectrum, and and my opinion is exactly usable and decentralised enough for what it needs to be and do at this moment in time.</p>
<p>Looking slightly further into the future, there are well-funded initiatives like <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/13/24342799/free-our-feeds-social-media-ecosystem-at-protocol-bluesky">Free our feeds</a>, ideologically and technologically supported by the Bluesky company but otherwise unconnected, which has amongst its <a href="https://freeourfeeds.com/">goals to &ldquo;build independently hosted infrastructure (a second &lsquo;relay&rsquo;) so that Bluesky users, developers and researchers always have full access to the stream of content and data no matter what the company decides to do in future&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>If you would like to know more, Faine Greenwood has written <a href="https://little-flying-robots.ghost.io/the-great-bluesky-migration-i-answer-some-of-your-questions/">this great Bluesky explainer</a>.</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</h2>
<p>My Life Systems are the guiding principles, rules, personal values and bags of tips that I have explicitly defined and refined over the years to help me be the best human that I can be.</p>
<p>Note: I write these up primarily as a reminder to myself. If it comes across as prescriptive, please remember that I&rsquo;m telling <em>me</em> how to live my life. I can do this, because I <em>am</em> the boss of me.</p>
<h3 id="core">Core</h3>
<p>You&rsquo;ll be happy to hear that the core of my Life Systems 2025 is exactly the same as the previous edition <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">Life Systems 2024</a>, except for the version number increase, and the concomitant price increase. (taking a leaf here from the Intel playbook!)</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to read <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">the 2024 write-up</a>, here is the compressed version:</p>
<p><em>Guiding principles:</em> 1. Love 2. Science. <em>Two no three rules for achieving great success in life, or just surviving, whichever comes first:</em> 1. Be useful. 2. be likable and 3. evolve. <em>Personal values:</em> 1. Be kind. 2. Be grateful. 3. Attend fully to the now. 4. Enjoy life with family and with my friends. 5. Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers. 6. Be there for my family. 7. Add value through work. 8. Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise. 9. Build and/or fix something. 10. Learn new things. 11. Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</p>
<h3 id="balance">Balance</h3>
<p>What I have been thinking about this year, especially when things get quite busy, is the sometimes tricky practice of applying balance to one&rsquo;s personal values.</p>
<p>A straight-forward example is when important work obligations start impacting my sleep or exercise schedule, in which case I have to apply balance and tone down slightly the ambition to fulfil personal value no 7.</p>
<p>It can easily get more tricky however; when something on that list of personal values, which is important to you, starts taking up more than its fair share of energy, that will come at the cost of all of the other endeavours that you value.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have a hard and fast rule for this, only the measure of remembering to <em>pay attention</em> also at that meta-level so that one can make suitable balancing adjustments when required.</p>
<h3 id="work-hard-party-hard-rest-hard">Work hard. Party hard. Rest hard.</h3>
<p>A lesson that has only become clearer for me over the years is that we humans function best when we are able to focus on one thing at a time, and when we have as few things as possible on the list that we select from.</p>
<p>This works at all scales of life, from what task do I work on during this half-hour all the way up to my main priority for today, or my three main priorities for this year.</p>
<p>The challenge in applying this lesson is three-fold:</p>
<ol>
<li>Know which thing to focus on at any time,</li>
<li>reduce switching between things and yet</li>
<li>get to all of the things that you should get to.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you have all three of these covered, then comes the truly difficult part: <strong>Attend fully to the now.</strong></p>
<p>Those of us who are lucky get about 4000 weeks of life.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not truly present in the thing that you&rsquo;ve chosen at this moment, you are not using that allotted time to its fullest extent.</p>
<p>You can never ever get that time back.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like you&rsquo;re in a Michelin-starred restaurant, and instead of going power level 9000 with all of your senses and your thoughts and your whole being into <em>experiencing</em> that food with your favourite human(s), you&rsquo;re scrolling on your phone, absent-mindedly shovelling forkfuls into your mouth.</p>
<p>Do the opposite.</p>
<p>Pick your battles, but sometimes also choose a party if you can and don&rsquo;t forget to rest like your life depends on it. Whatever you do, be the most maximally present in the thing you&rsquo;ve chosen. Presence and attention improve with regular practice.</p>
<p>In short: Work hard, party hard, rest hard.</p>
<!-- be maximally present to use that time right; do everything HARD -- came during my 2025-01-11 morning run -->
<h2 id="my-2024-to-2025-transition-wishes">My 2024 to 2025 transition wishes</h2>
<p>Humans<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> <em>at their peak</em> are a thing of beauty.</p>
<p>Above all they are truly kind.  They live and breathe the knowledge that we <em>homo sapiens</em> are at our absolute best when we connect with each other.</p>
<p>Peak humans are graceful, and they are elegant, and they are in harmony &ndash; the best sort of balance &ndash; with their surroundings, with those around them and with themselves.</p>
<p>Attaining this peak is hard. Maintaining it is nigh impossible. Best we can go for is <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">the never-ending practice</a> of these characteristics, and an eternal striving for moments to <em>become them</em>.</p>
<p>Friends, I wish you and your connected ones the willpower to strive for grace and elegance and harmony, and the presence of mind to attend fully to those perfect moments when they occur.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, you might be one of these&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #254: Ratio</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 15:02:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/</guid><description>Hello there WHV enjoyers, and welcome back! &amp;hellip;ish.
The last official WHV, by name, was WHV #253, published on September 2, 2023, although the 2023 to 2024 transition post certainly deserves its honorary WHV title.
In the meantime, I have been experimenting with the Daily Head Voices / lifelogs, which was fun, but ultimately not sufficiently meaty to fill the WHV vacuum.
We are clearly going through a pretty significant WHV-hiatus.
Although I&amp;rsquo;m still not sure what the new stable state is going to be, I have some extremely modest plans, and in addition to those I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to dust off and revive the draft of WHV #254 which was just lying there on my disc since September of last year, all languishing.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello there WHV enjoyers, and welcome back! &hellip;ish.</p>
<p>The last official WHV, by name, was <a href="/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/">WHV #253, published on September 2, 2023</a>, although the <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/">2023 to 2024 transition post</a> certainly deserves its honorary WHV title.</p>
<p>In the meantime, I have been experimenting with the <a href="/categories/lifelog/">Daily Head Voices / lifelogs</a>, which was fun, but ultimately not sufficiently meaty to fill the WHV vacuum.</p>
<p>We are clearly going through a pretty significant WHV-hiatus.</p>
<p>Although I&rsquo;m still not sure what the new stable state is going to be, I have <em>some</em> extremely modest plans, and in addition to those I&rsquo;ve decided to dust off and revive the draft of WHV #254 which was just lying there on my disc since September of last year, all languishing.</p>










<figure><a href="wilderness-view-from-the-views.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_3a2af3333e208e2c.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_81aa06121ae775ec.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_e50b29cbe418a449.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_51f1e144bf2c94d8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_81aa06121ae775ec.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: The view from our return-journey lunch at The Views in Wilderness was awe-inspiring."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>The view from our return-journey lunch at The Views in Wilderness was awe-inspiring.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="easter-break-on-the-garden-route">Easter break on the Garden Route</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m typing these words on my laptop in the family car, moving back home along the N2 after an absolutely fabulous Easter break-away on the Garden Route.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I have not yet figured out a safe way to drive and type at the same time, so my partner is graciously helping out with the driving bits during this shift.</p>
<p>GOU#1&rsquo;s exchange family &ldquo;sister&rdquo; from Germany is currently visiting, and so we have been doing our best to show her some of the best this amazing country has to offer.</p>
<p>Although this makes for a fairly jam-packed holiday programme (almost no time to work on hobby projects), it really has been loads of fun.</p>
<p>Some highlights (ask me in the comments if you&rsquo;re curious about anything):</p>
<ul>
<li>Ebb &amp; Flow rest camp in Wilderness - one of my favourite running routes next to the Serpentine river</li>
<li>Sun-down at Salinas Beach restaurant in Wilderness</li>
<li><a href="https://knysnaelephantpark.co.za">Elephant encounters at the Knysna Elephant Park</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.sanparks.org/parks/garden-route/camps/storms-river-mouth">Storms River Mouth rest camp (Tsitsikamma)</a> - beauty all round, hikes over the hanging bridges up past the view point, also the start of the Otter trail at the other end of the camp</li>
<li>Lunch at The Views in Wilderness</li>
<li>St Francis, beautiful as always, with specific mention of Etienne&rsquo;s surfing lessons at the main beach for our teenagers, and the super entertaining St Francis Bay canal sunset cruise</li>
<li>We were absolutely blessed with balmy later summer weather, except for one rainy morning in Storms</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="two-mention-worthy-personal-knowledge-tools">Two mention-worthy personal knowledge tools</h2>
<p>As is traditional around these parts, we have this nerdy section surprise here to talk about software tools that I really like, after which there will be some backyard philosophy sections.</p>
<h3 id="miniflux">miniflux</h3>
<p>My yearly <a href="https://www.inoreader.com">inoreader</a> rss reader subscription was up for renewal.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a really fantastic product that I&rsquo;ve been using (and paying for) for years as <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#mobile">a core part of my personal knowledge management approach</a>, but the renewal email and especially the price tag was a good reminder to review my options, especially since I already have an old Linux laptop serving <a href="https://pi-hole.net">Pi-hole</a> for family-wide ad-blocking, and <a href="https://www.home-assistant.io">Home Assistant</a> to track energy production and usage stats of some of our devices at home.</p>
<p>A few minutes of searching fortunately led me to <a href="https://miniflux.app">miniflux</a>, &ldquo;a minimalist and opinionated feed reader&rdquo;. After a few more minutes, I had the docker-compose up and running (miniflux and postgres containers), and after some more minutes I had a <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/en-gb/products/tunnel/">CloudFlare tunnel</a> up so that I can easily access my miniflux&rsquo;s web UI from anywhere via an automatic Cloudflare-supplied SSL certificate. Finally, through the magic of OPML, it was straight-forward to move my 130+ feed subscriptions from inoreader to miniflux.</p>










<figure><a href="screenshot-miniflux.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_ef74d383072aa1b5.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_4c429f2130b9c515.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_34a9379b4036d398.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_6bf961f84eb46697.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_4c429f2130b9c515.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: miniflux often looks like this"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>miniflux often looks like this</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been using this setup for the past week or two and so far it looks like a strong keeper!</p>
<p>miniflux has extensive keyboard support on the desktop, but it works great on mobile, which is where I mostly use it.</p>
<p>I really like its minimalism: It shows me a paged view of all my feeds (page size configurable), via which I can easily jump to the source page, or use miniflux&rsquo;s built-in reader mode, and also easily toggle the whole page as read before moving on to the next.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re in the market for a self-hosted RSS reader, take this as a strong recommendation for miniflux. Even if you don&rsquo;t want to self-host, <a href="https://miniflux.app/hosting.html">their $15 / year hosted offering</a> is probably worth a look.</p>
<h3 id="omnivore">omnivore</h3>
<p>After years of eschewing &ldquo;read-it-later&rdquo; apps like Pocket and friends for the more straight-forward but often klunky  <a href="/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">&ldquo;just print to PDF and store&rdquo; approach</a>, I had to give <a href="https://omnivore.app/">omnivore</a> a go, as it offered native support to sync article highlights into Obsidian&rsquo;s markdown, and I thought that I would be able to use this for my Emacs setup as well.</p>
<p>I was indeed able to co-opt the Obsidian integration to get saved article highlights into my Emacs setup, but in the process fell completely for the omnivore app as a whole.</p>
<p>On mobile, which is where I use this most, I am able to import any web-page or post into omnivore with two taps.</p>
<p>On average, it does a great job of extracting the article contents and rendering it in a far more consistent and reading-friendly way.</p>
<p>One can make different coloured highlights in any article, and even add a note to each highlight.</p>
<p>Finally, it also imports PDFs with aplomb, and offers most of its functionality there. There are additional subtle delights, like the fact that you can double-tap on one column of a multi-column PDF, at which point omnivore will zoom to bring only that column into maximum width view.</p>










<figure><a href="screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom_hu_7e164320f45eb29e.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom_hu_f767113c0785ef74.jpg 800w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom_hu_f767113c0785ef74.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Vertically partial screenshot of Omnivore during PDF column zoom. Maps of Bounded Reality is a piece by the great Daniel Kahneman (1934-03-05 - 2024-03-27, rest in peace) which gives an overview of his and Amos Tversky&rsquo;s groundbreaking work making sense of human behaviour." width="320px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Vertically partial screenshot of Omnivore during PDF column zoom. Maps of Bounded Reality is a piece by the great Daniel Kahneman (1934-03-05 - 2024-03-27, rest in peace) which gives an overview of his and Amos Tversky&rsquo;s groundbreaking work making sense of human behaviour.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For me the only downside of omnivore is that it violates <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#high-level-overview">both my single search interface and plain old files on local drives characteristics</a>. However, both of these violations are partially mitigated by the aforementioned note-syncing feature. I don&rsquo;t really want to have <strong>all</strong> of my saved articles to be part of my database, so here I should make syncable highlights when something is important enough to go into the primary notes database.</p>
<p>After some months of use, I strongly recommend omnivore as your web-resource-ingestion-and-assimilation tool!</p>
<h2 id="the-three-or-four-hours-rule-for-getting-creative-work-done">The three-or-four hours rule for getting creative work done</h2>
<p>Last year, I listened to a short piece by Oliver Burkeman, who has <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">featured on this blog a number of times</a>, which made an impression on me. I made a note of it in the pre-hiatus draft of this post, and then promptly forgot about it.</p>
<p>The core of Burkeman&rsquo;s three-or-four hours rule, which you can <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">read more about on his website</a>, is summarised in the following quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; use whatever freedom you do have over your schedule not to &ldquo;maximise your
time&rdquo; or &ldquo;optimise your day&rdquo;, in some vague way, but specifically to ringfence
three or four hours of undisturbed focus (ideally when your energy levels are
highest).</p>
<p>Stop assuming that the way to make progress on your most important projects is
to work for longer. And drop the perfectionistic notion that emails, meetings,
digital distractions and other interruptions ought ideally to be whittled away
to practically nothing.</p>
<p>Just focus on protecting four hours – and don&rsquo;t worry if the rest of the day is
characterised by the usual scattered chaos.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have definitely suffered from the &ldquo;maximise your time&rdquo; bug and can attest to its negative effects.</p>
<p>Burkeman suggests to worry only about a core few high-focus hours (he says 3 or 4, I think sometimes depending on your context, even 1 could work) and let the rest be what it wants to be.</p>
<p>I think this is a far better approach which strongly complements <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">the one main thing philosophy</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. There&rsquo;s another important tenet of Burkeman&rsquo;s approach, which he talks about in his post linked above, and which also <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">featured in WHV #230, namely: Know how to put down your work</a> (although I just noticed that back then I did not mention the chaos part&hellip;). In summary: Guard your focus hours, let &ldquo;the chaos&rdquo; fill the rest, but become really good at detaching and walking away at the end of the work day. Thank you <a href="http://noeskasmit.com">Noeska</a> for the reminder!</p>
<h2 id="the-magic-relationship-ratio-is-5-to-1">The Magic Relationship Ratio is 5 to 1</h2>
<p>I really enjoyed the <a href="https://lexfridman.com/shannon-curry/">fascinating podcast between Lex Fridman and Dr Shannon Curry</a>, a clinical and forensic psychologist, titled &ldquo;Johnny Depp &amp; Amber Heard Trial, Marriage, Dating &amp; Love&rdquo;, much of it in fact about human relationships (<a href="https://www.podcastworld.io/episodes/366-shannon-curry-johnny-depp-amber-heard-trial-marriage-dat-sz9ltosy">textual summary here</a>).</p>
<p>Among the many practical and science-based topics that Dr Curry talked about, she mentioned the <a href="https://www.gottman.com/blog/the-magic-relationship-ratio-according-science/">&ldquo;5 to 1magic relationship ratio&rdquo;</a>, which refers to the observation that the interactions between happy couples tend to consist of at least 5 positive interactions for each negative interaction.</p>
<p>It should come as no surprise that being able to spend decades together in a permanent state of happiness, by definition continuously facing various internal and external stressors in an often resource-constrained environment, is probably not realistic.</p>
<p>Thus I really like that this observation runs with the knowledge that almost no-one is going to get this right, and that the smart approach is instead to accept that and focus on what you can attain, namely, that more practical but still ambitious 5 to 1 ratio.</p>
<h2 id="ratio">Ratio</h2>
<p>This is the part of the post where I try to tie up some of the threads, or at least justify the title.</p>
<p>Burkeman&rsquo;s three-or-four hours rule is all about working towards a practical and healthy <em>ratio</em> between focus time and the rest of the daily chaos, instead of being continuously disappointed because it&rsquo;s not really possible to fill all of your days with pure focus hours.</p>
<p>The 5 to 1 ratio is the same: We make peace with reality, and work towards a healthy ratio between positive and negative interactions.</p>
<p>The third <em>ratio</em> I want to mention here refers to the Dutch word &ldquo;ratio&rdquo; (<a href="https://nl.bab.la/uitspraak/nederlands/ratio">pronunciation)</a>, one of whose definitions is &ldquo;reason&rdquo; or &ldquo;logic&rdquo;, or more idiomatically, the noun corresponding to adjective &ldquo;rationeel&rdquo;, which is the same as the English &ldquo;rational&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As with all things language, the use of this word implies subtle little differences. Whatever the case may be, I was delighted when I discovered that the Dutch had adopted the original Latin for this. To me it felt like that meant there was a special place for and focus on <em>ratio</em> in their world.</p>
<p>With that trifecta (a neologism, I just learned, for contrast!) of <em>ratio</em> examples, I think that I can now conclude this post with the earnest wish, for you and for me, that we are able to instantiate, maintain and propagate superb levels of <em>ratio</em>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #247: Precious moments</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 22:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/</guid><description>Welcome back friends!
This post attempts to cover the longer thann normal period of time from Monday September 26 to Sunday October 30, 2022.
Figure 1: This is what the view looks like just after a lunch at Pearl View Guest House, which itself with spectacular views.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends!</p>
<p>This post attempts to cover the longer thann normal period of time from Monday
September 26 to Sunday October 30, 2022.</p>










<figure><a href="knysna-heads.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_c8238dc56f0e3de0.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_acc7684da5d46e95.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_f46a88b64faaa876.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_870583e22b4106b8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_acc7684da5d46e95.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: This is what the view looks like just after a lunch at Pearl View Guest House, which itself with spectacular views."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>This is what the view looks like just after a lunch at Pearl View Guest House, which itself with spectacular views.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This is the year of me struggling to make the time and the energy to write
these posts. Between work (it&rsquo;s never been this truly busy before), family
(teenagers man) and other important activities, this previously
straight-forward endeavour has become really challenging.</p>
<p>I currently have no cunning plans to remedy this issue, except to keep on
trying.</p>
<p>Anyways, my main goal with this post below morphed from &ldquo;try to write a good
post&rdquo; to &ldquo;<em>any</em> post is better than no post&rdquo;, and so it is entirely possible that
you&rsquo;ll notice some unevenness.</p>
<h2 id="wilderness-energy">Wilderness Energy</h2>
<p>So after a number of paragraphs complaining about how little free time I have
at my disposal, I shall now briefly talk about our October family break-away to
the East coast!</p>
<p>As we often do, we decided to break the road-trip in two, staying for the night
in Wilderness, literally one of my favourite places on the planet.</p>
<p>As we don&rsquo;t often do, this time we stayed an extra night because the weather,
and that balmy Wilderness energy (it sounds like a pretty hip caffeinated
drink) were simply too amazing to pass up.</p>
<p>During our surprise extra day:</p>
<ul>
<li>I ran the Waterside dirt road next to the Serpentine river, in the direction of
Hoekwil. I love running dirt roads, and this one is high up on the list.</li>
<li>We (6 famjam + 1 friend) did the canoe trip at Kaaimanskloof, something that
we&rsquo;ve always dreamed about, to the waterfall, to the train bridge and later
up the river all the way to the bend right below the Map of Africa lookout,
far up above. I shared a canoe with my most favourite middle child in the
world, aka GOU #2. (We also won the race back, even beating out the far more
energetic canoe powered by GOU #1 and her friend, by applying a certain
degree of crystallized-intelligence-guided strategy.)</li>
<li>We squeezed in a beach day.</li>
<li>We went up to Map of Africa to enjoy the brilliant sunset.</li>
</ul>
<p>After all of that I was a bit worried that we had set the pace of the whole
week, the sustaining of which I would probably not have survived.</p>
<p>Fortunately the continuation of our vacation in St Francis was, whilst <em>quite</em>
active, an energetically more sustainable affair, consisting of balmy weather,
family beach days, and zen-inducing sunsets.</p>
<p>Personally, I will <em>remember</em> this week as a great example of How To Holiday.</p>










<figure><a href="st-francis-bay-canals.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_2636366ec22c5c37.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_b307460b68aefcdf.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_5771a46dd0d8be48.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_8666c277feba0dec.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_b307460b68aefcdf.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View of the canals in St Francis Bay, the village 7km to the North of Cape St Francis."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>View of the canals in St Francis Bay, the village 7km to the North of Cape St Francis.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="goldilocks-water-for-your-moka-pot">Goldilocks water for your Moka pot</h2>
<p>At home, we rely on our <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#coffee-machine-reincarnation">trusty (new) Saeco bean-to-cup</a> machine to keep us
continously and quite fully coffee-nated.</p>
<p>However, because there is no space for Saeco on our travels, we require a
mobile, preferably compact, coffee production modality.</p>
<p>This used to be the giant coffee syringe, also known as Aeropress, which I
wrote about in <a href="/2014/07/22/weekly-head-voices-78-aeroimpressed/">WHV #78, back in 2014</a>.</p>
<p>It makes really great tasting coffee, but it can feel a little clinical.</p>
<p>More recently, as we became older (a tenacious process that never seems to stop
until the end, I am told) and our appreciation for the slower, more deliberate
rituals of life grew, we decided to switch to a Bialetti Moka pot instead.</p>
<p>You would probably recognise it. It&rsquo;s that distinctive little aluminium pot
with the octagonal base and the friendly picture on the side.</p>
<p>Instead of the one minute stir, one minute push through of the Aeropress, this
artifact sits there on its hob for about five minutes when it magically fills
up with lovely espresso.</p>
<p>(Of course it&rsquo;s not magic, it&rsquo;s just <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moka_pot">Mr Alfonso Bialetti&rsquo;s brilliant
engineering from 1933</a>!)</p>
<p>Here is our Moka pot, this time posing in <a href="/tags/stilbaai/">Stilbaai</a>, another one of my favourite
vacation destinations:</p>










<figure><a href="stilbaai-moka.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_3bafdd46cb5bf89c.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_bc0795b9133db5d8.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_ca37d8803312a579.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_84eada315ce75bc9.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_bc0795b9133db5d8.jpg"
            

         width="320px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>More recently, I chatted with friend PH at work about the ideal starting
temperature for the fresh water in one&rsquo;s Moka.</p>
<p>I had naively always preferred to start with cold water, to emulate the camping
situation, but work-friend explained that he had understood warm water to be
better for the taste.</p>
<p>I had never considered this before. Doh!</p>
<p>(Later I learned from mutual friend SvdW that they had in fact previously
studied Moka pot temperature in detail during a work trip, an experience
perhaps partially forgotten by friend PH.)</p>
<p>Serendipitously, during a meeting later that afternoon with colleagues from the
US, one of our collaborators, sporting a pretty relevant scientific background,
explained that <em>he</em> had understood (in Fahrenheit, we had to translate) that 60
°C resulted in the best coffee extraction.</p>
<p>This obviously piqued my curiousity, quite intensely, and so I went searching
that evening&hellip;</p>
<p>Imagine my delight when I ran into <a href="http://www.msc.univ-paris-diderot.fr/~phyexp/uploads/Moka/article1.pdf"><em>The physics of a stove-top espresso
machine</em></a>, a 2008 scientific article by Dr Warren D. King in the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1119/1.2870524"><em>American
Journal of Physics</em>, vol. 76, no. 6, pp. 558–565</a>, in which he documents his
mathematical modeling and experiments showing that the optimal starting
temperature for the water in a Moka pot is in fact 70 °C!</p>
<p>The short version of the story is that this will result in most of the water
going through the coffee grounds, when extraction takes place, at about 95
°C, which results in the most  flavour.</p>
<p>If you start with cold water, extraction will happen at 70 °C, which is
too low, and if you start with hot water, it will go through the grounds at too
high a temperature, resulting in bitter coffee.</p>
<h2 id="take-a-picture-with-your-mind">Take a picture with your mind</h2>
<!-- The title of this section is due to friend PK. You have to say it in his voice, "take a picture with your miiii-iiiiind!" -->
<p>Back in <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#multiplicity-of-you">WHV #242 I talked about the remembering (narrating) self, and the
experiencing self</a>. (Please read that section if you have not yet. In fact, I
think that the whole of WHV #242 could be worth your time.)</p>
<p>Kahnemann&rsquo;s poignant quote bears repeating here:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Odd as it may seem, I am my remembering self, and the experiencing self, who
does my living, is like a stranger to me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just the other day, in the middle of a perfect run on the beach, with a breeze
that was just <em>so</em>, the sun all golden and ready to set, and with my bare feet
connecting with the sand and the earth beneath it, it felt like a full sensory
connect, experiencing self for once fully in control.</p>
<p>It was perfect, until I felt this superficially pretty reasonable urge to take
a photo, just a little something to remember the perfect moment by&hellip;</p>
<p>At that instant, I saw it for what it was &ndash; sneaky, remembering self
attempting to hijack the moment, and take it away from experiencing self, the
one who at that moment was generating by far the most positive energy.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We wants it, we needs it. Must have the precious. They stole it from us. Sneaky
little hobbitses. Wicked, tricksy, false! &ndash; JRR Tolkien</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The desire to remember the perfect moment is understandable, but there is a
cost: The moment itself.</p>
<p>Resist the urge.</p>
<p>Love,<br />
Remembering Self</p>










<figure><a href="cape-st-francis-light-house.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_97ddb7d8d1f7c08b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_b9a76019323c2de.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_f7a6964a6a668463.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_9b3e177a9240de5c.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_b9a76019323c2de.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: The light house in Cape St Francis, the village 7km to the South of St Francis Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>The light house in Cape St Francis, the village 7km to the South of St Francis Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #222: Scotty, we need more power!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 14:07:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/</guid><description>Welcome back everyone!
It&amp;rsquo;s now early(ish) Friday morning of the weekend after, but I would like to get the 222d edition of the WHV out, namely the one covering the two weeks from Monday, April 19 to Sunday, May 2, 2021.
My excuse for skipping a week is that the second week was spent on vacation. Exhibit A is shown below:
Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s now early(ish) Friday morning of the weekend after, but I would like to
get the 222d edition of the WHV out, namely the one covering the two weeks from
Monday, April 19 to Sunday, May 2, 2021.</p>
<p>My excuse for skipping a week is that the second week was spent on
vacation. Exhibit A is shown below:</p>










<figure><a href="st_francis_beach_run_202104.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_bbb76e39724cc3f7.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_bfb1ba72e5ab2b58.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_ec9238ff28cf4ddf.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_681f14d95b121950.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_bfb1ba72e5ab2b58.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The rest of this post has (imagine the following in Bill Hader&rsquo;s Stefon voice):</p>
<ul>
<li>migraines and science</li>
<li>scifi ipads</li>
<li>VR</li>
<li>a life tip</li>
</ul>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="brain-glitch">Brain glitch</h2>
<p>I lost almost half a work day to a <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/conditions/ocular-migraine.htm">visual migraine</a>.</p>
<p>Looking at my notes, it seems that these only started during the past few
years, although it could be that I just didn&rsquo;t record the previous ones.</p>
<p>It starts out with bright spots in the middle of your field of vision, which
slowly grow until they form jiggly circles. This is not ideal, but at least you
can now look through their centres. Haha.</p>
<p>It looks eerily identical to the illustration on the linked website.</p>
<p>After half an hour to about an hour, sometimes a headache will hit, and
sometimes not. This time it was unusually intense, and I had no choice but to
detach from work for a while.</p>
<p>Looking back at my notes now, I really appreciate the time-stamped entries as
the migraine developed all the way to its end.</p>
<p>Lesson reaffirmed: Take good notes, no matter what.</p>
<h3 id="fascinating-scientific-review-of-migraine-and-metabolism">Fascinating scientific review of migraine and metabolism</h3>
<p>After a related chat with a friend who reported that in his case blood sugar
played a role (he can&rsquo;t skip breakfast, and can&rsquo;t eat too sweet), my
permanently foraging internet tentacles entirely coincidentally dredged up this
publication in Nature Reviews Neurology titled &ldquo;The metabolic face of
migraine - from pathophysiology to treatment&rdquo; (<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31586135/">pubmed</a>, <a href="https://orbi.uliege.be/bitstream/2268/247255/1/Gross%20et%20al%20Metabolic%20face%20of%20migraine-Nat%20Rev%20Neurol%202019.pdf">PDF fulltext</a>).</p>
<p>The article is pretty dense, but here are some interesting observations:</p>
<p>The first is from box 1: In some humans, when brain energy demands outstrip
metabolic reserves, rendering them vulnerable to disruption of cortical
homeostatis (energy balance), there is a whole cascade of events that,
according to the article&rsquo;s authors, might be started by the pannexin channels
in neurons. (These channels act as sensors of cortical homeostasis.)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s quite straight-forward then that (haha):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The final result of this cascade is trigeminovascular activation and calcitonin
gene-related peptide release in the extradural space, which leads to headache.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Following from there, they postulate two alternate pathways that cause
respectively migraine with and without aura (visual effects).</p>
<p>In other words, when your brain requires more energy than you have available,
and you are one of the many genetic variants who suffer from this mechanism,
you could be in for some migraine when your body reacts to the imbalance.</p>
<p>On top of that, the authors present one more good reason <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#skip-you-some-breakfast-for-great-good">to become fat-adapted</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>These increases in lipolysis and ketogenesis can also be interpreted as
counter-​regulatory responses to a cerebral energy deficit. Given that ketone
bodies are an efficient alternative fuel for the brain when glucose
availability is low, their elevation would be expected to restore brain energy
homeostasis. However, the Western carbohydrate-​laden diet means that in most
people in Western countries the brain is not keto-​adapted so does not have the
enzymatic composition and transporters to make use of ketone bodies produced
during an energy crisis.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Box 2 in the article provides the following quite intriguing &ldquo;Suggested
approach to improving mitochondrial function and energy metabolism in
migraine&rdquo; (emphasis mine, so that you can skim over if you want):</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>Individualize supplementation of micronutrients. To ensure that all
micronutrients needed for mitochondrial function are available, laboratory
tests can be used to individualize supplementation with minerals,
hydrophobic and lipophilic vitamins and trace mineralsthat are deficient.</li>
<li>Reduce oxidative stress and increase antioxidants. Measurement of oxidative
and/or nitrosative stress levels and antioxidant status in individuals could
detect a potential mismatch between oxidative stress levels and antioxidant
capacity and enable therapeutic adjustments to be made, although studies are
needed to prove that such an approach improves migraine
management. Strategies to reduce oxidative stress could include <strong><strong>elimination
or reduction of processed food, food with a high glycaemic index and</strong></strong>
<strong><strong>alcohol, use of green or blue light filtering glasses, interruption of
hormone-based contraception, lifestyle changes</strong></strong> and addition of
antioxidants,such as polyphenols, coenzyme Q10, α-lipoic acid or
β-hydroxybutyrate mineral salts, to the diet.</li>
<li><strong><strong>Stabilize blood glucose levels</strong></strong>. An oral glucose tolerance testshould be
undertaken in patients with migraine and clinical features that suggest
glucose intolerance or a family history of glucose intolerance. Patients
with reactive hyperinsulinaemia and reactive hypoglycaemia are likely to
benefit from stabilization of blood glucose levels, which can often be
achieved with dietary adjustments.</li>
<li>Provide an <strong><strong>alternative energy substrate for the brain</strong></strong>. For patients with
compromised energy metabolism, an alternative source of fuel for the brain,
in addition to glucose and lactate, might be beneficial. This source can be
generated with a ketogenic diet and/or use of exogenous ketogenic
substances, such asmedium-chain triglycerides or exogenous ketone body
salts. Further placebo-controlled trials are needed to validate ketogenic
therapies in migraine.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="4-20-ipad-pro-supercomputers-straight-outta-scifi">4/20 iPad Pro supercomputers straight outta SciFi</h2>
<p>On 4/20 I tuned into a liveblog (I think it was <a href="https://live.arstechnica.com/apples-april-20-2021-spring-loaded-event/">the one by Ars Technica</a>) of
Apple&rsquo;s release event.</p>
<p>Apple is currently evolving the computing landscape quite substantially, so I
find it immensely interesting to see what they are bringing next.</p>
<p>They did a whole bunch this time, but what struck me as the most significant,
is that they introduced two new iPad Pro tablets with M1 chips.</p>
<p>You know, that same M1 chip powering <a href="/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/">the super fast and energy-efficient laptop
on which I&rsquo;m typing up this post</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to sticking a desktop-class processor (err, desktop-class
performance, but mobile-level battery efficiency) back into a mobile device
that you can also buy with 2 terabytes of built-in storage (I find this a bit
surreal), the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2021/4/21/22395449/apple-ipad-pro-2021-liquid-retina-xdr-mini-led-explainer">new Liquid Retina XDR display on the top-end iPad Pro</a> has 10000
of a new kind of micro-led just for the back-lighting and thus is able to offer
1000 nits of full-screen brightness and adaptively up to 1600 nits on portions
of the screen, all of that with a contrast ratio of 1 to&hellip;. ONE MILLION.</p>
<p>As I was reading this, and later listening as the excitement led (&hellip;) me to
tune in to the video stream, one of my inner voices marvelled at the sheer
technological innovation on display (sorry can&rsquo;t stop) here.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m curious to see how this new class of supercomputer-level tablet device is
going to change how we humans interact with the digital world.</p>
<h2 id="oculus-quest-2">Oculus Quest 2</h2>
<p>On that topic&hellip;</p>
<p>On the weekend that we returned from vacation, we welcomed an <a href="https://www.theverge.com/21437674/oculus-quest-2-review-features-photos">Oculus Quest 2 VR
headset</a> into the family.</p>
<p>In the early 2000s, <a href="https://graphics.tudelft.nl/">the TU Delft Graphics research lab</a> that I was part of had
an AR / VR research line, so I got some exposure to state-of-the-art equipment
then.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 15 years, and the self-contained Oculus Quest 2 at $299 is
mind-blowingly good.</p>
<p>Specifically the head tracking is phenomenal.</p>
<p>Graphics elements in VR are rock-solid in virtual space as you move your head
(and yourself) around. The resolution is high enough that you could even work
on a document if you would like. With the most recent firmware update, Quest 2
now does 120 Hz.</p>
<p>In short, when you put on the headset, immersion is total.</p>
<p>No more outside world.</p>
<p>You can double tap on the side of the helmet to switch on reality (viewing your
surroundings through the 4 cameras mounted on the outside), and double tap to
switch reality off and go back into VR.</p>
<p>Facebook (they own Oculus) has some interesting work-focused ideas with this:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/5_bVkbG1ZCo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>When I saw that video for the first time, before having tried out the Quest 2,
I thought &ldquo;haha look at fb faking VR&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s pretty much spot-on.</p>
<p>(We&rsquo;re not playing office-office with the kids though, beat saber is much more
fun in 3D!)</p>
<h2 id="flip-it">Flip it</h2>
<p>During a recent chat with a busy friend, seeing if we could have coffee
somewhere, I reminded us both (you have to imagine this in Afrikaans, but
failing that in English with a thick Afrikaans accent):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Remember that the moments of relaxation and humanity are the anchors. All of
the rest should flow around that.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is so easy to forget.</p>
<p>We (and I also mean I) postpone the chat, or the run, or time with the family,
because of work.</p>
<p>It should be the other way round!</p>










<figure><a href="st_francis_sunset_watch_202104.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_b36de7acfc1e6653.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_4ba8d8a922c30068.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_d77a49f3e110f83.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_876d61fb3f2dd092.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_4ba8d8a922c30068.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Awesome ritual in St Francis where people make a whole celebration of the sunset. We were there thanks to GOU#1&rsquo;s tip."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Awesome ritual in St Francis where people make a whole celebration of the sunset. We were there thanks to GOU#1&rsquo;s tip.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #109: GABA</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 11:17:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/</guid><description> From now on, I would like to limit WHVs to bullets (really) or to named sections, to ease reading. DOWN WITH WALLS OF TEXT! After a multi-year, completely coincidental, break from medical imaging, I am back to The Real Business since the start of July. I am super excited about the plans we’re cooking up and executing. I can obviously not say too much, unless beer is involved, or you hang around here for muuuuuch longer. I think I am allowed to mention digital pathology and machine learning and beer. Last week we road-tripped up the East Coast to St Francis Bay, via Oudtshoorn and the Cango Caves. Pro tip: When road tripping with more than 0 (zero) children (babies count double; sick babies +5 hit points), and you have to stay overnight somewhere, invest extra in the biggest suite you (or your children’s college fund) can afford. On the beach in St Francis Bay (right in the middle of winter, you still seem to get these lovely balmy beach days), it seemed that everybody was surfing. Whole families, with the mom, the dad, all the kids, and grandma and grandpa, were all on various sizes of surfboards in the sea catching some waves. Here’s a photo from the furthest point on what I call “Not The Ugliest Jogging Route in The World” (in St Francis Bay): Last night I accidentally discovered that I can pinpoint the exact weekend and location when and where I first tasted my favourite trappist beer (EVER), namely Rochefort #8. It’s all written up in this 2003 post. When Google send me an email this weekend asking me exactly how I would like them to use my email (yes, a few months ago I migrated my mail empire back to Google because my self-hosting experiment had started to cost me time and money) to show me custom advertisements, I was reminded that I do actually find the machine learning models they’re building about me quite creepy, and that perhaps I would prefer not also handing them 12 years of emails to make their models more accurate. There and then I migrated said 12 years of emails from GMail to FastMail. So far I’m really impressed by the product, mostly due to the speed and the user experience of the web-app. There might be a more detailed post in the near future, let me know if you’re interested. Most surprising and interesting (to me) new scientific discovery of the week: A team of scientists at Northeastern University in Boston have shown that one of the many kinds of bacteria living in your stomach eats exclusively GABA, a really important brain chemical (neurotransmitter) that plays a role in keeping you calm. Based on this and other work, it looks like the bacteria in your tummy, also known as your gastrointestinal microbiota, besides being crucially important to your digestive system and your general survival, probably also play quite an important role in your psyche. I find this slightly mind-blowing. Have a great week kids, I hope to see you on the other side.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>From now on, I would like to limit WHVs to bullets (really) or to named sections, to ease reading. DOWN WITH WALLS OF TEXT!</li>
<li>After a multi-year, completely coincidental, break from <strong>medical imaging</strong>, I am back to <em>The Real Business</em> since the start of July. I am super excited about the plans we’re cooking up and executing. I can obviously not say too much, unless beer is involved, or you hang around here for muuuuuch longer. I think I am allowed to mention <strong>digital pathology</strong> and <strong>machine learning</strong> and beer.</li>
<li>Last week we <strong>road-tripped up the East Coast to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Francis_Bay">St Francis Bay</a></strong>, via Oudtshoorn and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cango_Caves">Cango Caves</a>.
<ul>
<li>Pro tip: When road tripping with more than 0 (zero) children (babies count double; sick babies +5 hit points), and you have to stay overnight somewhere, invest extra in the biggest suite you (or your children’s college fund) can afford.</li>
<li>On the beach in St Francis Bay (right in the middle of winter, you still seem to get these lovely balmy beach days), it seemed that <em>everybody</em> was surfing. Whole families, with the mom, the dad, all the kids, and grandma and grandpa, were all on various sizes of surfboards in the sea catching some waves.</li>
<li>Here’s a photo from the furthest point on what I call “Not The Ugliest Jogging Route in The World” (in St Francis Bay):</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/20160714_170901.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/20160714_170901-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<ul>
<li>Last night I accidentally discovered that I can pinpoint the exact weekend and location when and where I first tasted my <strong>favourite <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trappist_beer">trappist beer</a> (EVER)</strong>, namely Rochefort #8. It’s all written up in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/">this 2003 post</a>.</li>
<li>When Google send me an email this weekend asking me exactly <em>how</em> I would like them to use my email (yes, a few months ago I migrated my mail empire back to Google because <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">my self-hosting experiment</a> had started to cost me time and money) to show me custom advertisements, I was reminded that I do actually find the machine learning models they’re building about me quite creepy, and that perhaps I would prefer not also handing them 12 years of emails to make their models more accurate. There and then <strong>I migrated said 12 years of emails from GMail to <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/">FastMail</a></strong>. So far I’m really impressed by the product, mostly due to the speed and the user experience of the web-app. There might be a more detailed post in the near future, let me know if you’re interested.</li>
<li><em>Most surprising and interesting (to me) new scientific discovery of the week:</em> A team of scientists at Northeastern University in Boston <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/2095769-gut-bacteria-spotted-eating-brain-chemicals-for-the-first-time/">have shown</a> that <strong>one of the many kinds of bacteria living in your stomach eats exclusively <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-Aminobutyric_acid">GABA</a></strong>, a really important brain chemical (neurotransmitter) that plays a role in keeping you calm. Based on this and other work, it looks like the bacteria in your tummy, also known as your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gut_flora">gastrointestinal microbiota</a>, besides being crucially important to your digestive system and your general survival, probably also play quite an important role in your psyche. I find this slightly mind-blowing.</li>
</ul>
<p>Have a great week kids, I hope to see you on the other side.</p>
<p>P.S. Those bullets made for quite an impressive wall of text, didn’t they?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>