<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Death on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/death/</link><description>Recent content in Death on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 13:35:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/death/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #176: Cycle of life.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 13:35:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/</guid><description>Oh hai there friends.
Alles komt tot een einde. This WHV covers the weeks from Monday July 29 to Sunday August 25.
This period had more than its fair share of lows and highs.
Loss. On Saturday, August 3 we lost one of our clan mothers, quite unexpectedly.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to find the words to describe the sudden emptiness left behind by a loved one.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Oh hai there friends.</p>
<figure>
<a href="journeys_end.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hu_a1b6efc85d4d6175.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hu_c5a2d42fee6de4a4.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hu_cbc80298dac6b66d.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hu_2d39d1bc8519c08d.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hu_c5a2d42fee6de4a4.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>Alles komt tot een einde.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This WHV covers the weeks from Monday July 29 to Sunday August 25.</p>
<p>This period had more than its fair share of lows and highs.</p>
<h2 id="loss">Loss.</h2>
<p>On Saturday, August 3 we lost one of our clan mothers, quite unexpectedly.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to find the words to describe the sudden <em>emptiness</em> left behind by
a loved one.</p>
<p>It was a painful reminder of how much of our experience, and of our <em>selves</em>,
are built upon our bonds with those around us.</p>
<p>It was also a reminder of how much more deliberately and intently we should
dive into and <em>merge</em> with the atoms of each and every moment that we get to
spend with our fellow humans.</p>
<h2 id="reunion">Reunion.</h2>
<p>This year I again had the exquisite pleasure of bringing a short summer visit
to my Dutch family.</p>
<p>Although I sometimes wish that I had eidetic memory so that I could savour this
experience more accurately, I do seem to be looking back at a perfect few days.</p>
<p>The weather was typically Dutch: a tad grey, with some rain now and then. So
when the sun made a brief appearance now and then, our enjoyment was only
intensified.</p>
<p>Each hour and each minute was squeezed for every drop of experience and
togetherness that it had to offer.</p>
<p>Each moment was filled to the brim with our shared <em>humanness</em>.</p>
<p>Dutch family if you are reading this: Thank you.</p>
<figure>
<a href="moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu_9718b35c6ba2bd30.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu_388fa448fd85e39f.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu_fa1f8a90a7735b43.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu_ee5a148df6f19176.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu_388fa448fd85e39f.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption> At this specific moment, the legend that is Giorgio Moroder was
taking us on a trip through his, and our, musical history. We were stationed, not
altogether statically, on one of the upper floors of the Terrazia across from
the Heineken, experiencing one of those exquisitely perfect summer festival
moments.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>P.S. The <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">Weekly Head Voices series was <em>born</em> in the afterglow of Lowlands
2009</a>.</p>
<h2 id="celebration">Celebration.</h2>
<p>Somewhere during the past three weeks I added another birthday to my scarily
growing collection.</p>
<p>When I woke up on the relevant weekend morning, I had made the deliberate
decision to fill the day with as many as possible of my favourite things.</p>
<p>So:</p>
<p>I started the day with a run.</p>
<p>You would probably not say it if you looked at my running frequency over the
last few weeks (&ldquo;winter weather&rdquo; is all I can say), but this is definitely one
of my favourite activities ever. (I just checked: It seems I have now racked up
just over 1000km on sandals, and about 200km on bare feet.)</p>
<p>After that, I cooked up some pretty respectable Indian cuisine for my <em>inner</em>
circle, that is: genetic progenitor, genetic co-offspring (sibling man, you
have to keep up!), genetic offspring units and life partners.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s something really special about having one&rsquo;s peeps at the kitchen table
with good wine while one, also armed with some of the aforementioned good wine,
does one&rsquo;s best not to embarrass the recipe one has meticulously selected for
the occasion.</p>
<p>(In this case the journey was great, and even the dhal-based destination was
nothing to sneeze at!)</p>
<p>Finally, I made a point of getting out at least one blog post. It turned out to
be <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/08/25/format-flowed-with-long-lines/">a fairly technical
job</a>, but it
checked the relevant box.</p>
<p>As I was working through the list, my real-time life satisfaction meter (what
do you mean you don&rsquo;t have one?) soon became stuck at the 12/10 mark, at which
point I just stopped looking and focused everything I have on the people. 🤗</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>