<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>subscription on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/subscription/</link><description>Recent content in subscription on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 10:52:57 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/subscription/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>You can now also join the special head voices telegram group to stay up to date with this blog!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/11/18/you-can-now-also-join-the-special-head-voices-telegram-group-to-stay-up-to-date-with-this-blog/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2018 10:52:57 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/11/18/you-can-now-also-join-the-special-head-voices-telegram-group-to-stay-up-to-date-with-this-blog/</guid><description> As an alternative to the email list, I have just setup a telegram group which you could join if you’d like to be kept up to date with posts from this blog via instant messenger!
If all goes according to plan, a notification should be sent to the group automatically whenever I publish a post over here.
P.S. I first did this with IFTTT’s Telegram applet, but its post preview was pretty bad.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>As an alternative to the email list, I have just setup a <a href="https://t.me/headvoices">telegram group</a> which you could join if you’d like to be kept up to date with posts from this blog via instant messenger!</p>
<p>If all goes according to plan, a notification should be sent to the group automatically whenever I publish a post over here.</p>








<figure><a href="https://telegram.org/">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/5842a8fba6515b1e0ad75b03.png"
        
            alt="Logo image courtesy of http://www.stickpng.com/img/icons-logos-emojis/tech-companies/telegram-logo" width="50%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>P.S. I first did this with <a href="https://ifttt.com/applets/RXm2WDyZ-send-new-feed-items-to-a-telegram-chat">IFTTT’s Telegram applet</a>, but its post preview was pretty bad. <a href="http://thefeedreaderbot.com/">TheFeedReaderBot</a> seems to do a much better job!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Please update your email and RSS subscriptions (cpbotha.net)</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/12/24/please-update-your-email-and-rss-subscriptions-cpbotha-net/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:56:49 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/12/24/please-update-your-email-and-rss-subscriptions-cpbotha-net/</guid><description> Dear readers,
I will soon be starting a new life adventure. In fact, maybe even two of them. Hence, there is a significant probability that this weblog will again be updated more frequently in 2013.
Also, I have just changed the email and RSS subscription system:
If you were subscribed via email, please subscribe anew via the subscribe button to the right. If you still receive emails from feedburner concerning this blog, please unsubscribe using the instructions in those emails.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear readers,</p>
<p>I will soon be starting a new life adventure. In fact, maybe even two of
them. Hence, there is a significant probability that this weblog will again be
updated more frequently in 2013.</p>
<p>Also, I have just changed the email and RSS subscription system:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you were subscribed via email, please subscribe anew via the subscribe
button to the right. If you still receive emails from feedburner concerning
this blog, please unsubscribe using the instructions in those emails. The
idea is to stop using the feedburner email subscription (which was active
for the past few years) and to start using wordpress.com for this (the new
system).</li>
<li>If you were subscribed via RSS reader, double check that your feed address
is <a href="http://cpbotha.net/feed">http://cpbotha.net/feed</a> and NOT anything to do with feedburner
anymore. The feedburner feed should redirect to my own feed in any case.</li>
</ul>
<p>I hope that you have a fabulous vacation, and a happy and healthy 2013! I look
forward to seeing you then.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>