<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Gou-3 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-3/</link><description>Recent content in Gou-3 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #261: Father's day</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</guid><description>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.
Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive
The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.
&amp;ndash; Marcel Proust
Bliss It&amp;rsquo;s father&amp;rsquo;s day today.
When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250428_clarence_pano.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_9407df7811cef8cf.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_4f5b997776ce1c56.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_72fa3b251facc47.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp"
            

        
            alt="Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<blockquote>
<p>The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.</p>
<p>&ndash; Marcel Proust</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="bliss">Bliss</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s father&rsquo;s day today.</p>
<p>When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</p>
<p>Hearing that we were up, GOU #2 came out of her room, with a beautiful illustration she had made for (and of!) me. (GOU #2 has found her passion in drawing. She practises on most days, and her skill and talent are very obvious.)</p>
<p>Soon after, GOU #1 arrived home with flat whites (my favourite), fresh ciabatta and croissants from the bakery, and hugs.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m trying to say here is that when your offspring units all tell you in their different ways that they appreciate you being their dad, when you&rsquo;re fundamentally dedicated to and deeply grateful for being just that, and those very offspring units constitute the whole focus of this important life endeavour, you better hope that you are able to keep those eyes dry.</p>
<h2 id="vo-max-redux">VO₂ Max redux</h2>
<p>One of my <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">exercise goals for 2024</a> was to reach a VO₂ Max of at least (HAHAHA) 50.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t make it in 2024, but I also didn&rsquo;t do anything other than just my normal running during the year. I know that I should probably engage in some high intensity interval training of some sort if I really want to move the needle, but I run because I like running and not because I want to be fit, although I do want to be fit. (It&rsquo;s complicated being a teenager.)</p>
<p>At the start of 2025, I stated, much more softly this time, that I would maybe <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">still like to hit that 50 VO₂ Max</a>.</p>
<p>Again I realized I would have probably have to <em>do</em> something interval-ly about it, but again I kept on postponing.</p>
<p>WELL KIDS it turns out that postponing can also be a winning strategy! On Monday, May 19, my Garmin reported that I had indeed hit a VO₂ Max of 50, which, <a href="https://www8.garmin.com/manuals/webhelp/GUID-C001C335-A8EC-4A41-AB0E-BAC434259F92/EN-US/GUID-1FBCCD9E-19E1-4E4C-BD60-1793B5B97EB3.html">according to its tables</a>, places me at the bottom of the coveted top-most category for my age and gender, namely <em>Superior</em>.</p>
<p>I always knew it, but thanks anyways Garmin!</p>
<p>P.S. I do have to deflate my <em>superiority</em> a bit by reminding us all that, in addition to finding myself at the bottom of the superior range, I have also only recently entered my current age section, giving me an extra advantage. Jokes aside, 50 at 50 is not bad, so allow me to bask for a while.</p>
<h2 id="org-mode-timestamps-in-obsidian">org-mode timestamps in obsidian</h2>
<p>One feature I have really been missing in Obsidian since <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my recent break-up with Org-mode</a> is the amazing org timestamps.</p>
<p>There is no real convention in Obsidian, whilst in Org-mode timestamps <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Timestamps.html">are well-defined and quite functional</a>. My &ldquo;old&rdquo; notes are scattered with them: time ranges, scheduled times, deadlines, random timestamps inside random text notes.</p>
<p>The time logging script <a href="/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/#loggin-time">I mentioned previously</a> made use of the dataview-convention of adding timestamps to work items for example:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 (start:: 2025-05-20T07:55) - (end:: 2025-05-20T08:10)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; which did work but was no fun to work with.</p>
<p>Long story short, I could not resist for much longer, and so I hacked together a new Obsidian plugin called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian-org-timestamps">Org timestamps</a>.</p>
<p>As you can see in the comparative screenshots below, I&rsquo;ve copied the org-mode timestamp and time range format verbatim, with the additional bonus of rendering these timestamps nicely in preview mode, inspired by <a href="https://github.com/minad/org-modern">the Emacs package org-modern</a>.</p>
<p>Deviating from org-mode proper, my plugin also renders date-less timestamps &ndash; I often use these when adding entries to daily file. Speaking of which, full org timestamps can have <code>[[...]]</code> links around the date parts so that they link back to the relevant daily file.</p>








    


<figure><a href="obsidian-org-timestamps.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_e1ef46eb4edabd57.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_2719acebe5e07bc9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_f52dbf2785777e5.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>In addition to the rendering, the plugin also offers commands to move any timestamps to the nearest 5 minutes forward or backward, similar to what org-mode does with <code>shift-up/down</code>, and a feature I have always used multiple times per day.</p>
<p>Putting all of this together, my monthly time logging files now has entries that look like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 &lt;2025-05-20 07:55-08:10&gt;
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; and I can tweak those timestamps with the adjustment commands.</p>
<p>I have adapted the logging script to support both the old dataview-style and org-timestamp-style timestamps, and now the barely usable UX has become a tad less barely.</p>
<p><em>(10 minutes later&hellip;)</em></p>
<p>Because I keep on mentioning the script, I guess it&rsquo;s time to <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian_dataview_timelogging">put it online</a>, albeit extremely barely. Let me know in the comments below if you are the one other user on the planet who would like to try this.</p>
<h2 id="my-friend-this-is-the-end-again">My friend this is the end again</h2>
<p>This was one of the most stubborn WHVs I have pushed out in a very long time.</p>
<p>Before it became this hard, it used to be easier: Somehow there was always something to talk about, either interesting or entertaining, or both.</p>
<p>Although this could also just be another symptom of  me getting older, it does feel like the whole online landscape has changed quite substantially.</p>
<p>Up until recently, it was only dopamine-targeting social media which affected the way people read (or don&rsquo;t) blog posts, but these days I imagine that I&rsquo;m also detecting a whiff of AI-nihilism. Although I still feel strongly about writing each of these words by myself, the experience of the resultant output happens on the background of machines that can now generate hundreds of perfectly-written versions of this post in an instant.</p>
<p>Anyways, I plan to continue with this labour of love, even as it becomes increasingly difficult.</p>
<p>P.S. My recent reading / book-listening has taken me on fascinating journeys through neuroscience and consciousness. Before reaching this point right here, I mistakenly thought that I would share more about them in this post. Instead I&rsquo;m going to leave you with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I am not a thing in the world; I am the space in which the world is happening.</p>
<p>&ndash; Richard Lang</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #260: I'm not your guy, buddy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</guid><description>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.
The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. GOU #3 (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining. It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250322_palmiet_hike.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_94326a752c7d0837.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_3039937a478d9ff0.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_95661b4813429562.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&rsquo;s Bay. <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #3</a> (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining.  It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</p>
<p>A week or two later, GOU #3 recovered by being an absolute trooper through the whole of the slightly more substantial and absolutely brilliant 6.5km family hike all around the little <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/rreQJ7uyT1SFSKfJ7">Sea Farm private reserve&rsquo;s peninsula</a>. I tell myself, and others, that this is partially due to involving her in the progress of the event, by showing her at regular intervals on Google Maps exactly where we found ourselves, and how we were making progress around the peninsula.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, we will both have better answers to the question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why am I in such a rush to get through life when I want so much to enjoy it?</p>
<p>&ndash; Jan Chozen Bays</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(With that in mind, you might also find <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237</a> interesting!)</p>
<h2 id="the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-migrates-again">The whole cpbotha.net-hive migrates again</h2>
<p>Slightly more than five years after <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">the previous migration of the whole so-called cpbotha.net-hive from WebFaction (RIP) to Hetzner</a>, I got an offer I could not refuse, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/mackuba.eu/post/3ll7dgrep7c25">on Bluesky (!)</a>, for a <a href="https://www.netcup.com/en/server/vps/vps-1000-g11-12m-iv">netcup VPS</a> with double the number of vCPUs, double the RAM and 5x the storage, all for about 25% cheaper every month.</p>
<p>On the weekend of March 28 I managed to port the six websites in question across (3 easy static ones, including this blog, and 3 slightly more tricky wordpress ones).</p>
<p>I am most grateful that as part of this porting effort I have now finally been able to dockerize the binaries I built years ago of the super obscure <a href="https://github.com/ma-tech/WlzIIPSrv">WlzIIPSrv fork of the C++ IIP image slice server</a> and will in future be able to migrate much more easily if I ever need to do so again. WlzIIPSrv is the software that serves the pannable and zoomable histology slices when you browse a <a href="https://visible-orbit.org/slices/dk2904l-registered/">visible-orbit.org (wordpress site also hosted on this new server) stack like this one</a>.</p>
<p>Although this migration is a significant and positive technical event for me, most of you will probably not even notice that this site responds a tad (or three) more snappily than it used to.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am celebrating that this is officially the first blog post coming to you from this shiny new server!</p>
<h2 id="productivity-devolution">Productivity (d)evolution</h2>
<h3 id="just-get-it-done-with-kanban">Just get it done with Kanban</h3>
<p>Someone once called using Trello for task management &ldquo;the time management connoisseur equivalent of lying in the gutter with a cheap bottle of wine in a brown paper bag&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(So, by the way, that someone was me! See <a href="/2014/11/27/weekly-head-voices-86-beardy/#note-taking-and-todo-system-chaos-nerd-warning">the previous admission on this blog, in WHV #86 from 2014</a>, original source of my statement is <a href="https://noeskasmit.com/comparison-of-task-managers-rtm-astrid-wunderlist-todoist/#comment-71">this comment on Noeska&rsquo;s blog</a>.)</p>
<p>I mention this now, because my current system, the one which has to act as replacement for <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my almighty Emacs Org-mode</a>, is a monthly Kanban board with columns for &ldquo;todo&rdquo;, &ldquo;today / next&rdquo;, &ldquo;doing&rdquo; and &ldquo;done&rdquo;, and task cards that I can move, quite satisfyingly, from column to column, which is essentially a less full-featured but fully local version of my old Trello-based system.</p>
<p>While the 2014-org-mode-me mind really cannot comprehend this, the current system, based on the plugins <a href="https://github.com/mgmeyers/obsidian-kanban">obsidian-kanban</a> and <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/tasks/Introduction">obsidian-tasks</a>, is working just fine for the moment.</p>
<h3 id="pomodori-made-from-100-xbar">pomodori made from 100% xbar</h3>
<p>You might recall from the previous WHV that I was still <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#productivity-hack-of-the-year">using Emacs as an over-powered pomodoro timer</a>.</p>
<p>Well, even that started itching a bit too much, and now I&rsquo;ve just re-implemented the whole thing, along with the productivity boosting auto-DnD setting, by <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/xbar-pomodoro-timer-with-DnD-for-macOS">modifying an existing self-contained macOS xbar script</a> which you can use if you too wish to work harder.</p>
<h3 id="loggin-time">Loggin&rsquo; time</h3>
<p>Together with the pomodoro timing, I was also using org-mode to maintain detailed time logs for work, using the built-in org-clock functionality.</p>
<p>Because of above-mentioned itch, I now have a semi-usable replacement which I put together as an <a href="https://blacksmithgu.github.io/obsidian-dataview/api/code-reference/#dvviewpath-input">Obsidian Dataview custom view</a>, in other words, a bunch of javascript that piggy-backs on the dataview parser and groups bullet items with start and end timestamps under their parent tasks and container headings, as projects, in order to spit out daily and monthly timelog breakdowns.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve only been testing this since the start of April. Although it&rsquo;s giving me all of the data that I need, the UX is just barely over the threshold of usable-by-me.</p>
<p>Perhaps in the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll find some time to write more about this tool to hear what others think.</p>
<h2 id="the-bozo-explosion">The Bozo explosion</h2>
<p>My great friend Dave told me about this phenomenon, of which I then had to go find the source.</p>
<p>It turns out the originator is none other than Steve Jobs, with the idea being injected into the internet hive-mind by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_Kawasaki">Guy Kawasaki</a>, a Guy who worked for Jobs at Apple (I see what I&rsquo;m doing here) from 1983 until about 1986.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a short but great post by Guy Kawasaki titled <a href="https://guykawasaki.com/what-i-learned-from-steve-jobs/">What I Learned From Steve Jobs</a> which is definitely worth a few minutes of your time.</p>
<p>Here I want to focus on point 9, namely &ldquo;A players hire A+ players&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve personally seen this a number of times with the smartest and best leaders I&rsquo;ve ever had the privilege of interacting with. They, the A players, actively seek and appoint colleagues who are smarter or better than they are, the A+ players. They absolutely revel in the opportunity of being challenged by the best people they can find. This turns into a positive feedback loop, with more and more similarly capable people seeking out their peers.</p>
<p>The opposite of this happens when you start with B players. B players easily feel threatened by more capable folks, and so they tend to recruit C players so that they can maintain the pecking order. Those C players will accordingly recruit D players and so on. This process of course leads to what Jobs coined as &ldquo;the Bozo explosion&rdquo;, which sounds frighteningly similar to what is currently happening in some parts of the world today.</p>
<p>Next time when you&rsquo;re evaluating a new opportunity, do make some time to ensure that the folks involved have the A player mentality.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>For future me, here&rsquo;s a list of other notable events from the period under review:</p>
<ul>
<li>Two 50th celebrations.</li>
<li>Various very special eating and drinking occasions with treasured friends, some from afar, and family.</li>
<li>Three family hikes.</li>
<li>1 Sting concert (with my life partner) which exceeded all my expectations.</li>
<li>My first running race (Spookhill challenge).</li>
<li>Visits with Parisian friends and family to the breathtaking <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeitz_Museum_of_Contemporary_Art_Africa">Zeitz Museum of Contemporary Art Africa (MOCAA)</a> and the Two Oceans aquarium.</li>
<li>Far too many marshmallow eggs.</li>
</ul>
<p>&hellip; and with that, I would like to leave you with this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The trick is to learn how to want the things you already have.</p>
<p>&ndash; William B. Irvine</p>
</blockquote>








    


<figure><a href="zeitz_mocaa_ocular.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7e8591922bb9e2d9.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_426183b3ab1ebea9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7a603b5cd15f6d27.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp"
            

        
            alt="Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!-- "not your guy, buddy" from the South Park episode "Canada on strike" https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1211261/characters/nm0005295/ --> ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2024 to 2025 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to the year 2025!
We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this traditional yearly transition blog post here to keep you busy in the meantime.
The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2025!</p>
<p>We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this <a href="/tags/transition">traditional yearly transition blog post</a> here to keep you busy in the meantime.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20241228-st-francis-light-house.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a7c8fad0a4fb3336.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_c471bba5b301f4e3.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_7e36ecc6dd88d868.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp"
            

        
            alt="The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For those of you who are new here, 1) welcome! and 2) the traditional yearly transition post is where I both ramble semi-coherently on about the year that is closest to its conclusion and also speculate a bit about the year that is closest to its inception.</p>
<p>The main audience for this post is me &ndash; writing this up and the concomitant thinking and formulating bits form an important part of my maintenance process &ndash; but to anyone else who is reading this, there is hopefully something of value (or just a bit of entertainment) for you in these words. In any case, I am super happy that you&rsquo;re here!</p>
<h2 id="life-events">Life events</h2>
<p>In 2024, <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#i-turned-50">I turned 50</a> while <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#gou-1-turned-18">GOU#1 turned 18</a>, finished high school and is now on her way to university.</p>
<p>I mention these two in the same breath, because looking back it feels like the 5 years of her high school, a substantial chunk of time in terms of her development, went by in a flash.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s almost like we blinked <a href="/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">when she was still our little girl going to high school</a> and now suddenly she is an adult, and we finally feel like actual adults (aka old people) ourselves.</p>
<p>Although these have been amazing years for us, this experience of a whole period of life flashing by, through the lense of our children&rsquo;s development into adults, is a stark reminder to strive even harder to experience the living daylights out of every single moment that we are blessed with.</p>
<p>If all goes according to plan, we will have two more blink-blink-another-high-school-journey-is-complete experiences (GOU#2 is now in her second year of that journey, GOU#3 has a few years to go before she can start) so we should probably try to blink far less often.</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>After the dip both this blog and I went through in 2023 (total of 3 WHV posts&hellip;) and a very slow blogging start in 2024, it does feel like I might slowly be getting my WHV groove back, which seems to be evidenced by 66% more WHV posting in 2024, i.e. a whole 5 WHV posts! (Contrast this with the historic average of one post every two weeks.)</p>
<p>In the introduction to <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/">WHV #255 You lift me up</a> I speculate a bit about the reasons for my hiatus (I didn&rsquo;t mention there that maybe 2023 was actually just a real downer for me) and the current potential revival.</p>
<p>In addition to the posts here, I published <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">12 technical posts over on at the vxlabs</a> and a whole bunch of short howtos / recipes in the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">brand new TiL section of my other-OTHER website</a>. WHV #255 <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">explains the motivation behind the TiL section</a>.</p>
<p>I am also quite happy about the fact that I wrote a daily entry in my private diary for a large part of 2024, and this is something that I would like to continue, hopefully for an even larger part of 2025.</p>
<p>Spending some time every day to review that day, where the review is enriched by the deliberate activitity of trying to formulate everything into a story that I can write down, helps me to make sense of everything.</p>
<p>Writing in general seems to modulate positively my experience of reality.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a lot about this idea in various posts on this blog, but allow me to surface <a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#the-describers">two relevant sections from WHV 180</a>, and especially the quote below (but you should go read those two sections):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less faulty entity.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>My secret running goal for 2024 was to do 25km of running every week. In my head this was auto-simplified to 1200km for the year (you know, the way one often calculates a month as 4 weeks), but of course we&rsquo;re talking 1300km.</p>
<p>Well, I failed at all of these goals!</p>
<p>However, I did manage to run a total of 1149.7km over the year, which comes to an average of 22.1km per week, which I am pretty OK with. I had over 100 hours of fun (I truly enjoy running) and no injuries that I can remember.</p>
<p>The training calendar below shows that August was my laziest month, but that&rsquo;s because August has the worst weather, and because I was away for a week visiting my Dutch family and getting many tens of thousands of dancing steps instead. The calendar also shows how I made a last ditch effort in December to close the gap with my goal as much as possible.</p>










<figure><a href="20250101-strava-training-calendar.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_e13adc1c4101c63a.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_2caa5fcc1a219359.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_57229ed99a10234e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You might remember <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">my three metrics-focused goals from last year&rsquo;s post</a>, namely 50 consecutive push-ups, VO<sub>2</sub> Max of at least 50 and a resting state heart rate of 50 or under&hellip;</p>
<p>Well, 50 consecutive push-ups was not that hard, Apple Health reports my average resting state heart rate for 2024 as 48 BPM (this would be mostly via my Garmin Forerunner 245 and more recently 265) but my VO<sub>2</sub> briefly peaked at 49 (some time after I turned 50) before settling back on 48. I  would have loved that 50, but <a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/blog/fitness/whats-a-good-vo2-max-for-me/">48 is not the worst for a man of my age</a>.</p>
<p>My real goal for the coming year is the same as last year: I want to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>The older I get and the more I learn, the more I understand that with exercise, the more hours I can spend every week doing it, of course maintaining balance with the rest of my life (see life systems further down), the better my meat-coated skeleton will work, and the happier the ghost driving it will be.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’re a ghost driving a meat-coated skeleton made from stardust; what do you have to be scared of?</p>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2022/10/13/ghost-stardust/">@rat_sandwich on twitter, January 31, 2013</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>P.S. of course I will again go for 25km of running per week. I think logging substantially more than 120 hours of activities in Strava will be good. I might even give that VO<sub>2</sub> Max goal another shot.</p>
<p>P.P.S. I read <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/outlive/">Peter Attia&rsquo;s book Outlive</a> a few months ago. This is a detailed and practical manual for healthy living. There&rsquo;s a lot in there, but at the core he wants you, while you still have any say in the matter, to become as fit (measured by our friend VO<sub>2</sub> Max) and as strong (measured by grip strength) as you possibly can. You see, from middle age we&rsquo;re all on a downward curve, and there&rsquo;s not much we can do about it, except ensuring that we start as high as possible.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. It&rsquo;s funny; back in school, I thought little of athleticism, because it was a jock thing, and the jocks were generally not very kind to nerd-kind (my people). Now that I&rsquo;m older and quite ironically due to my nerdy lifelong learning habits, I strive for us much athleticism as I can &ldquo;fit&rdquo; in (jock joke harr harr).</p>
<h3 id="diet">Diet</h3>
<p>During this post&rsquo;s generously long incubation, I thought it worth adding here my approach to eating.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been practising 16-8 time-restricted eating (intermittent fasting in some circles) about 95% of the time since somewhere in 2019. I first <a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">wrote about it in WHV 186</a>, and then in <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#i-really-don-t-like-breakfast">WHV 221 I came out and stated the beef I have with breakfast</a> (that pun might be too heavy for this post).</p>
<p>Anyways, while I still believe that breakfast is bad for most people, I know that the scientific world has not yet reached consensus on time-restricted eating for healthy folks.</p>
<p>However, there is considerably more consensus that lowering daily caloric intake is good for most people.</p>
<p>For me, 16-8 TRE, where I simply don&rsquo;t ingest anything besides water and black coffee from about 7 in the evening until about noon the next day, is an extremely practical and especially low-effort way to reduce caloric intake.</p>
<p>When I do eat, the portions are modest, I try to stick to natural and unprocessed where I can and I keep an eye on protein.</p>
<p>When I do break these rules, I do so with deliberation. Great food, great wine, great beer and the company of friends and family, especially when combined, constitute a perfect reason to break all of these rules.</p>
<p>In short, reduce caloric intake, increase per-calorie value and/or enjoyment!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and Tools</h2>
<p>This is the place where I summarise (read: ramble on about) the current state of my digital tools and systems. If you&rsquo;re going to skip a (nerdy) section, this is the one! You can dive back in at <a href="#life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</a>.</p>
<p>I am one of those people who <em>regularly</em> finds and uses information from notes that I made.</p>
<p>If I have the note, and I often do because I make an effort to write stuff down with the lowest possible friction but the highest possible chance of being found again, this is generally miles faster than finding the information online, even with tools like the <a href="https://kagi.com/">premium search engine Kagi</a> which I have been using regularly for a few weeks now.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-and-obsidian">Emacs and Obsidian</h3>
<p>A year ago I <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#systems-and-tools">experienced a bit of a crisis of (Emacs) faith</a>.</p>
<p>Whilst that was more of a clash between the either-or poles of Emacs and Obsidian, I am now at a place where I&rsquo;m finding increasing uses for Obisidian as an <em>additional</em> note-taking tool, working on the same collection of hundreds of org-mode and a growing number of markdown files.</p>
<p>Emacs and org-roam treat <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">markdown files as if they are native org-roam nodes</a>. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/BBazard/obsidian-orgmode-cm6">Benoit Bazard&rsquo;s fantastic new CodeMirror 6 org-mode plugin for Obsidian</a> and my <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Monitor-rclone-cron-job-with-Home-Assistant">rclone + syncthing syncing setup for iPhone</a>, I have semi-usable org database support on my phone.</p>
<p><a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> and since recently <a href="https://orgro.org/">Orgro</a> are great for editing org files in the iPhone, but they are missing the searching and discovery, let&rsquo;s call it <em>note management</em>, aspects of a tool like Obsidian.</p>
<p>Long but quite important-to-me story short, it looks like for the time being I&rsquo;ll continue to use both Emacs and Obsidian for note-taking. Because interoperability is not perfect, there will be some natural gravitational pull towards the one or the other which I have decided to explore.</p>
<p>At the moment, it looks like I might be writing more of my atomic notes as markdown files, whilst using org for the lab journal / logbook and project management type of notes.</p>
<p>On a deeper note, the Obsidian team is doing fantastic work.</p>
<p>Apart from their <a href="https://stephango.com/file-over-app"><em>file over app</em> philosophy</a>, Obsidian is <em>programmable</em> as can be witnessed by the thriving extension ecosystem.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?id=ai-chat-as-md">written a modest extension</a> to test this out from the inside. The programmability is not as extensive as that of Emacs, but it runs everywhere, even on mobile devices, and it might be extensive enough for the note-taking platform that Obsidian has become.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Emacs on and off since the late 90s, but for the past 10 years it has become an always-running and integral part of my life. It feels really strange, disconcerting if I&rsquo;m being honest, that it seems to be losing its core spot.</p>
<p>I console myself in these moments with the observation that science must trump dogma, always.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m writing this post in Emacs.</p>
<h4 id="til">TiL</h4>
<p>Thanks to Obsidian, my other, OTHER website <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">now has a &ldquo;today I learned&rdquo; (TIL) section</a> at <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">charlbotha.com/til</a>, published directly from a sub-directory of my main notes directory.</p>
<p>The benefit is that there is even less friction than usual and, perhaps more importantly, the psychological friction has also been reduced because I have convinced myself that the posts there are just notes and not true blog posts.</p>
<h3 id="honorable-tool-mentions-zotero-and-quarto">Honorable tool mentions: Zotero and Quarto</h3>
<p>After <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#omnivore-is-no-more">my distastrous recommendation of Omnivore turned into a disaster</a>, it is with some emotional trepidation but intellectual confidence (thanks to file over app and its staunchly open source nature) that I can re-recommend Zotero as a reference (of all kinds!) management tool for the long term.</p>
<p>After I last mentioned it on my blog, I have been using it quite intensively, and <a href="https://bsky.app/hashtag/zotero?author=charlbotha.com">I keep on running into delightful features</a>, like the built-in PDF reader&rsquo;s pop-up visualization of citations and image references.</p>
<p>A more recent but high power entry into my toolbelt is <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, which I will contend strikes a fantastic usability-power balance in the world of technical document and presentation authoring. I&rsquo;ve now used it, in anger, to write a fairly extensive technical document, along with the afore-mentioned Zotero and <a href="https://retorque.re/zotero-better-bibtex/">Better BibTeX</a> for reference management, and the experience was magically smooth. To seal the deal, by the end I used Quarto to generate an attractive-looking docx for interoperability with the other stakeholders, but my contact time with Word was mercifully minimised.</p>
<h3 id="my-micro-blogging-history-2008---2025">My micro-blogging history 2008 - 2025</h3>
<p>Twitter says I created my account there in December of 2008. However, <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">this blog here says I only started using it in April of 2009</a>. (Twitter first launched in July of 2006.)</p>
<p>Some years later in 2016, coincidentally right before the previous Trumpocalypse, I wrote a post naively suggesting that we should <a href="/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/">replace twitter with something better (blogs&hellip;)</a> due to the risk of Twitter possibly going bad (ahem) and to the observation then that it was (then already) doing a crappy job keeping out abusive users (AHEM).</p>
<p>That post <a href="/2016/11/20/look-mom-hacker-news-front-page/">reached the front page of Hacker News</a>, and was thus read and discussed over there (and probably in the comments here) by tens of thousands of nerds, and a surprisingly small share of the usual &ldquo;Ackchyually&rdquo;-Bros.</p>
<p>(Please allow me this little tangent: A mental model that will really ease your time on sites like HN and reddit, is that the person on the other side, especially when they come across as super confident and assertive, is probably <strong>not</strong> an expert, not even by a long shot, on the topic that they are so confidently mansplaining. In fact, they are probably the least qualified to say anything. ChatGPT avant le lettre one might say. Ok back to your regular programming&hellip;)</p>
<p>Needless to say, my specific idea of replacing twitter with&hellip; blogs and rss was not implemented by the internet, at least not at that point&hellip;</p>
<p>When Musk acquired Twitter in October of 2022, the writing started appearing on the wall, at first vaguely, but with more and more definition as the months went on. I started looking for micro-blogging alternatives that were not twitter.</p>
<p>At first Mastodon looked too complicated, but then someone setup a <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#emacs-mastodon-server-was-irresistible">mastodon server dedicated to Emacs and I was immediately sold</a>.</p>
<p>However, Mastodon indeed turned out to be too complex and fundamentally quite fragile (all but the larger instances have a just a volunteer human or two behind them), leading to the owner of my favourite instance bascially being harassed to such an extent that it was better for him to get out of this business and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@cpbotha/113340325817581254">shut the Emacs mastodon server down</a>.</p>
<p>When I saw this announcement, I was disheartened.</p>
<p>When I read that Mastodon supports message export, but not message import, meaning that my posts would languish in a sad archive file somewhere, I was convinced that I had to try something out that was not Mastodon.</p>
<p>In parallel to my Mastodon efforts, I did also try Threads and was quite enthusiastic about its scale, and the speed with which Meta managed to build it, but I didn&rsquo;t manage to get any sort of interaction there. I think that it might be more geared for the Instagram model of influencers broadcasting to large groups of followers, in contrast to a more collaborative setup. (Urgh, the recent news about Meta&rsquo;s new &ldquo;free speech&rdquo; overhaul is additional motivation for me to spend even less energy there.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, it turns out that the newer and shinier microblogging service Bluesky was conceived in 2019 with the goal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluesky">&ldquo;to find or develop an open and decentralized standard for social media that would give users more control over their data and experience&rdquo;</a>, precisely the sort of thing that has suddenly become even more painfully relevant with the advent of the Trumpocalypse part deux, now with more Musk-power.</p>
<p>Long story short, in a very short time, Bluesky has proven to be almost exactly the microblogging platform that I enjoy participating in. Lots of human interaction, no ads, many different user-contributed algorithms to choose from, including just seeing the stuff your people post, in the order that they post it &ndash; it really feels like the thing was put together with semi-normal human interaction as the central concern.</p>
<p>Up to now, it also feels like <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#bluesky-is-my-new-micro-blogging-thing-of-choice">many folks on there prefer being decent to each other</a>, something I militantly (haha) support.</p>
<p>Some mastodon folks are downright unhappy with bluesky, because they feel that it&rsquo;s not truly decentralized like mastodon.</p>
<p>Thing is, Bluesky has chosen a different spot on the usability - decentralization spectrum, and and my opinion is exactly usable and decentralised enough for what it needs to be and do at this moment in time.</p>
<p>Looking slightly further into the future, there are well-funded initiatives like <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/13/24342799/free-our-feeds-social-media-ecosystem-at-protocol-bluesky">Free our feeds</a>, ideologically and technologically supported by the Bluesky company but otherwise unconnected, which has amongst its <a href="https://freeourfeeds.com/">goals to &ldquo;build independently hosted infrastructure (a second &lsquo;relay&rsquo;) so that Bluesky users, developers and researchers always have full access to the stream of content and data no matter what the company decides to do in future&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>If you would like to know more, Faine Greenwood has written <a href="https://little-flying-robots.ghost.io/the-great-bluesky-migration-i-answer-some-of-your-questions/">this great Bluesky explainer</a>.</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</h2>
<p>My Life Systems are the guiding principles, rules, personal values and bags of tips that I have explicitly defined and refined over the years to help me be the best human that I can be.</p>
<p>Note: I write these up primarily as a reminder to myself. If it comes across as prescriptive, please remember that I&rsquo;m telling <em>me</em> how to live my life. I can do this, because I <em>am</em> the boss of me.</p>
<h3 id="core">Core</h3>
<p>You&rsquo;ll be happy to hear that the core of my Life Systems 2025 is exactly the same as the previous edition <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">Life Systems 2024</a>, except for the version number increase, and the concomitant price increase. (taking a leaf here from the Intel playbook!)</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to read <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">the 2024 write-up</a>, here is the compressed version:</p>
<p><em>Guiding principles:</em> 1. Love 2. Science. <em>Two no three rules for achieving great success in life, or just surviving, whichever comes first:</em> 1. Be useful. 2. be likable and 3. evolve. <em>Personal values:</em> 1. Be kind. 2. Be grateful. 3. Attend fully to the now. 4. Enjoy life with family and with my friends. 5. Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers. 6. Be there for my family. 7. Add value through work. 8. Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise. 9. Build and/or fix something. 10. Learn new things. 11. Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</p>
<h3 id="balance">Balance</h3>
<p>What I have been thinking about this year, especially when things get quite busy, is the sometimes tricky practice of applying balance to one&rsquo;s personal values.</p>
<p>A straight-forward example is when important work obligations start impacting my sleep or exercise schedule, in which case I have to apply balance and tone down slightly the ambition to fulfil personal value no 7.</p>
<p>It can easily get more tricky however; when something on that list of personal values, which is important to you, starts taking up more than its fair share of energy, that will come at the cost of all of the other endeavours that you value.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have a hard and fast rule for this, only the measure of remembering to <em>pay attention</em> also at that meta-level so that one can make suitable balancing adjustments when required.</p>
<h3 id="work-hard-party-hard-rest-hard">Work hard. Party hard. Rest hard.</h3>
<p>A lesson that has only become clearer for me over the years is that we humans function best when we are able to focus on one thing at a time, and when we have as few things as possible on the list that we select from.</p>
<p>This works at all scales of life, from what task do I work on during this half-hour all the way up to my main priority for today, or my three main priorities for this year.</p>
<p>The challenge in applying this lesson is three-fold:</p>
<ol>
<li>Know which thing to focus on at any time,</li>
<li>reduce switching between things and yet</li>
<li>get to all of the things that you should get to.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you have all three of these covered, then comes the truly difficult part: <strong>Attend fully to the now.</strong></p>
<p>Those of us who are lucky get about 4000 weeks of life.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not truly present in the thing that you&rsquo;ve chosen at this moment, you are not using that allotted time to its fullest extent.</p>
<p>You can never ever get that time back.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like you&rsquo;re in a Michelin-starred restaurant, and instead of going power level 9000 with all of your senses and your thoughts and your whole being into <em>experiencing</em> that food with your favourite human(s), you&rsquo;re scrolling on your phone, absent-mindedly shovelling forkfuls into your mouth.</p>
<p>Do the opposite.</p>
<p>Pick your battles, but sometimes also choose a party if you can and don&rsquo;t forget to rest like your life depends on it. Whatever you do, be the most maximally present in the thing you&rsquo;ve chosen. Presence and attention improve with regular practice.</p>
<p>In short: Work hard, party hard, rest hard.</p>
<!-- be maximally present to use that time right; do everything HARD -- came during my 2025-01-11 morning run -->
<h2 id="my-2024-to-2025-transition-wishes">My 2024 to 2025 transition wishes</h2>
<p>Humans<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> <em>at their peak</em> are a thing of beauty.</p>
<p>Above all they are truly kind.  They live and breathe the knowledge that we <em>homo sapiens</em> are at our absolute best when we connect with each other.</p>
<p>Peak humans are graceful, and they are elegant, and they are in harmony &ndash; the best sort of balance &ndash; with their surroundings, with those around them and with themselves.</p>
<p>Attaining this peak is hard. Maintaining it is nigh impossible. Best we can go for is <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">the never-ending practice</a> of these characteristics, and an eternal striving for moments to <em>become them</em>.</p>
<p>Friends, I wish you and your connected ones the willpower to strive for grace and elegance and harmony, and the presence of mind to attend fully to those perfect moments when they occur.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, you might be one of these&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 9 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/10/daily-head-voices-2024-week-9/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/10/daily-head-voices-2024-week-9/</guid><description>Monday 2024-02-26 started the morning (and the work week!) with stupid indecision: Had all my work gear in the car, but chose to drive back home after dropping of GOU#3 for a logistical task which one of my other clan members would gladly have taken care of. Indecision irrelevant against the backdrop: We had such a good time in the car first being on time (GOU#3 loves that), then listening to Skrillex together, then talking, and then performing our morning ritual of verbally attesting our super-infinite love for each other as I drop her off at school. During highly technical demo outside of my domains, used perplexity in real-time to lookup various details as the demo was going on, and thus could focus on the really interesting questions for the presenter. Between meetings, struggled a bit to focus in the focusy bits, but managed to do quite a bit of work eventually (with focusapp and some deep house) and even got milestones done. Tuesday 2024-02-27 Super frustrated during the morning rush, because could not find running shoes at the critical moment when we had to leave for school Reverted to backup shoes (old ones, with too many kilometres on them) Good run in L&amp;amp;Z, but it took so long to disconnect from my shoe moment, in spite of really putting my mind to it. Succeeded a little bit at the end, shocked at the mental cost of something this trivial. BTW, it was almost a textbook &amp;ldquo;not inside it&amp;rsquo;s on top!&amp;rdquo; situation. Wednesday 2024-02-28 For once some Waking Up in the morning! (I once had a streak of more than a year. Currently happy if I do just one!) Started the day in pensive mood (before and after the meditation) thinking about what I would like from the future Naturally I wanted to write a note, so then I tapped out a topic in the daily list so that I could use org-roam-node-find-similar to surface similar notes from the past. I did find the correct historic note which I would not have otherwise, but then I got sucked into emacs config&amp;hellip; why has my org-roam-node-find-* never done live preview like other consult commands? &amp;ndash; solved by installing https://github.com/jgru/consult-org-roam/tree/main and then tooting about it: https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/112008312753264000 During the day I was surprised at the amount of traction that toot got. It seems there are more people who missed this. It seems it can sometimes really help to share the minutiae. realised that org-roam-node-find-similar did not sort the similar nodes by similarity, so fixed that: https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity/commit/d940c12e70468adfbc1e41ef997c5f797540ebf7 After extricating myself back out of Emacs config yak shaving, I did spend some quality time writing up my thoughts, helping to clarify them. I don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer yet, but the direction I&amp;rsquo;m moving in feels good. Lunch with inner circle friend and mentor DMW at No Way Jose was great thank you! Thursday 2024-02-29 Run at shortly after 7. Legs did not really want to cooperate. Got distracted by meetings day at work, so almost no writing in the daily. Now, [2024-03-10 Sun 18:35], I&amp;rsquo;m really sorry. Friday 2024-03-01 Pool repair at my house. They are able to pump out all water, repair floor of pool, then pump all water back all in a few hours. I have two ideas for the weekend Build and publish a QRCode contact card generator using marimo and wasm build a telegram bot to manipulate my org-mode database, e.g. adding tasks, searching for existing tasks and notes. I don&amp;rsquo;t like this second idea, but it keeps on coming back to me. Saturday 2024-03-02 12km run with tired legs, so tired that I decided to stop the fast and get Powerade for the last 5km, which felt like it really helped. Super happy that I could get the promised marimo-wasm-qrcode generator online: https://vxlabs.com/2024/03/02/contact-qrcode-generator-with-marimo-and-wasm/ Sunday 2024-03-03 After sunday morning coffee and scrolling, dug into marimo to see if there&amp;rsquo;s some way to create the WASM locally. There does not seem to be. Scanned through https://core.telegram.org/bots to see (again&amp;hellip;) what might be possible. Actually, now I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about the idea of making a telegram bot that sends me random tasks from my org-mode every day. I already have a proof of concept in Python that uses emacsclient to expose org-roam nodes via API (see https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas ) so I would probably follow a similar path, probably with something like org-ql. Does anyone know if something like this exists somewhere? Apple&amp;rsquo;s Journal app, that suggests a new journalling possibility now and then, made me think that this could help. In iTerm2, press the Option-Cmd keys together to make a rectangular selection. Sublime lunch at Millhouse Kitchen with inner circle family Back home, tried to get MobileOrg going again; looked promising, but then after successful sync ran into this bug with empty outlines in the app when synced via iCloud. 😥 Configured perplexity via gptel in my Emacs; I am especially interested in using perplexity&amp;rsquo;s sonar-online internet-capable models.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-02-26">Monday 2024-02-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>started the morning (and the work week!) with stupid indecision: Had all my work gear in the car, but chose to drive back home after dropping of GOU#3 for a logistical task which one of my other clan members would gladly have taken care of.
<ul>
<li>Indecision irrelevant against the backdrop: We had such a good time in the car first being on time (GOU#3 loves that), then listening to Skrillex together, then talking, and then performing our morning ritual of verbally attesting our super-infinite love for each other as I drop her off at school.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>During highly technical demo outside of my domains, used perplexity in real-time to lookup various details as the demo was going on, and thus could focus on the really interesting questions for the presenter.</li>
<li>Between meetings, struggled a bit to focus in the focusy bits, but managed to do quite a bit of work eventually (with focusapp and some deep house) and even got milestones done.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-02-27">Tuesday 2024-02-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super frustrated during the morning rush, because could not find running shoes at the critical moment when we had to leave for school
<ul>
<li>Reverted to backup shoes (old ones, with too many kilometres on them)</li>
<li>Good run in L&amp;Z, but it took so  long to disconnect from my shoe moment, in spite of really putting my mind to it. Succeeded a little bit at the end, shocked at the mental cost of something this trivial.</li>
<li>BTW, it was almost a textbook &ldquo;not inside it&rsquo;s on top!&rdquo; situation.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-02-28">Wednesday 2024-02-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>For once some <a href="https://www.wakingup.com/">Waking Up</a> in the morning! (I once had a streak of more than a year. Currently happy if I do just one!)</li>
<li>Started the day in pensive mood (before and after the meditation) thinking about what I would like from the future
<ul>
<li>Naturally I wanted to write a note, so then I tapped out a topic in the daily list so that I could use <code>org-roam-node-find-similar</code> to surface similar notes from the past. I did find the correct historic note which I would not have otherwise, but then I got sucked into emacs config&hellip;
<ul>
<li>why has my <code>org-roam-node-find-*</code> never done live preview like other consult commands? &ndash; solved by installing <a href="https://github.com/jgru/consult-org-roam/tree/main">https://github.com/jgru/consult-org-roam/tree/main</a> and then tooting about it: <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/112008312753264000">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/112008312753264000</a>
<ul>
<li>During the day I was surprised at the amount of traction that toot got. It seems there are more people who missed this. It seems it can sometimes really help to share the minutiae.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>realised that <code>org-roam-node-find-similar</code> did not sort the similar nodes by similarity, so fixed that: <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity/commit/d940c12e70468adfbc1e41ef997c5f797540ebf7">https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity/commit/d940c12e70468adfbc1e41ef997c5f797540ebf7</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>After extricating myself back out of Emacs config yak shaving, I did spend some quality time writing up my thoughts, helping to clarify them.
<ul>
<li>I don&rsquo;t know the answer yet, but the direction I&rsquo;m moving in feels good.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lunch with inner circle friend and mentor DMW at No Way Jose was great thank you!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-02-29">Thursday 2024-02-29</h2>
<ul>
<li>Run at shortly after 7. Legs did not really want to cooperate.</li>
<li>Got distracted by meetings day at work, so almost no writing in the daily. Now, <span class="timestamp-wrapper"><span class="timestamp">[2024-03-10 Sun 18:35]</span></span>, I&rsquo;m really sorry.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-03-01">Friday 2024-03-01</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pool repair at my house. They are able to pump out all water, repair floor of pool, then pump all water back all in a few hours.</li>
<li>I have two ideas for the weekend
<ul>
<li>Build and publish a QRCode contact card generator using marimo and wasm</li>
<li>build a telegram bot to manipulate my org-mode database, e.g. adding tasks, searching for existing tasks and notes.
<ul>
<li>I don&rsquo;t like this second idea, but it keeps on coming back to me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-03-02">Saturday 2024-03-02</h2>
<ul>
<li>12km run with tired legs, so tired that I decided to stop the fast and get Powerade for the last 5km, which felt like it really helped.</li>
<li>Super happy that I could get the promised marimo-wasm-qrcode generator online: <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/03/02/contact-qrcode-generator-with-marimo-and-wasm/">https://vxlabs.com/2024/03/02/contact-qrcode-generator-with-marimo-and-wasm/</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-03-03">Sunday 2024-03-03</h2>
<ul>
<li>After sunday morning coffee and scrolling, dug into marimo to see if there&rsquo;s some way to create the WASM locally. There does not seem to be.</li>
<li>Scanned through <a href="https://core.telegram.org/bots">https://core.telegram.org/bots</a> to see (again&hellip;) what might be possible.</li>
<li>Actually, now I&rsquo;m thinking about the idea of making a telegram bot that sends me random tasks from my org-mode every day. I already have a proof of concept in Python that uses emacsclient to expose org-roam nodes via API (see <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas</a> ) so I would probably follow a similar path, probably with something like org-ql. Does anyone know if something like this exists somewhere?
<ul>
<li>Apple&rsquo;s Journal app, that suggests a new journalling possibility now and then, made me think that this could help.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In iTerm2, press the Option-Cmd keys together to make a rectangular selection.</li>
<li>Sublime lunch at Millhouse Kitchen with inner circle family</li>
<li>Back home, tried to get MobileOrg going again; looked promising, but then after successful sync ran into <a href="https://github.com/MobileOrg/mobileorg/issues/292">this bug with empty outlines in the app when synced via iCloud</a>. 😥</li>
<li>Configured perplexity via gptel in my Emacs; I am especially interested in using perplexity&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/hub/blog/introducing-pplx-online-llms"><code>sonar-online</code> internet-capable models</a>.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 7 of 2024: Rest For Success</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/18/daily-head-voices-week-7-2024/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 17:42:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/18/daily-head-voices-week-7-2024/</guid><description> Most people in high-stress, decision-making industries are always operating at this kind of simmering six, as opposed to the undulation between just deep relaxation and being at a 10. Being at a 10 is millions of times better than being at a 6. It’s just in a different universe. &amp;ndash; Josh Waitzkin (see Sunday below)
Monday 2024-02-12 I really enjoyed this Rolling Stone article about Nine Inch Nails&amp;rsquo; Head Like a Hole Yes, that&amp;rsquo;s also a subtle jab at those of you who read last week&amp;rsquo;s title and did not get the reference. :P Extreme almost asymptotic anger moment at Outlook PWA: Spent time crafting a detailed meeting description. Unrelated meeting notification came in, meeting edit dialog disappears, all of those beautiful words gone. Forever. Accidentally upgraded Emacs to 29.2 (brew upgrade if you must now, and there it went building emacs along with installing all the other smaller dependencies, the ones I actually had in mind) Added ad-hoc similar node search for org-roam-similarity (that links to the new function&amp;rsquo;s documentation) This means you can also select any text, or just use the whole current buffer as your input, and then get a completing read list of similar nodes to open The area of my forehead around the scar feels like it has substantial nerve drop-out. I can&amp;rsquo;t feel much there, and I also can&amp;rsquo;t actuate much. The reconstructive surgeon warned before the time that this might be the case. Thanks again cancer. I&amp;rsquo;m crossing my fingers that there&amp;rsquo;s still some recovery that needs to happen and this is not my forehead&amp;rsquo;s final form. bitbar is now xbar. It looks like xbar can eat RAM https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725 I looked this up, because during my previous macOS phase I contributed code to bitbar to support Lua plugins. That work is now gone. Oh well. What a craptastically unproductive day. I had all of the time, and in that time I utterly failed at my selected task. I did some other interesting and possibly valuable stuff, but the majority of the time was wasted. Old lesson on this blog: some days gonna be crap However, responded to this by reviving my old FocusApp licence (see pro-tip #2 in WHV #126) and installed on my machine Tuesday 2024-02-13 First day back at the office. Lots of conversations due to the giant scar criss-crossing over half my forehead. Implemented the new (but very very old) &amp;ldquo;avoid all social media during work hours except a little bit on your phone during real breaks&amp;rdquo; rule. Using terminal Emacs for some remote work, because reasons Bothersome delay when pressing escape to get out of insert mode into normal mode. IT WAS TMUX. https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868 Noticed how much I rely on the cursor shape to know in what mode (insert, normal, emacs) I am. Fortunately found https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer and it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;hellip; game changer. Today was much fun at the office. Also much higher productivity due to above-mentioned no-social-media-goofing-off-rule. Wednesday 2024-02-14 Happy Valentine&amp;rsquo;s day everyone! Utterly crazy this morning because load-shedding, but due to GOU#3 being so very on time we left at 7:05 and could avoid most of that chaos. 6.5km short run just to get back into it, after 1.5 weeks out thanks to surgery and recovery. Garmin not happy with my fitness, but man it felt good. Went to doctor&amp;rsquo;s rooms to have stitches removed. Kind and professional nurse left the stitches in the middle, because skin there still needed some time to relax into the new situation. Feels really good to have the others out. Will go back on Friday for the rest. Pro-tip: it was a bit of a change management challenge, but I&amp;rsquo;ve converted my household to the new shopping list support in Apple Reminders. If you&amp;rsquo;re an Apple family, this woks much better than a WhatsApp group named &amp;ldquo;Shopping&amp;rdquo;. True story. Thanks to said app, remembered to get flowers. FocusApp really did its work today. I&amp;rsquo;m a tiny little bit bummed that no-one picked up on the Head like a Hole reference from last week&amp;rsquo;s Daily Head Voices. Or maybe someone did, but they just have not contacted me about it. Hopefully this week&amp;rsquo;s title does better. SUCH A GOOD DAY today thank you! Thursday 2024-02-15 Pretty busy day with meetings (Thursday is secondary meeting day at work after all), good conversations with colleagues, and an internal product playbook workshop. Friday 2024-02-16 Sublime run in Land &amp;amp; Zeezicht (school district) right after dropping off GOU#3, which also helped to avoid most of the traffic back home, again utterly crazy due to the 6 - 8:30 AM load-shedding slot disabling some critical (for us) traffic lights. Best afternoon ever: Father and daughter picnic with GOU#1 (school event, so many other fathers and daughters) at Zorgvliet Wine Estate In the evening, got my work inbox unread email count to just under 4000. Thank you for coming to my TED talk. Spent a bit more time reading about the new and open source Observable Framework I&amp;rsquo;ve always liked the ObservableJS notebooks, but this new development which supports working locally and self-hosting is really exciting! marimo is very nice for experimentation, but big advantage of OF is that it builds a static site as output. marimo needs Python to be running on the server. Again that idea: How automatically could I push a completely new OF built dashboard to a newly allocated CloudFlare pages site? Tried it out on Sunday evening (IN THE FUTURE): Was really quick to get the intro dashboard going in my case with pnpm, but a big challenge at this moment is the developer experience: There is very little coding assistance of any kind as you work on the javascript code blocks in the markdown pages. Hopefully they will be able to improve this with a vscode extension and/or a web-based editing experience, like marimo. Tried out Thunderbird 115.7 on the macbook. Much better than the TB 115 experience I had just after its release on Windows, where its currently selected mail logic handled it very badly when I archived a mail. I am trying out TB, because I miss the today, yesterday, last week date grouping. Saturday 2024-02-17 Woke up with low body battery (Garmin). Somewhat surprised, because only two beers last night. Perhaps the stress of the arguments, and probably still the alcohol because I&amp;rsquo;m old now. Wrote some Mojo to see if I could create a Pandas DataFrame and write to disc as Parquet. I love parquet. Although Mojo is still missing some data structures, it was not too involved to use the imported numpy and pandas libraries to do this job. Smoked snoek braai (so good! 🤤) at friend LM&amp;rsquo;s place with more friends. Sunday 2024-02-18 Super enjoyable 13km run. Not too hot, just a little bit of wind, and enough energy to finish strong. George Mack makes the statement: &amp;ldquo;There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.&amp;rdquo; This might indeed be a controversial statement, but I really like that his advice is to focus on the quality and purity of one&amp;rsquo;s rest (a very mindful idea), leading to much more energy for intensity 10 work. See his tweet (also embedded below, but please do click on &amp;ldquo;show more&amp;rdquo;) for a bunch of interesting examples. Figured out that it&amp;rsquo;s pretty easy to setup &amp;ldquo;Smart Mailboxes&amp;rdquo; on Apple Mail for today, yesterday, last week and so on. Truly sublime lunch with family at Stables on Vergelegen wine estate. Semi-controversial opinion: There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.
1. Winston Churchill used to work 16 hours per day in his old age during the war — but he also worked in bed every day until 11am. He had a nap after lunch, and a 2 hour nap… pic.twitter.com/kyiAuTEwjA</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Most people in high-stress, decision-making industries are always operating at this kind of simmering six, as opposed to the undulation between just deep relaxation and being at a 10. Being at a 10 is millions of times better than being at a 6. It’s just in a different universe. &ndash; Josh Waitzkin (see Sunday below)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="monday-2024-02-12">Monday 2024-02-12</h2>
<ul>
<li>I really enjoyed this <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-features/nine-inch-nails-head-like-a-hole-anthem-900750/">Rolling Stone article about Nine Inch Nails&rsquo; Head Like a Hole</a>
<ul>
<li>Yes, that&rsquo;s also a subtle jab at those of you who read last week&rsquo;s title and did not get the reference. :P</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Extreme almost asymptotic anger moment at Outlook PWA: Spent time crafting a detailed meeting description. Unrelated meeting notification came in, meeting edit dialog disappears, all of those beautiful words gone. Forever.</li>
<li>Accidentally upgraded Emacs to 29.2 (<code>brew upgrade</code> if you must now, and there it went building emacs along with installing all the other smaller dependencies, the ones I actually had in mind)</li>
<li>Added ad-hoc similar node search for <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity?tab=readme-ov-file#key-bind-the-ad-hoc-similarity-search">org-roam-similarity</a> (that links to the new function&rsquo;s documentation)
<ul>
<li>This means you can also select any text, or just use the whole current buffer as your input, and then get a completing read list of similar nodes to open</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The area of my forehead around the scar feels like it has substantial nerve drop-out. I can&rsquo;t feel much there, and I also can&rsquo;t actuate much. The reconstructive surgeon warned before the time that this might be the case. Thanks again cancer. I&rsquo;m crossing my fingers that there&rsquo;s still some recovery that needs to happen and this is not my forehead&rsquo;s final form.</li>
<li>bitbar is now xbar. It looks like xbar can eat RAM <a href="https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725">https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725</a>
<ul>
<li>I looked this up, because during <a href="/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/#new-laptop">my previous macOS phase</a> I contributed code to bitbar to support Lua plugins. That work is now gone. Oh well.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What a craptastically unproductive day. I had all of the time, and in that time I utterly failed at my selected task. I did some other interesting and possibly valuable stuff, but the majority of the time was wasted.
<ul>
<li>Old lesson on this blog: <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning">some days gonna be crap</a></li>
<li>However, responded to this by reviving my old FocusApp licence (see pro-tip #2 in <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">WHV #126</a>) and installed on my machine</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-02-13">Tuesday 2024-02-13</h2>
<ul>
<li>First day back at the office. Lots of conversations due to the giant scar criss-crossing over half my forehead.</li>
<li>Implemented the new (but very very old) &ldquo;avoid all social media during work hours except a little bit on your phone during real breaks&rdquo; rule.</li>
<li>Using terminal Emacs for some remote work, because reasons
<ul>
<li>Bothersome delay when pressing escape to get out of insert mode into normal mode. IT WAS TMUX. <a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868">https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868</a></li>
<li>Noticed how much I rely on the cursor shape to know in what mode (insert, normal, emacs) I am. Fortunately found <a href="https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer">https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer</a> and it&rsquo;s a &hellip; game changer.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Today was much fun at the office. Also much higher productivity due to above-mentioned no-social-media-goofing-off-rule.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-02-14">Wednesday 2024-02-14</h2>
<ul>
<li>Happy Valentine&rsquo;s day everyone!</li>
<li>Utterly crazy this morning because load-shedding, but due to GOU#3 being so very on time we left at 7:05 and could avoid most of that chaos.</li>
<li>6.5km short run just to get back into it, after 1.5 weeks out thanks to surgery and recovery. Garmin not happy with my fitness, but man it felt good.</li>
<li>Went to doctor&rsquo;s rooms to have stitches removed. Kind and professional nurse left the stitches in the middle, because skin there still needed some time to relax into the new situation. Feels really good to have the others out. Will go back on Friday for the rest.</li>
<li>Pro-tip: it was a bit of a change management challenge, but I&rsquo;ve converted my household to the new shopping list support in Apple Reminders. If you&rsquo;re an Apple family, this woks much better than a WhatsApp group named &ldquo;Shopping&rdquo;. True story.
<ul>
<li>Thanks to said app, remembered to get flowers.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>FocusApp really did its work today.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m a tiny little bit bummed that no-one picked up on the Head like a Hole reference from last week&rsquo;s Daily Head Voices. Or maybe someone did, but they just have not contacted me about it.
<ul>
<li>Hopefully this week&rsquo;s title does better.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>SUCH A GOOD DAY today thank you!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-02-15">Thursday 2024-02-15</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pretty busy day with meetings (Thursday is secondary meeting day at work after all), good conversations with colleagues, and an internal product playbook workshop.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-02-16">Friday 2024-02-16</h2>
<ul>
<li>Sublime run in Land &amp; Zeezicht (school district) right after dropping off GOU#3, which also helped to avoid most of the traffic back home, again utterly crazy due to the 6 - 8:30 AM load-shedding slot disabling some critical (for us) traffic lights.</li>
<li>Best afternoon ever: Father and daughter picnic with GOU#1 (school event, so many other fathers and daughters) at Zorgvliet Wine Estate</li>
<li>In the evening, got my work inbox unread email count to just under 4000. Thank you for coming to my TED talk.</li>
<li>Spent a bit more time reading about the new and open source <a href="https://observablehq.com/framework/">Observable Framework</a>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve always liked the ObservableJS notebooks, but this new development which supports working locally and self-hosting is really exciting!</li>
<li>marimo is very nice for experimentation, but big advantage of OF is that it builds a static site as output. marimo needs Python to be running on the server.</li>
<li>Again that idea: How automatically could I push a completely new OF built dashboard to a newly allocated CloudFlare pages site?</li>
<li>Tried it out on Sunday evening (IN THE FUTURE): Was really quick to get the intro dashboard going in my case with <code>pnpm</code>, but a big challenge at this moment is the developer experience: There is very little coding assistance of any kind as you work on the javascript code blocks in the markdown pages. Hopefully they will be able to improve this with a vscode extension and/or a web-based editing experience, like marimo.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Tried out Thunderbird 115.7 on the macbook.
<ul>
<li>Much better than the TB 115 experience I had just after its release on Windows, where its currently selected mail logic handled it very badly when I archived a mail.</li>
<li>I am trying out TB, because I miss the today, yesterday, last week date grouping.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-02-17">Saturday 2024-02-17</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up with low body battery (Garmin). Somewhat surprised, because only two beers last night. Perhaps the stress of the arguments, and probably still the alcohol because I&rsquo;m old now.</li>
<li>Wrote some Mojo to see if I could create a Pandas DataFrame and write to disc as Parquet.
<ul>
<li>I love parquet.</li>
<li>Although Mojo is still missing some data structures, it was not too involved to use the imported numpy and pandas libraries to do this job.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Smoked snoek braai (so good! 🤤) at friend LM&rsquo;s place with more friends.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-02-18">Sunday 2024-02-18</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super enjoyable 13km run. Not too hot, just a little bit of wind, and enough energy to finish strong.</li>
<li>George Mack makes the statement: &ldquo;There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.&rdquo;
<ul>
<li>This might indeed be a controversial statement, but  I really like that his advice is to focus on the quality and purity of one&rsquo;s rest (a very mindful idea), leading to much more energy for intensity 10 work.</li>
<li>See <a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1759122352036577546">his tweet</a> (also embedded below, but please do click on &ldquo;show more&rdquo;) for a bunch of interesting examples.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Figured out that it&rsquo;s pretty easy to setup &ldquo;Smart Mailboxes&rdquo; on Apple Mail for today, yesterday, last week and so on.</li>
<li>Truly sublime lunch with family at <a href="https://vergelegen.co.za/restaurants/stables-at-vergelegen/">Stables on Vergelegen wine estate</a>.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-dnt="true"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Semi-controversial opinion: There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.<br><br>1. Winston Churchill used to work 16 hours per day in his old age during the war — but he also worked in bed every day until 11am. He had a nap after lunch, and a 2 hour nap… <a href="https://t.co/kyiAuTEwjA">pic.twitter.com/kyiAuTEwjA</a></p>&mdash; George Mack (@george__mack) <a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1759122352036577546?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 18, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 4 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-22 As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&amp;rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS! At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&amp;hellip; Short but really nice streamlit demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually played with it. Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3. In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola. Tuesday 2024-01-23 At the office nice and early (7:30). Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at react-flow and comfyui react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY! streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &amp;ldquo;things I learned&amp;rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document. Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&amp;rsquo;s a zero day vulnerability in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites. Wednesday 2024-01-24 8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW! Remember kids: Our spine&amp;rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally. This is also the reason why I&amp;rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair. Lovely working lunch with friend S at No Way José Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work: idea: make github so that people can pipx install marimo-turbo to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on. idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS &amp;hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844 (post is also embedded below) idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&amp;gt; nginx -&amp;gt; supervisord -&amp;gt; tornado systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation I would prefer to use supervisord for this This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick? ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &amp;ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&amp;rdquo; googling blog post: https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/ the kubernetes thing: https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&amp;rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via iframe.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-22">Monday 2024-01-22</h2>
<ul>
<li>As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &ldquo;When you&rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS!</li>
<li>At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&hellip;</li>
<li>Short but really nice <a href="https://streamlit.io/">streamlit</a> demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&rsquo;ve never actually played with it.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3.
<ul>
<li>In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-23">Tuesday 2024-01-23</h2>
<ul>
<li>At the office nice and early (7:30).</li>
<li>Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at <a href="https://reactflow.dev/">react-flow</a> and comfyui
<ul>
<li>react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see <a href="https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary">https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary</a>
<ul>
<li>it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster</li>
<li>marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &ldquo;things I learned&rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document.</li>
<li>Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&rsquo;s a <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/news/apple-issues-urgent-security-updates-to-fix-zero-day-flaw-update-your-iphone-and-mac-right-now">zero day vulnerability</a> in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-24">Wednesday 2024-01-24</h2>
<ul>
<li>8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot</li>
<li>dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work</li>
<li>right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW!
<ul>
<li>Remember kids: Our spine&rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally.</li>
<li>This is also the reason why I&rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lovely working lunch with friend S at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/NoWayJoseSomerset">No Way José</a></li>
<li>Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work:
<ul>
<li>idea: make github so that people can <code>pipx install marimo-turbo</code> to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on.</li>
<li>idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap
<ul>
<li>sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets</li>
<li>in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS
<ul>
<li>&hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844</a> (post is also embedded below)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&gt; nginx -&gt; supervisord -&gt; tornado
<ul>
<li>systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: <a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation">https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation</a></li>
<li>I would prefer to use supervisord for this</li>
<li>This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&rdquo; googling
<ul>
<li>blog post: <a href="https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/">https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/</a></li>
<li>the kubernetes thing: <a href="https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s">https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0" width="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><script src="https://emacs.ch/embed.js" async="async"></script>
<h3 id="til-mastodon-embeds-are-not-as-durable-as-twitter-embeds">TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds</h3>
<p>As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via <code>iframe</code>.</p>
<p>With twitter, you get more self-contained HTML which will render even when twitter or just the original tweet don&rsquo;t exist anymore.</p>
<p>This is probably just another reason to figure out how I can get more low-friction microblogging going on my own websites so that the embedding implementations of other microblogging sites become irrelevant.</p>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-25">Thursday 2024-01-25</h2>
<ul>
<li>Took a look at <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/connections/connect-networks/get-started/">cloudflare tunnels</a> to expose marimo and other dashboards to the internet
<ul>
<li>great that I can use my existing domains for this, and I can route between multiple domains to multiple locally running services</li>
<li>some more steps to setup, but it did not take more than about 5 minutes, and gives me even more options than tailscale funnels. OPTIONS MAN!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At work, quickly got react-flow&hellip; flowing. SHINY!</li>
<li>In the evening, found <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/">https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/</a> which is the new Shortcuts based way, based on the old AppleScript way, of getting a <code>message://</code> link onto the clipboard.
<ul>
<li>You <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#email-linking">might recall from this blog</a> that <code>message://</code> are the most durable and cross-platform way to link to emails from your notes (or anywhere else)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-26">Friday 2024-01-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up to cool, overcast weather, a big change from a series of 30℃ + days. Really had to resist going out for a run (normal run day + that amazing coolness), because of Wednesday&rsquo;s partially pulled back muscle not being 100% yet.</li>
<li>Worked on mystery visualization project (react-flow)</li>
<li>Lovely and energising lunch with previous colleague and friend. Happy that I reached out on Thursday although they have a packed schedule because only in country for limited time. I guess this is quite related to <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">calling up your friends</a>, with a ping of serendipity salt.</li>
<li>I was shocked by how well and fast <a href="https://ollama.ai/">ollama</a> worked on my MacBook. See embedded tweet below.</li>
<li>Almost at the end of the afternoon, friend S and I went to some more friends for the first Weiss-off, that is, a Weiss beer tasting contest. It was huge fun blind-tasting 10 different Weiss beers, ranking them, trying to identify them (so much harder than I thought!), and then having them revealed at the end.
<ul>
<li>Between the experts there (read: us), Stangen Weiss Bier came out on top, followed by Weisbier No5 and Jack Black Atlantic Weiss. The fourth place was shared by Erdinger and CBC Amber Weiss.</li>
<li>My favourite, Stellenbrau Jonkersweiss, is glaringly absent from the top. I&rsquo;ll live, probably consoled by just such a Jonkersweiss. Super happy that Amber Weiss and Atlantic are both present!</li>
<li>There was a trophy (for the taster who could blind-identify the most beers in the Weiss-off), which we have christened the <em>David Weisselhoff wisseltrofee</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">With <a href="https://twitter.com/MistralAI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@MistralAI</a>&#39;s Mistral 7B at Q4_0 on this MacBook M1 Pro 10C / 16C, <a href="https://twitter.com/ollama?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ollama</a> looks like it&#39;s easily 3 times faster than the new MLX 0.0.11 (with GGUF support).<br><br>It&#39;s subjectively (visually) faster, and the tokens/s measurements confirm this. <a href="https://t.co/9vyluimLKK">pic.twitter.com/9vyluimLKK</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1750824125419942036?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 26, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-27">Saturday 2024-01-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yesterday&rsquo;s Wonderful Weiss-off also had some, thankfully quite minor, effect the next morning, but I went out for a careful weekday distance run, which fortunately went without a hitch. Just very hot thanks.</li>
<li>Went to Buco and then to <a href="https://appletoolandgas.com/">Apple Tool and Gas</a> to find the rest of the screws I needed to repair the shower door. Friendly gentleman at Apple even sawed some of my screws to size! Shower door back in operation.</li>
<li>Updated my &ldquo;old&rdquo; M1 MBA to macOS 14.3 and then reset to transfer to GOU#1&rsquo;s iCloud. Say what you want about Apple, but that part of their stuff works <em>really</em> well.</li>
<li>Left for Betty&rsquo;s Bay at about 16:00 with GOUs #1 and #2. The rest of the family already there.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-28">Sunday 2024-01-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up in Betty&rsquo;s Bay after a longer than normal night of sleep, but Garmin body battery was still not completely happy.</li>
<li>In spite of having run yesterday and still feeling a bit tired (see body battery above), I had the best run of the month so far in Betty&rsquo;s. Go figure.</li>
<li>Spent some time with Canva &ndash; what a great resource for doing nice designs, even flow charts &ndash; but not sure where I could use this.</li>
<li>Background thought through the past weeks, and mentioned on Tuesday: I would really like to do (and promite) more TIL-style writing at work and at home. See <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/">Simon Willison&rsquo;s amazing TIL collection</a> for inspiration.</li>
<li>Ran into <a href="https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines">https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines</a> a Python library that can guarantee structured text generation from many LLMs, e.g. 100% valid JSON according to a specified schema. What makes it different from similar libraries? &ldquo;Unlike other libraries, regex-guided generation in Outlines is almost as fast as non-guided generation.&rdquo;</li>
<li>I already had <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/autogen">AutoGen</a> on my list for experimenting with multi-agent LLM applications, but now it has been joined by <a href="https://github.com/joaomdmoura/crewAI">crewAI</a> which I have also just ran into (thanks reddit!) and which seems to have significant support online.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Monday 2024-01-01</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/02/daily-head-voices-on-monday-2024-01-01/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 17:36:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/02/daily-head-voices-on-monday-2024-01-01/</guid><description> Typing this note in the fresh new 2024-01-Jan.org file, in the completely fresh new journals/2024/ directory. Had to fetch GOU#1 from her NYE party in Hermanus, where they had been focusing more on the party parts and less on the sleeping parts. On the way back, stopped at my aunt and uncle in Onrust to give best wishes for the new year in person. Slipped and talked about AI a bit. Oops. Back home, read to GOU#3 (now 7) what I wrote about her in this blog when she was born, and at various points since then. Seeing her reaction makes this activity even more worth it. (pro-tip: Tag post with the GOU in question!) Read about the evolution of aging, the mutation accumulation (MA) and the antagonistic pleiotropy (AP) hypotheses in https://www.nature.com/scitable/knowledge/library/the-evolution-of-aging-23651151/ during the preparation of my traditional year transition blog post. Not depressing at all! Reclining on sofa, back almost horizontal, with laptop on lap, is an underrated ergonomic lifehack.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Typing this note in the fresh new <code>2024-01-Jan.org</code> file, in the completely fresh new <code>journals/2024/</code> directory.</li>
<li>Had to fetch GOU#1 from her NYE party in Hermanus, where they had been focusing more on the party parts and less on the sleeping parts.</li>
<li>On the way back, stopped at my aunt and uncle in Onrust to give best wishes for the new year in person. Slipped and talked about AI a bit. Oops.</li>
<li>Back home, read to GOU#3 (now 7) what I wrote about her in this blog when she was born, and at various points since then. Seeing her reaction makes this activity even more worth it. (pro-tip: Tag post with the GOU in question!)</li>
<li>Read about the evolution of aging, the mutation accumulation (MA) and the antagonistic pleiotropy (AP) hypotheses in <a href="https://www.nature.com/scitable/knowledge/library/the-evolution-of-aging-23651151/">https://www.nature.com/scitable/knowledge/library/the-evolution-of-aging-23651151/</a> during the preparation of my <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional year transition blog post</a>. Not depressing at all!</li>
<li>Reclining on sofa, back almost horizontal, with laptop on lap, is an underrated ergonomic lifehack.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #190: 3=4.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 15:38:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</guid><description> Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok, because that's how life is. Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!
This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to Sunday March 8, 2020.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hu_e8fa884e0959fa6f.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hu_390734a1cd990820.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hu_d75900d0fff18d5.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hu_afcee184974f8438.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hu_390734a1cd990820.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was
still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok,
because that's how life is.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to
Sunday March 8, 2020.</p>
<p>(I had made a good start on the post on March 8, but then the work week and a
bunch of homing missile deadlines hit. As I write this bit, it is Saturday
March 14, 14:30 SAST.)</p>
<h2 id="gou-3-turns-4">GOU #3 turns 4!</h2>
<p>Our third Genetic Offspring Unit, creative named GOU #3, fairly recently
completed another year of life.</p>
<p>She has now collected the grand total of 4.</p>
<p>It was a pleasure celebrating her birthday with her as it felt like this was
the first time that she was intellectually fully present.</p>
<p>With apparent ease she even understood the sometimes tricky concept of having
one&rsquo;s party on a different day than one&rsquo;s birthday.</p>
<p>For future us, I would also like to note that her pronunciation and sentence
construction are growing more and more precise, sometimes even overly so, the
observation of which delights me.</p>
<p>GOU#3, if you read this years and years in the future: We can already see that
you are an amazing human being. We are deeply happy that you have come here to
join our clan.</p>
<h2 id="new-pair-of-altras-acquired">New pair of Altras acquired.</h2>
<p>In an unexpected but quite happy turn of events, it is starting to look like I
might have to take part in a trail run in July.</p>
<p>(Charl from the future: Only if my finicky ankles man up between now and then.)</p>
<p>Once I&rsquo;ve actually done it, and I&rsquo;m still able to tell the tale, I will surely
do so.</p>
<p>Because I am one of the World&rsquo;s Worst Trail Runners, I will definitely have to
step up my training between now and then.</p>
<p>As with many other endeavours in life, an important component of all of this is
acquiring suitable shoes.</p>
<p>Because <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">my giant-toe-box-zero-drop
Escalantes</a> have been treating
me very well, I had soon narrowed it down to any one of the Altra trail shoes:
Superiors (minimalist), Lone Peaks (jack-of-all-trades), Timp (sightly more
support) and Olympus (maximalist-ish).</p>
<p>After having read all of the internet regarding the different Altra trail
shoes, I reluctantly came to the conclusion that none of them really knocked it
out of the park.</p>
<p>Anyways, one Sunday I walked into our local sports super store (I&rsquo;m sorry my
fellow nerds), and it so happened that they had a pair of Lone Peak 4.5s in my
size: GINORMOUS CLOWN SHOE SIZE.</p>
<p>Trying them on, I tripped and fell right into the psychological black hole of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases">biases</a> and
<em>instantly</em> convinced myself that these were the shoes for me.</p>
<p>Fast forward a week of calling my behavioural insurer (starts with a Disco ends
with a Y) every single day, and they finally managed to figure out what was
wrong somewhere deep in their unfortunately quite sub-par IT systems, and
flipped the <a href="https://www.discovery.co.za/vitality/fitness-booster-shoe">Shoe Purchase Gamification
switch</a>.</p>
<p>In short, if you are able to activate this feature (you have to be super
patient and a bit stubborn), said insurer will subsidise the purchase of a pair
of running shoes based on how often you exercise every week.</p>
<p>This is one neat way of making your running addiction work for you, if you can
somehow absorb the possibly substantial startup cost, i.e. the hours you have
to spend on the phone with the friendly support agents.</p>
<p>Behold my beautiful new trail running shoes:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hu_31640770d2089a71.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hu_47681907a9bde6d1.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hu_4201425aad6b6684.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hu_29895110859f8aef.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hu_47681907a9bde6d1.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>State-of-the-art trail-running shoes for the World's Worst Trail
Runner.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="crabby-wallet">Crabby Wallet!</h2>
<p>After years of eyeing Fido U2F and FIDO2 hardware security keys on the
internet, I finally took the plunge and acquired <a href="https://www.yubico.com/product/security-key-nfc-by-yubico">a Yubico Security Key
NFC</a>.</p>
<p>Up to now I used mostly the LastPass Authenticator app and more recently Authy
to generate OTPs as second factor (2FA) for most of my important accounts.</p>
<p>(BTW, if you&rsquo;re not yet using 2FA for your important accounts, such as email,
now is the best time to upgrade. I would recommend getting <a href="https://authy.com/">the Authy
app</a> because it optionally supports multi-device
synchronization.)</p>
<p>The YubiCo hardware device is supposed to be more secure than authenticator
apps due to domain hashing, and it&rsquo;s pretty cool that you don&rsquo;t have to copy
across 6-digit codes, but what I didn&rsquo;t foresee as clearly was the following
simple difference:</p>
<p>I almost always have my phone with me. However, I don&rsquo;t always have my keyring
with me.</p>
<p>I set out to find a new wallet to replace my already pretty minimalist fake
leather credit card booklet. The new wallet had to be at least as minimalist,
but it had to have some sort of lanyard to which I could attach the security
key.</p>
<p>I was delighted to discover that (of course) there&rsquo;s a whole community of
minimalist wallet enthusiasts on the internet.</p>
<p>I was even more delighted when I discovered that the Crabby Wallet C3, a
second-generation product of a <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1369622196/the-crabby-wallet-a-wallet-that-is-not-for-everyon">super successful 2015
kickstarter</a>,
was available all the way down here!</p>
<p>Behold the minimalist wonder that is my new Crabby Wallet:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu_6dfcdc0ea91c0c86.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu_c5f90a9cd0895d27.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu_4048a1188eadfdb1.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu_a56739669ff9aebb.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu_c5f90a9cd0895d27.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The Crabby Wallet C3. As you can see, it's only slightly larger than a credit
card. It's made of canvas which looks pretty durable. After a breaking-in
period, it easily holds up to 10 cards. Sometimes there's even cash stashed
under the rubber-band.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>(Charl from 6 days in the future writes: This looks like it&rsquo;s going to be a
keeper. It&rsquo;s more compact and more secure than my previous credit card booklet,
and it has become much more ergonomic after the initial break-in period.)</p>
<h2 id="the-end-of-this-post">The end of this post.</h2>
<p>Thank you for connecting with me here!</p>
<p>Remember, it&rsquo;s now Saturday March 14, 15:26 SAST, but this post will forever
act like it finds itself on Sunday March 8.</p>
<p>I hope that tomorrow I can write WHV #191, a less complicated post that will
come into being not too far away from the moment that is its observation point.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Do you feel like you have an observation point, a specific location that is
your momentary source of perception and thought?</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been getting back into the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up guide</a>, and
there are some truly delightful exercises of the all-encompassing
consciousness.</p>
<p>Remember: <em>There is no observation point!</em></p>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu_72b2408429c6c9e.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu_e445bb81feba1de2.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu_2fb8cddafc9b6536.jpg 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu_e445bb81feba1de2.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #165: Get in my Pocket.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 15:01:20 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/</guid><description>This short WHV looks back at the week from Monday March 4 to Sunday March 10.
In the week after that, I had actually decided not to publish this one, instead folding whatever I wanted to say into the next edition.
However, fear of yet another much-too-long WHV, along with my current preference for a short warming-up of the writing pipes, have led me to change my mind, and so here we are!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This short WHV looks back at the week from Monday March 4 to Sunday March 10.</p>
<p>In the week after that, I had actually decided not to publish this one,
instead folding whatever I wanted to say into the next edition.</p>
<p>However, fear of yet another much-too-long WHV, along with my current
preference for a short warming-up of the writing pipes, have led me to change
my mind, and so here we are!</p>
<p>This post consists of a really short life part, followed by a longer nerdy
pro-tip for the storage and retrieval of your web references.</p>
<h2 id="gou3-turns-3">GOU#3 turns 3.</h2>
<p>It seems like <a href="/2016/05/05/weekly-head-voices-106-ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/">just the other day when Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3 joined
us</a> here in the warm and fuzzy Humanist Kingdom of WHV.</p>
<p>Well, the &ldquo;beautiful pink little not-yet-walking but rapidly expanding
cellular mega-city&rdquo; never stopped expanding, and is currently surprising us
every day with the new ways in which her neural network processes and
transforms the reality she finds herself in.</p>
<h2 id="replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">Replacing Pocket with Just a Bunch Of PDFs (JBOP).</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been a happy user of Pocket Premium since October 23, 2016, when they
cleverly offered me a locked discount on the annual plan.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m a sucker for a deal, and I needed something with which to store archive
versions of interesting blog posts and other web resources.</p>
<p>It served me well, as I frequently access and share especially
research-related articles and blurbs, such as <a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161122193100.htm">this one</a> discussing the
observation that aspartame (a sugar substitute found in popular fizzy drinks)
interferes with some of your enzymes, possibly resulting in more weight gain
that straight sugar!</p>
<p>(For Real Academic Articles, i.e. RAA-RAA, I am still a huge fan
of <a href="https://www.zotero.org">Zotero</a>. If Zotero had better mobile access, I would have used it for
these straight web references also.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, recently the new beta pocket interface was failing me horribly as I
was trying to find the exact article mentioned up above.</p>
<p>Typing &ldquo;glu&rdquo; or &ldquo;glucose&rdquo; was unsuccessful in finding another article
&ldquo;Artificial sweeteners induce glucose intolerance by altering the gut
microbiota&rdquo;, even although I could see that exact article in the overview
screen. To add insult to injury, searching for &ldquo;aspartame&rdquo; also did not find
that entry, although I had explicitly tagged it with &ldquo;aspartame&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It could very well be that this is just a (serious) glitch in the beta system,
but it was a frustrating reminder that for something as important (to me) as
my collection of references (aka “argument-winning potion”), I was
at the mercy of someone else, with almost no other recourse.</p>
<p>This frustrating led me to find an alternative solution, which became&hellip; a big
ol&rsquo; bunch of PDFs! (call this JBOP, inspired by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-RAID_drive_architectures">JBOD</a>)</p>
<p>In order to do this, we need a method of turning web-pages into readable PDFs,
and some system for the storage and retrieval of said PDFs.</p>
<h3 id="use-a-browser-with-ad-blocking-and-reader-mode">Use a browser with ad-blocking and Reader Mode</h3>
<p>The general idea is to use a browser with ad-blocking and some sort of reader
mode, and then to print to PDF.</p>
<p>On desktop, I am using <a href="https://brave.com">Brave Browser</a> because of the great
built-in ad-blocking, and because I strongly support the idea of
micro-payments to long-form content producers instead of content-destroying
ads in my face.</p>
<p>Because its built in reader mode, called <a href="https://brave.com/speed-reader/">Speed Reader</a>, has not
shipped yet, I&rsquo;m currently using the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/print-friendly-pdf/ohlencieiipommannpdfcmfdpjjmeolj">Print Friendly &amp; PDF extension</a>.</p>
<p>Safari on macOS and Firefox have built-in reader modes / views. I can
recommend the <a href="https://adguard.com/en/adguard-browser-extension/safari/overview.html">AdGuard ad-blocking extension</a> for Safari.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, Safari on iOS 12 does not currently add the source URL to its
virtually printed PDFs, so I&rsquo;m using Brave there also, although on iOS I
generally prefer Safari, also with AdGuard.</p>
<p>To print to PDF on iOS, simply print (swipe up, tap share, tap print), then do
the zoom-in gesture to turn the print into a PDF, then share again to save out
the PDF.</p>
<h3 id="store-and-name-your-pdfs-so-you-can-search-them-from-everywhere">Store and name your PDFs so you can search them from everywhere</h3>
<p>I store all of these PDFs in year-named sub-directories of a directory
called <code>refs</code> in my Dropbox.</p>
<p>Each PDF is named &ldquo;publication-date - publisher / author - title / stub&rdquo;, so
the full path is e.g. <code>~/Dropbox/refs/2019/2019-03-09 - CBC Radio - Your brain may need sleep to repair DNA 'potholes'</code>.</p>
<p>On macOS, all of these PDFs are indexed by Spotlight, so I can find the ones I
want quite quickly. Your operating system of choice should have something
similar.</p>
<p>If you are a Dropbox Pro subscriber, the mobile app provides full-text
searching to mobile spotlight also, so you can find any article lightning fast
on your phone.</p>
<p>Google Drive will do this for cheaper, but <a href="/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/#my-big-and-stupid-misstep-into-google-drive">Google Drive might also end up
eating your files</a>. ;)</p>
<h3 id="profit">Profit!</h3>
<p>Now all of your web references are in PDF format, arguably the
typeset-document equivalent of plaintext in terms of accessibility and future
proofing.</p>
<p>As you change around your syncing and storage systems in the coming years,
your faithful directory of PDFs will follow you wherever you go.</p>
<p>As an added bonus, these PDFs can be annotated with your notes and text
highlights.</p>
<h2 id="this-ending-is-only-a-pause">This ending is only a pause.</h2>
<p>Thank you for sticking around for the warming up of the pipes.</p>
<p>I hope that they will not have cooled down too much before I find another bit
of time to start on WHV #166.</p>
<p>There will be pretty pictures!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #142: Theory of mind.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/05/13/weekly-head-voices-142-theory-of-mind/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 20:27:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/05/13/weekly-head-voices-142-theory-of-mind/</guid><description> Autumn is really pretty down here.
We’re getting back on track with the WHVs friends!
In the hardly started tradition of writing blog posts in music-backed focus blocks, I have my “upbeat thinking” playlist teed up and ready to go. The outline of this post formed itself as a Real Bullet List(tm) in my Emacs about an hour ago.
Let’s go.
They grow up so fast Theory of Mind, or ToM, is an important mental capability that we use to model and predict the thoughts and desires of fellow humans.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/img_0007.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/img_0007-1024x661.jpg"
        
            alt="Autumn is really pretty down here."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Autumn is really pretty down here.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>We’re getting back on track with the WHVs friends!</p>
<p>In the hardly started tradition of <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">writing blog posts in music-backed focus blocks</a>, I have my “upbeat thinking” playlist teed up and ready to go. The outline of this post formed itself as a Real Bullet List(tm) in my Emacs about an hour ago.</p>
<p>Let’s go.</p>
<h1 id="they-grow-up-so-fast">They grow up so fast</h1>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_mind">Theory of Mind, or ToM</a>, is an important mental capability that we use to model and predict the thoughts and desires of fellow humans.</p>
<p>Just the other day, as we were going through our school morning ritual of the offspring units eating breakfast together and the adults self-administering the correct number of espressos required for normal functioning, GOU#3 calmly informed me from her mother’s lap:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Daddy, mommy would like another biscuit with her coffee.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Genetic Offspring Unit #3 only very recently turned 2.</p>
<p>With this request, she demonstrated surprising levels of ToM and planning ability. She inferred, entirely correctly,  what her parental unit required at that moment, and performed exactly the correct action (delegation, yikes!) to satisfy that requirement.</p>
<p>I am still suitably impressed.</p>
<h1 id="sketchnote-your-life">Sketchnote your life</h1>
<p><a href="http://rohdesign.com/sketchnotes/">Sketchotes</a> refer to a type of hand-written notes that employs both writing and drawing techniques. Here’s an example by Emacs guru and famous internet person <a href="http://sachachua.com/blog/">Sacha Chua</a>:</p>










<figure><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sachac/9040714189">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/9040714189_4c88f63bb3_z.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I’m trying to spend more time dedicated to thinking and so-called conceptualising. Sketchnotes seems like a good tool to use during these thinking sessions, so last week this formed the ideal excuse to go out and acquire a new large Moleskine with blank pages (I used to use Moleskines for all my note-taking before going digital), and a whole bunch of sketchnote-recommended pens (Pilot Hi-TecPoint 0.5 which I already had one of; Pilot G-TEC-C4 for super fine drawing, pen also turned out to have best handling of the lot despite its simplicity; Pentel Energel 0.7mm).</p>
<p>My first session was spent sketching out my current life landscape (thank you KvG for this tip years ago), including work, side-projects and a bunch of developing and potential opportunities, as well as the links between them.</p>
<p>I can report that drawing like this is a great trick to keep one’s attention glued to the page, and hence to the chosen focus, whilst at the same time maintaining sufficient mental distance to process the more substantial  thoughts and all of their interactions.</p>
<h1 id="telegram-has-the-public-group-chat-market-cornered">Telegram has the public group chat market cornered</h1>
<p>For private messaging, I have a <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">strong preference for Signal</a>, especially over WhatsApp.</p>
<p>Besides the dubious future of WhatsApp’s privacy (Founder #1 Jan Koum is planning to leave while Founder #2 Brian Acton recently donated 50 million dollars to Signal), the WhatsApp web-app is more irritation than it’s worth. The fact that I have to keep my phone awake and connected to the network is a silly constraint which even the far more secure Signal desktop app does not require.</p>
<p>Anyways, I digress.</p>
<p>This section is about <a href="https://telegram.org/">Telegram</a>, another messaging app with dubious security that at least does not belong to Facebook.</p>
<p>Besides all of its stickers, animated gifs, and (non-)useful bots everywhere, Telegram has two additional features which are quiet compelling:</p>
<p>Although it requires a telephone number to be setup, you can configure a username which you can give out to people instead of your telephone number to have them contact you. This adds an extra layer of privacy which is sometimes useful.</p>
<p>More interestingly, Telegram has the concept of “supergroups”. These are public groups which can be joined by anyone if they have the name, and <a href="https://telegram.org/blog/admin-revolution">support up to 10000 (yes ten thousand) users</a>.</p>
<p>This is ideal for easily starting special interest groups, and can be seen as a modern and mobile-first form of IRC. The mobile apps are generally really fast and full featured.</p>
<p>Anyways, on a lark we created one such group, called <a href="https://t.me/zatechlight">ZA Tech Light</a>, for tech people (aka nerds) in ZA. If you are such a person, or you just like chatting with nerds in ZA, feel free to <a href="https://t.me/zatechlight">drop in at @zatechlight</a>. Although primarily lark-based, this could be seen as a sort of splinter group of the much larger (because older) Slack group called <a href="https://zatech.slack.com/">ZA Tech</a>.</p>
<h1 id="running-update">Running update</h1>
<p>Yesterday, I did my second 10km+ run in the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2018/04/08/weekly-head-voices-139-luna/">Lunas</a>, bringing total sandal running distance to 107km.</p>
<p>I am now back up to my pre-sandal standard running route distance.</p>
<p>That being said, my calf muscles are still complaining quite loudly after every run. The recovery perioud seems to be shortening however, and the calf muscle complaints are less convincing every time.</p>
<p>All of THAT being said, running barefoot- aka primitive-style feels amazing, so much so that although one does keep an eye on things, one does not perceive the above-mentioned muscle discomfort as an issue at all.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the patella strap I previously had to wear during running, to prevent knee pain, has been lying in my cupboard, unused for the past 107km.</p>
<h1 id="the-side-project-dilemma">The side-project dilemma</h1>
<p>Most nerds I know have side-projects.</p>
<p>It’s how we learn new things and keep ourselves constructively entertained.</p>
<p>Up to now, I’ve usually chosen my side-projects not only on the basis of learning, but also based on their business potential. Some of them have indirectly led to revenue, partially through the business-relevance check, but so far never directly. That is, I’ve never brought a side-project to market.</p>
<p>This weekend I had an idea for a pretty obscure side-project. In terms of creativity and learning, and of passion and brain-fit, it scores highly, but in terms of direct business potential quite the opposite.</p>
<p>I’m probably at least going to start, because it’s too much fun not to.</p>
<p>What is your approach in situations like this? Do side-projects have to satisfy any kind of utility requirement? Which criteria do you use to select your next side-project?</p>
<h1 id="bhayi-bhayi">Bhayi bhayi</h1>
<p>Thanks for reading this far peeps! I hope you have a beautiful week, and that we might meet again at the end.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>