<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>gou-3 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-3/</link><description>Recent content in gou-3 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 15:38:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #190: 3=4.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 15:38:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</guid><description> Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok, because that's how life is. Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!
This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to Sunday March 8, 2020.
(I had made a good start on the post on March 8, but then the work week and a bunch of homing missile deadlines hit.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was
still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok,
because that's how life is.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to
Sunday March 8, 2020.</p>
<p>(I had made a good start on the post on March 8, but then the work week and a
bunch of homing missile deadlines hit. As I write this bit, it is Saturday
March 14, 14:30 SAST.)</p>
<h2 id="gou-3-turns-4">GOU #3 turns 4!</h2>
<p>Our third Genetic Offspring Unit, creative named GOU #3, fairly recently
completed another year of life.</p>
<p>She has now collected the grand total of 4.</p>
<p>It was a pleasure celebrating her birthday with her as it felt like this was
the first time that she was intellectually fully present.</p>
<p>With apparent ease she even understood the sometimes tricky concept of having
one&rsquo;s party on a different day than one&rsquo;s birthday.</p>
<p>For future us, I would also like to note that her pronunciation and sentence
construction are growing more and more precise, sometimes even overly so, the
observation of which delights me.</p>
<p>GOU#3, if you read this years and years in the future: We can already see that
you are an amazing human being. We are deeply happy that you have come here to
join our clan.</p>
<h2 id="new-pair-of-altras-acquired">New pair of Altras acquired.</h2>
<p>In an unexpected but quite happy turn of events, it is starting to look like I
might have to take part in a trail run in July.</p>
<p>(Charl from the future: Only if my finicky ankles man up between now and then.)</p>
<p>Once I&rsquo;ve actually done it, and I&rsquo;m still able to tell the tale, I will surely
do so.</p>
<p>Because I am one of the World&rsquo;s Worst Trail Runners, I will definitely have to
step up my training between now and then.</p>
<p>As with many other endeavours in life, an important component of all of this is
acquiring suitable shoes.</p>
<p>Because <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">my giant-toe-box-zero-drop
Escalantes</a> have been treating
me very well, I had soon narrowed it down to any one of the Altra trail shoes:
Superiors (minimalist), Lone Peaks (jack-of-all-trades), Timp (sightly more
support) and Olympus (maximalist-ish).</p>
<p>After having read all of the internet regarding the different Altra trail
shoes, I reluctantly came to the conclusion that none of them really knocked it
out of the park.</p>
<p>Anyways, one Sunday I walked into our local sports super store (I&rsquo;m sorry my
fellow nerds), and it so happened that they had a pair of Lone Peak 4.5s in my
size: GINORMOUS CLOWN SHOE SIZE.</p>
<p>Trying them on, I tripped and fell right into the psychological black hole of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases">biases</a> and
<em>instantly</em> convinced myself that these were the shoes for me.</p>
<p>Fast forward a week of calling my behavioural insurer (starts with a Disco ends
with a Y) every single day, and they finally managed to figure out what was
wrong somewhere deep in their unfortunately quite sub-par IT systems, and
flipped the <a href="https://www.discovery.co.za/vitality/fitness-booster-shoe">Shoe Purchase Gamification
switch</a>.</p>
<p>In short, if you are able to activate this feature (you have to be super
patient and a bit stubborn), said insurer will subsidise the purchase of a pair
of running shoes based on how often you exercise every week.</p>
<p>This is one neat way of making your running addiction work for you, if you can
somehow absorb the possibly substantial startup cost, i.e. the hours you have
to spend on the phone with the friendly support agents.</p>
<p>Behold my beautiful new trail running shoes:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>State-of-the-art trail-running shoes for the World's Worst Trail
Runner.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="crabby-wallet">Crabby Wallet!</h2>
<p>After years of eyeing Fido U2F and FIDO2 hardware security keys on the
internet, I finally took the plunge and acquired <a href="https://www.yubico.com/product/security-key-nfc-by-yubico">a Yubico Security Key
NFC</a>.</p>
<p>Up to now I used mostly the LastPass Authenticator app and more recently Authy
to generate OTPs as second factor (2FA) for most of my important accounts.</p>
<p>(BTW, if you&rsquo;re not yet using 2FA for your important accounts, such as email,
now is the best time to upgrade. I would recommend getting <a href="https://authy.com/">the Authy
app</a> because it optionally supports multi-device
synchronization.)</p>
<p>The YubiCo hardware device is supposed to be more secure than authenticator
apps due to domain hashing, and it&rsquo;s pretty cool that you don&rsquo;t have to copy
across 6-digit codes, but what I didn&rsquo;t foresee as clearly was the following
simple difference:</p>
<p>I almost always have my phone with me. However, I don&rsquo;t always have my keyring
with me.</p>
<p>I set out to find a new wallet to replace my already pretty minimalist fake
leather credit card booklet. The new wallet had to be at least as minimalist,
but it had to have some sort of lanyard to which I could attach the security
key.</p>
<p>I was delighted to discover that (of course) there&rsquo;s a whole community of
minimalist wallet enthusiasts on the internet.</p>
<p>I was even more delighted when I discovered that the Crabby Wallet C3, a
second-generation product of a <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1369622196/the-crabby-wallet-a-wallet-that-is-not-for-everyon">super successful 2015
kickstarter</a>,
was available all the way down here!</p>
<p>Behold the minimalist wonder that is my new Crabby Wallet:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The Crabby Wallet C3. As you can see, it's only slightly larger than a credit
card. It's made of canvas which looks pretty durable. After a breaking-in
period, it easily holds up to 10 cards. Sometimes there's even cash stashed
under the rubber-band.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>(Charl from 6 days in the future writes: This looks like it&rsquo;s going to be a
keeper. It&rsquo;s more compact and more secure than my previous credit card booklet,
and it has become much more ergonomic after the initial break-in period.)</p>
<h2 id="the-end-of-this-post">The end of this post.</h2>
<p>Thank you for connecting with me here!</p>
<p>Remember, it&rsquo;s now Saturday March 14, 15:26 SAST, but this post will forever
act like it finds itself on Sunday March 8.</p>
<p>I hope that tomorrow I can write WHV #191, a less complicated post that will
come into being not too far away from the moment that is its observation point.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Do you feel like you have an observation point, a specific location that is
your momentary source of perception and thought?</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been getting back into the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up guide</a>, and
there are some truly delightful exercises of the all-encompassing
consciousness.</p>
<p>Remember: <em>There is no observation point!</em></p>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #165: Get in my Pocket.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 15:01:20 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/</guid><description> This short WHV looks back at the week from Monday March 4 to Sunday March 10.
In the week after that, I had actually decided not to publish this one, instead folding whatever I wanted to say into the next edition.
However, fear of yet another much-too-long WHV, along with my current preference for a short warming-up of the writing pipes, have led me to change my mind, and so here we are!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This short WHV looks back at the week from Monday March 4 to Sunday March 10.</p>
<p>In the week after that, I had actually decided not to publish this one,
instead folding whatever I wanted to say into the next edition.</p>
<p>However, fear of yet another much-too-long WHV, along with my current
preference for a short warming-up of the writing pipes, have led me to change
my mind, and so here we are!</p>
<p>This post consists of a really short life part, followed by a longer nerdy
pro-tip for the storage and retrieval of your web references.</p>
<h2 id="gou3-turns-3">GOU#3 turns 3.</h2>
<p>It seems like <a href="/2016/05/05/weekly-head-voices-106-ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/">just the other day when Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3 joined
us</a> here in the warm and fuzzy Humanist Kingdom of WHV.</p>
<p>Well, the &ldquo;beautiful pink little not-yet-walking but rapidly expanding
cellular mega-city&rdquo; never stopped expanding, and is currently surprising us
every day with the new ways in which her neural network processes and
transforms the reality she finds herself in.</p>
<h2 id="replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">Replacing Pocket with Just a Bunch Of PDFs (JBOP).</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been a happy user of Pocket Premium since October 23, 2016, when they
cleverly offered me a locked discount on the annual plan.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m a sucker for a deal, and I needed something with which to store archive
versions of interesting blog posts and other web resources.</p>
<p>It served me well, as I frequently access and share especially
research-related articles and blurbs, such as <a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161122193100.htm">this one</a> discussing the
observation that aspartame (a sugar substitute found in popular fizzy drinks)
interferes with some of your enzymes, possibly resulting in more weight gain
that straight sugar!</p>
<p>(For Real Academic Articles, i.e. RAA-RAA, I am still a huge fan
of <a href="https://www.zotero.org">Zotero</a>. If Zotero had better mobile access, I would have used it for
these straight web references also.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, recently the new beta pocket interface was failing me horribly as I
was trying to find the exact article mentioned up above.</p>
<p>Typing &ldquo;glu&rdquo; or &ldquo;glucose&rdquo; was unsuccessful in finding another article
&ldquo;Artificial sweeteners induce glucose intolerance by altering the gut
microbiota&rdquo;, even although I could see that exact article in the overview
screen. To add insult to injury, searching for &ldquo;aspartame&rdquo; also did not find
that entry, although I had explicitly tagged it with &ldquo;aspartame&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It could very well be that this is just a (serious) glitch in the beta system,
but it was a frustrating reminder that for something as important (to me) as
my collection of references (aka “argument-winning potion”), I was
at the mercy of someone else, with almost no other recourse.</p>
<p>This frustrating led me to find an alternative solution, which became&hellip; a big
ol' bunch of PDFs! (call this JBOP, inspired by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-RAID_drive_architectures">JBOD</a>)</p>
<p>In order to do this, we need a method of turning web-pages into readable PDFs,
and some system for the storage and retrieval of said PDFs.</p>
<h3 id="use-a-browser-with-ad-blocking-and-reader-mode">Use a browser with ad-blocking and Reader Mode</h3>
<p>The general idea is to use a browser with ad-blocking and some sort of reader
mode, and then to print to PDF.</p>
<p>On desktop, I am using <a href="https://brave.com">Brave Browser</a> because of the great
built-in ad-blocking, and because I strongly support the idea of
micro-payments to long-form content producers instead of content-destroying
ads in my face.</p>
<p>Because its built in reader mode, called <a href="https://brave.com/speed-reader/">Speed Reader</a>, has not
shipped yet, I&rsquo;m currently using the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/print-friendly-pdf/ohlencieiipommannpdfcmfdpjjmeolj">Print Friendly &amp; PDF extension</a>.</p>
<p>Safari on macOS and Firefox have built-in reader modes / views. I can
recommend the <a href="https://adguard.com/en/adguard-browser-extension/safari/overview.html">AdGuard ad-blocking extension</a> for Safari.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, Safari on iOS 12 does not currently add the source URL to its
virtually printed PDFs, so I&rsquo;m using Brave there also, although on iOS I
generally prefer Safari, also with AdGuard.</p>
<p>To print to PDF on iOS, simply print (swipe up, tap share, tap print), then do
the zoom-in gesture to turn the print into a PDF, then share again to save out
the PDF.</p>
<h3 id="store-and-name-your-pdfs-so-you-can-search-them-from-everywhere">Store and name your PDFs so you can search them from everywhere</h3>
<p>I store all of these PDFs in year-named sub-directories of a directory
called <code>refs</code> in my Dropbox.</p>
<p>Each PDF is named &ldquo;publication-date - publisher / author - title / stub&rdquo;, so
the full path is e.g. <code>~/Dropbox/refs/2019/2019-03-09 - CBC Radio - Your brain may need sleep to repair DNA 'potholes'</code>.</p>
<p>On macOS, all of these PDFs are indexed by Spotlight, so I can find the ones I
want quite quickly. Your operating system of choice should have something
similar.</p>
<p>If you are a Dropbox Pro subscriber, the mobile app provides full-text
searching to mobile spotlight also, so you can find any article lightning fast
on your phone.</p>
<p>Google Drive will do this for cheaper, but <a href="/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/#my-big-and-stupid-misstep-into-google-drive">Google Drive might also end up
eating your files</a>. ;)</p>
<h3 id="profit">Profit!</h3>
<p>Now all of your web references are in PDF format, arguably the
typeset-document equivalent of plaintext in terms of accessibility and future
proofing.</p>
<p>As you change around your syncing and storage systems in the coming years,
your faithful directory of PDFs will follow you wherever you go.</p>
<p>As an added bonus, these PDFs can be annotated with your notes and text
highlights.</p>
<h2 id="this-ending-is-only-a-pause">This ending is only a pause.</h2>
<p>Thank you for sticking around for the warming up of the pipes.</p>
<p>I hope that they will not have cooled down too much before I find another bit
of time to start on WHV #166.</p>
<p>There will be pretty pictures!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #142: Theory of mind.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/05/13/weekly-head-voices-142-theory-of-mind/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 May 2018 20:27:27 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/05/13/weekly-head-voices-142-theory-of-mind/</guid><description> Autumn is really pretty down here.
We’re getting back on track with the WHVs friends!
In the hardly started tradition of writing blog posts in music-backed focus blocks, I have my “upbeat thinking” playlist teed up and ready to go. The outline of this post formed itself as a Real Bullet List(tm) in my Emacs about an hour ago.
Let’s go.
They grow up so fast Theory of Mind, or ToM, is an important mental capability that we use to model and predict the thoughts and desires of fellow humans.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/img_0007.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/img_0007-1024x661.jpg"
        
            alt="Autumn is really pretty down here."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Autumn is really pretty down here.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>We’re getting back on track with the WHVs friends!</p>
<p>In the hardly started tradition of <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">writing blog posts in music-backed focus blocks</a>, I have my “upbeat thinking” playlist teed up and ready to go. The outline of this post formed itself as a Real Bullet List(tm) in my Emacs about an hour ago.</p>
<p>Let’s go.</p>
<h1 id="they-grow-up-so-fast">They grow up so fast</h1>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_mind">Theory of Mind, or ToM</a>, is an important mental capability that we use to model and predict the thoughts and desires of fellow humans.</p>
<p>Just the other day, as we were going through our school morning ritual of the offspring units eating breakfast together and the adults self-administering the correct number of espressos required for normal functioning, GOU#3 calmly informed me from her mother’s lap:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Daddy, mommy would like another biscuit with her coffee.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Genetic Offspring Unit #3 only very recently turned 2.</p>
<p>With this request, she demonstrated surprising levels of ToM and planning ability. She inferred, entirely correctly,  what her parental unit required at that moment, and performed exactly the correct action (delegation, yikes!) to satisfy that requirement.</p>
<p>I am still suitably impressed.</p>
<h1 id="sketchnote-your-life">Sketchnote your life</h1>
<p><a href="http://rohdesign.com/sketchnotes/">Sketchotes</a> refer to a type of hand-written notes that employs both writing and drawing techniques. Here’s an example by Emacs guru and famous internet person <a href="http://sachachua.com/blog/">Sacha Chua</a>:</p>








<figure><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/sachac/9040714189">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/9040714189_4c88f63bb3_z.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I’m trying to spend more time dedicated to thinking and so-called conceptualising. Sketchnotes seems like a good tool to use during these thinking sessions, so last week this formed the ideal excuse to go out and acquire a new large Moleskine with blank pages (I used to use Moleskines for all my note-taking before going digital), and a whole bunch of sketchnote-recommended pens (Pilot Hi-TecPoint 0.5 which I already had one of; Pilot G-TEC-C4 for super fine drawing, pen also turned out to have best handling of the lot despite its simplicity; Pentel Energel 0.7mm).</p>
<p>My first session was spent sketching out my current life landscape (thank you KvG for this tip years ago), including work, side-projects and a bunch of developing and potential opportunities, as well as the links between them.</p>
<p>I can report that drawing like this is a great trick to keep one’s attention glued to the page, and hence to the chosen focus, whilst at the same time maintaining sufficient mental distance to process the more substantial  thoughts and all of their interactions.</p>
<h1 id="telegram-has-the-public-group-chat-market-cornered">Telegram has the public group chat market cornered</h1>
<p>For private messaging, I have a <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">strong preference for Signal</a>, especially over WhatsApp.</p>
<p>Besides the dubious future of WhatsApp’s privacy (Founder #1 Jan Koum is planning to leave while Founder #2 Brian Acton recently donated 50 million dollars to Signal), the WhatsApp web-app is more irritation than it’s worth. The fact that I have to keep my phone awake and connected to the network is a silly constraint which even the far more secure Signal desktop app does not require.</p>
<p>Anyways, I digress.</p>
<p>This section is about <a href="https://telegram.org/">Telegram</a>, another messaging app with dubious security that at least does not belong to Facebook.</p>
<p>Besides all of its stickers, animated gifs, and (non-)useful bots everywhere, Telegram has two additional features which are quiet compelling:</p>
<p>Although it requires a telephone number to be setup, you can configure a username which you can give out to people instead of your telephone number to have them contact you. This adds an extra layer of privacy which is sometimes useful.</p>
<p>More interestingly, Telegram has the concept of “supergroups”. These are public groups which can be joined by anyone if they have the name, and <a href="https://telegram.org/blog/admin-revolution">support up to 10000 (yes ten thousand) users</a>.</p>
<p>This is ideal for easily starting special interest groups, and can be seen as a modern and mobile-first form of IRC. The mobile apps are generally really fast and full featured.</p>
<p>Anyways, on a lark we created one such group, called <a href="https://t.me/zatechlight">ZA Tech Light</a>, for tech people (aka nerds) in ZA. If you are such a person, or you just like chatting with nerds in ZA, feel free to <a href="https://t.me/zatechlight">drop in at @zatechlight</a>. Although primarily lark-based, this could be seen as a sort of splinter group of the much larger (because older) Slack group called <a href="https://zatech.slack.com/">ZA Tech</a>.</p>
<h1 id="running-update">Running update</h1>
<p>Yesterday, I did my second 10km+ run in the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2018/04/08/weekly-head-voices-139-luna/">Lunas</a>, bringing total sandal running distance to 107km.</p>
<p>I am now back up to my pre-sandal standard running route distance.</p>
<p>That being said, my calf muscles are still complaining quite loudly after every run. The recovery perioud seems to be shortening however, and the calf muscle complaints are less convincing every time.</p>
<p>All of THAT being said, running barefoot- aka primitive-style feels amazing, so much so that although one does keep an eye on things, one does not perceive the above-mentioned muscle discomfort as an issue at all.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the patella strap I previously had to wear during running, to prevent knee pain, has been lying in my cupboard, unused for the past 107km.</p>
<h1 id="the-side-project-dilemma">The side-project dilemma</h1>
<p>Most nerds I know have side-projects.</p>
<p>It’s how we learn new things and keep ourselves constructively entertained.</p>
<p>Up to now, I’ve usually chosen my side-projects not only on the basis of learning, but also based on their business potential. Some of them have indirectly led to revenue, partially through the business-relevance check, but so far never directly. That is, I’ve never brought a side-project to market.</p>
<p>This weekend I had an idea for a pretty obscure side-project. In terms of creativity and learning, and of passion and brain-fit, it scores highly, but in terms of direct business potential quite the opposite.</p>
<p>I’m probably at least going to start, because it’s too much fun not to.</p>
<p>What is your approach in situations like this? Do side-projects have to satisfy any kind of utility requirement? Which criteria do you use to select your next side-project?</p>
<h1 id="bhayi-bhayi">Bhayi bhayi</h1>
<p>Thanks for reading this far peeps! I hope you have a beautiful week, and that we might meet again at the end.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #135: It’s all rainbows and unicorns, no really!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/03/11/weekly-head-voices-135-its-all-rainbows-and-unicorns-no-really/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 20:04:08 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/03/11/weekly-head-voices-135-its-all-rainbows-and-unicorns-no-really/</guid><description> This rainbow unicorn, floating serenely on a cloudy background, is winking right at you. Down below, we are celebrating GOU #3’s second birthday. Photo taken with the expert assistance of GOU#1, age 11 going on 32.
Hi there friends, welcome back to the weekly (!!!) head voices! I missed you.
Software Release Frazzle Releasing desktop software, even for a small group of people, can get tricky quickly yo!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/rainbow_unicorn_2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/rainbow_unicorn_2.jpg"
        
            alt="This rainbow unicorn, floating serenely on a cloudy background, is winking right at you. Down below, we are celebrating GOU #3’s second birthday. Photo taken with the expert assistance of GOU#1, age 11 going on 32."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>This rainbow unicorn, floating serenely on a cloudy background, is winking right at you. Down below, we are celebrating GOU #3’s second birthday. Photo taken with the expert assistance of GOU#1, age 11 going on 32.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Hi there friends, welcome back to the weekly (!!!) head voices! I missed you.</p>
<h1 id="software-release-frazzle">Software Release Frazzle</h1>
<p>Releasing desktop software, even for a small group of people, can get tricky quickly yo!</p>
<p>Yes, people still write desktop software, and we do love doing it. However, compared to web-apps, there are some additional challenges.</p>
<p>One can’t easily roll-out an incremental fix while no-one is watching, because every release is a significant event where users have to go to the effort of downloading and installing your baby.</p>
<p>It’s a fairly new product, so our release process is still being refined. Long story short, we caught a bug on the release platform (we develop cross-platform, but deploy for a single platform) shortly before release and so we really had to scramble to fix. This, together with the fact that the preparations for the release were already generally intense, left me quite frazzled by Wednesday evening after dinner.</p>
<p>Lesson learned: In a cross-platform development, don’t allow <em>any</em> dependency version discrepancies between platforms, no matter if it causes developer inconvenience.</p>
<h1 id="unicorns-and-rainbows">Unicorns and rainbows</h1>
<p>GOU #3 turned 2 on Thursday.</p>
<p>The littlest genetic offspring unit seems to be verbally well developed. She’s already using words like “eintlik” (“eigenlijk” in Dutch, “actually” in English) in fairly well-structured sentences. I have taught her to say phrases like “universiteit” and “lekker internet”, which she does with a smile.</p>
<p>She is able to express her wants and needs at a level which exceeds that of some 30 year olds.</p>
<p>Anyways, yesterday we held a birthday party for her.</p>
<p>It was a fabulously enjoyable affair with far too many delectable delicacies, and more than sufficient amounts of craft beer and good wine (expensive local Chardonnay is my current preference, if you must know).</p>
<p>It was beautiful to see so much of the family together in one place, all connecting like we humans should be doing as often as we can, but often don’t.</p>
<p>Thank you little GOU #3, for everything.</p>
<h1 id="your-complimentary-grab-bag-of-interesting-cocktail-party-conversational-tidbits">Your complimentary grab-bag of interesting cocktail party conversational tidbits</h1>
<h2 id="trump--brexit-voters-were-scared">Trump / Brexit voters were scared.</h2>
<p>In my <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#the-bad-with-a-hopefully-slightly-positive-outlook-at-the-end">2016 to 2017 transition post</a>, I lamented the observation that for both Brexit and the Trumpocalypse, a lower level of education was the strongest indicator for a vote for leave and for Trump respectively.</p>
<p>A new study by the Queensland University of Technology has now shown that in both cases <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2018-03/quot-2be030818.php">the vote for Brexit / Trump was also driven by fear</a>. It also makes the scary point that the respective campaigns deliberately targeted this fear, which is more than worrisome.</p>
<p>Use this tidbit with care, or right before you were planning to leave the party anyways.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-defend-your-exercise-addiction">How to defend your exercise addiction</h2>
<p><a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acel.12750/full">A recent study published in Aging Cell</a>, showed that older people who exercised regularly (in this case cycling), had the same levels of T-cells as 20 year olds. In other words, their immune systems are as effective as people a fraction of their age.</p>
<p>One of the co-authors of the study, 82-year old Prof Norman Lazarus (who himself cycles 100km at a time), <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/health-43308729">summarised it neatly in the media as follows</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>If exercise was a pill, everyone would be taking it.</strong> It has wide-ranging benefits for the body, the mind, for our muscles and our immune system.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(I like how he casually takes aim at our pill-obsession.)</p>
<h2 id="the-carmack-productivity-method-cpm">The Carmack Productivity Method (CPM)</h2>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Carmack">John Carmack</a> is the modern-day genius who was the lead programmer of genre- and era-defining games like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfenstein_3D">Wolfenstein 3D</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(1993_video_game)">DOOM</a> (“one of the most significant and influential titles in video game history”) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quake_(video_game)">Quake</a>. During working on these projects, he invented a number of important computer graphics techniques.</p>
<p>It turns out that Carmack is not only a genius, but a productivity and focus <em>monster</em>.</p>
<p>In <a href="http://bookofhook.blogspot.co.za/2013/03/smart-guy-productivity-pitfalls.html">this 2013 blog post</a>, a colleague of Carmack at id Software describes how Carmack would apparently play CDs while he was working. If he was checking his email, or if he was interrupted by a colleague, or he needed to go to the bathroom, in other words, if he was not focusing on the core of his work, he would pause the CD player.</p>
<p>By the end of the day, he knew exactly how much focused work he had done by how far he had gotten through his playlist.</p>
<p>Compared to the interrupt-driven way programmers work today (thanks internet!) this sounds like an amazingly visceral way to recognise and signal interruptions in your flow: THE MUSIC SIMPLY STOPS.</p>
<p>Would you be able to implement something like this for your work?</p>
<h1 id="à-bientôt">À bientôt</h1>
<p>Thank you very much for stopping by! Have a productive week, and don’t forget to exercise.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #106: Ch-ch-ch-ch-changes.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/05/05/weekly-head-voices-106-ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 21:19:18 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/05/05/weekly-head-voices-106-ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/</guid><description> From me to you: The view from the top of Paarl Rock as seen through my telephone and google’s megamind going through all my photos and trying to stitch them together.
Well hello everyone! I missed you, but due to reasons (read on…), this is the first time I’ve been able to get around to a weekly head voices.
I woke up one day and decided that the super-inventive internet handle I had chosen when registering my first personal domain in 1999 somewhere, namely cpbotha, was not cutting it anymore.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/view_from_paarl_rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/view_from_paarl_rock-1024x166.jpg"
        
            alt="From me to you: The view from the top of Paarl Rock as seen through my telephone and google’s megamind going through all my photos and trying to stitch them together."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>From me to you: The view from the top of Paarl Rock as seen through my telephone and google’s megamind going through all my photos and trying to stitch them together.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Well hello everyone! I missed you, but due to reasons (read on…), this is the first time I’ve been able to get around to a weekly head voices.</p>
<p>I woke up one day and decided that the super-inventive internet handle I had chosen when registering my first personal domain in 1999 somewhere, namely cpbotha, was not cutting it anymore. I think this specific seed of discontent was planted when I joined someone’s <a href="https://www.livecoding.tv/livestreams/">livecoding.tv</a> stream, only to have them mangle the in hindsight unpronounceable pronunciation of cpbotha (ku-pu-byooothuh).</p>
<p>CURSES.</p>
<p>Nobody told me about this additional requirement in ’99! I will ask for my money back.</p>
<p>In any case, after some fancy twitter footwork, I now have an additional handle: <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel">cvoxel</a>. I realise this is only interesting to me and maybe one or two other nerds, but here we are. There might be some personality fragmentation behind all of this. I’ll have a chat with me later.</p>
<p>Friends in more advanced countries, when I show them the sun and the beer and the beaches and the mountains and the WILD BEASTS over here, usually simply point at my miserably slow internet connection, thereby restoring their faith in the balance that exists in our world. Due to another recent change, I can now offer this as a retort:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/speedtest.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/speedtest.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>This kind of bandwidth is pretty respectable for the balmy southern tip of the African continent. (plus that those internet packets are flying about 1km through the air, which is pretty cool!)</p>
<p>This year I did not go to AfrikaBurn, because reasons (read on…). Fortunately the photos only started showing up after the week (no internets for the burners of course!), but they did cause some really acute feels of nostalgia. It’s strange how <a href="/2015/06/14/weekly-head-voices-91-theyre-back/">last year’s experience</a>, our first (Pompen en Pimpen forever!), has managed to become so deeply ingrained. I really hope to see you there next year.</p>
<p>My oldest sibling has started an adventure in Kiwi-land. His family will soon follow. I am happy for the adventurers, but I’m also sad to have them so far away.</p>
<h2 id="a-caffeine-infused-mitochondrial-interlude">A caffeine-infused mitochondrial interlude</h2>
<p>You probably remember that adenosine triphosphate, or ATP, is the most important form of energy that is produced for the largest part by the mitochondria in the nuclei of all of your cells. ATP is broken down when energy is required. ATP powers things like muscle contraction, cellular metabolism, signaling, and so on. Without it, you would be useless. Dead actually.</p>
<p>I just learnt from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adenosine_triphosphate">wikipedia article</a> that your body turns over its own weight (!!!) in ATP every day, which is pretty awesome.</p>
<p>The first factoid I wanted to mention, is the curious link caffeine has with ATP. So as you’re going through the day expending all that energy, ATP gets broken down into its constituents, one of which is of course adenosine. This adenosine binds to the adenosine receptors in your brain. When a certain threshold of adenosine receptors are bound, your body decides that it’s time to rest, so you get sleepy. During sleep, the adenosine is cleared as your body builds up new energy stores.</p>
<p>Caffeine is, besides being magical, a sort of adenosine impostor. When you drink coffee for example, the caffeine in your tasty drink will go and bind with your adenosine receptors, hence making it impossible for real adenosine to bind, but it will do so without actually activating those receptors. The end result is that your brain does not realise that it should be feeling sleepy, and so you don’t feel so tired.</p>
<p>I find it interesting that caffeine in fact interferes so fundamentally with this important physiological process.</p>
<p>What I found slightly more mind-blowing than that however, is the fact that the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitochondrion">mitochondria</a>, the little organelles where most of this ATP production takes place, and which are embedded right in all of your cell nucei, actually contain <em>foreign</em> DNA.</p>
<p>TUN-TUN-DUUUUUUUUUN!!!</p>
<p>Yes children, you have your own precious DNA in your cell nucleus, but the mitochondrion, the cell’s powerhouse, has its own separate genome. Long ago, we seem to have started a symbiotic relationship with a bacterial organism. Actually, we flat-out went and merged with them at an extremely intimate level.</p>
<p>Let us all take a few minutes to say hi to the beautiful little alien endo-symbionts embedded in our cell nuclei, without whom everything falls apart. We are all chaotic but somehow walking cellular mega-cities, and it’s just lovely.</p>
<h2 id="my-universe-expanded">My universe expanded</h2>
<p>About those reasons…</p>
<p>Well, GOU#3 was born a few weeks ago.</p>
<p>She’s a beautiful pink little not-yet-walking but rapidly expanding cellular mega-city. I and the other more developed cellular mega-cities in this neck of the woods and all of our billions of cells are truly happy to have her with us.</p>
<p>May your neurotransmitters rejoice.</p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>