<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Gnupg on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gnupg/</link><description>Recent content in Gnupg on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 13:44:42 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gnupg/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #217: Continuum of Consciousness</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 13:44:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/</guid><description>Hey, welcome to the Monthly Weekly Head Voices!
This one covers the extensive period from Monday Feb 15 to Sunday March 21, 2021.
Since we last connected here, much has transpired, a strangely selected subset of which is mentioned below:
New computer An M1 MacBook Air became part of my computing zoo. See the new computer post if you&amp;rsquo;re into that sort of thing. Short version if you&amp;rsquo;re not: It&amp;rsquo;s the best Emacs-capable device I&amp;rsquo;ve ever used.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hey, welcome to the Monthly Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This one covers the extensive period from Monday Feb 15 to Sunday March
21, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="bettys_bay_somewhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_8f9c87f732124c86.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_b0df16242502fa52.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_dc5a53dcce727ffb.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_147a9746ca3986c1.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_b0df16242502fa52.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Since we last connected here, much has transpired, a strangely selected subset
of which is mentioned below:</p>
<h2 id="new-computer">New computer</h2>
<p>An M1 MacBook Air became part of my computing zoo. See <a href="/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/">the new computer post</a> if
you&rsquo;re into that sort of thing. Short version if you&rsquo;re not: It&rsquo;s the best
Emacs-capable device I&rsquo;ve ever used.</p>
<h2 id="pgp-i-m-not-dead-yet">PGP: I&rsquo;m not dead yet!</h2>
<p>In a pleasantly surprising turn of events, I found myself counter-signing PGP
encryption keys with different sets of friends.</p>
<p>In spite of my <a href="/2016/12/11/pgp-never-gonna-give-you-up/">PGP never gonna give you up post</a> of 2016, the thought that
old-fashioned PGP might soon disappear even from my archaic view, to be
replaced by more user-friendly and modern solutions such as <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">Signal</a>, has been on
my mind more often recently.</p>
<p>This would not be the worst turn of events. The more people are using secure
and private communication, the better.</p>
<p>However, it <strong>was</strong> fun doing our modest part to bolster the tiny and dwindling
group of humans who know how to use PGP and think that they still should.</p>
<p>All of that being said, we did also make use of the opportunity to perform
defensible <a href="https://support.signal.org/hc/en-us/articles/360007060632-What-is-a-safety-number-and-why-do-I-see-that-it-changed-">Signal safety number verification</a>.</p>
<h2 id="stone-three-healthcare-has-joined-back-up-with-the-rest-of-voltron">Stone Three Healthcare has joined back up with the rest of Voltron</h2>
<p>Back in July of 2019, I <a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">announced that Stone Three Healthcare had been
officially spun out from Stone Three Venture Technology</a>.</p>
<p>More recently, our corporate mothership embarked on a newly engineered (and
funded) scaling-up journey, bringing with it a host of opportunities for
positive impact on the world.</p>
<p>In the Healthcare company we had to make a choice between sticking it out as a
smaller startup on the one hand, or re-integrating into a newly-designed merged
organization and making use of the extended new capabilities to further our
vision.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m really trying to keep it real here, but the line between that and
corp-speak is like mono-filament!)</p>
<p>So, since this past week or so, I&rsquo;m working together with the new merged
entity.</p>
<p>My mandate is now broader in two ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll be focusing on technological solutions for precision Health <strong>and</strong>
Safety, where it was previously healthcare only.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ll be assisting all parts of the company by optimizing technological
processes of all sorts.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is all very exciting to me, and they&rsquo;re even letting me keep some of the
science in my new official title!</p>
<h2 id="the-strange-continuum-of-consciousness">The strange continuum of consciousness</h2>
<p>This is a tricky one to mention, because it probably needs much more space than
I have here, and much more skill than I have to explain.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to try in any case, because just maybe it sparks something for
someone.</p>
<p>A large part of the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up meditation</a> daily practice is exploring the exact
nature of one&rsquo;s experienced consciousness.</p>
<p>Specifically, there is the realisation that the whole of your consciousness,
including your thoughts, your interactions with real, live people, and
everything else, takes place in <strong>your</strong> mind.</p>
<p>Furthermore, <em>internal</em> sensations, like an itch, or pain, or a tingling on
your skin, and <em>external</em> sensations, like hearing or sight, although they seem
to be localised <em>inside</em> and <em>outside</em>, take place in the exact same
consciousness.</p>
<p>Everything that you experience, whether &ldquo;real&rdquo;, like looking at the sea, or
imaginary, like thinking about (and hence &ldquo;seeing&rdquo;) something that you need to
take care of tomorrow, or something that you experienced yesterday, are all
simulations that are running as part of your consciousness.</p>
<p>There is a continuum from internal to external, and a continuum from direct
sensory experience to remembered or predicted experience, along with all of its
thoughts and emotions.</p>
<p>These are all the same sort of signals coursing through the same neural
pathways.</p>
<p>Another core idea here is that although your brain is housed in your skull,
your feeling that your consciousness is somehow also localised behind your eyes
is not entirely apt.</p>
<p>Your consciousness is the <em>whole</em> space, with all of your observed reality in
it, <em>including</em> the illusion (or rather simulation) of your localisation.</p>
<p>You (the observer) are not at a single point, but rather everywhere where
consciousness is.</p>
<p>Everything that you perceive to happen, by definition &ldquo;happens&rdquo; in the space
that you call consciousness.</p>
<p>These are tricky lessons to learn, and it seems that at least in my case we are
destined to spend only fleeting moments together, but they have profound and
positive implications for how we go through life.</p>










<figure><a href="machineray2-668-16.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/machineray2-668-16_hu_f99d79eecee7f0e1.png 480w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/machineray2-668-16.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: I used the neural network-based artwork generator, called MachineRay 2, by artist Robert A. Gonsalves to generate this piece. Read more in his blog post."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: I used the neural network-based artwork generator, called MachineRay 2, by artist Robert A. Gonsalves to generate this piece. Read more in <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/creating-abstract-art-with-stylegan2-ada-ea3676396ffb">his blog post</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>