<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Gitlab on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gitlab/</link><description>Recent content in Gitlab on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 20:04:13 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gitlab/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #105: There will be tears.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/15/weekly-head-voices-105/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 20:04:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/15/weekly-head-voices-105/</guid><description>Congratulations, you have successfully completed the week of Monday February 8 to Sunday February 14, 2016!
About 4 seconds after posting previous edition WHV #104 to Facebook with the “When you’re a vegan and haven’t told anyone in 10 minutes” meme image included, friend Ivo T. zinged me with this reply:
So much truth. I have been put back in my place. Sorry vegans. Sorry MBA students. Not sorry Ayn Randers.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Congratulations, you have successfully completed the week of Monday February 8 to Sunday February 14, 2016!</p>
<p>About 4 seconds after posting previous edition <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/08/weekly-head-voices-104-let-me-update-you/">WHV #104</a> to Facebook with the “When you’re a vegan and haven’t told anyone in 10 minutes” meme image included, friend Ivo T. zinged me with this reply:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/12651073_10153234132252035_804640390912092906_n.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/12651073_10153234132252035_804640390912092906_n.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>So much truth. I have been put back in my place. Sorry vegans. Sorry MBA students. Not sorry Ayn Randers.</p>
<p>This is currently my favourite lager ever (at least until next week):</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/jack_black_lager.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/jack_black_lager-576x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>It is indeed a craft beer. If we’ve ever chatted more than 10 minutes in the past (or in the future), you’ll know everything about my braai, and you probably also know that I find craft beer to be one of the greatest inventions ever, along with fire, and the internet.</p>
<p>Here’s a another beer which I recently had the pleasure of enjoying, at a secret networking meeting (yes, we have secret meetings where we in fact do manage a large number of aspects of your daily life, and where we also orchestrate it so you’ll never suspect that we are behind everything, subtly manipulating reality) where, when the beer arrived at the table, everyone who looked vaguely hipster-like claimed vocally not in fact to be even remotely hipster-like:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/tears_of_the_hipster.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/tears_of_the_hipster-576x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>META-HIPSTER CRAFT BEER! At first I was confused, but then I realised it was just another case of <strong>WHAT A TIME TO BE ALIVE!</strong></p>
<p>(By the way, I stripped the EXIF GPS data from the Jack Black photo, because privacy, but I left it hidden in the tears of the hipster. First one who tells me in the comments where the secret meeting was held gets a free craft beer!)</p>
<p><em>Nerd tip of the week</em>: It’s somehow not prominent enough on their site, but GitLab, the open source GitHub alternative, also <a href="https://about.gitlab.com/gitlab-com/">offer free hosting of an unlimited number of private repositories with an unlimited number of private collaborators</a>. In other words, if you’re on a budget, you can host your commercial and proprietary project git repositories (and bug tracking and wikis) there at <em>no cost</em>. This is cheaper than github ($7 for the smallest subscription for 5 private repos) and better than bitbucket (private repos for free, but if you have more than 5 team members you have to pay). I pay quite gladly for the online services I use, but in this particular case, such a level of free is hard not to like.</p>
<p><em>Nerd tip #2 of the week:</em> The <a href="http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/">Clang static C++ analyser</a> is brilliant. If you program in C++, and you need to up your game, integrating this into your workflow is a solid step in the right direction. I’ve been using this via the <a href="http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/scan-build.html">scan-build method</a>. Let me know in the comments if you’d like to know more about this!</p>
<p>After some <a href="http://www.pcservices.co.za/">professional</a> ethernet cabling down to the sort-of basement of our new house, I have checked off another item from my non-existent bucket list: <em>We now have a lab at our house.</em> So far there are computers, all kinds of DIY supplies and art stuff for the genetic offspring units, and all of this to <em>create</em>. I spent some of the best times of my life in labs of some sort of another. It’s really great bringing some of that back home to my clan.</p>
<p>Have a great week kids, see you on the other side!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>