<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Health on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/health/</link><description>Recent content in Health on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 07:42:28 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 6 of 2024: Head Like a Hole</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</guid><description>Why do I lifelog? One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&amp;rsquo;s not form their own mind.
Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="why-do-i-lifelog">Why do  I lifelog?</h2>
<p>One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&rsquo;s not form their own mind.</p>
<p>Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</p>
<h3 id="journalling-vs-lifelogging">Journalling vs lifelogging</h3>
<p>In my view, <em>journalling</em> is a more developed form of <em>lifelogging</em>. While the latter is just the direct jotting down of happenings and noteworthy items, the former, at least to me, entails more thinking and more processing, i.e. there is more retro- and introspection going on. I would prefer to be <em>journalling</em>, because that has even more benefits, but I&rsquo;ll take <em>lifelogging</em> when I can&rsquo;t make the prerequisite time to think, and really craft my words.</p>
<p>On to the lifelog:</p>
<h2 id="monday-2024-02-05">Monday 2024-02-05</h2>
<ul>
<li>Friend LM told me about wikitree.org, which is a collaborative online family tree thingy. I tried to import the myheritage.com exported GEDCOM, but wikitree.org wants me to reject or accept each and everyone of the hundreds of people in my database. This is understandable, but it&rsquo;s also a  blocker, exacerbated by the fact that wikitree&rsquo;s matching algorithm is quite bad.</li>
<li>Casey Neistat&rsquo;s Apple Vision Pro review is insightful. See the bit from 7:20 onwards: <a href="https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440">https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440</a> &ndash; &ldquo;&hellip; This is it. This is the future of computing&hellip;&rdquo;
<ul>
<li>also see my tweet embedded below</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>NVIDIA&rsquo;s GenAI competition <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/">https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/</a>
<ul>
<li>Use TensorRT or TensorRT-LLM on Windows to build something cool, submit by Feb 23, win RTX 4090 and GTC conf attendance. EZ PZ!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Remember that life is <em>supposed</em> to be just a long sequence of problems that you need to solve.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is such a fun &quot;review&quot; of the Apple Vision Pro by Casey Neistat, but his discussion at 7:20 on the significance of the product is so spot on.<br><br>I had similar ideas about ubiquitous face-computing back in 2009: <a href="https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc">https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc</a> <a href="https://t.co/au9RBh7as0">https://t.co/au9RBh7as0</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1754421449719193753?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 5, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>










<figure><a href="avp-angry-gf.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b5f62d2dc15edfd3.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b31467e1ec255b77.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_c35fee7f6f8120f9.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-06">Tuesday 2024-01-06</h2>
<ul>
<li>Using inkscape to draw SVG glyphs which can be converted with <a href="https://react-svgr.com/">svgr</a> into React components, for my visualization project. This works so well!</li>
<li>Definitely a bit stressed about tomorrow&rsquo;s surgery. Also little throat niggle, and as if that was not enough, stomach issues due to droëwors I ate in the afternoon to preload a bit for tomorrow&rsquo;s required fasting.
<ul>
<li>Narrator: This would be followed by one of <em>the</em> worst nights in a long time, including fever chills, nausea, and so on.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>My brain keeps on jumping on ideas for 3D / VR / AR / AI friendly / native ideas for managing personal knowledge / notes
<ul>
<li>on the one hand, it feels like the atomic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten">Zettelkasten</a> approach could work well here</li>
<li>on the other, we have chunking techniques to break up documents, so that we can extract the nuggets we want in order to embed them
<ul>
<li>this chunking can be dynamic and adaptive, perhaps even going down to sentences and individual diagrams, or dynamically constructed chunks consisting of sub-chunks merged from different sources</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>in the end, will it help  or even just be interesting to be able to walk / move through / manipulate different projections of your (or someone else&rsquo;s) thoughts, possibly even connected in different ways?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-07">Wednesday 2024-01-07</h2>
<ul>
<li>Microsoft Lens makes me login every single time, and is quite temperamental
<ul>
<li>alternatives are OneDrive app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo; or Files app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At Summerhill day clinic for the excision of the morpheaform basal cell carcinoma (BCC) on my forehead
<ul>
<li>Fortunately, the doctor decided the excision on my back (with clean borders pronounced by pathology lab) does not need to be re-excised.</li>
<li>Excision of 2cm x 1.5cm patch from my forehead via <a href="https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/conditions-and-diseases/mohs-surgery">Mohs surgery</a> is successful after first attempt, happiness!</li>
<li>Reconstructive surgeon however now has a challenge: How to close up hole with no loose skin in sight? (I am a tightly wrapped person)
<ul>
<li>problem is solved with step-wise incision from the top middle of my forehead all the way down to my right temple, about 20cm in total.</li>
<li>I look like I could be the son of Frankenstein and Harry Potter</li>
<li>The care at Summerhill is beyond excellent. Now I just have to follow instructions, drink many pills, and my new friend-for-life Scar should heal up nicely.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-08">Thursday 2024-01-08</h2>
<ul>
<li>Working from home because reasons</li>
<li>I have to work hard to focus, the medication seems to affect my concentration. I will grit my teeth harder.</li>
<li>In break time, tried out <a href="https://www.modular.com/blog/mojo-sdk-v0-7-now-available-for-download">Mojo v0.7.0 (released 2024-01-25)</a> through its REPL and also just a simple <code>hello.mojo</code>, which compiled into a nice 300kB binary on this MacBook! Cautiously excited for the future of this. (also&hellip;. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Lattner">Chris Lattner</a>! 😍)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-09">Friday 2024-01-09</h2>
<ul>
<li>In the morning, got mu4e setup and working on the new MacBook, although I thought I was not going to need this mail client
<ul>
<li>What is your favourite mail client?</li>
<li>I use the Fastmail web client, mu4e for Emacs and macOS Mail, but none of them is perfect. mu4e comes close. ;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Really struggled during the day with drowsiness, although I&rsquo;m sleeping extra well every night.</li>
<li>By the end, at least was able to make demo video of my in-progress visualization project.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-10">Saturday 2024-01-10</h2>
<ul>
<li>head still feeling quite woozy</li>
<li>happy to have kids at home, and have a pretty relaxed morning</li>
<li>I would really like to write / create something today. What?</li>
<li>family tree updates
<ul>
<li>tried out ancestris, which is unusably slow on my m1pro. just getting a context menu on a person in the tree, or scrolling around, has too much lag. Tried on my Windows desktop where it&rsquo;s better but still really slow.</li>
<li>Went back to wikitree (recommended by LM) where I updated some more records (extremely laboriously).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.familysearch.org/en/">https://www.familysearch.org/en/</a> has been really useful for scans of church registers and so on, confirming more of my earlier findings.
<ul>
<li>See for example <a href="https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910">https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910</a> which just came in as I was typing this. That&rsquo;s the death notice of my paternal great grandmother in 1919, very shortly after the birth of my grandfather.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I think I might have spent too much time on this today. There&rsquo;s a bit of a dopamine rush every time you solve a mini riddle. Here also I would like to have something shareable and reusable for other members of my family. For that, wikitree, although painful, seems like a good bet.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>mind wandered at 13:30ish, of course it ended up in infinite canvases and pkm
<ul>
<li>wanted to keep on letting it wander, but also wanted to use laptop to read about freeform
<ul>
<li>Apple Freeform looks like the pretty-ok-like-notes canvas solution: <a href="https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue">https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Instead of going to bed early, experimented with round-tripping markdown to docx and back with pandoc. See tomorrow for results.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-11">Sunday 2024-01-11</h2>
<ul>
<li>Briefly tried out the new(ish) built-in <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-za/guide/iphone/iph0e5ca7dd3/ios">iOS Journal app</a>
<ul>
<li>Super nice that it taps into your activities (photos, music, workouts, etc.) and makes recommendations for packets of media you could add to a journal, all of this entirely on-device.</li>
<li>Private, encourages folks to lock the app and so on.</li>
<li>No export capability, so your journals remain utterly locked in for now.</li>
<li>Makes it easy to configure reminders that will prompt you to write  a journal at specific moments during the week.</li>
<li>Minimalistic and well-executed app, will probably get quite a few iPhone users to start journalling, but not for me. I already have too many Apple apps in my personal system that I need to use (e.g. Apple Notes) but that don&rsquo;t interoperate particularly well with other systems.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent some more time on familysearch.org creating and attaching person records (from my family) to scans of old archive documents. Also uploaded a PDF of hand-written notes made by one of my family members from the headstones on a farm on which a number of my ancestors were buried.
<ul>
<li>Two-world problem. Bringing the physical into the digital.</li>
<li><strong>familysearch really does work better than wikitree&hellip;</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>About that Two World Problem. Had some thoughts about it in the context of my personal knowledge management, but it was slightly too much for the bullets I had allocated to it, and so it become a short post titled <a href="/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/">On the two world problem and personal knowledge management</a>.
<ul>
<li>In an ideal world, I am able to publish mini posts like that on a weekly basis.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Oh wait, I also made a short post on vxlabs with the results of last night&rsquo;s pandoc experiments, titled <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/02/11/pandoc-roundtrip-from-markdown-to-docx-and-back/">Pandoc roundtrip from markdown to docx and back</a>
<ul>
<li>In this case, I went direct to Hugo markdown instead of starting in Emacs Orgmode first, in order to further reduce activation energy. This makes sense for posts I want to get published where I don&rsquo;t necessarily need the benefit of having the content integrated with my main notes database.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #221: The anti-breakfast club</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 08:54:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/</guid><description>Hello there friends, and welcome to Weekly Head Voices #221, covering the week from Monday April 12 to Sunday April 18, 2021, and focusing on the programming language Erlang and the evil that is breakfast.
Figure 1: Entrance to Vergelegen and Morgenster, taken during an Autumn morning long(er) run. I&amp;rsquo;m three bananas strong.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello there friends, and welcome to Weekly Head Voices #221, covering the week
from Monday April 12 to Sunday April 18, 2021, and focusing on the programming
language Erlang and the evil that is breakfast.</p>










<figure><a href="vergelegen_entrance_autumn_run_202104.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/vergelegen_entrance_autumn_run_202104_hu_3f4a51e22e02c3ea.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/vergelegen_entrance_autumn_run_202104_hu_4410996cb8883e35.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/vergelegen_entrance_autumn_run_202104_hu_daf143d3ce11da7b.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/vergelegen_entrance_autumn_run_202104_hu_df2ded2b472dbbe2.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/vergelegen_entrance_autumn_run_202104_hu_4410996cb8883e35.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Entrance to Vergelegen and Morgenster, taken during an Autumn morning long(er) run. I&rsquo;m three bananas strong."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Entrance to Vergelegen and Morgenster, taken during an Autumn morning long(er) run. I&rsquo;m three bananas strong.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="learn-you-a-tiny-bit-of-erlang-for-great-good">Learn you a tiny bit of Erlang for Great Good!</h2>
<p>Last week I attended a meetup that turned out to be primarily about Erlang and
not so much about automated crypto arbitrage, the other topic of the
talk. Although it&rsquo;s interesting to me that we have a company right here in
this town that has been successfully doing automated crypto arbitrage for a few
years now, using Erlang!</p>
<p>Like many other folks, I became interested in Erlang back in 2013 (I just
checked my notes, but it was also <a href="/2014/04/21/weekly-head-voices-68-harsh-autumn-weekends/">mentioned on this blog in 2014</a>, when I
decided not to learn it) when WhatsApp started becoming well-known. The
WhatsApp backend was famously implemented in Erlang, enabling them to handle
hundreds of millions, and now billions, of users with relatively little
resources.</p>
<p>The first two hours of the talk was a detailed intro to Erlang that did require
a substantial amount focus and grit to keep up with.</p>
<p>However, understanding how light-weight Erlang processes work and talk to each
other was quite interesting. More importantly the speaker both really knew what
he was talking about, and spoke really well.</p>
<p>The last 20 minutes or so after that were great, more about how and why exactly
Shiftly uses Erlang to do their real-time crypto arbitrage.</p>
<p>Their Erlang system is self-healing (when one of the light-weight processes
dies, for whatever reason, its supervisor simply replaces it; there are
supervisors watching the other supervisors!), and usually runs for years on
end, keeping all of its state in memory. They usually only have to stop it to
perform security upgrades on the underlying operating system.</p>
<p>Erlang processes pull in feeds from forex and various other suppliers, monitor
order books in real-time, and then execute movements on crypto trading pairs
that are affected by any order book entry.</p>
<p>My main take-home was that Erlang seems to combine super light-weight processes
(you can run millions of them on a single machine) that are fully isolated (a
process can divide by zero, be killed and a new one takes its place) but can
still easily share code and data via messages.</p>
<p>It seems like the antithesis to the sticky and sometimes over-complicated
micro-services situation we have collectively gotten ourselves into.</p>
<p>All of that being said, the same caveats apply as using another actor platform
like akka.net for example: Everything is unicorns and rainbows if you stay
within the lines (i.e. strict Erlang, or pure .NET managed code in akka&rsquo;s
case).</p>
<p>When you start adding native code, things can still go quite badly awry.</p>
<p>Still, the Erlang actor-based approach to writing highly concurrent and
fault-tolerant code sure looks amazing!</p>
<h2 id="i-really-don-t-like-breakfast">I really don&rsquo;t like breakfast</h2>
<p>Some of my friends know that I&rsquo;ve been quite angry at breakfast for a while
now.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m referring specifically to the idea that has been quite successfully
propagated by the makers of breakfast cereal for as long as I can remember:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Breakfast is the most important meal of the day.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So they really want you to eat their usually sugar-filled products first thing
in the morning, and they&rsquo;ve convinced you, and most of the &ldquo;field&rdquo;, that this
is healthy.</p>
<h3 id="eating-causes-inflammation">Eating causes inflammation</h3>
<p>What many people don&rsquo;t realise, is that every single meal causes inflammation.</p>
<p>Postprandial inflammation, as this is called, is your body&rsquo;s normal response to
any foreign material entering its systems.</p>
<p>Refined foods, and especially sugar, cause much more inflammation per volume
than natural foods, such as fruit and vegetables. Some food types even
counteract the inflammation to a certain extent.</p>
<p>Can you see where this is going?</p>
<p>A few hours after dinner you go to bed, your body still dealing with
the inflammation caused by that dinner.</p>
<p>You <em>hopefully</em> sleep for 8 hours or more, and your body finally gets a break.</p>
<h3 id="the-problem-with-breakfast">The problem with breakfast</h3>
<p>What do you do when you get up? You eat breakfast, because it&rsquo;s entrenched in
your brain (thanks to years of marketing) that breakfast is healthy and should
not be skipped, instead starting up a full day&rsquo;s inflammation again.</p>
<p><a href="https://nutritionandmetabolism.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12986-016-0142-6">This article in Nutrition &amp; Metabolism</a> describes the phenomenon quite nicely:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The typical Western diet is characterized by sizable portions of highly
processed foods, large amounts of added sugars, and a high total fat
content. The average fat content of a Western meal is between 20 and 40 g, and
three to four meals per day are consumed regularly. Therefore, many individuals
spend the majority of their day in a postprandial state, characterized by
elevated levels of circulating triglycerides (TRG) following a meal.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Chronic low-grade inflammation is associated with metabolic disorders that
include obesity, type 2 diabeters and the metabolic syndrome. Furthermore, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26629551/">low
inflammation predicts successful ageing</a>.</p>
<p>In short, we want as little as possible inflammation, not more.</p>
<p>There are fortunately a few great ways to mitigate feeding&rsquo;s role in
inflammation: 1. Eat the best food you can find, 2. eat less food and,
importantly, 3. try not to eat for the whole dang day.</p>
<p>My anger at breakfast and its cereal-maker proponents is because they have
sabotaged point 3 above, sending a large part of the western populace into
glucose metabolism and inflammation every single morning.</p>
<h3 id="skip-you-some-breakfast-for-great-good">Skip you some breakfast for great good</h3>
<p>This <a href="https://www.dietdoctor.com/intermittent-fasting/time-restricted-eating">blog post on time-restricted eating</a> is definitely worth your time. Here I
would like to reproduce what it has to say about breakfast:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We have all been told to eat breakfast. Unfortunately this is inaccurate
advice.</p>
<p>When you first wake up in the morning, your insulin level is quite low and most
people are just starting to enter the fasted state, 12 hours after eating the
last meal of the previous day. Eating at this time raises insulin and glucose
and immediately shuts off fat-burning. This is especially true for a high carb
breakfast. A potentially better choice would be to push the first meal of your
day out at least a few hours, during which time you can continue in the fasted
state and burn stored body fat.</p>
<p>Interestingly, many properly fat-adapted people aren&rsquo;t very hungry in the
morning and have no problem skipping breakfast.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>From personal experience I can confirm this: I usually don&rsquo;t get hungry <em>at
all</em> until lunch-time, at the earliest.</p>
<p>(If I&rsquo;m planning to go on a morning run, I will usually eat a few bananas right
before the outing to be able to keep up a higher pace. I have also run fasted,
but in that case my pace is automatically more relaxed.)</p>
<p>In this context, it&rsquo;s interesting to look at <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/my-nutritional-framework/">Peter Attia&rsquo;s nutritional
framework</a> as well. He refers to eating less, eating specific things and
restricting when you eat as three levers that have to be regularly
pulled.</p>
<p>Pulling these levers helps your body to become metabolically flexible, that is,
being able to switch easily between glucose burning and fat burning, the latter
of which many western humans are not capable of anymore.</p>
<p>It is interesting in this regard that our brains, although they can run on fat
when required, strongly prefer glucose (source: fascinating podcast episode
<a href="https://peterattiamd.com/husseinyassine/">&ldquo;Hussein Yassine, M.D.: Deep dive into the &lsquo;Alzheimer’s gene&rsquo; (APOE), brain
health, and omega-3s&rdquo;</a>). I&rsquo;m still working out the implications of this on my
personal intellectual requirements.</p>
<p>Ok friends, thank you for sticking around for this sermon!</p>
<p>Next week: A whole bunch of information that in fact does constitue financial
and investment advice that I take full responsibility for. (haha just
joking. it&rsquo;ll be politics or religion.)</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #186: Helderberg 20.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 16:08:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/</guid><description>Friends, it is with great pleasure that I welcome you back here to the Weekly Head Voices!
The passing of time usually seems to be quite a theoretical affair, but at this moment I can really feel the year taking its last few breaths.
(People even seem to think of this as the last year of the decade, which makes it all the more dramatic, but not everyone is convinced. If the first day of the first year was January 1, year 1, the end of the first year was December 31, year 1, and the end of that first decade was on December 31, year 10. By this reasoning, the end of the current decade is still more than a year away, on December 31, 2020. Yes, the calendar has changed drastically over the years, but the principle of when decades start and end is the same.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Friends, it is with great pleasure that I welcome you back here to the Weekly
Head Voices!</p>
<p>The passing of time usually seems to be quite a theoretical affair, but at this
moment I can really feel the year taking its last few breaths.</p>
<p>(People even seem to think of this as the last year of the decade, which makes
it all the more dramatic, but <a href="https://www.withum.com/resources/end-of-the-decade/">not everyone is
convinced</a>. If the first
day of the first year was January 1, year 1, the end of the first year was
December 31, year 1, and the end of that first decade was on December 31,
year 10. By this reasoning, the end of the current decade is still more than a
year away, on December 31, 2020. Yes, the calendar has changed drastically over the years, but the principle of when decades start and end is the same.)</p>
<p>Anyways, one thing I am only slightly more sure about is that this edition of
the WHV Monday looks back on the days from Monday December 9 to Sunday December
15, 2019!</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu_52a86bef4be3fcfe.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu_84eff41eefa5f3d0.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu_d1925304afd824a7.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu_2be7c8e5577b4875.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu_84eff41eefa5f3d0.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
<p>There&rsquo;s a buck (a sort of goat), probably of the duiker variety, really showing
off its camouflage on one of the ledges in this photo taken along the West Peak
/ Woody&rsquo;s Walk route on Helderberg mountain. See if you can find it!</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="we-are-load-shedding-again">We are load shedding again.</h2>
<p>So yeah, there&rsquo;s that.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re load shedding again.</p>
<p>Everything I wrote &ldquo;<a href="/2019/03/24/weekly-head-voices-166-morgan-bay/#on-being-powerless">on being
powerless</a>&rdquo;
in March of this year is again happening, down to me spending more time on
Twitter again (DANG IT) searching for voices that might indicate justice
eventually being served.</p>
<p>In spite of the fact that our home is now more or less load-shedding-proof due
to it being for the largest part <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">solar
powered</a> this time
around, the rotating power outages (we had a week or two of stage 4, i.e. 3 x
2.5 hour outages per day, and one evening of escalation to stage 6) are an
upsetting reminder of the decades-long and now continuing incompetence and
corruption of the country&rsquo;s leadership.</p>
<p>Apart from the numerous mental cycles this phenomenon has been <em>stealing</em> (see
what I did there) from my work focus, it is hard not to notice how businesses,
colleagues and friends are being hit by this.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s perhaps new this time, is that <a href="https://www.timeslive.co.za/politics/2019-10-29-eskom-board-member-slams-interference-says-there-should-be-load-shedding/">it has been confirmed by an Eskom board
member</a>
that the same politicians who have caused this mess, are <em>still</em> meddling in
technical affairs they have no idea about, for all of the wrong reasons.</p>
<p>To put it quite bluntly, instead of trying to address the almost insurmountable
technical problems at the electricity supplier, it seems that the ruling party
(the ANC of course) for example insisted that the electricity be kept on at all
costs during the elections.</p>
<p>Numerous incidences of this sort of interference helped them to save face over
the years, at the cost of further debilitating the already fragile South
African economy.</p>
<p>At this moment, as large parts of industry are shutting down for the Christmas
period, we are enjoying a respite from load shedding.</p>
<p>We will see what happens in the new year.</p>
<p>The board member quoted above stated that if meddling had not been such a
concern, and they could face the technical problems head-on, we were looking at
at least 8 months of load shedding.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m sure that the people would be able to deal with it if those cards were
simply laid on the table, without all of the political meddling and backroom
dealings.</p>
<p>As was the case the previous time, I do remain hopeful that the number of
spines in power grows, and that the electricity provider is able to focus all
of its energy on addressing the significant problems that it faces.</p>
<h2 id="time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">Time-restricted Eating (TRE) with Black Coffee please.</h2>
<p>I think it was Reader K who introduced me to the idea of time-restricted
eating, or TRE, a year or two ago.</p>
<p>(Together we tried to figure out on which medium this happened, because under
normal circumstances I would have wanted to look up the exact time and contents
of the messages.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, we discovered that it must have been via Facebook Messenger, and
somewhere between then and now Reader K had expunged their whole Facebook
history.</p>
<p>I think there&rsquo;s a lesson in here somewhere, but we have to forge ahead, so
we&rsquo;re going to have to side-step it.)</p>
<p>Time-restricted eating, or TRE, is a sort of intermittent fasting where the
eating window is deliberately limited to an as short as possible duration
during the daytime.</p>
<p>The theory behind it is that our metabolism is in fact also ruled by the
all-powerful circadian clock.</p>
<p>During our long evolution, we would have been foraging and feeding during
daylight, and resting during the night.</p>
<p>With artificial light and the ubiquitousness of food of modern times, we easily
fall into the habit of starting to eat when we wake up, and having the last
snack shortly before going to sleep, hours after sunset.</p>
<p>In short, we really do eat too much, and to make it even worse, we eat at all
the wrong times.</p>
<p>With research around TRE, science, as is its wont, is showing us the way back
to redemption.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s starting to look like limiting one&rsquo;s feeding window to a few hours during
daylight could have a number of health advantages.</p>
<p>See for example:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4255155/">Time-restricted feeding is a preventative and therapeutic intervention
against diverse nutritional
challenges</a> - a 2014
Cell Biology study with mice.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/12/191205141731.htm">Clinical study finds eating within 10-hour window may help stave off
diabetes, heart
disease</a> - a 2019 Science Daily summary.</li>
<li><a href="https://m2performancenutrition.com/blog/can-time-restricted-feeding-make-you-fitter">Can time restricted feeding make you
fitter</a> -
a reasonable overview.</li>
</ul>
<p>After a debate with friend LM about whether black sugarless coffee constituted
a break of the TRE fast (I thought that it did due to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m6KClPkotxM">this conversation
between Rhonda Patrick and Joe
Rogan</a>, friend LM did not, so I
initially did not even try TRE because I am unable to operate without black
coffee in the mornings), I have been dipping my toes in the TRE pool.</p>
<p>I have never been a breakfast person (&ldquo;Breakfast is the most important meal of
the day&rdquo; ??! TRUST NO ONE.), so sticking to black coffee in the mornings until
as late as possible, which is in many cases lunch, and not eating anything
after dark, has subjectively worked out pretty well so far.</p>
<p>Sometimes, shortly before lunch, there seems to be a slight delusional quality
to my seemingly enhanced mental clarity, but let&rsquo;s keep that between you and
me.</p>
<h2 id="anniversary-walk-up-the-mountain">Anniversary walk up the mountain.</h2>
<p>Recently, my life partner and I celebrated two decades of official
togetherness by walking up the Helderberg mountain.</p>
<p>We did not quite make West Peak, and we were pretty bushed by the end, but
that&rsquo;s ok. The scenery was epic, and getting back home was brilliant.</p>
<p>We will try again in 2029.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_hu_f36e0d1f02b2b266.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_hu_21e6cad14eb163f8.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_hu_898647e673d4e8e8.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_hu_1b01c56de5f46cb7.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_hu_21e6cad14eb163f8.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
<p>All by itself, Google&rsquo;s AI stitched together a bunch of my photos of the
Helderberg hike to make this lovely panorama. It&rsquo;s better than the panorama I
made by myself, so I&rsquo;m giving you this one. Click for higher resolution.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #159: Extreme.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 21:16:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/</guid><description> The view from Waterkloof Restaurant’s balcony, on a fairly perfect evening.
In theory, this edition should cover the period of time from Monday November 19 to today, Wednesday December 19, 2018.
I am very late with this post, because down here we were first busy winding down the year with all of the completion-madness that that entails, and then the vacation started starting.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/waterkloof_perfect_evening.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/waterkloof_perfect_evening-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from Waterkloof Restaurant’s balcony, on a fairly perfect evening."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from Waterkloof Restaurant’s balcony, on a fairly perfect evening.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In theory, this edition should cover the period of time from Monday November 19 to today, Wednesday December 19, 2018.</p>
<p>I am very late with this post, because down here we were first busy winding down the year with all of the completion-madness that that entails, and then the vacation started starting.</p>
<p>It hasn’t yet stopped being busy starting.</p>
<p>We are now entering what the Dutch call <a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komkommertijd">komkommertijd</a>, and, as I’ve just learned, the Germans <em>Sauregurkenzeit</em>, referring to the period when everyone has left and there’s not really anything news-worthy happening.</p>
<h2 id="extreme-dining">Extreme dining</h2>
<p>To celebrate the occasion of the official partnership between my partner and me adding another year to its growing collection, and due to my partner’s impeccable timing and ingenuity, we spent an amazing evening at what is currently South Africa’s best restaurant, at least according to <a href="https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/lifestyle/food/2018-11-20-this-eatery-in-the-western-cape-has-been-named-sas-best-restaurant/">the 2018 Eat Out Mercedes-Benz Restaurant Awards</a>.</p>
<p>I would like to share three observations:</p>
<ol>
<li>The Waterkloof experience is a superbly balanced combination of location (see the photo above), architecture and interior design, art and ambience, all acting as context for the almost other-worldly culinary adventure, itself consisting of pairings of wine and perfect little dishes, the latter again artfully manipulating appearance and taste, space and time.</li>
<li>South Africa is a country of extremes. Just the previous night, close family had been the victims in a violent but fortunately non-fatal home invasion.</li>
<li>If you ever manage to find yourself at Waterkloof, take this advice to heart: The <em>small</em> dégustation menu with wine pairing is most probably more than enough. (We selected the <em>normal</em>. By what felt like the 15th course, we were dealing with the dilemma of having to abstain from eye-wateringly beautiful culinary creations.)</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="extreme-solar">Extreme Solar</h2>
<p>For many good reasons, we are currently seriously evaluating upgrading the house with a photovoltaic solar power system.</p>
<p>It turns out, as I should have expected, that there’s a whole universe of new toys and gadgets to evaluate.</p>
<p>We are currently looking at the following main components:</p>
<ul>
<li>2 x <a href="http://www.pylontech.com.cn/pro_detail.aspx?id=121&amp;cid=23">PylonTech US3000B</a> LithiumIon batteries for a total of about 7 kWh of stored electricity.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.goodwe.co.uk/Products/index_em.html">GoodWe GW3648-EM Hybrid inverter</a>: This coordinates everything between the PV Solar panels, the grid and the batteries. When the sun is shining, it charges the batteries, and powers as much as possible of the house, only using the grid when there’s no other option. During the evening, it powers the house using the batteries, again only using the grid when absolutely required. Due to strict rules down here in Cape Town, we are limited to inverters with a maximum output of 3.6 kW, even when no feed-in (to the grid) is planned.</li>
<li>The PV Solar Panels: I am still considering options here. I would prefer monocrystalline, and as close as possible to the 4.6 kWp maximum supported by the GoodWe inverter to maximise the amount of sun in our power diet.</li>
</ul>
<p>As a first step, today we had a number of intelligent geyser controllers installed. These devices enable me to keep the geysers (we heat all of our water electrically down here…) off for most of the day, only switching them on an hour or two before hot water is usually required.</p>
<p>They look like this:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/geyserwise_tse.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/geyserwise_tse-888x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="GeyserWise TSE geyser controller. I should have done this ages ago. Who came up with the idea that a water geyser needs to maintain its high temperature 24/7?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>GeyserWise TSE geyser controller. I should have done this ages ago. Who came up with the idea that a water geyser needs to maintain its high temperature 24/7?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The rest of this exercise will be considerably more expensive, but  am really looking forward to being able to harvest most of our electricity from the lovely African sun!</p>
<p>I have one final bit of nerd-news, and it comes in the form of a…</p>
<p>WHV pro-tip #23972847376: If you are doing data science(tm), or machine learning, or visualization, or any other dataset-oriented work, I can highly recommend <a href="https://dvc.org/">DVC, or DataVersionControl</a>. We have started using this on one of our projects to manage different collections of DICOM images, and it works incredibly well.</p>
<h2 id="extreme-health">Extreme health</h2>
<p>In conclusion, I would like to mention a recent and very <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2707428?resultClick=3">impressive study by the Cleveland Clinic about the correlation between cardiorespiratory fitness and all-cause mortality</a>.</p>
<p>I’ll start with this quote:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>
    In this cohort study of 122 007 consecutive patients undergoing exercise treadmill testing, cardiorespiratory fitness was inversely associated with all-cause mortality without an observed upper limit of benefit.
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let’s “unpack” that, as they say.</p>
<p>The researchers spent about 23 years measuring the cardiorespiratory fitness of just over 122 thousand subjects as they were running on a treadmill.</p>
<p>Measuring that many people gives your conclusions quite some statistical power. Also, the treadmill doesn’t lie, as people will often do, inadvertently or not, when self-reporting their fitness level.</p>
<p>What’s also interesting to me is that they didn’t observe any upper limit to the positive effect of fitness. Every additional amount of cardiorespiratory fitness, up to crazy levels, correlated with longer life.</p>
<p>The upshot of all of this is that there’s really no excuse. That one most important thing we can do to live long and prosper is to exercise.</p>
<p>It’s what Spock would have wanted.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/bettys_gravel_running.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/bettys_gravel_running-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Running on a dirt road in Betty’s Bay. I love running on dirt roads, although on this particular morning I was already tired before I started. The tiredness unfortunately did not decrease. I think there might still have been some virus involved, or, more probably, just standard bad vacation habits involving craft beer in the evening."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Running on a dirt road in Betty’s Bay. I love running on dirt roads, although on this particular morning I was already tired before I started. The tiredness unfortunately did not decrease. I think there might still have been some virus involved, or, more probably, just standard bad vacation habits involving craft beer in the evening.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #156: Karma Chameleon.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 20:56:19 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/</guid><description> Scene from a recent lunch with a very flat cat. Whilst appreciating these moments with direct experience mode set to 11, one does have to realise that it’s all much more complicated than it looks.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/cavalli_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/cavalli_view-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Scene from a recent lunch with a very flat cat. Whilst appreciating these moments with direct experience mode set to 11, one does have to realise that it’s all much more complicated than it looks."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Scene from a recent lunch with a very flat cat. Whilst appreciating these moments with direct experience mode set to 11, one does have to realise that it’s all much more complicated than it looks.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to this, the 156th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, voices who are planning to sing about the two weeks from Monday October 8 to Sunday October 21.</p>
<p>Summer has arrived, and it’s really very hot down here.</p>
<p>As I’m writing this at 21:41, I am doing my best to limit my motion to the absolute minimum in a bid to keep my temperature within healthy limits.</p>
<p>You have to imagine me sitting utterly still, almost like a chameleon on a twig, with only my fingers making small darting movements over the keyboard.</p>
<p>Time is fun when you’re having flies.</p>
<h1 id="karma-running">Karma Running.</h1>
<p>This morning, after losing all my karma in traffic (there was an accident on one of the main roads in my town, resulting in the normally already impressive level of stupidity of the driving mob, which I am part of, reaching hitherto unseen levels; WHEN IS THE AI GOING TO TAKE OVER PLEASE?!), I started my long road to forgiveness, and zen, by taking a barefoot run on the beach near my place of work.</p>
<p>It looked like this:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/strand_run.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/strand_run-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Goldilocks sand: Not too hard, not too soft, just right."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Goldilocks sand: Not too hard, not too soft, just right.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I wish I could better communicate how it felt.</p>
<p>Imagine the 30 Celsius morning sun on your back, a slight breeze from the sea and your bare feet rhythmically brushing the wet sand as you glide softly along the coast.</p>
<p>Simply keep on doing this until your body creates the stillness that your mind needs.</p>
<p>This is my new favourite run.</p>
<h1 id="mafish">MAF(ish).</h1>
<p>A friend from work told me about this idea of exercising at 80% of your maximum heart rate.</p>
<p>The idea behind this is to <a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/beginner/a20812270/should-i-do-heart-rate-training/">train your aerobic system without injuring anything, and also to be able to do so with much more volume</a> (read: more kilometres).</p>
<p>Four weeks ago I tried to squeeze in too much running in the half hour I had at my disposal. Due to me being doubly stupid, I also did this in my Xero Tolerance 5mm sole sandals, and so I was rewarded with a brand new kind of pain in my posterior tibial tendon.</p>
<p>This is the same tendon <a href="/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/#weekend-running-update">previously mentioned on this blog</a>, also in the context of running injuries.</p>
<p>However, this time I must have injured the tendon more effectively than the previous time (practice makes perfect!), because the pain seemed to be a more permanent new inhabitant of my foot.</p>
<p>Long story short, the suggestion of lower heart rate training came at the perfect time, with my ankle serving as a continuous and visceral (literally) reminder to keep an eye on my heart rate.</p>
<p>This has been going swimmingly.</p>
<p>I am slowly increasing my distance, but, more importantly, runs are again characterised by a whole lot of grinning.</p>
<p>It has not escaped me that a man running on sandals (or barefoot) with a probably fairly unpredictable-looking grin on his big hairy face could give fellow humans pause for thought.</p>
<h1 id="grab-bag-of-thought--andor-debate-provoking-pieces">Grab bag of thought- and/or debate-provoking pieces.</h1>
<h2 id="not-exercising-worse-for-your-health-than-smoking-diabetes-and-heart-disease-study-reveals"><a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2018/10/19/health/study-not-exercising-worse-than-smoking/index.html">Not exercising worse for your health than smoking, diabetes and heart disease, study reveals</a></h2>
<p>Over a period of more than 20 years, 122000 people were put on a treadmill at Cleveland clinic. It turns out that exercise plays a crucial role in not dying.</p>
<p>Core quote: “Being unfit on a treadmill or in an exercise stress test has a worse prognosis, as far as death, than being hypertensive, being diabetic or being a current smoker”.</p>
<h2 id="avoiding-meat-and-dairy-is-single-biggest-way-to-reduce-your-impact-on-earth"><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2018/may/31/avoiding-meat-and-dairy-is-single-biggest-way-to-reduce-your-impact-on-earth">Avoiding meat and dairy is ‘single biggest way’ to reduce your impact on Earth</a></h2>
<p>I’m really sorry about this one, fellow meat lovers.</p>
<p>This also looks like a pretty solid study. Core quote: “The new research shows that without meat and dairy consumption, global farmland use could be reduced by more than 75% – an area equivalent to the US, China, European Union and Australia combined – and still feed the world.”</p>
<p>(I have slowly started to work on the vegetarian recipe section of my notes.)</p>
<h2 id="worlds-largest-sleep-study-shows-too-much-shut-eye-can-be-bad-for-your-brain"><a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2018-10/uowo-wls100918.php">World’s largest sleep study shows too much shut-eye can be bad for your brain</a></h2>
<p>It is <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">well known</a> that we here at The Voices are huge fans of sleep.</p>
<p>However, now it turns out that lots of sleep is not going to cut it. You have to sleep just the right amount: Not too much and not too little.</p>
<p>You probably knew this, but this large study confirms it: Between 7 and 8 hours of sleep, no more and no less, is best for optimal mental performance.</p>
<p>Hard hitting quote: “One startling revelation was that most participants who slept four hours or less performed as if they were almost nine years older.”</p>
<h1 id="the-end">The End</h1>
<p>Thank you for connecting with me by reading this post. I am already looking forward to our next encounter, whichever form that may take!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>You must vaccinate</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/05/21/you-must-vaccinate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2009 09:02:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/05/21/you-must-vaccinate/</guid><description> Image courtesy of dbtechno.com. I was mistakenly under the impression that, at least in my social circles, the whole vaccination issue had been put completely to rest, but based on the number of serious questions that I’ve been asked recently, this unfortunately does not seem to be the case.
For those of you who don’t have time, I’ll cut to the chase immediately:
Yes, you simply must vaccinate your children. This is the best and safest choice, for both your child and your fellow humans.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<img alt="" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/05/vaccine_autism_vaccinations.jpg" style="margin-left: 0px;"/>
<figcaption>Image courtesy of dbtechno.com.</figcaption>
</figure> 
<p>I was mistakenly under the impression that, at least in my social circles, the
whole vaccination issue had been put completely to rest, but based on the
number of serious questions that I’ve been asked recently, this
unfortunately does not seem to be the case.</p>
<p>For those of you who don’t have time, I’ll cut to the chase immediately:</p>
<p><strong>Yes, you simply <em>must</em> vaccinate your children.  This is the <em>best and
safest</em> choice, for both your child and your fellow humans.</strong></p>
<p><strong>No, there is no link between vaccination and autism. No, spreading out the
(MMR) vaccinations is not safer, it is in fact more dangerous.  Also, the
“vaccine overload” hypothesis is flawed.</strong></p>
<p>For those of you with a bit more time or those of you who are not willing to take me on my word, I’ll go into some more detail on each of the points mentioned above.  Most of what I write here is based on articles in the Wikipedia.  I’ve deliberately done this, because these articles are accessible and readable to everyone, and they do link to the original scientific articles that they are based on.  Feel free to jump to any section.  Also, each section ends with a short summary of its contents to make it easier for you to skip.</p>
<h1 id="recent-history">Recent history</h1>
<p><em>This section is based on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MMR_vaccine_controversy" title="Wikipedia article on MMR vaccine controversy">Wikipedia article on the MMR vaccine
controversy</a>.</em></p>
<p>In 1998, Andre Wakefield and co-authors published a paper in the Lancet where,
based on 12 case reports, they speculated on a possible link between the MMR
vaccination and autism, and also speculated that it might be better to space
out the vaccinations.  Of course the press and media picked this up and went
completely wild, causing a health scare in the UK.  It is important to note
that both of these claims were highly speculative.</p>
<p>It later turned out that Wakefield had received 55000 (fifty-five thousand) UK
pounds from Legal Aid Board solicitors who were gathering evidence to use in a
case against vaccine manufacturers, and that a number of parents of the
children taking part in Wakefield’s study were directly involved in the
law-suit.  Wakefield did not mention any of this at the time of publication. 
Ten of his 12 co-authors have since completely retracted their interpretation
of the paper.</p>
<p>In short, the author of the paper that started most of the modern vaccination-autism scare was completely corrupt, and his corruption directly affected this specific research.</p>
<p>He did manage to cause such a scare in the UK, that measles (one of the diseases that MMR vaccinates against) is for the first time in decades at almost epidemic levels.   Since then, there have been cases of measles killing children, something which would most probably not have happened had the vaccination compliance not been at an all-time low.  Isn’t that absolutely crazy when one considers that measles was all but eradicated?</p>
<p>In the years between 1998 and the present, there have been numerous extremely well-designed and large studies, none of which have been able to find <em>any</em> kind of link between vaccination and autism.</p>
<p><em>To summarise this section: The research that the vaccination scare is based
on, was deeply flawed and based on corruption, not science.</em></p>
<h1 id="spreading-out-of-vaccines">Spreading out of vaccines</h1>
<p><em>This section is based on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaccine_controversy#Vaccine_overload" title="Wikipedia article on Vaccine controversy.">Wikipedia article on the general Vaccine
Controversy</a>.</em></p>
<p>In some cases, parents opt for spreading out the vaccinations, because they
mistakenly think that this is safer than not doing so.  The flawed idea that
administering all these vaccines together could be dangerous is called the
“vaccine overload hypothesis”.  It is flawed for the reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Common childhood ilnesses represent a much heavier load on the infant immune system.</li>
<li>The vaccination cocktail given currently represents less than 10% of the immunological load of the vaccinations given to children in the 80s.</li>
<li>Numerous studies have shown that the combination of vaccinations does NOT damage the infant immune system.</li>
</ul>
<p>Importantly, if you spread out vaccines, you increase the time during which your child is susceptible to the diseases that are being vaccinated again, thus greatly increasing the health risk to your child and all other children it comes into contact with.  You are a bad parent if you do this.</p>
<p><em>To summarise this section:</em> <em>Administering the vaccinations together does not damage your child’s immune system.</em> <em>Spreading out vaccines is dangerous for both your child and all children it comes into contact with.</em></p>
<h1 id="celebrities-campaigning-against-vaccination">Celebrities campaigning against vaccination</h1>
<p>Recently, a number of celebrities, most prominent of which Jenny McCarthy and
her partner Jim Carrey, supported by Oprah, have been campaigning against
vaccination.  You have to remember that these are actors and entertainers,
with almost ZERO medical or scientific background or training.   McCarthy
dropped out of nursing school to become a Playboy Bunny: There’s nothing
wrong with that, but you really cannot base important medical decisions,
concerning the health and survival of your child (!!), on the opinions of an
erstwhile nude model!</p>
<p>_To summarise: Think carefully about the scientific and medical backgrounds of
actors telling you how to care for the health and well-being of your child,
even more so when it concerns life and death issues such as vaccination.</p>
<h1 id="the-logical-conclusion">The logical conclusion</h1>
<p>To the best of our scientific knowledge, vaccinations as they are administered today are safe and do not cause autism.  In spite of this, research continues day and night to make sure of this observation.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you don’t vaccinate, the risk of your child
getting ill and dying is <em>significantly</em> higher.  If a large enough number of
you don’t vaccinate, we lose our herd immunity and then there is a very
real risk that <em>many</em> more of our children will get ill and die due to your
inaction.  Do you seriously want to take this very real risk with your <em>and</em>
my children’s lives?</p>
<h1 id="post-scriptum">Post scriptum</h1>
<p>I hope that this has helped.  If there are any issues that are not clear, or
missing, or you are not convinced, please let me know so that we can discuss
and so that I can improve this article.</p>
<h1 id="extra-resources">Extra resources</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://tallguywrites.livejournal.com/148012.html" title="Andrew Wakefield comic">Brilliant comic</a> explaining how the corrupt Andrew Wakefield managed to cause this whole debacle.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.slate.com/id/2217798/" title="aritcle in slate criticising oprah for supporting mccarthy">Article in Slate</a> criticising Oprah’s support of Jenny McCarthy.</li>
<li>Popular <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2006/feb/12/health.medicineandhealth" title="Observer article about medical backlash over vaccine scare">article in the Guardian’s Observer</a> about spreading out vaccines.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nhs.uk/chq/Pages/1034.aspx?CategoryID=68&amp;SubCategoryID=154" title="statement on the NHS on why separate vaccinations are not necessary.">Clear statement by the NHS</a> on why there is no reason to offer MMR vaccine in a spaced / spread out fashion, and that spreading out is in fact dangerous.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="updates">Updates</h1>
<ul>
<li>July 25, 2012: <a href="http://io9.com/5928722/this-graph-of-whooping-cough-cases-in-washington-state-should-scare-the-crap-out-of-you" title="io9 article with increasing incidence of whooping cough in Washington State in 2012">Whooping Cough incidence in Washington State is up by 1300% in 2012</a> relative to 2011, most probably due to the anti-vaccination movement.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>