<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>zuma on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/zuma/</link><description>Recent content in zuma on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 22:21:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/zuma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #228: Komkommertijd</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 22:21:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/</guid><description> Figure 1: On the side opposite to Map of Africa, on the grass that shall not be entered if one is not a club member.
This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number two tenny eight, covers the period of time from Monday June 28 to Sunday July 18 of the year 2021.
Bad glitch in the South African matrix Although I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say here (hence the title), the country has been all over the news for less than great reasons.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="map_of_africa_other_side.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: On the side opposite to Map of Africa, on the grass that shall not be entered if one is not a club member."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: On the side opposite to Map of Africa, on the grass that shall not be entered if one is not a club member.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number two tenny eight, covers the
period of time from Monday June 28 to Sunday July 18 of the year 2021.</p>
<h2 id="bad-glitch-in-the-south-african-matrix">Bad glitch in the South African matrix</h2>
<p>Although I don&rsquo;t have much to say here (hence <a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komkommertijd">the title</a>), the country has been
all over the news for less than great reasons.</p>
<p>Shortly after former president Zuma finally finally handed himself over to the
police on Sunday July 4 to serve his 15 month jail sentence for contempt of the
Constitutional court (there are more cases to come), looting, arson and
violence broke out primarily in Kwazulu-Natal, but also in Gauteng.</p>
<p>Various shopes and malls have been stripped bare and/or destroyed.</p>
<p>This looked like a perfect storm, initiated by Zuma&rsquo;s incarceration (he has a
great deal of support in Kwazulu-Natal), partially fanned on by his children
and allies on social media, and intensified by systemic poverty.</p>
<p>There were many videos on social media of folks with luxury items, some trying
to stuff flat-screen TVs into their cars, or crossing the street with a basket
full of goods to dump in their luxury Mercedes, but there were also many more
who are only trying to survive under the poverty line and can&rsquo;t be blamed for
any of this.</p>
<p>As far as I can see, our current president Ramaphosa has for years now been
doing his best to unravel the nest of corruption and dishonesty that his party
the ANC has unfortunately become.</p>
<p>This is tricky work, as he needs to circumnavigate and/or defuse the same
internal forces that managed to oust president Thabo Mbeki and usher in the
terrible era of Zuma.</p>
<p>The poor man has had to endure even more flak in these days, both from his
political enemies and from other commentators.</p>
<p>Until convincingly shown otherwise, my opinion is that president Ramaphosa is
the best shot we currently have at a better future.</p>
<p>You can read <a href="https://www.gov.za/speeches/president-cyril-ramaphosa-update-security-situation-country-16-jul-2021-0000">his July 16 speech about the unrest here</a>.</p>
<p>A slight silver edge is that these events have put more pressure on the
<a href="https://businesstech.co.za/news/finance/506914/government-considers-basic-income-grant-after-riots-and-looting-in-south-africa/">discussions around the possible implementation of a basic income grant</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. It seems that the looting was not disruptive enough for some folks, and so
now we are dealing with <a href="https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/article/2021-07-20-why-the-western-cape-is-being-rocked-by-taxi-violence/">taxi-company-related violence in the Western Cape</a>.</p>
<p>P.P.S. let me just hide this here: far more locally, we are dealing with some
pandemic-related stressors.</p>
<h2 id="reserve-bench-holidays">Reserve bench holidays</h2>
<p>As <a href="/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/#groundhog-lockdown">I supected in the previous WHV</a> (three weeks ago, ahem&hellip;), our country&rsquo;s
struggles with the pandemic did in fact manage to get our Kruger National Park
visit cancelled.</p>
<p>To be clear, I have no illusions about the relative importance of our holiday
under these circumstances and in this context (close to utterly unimportant, in
other words), but we humans are gonna human and I&rsquo;m not gonna lie, we were
really looking forward to that week of sun in Mpumalanga.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve often said that the winter down here is more bearable than one would
expect, due to it being quite often punctuated by brilliant and sunny days
outside, but this year I&rsquo;ve come to realise that I might have underestimated
the positive effects of <a href="/tags/knp/">spending the darkest week under the sun of the North</a>.</p>
<p>Anyways, we were super fortunate to be able to arrange for a long weekend in
another one of our favourite places, namely Wilderness, where we were treated
with absolutely balmy days, some of them on the Touw river (inflatable SUPs
FTW!), some of them on the most beautiful beaches, and some of them hiking and
running on various trails.</p>








<figure><a href="wilderness_running_rondevlei.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Scene from one of my favourite running routes, this time with GOU #1!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Scene from one of my favourite running routes, this time with GOU #1!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>If it sounds to you like we had to go outside every day to warm up in the
winter sun, I can hereby confirm your astute observation.</p>
<p>To be fair, this was literally in the deepest part of winter, from which there
is no true escape if one remains within the Western Cape.</p>
<p>In spite of that, or perhaps because of it, we enjoyed the wonderful days to
bits.</p>








<figure><a href="kaaimans_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: The rail bridge over Kaaimansrivier. We have this on the todo list for next time."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 3: The rail bridge over <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaaimans%5FRiver">Kaaimansrivier</a>. We have this on the todo list for next time.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #120: May you live in interesting times.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/04/02/weekly-head-voices-120-may-you-live-in-interesting-times/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 19:46:11 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/04/02/weekly-head-voices-120-may-you-live-in-interesting-times/</guid><description> (Warning: Due to the momentous events of the past week, this post is 80% South African politics. If this is not your thing, eject right before the large warning further down! Maybe next week we’ll be back to our usual programming, all depending on how above-mentioned momentous events play out.)
Between all of the retinal excitement of the (gorgeous) new Justice League trailer and the release of the new Ghost in the Shell movie (pretty but soulless the reviews seem to be saying), you might have missed the new Valerian trailer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(Warning: Due to the momentous events of the past week, this post is 80% South African politics. If this is not your thing, eject right before the large warning further down! Maybe next week we’ll be back to our usual programming, all depending on how above-mentioned momentous events play out.)</em></p>
<p>Between all of the retinal excitement of the (gorgeous) new <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="https://youtu.be/3cxixDgHUYw">Justice League trailer</a> and the release of the new Ghost in the Shell movie (pretty but soulless the reviews seem to be saying), you might have missed the new Valerian trailer.</p>
<p>This would be a shame, because it looks mind-expandingly stunning:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cPeqNTqZNN0?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>On Tuesday, March 28, 2017, when I arrived home and Genetic Offspring Unit #3 (GOU#3 for short) saw me, she all-matter-of-factly stood up and <em>walked</em> towards me.</p>
<p>My heart burst.</p>
<h1 id="warning-whats-happening-in-sa-politics-at-the-moment-in-60-seconds">WARNING: What’s happening in SA politics at the moment, in 60 seconds.</h1>
<p>One would think that one heart bursting per week is sufficient, but on Friday morning this happened again for unfortunately far less than positive reasons.</p>
<p>We woke up to the news that our president <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/mar/31/jacob-zuma-sacks-finance-minister-pravin-gordhan">Jacob Zuma had fired 9 ministers shortly before midnight</a>.</p>
<p>Capable ministers, especially so Pravin Gordhan, the minister of finances (who was doing a great job trying to steer our fragile economy in the right direction, often opposing deals that were bad for the economy but great for the pockets of Zuma and his bosses, the Gupta brothers) were replaced with ministers who <em>might</em> indeed be capable, but have clearly been selected not for that but rather for their loyalty to the Zuma network.</p>
<p>Amongst many other ramifications, this also means that the 1 trillion Rand nuclear deal with Russia is officially back on the table!</p>
<p>This was one of the many unhealthy projects blocked by Pravin Gordhan.</p>
<p>Besides <a href="https://businesstech.co.za/news/government/124993/zuma-the-guptas-and-south-africas-r1-trillion-nuclear-plans/">crippling our economy and enriching Zuma, his patronage network, and the Gupta brothers</a> (they seem to be pulling many of the strings, including those of Zuma), we really don’t need these power plants.</p>
<p>Our country’s renewable energy programmes <a href="http://theconversation.com/zumas-cabinet-reshuffle-opens-the-door-for-nuclear-deal-in-south-africa-75553">will be able to supply all of our energy needs in a cost-effective way for decades to come</a>, without any new nuclear plants in sight, thank you very much.</p>
<p>Nuclear power certainly has its place, but under these circumstances definitely not.</p>
<p>This cabinet reshuffle is the most recent in a long line of increasingly destructive moves by president Zuma and his supporters. The country is still reeling from the billions of Rands that have been and are still being extorted from the poorest of citizens by a foreign company, <a href="https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/article/2017-03-16-amabhungane-social-grants-payment-crisis-everything-you-need-to-know-but-were-afraid-to-ask/">all right under the nose of minister Bathabile Dlamini</a>.</p>
<p>Guess who did NOT get fired on Friday?</p>
<p>Loyalty seems to be sufficient to cancel out any amount of malice, greed and/or incompetence.</p>
<p>However, people in the know <a href="http://www.news24.com/Columnists/Mondli-Makhanya/how-zuma-fell-into-his-own-web-20170401">expect serious fireworks the coming weeks</a>.</p>
<p>I am hoping that they are right, and that these will be the <em>right</em> sort of fireworks. With a bit of luck and the willingness of many good-hearted and talented people who have <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.co.za/2017/04/01/kathrada-memorial-zuma-must-go-demands-crowds_a_22021430/">started speaking out and coming into action</a>, our country could soon find itself with the kind of leadership that it desperately needs.</p>
<p>Keep your fingers crossed. I look forward to seeing you on the other side!</p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>