<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>remote work on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/remote-work/</link><description>Recent content in remote work on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 16:07:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/remote-work/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #226: Stress practice</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 16:07:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</guid><description> Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.
Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.
As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&amp;rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (Youth Day), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth Emacs Org-mode / ox-hugo blogging machine (read this github issue for more details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this combination has saved me in the past.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the
week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys_run_pano_20210612.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (<a href="https://www.gov.za/youth-day">Youth
Day</a>), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth
Emacs Org-mode / <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo">ox-hugo</a> blogging machine (read <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo/issues/447">this github issue</a> for more
details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this
combination has saved me in the past.</p>
<h2 id="solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">Solstice tipping point is coming!</h2>
<p>The last thing we&rsquo;re supposed to do is to wish even just a little bit for time
to pass more quickly, for fairly obvious reasons.</p>
<p>However, when you&rsquo;re a few days from the darkest point in the year, it&rsquo;s hard
not to.</p>
<p>We currently have 9 hours and 56 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s just two minutes, and a few days, from the winter solstice on June 21,
when we&rsquo;ll have to make do with 9 hours and 54 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>I mention this here, because those 6 AM wake-ups feel more and more like the
middle of the night.</p>
<p>After the solstice, I&rsquo;ll start imagining the sun coming up a few moments
earlier every morning, and it will.</p>
<p>(Well, it will, eventually. Reader WIMM just pointed out via email that
although the days start getting longer, the sunrise will initially become even
a minute later, before finally becoming earlier starting from July 11. Read
more <a href="https://theconversation.com/why-the-sunrise-is-still-later-after-the-winter-solstice-shortest-day-77628">here</a> (thanks WIMM) or check the tables <a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-africa/stellenbosch?month=6&amp;year=2021">here</a>.)</p>
<p>It has been &hellip; <code>1 year and 11 months</code> &hellip; since <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/">the previous mention of winter
solstice on this blog</a>.</p>
<h2 id="avoid-the-jbl-endurance-run-bt-earphones-at-all-costs">Avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones at all costs</h2>
<p>A month ago <a href="/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/#world-in-my-eyes">I wrote about the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a> that I was
initially so happy with, which then spontaneously broke after a few hours of
running, and which I then returned for a replacement.</p>
<p>Well, the replacement set of <a href="https://eu.jbl.com/JBL+ENDURANCE+RUNBT.html?dwvar%5FJBL%20ENDURANCE%20RUNBT%5Fcolor=Black-GLOBAL-Current">proudly sweat-proof JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a>
lasted for about 9 hours of running, at which point they spontaneously broke in
exactly the same way.</p>
<p>Out of nowhere, the loud crackling sound started in the earpiece opposite to
the site with the control unit.</p>
<p>This crackling sound (similar to the disturbance you hear when speaker wires
have a connection issue) did not stop, even after un-pairing and even after
switching off the unit.</p>
<p>Connecting the charger after this would result in the charge light flickering
and fading in-and-out in a decidedly analogue fashion.</p>
<p>After experiencing the exact same problem with two different units, I am wary
wasting more time on a third set.</p>
<p>This was quite a disappointment, because mechanically this design was perfect
for me.</p>
<p>I will continue on my search for the perfect (1. secure in my large and
sometimes perspiring ears, so needs something in addition to just ear canal fit
and 2. durable, i.e. continues working <em>long</em> after the first 9 hours of
running) set of running earphones, and I&rsquo;ll keep you up to date on my findings.</p>
<p>In the meantime, please avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones.</p>
<h2 id="remote-work-culture-is-hard-work">Remote work culture is hard work</h2>
<p>During our Tuesday evening meetup, Theunis de Klerk of <a href="https://www.noldor.co.za/">Noldor</a> (the now fully
remote tech company, not <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noldor">the race of elves from Middle Earth</a>, although there is
a link here) gave an interesting and inspiring talk on how they have built and
cultivate great remote work culture.</p>
<p>This was an insightful look into an organization where the top leadership
continuously pours a great deal of thought and energy into maintaining healthy
culture, even in a fully remote environment with parts in different timezones.</p>
<p>On the one hand, it&rsquo;s great seeing working examples like this, on the other, it
can be quite a daunting prospect when you start thinking about how to apply
this in your own environment.</p>
<p>I believe that the future of knowledge work will <em>not</em> involve highly qualified
folks having to spend 8 hours per day at their desk because we still have not
learned that work is all about contributing value, and not about the number of
hours spent in captivity at one&rsquo;s desk.</p>
<p>That being said, during the current global remote working experiment, although
we are learning how to roll with value-generation, I do miss some of the almost
effortlessly and socially generated collaboration glue that at its best gets
folks almost instinctively chasing the same worthy goals.</p>
<p>(On the other hand, at its worst, it causes conflicts, grudges and ulcers, so
there&rsquo;s that&hellip;)</p>
<p>I would like to wrap this ramble up with one conclusion, and one interesting
tweet storm by Steven Sinofsky of Andreesen Horowitz:</p>
<ul>
<li>Conclusion: 1. Am I overestimating how &ldquo;easy&rdquo; social cohesion was when we
were in the office? 2. How do we go about getting back that real or imagined
social cohesion in this fully remote setting?</li>
<li><a href="https://a16z.com/2021/06/12/disruption-at-work-its-more-than-just-wfh/">Highly interesting tweet storm about the issue being larger and more
intricate than just WFH vs hybrid vs HQ</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="eternal-practice-vs-stress">Eternal practice vs stress</h2>
<p>I do need to note here (for future me) that I was consistently far grumpier
than usual for the last few days of the week under examination here.</p>
<p>When I say grumpy, I do mean quite detectably so.</p>
<p>This is definitely not my preferred state, so I&rsquo;m even meta-grumpy about that.</p>
<p>My retro- and introspection during the weekend came up with &ldquo;more stress than
usual&rdquo;, which is indeed probably a main contributor (wow, thanks work).</p>
<p>However, being grumpy or not is still fully my responsibility.</p>
<p>Increased stress at work is currently primarily due to new responsibilities and
the (often amplified by one&rsquo;s own imagination) expectations of colleagues, and
the unsurprising feeling of discomfort that is associated with finding oneself
faced with new kinds of challenges that you are not accustomed to (<em>cf.</em>
&ldquo;comfort zone&rdquo; and <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">stages 2 to 4 of the creative process</a>).</p>
<p>During the weekend I first resolved simply to be less grumpy (yes, you can do
that).</p>
<p>Fortunately, I also had a spot of insight as to how the root cause, i.e. the
work-related stress, could be better addressed in my specific case.</p>
<p>You see, I have chosen to be in this situation. I would have preferred the new
challenges without the concomitant stress, but that&rsquo;s unfortunately not how
<em>this</em> human normally works.</p>
<p>The realisation that I had was that this too is simply part of my lifelong
practice session.</p>
<p>I first talked about the idea of life being continuous pracrtice back in <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">WHV
#133</a>, and again later in <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">WHV #144</a> when I got around to reading a
reader-recommended book on the topic, titled &ldquo;Mastery&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Something I did not mention back then, probably because I only experience the
stress aspect as acutely at this moment, is that this particular framing helps
me to approach my current problems with curiosity, with an appetite for
learning and experimentation, and with the acceptance that my performance could
be far from perfect, perhaps even to the point of failure.</p>
<p>Some days will be good and some days will be bad.</p>
<p>(Even outside of the practice framing, one just has to accept that <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"><em>some days
gonna be crap</em></a>.)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, every day is a brand new opportunity to practice the
difficult new stuff, and to become gradually better at it, until one day, just
maybe, comfort slowly starts overtaking discomfort.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>An introduction to Asynchronous Communication for the workplace</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/16/intro-asynchronous-communication/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:10:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/16/intro-asynchronous-communication/</guid><description> Thanks to COVID-19, many organizations and their their workers have had to fast-track their previously hypothetical plans and dreams to adopt remote working.
Where this was once a long-running debate with a handful of more progressive companies actually executing, all of a sudden many of us found ourselves working from home, including spending significant parts of our day in video meetings.
Less commuting, less polluting and much more flexibility in how one achieves work-life balance are amazing benefits.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure>
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/16/intro-asynchronous-communication/undraw_working_from_anywhere_ub67_hu61004db2dd9bc9ffba05fd7d949668a3_39797_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/16/intro-asynchronous-communication/undraw_working_from_anywhere_ub67_hu61004db2dd9bc9ffba05fd7d949668a3_39797_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/16/intro-asynchronous-communication/undraw_working_from_anywhere_ub67_hu61004db2dd9bc9ffba05fd7d949668a3_39797_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        
            alt="Working from anywhere image from undraw.co"/> 
</figure>

<p>Thanks to COVID-19, many organizations and their their workers have had to
fast-track their previously hypothetical plans and dreams to adopt remote
working.</p>
<p>Where this was once a long-running debate with a handful of more progressive
companies actually executing, all of a sudden many of us found ourselves
working from home, including spending significant parts of our day in video
meetings.</p>
<p>Less commuting, less polluting and much more flexibility in how one achieves
work-life balance are amazing benefits.</p>
<p>However, it almost feels like we have to meet, albeit virtually, more than ever
before. Add to that the constantly busy office chat (Teams, Slack, Mattermost,
and many more offerings) with its groups and private chats, and the day can be
quite exhausting even before doing the actual work that is discussed in all of
these meetings.</p>
<p>Now just imagine that there was a way to skip most of those meetings, and to
keep the office chat only for social reasons.</p>
<p>Wouldn&rsquo;t that be great?</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that there is an important missing ingredient to making
exactly that happen.</p>
<p>The missing ingredient is called <em>asynchronous communication</em>.</p>
<p>With a bit of discipline and some good expectation setting, the application of
<em>real-time sometimes, asynchronous most of the time</em> will lead to a
more efficient, better documented and, importantly, a far less stressful remote
workplace.</p>
<p>To be clear, <em>real-time sometimes, asynchronous most of the time</em> makes a great
deal of sense also in non-remote work settings.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-asynchronous-communication">What is asynchronous communication?</h2>
<p>The following is an extended version of the definitions from the company
<a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/">Doist&rsquo;s blog post on the topic</a>.</p>
<h3 id="synchronous">Synchronous</h3>
<p>Synchronous communication is sending a message and <em>expecting</em> the recipient to
process the information and respond <em>immediately</em>.</p>
<p>A meeting is a pretty intensive form of this.</p>
<p>You say something, and I usually have to respond on the spot.</p>
<p>In many cases, email is also treated as synchronous communication.</p>
<p>You hear that notification ping, so you stop whatever you&rsquo;re doing and you
check the email.</p>
<p>Whether you answer immediately or not, you have succeeded in losing
concentration on your main task.</p>
<h3 id="asynchronous">Asynchronous</h3>
<p>Asynchronous communication is sending a message without <em>expecting</em> an
immediate response.</p>
<p>For example, you send me an email, and because our workplace policy sets these
expectations, I can respond thoughtfully and in depth, in a few hours, during
the following day or even later.</p>
<p>A more modern asynchronous communication tool would be the company discussion
forum, or online project management system, where thoughtful and usually longer
form messages can be <em>contextually</em> posted, that is, close to the project or
task they pertain to.</p>
<p>These messages can be read by all relevant colleagues, and discussed in the
comments.</p>
<p>A key idea here is that all communication happens asynchronously, with each
colleague taking time to think and to respond when it best fits their schedule.</p>
<p>Please see <a href="#gitlab-async-mindset-test">Gitlab&rsquo;s anynchronous mindset test</a> below.</p>
<p>An additional advantage of this method is that all of these discussions and
decisions are by default perfectly documented, can be shared with future
colleagues, and can even be surfaced later via intranet search.</p>
<h2 id="what-are-the-disadvantages-of-a-synchronous-communication-environment">What are the disadvantages of a synchronous communication environment?</h2>
<p>The following four problems that occur due to a synchronous communication
environment are paraphrased from the <a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/">Doist post</a>:</p>
<dl>
<dt>Constant interruptions</dt>
<dd>Each notification of each incoming message breaks
concentration to such an extent that people will have a hard time making
progress on the sort of valuable work that requires blocks of focus. Apart
from the immediate break, there is also the aggregate effect of all of the
day&rsquo;s interruptions which cause a great deal of unnecessary mental cycles
that could have been spent on deep work.</dd>
<dt>It becomes more important to be connected than to be productive</dt>
<dd>In such
environments, it becomes a priority to be available when someone pings
you. All energy is now diverted from valuable work into being available and
reactive.</dd>
<dt>More stress</dt>
<dd>Instead of setting their own schedules, and determining how
most of their day can be productively spent, workers spend their days
reacting to incoming messages, hence losing control of their schedules.</dd>
<dt>Lower quality discussions and sub-optimal solutions</dt>
<dd>An immediate response
is expected, especially during a meeting, so there&rsquo;s no time to come up with
a thoughtful and in-depth response.</dd>
</dl>
<p>In addition to these, there is the issue that synchronous communication further
complicates good organizational documentation and knowledge management.</p>
<p>When meetings are minuted, those minutes are brief notes of a third party who
does their best to capture the gist of the meeting.</p>
<p>However, when the &ldquo;meeting&rdquo; takes place in writing in the first place, the
documentation is by construction the most canonical description.</p>
<p>Group chat messages can be stored and indexed, but due to the nature of the
medium, namely large collections of many short messages most of which are
understandably chatter, this is a not a great way to have in depth discussions
or document decisions.</p>
<h2 id="what-are-the-advantages-of-an-asynchronous-communication-environment">What are the advantages of an asynchronous communication environment?</h2>
<p>The following is paraphrased from <a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/">Doist</a>:</p>
<dl>
<dt>Workers schedule their workday</dt>
<dd>With fewer to no meetings or other
synchronous communication expected, workers have full control over when they
do their work, which leads to greater work satisfaction and higher quality
work. Furthermore, struggling to find a meeting time that in the packed
agendas of all participants is a problem of the past.</dd>
<dt>High quality communication vs knee-jerk responses</dt>
<dd>By default, people can
spend more time thinking and drafting their messages and
responses. Communication becomes more thoughtful and in-depth. As a bonus,
there are built-in cool-down periods between every message.</dd>
<dt>Less stress thanks to better planning</dt>
<dd>When people can&rsquo;t rely on instant
communication (requests) anymore, they learn to plan ahead more carefully.</dd>
<dt>Deep work becomes the default</dt>
<dd>Because there is no expectation of being
connected and always available, people start their day with a block of deep
work. Again because of the change in expectation, workers can check async
messages a few time a day, when it suits them, and especially when it doesn&rsquo;t
interrupt a block of deep work!</dd>
<dt>Automatic documentation and greater transparency</dt>
<dd>As mentioned in the
previous section, because good asynchronous communication happens through
thoughtful writing and written discussion, all decisions are automatically
documented. Furthermore, it is straight-forward to make discussions available
to any group of people, now and in the future.</dd>
<dt>Time zone equality</dt>
<dd>For organizations that are spread out over multiple
timezones, asynchronous communication means that everyone participates on the
same platform with the same opportunities.</dd>
</dl>
<h2 id="the-solution-real-time-sometimes-asynchronous-most-of-the-time">The solution: Real-time sometimes, asynchronous most of the time</h2>
<p>Sometimes synchronous communication is justified.</p>
<p><a href="https://buffer.com/resources/asynchronous-communication/amp/">Buffer</a> lists the following reasons for synchronous, real-time communication,
such as a video meeting or a distanced face-to-face meeting:</p>
<ul>
<li>Casual hangouts, catch-ups, and celebrations</li>
<li>Urgent situations</li>
<li>Relationship-building (one-on-ones, masterminds, etc.)</li>
</ul>
<p>In their <a href="https://about.gitlab.com/company/culture/all-remote/asynchronous/">extensive asynchronous communication guide, Gitlab</a> has a longer list
of occasions that merit starting with synchronous communication:</p>
<ul>
<li>A sales engagement</li>
<li>First-time meetings with external parties</li>
<li>First-time meetings with team members who have not previously worked together</li>
<li>One-way door decisions (e.g. when stakes are high and decisions are difficult to reverse)</li>
<li>Complex initializations (e.g. defining a corporate narrative, a major overhaul to scope, etc.)</li>
<li>Emotionally sensitive topics (e.g. discussing personal issues, career path/promotion, difficult feedback, etc.)</li>
<li>Supporting and unblocking your direct reports (e.g. a regular 1:1)</li>
<li>Celebrations and retrospectives (it feels good to celebrate wins with a
group, and lightweight retrospectives can serve as kickoff points for future
sprints)</li>
</ul>
<p>If asynchronous is to be preferred, but we do sometimes need to use
synchronous, what would be the best way to approach this?</p>
<p>Fortunately, <a href="https://basecamp.com/guides/group-chat-problems#whattodo">Basecamp has a great perfect-world rule of thumb</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>real-time sometimes, asynchronous most of the time</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In other words, prefer and default to asynchronous.</p>
<p>If you opt for synchronous communication such as a meeting or a phone call, you
should have a really good reason to do so.</p>
<p>By making asynchronous the default, with synchronous the exception, your
organization will be able to reap all of the benefits listed in previous
sections.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion-just-do-it">Conclusion: Just do it</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s clear that applying the <em>real-time sometimes, asynchronous most of the
time</em> communication strategy can contribute greatly to an organization&rsquo;s
performance.</p>
<p>More thoughtful communication, better decision-making, more focused work,
automatic documentation and increased work satisfaction constitute an offer
that really should not be refused.</p>
<p>Applying this in your organization starts with ensuring that:</p>
<ol>
<li>everyone understands and applies the asynchronous mindset (see <a href="#gitlab-async-mindset-test">gitlab&rsquo;s
async mindset test</a> for an example),</li>
<li>your async practices and expectations are documented, and</li>
<li>you have the necessary tools available to apply asynchronous communication
effectively.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="further-reading">Further reading</h2>
<p>If you read one other piece, <a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/"><strong><strong>Doist</strong></strong>&rsquo;s post</a> would be my recommendation. It
contains a complete description of asynchronous communication, with interesting
statistics, and it also contains a short guide on how to apply this in your
organization.</p>
<p>As part of their Virtual First Toolkit, <strong><strong>Dropbox</strong></strong> has also made available their
guide <a href="https://blog.dropbox.com/topics/work-culture/-virtual-first-toolkit--how-to-communicate-effectively">&ldquo;How to communicate effectively&rdquo;</a>. This has practical tips on writing,
tools that can be used for different forms of communication and tips for
effective meeting.</p>
<p><strong><strong>Basecamp</strong></strong> have been making the case for remote work and for asynchronous
communication long before most others.</p>
<p>In their post <a href="https://basecamp.com/guides/group-chat-problems">&ldquo;Group Chat: The Best Way to Totally Stress Out Your Team&rdquo;</a> they
discuss the disadvantages of group chat, and how you can go about addressing
them.</p>
<p>I first wrote about that post of theirs in <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">WHV #205</a>.</p>
<p>Their piece <a href="https://basecamp.com/guides/how-we-communicate">&ldquo;The Basecamp Guide to Internal Communication&rdquo;</a> contains 30 general
principles and rules of thumb for communication, followed by a compact and
practical description of the tools and procedures that they apply.</p>
<p><strong><strong>Gitlab</strong></strong> wins the extensiveness competition with their detailed manual titled
<a href="https://about.gitlab.com/company/culture/all-remote/asynchronous/">&ldquo;Embracing asynchronous communication&rdquo;</a>. This contains low-level and detailed
sections on how async is used within the gitlab organization, <a href="https://about.gitlab.com/company/culture/all-remote/asynchronous/#how-to-implement-asynchronous-workflows">how to implement
asynchronous workflows</a>, <a href="https://about.gitlab.com/company/culture/all-remote/asynchronous/#benefits-of-asynchronous-workflows">benefits of asynchronous</a>, and finally limitations and
challenges of async.</p>
<h3 id="gitlab-async-mindset-test">Gitlab asynchronous mindset test</h3>
<p>Their rule of thumb to enter an asynchronous mindset is worth quoting here:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The easiest way to enter into an asynchronous mindset is to ask this question:
&ldquo;How would I deliver this message, present this work, or move this project
forward right now if no one else on my team (or in my company) were awake?&rdquo;</p>
<p>This removes the temptation to take shortcuts, or to call a meeting to simply
gather input. (After all, every meeting should be a review of a concrete
proposal, and only called when it will lead to a more efficient outcome than
would be possible asynchronously.)</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #192: COVID-19 part 2.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 11:09:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/</guid><description> A scene from Stilbaai, my number one favourite new vacation destination, taken on the morning after the lockdown had been announced. We were extremely fortunate to spend our last day of freedom in a place like this. Greetings, fellow humans!
It&amp;rsquo;s 16:15 (UTC+2) on Sunday afternoon as I sit here writing this.
The post seems to be mostly planned out, with fragments of text strewn around the editor window right below this sentence.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
A scene from Stilbaai, my number one favourite new vacation destination, taken
on the morning after the lockdown had been announced. We were extremely
fortunate to spend our last day of freedom in a place like this.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Greetings, fellow humans!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s 16:15 (UTC+2) on Sunday afternoon as I sit here writing this.</p>
<p>The post seems to be mostly planned out, with fragments of text strewn around
the editor window right below this sentence.</p>
<p>With sheer luck, I&rsquo;ve managed to find music that interacts well with my current
mood trajectory (finding <em>the right music</em> seems like a truly hard problem),
and at this moment I&rsquo;m still hopeful that I might also have found <a href="/tags/pomodoro/">one whole
pomodoro</a> to work with here.</p>
<p>We are living through some of the most surrealistic times I have ever
experienced.</p>
<p>For friends, for other curious observers and for posterity I think it&rsquo;s now an
even better idea than usual to write down at least some of my observations.</p>
<p>On that note, the older I get, the more clearly I see how the idea of a unified
&ldquo;I&rdquo; going through life is nothing more than an illusion, albeit seemingly
well-made.</p>
<p>In 2014 I <a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">wrote about us being patterns continuously shifting in the sands of
the universe</a>.</p>
<p>Back then, at least if I can go by my writing, it was a dawning
realisation. Now it has become Captain Obvious territory.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS</p>
<p>In this post, I look back at the period of time from Wednesday March 25 to
Sunday April 11.</p>
<h2 id="lockdown-extension">Lockdown extension.</h2>
<p>The South African national lockdown started at midnhight on Thursday, March 26
and would continue for three weeks until April 16.</p>
<p>Of course this virus wasn&rsquo;t magically going to give up and go home after
exactly three weeks.</p>
<p>Just like everyone else, we were only buying time, and I&rsquo;m super happy that we
started when we did.</p>
<p>We know <em>much</em> more now than we knew then. In three weeks more, we&rsquo;ll know even
more.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I&rsquo;ve never before seen the whole of South Africa work
together this well.</p>
<p>There is certaintly some dissent, but by and large the measures seem to be
working, and the curve looks like it is flattening for us.</p>
<p>(There will <em>of course</em> be those, as there always are, who will claim that it
was all much ado about nothing&hellip;)</p>
<p>Although we sort of saw it coming, it was still quite something hearing on
Friday evening, April 10, that the national lockdown would be extended to April
30.</p>
<h2 id="masks4all">#Masks4All</h2>
<p>On March 30, I &ldquo;joined&rdquo; the twitter #masks4all campaign by doing my little bit
to try and convince people everywhere that if <strong>all</strong> of us started wearing
home-made (the good stuff is for the healthcare workers yo!) masks as a rule,
it would contribute substantially to preventing the virus from spreading.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">South Africans, how do
we get our leaders and their advisors to look into <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Masks4All?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Masks4All</a>
as a way to end this lockdown *safely* and get the economy back into action
again? See e.g. <a href="https://t.co/iCMNAwAJhr">https://t.co/iCMNAwAJhr</a>
for a summary. <a
href="https://twitter.com/DrZweliMkhize?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@DrZweliMkhize</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/PresidencyZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@PresidencyZA</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/nicd_sa?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nicd_sa</a></p>&mdash;
Charl Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a
href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1244511197921185792?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March
30, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>I find this extra important, because it could play a really important role,
together with physical distancing, hand-washing and more, in how we end the
lockdown safely and get our already-less-than-robust economy back up and
running.</p>
<p>At the start it felt like no-one was listening, and I was getting anxious.</p>
<p>SOMEONE WAS WRONG ON THE INTERNET, AND THIS TIME IT WAS SERIOUS!</p>
<p>It really did not help that the <a href="https://www.westerncape.gov.za/gc-news/147/54065">official line of the Western Cape Health
Department on March 29 was warning <em>against</em> masks and
gloves</a>. (I&rsquo;ve archived the
statement in case anyone loses it.)</p>
<p>The point that many people were utterly missing at that point but that is
hopefully now embarrassingly obvious, is that the mask is not there to protect
the wearer, it&rsquo;s there to help protect <em>everyone else</em> from being infected by the
wearer.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a week or so (an eternity in COVID-19 time) to April 10, and South
Africa&rsquo;s very own and very respected health minister Dr Zweli Mkhize started
tweeting the new official line that the department of health now also
recommends that everyone wears cloth masks:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Cloth face mask
recommendations: <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MasksCOVID19?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#MasksCOVID19</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ClothFaceMask?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ClothFaceMask</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/COVID_19_ZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@COVID_19_ZA</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/HealthZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@HealthZA</a> <a
href="https://t.co/ptNsa4oUFl">pic.twitter.com/ptNsa4oUFl</a></p>&mdash; Dr
Zweli Mkhize (@DrZweliMkhize) <a
href="https://twitter.com/DrZweliMkhize/status/1248613456934129667?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April
10, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>See the great <a href="https://masks4all.co/">#masks4all.co</a> for more information.</p>
<p>My (microscopic little) work here is done.</p>
<h2 id="work-exercise-and-the-future-in-captivity">Work, exercise and the future, in captivity.</h2>
<h3 id="remote-work">Remote work.</h3>
<p>In <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#outlook">the previous
WHV</a>, I might have
mentioned remote work once or twice.</p>
<p>Well, since then it feels like I&rsquo;ve spent at least three and a half years
working remotely, hard.</p>
<p>I underestimated the amount of automatic, implicit, in-person communication
that happens when you&rsquo;re at the office.</p>
<p>All of that currently has to happen via various video meetings, instant
messenging, emails, and then many more instant messages during the rest of the
day.</p>
<p>In its new form, all of this communication takes quite an amount of time and
energy. It feels like I can only bunker down late morning to start on the
actual work.</p>
<p>(Microsoft Teams is our tool for all of this. Whilst it&rsquo;s not perfect, it has
been serving us quite well.)</p>
<p>In spite of the feeling that communication is taking up significantly more time
and energy, my perception is that, over-all, we engineers get a lot more done
in this new configuration.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I am hopeful that continued practice will reduce the perceived
additional communication effort.</p>
<h3 id="exercise">Exercise.</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s not allowed to leave the house even for exercise, and so my running has
taken quite a hit.</p>
<p>I have had to resort to running circles around the house for half an hour at a
time, which, in spite of me usually really enjoying the monotony of
road-running, is quite a challenge.</p>
<p>On the other hand, there are people who are stuck in apartments and <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/mar/21/man-runs-marathon-on-7-metre-balcony-during-french-lockdown">then run
42km on the
balcony</a>,
and there&rsquo;s even the South African <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/southafrica/comments/fzvtak/south_african_runner_from_george_runs_100_miles/">Eddie Mouton who ran 160km in his
yard</a>.</p>
<p>The elliptical trainer which we bought on July 31 of 2007 (it&rsquo;s the FINNLO
crosstrainer 3252), and for the almost 13 years since then has been nothing
more than an overpriced clothing and towel hanger, has seen more actual
exercise use in the past weeks than during its whole lifetime up to now.</p>
<p>One great upshot of all of this is that we more often train together, or at
least close enough for a high-five now and then.</p>
<h3 id="the-future">The future.</h3>
<p>As I alluded to in the previous <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#outlook">WHV
#191</a>, and
especially as the lockdown has now been extended, giving us even more time to
practise and build habits, I would really like to know how much of what we
learn and experience now is going to stick in the post-covid-19-era?</p>
<p>Noticing how we have to pay much more attention to how exactly we communicate,
realising how much work can actually be fit into a day without too many
interruptions, and seeing how quickly nature uses this time to recover from our
normally incessant onslaught, all lead me to think that we should not stop
analysing and discussing the changes that COVID-19 has brought.</p>
<p>Do you think we&rsquo;ll just flip back to the old normal as soon as we (hopefully)
get through this, or do you think we can look forward to a slightly upgraded
humanity?</p>
<h2 id="thats-all-folks">That&rsquo;s all folks!</h2>
<p>Because this post had already grown substantially larger than I had intended, I
just removed two whole subsections, the beefiest one about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niklas_Luhmann">Niklas
Luhmann</a> and <a href="https://writingcooperative.com/zettelkasten-how-one-german-scholar-was-so-freakishly-productive-997e4e0ca125">his amazing
Zettelkästen / external
brain</a>.</p>
<p>Do not fear, they&rsquo;ll probably make an appearance in a subsequent WHV, or
perhaps even separate posts.</p>
<p>As some of you might have read previously on this blog, the struggle in my head
between these longer form mish-mash-life-snapshot WHV posts on the one hand and
more topic-focused shorter posts on the other has been going on for years, and
will hopefully continue for years more.</p>
<p>(I say hopefully, because that means I might still be posting as well.)</p>
<p>This specific thought is still developing, but I might be starting an
experiment where I do try to write some shorter, more focused posts.</p>
<p>I will keep you up to date!</p>
<p>Ok reader, whoever and wherever you are, I wish you the very best that humanity
has to offer!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>