<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>keyboards on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/keyboards/</link><description>Recent content in keyboards on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 21:24:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/keyboards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #238: Live deep and suck out all the marrow of life</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 21:24:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/</guid><description> Welcome everyone to the 238th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the week from Monday, January 31 to Sunday, February 6, 2022.
I would like to get you started with some flowers, after which there is a possibly boring bit about improving my keyboard, followed by a final bit with a quote which I think is a bit more than just a two-bit quote.
Figure 1: Photo taken by GOU #1 at Vergelegen Wine Estate during a solidly Thing-level (see WHV #237) Sunday lunch with my inner inner circle.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome everyone to the 238th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one
covering the week from Monday, January 31 to Sunday, February 6, 2022.</p>
<p>I would like to get you started with some flowers, after which there is a
possibly boring bit about improving my keyboard, followed by a final bit with a
quote which I think is a bit more than just a two-bit quote.</p>








<figure><a href="vergelegen-sunflowers.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo taken by GOU #1 at Vergelegen Wine Estate during a solidly Thing-level (see WHV #237) Sunday lunch with my inner inner circle."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo taken by <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> at Vergelegen Wine Estate during a solidly Thing-level (see <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237</a>) Sunday lunch with my inner inner circle.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="womier-k87-keyboard-customization-unlocked">Womier K87 keyboard: Customization unlocked!</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/#yet-another--new-keyboard-yank">WHV #235 that I was quite happy with my new Varmilo
VA87m mechanical keyboard</a> and that I was also quite surprised to learn that I
might prefer <em>linear</em> switches over <em>tactile</em>, thanks to the super smooth Cherry MX
Speed Silver switches.</p>
<p>Furthermore, its stabilisers were exceptionally smooth, and quiet. It taught me
that one did not have to live with rattly stabilisers.</p>
<p>As is often the case with new knowledge, this made me re-evaluate my
relationship with my other keyboard, the Womier K87 (aka &ldquo;RGB-with-unicorns&rdquo;),
which was introduced here in <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204</a>.</p>
<p>You see, that board came with both <em>tactile</em> switches (Gateron browns), and with
rattly <a href="https://switchandclick.com/stabilizer-guide/">stabilisers</a>.</p>
<p>&hellip; and so it came to pass that I ordered 90 Cherry MX Red switches from
<a href="https://www.ctrlshiftesc.co.za/">Ctrl.Shift.Esc</a>, as well as a super cheap (R109 when I ordered, it seems the
price has just doubled!) 100g tube of SPANJAARD silicone paste.</p>
<p>The red switches are quintessentially linear. They have a more conventional
actuation distance of 2mm versus the perhaps too-quick-for-me 1.2mm of the
speed silvers.</p>
<p>Plus, they were in stock.</p>
<p>I selected the SPANJAARD silicone paste as a cheap local alternative after
reading more than I ever wanted to know about lubricants and greases for
respectively the switches themselves and the stabilisers.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m just kidding, this is exactly the sort of thing I love knowing everything
about.)</p>
<p>On the evening of Monday, January 31, our dinner table looked like this:</p>








<figure><a href="womier-red-switches-in-progress.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Brown switches out, reds are in. I kept those three browns top right for comparison. The white cap puller was much faster for me than the wire one above the keycaps."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Brown switches out, reds are in. I kept those three browns top right for comparison. The white cap puller was much faster for me than the wire one above the keycaps.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Shortly after that, I was typing on the &ldquo;new&rdquo; board, entirely unconvinced that
the switch (haha) had been worthwhile.</p>
<p>As I&rsquo;m typing this, it&rsquo;s a more than a week later, and I am now entirely
convinced.</p>
<p>Based on how they feel, and an improvement of my typing speed and accuracy on
these switches relative to brown, I am hereby joining team linear!</p>
<p>With regard to the rattly stabs: On February 2 I removed the spacebar,
backspace and return keys, disassembled the stabilisers, and coated the wire
ends in as much silicone paste as I could. Although not quite at Varmilo
levels, the three respective stabilisers have improved massively, and have
convincingly crossed my satisfaction threshold.</p>
<h2 id="live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life">Live deep and suck out all the marrow of life</h2>
<p>I used to encourage friend PK, and probably others (and probably most often
just myself), but he usually just <em>got it</em>, with the following: &ldquo;Please remember
to squeeze out every last drop from that experience&rdquo;.</p>
<p>There was a distinctly visual, almost palpable, element to this wish.</p>
<p>You have to imagine somehow grabbing the moment in question, and then wringing
it out like a wet towel to extract every last iota of juicy experience.</p>
<p>As I&rsquo;m desperately scrambling here for the right words to describe precisely
the intention, you can image how happy I was to run into the following quote by
Henry David Thoreau just the other day:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I went to the woods because I wished to live deliberately, to front only the
essential facts of life, and see if I could not learn what it had to teach, and
not, when I came to die, discover that I had not lived. I did not wish to live
what was not life, living is so dear; nor did I wish to practise resignation,
unless it was quite necessary. I wanted <strong>to live deep and suck out all the
marrow of life</strong>, to live so sturdily and Spartan-like as to put to rout all that
was not life, to cut a broad swath and shave close, to drive life into a
corner, and reduce it to its lowest terms&hellip; &ndash; Henry David Thoreau (<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/2690-i-went-to-the-woods-because-i-wished-to-live">ref</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(I just spent some time on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_David_Thoreau">Thoreau&rsquo;s wikipedia page</a>. It turns out it was not
just this quote, he was an impressive human.)</p>
<p>Folks, remember to squeeze out every last drop from <em>your</em> experience!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #235: Speed silvers</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 08:39:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/</guid><description> Welcome to the 235th edition of the (secretly bi-)Weekly Head Voices!
This one looks back at the period from Monday October 11 to Sunday October 24, 2021.
Figure 1: None of my outdoors photos satisfied the WHV guidelines, and so now you get this collage. Notable here are the two artworks by GOU #2. It looks like she has discovered one of her blisters.
(Yet Another) New Keyboard #YANK You might remember my previous semi-accidental keyboard acquisition, namely the Keychron K1 with low profile brown, no I mean red!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the 235th edition of the (secretly bi-)Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This one looks back at the period from Monday October 11 to Sunday October
24, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="whv-235-collage.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hubfbb97fc4f59ac091f45ef0e9fda8b2f_1272720_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hubfbb97fc4f59ac091f45ef0e9fda8b2f_1272720_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hubfbb97fc4f59ac091f45ef0e9fda8b2f_1272720_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hubfbb97fc4f59ac091f45ef0e9fda8b2f_1272720_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hubfbb97fc4f59ac091f45ef0e9fda8b2f_1272720_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: None of my outdoors photos satisfied the WHV guidelines, and so now you get this collage. Notable here are the two artworks by GOU #2. It looks like she has discovered one of her blisters."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: None of my outdoors photos satisfied the WHV guidelines, and so now you get this collage. Notable here are the two artworks by GOU #2. It looks like she has discovered one of her <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/">blisters</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="yet-another--new-keyboard-yank">(Yet Another) New Keyboard #YANK</h2>
<p>You might remember my previous semi-accidental keyboard acquisition, namely the
<a href="/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/#keyboard-update-k1">Keychron K1 with low profile brown, no I mean red!, Gateron switches all the way
back in June</a>.</p>
<p>Well, the K1 turned out to be not my favourite keyboard.</p>
<p>Perhaps a bit more surprising, at least to me, was that I only discovered a
week or so ago that the keyboard had RED low-profile switches and not BROWN as
I had ordered.</p>
<p>As everyone knows, reds are usually linear and browns usually have a tactile
bump.</p>
<p>However, this confusion, that my brain expected a tactile bump all this time
and never got one, only partially explains my not-liking of this keyboard. I
think the low profile reds have too muc bounce at the bottom for the way that I
type.</p>
<p>Anyways, this discovery came just after I had already accidentally ordered
another keyboard, namely the <a href="https://www.ctrlshiftesc.co.za/product/varmilo-va87m-charcoal/">Varmilo VA87m with Cherry MX Speed Silvers</a>.</p>
<p>The accident was partially caused by the fact that this keyboard was available
from a local retailer named inexplicably <a href="https://www.ctrlshiftesc.co.za/">Ctrl.Shift.Esc</a>, who dispatched the
board in record time. (Super happy with their service, and of course joking
about the name)</p>
<p>Having discovered that I really don&rsquo;t like the red switches in the K1 with the
new keyboard in transit, I was in trepidation that it would arrive and that I
would not like the Speed Silver linears at all&hellip;</p>
<p>Well, it came as yet another surprise (that&rsquo;s the world of mechanical keyboards
for me, it seems) that the new switches actually felt quite amazing in this new
board.</p>
<p>TaeKeyboards, a YouTube keyboard reviewer whom I rate highly and I believe many
others do too, called it <a href="https://youtu.be/7b2G2%5FosvxY">one of the best prebuilts he&rsquo;s ever reviewed</a>, so it
seems I&rsquo;m in good company.</p>
<p>I think that it&rsquo;s probably due to the sensitivity of the keys, but I tend to
swap characters (a friend from work gave me the tip to &ldquo;just type better&rdquo;
haha).</p>
<p>Other than that, my only other criticism of the board is that the backlight,
which I often need in the evenings, does not shine through the lettering on the
keycaps, a specific example where function should perhaps have triumphed over
form.</p>
<p>At this moment my fingers seem to be luxuriating on this keyboard. If they can
start &ldquo;just typing better&rdquo; soon, their owner would be pretty chuffed as well.</p>
<h2 id="programming-languages-is-this-the-best-we-can-do">Programming languages: Is this the best we can do?</h2>
<p>I really love programming.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a large part of my job, but it also often features during hobby time
(often the same languages and tools, just different projects, somehow
refreshing!).</p>
<p>That being said, I wonder if this, i.e. &ldquo;programming languages&rdquo;, is really the
best we can do in terms of enabling creative folks to construct reliable
software systems.</p>
<p>Aspects of this topic came up during a recent local meetup, where I (perhaps
ironically) presented my blog post comparing API construction using three
different programming languages, namely Python, Go and C#. (This too was the
output of a hobby project.)</p>
<p>The discussion was about the fact that it is increasingly more difficult
acquiring and especially retaining programming talent.</p>
<p>There are more issues at play here, notably the fact that remote work has
really opened up the market (this has been greatly accelerated by the
pandemic), enabling programmers from around the globe to work for employers
anywhere else on the globe.</p>
<p>Whilst I think this is a healthy development, it has really exacerbated the
effects of the scarcity of good programmers.</p>
<p>Some of my business owner friends, who really do their best to create great
working environments, are feeling this crunch.</p>
<p>As programmers on the fortunate side of this see-saw, we could just call it a
day at this point and continue cashing our pay cheques.</p>
<p>However, as science-minded humans, we should also be thinking about the larger
space of software construction.</p>
<p>While programming skills can certainly be learned, there is a certain specific
set of personality traits that is almost required to become really good at
programming.</p>
<p>My contention is that whilst these traits often correlate with programming
ability, they don&rsquo;t necessarily correlate with the broader sort of structured
creativity required to construct software systems.</p>
<p>Empowering more humans to be able to construct reliable and delightful software</p>
<p>In fact, the world of so-called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No-code%5Fdevelopment%5Fplatform">no-code</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Low-code%5Fdevelopment%5Fplatform">low-code</a> has been heating up for a
few years now and is&hellip; so hot right now. Friend and reader of this blog, who
goes by the codename of KB, works on <a href="https://journeyapps.com/">what looks like a pretty good entry in
this arena</a>.</p>
<p>Is this the conclusion of that line of evolution, or is there more that can be
explored?</p>
<p>How can software construction be further democratized? Are there perhaps
software construction modalities that we are currently completely blind to?</p>
<p>Could it be that one day (maybe even soon) that we just explain to the AI what
the new (AI) software construct should be able to do?</p>
<h2 id="the-power-of-fika">The power of fika</h2>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/Helena%5FLB">the High Priestess of Fika and #scicomm</a>, I have learned about the
amazing Swedish custom called &ldquo;fika&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It seems that in Swedish companies, employees <strong>from all levels in the
organization</strong> take a morning and afternoon break from work (called <em>fikapaus</em>
or <em>fikarast</em>) to eat cake and drink coffee <em>together</em>.</p>
<p><a href="https://hejsweden.com/en/have-coffee-breaks-called-fika-swedish/">Hej Sweden</a> tells me:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Among the consensus-oriented Swedes, fika is a great way to exchange knowledge,
opinions about what&rsquo;s going on in the company, and generally bond with your
colleagues. Resulting in better productivity for the company and better
wellbeing for each employee.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&hellip; and then drops this sweet nugget (I see what I did there):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Swedes spend in total 9.5 days each year having fika.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Besides that this sounds like great fun, I think the idea of having an
equalizing cultural institution like this where folks from all levels of the
organization get to bond in a more social setting would contribute
substantially to knowledge and culture dissemination in the organization.</p>
<p>In neurological terms, this reminds me strongly of the growing understanding of
<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29739890/">the role of long-distance, interareal connections in the brain</a>.</p>
<p>You could almost imagine your neurons having coffee and cake together every day
at 10:00 and 15:00.</p>
<p>On some days, it feels like my neurons do nothing <em>but</em> drink coffee and eat
cake the whole day, while on other days, it feels like they decided during fika
to push my analogies far too far.</p>
<p>Folks have a really great week, and please beware those exploding analogies!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #225: Just a perfect weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</guid><description> Dear reader,
Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.
Keyboard update: K1 You&amp;rsquo;ll remember from WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the Womier K87 with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown switches.
That keyboard is so much fun to type on.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear reader,</p>
<p>Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th
installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="la_autumn_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="keyboard-update-k1">Keyboard update: K1</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll remember from <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the
Womier K87</a> with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown
switches.</p>
<p>That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt
Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the case that fingers also like the exercise, just like their
human owners.</p>
<p>I was not planning to buy any keyboards again soon, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was quite curious whether low profile key switches (that is, slightly less
finger travel) would be a good compromise between the fun of the Womier and the
efficiency of the Sculpt.</li>
<li>The K1 was on my list of candidates of keyboards with low-profile mechanical
switches.</li>
<li>I find it difficult to resist a good deal.</li>
</ul>
<p>You see, a friendly little bird (who also hangs out on the keyboards channel of
the zatech slack) told me about the extra-special Takealot birthday special
discount on <a href="https://www.imore.com/keychron-k1-v4-review">the Keychron K1 V4 87-key keyboard</a>.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a credit card transaction, a week of waiting for delivery and
another week of getting accustomed to the new board, and here we are, with at
least me typing these words on the new K1.</p>
<p>It took a while to get used to the keycaps, which can be a slippery sometimes
(or rather, my finger tip traction is variable), but my typing speed and
accuracy on this thing are in the neighbourhood of where they should be.</p>
<p>The thing is a great deal more <em>stylish</em> than my Womier; the Womier is that
guilty pleasure 80s disco that you really love, the K1 could work in a serious
coffee shop.</p>
<p>Also, having a keyboard which can switch this easily between wired operation
(the default for my desktop) and three different bluetooth connections is
pretty convenient. On trips where I usually only take the MacBook, I could
consider taking the K1 along when I have to do A Great Deal of Serious Typing.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I can&rsquo;t yet say if the low profile switches are indeed
the compromise that I wondered about. My subjective impression now is indeed
that my fingers don&rsquo;t get so physically tired as sometimes happens with the
Womier, but I&rsquo;ll have to switch between them a few times to get a better idea.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am certainly enjoying the experience of typing on
this thing, and I am certainly wondering about the interesting role that
different types of mechanical keyboards have begun to play in my computing
life.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-about-a-new-book-notes-post-about-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Lessons about a new book notes post about Seven and a Half Lessons about the Brain</h2>
<p>After two months of early(ish) morning typing on various keyboards, I finally
managed to wrap up <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">my book notes about Seven and a Half Lessons about the
Brain</a>, a fantastic book by neuro-scientist and psychologist Lisa Feldman
Barrett.</p>
<p>I had plans, in retrospect clearly too ambitious, to have at least two (2) book
notes posts out in Q1 of this year (after it took me months to complete <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my book
notes on Creativity, Inc.</a> by the end of last year).</p>
<p>That goal was necessarily postponed to Q2, and as we can all see now, there is
not enough time for a second post like this.</p>
<p>Either I have to change the format of the book notes to something more compact,
like a bunch of bullet lists, or I should make peace with the fact that I write
these like I write them, a little prose with quotes interspersed that can
generally be read like a mini story itself, and with the fact that they&rsquo;re
going to take as much time as they do.</p>
<p>Sometimes I have mixed feelings about the practice itself.</p>
<p>It takes fragments of hobby time spread out over weeks, fragments of time that
I could probably use for more reading, other interesting tidbits and, uhm,
extra work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it feels like a sort of a mini-rebellion doing exactly this,
assembling so many little pieces into something slightly more coherent and
significant, something that stands apart from work.</p>
<p>It seems I do know what to do.</p>
<p>Thanks for the chat!</p>
<h2 id="perfect-weekends-and-the-necessary-reminders-that-precede-them">Perfect weekends and the necessary reminders that precede them</h2>
<p>The weekend of June 4, 2021, was unexpectedly perfect, and I would like to make
note of that here for future me.</p>
<p>This is the recipe that we followed, utterly by happy accident:</p>
<ul>
<li>1x reminder during the week to really focus on the now.</li>
<li>1x absolutely perfect autumn weather package: balmy 20ish degrees Celsius,
lots of sun, very little wind.</li>
<li>3x braais, one per day, with various subsets of family.</li>
<li>2x runs: one a long weekend morning run, and the other an unplanned one
with GOU#1.</li>
<li>1x polishing and publishing of the blog post mentioned above.</li>
<li>1x unexpected Sunday evening star watching with GOU#2.</li>
</ul>
<p>One would think that daily practice would help, but it turns out that sometimes
a serendipitous reminder by a friend can help to switch one&rsquo;s brain into
exactly the right gear, right before the weekend.</p>
<p>During our Friday evening start-the-weekend ritual (it&rsquo;s a braai. surprise!), I
had my first quite visceral &ldquo;THIS, this is it, this is everything&rdquo;
experience. (so lovely)</p>
<p>From then on, brain remained in the right mode right through most of the
weekend.</p>
<p>If you ever run into me before the weekend (it&rsquo;s always before the weekend!), I
would be grateful if you could remind me that it is in fact now.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you much nowness.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #204: What is your purpose?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 22:22:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</guid><description> Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September 13, 2020.
Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.
Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.
Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices,
examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September
13, 2020.</p>
<p>Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more
subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being
outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.</p>








<figure><a href="guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with Microsoft Research&amp;rsquo;s Image Composite Editor, and the power of math."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/product/computational-photography-applications/image-composite-editor/">Microsoft Research&rsquo;s Image Composite Editor</a>, and the power of math.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="sleep-update">Sleep update</h2>
<p>With our teenager back in school, we have to get up at 5:45, mercifully only
for two days of the week with the school in COVID-19-mode.</p>
<p>On other days we get to sleep in until 6:45. LUXURY!</p>
<p>(The lock-down also saved us from a few months of 5:45 wake-ups 5 time per
week during the darkest part of the winter, so there&rsquo;s that.)</p>
<p>This, together with increased pressure at work, has again brought into sharp
focus my sleep hygiene.</p>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t been doing too badly during the past months, but the current period
seemed to require a tad more attention to good sleep.</p>
<p>After reading the disappointing news that the promised first-party (Apple, in
other words) sleep-tracking in the new WatchOS 6 release was not going to be
much more than tracking time in bed, I searched around for the best third-party
sleep tracking app.</p>
<p>Well folks, after a few weeks of testing, I think that <a href="http://autosleep.tantsissa.com/">AutoSleep</a> is it!</p>
<p>(Beware, there&rsquo;s a straight rip-off app in the Google Play store. It&rsquo;s not even
in the same reality as the real thing, although the scammers have stolen a
bunch of visual elements and even copy from the real autosleep website. Oh
Android&hellip;)</p>
<p>The app appears to be almost too full of complicated-looking visual gizmos, so
much so that initially I was not as positive about it. See below for an example
of my sleep history overview:</p>








<figure><a href="autosleep_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot_huce0efa54e288cea4a99599142a3b63a7_817330_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot.png"
            

         width="240px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>However, after using it for a while, and coming to grips with the various
pieces of feedback, this app has turned out to be a great tool in my quest for
sleep hygiene nirvana.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I did have to change my watch charging habits by charging my watch
in the evening hours, so that I can sleep with it on my wrist, and I also have
to remember to tap the &ldquo;lights out&rdquo; button when I attempt to start my sleep
(you don&rsquo;t have to do this, but it gives more accurate tracking that way).</p>
<p>Now I have measurements to show how important the wind-down routine is (if I
can fit in some book-reading in bed, I can fall asleep after that in almost no
time); how some nights when it feels like I&rsquo;m quite restless, I actually do get
quite an amount of sleep; and finally how a drink or two on a weekend night can
affect my average heart rate through the night (+5 beats, oof), and more.</p>
<h2 id="wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 and nativecomp Emacs workflow update</h2>
<p>The following is for my more nerdy readers.</p>
<p>After running into <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/WSL/issues/4619#issuecomment-678652118">this comment</a> on a github issue I am subscribed to, I learned
that you can use the versatile <a href="http://www.dest-unreach.org/socat/">socat</a> tool to forward connections from a unix
socket on WSL2, via the WSL bridge and a WSL1 instance, to a TCP port on
localhost.</p>
<p>The upshot of this is that I now have a robust X11 connection from WSL2 to X410
running on my Windows laptop.</p>
<p>This is possible without socat, but you either need to forward ports using SSH
(which I&rsquo;ve done), or punch holes in the firewall, and then, as if that&rsquo;s not
bad enough, deal with a connection that breaks every time the laptop goes into
suspend.</p>
<p>With the socat X11 connection in place, I decided that it was time to go
further around the WSL2 bend and replace my complicated rsync-based scripts for
copying source code from the Windows host to the WSL2-native filesystem with a
second instance of dropbox running directly on WSL2, with a severe selective
sync configuration.</p>
<p>By the way, after <a href="https://dropbox.tech/infrastructure/rewriting-the-heart-of-our-sync-engine">Dropbox rewrote their sync engine (in Rust)</a>, nothing else
even comes close in terms of performance.</p>
<p>Thanks to this perfect storm of socat-X11-boosted WSL2 and MULTI-dropbox, I
decided that it was finally time to commit to <a href="https://akrl.sdf.org/gccemacs.html">the new nativecomp Emacs &ldquo;capable
of compiling and running Emacs Lisp as native code&rdquo;</a>, so I busted out my
slightly modified version of <a href="https://masteringemacs.org/article/speed-up-emacs-libjansson-native-elisp-compilation">Mickey Petersen&rsquo;s</a> Dockerfile and compiled me one.</p>
<p>This very post is being written on native-compiled Emacs Lisp, running on WSL2,
displaying via socat to X410.</p>
<p><code>#feelsgoodman</code></p>
<p>(P.S. I&rsquo;ve been running like this for about three weeks, with nary an
issue. The future is now.)</p>
<h2 id="keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">Keyboard update: Unicorns-with-RGB</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/#my-attempt-at-dipping-my-toes-carefully-into-the-world-of-mechanical-keyboards">WHV #200 how I carefully started dipping my toes in the
clickity-clackety waters of mechanical keyboards</a> by acquiring a cheap keyboard
with hot-swappable <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile-clicky/outemu-blue/">Outemu blue switches</a>.</p>
<p>What I did not tell you then, was that shortly after acquiring that keyboard, I
had already ordered the <a href="https://youtu.be/e9gRESbY-e8">Womier K87 all-acrylic RGB-overload keyboard</a> from
Banggood.</p>
<p>My reason for ordering that specific board was not so much the lighting (WHICH
IS FREAKING SPECTACULAR BUT BACK THEN I DID NOT KNOW THIS), but rather because
it was the most affordable mechanical keyboard with universal(-ish)
hotswappable switches.</p>
<p>You see, the Outemu board can only take Outemu switches, while with a board
with universal sockets, you have access to a whole smorgas(key)bord of
different switches!</p>
<p>The Womier finally arrived after slightly more than a month, with <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile/gateron-brown/">Gateron brown
switches</a> installed as I had requested.</p>
<p>Probably due to both the brown switches (rated 45g actuation force but probably
less, tactile but not clicky) and due to the board&rsquo;s far more solid
composition, my typing comfort and speed on this thing are close to what I
usually have on my Microsoft Sculpt ergonomic.</p>
<p>Because of this, I don&rsquo;t swap back to the Sculpt nearly as often.</p>
<p>Together with the fact that the keyboard has an impressive and varied
collection of intricate animated lighting patterns thanks to the RGB LED behind
each and every single key, and a whole bunch of extra LEDs in the acrylic body,
this leads to a great deal of typing fun.</p>
<p><code>#feelsbrightman</code></p>
<h2 id="running-update">Running update</h2>
<p>Back in <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">WHV #177</a> I embraced the space and acquired my first pair of Altras, a
pair of road shoes named Escalante 1.0, for a good price, because the 1.5 had
already been released.</p>
<p>Recently I was again in the fortunate position to buy a pair of 1.5s for a good
price, as, you guessed it, the 2.0 had already been released.</p>
<p>The new babies look like this:</p>








<figure><a href="altra_escalante_1.5.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Running in them has been super enjoyable.</p>
<p>(The 1.0s are at about 700km, which is usually a good time to retire them from
running. Now they are just for cocktail parties and business meetings.)</p>
<p>On a more philosophical note, with the aforementioned improving weather, the
aforementioned increased pressure at work, and the non-aforementioned abundance
of mountains all around me, I have taken to randomly taking a few hours off
from aforementioned work to go run in the now aforementioned mountains.</p>
<p><code>#feelslifeaffirmingman</code></p>
<h2 id="what-is-your-purpose">What is your purpose?</h2>
<p>We have a great tradition here at the WHV of revising our official and utterly
complete life philosophy based on discussions with wise friends.</p>
<p>See for example <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">WHV #124</a> where I had to add a third rule to <em>WHV&rsquo;s Two Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em>.</p>
<p>Quite poetically, the additional rule was &ldquo;Evolve&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(FYI, the current official WHV approach to life, the universe and everyhing is
summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.)</p>
<p>During the beautifully-surrounded lunch discussion with longest-time friend
(LTF, henceforth), as depicted in the panoramic photo at the start of this
post, we also spent some time talking about life directions vs. goals.</p>
<p>As you know, I am <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">not a fan of life goals, instead opting for life directions</a>.</p>
<p>LTF agreed with some of my reasoning, but made the valid point that goals were
required to measure and maintain velocity along one&rsquo;s chosen directions, or
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">systems</a>.</p>
<p>In principle we agree on this point also, but I believe that the conversation
will have to continue, as we still need to define and then articulate a
closed-form solution to the directions vs goals issue, or rather a guideline
that can be used to determine the correct relative dosage.</p>
<p>Probably more important was LTF&rsquo;s contribution of the concept of &ldquo;purpose&rdquo;.</p>
<p>One could argue that life directions form one&rsquo;s purpose, but that would be
missing an opportunity I think.</p>
<p>As LTF later quipped:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Purpose = the reason you get up in the morning. Goals = help you go to sleep at
night.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At least in my case, I have a number of life directions, but I think a purpose
is a higher-level, mostly singular, desired outcome of your life&rsquo;s work.</p>
<p>Ideally, <em>life directions</em> should be set in order to orient one towards
fulfilling one&rsquo;s <em>purpose</em>, with continuously evolving <em>goals</em> punctuating the way
there.</p>
<p>What is <em>your</em> purpose?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #200: We are extremely pleased to be here</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 17:45:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/</guid><description> Figure 1: A rainbow over Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay, captured by GOU#1.
Well hello there everyone, and welcome to this, the 200th edition of the Weekly Head Voices.
While I am super happy that we&amp;rsquo;ve reached this number of episodes, I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything special planned, besides being festively two weeks late.
Being that late also means that this post looks back at the three weeks from Monday June 29 to Sunday July 19 of the year 2020, also known as Cray-cray 20.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="bb_rainbow.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu98b33b7c39616f8f4db766c017c9e6b0_1401064_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu98b33b7c39616f8f4db766c017c9e6b0_1401064_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu98b33b7c39616f8f4db766c017c9e6b0_1401064_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu98b33b7c39616f8f4db766c017c9e6b0_1401064_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu98b33b7c39616f8f4db766c017c9e6b0_1401064_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A rainbow over Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay, captured by GOU#1."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A rainbow over Betty&rsquo;s Bay, captured by GOU#1.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there everyone, and welcome to this, the 200th edition of the Weekly
Head Voices.</p>
<p>While I am super happy that we&rsquo;ve reached this number of episodes, I don&rsquo;t have
anything special planned, besides being festively two weeks late.</p>
<p>Being that late also means that this post looks back at the three weeks from
Monday June 29 to Sunday July 19 of the year 2020, also known as Cray-cray 20.</p>
<h2 id="my-attempt-at-dipping-my-toes-carefully-into-the-world-of-mechanical-keyboards">My attempt at dipping my toes carefully into the world of mechanical keyboards</h2>
<p>You might remember that <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#ergonomic-keyboard-one-way-street">back in May I wrote the following</a> after having tried
out a cheap non-ergonomic (i.e. straight) keyboard:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One could perhaps get used to the mushiness, or preferably just invest in a
more expensive (mechanical) keyboard, but that ulnar deviation is a total deal
breaker.</p>
<p>My dreams of joining the clickety-clackety cliques of the mechanical keyboard
digerati had been shattered, fortunately quite cheaply.</p>
<p>Instead, I shall be redoubling my Sculpt stockpiling efforts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well about that&hellip;</p>
<p>The clickety-clackety cliques continued calling, and so I decided to apply an
additional but small amount of money on a very much entry-level mechanical
keyboard in order to determine if my mechanical keyboard dreams were to remain
just that.</p>
<p>The cheap but still quite respectable (well, if you&rsquo;re ok with rainbow
lighting) <a href="https://youtu.be/IYN3aHjbxmU">T-Dagger Corvette</a> arrived this past Wednesday around lunch time,
along with its extremely clicky and hotswappable (!!) <a href="https://mechanicalkeyboards.com/switches/index.php?switch=Outemu-Blue">Outemu blue switches</a>.</p>
<p>(Each and every key has its own removable, mechanical switch, in this case
Outemu blues, which are tactile and clicky. Each colour of each brand has its
own characteristics, so you can fine-tune how you would like to type, and how
you would like it to sound while you type.)</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve only spent a few days working with it, but my word, what a bunch of fun
typing has become!</p>
<p>The extreme tactility of the keys, together with the calmly confident click that
each press causes (this dream can of course only really take place during the
current WFH phase we are going through), has really put the titillation back
into typing.</p>
<p>This is so much fun that I&rsquo;ll probably keep at it for a while.</p>
<p>Also, compared to <a href="/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/#microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-desktop-at-4-years-rip">one of my previous Sculpt keyboards where the failure of a
single key meant that I had to replace the whole keyboard</a>, it&rsquo;s great that with
this far cheaper mechanical keyboard I am able to pull and replace, quite
trivially, the mechanical switch in question.</p>
<p>The only problem now is that I have this strange new craving to acquire more
mechanical keyboards and keyboard paraphernalia&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="keyboard-addendum">Keyboard addendum</h3>
<p>The keyboard officially supports &ldquo;full key non-conflict&rdquo;, which sounds like
some sort of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rollover%5F(key)#Keyboard%5Fusage">key roll-over</a>.</p>
<p>As a non-gamer, this will probably never affect me, although I have
experimented with it by mashing down on as many keys simultaneously as
possible, and then seeing them all still appear on the screen.</p>
<p>I do fantasise that sometimes I type that fast, and that then this rollover
will really help!</p>
<p>(I just did a quick experiment: 8 fingers mashing down at the same time on the
dvorak home row gave me &ldquo;ansoeuht&rdquo;. Keys in order from left to right are
&ldquo;aoeuhtns&rdquo;. Neat.)</p>
<p>Not unimportantly, my GOUs are fascinated by the pretty water droplet mode of
the RGB backlighting, which I can fortunately disable when working.</p>
<p>To my surprise, the backlighting in one of its static not-too-bright modes is
really quite useful when the sun starts setting at the end of a work day.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-update">Lazar Focus update</h2>
<p>Since <a href="/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/#on-slipping-and-shipping-a-side-project">I last mentioned</a> my shipping little side-project <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a>, the windows
distraction blocker that helps you focus like a boss (I&rsquo;m still working on the
marketing over here, sorry), another big feature update shipped, namely fully
automatic time-tracking.</p>
<p>The number of sales is currently somewhat more than one, but still fewer than
ten.</p>
<p>Although I use LF almost every day, it&rsquo;s brilliant when someone else who
generally does not even know me, decides to <strong>buy</strong> a copy for themselves.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re into relaxing (some might say sleep-inducing) screencasts, I have two
new ones on offer.</p>
<p>The first is 4 minutes, and shows how to get started with Lazar Focus and its
automatic activity logging:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G8z7ZACPtrc" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>The second got a bit out of hand.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s 12 minutes of me, in my evening voice, taking you through the minute
details of a work day as tracked by Lazar Focus:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ccMp1yYBOd0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>If you&rsquo;re on twitter, and you&rsquo;d like to keep an eye on Lazar Focus, you could
consider following <a href="https://twitter.com/LazarFocused">@LazarFocused</a>! (tweet frequency is currently about once to
twice per week)</p>
<h2 id="camper-philosohpy">Camper philosohpy</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>Driving along <a href="/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/#the-beach">Clarence drive</a> three weeks ago, with the usual awe-inspiring
views over the bay, we saw a couple sitting beside the road next to their
camper, bathed in the golden, nay <em>divine</em>, late-afternoon sun.</p>
<p>They were clearly having a ridiculously good time.</p>
<p>On the back of their camper, the following important message stood lettered:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We are extremely pleased to be here.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Folks, I really wish each and every one of you moments like that, moments so
good that you can be extremely pleased to be exactly where you are.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #195: Pragmatic</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 23:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/</guid><description> Figure 1: Photo from a walk with the fam jam up the mountain a little while out from our backyard, all within the sanctioned exercise hours between 6 and 9 in the mornings.
This edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the week from Monday May 11 to Sunday May 17, 2020.
The rest of this post consists of a part about keyboards, a part chock full of ways to waste your time with WSL and f#, a part about why you might be wasting your time with aforementioned, and then finally a part about a really interesting book.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="nbh_mountain_walk_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo from a walk with the fam jam up the mountain a little while out from our backyard, all within the sanctioned exercise hours between 6 and 9 in the mornings."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Photo from a walk with the fam jam up the mountain a little while out from our backyard, all within the sanctioned exercise hours between 6 and 9 in the mornings.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the week from Monday May
11 to Sunday May 17, 2020.</p>
<p>The rest of this post consists of a part about keyboards, a part chock full of
ways to waste your time with WSL and f#, a part about why you might be wasting
your time with aforementioned, and then finally a part about a really
interesting book.</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t like keyboards, and you&rsquo;re wondering in a non-curious way what a
WSL is, I would strongly recommend that you jump to the part, at the end of the
post, about the really interesting book.</p>
<h2 id="ergonomic-keyboard-one-way-street">Ergonomic keyboard one-way street</h2>
<p>As you will recall from <a href="/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/#microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-desktop-at-4-years-rip">the thrilling events of episode #193</a>, one of my two
(home-office and office-office) Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboards gave up
the ghost.</p>
<p>After far too many keyboard reviews and a fruitless search for a worthy
alternative, I indeed gave up and tried to make peace with the fact that over
the coming years I&rsquo;ll be slowly buying up the rest of the world&rsquo;s Sculpt
supply.</p>
<p>My secret campaign got off to a pretty unspectacular start as I was able to
find exactly one (1) online retailer that was able to supply at this moment.</p>
<p>I mundanely ordered the thing, and it was pretty mundanely delivered to my
house a few days later.</p>
<p>After some breaking in, I am happy to report that a brand-new Sculpt indeed
feels a great deal more amazing than a 4-year-old Sculpt.</p>
<p>As backups for any additional future apocalyptic situations, I also bought two
much cheaper &ldquo;normal&rdquo; keyboards, namely <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/accessories/en-us/products/keyboards/wired-keyboard-600/anb-00001">the Microsoft Wired Keyboard 600</a>.</p>
<p>I tried typing on one just to see what it was like, but more specifically to
develop some sort of intuition for if I would ever be able to return to
straight boards.</p>
<p>To be quite frank, my first impressions were pretty horrible.</p>
<p>Wrists having to bend outwards like that is positively uncomfortable, while the
keys on that unit make for a solid 14 on the 10-point mushiness scale.</p>
<p>One could perhaps get used to the mushiness, or preferably just invest in a
more expensive (mechanical) keyboard, but that ulnar deviation is a total deal
breaker.</p>
<p>My dreams of joining the clickety-clackety cliques of the mechanical keyboard
digerati had been shattered, fortunately quite cheaply.</p>
<p>Instead, I shall be redoubling my Sculpt stockpiling efforts.</p>
<h2 id="interlude-of-even-more-nerdy-miscellany-dot">Interlude of even more nerdy miscellany.</h2>
<p>On Friday evening I was sucked into Windows and WSL2 again.</p>
<p>I stayed up a bit too late because I discovered that instead of displaying to
X410 on Windows, which is slightly painful with WSL2 due to port redirects
and/or firewalling and/or the connection dying every time the Windows host
suspends, one can also start xrdp on WSL2, and then connect to that with
Windows remote desktop.</p>
<p>For WSL2, this is much more robust than X11, and for some use-cases it offers a
better experience. (I&rsquo;m writing this on Tuesday, and <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/commandline/the-windows-subsystem-for-linux-build-2020-summary/">MSBuild has just made a
number of super relevant announcements with regard to native WSL2 Linux GUI
support</a>. For the demo of WSL2 Linux GUI apps, they were displaying to Wayland
on WSL2 and connecting to that using RDP.)</p>
<p>On Saturday, I wrestled with and was solidly trounced by .net core 5 preview 3
and the preview of F# 5.</p>
<p>My goal was to try out the <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-f-5-preview-1/">new <code>r# nuget</code> package references</a>, and specifically
to try this out with the PowerShell type provider in <a href="https://github.com/fsprojects/FSharp.Management">FSharp.Management</a>.</p>
<p>At this point, I also can&rsquo;t tell you exactly why.</p>
<p>I now believe that this was just an instance of the eternal and far broader
learn-something-completely-new vs. work-on-some-compounding-activity conundrum.</p>
<p>(I would later learn that Fsharp.Management has not been updated in a while,
and the packages are not compatible with netcore or netstandard.)</p>
<p>Probably more importantly, I learned that when you&rsquo;re an utter F# noob like me
you should probably just avoid the bleeding edge altogether.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s called the <em>bleeding</em> edge for good reason.</p>
<h3 id="the-story-behind-this-story-one-context-to-rule-them-all">The story behind this story: One context to rule them all!</h3>
<p>When I bought my ex-MacBook Pro 2017 in 2017 on my birthday, you might remember
<a href="/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/#new-laptop">how I justified it then</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Up to then, I had been working on all of three different machines:
Linux-running i7 desktop (acquired in Feb of 2015), early 2015 13 retina
MacBook Pro (acquired in June of 2015) and my trusty old klunky i7 Acer
Linux-running laptop (acquired around March 2013).</p>
<p>Data is kept in sync, but context switching between different projects with
different development environments on different machines at home and at work
does seem to take up more time than I would care to admit.</p>
<p>Having everything on a single powerful-enough laptop would indeed make the most
sense from a time-efficiency perspective.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That part of the MacBook Pro experiment worked out quite well: The hardware and
software was good enough for <em>everything</em> that I needed to do, so I hardly ever
needed to context switch out of the laptop.</p>
<p>Although <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">the new ThinkPad</a> is more powerful, the fact that I reboot multiple
times per day in and out of Windows and two different Linux configurations on
the laptop is almost like having three different machines, which of course
kills the whole single context dream.</p>
<p>(spoiler alert: In the book-review section after this, context-switching is one
of the main villains!)</p>
<p>Anyways, the reason I keep on returning to WSL2 and then wasting time trying to
make it work more like native Linux and to integrate better with my workflow on
Windows is because I would really like to get rid of this specific context
switch.</p>
<h2 id="pragmatic-thinking-and-learning">Pragmatic Thinking and Learning</h2>
<p>This past weekend I finished reading <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3063393-pragmatic-thinking-and-learning">Pragmatic Thinking &amp; Learning - Refactor
Your Wetware (ed: ahem) by Andy Hunt</a>.</p>
<p>The book is chock full of valuable guidelines for trying to improve the way in
which I apply the limited mental energy I have at my disposal.</p>
<p>(Quite ironically, it felt like the weekend was pretty much me flying right in
the face of just about every piece of advice in the book.)</p>
<p>Here is a selection of the notes I made, slightly massaged for your
consumption. Bon appetit!</p>
<ul>
<li>Make room for the creative part of your brain to fly. First pour in some
reading and structured thinking, and then take a walk, stare out into space,
shower (again), take a nap, make a drawing upside-down. Do whatever&rsquo;s
required to shut logical Spock voice up for a while. When the ideas start
flying in, and they do, switch logical Spock voice back on to structure and
process them.</li>
<li>Build and start using an exocortex. (The reason I bought this book, is
because it was pointed out to me as a good reference for the context and term
<em>exocortex</em>. I&rsquo;m planning to write more about it <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/#the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">here</a> and <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">elsewhere</a>.)</li>
<li>Science says that happiness enhances cognition. In other words, when you&rsquo;re
happier, you&rsquo;re really smarter.</li>
<li><strong>Write drunk, revise sober.</strong></li>
<li>Get in the habit of collecting snippets of your writing. That&rsquo;s what the
exocortex is for. You might be surprised at what you&rsquo;re able to construct
with all of the snippets you collect over time. In the book, this is called
the Fieldstone method, but it sounds suspiciously similar to slips of paper
in a slipbox, aka Zettelkasten.</li>
<li>Formulate SMART goals, that is Specific, Measurable, Achivable, Relevant and
Time-boxed. If you read this blog, you&rsquo;re probably &ldquo;smart&rdquo; enough (dad joke,
sorry) to figure out why this is good.</li>
<li>Manage your mind along three axes:
<ol>
<li>Increase focus and attention, e.g. by training focus and attention also
through practising meditation and by sometimes just doing nothing. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple%5Fdrafts%5Fmodel">Daniel
Dennett&rsquo;s <em>multiple drafts</em> model of consciousness</a> is discussed here,
super interesting stuff.
<ul>
<li>On that note, your whole brain and all of its high-level capabilities
are squarely in the use-it-or-lose-it camp.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Manage your knowledge. You guessed it: Exocortex.</li>
<li>Optimise your current context. Keep in your view only what is required to
work on the current thing. Minimise context switching. Avoid distractions
and manage interruptions.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Well, that was basically my exocortex flexing for you.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS</p>
<p>After all of that, my favourite part of the book was this:</p>








<figure><a href="pragmatic_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="pragmatic_screenshot.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>For those of you viewing this blog in its 100% text-only form, the screenshot
above is of the part of the text explaining that not every day is going to be a
productive one.</p>
<p>I highlighted that, and added the comment:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Some days gonna be crap.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As life goes on, I have come to the realisation that no matter how hard you
work and how much you practise, the days when everything seems to go right
according to plan are truly scarce and should be celebrated.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s probably best to make peace with that fact, and simply to never stop
trying.</p>
<p>Also remember that it is quite possible to bend time just a little bit so as to
create a little more space around the small victories and pleasures that one
experiences even on <em>those</em> days.</p>
<p>See you around friends!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #145: The Narrating Self.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 20:12:44 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/</guid><description> View of the False Bay from the Helderberg Nature Reserve.
The work part of the week flew by.
(I think this is the reason for the shortness of this post. As is often the case, we start with journal stuff, then nerd stuff and, hidden at the end, some backyard philosophy stuff.)
Dear diary The weekend part on the other hand started with a welcome-back-braai (HI MOM!) on Friday, followed by a sublime oxtail potjie on Saturday and concluded today with a sublime long(ish, by my standards as always) run in the morning (showing a little solidarity with the Comrades participants whilst not completely busting my barefoot-style-acclimatising feet and ankles) plus Helderberg stroll and lunch, and is now ending with a WHV writing session.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/false_bay_from_helderberg.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/false_bay_from_helderberg-1024x502.jpg"
        
            alt="View of the False Bay from the Helderberg Nature Reserve."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>View of the False Bay from the Helderberg Nature Reserve.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The work part of the week flew by.</p>
<p>(I think this is the reason for the shortness of this post. As is often the case, we start with journal stuff, then nerd stuff and, hidden at the end, some backyard philosophy stuff.)</p>
<h2 id="dear-diary">Dear diary</h2>
<p>The weekend part on the other hand started with a welcome-back-braai (HI MOM!) on Friday, followed by a sublime oxtail potjie on Saturday and concluded today with a sublime long(ish, by my standards as always) run in the morning (showing a little solidarity with the <a href="http://ewn.co.za/2018/06/10/it-was-an-emotional-race-says-2018comrades-winner">Comrades</a> participants whilst not completely busting my barefoot-style-acclimatising feet and ankles) plus Helderberg stroll and lunch, and is now ending with a WHV writing session.</p>
<p>(Sundays which start with a run, have family stuff in between, and end with WHV are automatically awarded a 12/10-would-do-again rating according to my patented How Was Your Day Honey evaluation system.)</p>
<h2 id="nerdy-pro-tip">Nerdy Pro-tip</h2>
<p>Just in case you missed it, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gboard/id1091700242?mt=8">Googles Gboard keyboard for iOS</a> quietly shipped an update last week that includes as one of its new features support for Afrikaans. This brings the number of smart iOS keyboards (smart, as in AI-based) that support Afrikaans up to the total of two (2). The other is <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/za/app/swiftkey-keyboard/id911813648?mt=8">SwiftKey</a>, which has supported Afrikaans for some years now.</p>
<p>(The lack of a mobile keyboard with native support for ones language can really complicate effective communication. Preferring fully formed sentences, Ive never really gotten the hang of SMS-speak.)</p>
<h2 id="homo-deus">Homo Deus</h2>
<p>After a slight detour with a number of other books that have featured on this blog, I have returned to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2016/sep/11/homo-deus-brief-history-tomorrow-yuval-noah-harari-review">Yuval Hararis Homo Deus</a>.</p>
<p>I am about 75% through, but I can already say that this is one of the best works Ive read in the past decade.</p>
<p>The way in which Harari, a history professor, weaves together so many strands of history and present to extrapolate our planets future is nothing short of magical. Along the way, he takes the reader along on many mind-expanding tangents.</p>
<p>The one tangent I made note of to mention here, was his treatment of the illusion, which we are all brought up to entertain, that each human houses a single ego or individual.</p>
<p>By citing and discussing several examples of humans with separated brain hemispheres, he makes a strong case for the observation that most probably you house multiple identities.</p>
<p>There is a strong narrating self who tries to weave together the experiences and inputs of the other selves, and who will go to great lengths to make everything fit.</p>
<p>Thinking about all of the internal discussions one has throughout every day, and the seeming disagreements one can have between yesterdays you and todays you, Hararis thesis starts to sound like a really good explanation.</p>
<p>This soon leads to interesting new questions: What would be the best way to manage ones multiple aspects, especially in the light of the fact that one does not even know with certainty who is asking this question?</p>
<p>(Astute readers will have noticed that my choice of a title for this blog has finally been vindicated after all this time.)</p>
<p>See you next week, my suddenlymultitudinous readers!</p>
<p>P.S. Harari says that intelligence and consciousness dont necessarily go together. We are entering a future where many of us are going to be made obsolete by constructs which dont possess consciousness but are far more intelligent than we are.</p>
<p>P.P.S. For one of the best hard sci-fi books dealing with our often-held but anthropocentrically flawed perspective that consciousness and intelligence go together, you can do a lot worse than <a href="https://books.google.co.za/books/about/Blindsight.html?id=FVMzz-xINLsC&amp;source=kp_cover&amp;redir_esc=y">Blindsight, by Peter Watts</a>. Read that book.</p>
<p></p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Getting the FRIKKING euro key working on a Dvorak keyboard layout in Ubuntu 5.04</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2005/09/22/getting-the-frikking-euro-key-working-on-a-dvorak-keyboard-layout-in-ubuntu-504/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2005 14:16:16 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2005/09/22/getting-the-frikking-euro-key-working-on-a-dvorak-keyboard-layout-in-ubuntu-504/</guid><description><![CDATA[ I&rsquo;ve lost at least 5 hours of my life to the frikking euro key on my Microsoft Natural (old-style) keyboard. It seems that Gnome 2.10 on Ubuntu 5.04, otherwise a great combination, enjoys torturing its Dvorak keyboard layout users with the euro-symbol on the &ldquo;5&rdquo; key. It simply doesn&rsquo;t work, no matter what you try.
After sacrificing the prerequisite 5 hours to the Linux gods of Ultimate Non-Usability, I came up with the following solution.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I&rsquo;ve lost at least 5 hours of my life to the frikking euro key on my Microsoft
Natural (old-style) keyboard. It seems that Gnome 2.10 on Ubuntu 5.04,
otherwise a great combination, enjoys torturing its Dvorak keyboard layout
users with the euro-symbol on the &ldquo;5&rdquo; key. It simply doesn&rsquo;t work, no matter
what you try.</p>
<p>After sacrificing the prerequisite 5 hours to the Linux gods of Ultimate
Non-Usability, I came up with the following solution. Make the following change
to your <code>/etc/X11/xkb/symbols/pc/dvorak</code> file:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-diff" data-lang="diff"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#d33682">--- dvorak.ORIG 2005-09-22 11:28:18.704428504 +0200
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#d33682"></span><span style="color:#d33682">+++ dvorak      2005-09-22 11:45:14.296035112 +0200
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#d33682"></span><span style="color:#d33682">@@ -16,7 +16,7 @@
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#d33682"></span>     key &lt;ae02&gt; { [         2,  at              ]       };
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>     key &lt;ae03&gt; { [         3,  numbersign      ]       };
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>     key &lt;ae04&gt; { [         4,  dollar          ]       };
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#d33682">-    key &lt;ae05&gt; { [         5,  percent         ]       };
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#d33682"></span><span style="color:#d33682">+    key &lt;ae05&gt; { [         5,  percent, EuroSign, EuroSign ] };
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#d33682"></span>     key &lt;ae06&gt; { [         6,  asciicircum, dead_circumflex, dead_circumflex ]};
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>     key &lt;ae07&gt; { [         7,  ampersand       ]       };
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>     key &lt;ae08&gt; { [         8,  asterisk        ]       };
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Now make sure that your right-ALT generates <code>ISO_Level3_Shift</code> (also known as
<code>AltGr</code>) by using <code>xev</code>. If your font and roughly 8000 other little settings
support it, pressing right-alt-5 should make a pretty euro symbol.
</ae08></ae07></ae06></ae05></ae05></ae04></ae03></ae02></p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>