<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Leaving on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/leaving/</link><description>Recent content in Leaving on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 11:31:04 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/leaving/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>On leaving the Netherlands</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2013/12/14/on-leaving-the-netherlands/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 11:31:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2013/12/14/on-leaving-the-netherlands/</guid><description>Moving consists of leaving one place and going to another. This post is about the first part. It’s really not easy to write, but I would like for people to understand that the leaving part of this decision is one of the more difficult things I have ever had to do.
So after 13 beautiful years in this great little country, we are leaving the Netherlands.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><span style="line-height: 1.6;">Moving consists of </span><em style="line-height: 1.6;">leaving</em> <span style="line-height: 1.6;">one place and </span><em style="line-height: 1.6;">going to</em> <span style="line-height: 1.6;">another. This post is about the first part. It’s really not easy to write, but I would like for people to understand that the </span><em style="line-height: 1.6;">leaving</em> <span style="line-height: 1.6;">part of this decision is one of the more difficult things I have ever had to do.</span></p>
<p>So after 13 beautiful years in this great little country, we are leaving the Netherlands.</p>
<p>Our life here has been exceptionally happy and fulfilling. We’ve made many great friends, and even some best friends. Our children are super happy in their little lives. Hey, we made a little family!</p>
<p>The single downside of the beautiful life that we’ve had here, is that <em>leaving</em> is complicated, and even a little painful.</p>
<p>It’s complicated, because that’s the way it is when one has to move a whole household and wrap up 13 years of accumulated <em>stuff.</em> It’s complicated, because we’re moving in the wrong direction, away from our adopted country. We can’t leave a trace behind.</p>
<p>It hurts, because we would love to stay with our friends here, but we have now made the choice to live far away.</p>
<p>We actually have no good reasons to leave, while there are many reasons to stay. The thing is, our reasons for moving are all in the <em>going to</em> part.</p>
<p>I think this might be a healthy perspective on moving. Unfortunately, but not unexpectedly, it’s just not the easiest.</p>
<p><em>Dearest friends, thank you for the parties, for the laughter, for the warmth and for making us feel so at home. Thank you for being the kind of human beings that never stop striving to be more human.</em></p>
<p><em>I would love to see you on the other side.</em></p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>