<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/</link><description>Recent content on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 22:24:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #234: Huis op die duin</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 22:24:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/</guid><description> Hello and welcome back my friends!
It&amp;rsquo;s 17:50 on Sunday, October 10, 2021 as I write this.
We have just returned from the most amazing spring break in one of our favourite spots. I&amp;rsquo;m relaxing on the sofa, with GOU #3 to my right doing what little digital natives do.
Figure 1: Beach run on Lappiesbaai at low tide is as great as it looks.
I&amp;rsquo;m not sure when exactly this post will be done, but whatever the case may be, it samples, extremely sparsely as always, the period of time from Monday September 27 to Sunday October 10, 2021.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello and welcome back my friends!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s 17:50 on Sunday, October 10, 2021 as I write this.</p>
<p>We have just returned from the most amazing spring break in one of our
favourite spots. I&rsquo;m relaxing on the sofa, with GOU #3 to my right doing what
little digital natives do.</p>








<figure><a href="lappiesbaai-run.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Beach run on Lappiesbaai at low tide is as great as it looks."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Beach run on Lappiesbaai at low tide is as great as it looks.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure when exactly this post will be done, but whatever the case may be,
it samples, extremely sparsely as always, the period of time from Monday
September 27 to Sunday October 10, 2021.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m wrapping this up on Thursday evening, four pretty full days
later. Phoowee!)</p>
<h2 id="strange-days">Strange days</h2>
<p>In the previous edition of the WHV, <a href="/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">I mentioned that I had found a solution for
making my Org mode notes database accessible from my phone</a>.</p>
<p>Well, it&rsquo;s a rather unconventional trick involving CMake, pandoc and Microsoft
Word that you can read about in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">this probably nerdy vxlabs post</a>.</p>
<p>(Back in 2018, I <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">did something similar by exporting my Org mode database to
Apple Notes</a>, which worked well when most of my devices were of Apple
manufacture. Fortunately the Org mode part of the equation, the most important bit,
remains the same.)</p>
<p>Continuing on from the <a href="/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/#this-blog-hopefully-immortalised-on-github">blog mirroring work mentioned in WHV #232</a>, I configured
the necessary github workflows to auto-publish this site to a github.io site.</p>
<p>In other words, if I were to disappear for whatever reason, this blog should
remain available via <a href="https://cpbotha.github.io/">https://cpbotha.github.io/</a> for quite a while longer after
my hosting and domain registration eventually expire.</p>
<h2 id="spring-break">Spring break</h2>
<p>As part of the week-long Sprink break, we spent an absolutely fabulous long
weekend in Stilbaai, more specifically in the Bosbokduin private game reserve,
in a <a href="http://huisopdieduin.co.za/">house with the most amazing views over the ocean</a>.</p>
<p>Although we were there for only a few days, it feels like we were somehow able
to compress the experiences of a substantially longer period into the time at
our disposal.</p>
<p>I am grateful for all of the runs and walks on beautiful trails on various bits
of the coast, notably the trail passing right in front of the house connecting
Stilbaai and Jongensfontein, paddling on the river, lounging on the beach, and
just lots of family time in that beautiful house.</p>
<p>(When I look back at my notes from the return on Sunday, it&rsquo;s quite clear that
we were still on a sort of perfect vacation high.)</p>
<p>What was interesting to me this time, was that almost immediately after the
initial <a href="/tags/disconnecting/">disconnect</a> which thankfully happened quite soon, my brain started
producing strange (as in, far removed from work, and in some cases just plain
unconventional) but quite plausible new (engineering) ideas.</p>
<p>In other words, this is the nerd version of experiencing creativity.</p>
<p>This made me reconsider the effect of spending a fair bit of energy on work
every day.</p>
<p>Of course the picture is almost always complicated, but my work currently
requires a great deal of <em>focused</em> creativity, that is, thought and effort that
goes in one primary direction.</p>
<p>This is great in terms of getting those big things done, and also of
compounding (personal) improvement in that same direction, but the trade-off is
that the energy spent is now spent, and can&rsquo;t go into the exhilarating feeling
of ideas shooting off in different and often new directions.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #233: Atomic party sections</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</guid><description> Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.
Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.
(Don&amp;rsquo;t) Stress for success (aka 4000 weeks at 60%) It&amp;rsquo;s really quite busy at work, perhaps even verging on the slightly too busy territory.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering
the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="don-t--stress-for-success--aka-4000-weeks-at-60">(Don&rsquo;t) Stress for success (aka 4000 weeks at 60%)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s really quite busy at work, perhaps even verging on the slightly too busy
territory.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m consistently putting in stretches of focused, high intensity work to help
push us into calmer waters.</p>
<p>However, in spite of all of this, my stress levels seem to have have subsided
to quite an extent over the last few weeks.</p>
<p>This could be ascribed to me slowly moving out of <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">new challenge discomfort
territory</a>, because I&rsquo;m either getting better at what I&rsquo;m supposed to be doing,
or, if you want to be cynical, I just care a little less.</p>
<p>Maybe these two are the same.</p>
<p>I like to think that it could also be the growing effect of <em>Four Thousand
Weeks: Time and How to Use It</em>, <a href="/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/#how-i-m-putting-down-my-work">the book I mentioned in WHV-231</a> that so
eloquently and quite urgently makes the case that because life is so stupidly
short, and you&rsquo;re not even going to get close to Getting your Things Done, and
that working hard so that you can relax at some future point in time is a
terribly imprudent approach forced upon us by our instrumentalist society, you
should instead do your best extracting every bit of enjoyment from every moment
that you get, when you get it.</p>
<p>Every morning is an opportunity for a mini coffee and breakfast party, and
every evening is an opportunity for a mini dinner party, both of these with the
people, big and small, I hold the most dear.</p>
<p>Every day I do need to work, but there is ample opportunity for curiosity, for
learning, and for offering a helping hand.</p>
<p>There is generally also time to go out for a wide-open-perception run in the
sun.</p>
<p>All of this is available to you if you can just learn how to keep your own set
of instrumentalising demons safely locked up in their cages. (these are the
gremlins who keep on bugging you to try to finish one more thing.)</p>
<p>As Burkeman writes on page 144:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To the philosophers of the ancient world, leisure wasn&rsquo;t the means to some
other end; on the contrary, it was the end to which everything else worth doing
was a means.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Back in <a href="/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/#flip-it">WHV #222, I tried to say something similar, just far less eloquently</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve completed only a pinch over 60% of the book. I might have more to say when
it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">Dropbox Paper (aka mobile note-taking evolving)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s no secret around these parts that <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#mobile">the mobile aspects of my otherwise
pretty respectable note-taking game are weak</a>. (In short: Emacs Org mode is
amazing and can do <em>anything</em>, <strong>except</strong> when on my iPhone. Moar shorter: iPhone =
Org mode Kryptonite)</p>
<p>Somehow, in spite of being so deep in with Dropbox, and in spite of using
<a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper">Dropbox Paper</a> for other things, I overlooked it when evaluating solutions for
mobile note capture all the way back in 2019.</p>
<p>This weekend, because I had to scrounge around for an important bit of
information I <em>knew</em> I had stored somewhere (it turned out to be in my Apple
Notes doh), I spent some time trying to find a tool that would give me
mobile-editable notes that would turn up more readily in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that Dropbox Paper documents turn up in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Who would have guessed?!</p>
<p>In addition to that, Paper has:</p>
<ul>
<li>markdown support</li>
<li>syntax highlighting of triple-backtick source code blocks</li>
<li>LaTeX math!</li>
<li>embedding of arbitrary media which gets automatically uploaded to dropbox on
drag and drop</li>
<li>easy linking to other Paper docs</li>
<li>checklists</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Cue sound of another personal knowledge management puzzle piece snapping into place&hellip;</em></p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m not allowed to talk about it here, because the blog post in question
happened <em>after</em> this blog post&rsquo;s legally allowed observed timespan, but shortly
in the future, I will also solve the issue of being able to search through and
preview all of my Org mode notes on the iPhone.</p>
<p>Post is on vxlabs if you&rsquo;re from the (near) future.</p>
<h2 id="a-truly-spectacular-long-weekend-in-betty-s">A truly spectacular long weekend in Betty&rsquo;s</h2>
<p>The second week ended with a weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay that was so spectacular
that it deserves its own section in this blog post.</p>
<p>Well this is it. The section dedicated to the weekend. I hope you like it.</p>
<h2 id="the-section-at-the-end">The section at the end</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this.</p>
<p>I wish you continuous and consistent atomic party moments.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #232: Side-project Smorgasbord</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 21:38:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from a park not too far from my house.
Welcome back friends to WHV #232, looking back at the two weeks from Monday August 30 to Sunday September 13, both fortunately in the year 2021.
Give me some more of that mRNA I&amp;rsquo;m happy to report that I got my second Pfizer shot at the start of this month, at the Somerset West Town Hall.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="view_from_park.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a park not too far from my house."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a park not too far from my house.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome back friends to WHV #232, looking back at the two weeks from Monday
August 30 to Sunday September 13, both fortunately in the year 2021.</p>
<h2 id="give-me-some-more-of-that-mrna">Give me some more of that mRNA</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m happy to report that I got my second Pfizer shot at the start of this
month, at the Somerset West Town Hall.</p>
<p>The whole procedure took 30 minutes, from when I entered the front door, until
I exited after the 15 minute wait in the side-effect area with friend LM, at
which point I unfortunately jammed my shoulder on an inconveniently positioned
aloe branch, an event that under normal circumstances would not even have been
worth a mention, were it not for the fact that I was wearing my fortunately
entry-level puffer jacket, which now sports a gash with stuffing peeking out.</p>
<p>I believe that I digressed ever so slightly there.</p>
<p>Anyways&hellip;</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m super happy that all of the adults in my close family unit have now been
vaccinated, and grateful for the superbly efficient way in which this could
come to pass.</p>
<h2 id="this-blog-hopefully-immortalised-on-github">This blog hopefully immortalised on github</h2>
<p>(aka you can never escape)</p>
<p>At a recent meetup, I brought up the cheerful topic of what happens to one&rsquo;s
website(s) when one invariably gets to kick the proverbial bucket.</p>
<p>This is probably a pretty abstract concept to many folks, but as I&rsquo;m now
getting within spitting distance of my half century, it is something that I do
think about now and then.</p>
<p>The thing is, when my credit card finally decides to stop paying the monthly
Hetzner bill (at this moment, <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">these pages are served by a Hetzner VPS in
Nuremburg</a>), they will pull the plug.</p>
<p>Even if they don&rsquo;t do so immediately, cpbotha.net&rsquo;s domain registrar will for
related reasons unplug the domain as it were, rendering this site unreachable.</p>
<p>Now that I think about this some more, the shadowy company paying for all of
this has been setup in a pretty robust fashion. It&rsquo;s not quite <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accelerando">Accelerando</a>
levels of indirection, but it could remain standing and paying for hosting and
domains somewhat longer than expected.</p>
<p>In spite of that, for the one or two people who might want to read some of this
content after I&rsquo;m gone (close family members, I&rsquo;m looking right at you!), I
really wanted to have some sort of more long-term backup plan in place, in
addition to what <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/*/cpbotha.net">the wonderful Wayback Machine is already doing</a>.</p>
<p>The solution I decided upon was to spend a great many hours going through 20
years of cpbotha.net posts, mostly to fix all of the badly linked legacy
wordpress figure sections, so that the whole thing could be pushed
to&hellip; <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/cpbotha.github.io">github</a>!</p>
<p>Yep, you heard me right&hellip;</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve taken care of the bulk of rewriting, mostly through putting together <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/cpbotha.github.io/blob/main/mine/convert%5Fwp%5Ffigures.py">this
horrible script</a>, and manually reviewing the diffs, sometimes applying fixes, to
over 600 files.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/">Beautifulsoup 4</a> is amazing by the way. Wordpress on the other hand, or rather
wordpress plugins, just made so many random changes to figure markup over the
years that I&rsquo;m not really sure what to think anymore.</p>
<p>Anyways, most of the markdown content, which has been thankfully simplified, is
now on the github and should remain available for significantly longer in the
hopefully far future event of my demise.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to spend some more hours to get the whole thing also buildable on
github so that there&rsquo;s a browseable version in addition to just the markdown
sources. (Update on 2021-10-04: There is now a browseable version at
<a href="https://cpbotha.github.io/">https://cpbotha.github.io/</a>.)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I hope that I can keep this site alive, and maybe even
kicking, for at least twenty more years!</p>
<h2 id="on-always-maintaining-a-menu-of-tasty-side-projects">On always maintaining a menu of tasty side-projects</h2>
<p>Oh <a href="/tags/side-projects/">side-projects</a>&hellip;</p>
<p>As I&rsquo;ve mentioned before, we side-project for learning and for relaxation.</p>
<p>In addition to that, we also often lament the apparent cost of these
side-projects, with some of us even having whole side-project graveyards to
show for our sins.</p>
<p>On the basis of what I just said, one might think it prudent to try and avoid
these clearly nefarious side-projects, or maybe just to try and reduce their
impact as much as possible, but of course we&rsquo;ll do nothing of the sort.</p>
<p>Instead, we&rsquo;re going to double down.</p>
<p>You see, the other day I figured out that my problem with side-projects was
clearly that I didn&rsquo;t have enough of them.</p>
<p>Ideally, one has a whole menu of tasty side-projects lined up, each one a
different mix of activity types and learnings.</p>
<p>Whenever you have a bit of free time (<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2021/sep/09/study-links-too-much-free-time-to-lower-sense-of-wellbeing">not too much though!</a>), you can <em>quite</em>
simply select the most suitable side-project from your list and hammer away for
a bit.</p>
<p>Of course you will need a substantial amount of willpower, as well as the
presence of mind to actually initiate this selection action&hellip;</p>
<p>Somewhat more seriously though, always having a creative and fitting project
closely at hand that you can <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a> upon sounds like a solid strategy.</p>
<p>(err, a solid strategy for what exactly? well that&rsquo;s a topic for a future post&hellip;)</p>
<p>In the meantime:</p>
<p>LONG LIVE  YOUR GROWING MULTITUDE OF SIDE-PROJECTS!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #231: Two thousand four hundred fourty-four</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW
This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to Sunday August 29, 2021.
Orbital mechanics that are important to me Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.
That&amp;rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.
Let me try again:
Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="pano_from_watsonia.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &ldquo;run&rdquo; with bestie DW</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to
Sunday August 29, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="orbital-mechanics-that-are-important-to-me">Orbital mechanics that are important to me</h2>
<p>Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.</p>
<p>Let me try again:</p>
<p>Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for
another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</p>
<p>As is our custom here, I get to increase the mathematical encoding (this is a
fantastically consistent and useful approach to the structured modelling of
reality) of my time as an alive unit by one.</p>
<p>When I was younger, it was possible to use this number to impress one&rsquo;s
friends. Sometimes, the number of an older sibling or even a parent could also
be used to increase social standing, if one&rsquo;s own number was still quite small.</p>
<p>Ironically, as the number gets bigger, we prefer not to talk or even think
about it too much.</p>
<p>Thanks to math, the number could in theory be transformed into &ldquo;number of
revolutions remaining&rdquo;, but fortunately our complex physiologies and
environments greatly complicate the estimation of the required term for that
transformation, in this case greatly comforting us with uncertainty.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS&hellip;</p>
<p>I had an amazing birthday.</p>
<p>From morning video chats with homies, to working lunches that turned into
superbly relaxed lunches with old friends, surprise visits by far-off friends
the day before, birthday mountain runs with a bestie, and so many (voice)
messages on various platforms from friends everywhere, my birthday was a
friendship-and-life-affirming business.</p>
<p>Friends, thank you for working together like that. You are all breath-taking!</p>
<p>P.S. Experiencing this acted as a beautiful reminder to send that message,
write that email or make that call whenever you can find an excuse!</p>
<h2 id="how-i-m-putting-down-my-work"><em>How</em> I&rsquo;m putting down my work</h2>
<p>In the previous edition of the WHV, I talked about <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">the important skill of being
able to put down one&rsquo;s work</a>.</p>
<p>Here I would just like to mention how I&rsquo;ve been trying to practise this in my
life, especially because it really seems to have helped me since we last spoke.</p>
<p>Ok, get ready!</p>
<p>You Won&rsquo;t Believe This One Trick&hellip;</p>
<p>At 17:00, 17:30 at the latest, I explicitly switch off any tools that I use for
work, and disconnect from all dayjob-related systems.</p>
<p>Work email closed, development enviroments exited, docker containers all stopped.</p>
<p>For good measure, I roll a tumbleweed or two across my office floor, blowing
air out through my pursed lips.</p>
<p>The thing is, my brain has the tendency to continue cogitating on the last
thing I kept it busy with.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I used to have the tendency to still try and solve that problem
before bed, only resulting in me later lying in said bed, unable to get my
brain to stop cogitating, leading to bad sleep, contributing to subpar
performance the next day.</p>
<p>I have to qualify here that putting down work tools does not exclude me from
picking up hobby programming projects later in the evening, after &ldquo;The Making
of The Dinner, With Wine&rdquo; and &ldquo;The Chilling With The Family&rdquo; stages.</p>
<p>Although programming plays a substantial part of dayjob, I have never stopped
enjoying and being relaxed by this activity in the recreational setting.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, making a point of putting down work on time, starting
the gradual wind-down, has drastically reduced the number and severity of
<em>Trying Unsuccessfully to Solve All Work Problems In The Dark, From One&rsquo;s Bed</em> for
me.</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/">Oliver Burkeman</a>, author of <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">the putting-down-your-work post</a>, also wrote a
book titled <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2021/aug/16/four-thousand-weeks-time-and-how-to-use-it-by-oliver-burkeman-review">Four Thousand Weeks: Time and How to Use It</a>, which my mom got me
for my birthday (THANKS MOM!).</p>
<p>As soon as I&rsquo;m done with <a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">Seligman&rsquo;s book flourish</a>, I&rsquo;ll start with this book,
which will hopefully filter through to this blog.</p>
<p>In the meantime, here&rsquo;s the blurb which is already food  for thought:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The average human lifespan is absurdly, insultingly brief.</p>
<p>If you live to be 80, you’ll have had about 4,000 weeks. But that’s no reason for despair.</p>
<p>Confronting our radical finitude  and how little control we really have  is the key to a fulfilling and meaningfully productive life.</p>
</blockquote>








<figure><a href="helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&amp;rsquo;ve been treated with."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&rsquo;ve been treated with.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #230: Follow your blisters</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="van_breda_cottage_angles.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&amp;rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &amp;ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&amp;rdquo; (I didn&amp;rsquo;t and I don&amp;rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV covers the three weeks from Monday July 26 to Sunday August 15.</p>
<h2 id="why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">Why I don&rsquo;t like dark mode anymore</h2>
<p>As you might know, I spent most of my working (and sometimes hobby, we&rsquo;ll get
back to that further down) hours in front of this screen or some other screen.</p>
<p>Up to now, I was really convinced that I preferred dark mode everywhere, until
recently two events transpired:</p>
<p>I started noticing more eye-strain than usual, even on my 27&quot; screen, something
which had a perceptible effect on my productivity. This I resignedly ascribed
to my advancing age, although I did find the suddenness quite surprising,
especially since I recently had my glasses updated.</p>
<p>Then, after years with only the admittedly brilliant <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">zenburn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/fniessen/emacs-leuven-theme">Leuven (dark)</a>
Emacs themes checking all of the boxes for me, I finally ran into a really
interesting and usable theme called <a href="https://github.com/kunalb/poet">Poet</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s interesting, because it uses variable pitched fonts for everything but
code, tables and elements of the fixed width domain, where most Emacs fonts
stick to the traditional all-fixed-width approach.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="20210822-poet-theme-screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can probably understand that for someone who uses Emacs almost primarily
for technical notes and other writing, this book-like appearance could work
really well.</p>
<p>The theme was even more interesting for me personally, as it suddenly became
clear as day that I experienced almost no eye-strain when using Emacs with this
lighter theme than when I used any of my other usually dark-themed tools!</p>
<p>It became obvious that poet-theme&rsquo;s lighter background was much easier on my
eyes than dark mode in vscode. (No, this specific advantage can&rsquo;t be ascribed
to Emacs itself I&rsquo;m afraid.)</p>
<p>Reading pages such as <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/digital-eye-strain/is-dark-mode-better-for-eyes/">this</a> explains that dark mode leads to pupils having to
dilate more to let in more light, which there is less of with dark themes.</p>
<p>This leads to, just like with cameras and any other optics with lenses and
apertures, a shortened depth of field, and hence more difficulty focusing on
the screen!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/dark-mode/">This article by the well-known Nielsen Norman Group</a> nicely summarises research
on this topic. In short:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In people with normal vision (or corrected-to-normal vision), visual
performance tends to be better with light mode, whereas some people with
cataract and related disorders may perform better with dark mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Up until recently, I did not experience a qualitative difference in vision
between dark and light, but I sit here relieved that my eye-strain issue has
been resolved by an Emacs theme!</p>
<h2 id="know-how-to-put-down-your-work">Know how to put down your work</h2>
<p>The following take from <a href="https://twitter.com/brandsrock/status/1426163442256330753">a recent tweet by mike joubert</a> struck me
(tweet-take-strike! words are funny&hellip;):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly valuable skill isn&rsquo;t the capacity to push yourself harder, but to
stop and recuperate despite the discomfort of knowing that work remains
unfinished, emails unanswered, other people&rsquo;s demands unfulfilled.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">article, titled <em>The three-or-four-hours rule for getting creative work
done</em></a>, is itself a good read about the observation that creative types (amongst
which I count engineers) have at their best three to four hours of focus time
per day &mdash; so it is crucially important that their days are structured such
that there is an <strong>uninterrupted</strong> block of three to four hours inside of which
that lovely focus has the possibility of appearing.</p>
<p>The tweet-extract focuses on the similarly important but more subtle art of
being able to put one&rsquo;s work down, completely, when that block of time is over,
even when it feels like the work is far from complete.</p>
<p>I especially like that it also explicitly mentions the illusions created by
one&rsquo;s perception of &ldquo;other people&rsquo;s demands&rdquo;, something that ironically becomes
even harder to walk away from when one is more tired at the end of the work
day.</p>
<p>For me, becoming better at putting work down has pleasant echoes of running
slower to run faster, of emptiness in art and more broadly, <a href="https://zenhabits.net/work-less/">choosing fewer f*cks
to give</a>.</p>
<h2 id="follow-your-blisters">Follow your blisters</h2>
<p>On the topic of choosing your ducks&hellip;</p>
<p>I initially did not like <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/what-you-should-follow-instead-of-your-passion">this HBR</a> post when it first crossed my stream, because
it smacks a bit too much of the current social media style of &ldquo;wisdom&rdquo;, namely
&ldquo;everything you need to know in 280 characters&rdquo;, or &ldquo;this 1 minute tiktok video
will change your life&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the title is pretty clickbaity: <em>What You Should
Follow Instead of Your Passion</em>.</p>
<p>However, the core message of the post, which I could not help reading, did
stick with me, and after a few days I realised that I would have to go find the
article again in order to talk about it here.</p>
<p>The core message is to replace <em>find your passion</em> with <strong><em>Find your blisters.</em></strong></p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s point is that folks often get the wrong idea with <em>passion</em> as
something that is simply always delightful, whilst the thing you should
actually be looking for, is that activity that you simply are unable to stop
doing, even when you try, and especially even when you don&rsquo;t directly derive
pleasure from it, for example because you feel that you&rsquo;re not that good at it.</p>
<p>They give the personal example of writing.</p>
<p>Although they&rsquo;ve been at it for years, it&rsquo;s still a difficult and laborious
process, and they are often not happy with the results.</p>
<p>However, they have been unable to stop from returning to writing projects again
and again over the years.</p>
<p>Ironically, even although they find that they are still bad at it, they have in
fact become really good, simply because they have been pushing through and
practising more than almost anyone else over the years.</p>
<p>I really like this down-to-earth view.</p>
<p>One can indeed source almost unlimited amounts of energy from one&rsquo;s &ldquo;blisters&rdquo;,
but true benefits will for a large part be brought about by a <a href="/tags/practice/">lifetime of often
challenging practice</a>.</p>








<figure><a href="flowers_everywhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &amp;ldquo;blommetjieskyk&amp;rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #229: Staycation PERMA-Station</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 21:26:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/</guid><description> Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&amp;rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)
This edition of the WHV looks back at the week from Monday July 19 to Sunday July 25, 2021, a week of untold wonders and intense enjoyment, a week deserving of the hallowed title of&amp;hellip; STAYCATION!
Jokes aside, it was a perfectly enjoyable week of time off, most of it spent at home or close to it.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="bettys_jocks.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_huc11c02a8d554d1e07ce947f124c93b71_2055523_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_huc11c02a8d554d1e07ce947f124c93b71_2055523_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_huc11c02a8d554d1e07ce947f124c93b71_2055523_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_huc11c02a8d554d1e07ce947f124c93b71_2055523_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_huc11c02a8d554d1e07ce947f124c93b71_2055523_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&amp;rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the week from Monday July 19 to Sunday
July 25, 2021, a week of untold wonders and intense enjoyment, a week deserving
of the hallowed title of&hellip; <em>STAYCATION!</em></p>
<p>Jokes aside, it was a perfectly enjoyable week of time off, most of it spent at
home or close to it.</p>
<p>We spent time together, took care of hobby- and side-projects, and even had
time to daydream and come up with some wacky ideas which should probably never
see the light of day, but which one day just might.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-1-dot-3-released">Lazar Focus 1.3 released</h2>
<p>On the evening of Tuesday, July 20, after a flurry of programming and testing,
<a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2021/07/21/lazar-focus-1.3.0-released-real-time-focus-feedback/">Lazar Focus 1.3 was released</a>.</p>
<p>Noteworthy is its new ability to measure and give real-time feedback on your
current focus, as an easy to interpret percentage.</p>
<p>The more you resist distractions, the higher the focus percentage.</p>
<p>When developing this feature, I ended up selecting a 5 minute rolling window,
after I was initially planning a pomodoro length. Five minutes seem to be a
sort of sweet spot in terms of seeing one&rsquo;s distractions affect one&rsquo;s score,
but not having it immediately distroyed, so that there&rsquo;s still time to recover.</p>
<p>I wanted to mention here the interesting disconnect between the programming I
do for this completely disconnected hobby project in a language (Pascal-ish)
that I don&rsquo;t particularly prefer but don&rsquo;t mind on the one hand, and my day
job, for which I sometimes still get to program, on the other.</p>
<h2 id="perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA: The five building blocks of well-being</h2>
<p>So yeah, there&rsquo;s a pretty interesting disconnect&hellip;</p>
<p>Writing code for LF, in this case perhaps perhaps noteworthy the real-time
focus tracking data-structure, namely a run-length encoded series of (no)focus
time durations that automatically get truncated, lengthened and pruned as time
progresses, was 100% fun and relaxation.</p>
<p>This is not the most tricky thing to implement, but the process of first
cooking it up in my brain, and then later sitting down to implement it, and
seeing it work, was just challenging enough to result in several periods of
complete immersion in, or engagement with, the task.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Flourish-Visionary-Understanding-Happiness-Well-being/dp/1439190763/ref=sr%5F1%5F6?dchild=1&amp;qid=1627409990&amp;refinements=p%5F27%3AMartin+Seligman&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-6">Martin Seligman&rsquo;s book titled <em>Flourish</em></a>, which I&rsquo;m slowly working through
at the moment (he is a great and impactful psychologist, but perhaps not the
world&rsquo;s greatest story teller, sorry Prof Seligman), he explains that human
<a href="https://ppc.sas.upenn.edu/learn-more/perma-theory-well-being-and-perma-workshops">well-being, or flourishing, consists of five building blocks, namely</a>:</p>
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion: gratitude, savouring the present, hope and optimism,</li>
<li>Engagement: Lose oneself in a challenging (err) task,</li>
<li>Relationships: Love and be loved by friends and family,</li>
<li>Meaning: belonging to and serving some cause greater than oneself and</li>
<li>Accomplishment: Pursuing achievement and mastery for its own sake.</li>
</ol>
<p>My little LF programming exercise was <em>exactly</em> right for triggering a bit of
item number 2, namely engagement.</p>
<p>I am happy that I could slip a little PERMA in here on the back of Lazar Focus,
a little tool that is also proving useful in ways that I did not expect. ;)
Although the book is not the easiest going, it makes some valuable points if
you too are a fan of well-being.</p>
<h2 id="pfizer-jab-1-in-da-pocket">Pfizer jab #1 IN DA POCKET</h2>
<p>I really loves me some cutting edge science.</p>
<p>I know that the mRNA vaccines have been in development for decades now, but
they still represent such an amazing technological flex.</p>
<p>How fantastic is it that some of our cleverest humans have designed and tested
<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/different-vaccines/mrna.html">this vaccine that consists of usually unstable mRNA</a>, to be injected into human
cells where our the cellular machinery in our bodies will dutifully follow the
mRNA instructions to frikking synthesise and display a piece of spike protein
that looks enough like the COVID-19 spike protein so that our immune system
will notice and immediately start creating antibodies, all without us actually
getting infected.</p>
<p>As if that&rsquo;s not enough, the introduced mRNA is broken down ASAP after
synthesis.</p>
<p>HOT DAMN we live in the future and it&rsquo;s pretty awesome up here!</p>
<p>I AM EXCITE</p>
<p>I am also really happy with the super efficient walk-in vaccination procedure at the Town Hall here in Somerset West.</p>
<p>I would have been in and out in 30 minutes with Pfizer jab #1 had I not run
into and started chatting with friends in the side-effect waiting area.</p>
<p>Kudos to the Western Cape for running this like the Star Trek medical bay.</p>
<p>Still friends, how strange are the days that we find ourselves in?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #228: Komkommertijd</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 22:21:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/</guid><description> Figure 1: On the side opposite to Map of Africa, on the grass that shall not be entered if one is not a club member.
This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number two tenny eight, covers the period of time from Monday June 28 to Sunday July 18 of the year 2021.
Bad glitch in the South African matrix Although I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say here (hence the title), the country has been all over the news for less than great reasons.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="map_of_africa_other_side.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: On the side opposite to Map of Africa, on the grass that shall not be entered if one is not a club member."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: On the side opposite to Map of Africa, on the grass that shall not be entered if one is not a club member.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number two tenny eight, covers the
period of time from Monday June 28 to Sunday July 18 of the year 2021.</p>
<h2 id="bad-glitch-in-the-south-african-matrix">Bad glitch in the South African matrix</h2>
<p>Although I don&rsquo;t have much to say here (hence <a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komkommertijd">the title</a>), the country has been
all over the news for less than great reasons.</p>
<p>Shortly after former president Zuma finally finally handed himself over to the
police on Sunday July 4 to serve his 15 month jail sentence for contempt of the
Constitutional court (there are more cases to come), looting, arson and
violence broke out primarily in Kwazulu-Natal, but also in Gauteng.</p>
<p>Various shopes and malls have been stripped bare and/or destroyed.</p>
<p>This looked like a perfect storm, initiated by Zuma&rsquo;s incarceration (he has a
great deal of support in Kwazulu-Natal), partially fanned on by his children
and allies on social media, and intensified by systemic poverty.</p>
<p>There were many videos on social media of folks with luxury items, some trying
to stuff flat-screen TVs into their cars, or crossing the street with a basket
full of goods to dump in their luxury Mercedes, but there were also many more
who are only trying to survive under the poverty line and can&rsquo;t be blamed for
any of this.</p>
<p>As far as I can see, our current president Ramaphosa has for years now been
doing his best to unravel the nest of corruption and dishonesty that his party
the ANC has unfortunately become.</p>
<p>This is tricky work, as he needs to circumnavigate and/or defuse the same
internal forces that managed to oust president Thabo Mbeki and usher in the
terrible era of Zuma.</p>
<p>The poor man has had to endure even more flak in these days, both from his
political enemies and from other commentators.</p>
<p>Until convincingly shown otherwise, my opinion is that president Ramaphosa is
the best shot we currently have at a better future.</p>
<p>You can read <a href="https://www.gov.za/speeches/president-cyril-ramaphosa-update-security-situation-country-16-jul-2021-0000">his July 16 speech about the unrest here</a>.</p>
<p>A slight silver edge is that these events have put more pressure on the
<a href="https://businesstech.co.za/news/finance/506914/government-considers-basic-income-grant-after-riots-and-looting-in-south-africa/">discussions around the possible implementation of a basic income grant</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. It seems that the looting was not disruptive enough for some folks, and so
now we are dealing with <a href="https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/article/2021-07-20-why-the-western-cape-is-being-rocked-by-taxi-violence/">taxi-company-related violence in the Western Cape</a>.</p>
<p>P.P.S. let me just hide this here: far more locally, we are dealing with some
pandemic-related stressors.</p>
<h2 id="reserve-bench-holidays">Reserve bench holidays</h2>
<p>As <a href="/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/#groundhog-lockdown">I supected in the previous WHV</a> (three weeks ago, ahem&hellip;), our country&rsquo;s
struggles with the pandemic did in fact manage to get our Kruger National Park
visit cancelled.</p>
<p>To be clear, I have no illusions about the relative importance of our holiday
under these circumstances and in this context (close to utterly unimportant, in
other words), but we humans are gonna human and I&rsquo;m not gonna lie, we were
really looking forward to that week of sun in Mpumalanga.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve often said that the winter down here is more bearable than one would
expect, due to it being quite often punctuated by brilliant and sunny days
outside, but this year I&rsquo;ve come to realise that I might have underestimated
the positive effects of <a href="/tags/knp/">spending the darkest week under the sun of the North</a>.</p>
<p>Anyways, we were super fortunate to be able to arrange for a long weekend in
another one of our favourite places, namely Wilderness, where we were treated
with absolutely balmy days, some of them on the Touw river (inflatable SUPs
FTW!), some of them on the most beautiful beaches, and some of them hiking and
running on various trails.</p>








<figure><a href="wilderness_running_rondevlei.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Scene from one of my favourite running routes, this time with GOU #1!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Scene from one of my favourite running routes, this time with GOU #1!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>If it sounds to you like we had to go outside every day to warm up in the
winter sun, I can hereby confirm your astute observation.</p>
<p>To be fair, this was literally in the deepest part of winter, from which there
is no true escape if one remains within the Western Cape.</p>
<p>In spite of that, or perhaps because of it, we enjoyed the wonderful days to
bits.</p>








<figure><a href="kaaimans_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: The rail bridge over Kaaimansrivier. We have this on the todo list for next time."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 3: The rail bridge over <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaaimans%5FRiver">Kaaimansrivier</a>. We have this on the todo list for next time.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #227: Reality bending security blanket</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 22:15:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.
This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.
Groundhog Lockdown On the above-mentioned Sunday, president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4, one level more serious from where we were.
For us this means that schools are closing a week earlier for the July vacation, and hence will have to open a week earlier, and hence will have a severe effect on the breakaway we had planned, an effect of the cancellation variety.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="backyard_walk_s_and_i.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from
Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.</p>
<h2 id="groundhog-lockdown">Groundhog Lockdown</h2>
<p>On the above-mentioned Sunday, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/level-4-lockdown-for-south-africa-for-14-days-2021-6">president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4</a>,
one level more serious from where we were.</p>
<p>For us this means that schools are closing a week earlier for the July
vacation, and hence will have to open a week earlier, and hence will have a
severe effect on the breakaway we had planned, an effect of the
<em>cancellation</em> variety.</p>
<p>Although frustrating (some of us really need that precious time away to keep
calm and carry on afterwards), we don&rsquo;t really have anything to complain about
if that is our biggest problem.</p>
<p>Gauteng province has been hit really hard by the third wave of COVID, and
specifically this new Delta variant.</p>
<p>This modified lockdown level 4 explicitly prohibits travel into and out of the
province in order to help stem the disease&rsquo;s spread.</p>
<p>In other news, our vaccination is making progress, albeit at a slower pace than
most people had hoped.</p>
<p>In a few days they are going to start with the over 50s. No, this does not
include me yet, although I am close.</p>
<h2 id="amazon-document-culture">Amazon document culture</h2>
<p>Last week, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=27545331">Hacker News discussed</a> a really interesting <a href="https://www.justingarrison.com/blog/2021-03-15-the-document-culture-of-amazon/">blog post by an Amazon
employee about Amazon&rsquo;s document culture</a>.</p>
<p>In short, at Amazon, a meeting can only happen if a document has been written
detailing what is to be discussed during the meeting.</p>
<p>At the start of the meeting, everyone gets from 10 minutes to half an hour,
depending on what makes sense for the document under discussion, to read the
document, and only then the meeting starts.</p>
<p>This approach has many advantages, discussed in the blog post.</p>
<p>What I personally like about doing it this way, is that the convenor of the
meeting has to pay a price for that meeting, namely sitting down and spending
time to structure their thoughts on paper well enough so it will satisfy the
expectations of the participants.</p>
<p>Furthermore, by dedicating quiet time to reading the document, one has a
slightly better guarantee that everyone is up to date with the background, and,
more interesting to me, is that it sets a more deliberate and thoughtful mood
for the whole meeting.</p>
<p>Of course I tried this out at the first high-level meeting that I could, where
I had to present a plan to the participants.</p>
<p>It felt a bit strange initiating this silent reading at the start, but my
perception is that it contributed to a higher quality discussion afterwards.</p>
<p>In this case it was easy, because the goal of the meeting was to present a plan
that was already a document. However, this is something I will definitely want
to repeat.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, the document will be all that is required.</p>
<h2 id="your-choice">Your choice</h2>
<p>In <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">WHV #226</a> I wrote that I had chosen to be in the situation that was causing
stress due to its new challenges.</p>
<p>Friend SvdW (jokingly? chidingly?) commented via private communications
channels that that &ldquo;choice&rdquo; had surprised him, seeing that <a href="https://philosophybreak.com/articles/free-will-illusion-sam-harris/">we have no free
will</a>.</p>
<p>He is right of course, but in this case it <em>is</em> in fact all about the illusion,
about being subjectively convinced that one is the agent and the author of
one&rsquo;s current situation.</p>
<p>This did remind me something I wrote in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#productivity-system-tuneup">WHV #185</a> about how this same framing
can be effective against procrastination:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have chosen to
take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having decided
to commit, i.e. active.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the cases where you believe that you <em>are</em> probably the agent of your
situation, it can really help to verbalise that to yourself in the way
described above.</p>
<p>This can sometimes be tricky, because so much of it has to do with potentially
subjective-reality-bending framing, which could get in the way of addressing
problems external to oneself.</p>
<p>If you apply This One Trick, and you do a great job, how real were those
external problems in the first place?</p>
<p>On days like these, I get a feeling, albeit an extremely faint one, for why
Descartes constructed the mental security blanket of <em>cogito ergo sum</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #226: Stress practice</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 16:07:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</guid><description> Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.
Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.
As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&amp;rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (Youth Day), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth Emacs Org-mode / ox-hugo blogging machine (read this github issue for more details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this combination has saved me in the past.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the
week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys_run_pano_20210612.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (<a href="https://www.gov.za/youth-day">Youth
Day</a>), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth
Emacs Org-mode / <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo">ox-hugo</a> blogging machine (read <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo/issues/447">this github issue</a> for more
details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this
combination has saved me in the past.</p>
<h2 id="solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">Solstice tipping point is coming!</h2>
<p>The last thing we&rsquo;re supposed to do is to wish even just a little bit for time
to pass more quickly, for fairly obvious reasons.</p>
<p>However, when you&rsquo;re a few days from the darkest point in the year, it&rsquo;s hard
not to.</p>
<p>We currently have 9 hours and 56 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s just two minutes, and a few days, from the winter solstice on June 21,
when we&rsquo;ll have to make do with 9 hours and 54 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>I mention this here, because those 6 AM wake-ups feel more and more like the
middle of the night.</p>
<p>After the solstice, I&rsquo;ll start imagining the sun coming up a few moments
earlier every morning, and it will.</p>
<p>(Well, it will, eventually. Reader WIMM just pointed out via email that
although the days start getting longer, the sunrise will initially become even
a minute later, before finally becoming earlier starting from July 11. Read
more <a href="https://theconversation.com/why-the-sunrise-is-still-later-after-the-winter-solstice-shortest-day-77628">here</a> (thanks WIMM) or check the tables <a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-africa/stellenbosch?month=6&amp;year=2021">here</a>.)</p>
<p>It has been &hellip; <code>1 year and 11 months</code> &hellip; since <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/">the previous mention of winter
solstice on this blog</a>.</p>
<h2 id="avoid-the-jbl-endurance-run-bt-earphones-at-all-costs">Avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones at all costs</h2>
<p>A month ago <a href="/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/#world-in-my-eyes">I wrote about the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a> that I was
initially so happy with, which then spontaneously broke after a few hours of
running, and which I then returned for a replacement.</p>
<p>Well, the replacement set of <a href="https://eu.jbl.com/JBL+ENDURANCE+RUNBT.html?dwvar%5FJBL%20ENDURANCE%20RUNBT%5Fcolor=Black-GLOBAL-Current">proudly sweat-proof JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a>
lasted for about 9 hours of running, at which point they spontaneously broke in
exactly the same way.</p>
<p>Out of nowhere, the loud crackling sound started in the earpiece opposite to
the site with the control unit.</p>
<p>This crackling sound (similar to the disturbance you hear when speaker wires
have a connection issue) did not stop, even after un-pairing and even after
switching off the unit.</p>
<p>Connecting the charger after this would result in the charge light flickering
and fading in-and-out in a decidedly analogue fashion.</p>
<p>After experiencing the exact same problem with two different units, I am wary
wasting more time on a third set.</p>
<p>This was quite a disappointment, because mechanically this design was perfect
for me.</p>
<p>I will continue on my search for the perfect (1. secure in my large and
sometimes perspiring ears, so needs something in addition to just ear canal fit
and 2. durable, i.e. continues working <em>long</em> after the first 9 hours of
running) set of running earphones, and I&rsquo;ll keep you up to date on my findings.</p>
<p>In the meantime, please avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones.</p>
<h2 id="remote-work-culture-is-hard-work">Remote work culture is hard work</h2>
<p>During our Tuesday evening meetup, Theunis de Klerk of <a href="https://www.noldor.co.za/">Noldor</a> (the now fully
remote tech company, not <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noldor">the race of elves from Middle Earth</a>, although there is
a link here) gave an interesting and inspiring talk on how they have built and
cultivate great remote work culture.</p>
<p>This was an insightful look into an organization where the top leadership
continuously pours a great deal of thought and energy into maintaining healthy
culture, even in a fully remote environment with parts in different timezones.</p>
<p>On the one hand, it&rsquo;s great seeing working examples like this, on the other, it
can be quite a daunting prospect when you start thinking about how to apply
this in your own environment.</p>
<p>I believe that the future of knowledge work will <em>not</em> involve highly qualified
folks having to spend 8 hours per day at their desk because we still have not
learned that work is all about contributing value, and not about the number of
hours spent in captivity at one&rsquo;s desk.</p>
<p>That being said, during the current global remote working experiment, although
we are learning how to roll with value-generation, I do miss some of the almost
effortlessly and socially generated collaboration glue that at its best gets
folks almost instinctively chasing the same worthy goals.</p>
<p>(On the other hand, at its worst, it causes conflicts, grudges and ulcers, so
there&rsquo;s that&hellip;)</p>
<p>I would like to wrap this ramble up with one conclusion, and one interesting
tweet storm by Steven Sinofsky of Andreesen Horowitz:</p>
<ul>
<li>Conclusion: 1. Am I overestimating how &ldquo;easy&rdquo; social cohesion was when we
were in the office? 2. How do we go about getting back that real or imagined
social cohesion in this fully remote setting?</li>
<li><a href="https://a16z.com/2021/06/12/disruption-at-work-its-more-than-just-wfh/">Highly interesting tweet storm about the issue being larger and more
intricate than just WFH vs hybrid vs HQ</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="eternal-practice-vs-stress">Eternal practice vs stress</h2>
<p>I do need to note here (for future me) that I was consistently far grumpier
than usual for the last few days of the week under examination here.</p>
<p>When I say grumpy, I do mean quite detectably so.</p>
<p>This is definitely not my preferred state, so I&rsquo;m even meta-grumpy about that.</p>
<p>My retro- and introspection during the weekend came up with &ldquo;more stress than
usual&rdquo;, which is indeed probably a main contributor (wow, thanks work).</p>
<p>However, being grumpy or not is still fully my responsibility.</p>
<p>Increased stress at work is currently primarily due to new responsibilities and
the (often amplified by one&rsquo;s own imagination) expectations of colleagues, and
the unsurprising feeling of discomfort that is associated with finding oneself
faced with new kinds of challenges that you are not accustomed to (<em>cf.</em>
&ldquo;comfort zone&rdquo; and <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">stages 2 to 4 of the creative process</a>).</p>
<p>During the weekend I first resolved simply to be less grumpy (yes, you can do
that).</p>
<p>Fortunately, I also had a spot of insight as to how the root cause, i.e. the
work-related stress, could be better addressed in my specific case.</p>
<p>You see, I have chosen to be in this situation. I would have preferred the new
challenges without the concomitant stress, but that&rsquo;s unfortunately not how
<em>this</em> human normally works.</p>
<p>The realisation that I had was that this too is simply part of my lifelong
practice session.</p>
<p>I first talked about the idea of life being continuous pracrtice back in <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">WHV
#133</a>, and again later in <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">WHV #144</a> when I got around to reading a
reader-recommended book on the topic, titled &ldquo;Mastery&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Something I did not mention back then, probably because I only experience the
stress aspect as acutely at this moment, is that this particular framing helps
me to approach my current problems with curiosity, with an appetite for
learning and experimentation, and with the acceptance that my performance could
be far from perfect, perhaps even to the point of failure.</p>
<p>Some days will be good and some days will be bad.</p>
<p>(Even outside of the practice framing, one just has to accept that <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"><em>some days
gonna be crap</em></a>.)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, every day is a brand new opportunity to practice the
difficult new stuff, and to become gradually better at it, until one day, just
maybe, comfort slowly starts overtaking discomfort.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #225: Just a perfect weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</guid><description> Dear reader,
Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.
Keyboard update: K1 You&amp;rsquo;ll remember from WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the Womier K87 with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown switches.
That keyboard is so much fun to type on.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear reader,</p>
<p>Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th
installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="la_autumn_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="keyboard-update-k1">Keyboard update: K1</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll remember from <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the
Womier K87</a> with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown
switches.</p>
<p>That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt
Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the case that fingers also like the exercise, just like their
human owners.</p>
<p>I was not planning to buy any keyboards again soon, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was quite curious whether low profile key switches (that is, slightly less
finger travel) would be a good compromise between the fun of the Womier and the
efficiency of the Sculpt.</li>
<li>The K1 was on my list of candidates of keyboards with low-profile mechanical
switches.</li>
<li>I find it difficult to resist a good deal.</li>
</ul>
<p>You see, a friendly little bird (who also hangs out on the keyboards channel of
the zatech slack) told me about the extra-special Takealot birthday special
discount on <a href="https://www.imore.com/keychron-k1-v4-review">the Keychron K1 V4 87-key keyboard</a>.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a credit card transaction, a week of waiting for delivery and
another week of getting accustomed to the new board, and here we are, with at
least me typing these words on the new K1.</p>
<p>It took a while to get used to the keycaps, which can be a slippery sometimes
(or rather, my finger tip traction is variable), but my typing speed and
accuracy on this thing are in the neighbourhood of where they should be.</p>
<p>The thing is a great deal more <em>stylish</em> than my Womier; the Womier is that
guilty pleasure 80s disco that you really love, the K1 could work in a serious
coffee shop.</p>
<p>Also, having a keyboard which can switch this easily between wired operation
(the default for my desktop) and three different bluetooth connections is
pretty convenient. On trips where I usually only take the MacBook, I could
consider taking the K1 along when I have to do A Great Deal of Serious Typing.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I can&rsquo;t yet say if the low profile switches are indeed
the compromise that I wondered about. My subjective impression now is indeed
that my fingers don&rsquo;t get so physically tired as sometimes happens with the
Womier, but I&rsquo;ll have to switch between them a few times to get a better idea.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am certainly enjoying the experience of typing on
this thing, and I am certainly wondering about the interesting role that
different types of mechanical keyboards have begun to play in my computing
life.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-about-a-new-book-notes-post-about-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Lessons about a new book notes post about Seven and a Half Lessons about the Brain</h2>
<p>After two months of early(ish) morning typing on various keyboards, I finally
managed to wrap up <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">my book notes about Seven and a Half Lessons about the
Brain</a>, a fantastic book by neuro-scientist and psychologist Lisa Feldman
Barrett.</p>
<p>I had plans, in retrospect clearly too ambitious, to have at least two (2) book
notes posts out in Q1 of this year (after it took me months to complete <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my book
notes on Creativity, Inc.</a> by the end of last year).</p>
<p>That goal was necessarily postponed to Q2, and as we can all see now, there is
not enough time for a second post like this.</p>
<p>Either I have to change the format of the book notes to something more compact,
like a bunch of bullet lists, or I should make peace with the fact that I write
these like I write them, a little prose with quotes interspersed that can
generally be read like a mini story itself, and with the fact that they&rsquo;re
going to take as much time as they do.</p>
<p>Sometimes I have mixed feelings about the practice itself.</p>
<p>It takes fragments of hobby time spread out over weeks, fragments of time that
I could probably use for more reading, other interesting tidbits and, uhm,
extra work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it feels like a sort of a mini-rebellion doing exactly this,
assembling so many little pieces into something slightly more coherent and
significant, something that stands apart from work.</p>
<p>It seems I do know what to do.</p>
<p>Thanks for the chat!</p>
<h2 id="perfect-weekends-and-the-necessary-reminders-that-precede-them">Perfect weekends and the necessary reminders that precede them</h2>
<p>The weekend of June 4, 2021, was unexpectedly perfect, and I would like to make
note of that here for future me.</p>
<p>This is the recipe that we followed, utterly by happy accident:</p>
<ul>
<li>1x reminder during the week to really focus on the now.</li>
<li>1x absolutely perfect autumn weather package: balmy 20ish degrees Celsius,
lots of sun, very little wind.</li>
<li>3x braais, one per day, with various subsets of family.</li>
<li>2x runs: one a long weekend morning run, and the other an unplanned one
with GOU#1.</li>
<li>1x polishing and publishing of the blog post mentioned above.</li>
<li>1x unexpected Sunday evening star watching with GOU#2.</li>
</ul>
<p>One would think that daily practice would help, but it turns out that sometimes
a serendipitous reminder by a friend can help to switch one&rsquo;s brain into
exactly the right gear, right before the weekend.</p>
<p>During our Friday evening start-the-weekend ritual (it&rsquo;s a braai. surprise!), I
had my first quite visceral &ldquo;THIS, this is it, this is everything&rdquo;
experience. (so lovely)</p>
<p>From then on, brain remained in the right mode right through most of the
weekend.</p>
<p>If you ever run into me before the weekend (it&rsquo;s always before the weekend!), I
would be grateful if you could remind me that it is in fact now.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you much nowness.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>