<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/</link><description>Recent content on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 17:18:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #244: Biyamiti Bat-Fan</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 17:18:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/</guid><description> Welcome to Weekly Head Voices number 244, stretching from Monday June 20 to Sunday July 24, 2022.
Winter, don&amp;rsquo;t call us, we&amp;rsquo;ll call you Shortly after the start of this period, June 21 to be exact, I was frankly and quite pleasantly surprised by the Southern Hemisphere winter solstice.
This handy Time and Date website has more details, including but not limited to:
The June solstice (winter solstice) in Cape Town is at 11:13 on Tuesday, 21 June 2022.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to Weekly Head Voices number 244, stretching from Monday June 20 to
Sunday July 24,  2022.</p>








<figure><a href="giraffe.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="winter-don-t-call-us-we-ll-call-you">Winter, don&rsquo;t call us, we&rsquo;ll call you</h2>
<p>Shortly after the start of this period, June 21 to be exact, I was frankly and
quite pleasantly surprised by the Southern Hemisphere winter solstice.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-AFRICA/cape-town">This handy Time and Date website</a> has more details, including but not limited
to:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The June solstice (winter solstice) in Cape Town is at 11:13 on Tuesday, 21
June 2022. In terms of daylight, this day is 4 hours, 32 minutes shorter than
the December solstice. In locations south of the equator, the shortest day of
the year is around this date.</p>
<p>The earliest sunset is on 12 June. The latest sunrise is on 29 June or 30 June.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some of you <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">might remember</a> that this is an important point in the year for me,
the moment when I can see the big light, namely summer, at the end of the
tunnel.</p>
<h2 id="projections">Projections</h2>
<p>I recently finished reading the book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/55411738-projections"><em>Projections: A Story of Human Emotions</em>
by Karl Deisseroth</a>.</p>
<p>As a layperson, I found this psychiatrist and world-changing scientist&rsquo;s view
of the world, and especially of the psyches of his patients, absolutely
fascinating.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Deisseroth">Deisseroth</a> writes about several different types of psychiatric disorders, but
does so via specific but (probably) fictional patients who embody the important
aspects of the disorder in question.</p>
<p>He also writes about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optogenetics">Optogenetics</a>.</p>
<p>Optogenetics is a technique, invented by Deisseroth, for controlling neurons
with lasers, <em>in vivo</em>.</p>
<p>More specifically, by inserting specific genes from algae, neurons can be
modified to activate when struck by light.</p>
<p>Using this technique, researchers are able to activate very specific subsets of
neurons in mice brains, making the mice feel anxious for example, or
comfortable, or any of the different neural components making up these mental
states.</p>
<p>From the Wikpedia artictle:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In systems neuroscience, the ability to control the activity of a genetically
defined set of neurons has been used to understand their contribution to
decision making, learning, fear memory, mating, addiction, feeding, and
locomotion.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The use of this technique has already contributed significantly to our
fundamental understanding of the brain, and the first steps have been taken
towards using it in therapy.</p>
<p>Judging by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optogenetics#Awards">the list of awards</a>, the scientific world has really noticed the
value of this work.</p>
<p>Personally, I am optimistic that there&rsquo;s much more to come.</p>
<p>P.S. Close to the end of <a href="https://lexfridman.com/karl-deisseroth/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Deisseroth</a>, Deisseroth
mentioned that he really doubts whether he has done enough&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="batting-for-biyamiti">Batting for Biyamiti</h2>
<p>I am Bat-Fan.</p>
<p>No really, I appreciate bats. (and puns)</p>
<p>They&rsquo;re little flying mammals who see and navigate the world <em>expertly</em> using
echolocation (just imagine what that <em>feels</em> like?!) . They eat large numbers of
insects, including a <a href="https://news.wisc.edu/study-bolsters-bats-reputation-as-mosquito-devourers/">debatable</a> number of mosquitoes (I did not know about the
debate until right now).</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s not to like?</p>
<p>However, during our recent freshly reinstated yearly <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/">KNP break</a>, we enjoyed
fantastic summer weather (it&rsquo;s winter down here, but that&rsquo;s Mpumalanga for
you), we spent one night in Biyamiti with a pretty active bat in the room.</p>
<p>As we went to sleep, we thought that it would probably be ok.</p>
<p>It was not.</p>
<p>In addition to the bat expertly dropping something wet in my eye (your guess is
as good as mine), during parts of the night it started doing fly-bys so close
to our faces that we could feel the discrete wind gusts caused by the flapping
of its little wings.</p>
<p>On the one hand I was quite impressed by its sheer <em>mammalian</em> skill, but on
the other we just really wanted to sleep.</p>
<p>We decided that the price of a few extra insects in the room was worth it, and
so we opened the mesh.</p>
<p>Our bat friend, in spite of apparently having built a little nest in the nook
right up in the apex of the roof, fortunately obliged by exiting to perform the
rest of its manouevres outside in the night.</p>








<figure><a href="sunset-crocodile-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: The sun sets over the Crocodile. Nothing else matters."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>The sun sets over the Crocodile. Nothing else matters.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #243: Part-time role-model</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 22:26:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/</guid><description> Welcome back friends, welcome back me!
This WHV covers the multiple weeks from Monday May 23 to Sunday June 19, 2022.
It is this late, because it has been super busy at work (and at home), and by the time that I get any sort of opportunity to write, I am often too tired to focus.
I hope to say something about that a bit further down.
Whatever the case may be, I am happy to be here now, focusing on this post draft right here.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends, welcome back me!</p>
<p>This WHV covers the <em>multiple</em> weeks from Monday May 23 to Sunday June 19, 2022.</p>
<p>It is this late, because it has been super busy at work (and at home), and by
the time that I get any sort of opportunity to write, I am often too tired to
focus.</p>
<p>I hope to say something about that a bit further down.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am happy to be here now, focusing on this post
draft right here.</p>








<figure><a href="20220616-bettys-walk-famjam.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_huab9c1322188647837626b4904953e60a_3337321_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_huab9c1322188647837626b4904953e60a_3337321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_huab9c1322188647837626b4904953e60a_3337321_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_huab9c1322188647837626b4904953e60a_3337321_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/20220616-bettys-walk-famjam_huab9c1322188647837626b4904953e60a_3337321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a walk in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay with the fam-jam."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Scene from a walk in Betty&rsquo;s Bay with the fam-jam.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="a-drop-in-the-bucket-is-a-drop-in-the-bucket">A drop in the bucket is a drop in the bucket</h2>
<p>After taking a critical look at my discord subscription (I&rsquo;m too old for
animated emojis anyways), I decided to cancel that, and rather switch to
(small) monthly subscriptions to two services I find really important: <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">Signal</a>
(the private messaging app; I activated the sub via Apple) and <a href="https://donate.wikimedia.org/wiki/Ways_to_Give">Wikipedia</a>.</p>
<p>#feelsgoodman</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not that I have piles of cash to give away every month (come back in 6
months, hopefully that mythical ship will have come in), but I learned at a
recent course on the topic that it is possible, and even prudent, to review
critically and design with intent one&rsquo;s strategy of giving.</p>
<p>What do you find important, and which organizations appear to be applying their
resources effectively towards the furthering of their (and your) principles?</p>
<p>In that same vein, I subscribe (at the cheapest tier until ship comes in, see
above) to one of the <a href="https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/">better local news sources</a>, although their articles are
available for free online. We live in a society&hellip; where functional and honest
journalism is crucially important.</p>
<h2 id="tip-the-tailscale">tip the tailscale</h2>
<p>Some time back, a friend from work suggested tailscale as a tool to connect
computers and devices, separated by firewalls, into a virtual private network</p>
<p>My brain helpfully surfaced this information about three weeks back when I
wondered if there was a less painful way to connect to my home network from
work via the OpenVPN server on my home router.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that there&rsquo;s a <em>delightfully smooth</em> way to connect the
devices that you own together into a secure network, no matter behind which
firewalls they might be hiding.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s called <a href="https://tailscale.com/">tailscale</a>.</p>
<p>Within five minutes (literally) I had five of my devices hooked up, and
suddenly I was able to make point-to-point wireguard connections from anywhere
to anywhere, often via two firewalls, without having to click any buttons.</p>
<p>Each device is automatically assigned a &ldquo;static&rdquo; <code>100.*.*.*</code> IP number, and
hostnames can even be setup via tailscale MagicDNS, which is currently the
switching of a single toggle.</p>
<h2 id="typescript-with-emacs-and-tree-sitter">TypeScript with Emacs and tree-sitter</h2>
<p>In spite of the fact that I mostly use Visual Studio Code for my programming
these days (Emacs is for everything else), a question on reddit&rsquo;s <code>/r/emacs</code>
caused me to go down the Emacs-TypeScript-and-tree-sitter rabbit-hole.</p>
<p>I wrote up most of the results of this adventure a vxlabs post titled
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/06/12/typescript-development-with-emacs-tree-sitter-and-lsp-in-2022/">TypeScript development with Emacs, tree-sitter and LSP in 2022</a>.</p>
<p>After years of hearing its name mentioned, this was my first real contact with
tree-sitter, which turns out to be a fascinating recent development in
interactive source code parsing.</p>
<p>Thanks to tree-sitter, which was developed by the Atom editor team at GitHub,
and the combination of LSP and Microsoft&rsquo;s typescript compiler, Emacs (just
like other open source editors), gets access to state-of-the-art code
intelligence.</p>
<h2 id="when-the-going-gets-tough-double-down-on-the-side-projects">When the going gets tough, double-down on the side-projects</h2>
<p>If anything, this is a note to myself, but maybe also to you.</p>
<p>As evidenced by the lateness of this post and the one before it, the weekly
head voices had to take a backseat to other priorities.</p>
<p>However, writing posts on this here blog is one of <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#learning-at-the-burning">my &ldquo;show up to every day&rdquo;
things</a>, and so the fact that my frequency is currently reduced probably has
nothing to do with <a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">the general rickety raft of shifting life directions and
priorities</a>, but is indeed due to more urgent work sneakily taking precedence.</p>
<p>I have deliberately chosen the word &ldquo;sneakily&rdquo;, because when I start actually
paying attention (an activity the frequency of which is ironically also reduced
due to above-mentioned business), I realise that under these circumstances it
becomes even more important to buckle down and make time for the side-projects.</p>
<p>I could waste time on YouTube and reddit, or I could apply some intent and
create something interesting that is deliberately outside the broad umbrella of
work.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not that I don&rsquo;t like work (I love it), but rather spending that
carved-out time on side-projects is invigorating, and boosts creativity.</p>
<p>P.S. I like YouTube too, but it&rsquo;s time:leisure ratio (I recently coined that
term in a discussion with GOU#1 about her instagram usage) is not great.</p>
<h2 id="part-time--role--model">Part-time (role-)model</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve discussed the following with a small number of friends (some of them my
mentors; haha who am I kidding, they&rsquo;re all my mentors) over the years, so it
must be correct.</p>
<p>What I have learned over time, is that all of us are role models for fellow
humans at various (hopefully high) points in time, but we won&rsquo;t know when and
we often won&rsquo;t know for whom.</p>
<p>This knowledge has more than one important implication.</p>
<p>Firstly, we can never stop trying to be good humans, because we don&rsquo;t know who
might be depending on us at that moment.</p>
<p>This is reminiscent <a href="/2008/11/17/what-i-did-this-err-summer/">one of my favourite quotes, this one by Plato</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Be kind, for everyone you meet is fighting a hard battle.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Secondly, we will always have those ups and those downs, and often it will feel
like the ratio is hopelessly in the wrong direction.</p>
<p>I have explained to my children (my most important mentees, also the ones that
seem to pay the least attention) that athough I often fail, I will always keep
on trying.</p>
<p>Finally, even my own amazing mentors are humans who have ups and downs.</p>
<p>I love them for who they are, but I remember them at their best.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #242: Multiplicity of me</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 20:51:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</guid><description> This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.
If you like backyard philosophy, you&amp;rsquo;re in the right place.
Even if you only like bullet lists, you&amp;rsquo;re going to be ok.
Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL.
Learning at the Burning There&amp;rsquo;s an unwritten rule that you should not make any life decisions for at least three weeks after the (Afrika)Burn.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from
Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.</p>
<p>If you like backyard philosophy, you&rsquo;re in the right place.</p>
<p>Even if you only like bullet lists, you&rsquo;re going to be ok.</p>








<figure><a href="afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo by friend WvdL.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="learning-at-the-burning">Learning at the Burning</h2>
<p>There&rsquo;s an unwritten rule that you should not make any life decisions for at
least three weeks after the (Afrika)Burn.</p>
<p>Apparently people have, inspired by the sometimes weird experiences of the
event, made some major but unfortunately quite regrettable decisions in its
afterglow.</p>
<p>Anyways, I did not come back with anything like that.</p>
<p>Without sounding (too much) like Zaphod eating the fairy cake powering the
Total Perspective Vortex and walking away pretty much unscathed, through the
week&rsquo;s ups (mostly) and downs I learned a bunch, and I did come back with some
internal changes, but they were at their most extreme a strong reminder (kick
in the butt might even be appropriate) of a partially buried perspective or
two.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it is now exactly three weeks after the thing, and although that
dusty afterglow has definitely waned, it feels like I&rsquo;ve just merged back into
reality without any major incidents, just a slight tweak (or gentle kick in the
butt) here and there, for the better.</p>
<p>(Because inquiring minds might want to know, yes, we again brought the
BURNIVERSITY. We&rsquo;re probably one of the smallest theme camps, but we were
intense, and it feels like our interactions were too.)</p>
<p>Anyways, here are some completely random words, some of them loosely based (or
not at all, or something in between) on a recent conversation with friend PK,
and some of them from friend DW:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA</a> is a good framework for your well-being, and that of your loved ones:
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion</li>
<li>Engagement</li>
<li>Relationships</li>
<li>Meaning</li>
<li>Accomplishment</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>That thing you&rsquo;re stressing about is most probably not worth such a high
personal cost, and health-risk.</li>
<li>Just do the work.</li>
<li><a href="https://typesense.org/blog/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-just-showing-up-everyday/">Just showing up every day is a super power</a>. Pick your thing(s), show up to
them every single day, profit.</li>
<li>Chopping onions is the physical manifestation of your love for the people for
whom you are cooking. Give it (chopping onions, making food, loving) your
<em>whole</em> attention, and see what happens. Thank you DW, for this wisdom, and
for the food.
<ul>
<li>(Dear reader, between you and me, man that guy was burning so bright&hellip;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Practice will boost your powers of attention. This will deeply improve you,
and how you interact with others.</li>
<li>Kindness is still the most important super power.</li>
<li>Check up on yourself every day, about all of these completely random words.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="multiplicity-of-you">Multiplicity of you</h2>
<p><a href="/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/#homo-deus">In 2018, I talked about <em>Homo Deus</em></a>, a book by Yuval Harari in which he
discusses several thought-provoking ideas, one of which I highlighted then and
would like to discuss again now:</p>
<p>Your experience of being a single identity, a single <em>I</em>, is most probably an
illusion, as your brain most probably houses more &ldquo;me&quot;s than you would think.</p>
<p>Research by the Nobel prize-winner Daniel Kahneman and his various
collaborators showed that we house at the very least two major selves, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow#Two_selves">namely
the remembering / narrating self and the experiencing self</a>.</p>
<p>The experiencing self is the one who actually does the living and the
<em>experiencing</em> of each moment, while the narrating self is the one who
continuously stitches together your whole story, often bending the truth to fit
its (your) opinions of yourself and those around you.</p>
<p>The narrating self is the one who dominates, for better or for worse.</p>
<p>Kahnemann himself pointed out the irony of this the best:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Odd as it may seem, I am my remembering self, and the experiencing self, who
does my living, is like a stranger to me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(You might have heard of <a href="https://positivepsychology.com/what-is-peak-end-theory/">Peak-End Theory</a>, or the phenomenon that humans tend to
judge an experience based largley on the single peak moment, and on how they
felt at the end. You can thank your remembering self for this, and you can
imagine how this could really complicate your decision making.)</p>
<p>Harari discusses Kahneman&rsquo;s selves, but continues into more research with
people who for various reasons have separated brain hemispheres.</p>
<p>When you show one brain hemisphere one version of reality, and the other
another, it is as if there are multiple narrating selves in the same person who
come up with stories that they are convinced are the truth, although in this
case these stories conflict diametrically with other thanks to the design of
the experiment.</p>
<p>From this and other data, Harari concludes that humans generally house multiple
identities.</p>
<p>What I want to to get at, is that it helps to remember (always) that &ldquo;you&rdquo; are
in fact a collection of sometimes competing &ldquo;you&quot;s.</p>
<p>As if that were not challenging enough, your narrating self takes
responsibility for all of these feelings, and tries to weave it all into a
consistent story, although that is often extremely difficult or even
impossible.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.samharris.org/blog/the-illusion-of-the-self2">an 2012 interview with Sam Harris</a>, Bruce Hood had the following to say about
this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>By rejecting the notion of a core self and considering how we are a multitude
of competing urges and impulses, I think it is easier to understand why we
suddenly go off the rails. It explains why we act, often unconsciously, in a
way that is inconsistent with our self image &ndash; or the image of our self as we
believe others see us.</p>
<p>That said, the self illusion is probably an inescapable experience we need for
interacting with others and the world, and indeed we cannot readily abandon or
ignore its influence, but we should be skeptical that each of us is the
coherent, integrated entity we assume we are.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because this thought has become much more prominent for me in quite a positive
way, I would like to take it even further, by reminding you to practise
reminding yourself of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Although your perception is generally tied to your narrating self (the one
that&rsquo;s going to remember this blog post), the complete &ldquo;you&rdquo; in fact
constitutes the whole playing field, the consciousness and its physical
medium, in which <em>all</em> of these selves live and move around. In the words of
Harris, &ldquo;you can drop back into that&rdquo; and just <em>be</em> the consciousness, <em>be</em> that
which contains it all.</li>
<li>While your own selves truly live in this conciousness, high definition
versions of your surroundings and everyone you interact with are also
running in this same (your) neural network.
<ul>
<li>This means that you have a surprising amount of control of how you
experience life.</li>
<li>When you hear a dog barking, this is really nothing more than clusters of
neurons firing in your brain, but you visualize the dog <em>over there</em>. When
you feel the wind blowing over your skin, there&rsquo;s just another set of
neurons firing not far away from the barking dog. It&rsquo;s all inside your
head, and the borders between &ldquo;inside&rdquo; and &ldquo;outside&rdquo; are far more blurry
than you might think.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>All of your selves are <em>you</em>. Treat them like you would a group of your closest
friends. You can hold them up to the group&rsquo;s standards, but you have to
forgive, and you have to be kind.</li>
</ul>
<p>Folks, I wish you all (and all the yous), and all of your people, peace and
love.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #241: Best intentions</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 22:05:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/</guid><description> Welcome back folks to the Weekly Head Voices!
Edition 241 (this one) covers the four weeks from Monday March 21 to Sunday April 17 of the year 2022.
This time, my excuse for being so late is our autumn vacation trip to Augrabies and the Kgalagagi Transfrontier park.
The Knersvlakte-Augrabies-Kgalagadi-Calvinia vacation trip The super short summary is as follows:
My extremely resourceful partner had managed to book a few nights in rest camps in Kgalagadi about a year ago.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks to the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>Edition 241 (this one) covers the four weeks from Monday March 21 to Sunday
April 17 of the year 2022.</p>
<p><em>This</em> time, my excuse for being so late is our autumn vacation trip to Augrabies
and the Kgalagagi Transfrontier park.</p>








<figure><a href="augrabies-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-knersvlakte-augrabies-kgalagadi-calvinia-vacation-trip">The Knersvlakte-Augrabies-Kgalagadi-Calvinia vacation trip</h2>
<p>The super short summary is as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>My extremely resourceful partner had managed to book a few nights in rest
camps in Kgalagadi about a year ago. That&rsquo;s generally how early you need to
be for this.</li>
<li>As the vacation came closer, we accidentally configured a really cool road
trip (&ldquo;sloertoer&rdquo; as I recently learned) to sandwich the Kgalagadi bit in the
middle.
<ul>
<li>On the way there, we stayed at <a href="https://letsatsi.ncfamouslodges.com/">Letsatsi Lodge in Vanrhynsdorp</a>, and we spent
two nights at the Augrabies falls. The falls were absolutely
spectacular. Besides the panorama above, <a href="https://youtu.be/DW8SFHUP_18">this clip</a> of the falls at sunset
should give you a taste of what we experienced.
<ul>
<li>On the last night, our braai was attacked by a swarm of locusts. This was
so intense that the rest of the clan had to move indoors. I remained
outside with the braai and the locusts, witnessing thousands of the
beasts burn themselves up in the flames.
<ul>
<li>This event seemed like a great excuse to look up the difference between
grasshoppers and locusts. Maybe you already knew this, but I did
not. Grasshoppers <em>transform</em> into locusts. The transformation is both
physical, modulated by serotonin (which is also a super important
neurotransmitter in humans) and social; grasshoppers are loners, while
locusts are born, live and die as a swarm.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>On the journey&rsquo;s final leg back home from Nossob, we spent a night in the
Blou Nartjie in Calvinia.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Kgalagadi was magic.
<ul>
<li>On the one morning where we were able to get up early enough to exit as the
Tweerivieren gates opened (this is The Way), we were lucky enough to spend
some close-up alone time with two cheetah close to Kamfersboom. Ironically,
this happened much later in the morning as we were on our way back to the
camp. You never know&hellip;</li>
<li>On other drives we spotted lion, leopard (lazing in a tree, a lot further
away than the cheetah who were almost at touching distance), springbok,
lots of gemsbok (surprise!), meerkat and fox.</li>
<li>The balmy evenings outside, with intensely brilliant starry skies, were
unexpectedly good.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>








<figure><a href="kgalagadi-tfp-sign.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Red Karahari sand!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Red Karahari sand!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-period-after-the-trip">The period after the trip</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m writing this sentence here during the last few hours of the Easter weekend.</p>
<p>As I wrote in my mostly private and personal diary this morning: &ldquo;Man, these
days were really good for a reset, spending time on meta-work (emacs config,
planning config, and so on) and family.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(On the topic of keeping diaries and on the topic of deciding to publish some
of the private bits, here is another extract: &ldquo;Reviewing the past 4 weeks of
notes for hopefully soon-to-be-published WHV 241 also reminded me of so many
bits of peace and wisdom. I&rsquo;ve said this before, it&rsquo;s like I&rsquo;m up and down the
scale of human, and the high performing / balanced human needs to write
encouraging messages to the more frequently active normal / inferior me.&rdquo;)</p>
<p>Moving on&hellip;</p>
<p>In the time since the vacation trip, I&rsquo;ve been exceptionally privileged and
grateful to have a small selection of close friends visit in various
configurations.</p>
<p>In some cases I could offer only my ears although I desperately wanted to help
more, and in other cases they were less complicated life-affirming
celebrations.</p>
<p>In all cases, this is what I&rsquo;m here for.</p>
<p>(Later, I would really like to talk more about how easily and how often I
manage to forget that when I get caught up stress.)</p>
<h2 id="a-smidgen-of-nerd-news">A smidgen of nerd news</h2>
<p>It turns out that my <a href="/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/#new-diagramming-tool-of-the-insert-suitable-period-here">favourite quickly-sketch-out-your-idea tool excalidraw</a> is
a cinch to run locally, if you already have node and yarn installed, and who
doesn&rsquo;t these days?!</p>
<p>As you can see from the docs, it&rsquo;s just a <code>git clone</code>, <code>yarn</code> and <code>yarn start</code> away.</p>
<p>I thought this was going to be important during our Kgalagadi trip, because
patchy internet, so I got it going one evening in Twee Rivieren.</p>
<p>(Narrator: After that, he never used it, but he could have!)</p>
<p>Other than that, I had <a href="https://github.com/FuPeiJiang/VD.ahk/pull/10">fun helping to fix up an open source AutoHotkey library
for using Windows API calls to switch desktops quickly</a>.</p>
<p>I use this library in my simple but fast tool, called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/vxdesktops.ahk">vxdesktops.ahk, for
hotkey-based switching between virtual desktops on Windows</a>. I put this together
when I saw yet another screencast of someone showing off how quickly they could
switch using <a href="/2014/09/23/weekly-head-voices-82-tiles-and-platitutes/">i3wm</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-surprising-effectiveness-of-assuming-best-intentions">The surprising effectiveness of assuming best intentions</h2>
<p>With a small group of friends, we have for a while now been applying the idea
of always assuming best intentions, and always <em>having</em> the best intentions.</p>
<p>I knew that this is how I would generally like to operate, but I was still
pleasantly surprised by how this has turned so many potentially difficult
conversations into constructive and educational interactions that have enriched
us all.</p>
<p>So recently, <a href="https://rickmanelius.com/article/assume-positive-intent">a 2017 blog post by Rick Manelius, titled Assume Positive Intent</a>,
was again featured on HN where it caught my attention.</p>
<p>He makes the case for <em>always</em> assuming positive intent, also outside of groups
of friends where you can explicitly agree upon this principle.</p>
<p>Of course he excludes low trust environments from this mode, but generally in
business, and other interactions with strangers in non-low-trust environments,
assuming positive intent will work well (and be far less tiring) far more often
than it won&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>My humble suggestion here would be to try the explicit configuration of
bilaterally best intentioned environments wherever possible because this is
really an amazing way to connect with fellow humans, and to assume positive
intent everywhere else where it makes sense.</p>
<p>I hope to be able to write more eloquently about this in a future post.</p>
<p>Thank you for joining me here!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #240: I am just a copy of a copy of a copy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 21:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</guid><description> Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three weeks instead of one.
I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking
back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of
the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three
weeks instead of one.</p>
<p>I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about
alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more
resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough
time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</p>
<p>(Some more famous bloggers that I follow manage to put out a paragraph or two
every single day. It would be interesting to try an experiment like that.)</p>
<p>Anyways, switching out of meta mode back to the mishmash of on-topics for edition
240:</p>
<h2 id="blood-flowers">Blood flowers</h2>
<p>During a recent karma-restoring family beach walk, we came across the following
pretty striking flowers:</p>








<figure><a href="blood-flowers.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Blood flowers in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Blood flowers in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The <a href="http://pza.sanbi.org/haemanthus-coccineus">PlantZAfrica website tells us</a> that these are examples of <em>Haemanthus
coccineus</em>, also known as &ldquo;March flower&rdquo; (no idea why) or &ldquo;blood flower&rdquo;, the
latter which is more in line with the meaning of its Greek genus (haima =
blood, anthos = flower), and its Latin species.</p>
<p>We are not the first or only people to find it quite striking:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It was probably the first flower to be collected from Table Mountain and,
probably also the first illustration of a South African flower to appearin a
European publication. The illustration was by the Flemish botanis de L&rsquo;Obel
in 1605. &ndash; PlantZAfrica</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, as if the name &ldquo;Blood Flower&rdquo; is not metal enough, it turns out
<em>Haemanthus coccineus</em> lives fully underground in the form of a large bulb for
the dry summer months, only revealing its brilliant red flower when the rainy
season is about to start.</p>
<h2 id="fantastic-karma-and-how-to-destroy-it">Fantastic karma and how to destroy it</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s Friday evening. We&rsquo;ve just had a brilliant edition of our Friday evening
family braai tradition, and everyone starts retiring to their various
individual relaxation activities.</p>
<p>I decide that it&rsquo;s a great idea to forge ahead with the <a href="https://github.com/vega/react-vega/tree/master/packages/react-vega">react-vega</a> and <a href="https://redux-toolkit.js.org/rtk-query/overview">RTK
Query</a> visualization functionality I had ended my work week with.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d successfully worked with a previous version of the former, and my
confidence in RTKQ&rsquo;s quality was trending upwards due to recent experience in
one of our products.</p>
<p>I had already made a start with this new instance, and surely my first fully
backend-data-driven visualization was only an hour or two away, giving me a
final Friday evening boost.</p>
<p>Well friends, in hindsight I should have stopped right there and then.</p>
<p>Sure, it was the sort of gamble that had often paid off in the past &ndash; who does
not like to start their weekend with the dopamine rush that comes with the
solving of a little technical puzzle, especially one that results in pretty
pictures?! &ndash; but in this case it was doomed to failure.</p>
<p>The later it got, the less able I was to debug the issue, and the less
emotional control I was able to exert over my growing frustration.</p>
<p>(I am still less than happy with the new react-vega&rsquo;s limited documentation,
error handling and examples.)</p>
<p>I went to bed far later than normal, frustrated, and with no solution in sight.</p>
<p>All of this continued to affect my Saturday (grumpy with capital G&hellip; no wait,
all capitals&hellip;), until I finally made the conscious decision to disconnect
from the technical problem completely.</p>
<p>Anyways, I&rsquo;m writing this down as a reminder to me to be really, really careful
with the work-to-weekend transition.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-1-make-my-home-smart-but-do-it-really-slowly">Techno interlude #1: Make my home smart, but do it really slowly</h2>
<p>I finally got around to hooking up one (1) of the <a href="https://shelly.cloud/products/shelly-1-smart-home-automation-relay/">Shelly 1 smart relays</a> I
bought at the end of 2020.</p>
<p>My whole family is now able to open the main yard gate using&hellip; THEIR PHONES.</p>
<p>Noteworthy here is how easily the Shelly switches can be flashed, over the air
(OTA) no less, with the third party <a href="https://github.com/mongoose-os-apps/shelly-homekit">shelly-homekit firmware</a> to make them
natively Apple homekit compatible.</p>
<p>You can read about the how and the what in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/03/05/connecting-the-shelly-1-to-an-et-systems-gate-motor-for-apple-homekit-control/">this vxlabs post</a>.</p>
<p>Shortly after that post appeared, we held a <a href="https://fb.me/e/30MWR7Rq3">&ldquo;home automation&rdquo;-themed Helderberg
Software Developers and Entrepreneurs meetup</a>. Thanks to current interest in the
topic, and the three absolutely brilliant speakers who were willing to take us
along on their HA adventure, it was the biggest and most active we&rsquo;ve had in
years, by far!</p>
<p>In another probably surprising move, we are currently moving the meetup group
away from meetup.com and onto facebook as a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/helderberg.swdev.entrep.meetups/">group</a> (join if you&rsquo;re on fb!) from
where we can easily setup events.</p>
<p>Since 2019, meetup.com has been charging a pretty ridiculous $50 / 6-months fee
for a 100% free meetup with 0 commercial intent. In return for that, they
handle attendance (ish, we ofen had &gt;50% no-shows) and supply a bit of
discoverability.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, we now fortunately also have a snazzy website at
<a href="https://helderberg.dev/">https://helderberg.dev/</a> where you&rsquo;ll always be able to find the meetup, no
matter the events platform <em>du jour</em>.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-2-make-emacs-more-prettier">Techno interlude #2: Make Emacs More Prettier</h2>
<p>In spite of general business, I did have to make time for some <code>init.el</code>
wrangling, as is the privilege and sworn duty of every Emacs user.</p>
<p>This time, I refined my font and specifically <code>variable-pitch</code> setup.</p>
<p>I settled on the <a href="https://www.figma.com/blog/the-birth-of-inter/">Inter font</a> because I liked the look of <a href="https://obsidian.md/">obsidian.md</a>, where it&rsquo;s
the default. Then I discovered that it was designed (based on the Roboto font)
by Figma designer Rasmus Andersson as &ldquo;a font meant to make it easier to read
text on computer screens&rdquo; (hey, that&rsquo;s exactly what I need!), and is now also
the default on github, mozilla, and notion. Pretty good typographic company
right there.</p>
<p>The other small change I made which was much more satisfying than I expected,
was setting the default font size based on the estimated pixel density of the
current screen.</p>
<p>This means that my Emacs will render its default fonts at sizes that make sense
on whichever display I&rsquo;m using it.</p>
<p>Yes, I know that we should have been able to specify <a href="https://github.com/kickingvegas/12pt-should-be-the-same-everywhere/blob/master/absoluteMeasurementDPI.md">resolution invariant font
sizes by now</a>, but until that future arrives, my Emacs config will just have to
compensate.</p>
<p>The screenshot below shows an example of variable-pitch rendering on the left
(org-roam entry at the bottom, automatic topic backlinks at the top) and in the
centre (a slightly earlier draft of this post) and fixed-pitch on the right,
the relevant parts of my <code>init.el</code> showing the font and (<a href="https://github.com/humanoid-colors/emacs-humanoid-themes">humanoid</a>) theme setup.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Emacs screenshot. No, I don&amp;rsquo;t like dark themes."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Emacs screenshot. No, <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">I don&rsquo;t like dark themes</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="permutation-city">Permutation City</h2>
<p>When I saw a recommendation for <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156784.Permutation_City">Permutation City, a 1994 sci-fi novel by the
Australian author Greg Egan</a>, I was hesitant.</p>
<p>Would a novel, written more than 25 years ago, about uploading digital copies
of humans to virtual reality (I wrote a bit about that in <a href="/2020/07/01/weekly-head-voices-199-a-bit-stubborn/#a-totally-unexpected-ramble-on-cycles-patterns-and-teleportation">WHV #199</a> back in
2020), still be up to date with the latest ideas on the topic, seeing that
several adjacent fields of research have been advancing at a break-neck pace in
recent decades?</p>
<p>Weeeeell&hellip;.</p>
<p>It turns out great sci-fi has no problem reaching ahead through a quarter
century of modern technological development and then blowing my mind several
times.</p>
<p>With Permutation City, Egan has written the book I would have wanted to write,
in my wildest fantasies of course, about humans, and copies of humans, and the
philosophically indistinguishable self-awareness and consciousness of the
copies, and of their copies, and so on, literally ad infinitum.</p>
<p>Fortunately this is my first Egan novel, and even more fortunately it turns out
that he has produced a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/32699.Greg_Egan">considerable collection of stories</a> which I now have the
privilege to proceed to assimilate!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #239: Embarrassing finitude</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 22:05:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</guid><description> This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.
Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay.
House gets more energy reserves In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three
weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Fiery sunset in Betty&rsquo;s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="house-gets-more-energy-reserves">House gets more energy reserves</h2>
<p>In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium
ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of
the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</p>
<p>The complete stack looks as follows, with the new UP5000 on top, and the two
&ldquo;old&rdquo; US3000 units (3.5kWh each) under it:</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A cluster of lithium ion house batteries." width="400px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A cluster of lithium ion house batteries.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I can already see the positive effect of this on the daily line chart of solar
energy stored: Where previously there were gaps, because the battery was full,
the hot water geysers were either already hot or had not come on yet (in our
house, these act as water batteries on fixed charge times) and we were not
drawing much load, the gaps are smoothed out and the area under the curve is
consistently higher.</p>
<h2 id="dot-dot-dot-while-human-has-to-make-peace-with-limited-energy-reserves">&hellip; while human has to make peace with limited energy reserves</h2>
<p>As a human, you have to deal with a limited amount of energy every day, as if
the fact that your total time on earth was embarrassingly finite was not
challenging enough.</p>
<p>In other words, during one&rsquo;s waking hours, of which one gets a limited number,
one can&rsquo;t rely on operating at the highest energy output all of the time.</p>
<p>As far as I can surmise, one can increase one&rsquo;s daily energy through the
consistent and continuous application of positive lifestyle choices.</p>
<p>This can be hard work, and due to the infernal complexity of organics (have you
looked at a <a href="http://biochemical-pathways.com/">map of metabolic pathways recently</a>? &ndash; you should really go take a
look, it&rsquo;s complicated but also really interesting) and the effects of aging
maybe even an intractable problem, and as if that&rsquo;s not enough, the right
lifestyle can be extremely boring (to those around you).</p>
<p>My mornings usually start pretty nicely, but by the middle of the afternoon my
brain starts disassembling itself anywhere from just after lunch to later in
the afternoon.</p>
<p>What I have recently started noticing, is that when I enjoy one of those highly
productive days with focus straying sharp until late in the afternoon, I pretty
much have to tone it down a bit the next day.</p>
<p>I can still do good work, but I do need to approach the day in a slightly more
relaxed fashion in order to make it through the whole thing in one piece, and
to increase the chances of having a highly productive day after the toned down
one.</p>
<h2 id="the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">The rickety raft of life directions and priorities</h2>
<p>Staying on the theme of limited energy, but taking many steps back from the
cyclical alternate day grinding effect, I&rsquo;ve had to make peace with another
phenomenon:</p>
<p>Again thanks to embarrassingly limited energy, one can only focus on a subset
of one&rsquo;s life directions and priorities at any one time.</p>
<p>For example, when your children are younger, it&rsquo;s normal to dedicate a
substantial chunk of your time to them.</p>
<p>Between that and the necessary parts of work, not much time is left for one&rsquo;s
own hobbies, like Trying To Be a Better Human, or for other worthy goals, like
writing that novel(la) (short story, err or maybe just a nice haiku).</p>
<p>Conversely, when you&rsquo;re training for an important cycle race (not me, a
friend), some of those other dimensions by definition spend time on the
dimensional back burner.</p>
<p>So while you probably have a longer list of priorities which are all very
important to you, you have no choice but to make peace with the fact that at
any one point in time, you can only deal with a fairly narrow subset.</p>
<p>To me it looks the most important to make peace with this fact, and to treat it
as a deliberate and honest choice.</p>
<p>Oh and don&rsquo;t flip flop too much. (that&rsquo;s meant for me)</p>
<h2 id="young-human-wise-beyond-her-years">Young human wise beyond her years</h2>
<p><a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU#1</a> and I were chatting in the car, on way back from one of her social
commitments.</p>
<p>We talked about sleep. (Had she gotten enough?)</p>
<p>She mentioned people that get by on six hours per night and seem to get more
done&hellip;</p>
<p>As I was preparing to attempt commenting Socratically about this, she
pre-empted me by volunteering that when she sleeps well, and for much longer
than six hours, she experiences that she is better with other humans, and that
she feels emotions more intensely.</p>
<p>Goodness!</p>
<h2 id="two-pages-per-week">Two pages per week</h2>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. on the topic of GOU #1 and how best to spend my puny energy:</p>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/#gou-1-reveals-her-plans-and-makes-us-think--more">WHV #194</a> when GOU #1 revealed her cunning plan for
completing a PhD, part of which was writing only 136 words a day for a year,
leaving the two sandwich years for respectively planning and proofreading,
leading to a perfect thesis.</p>
<p>In the recent <a href="https://lexfridman.com/tim-urban/">Lex Fridman podcast #264 with Tim Urban</a>, he of <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/">Wait but why</a> fame,
they start <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Jd7fJgFkPU&amp;t=7166s">talking in-depth about procrastination at the 2 hour mark</a>. (relax,
you can listen to it later. <strong>&lt;ba dum tiss!&gt;</strong>)</p>
<p>(Urban considers himself a procrastinator, but he is a deep thinker, and so this
is a pretty interesting bit of conversation.)</p>
<p>He starts off with the example of a writer who is able to commit to producing
only two pages <em>per week</em>, and by consistently hitting this pretty modest
sounding goal, is able to prepare a book per year.</p>
<p>Glossing over the fact that 200 pages is perhaps not a very <em>impressive</em> book, at
least in terms of girth, publishing one every two years would be frankly
amazing.</p>
<p>He then talks about this idea of being able to attain something substantial and
worthwile by consistently chipping away.</p>
<p>He is clearly searching for the right word,
<a href="https://youtu.be/0Jd7fJgFkPU?t=7203">but then comes up with <em>compiling</em></a>.</p>
<p>I would really like to think that he was in fact searching for our old friend
<a href="/tags/compounding"><em>compounding</em></a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #238: Live deep and suck out all the marrow of life</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 21:24:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/</guid><description> Welcome everyone to the 238th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the week from Monday, January 31 to Sunday, February 6, 2022.
I would like to get you started with some flowers, after which there is a possibly boring bit about improving my keyboard, followed by a final bit with a quote which I think is a bit more than just a two-bit quote.
Figure 1: Photo taken by GOU #1 at Vergelegen Wine Estate during a solidly Thing-level (see WHV #237) Sunday lunch with my inner inner circle.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome everyone to the 238th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one
covering the week from Monday, January 31 to Sunday, February 6, 2022.</p>
<p>I would like to get you started with some flowers, after which there is a
possibly boring bit about improving my keyboard, followed by a final bit with a
quote which I think is a bit more than just a two-bit quote.</p>








<figure><a href="vergelegen-sunflowers.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo taken by GOU #1 at Vergelegen Wine Estate during a solidly Thing-level (see WHV #237) Sunday lunch with my inner inner circle."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo taken by <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> at Vergelegen Wine Estate during a solidly Thing-level (see <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237</a>) Sunday lunch with my inner inner circle.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="womier-k87-keyboard-customization-unlocked">Womier K87 keyboard: Customization unlocked!</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/#yet-another--new-keyboard-yank">WHV #235 that I was quite happy with my new Varmilo
VA87m mechanical keyboard</a> and that I was also quite surprised to learn that I
might prefer <em>linear</em> switches over <em>tactile</em>, thanks to the super smooth Cherry MX
Speed Silver switches.</p>
<p>Furthermore, its stabilisers were exceptionally smooth, and quiet. It taught me
that one did not have to live with rattly stabilisers.</p>
<p>As is often the case with new knowledge, this made me re-evaluate my
relationship with my other keyboard, the Womier K87 (aka &ldquo;RGB-with-unicorns&rdquo;),
which was introduced here in <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204</a>.</p>
<p>You see, that board came with both <em>tactile</em> switches (Gateron browns), and with
rattly <a href="https://switchandclick.com/stabilizer-guide/">stabilisers</a>.</p>
<p>&hellip; and so it came to pass that I ordered 90 Cherry MX Red switches from
<a href="https://www.ctrlshiftesc.co.za/">Ctrl.Shift.Esc</a>, as well as a super cheap (R109 when I ordered, it seems the
price has just doubled!) 100g tube of SPANJAARD silicone paste.</p>
<p>The red switches are quintessentially linear. They have a more conventional
actuation distance of 2mm versus the perhaps too-quick-for-me 1.2mm of the
speed silvers.</p>
<p>Plus, they were in stock.</p>
<p>I selected the SPANJAARD silicone paste as a cheap local alternative after
reading more than I ever wanted to know about lubricants and greases for
respectively the switches themselves and the stabilisers.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m just kidding, this is exactly the sort of thing I love knowing everything
about.)</p>
<p>On the evening of Monday, January 31, our dinner table looked like this:</p>








<figure><a href="womier-red-switches-in-progress.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Brown switches out, reds are in. I kept those three browns top right for comparison. The white cap puller was much faster for me than the wire one above the keycaps."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Brown switches out, reds are in. I kept those three browns top right for comparison. The white cap puller was much faster for me than the wire one above the keycaps.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Shortly after that, I was typing on the &ldquo;new&rdquo; board, entirely unconvinced that
the switch (haha) had been worthwhile.</p>
<p>As I&rsquo;m typing this, it&rsquo;s a more than a week later, and I am now entirely
convinced.</p>
<p>Based on how they feel, and an improvement of my typing speed and accuracy on
these switches relative to brown, I am hereby joining team linear!</p>
<p>With regard to the rattly stabs: On February 2 I removed the spacebar,
backspace and return keys, disassembled the stabilisers, and coated the wire
ends in as much silicone paste as I could. Although not quite at Varmilo
levels, the three respective stabilisers have improved massively, and have
convincingly crossed my satisfaction threshold.</p>
<h2 id="live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life">Live deep and suck out all the marrow of life</h2>
<p>I used to encourage friend PK, and probably others (and probably most often
just myself), but he usually just <em>got it</em>, with the following: &ldquo;Please remember
to squeeze out every last drop from that experience&rdquo;.</p>
<p>There was a distinctly visual, almost palpable, element to this wish.</p>
<p>You have to imagine somehow grabbing the moment in question, and then wringing
it out like a wet towel to extract every last iota of juicy experience.</p>
<p>As I&rsquo;m desperately scrambling here for the right words to describe precisely
the intention, you can image how happy I was to run into the following quote by
Henry David Thoreau just the other day:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I went to the woods because I wished to live deliberately, to front only the
essential facts of life, and see if I could not learn what it had to teach, and
not, when I came to die, discover that I had not lived. I did not wish to live
what was not life, living is so dear; nor did I wish to practise resignation,
unless it was quite necessary. I wanted <strong>to live deep and suck out all the
marrow of life</strong>, to live so sturdily and Spartan-like as to put to rout all that
was not life, to cut a broad swath and shave close, to drive life into a
corner, and reduce it to its lowest terms&hellip; &ndash; Henry David Thoreau (<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/2690-i-went-to-the-woods-because-i-wished-to-live">ref</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(I just spent some time on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_David_Thoreau">Thoreau&rsquo;s wikipedia page</a>. It turns out it was not
just this quote, he was an impressive human.)</p>
<p>Folks, remember to squeeze out every last drop from <em>your</em> experience!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #237: Don't step over the thing</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 22:29:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/</guid><description> Well hello there and welcome to the first Weekly Head Voices of the year 2022!
Figure 1: So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay.
Where we usually pretend that a WHV covers a certain period of time since the previous one, this one will simply engage in some excessive but pretty skillful hand-waving and say that if you read it and the 2021 to 2022 year transition post, you should be more or less up to date with the state of this nation up to Sunday, January 30, 2022.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well hello there and welcome to the first Weekly Head Voices of the year 2022!</p>








<figure><a href="stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&rsquo;s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Where we usually pretend that a WHV covers a certain period of time since the
previous one, this one will simply engage in some excessive but pretty skillful
hand-waving and say that if you read it and the <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/">2021 to 2022 year transition
post</a>, you should be more or less up to date with the state of this nation up to
Sunday, January 30, 2022.</p>
<h2 id="eaz-and-sleep">EAZ and sleep</h2>
<p><a href="/tags/eaz/">EAZ (Experiment Alcohol Zero - no alcohol for at least a month but usually
more)</a> is still going strong, and it&rsquo;s getting harder for me to ignore the fact
that it&rsquo;s (again) having a drastic impact on my sleep quality.</p>
<p>Where I normally am quite chuffed to wake up feeling that I&rsquo;ve had a solid
night of sleep, these days it feels like I&rsquo;m almost guaranteed a great night of
shut-eye as long as I can get to bed on time.</p>
<h2 id="gou-updates">GOU updates</h2>
<p>In other much more important news, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> has left the nest.</p>
<p>Ok fortunately only sort of&hellip; She now spends her weeks in the school&rsquo;s
dormitory.</p>
<p>They are extremely well looked-after, and she gets to participate even more
fully in school activities where previously this was a bit constrained by the 1
to 1.5 hour travel time (school bus in traffic) involved.</p>
<p>We do miss her quite a lot in the weeks.</p>
<p>In her absence, GOU #2 (2IC, IOW) has quickly taken on a new role, which is
interesting to see.</p>
<p>GOU #3 has just started with Grade R (first year of &ldquo;big school&rdquo;), and it looks
like she&rsquo;s taken to it like a fish to water.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a lot more fun now with both #2 and #3 in the car in the mornings,
although we could probably do without all the karma loss I suffer in traffic
every morning. The 4km from my house to school can easily take up to 25
minutes, during which I&rsquo;m obviously surrounded by people who clearly can&rsquo;t
drive.</p>
<h2 id="the-apple-doesn-t-fall-far-from-the-tree">The apple doesn&rsquo;t fall far from the tree</h2>
<p>At the start of 2019 I decided for some or other reason that I really wanted to
know how my branch of the Botha family connected to the rest of the tree.</p>
<p>Botha is a pretty common surname down here.</p>
<p>Many Botha&rsquo;s probably know that we are the descendants of <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Both-15">Friedrich Both</a>, a
soldier who came to the Cape from Wagenheim (from the Thuringen region of
Germany) in 1678 to assist the Dutch colonists.</p>
<p>OR ARE WE?</p>
<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23948326/">A 2013 study by Greeff and Erasmus, titled <em>Appel Botha: The abc of a three
hundred year old divorce case</em></a>, showed that Theunis Botha, the first of four
sons of Friedrich Both and his Dutch wife, Maria Kickers (divorced from Jan
Cornelisz because they could not have children), was in fact the extra-marital
product of Maria&rsquo;s relationship with Ferdinandus Appel!</p>
<p>DUN DUN DUUUUUUUN!</p>
<p>According to the study, Theunis Appel is responsible for roughly half (38000) of all
of the Botha&rsquo;s (78000) living in 2013.</p>
<p>Returning to my branch all the way down here: My uncle E was so kind to send me
notes he made of the gravestones on one of the farms my ancestors lived on,
including full names and dates of birth and death of a number of said
ancestors. As you might realise, full names and birth / death dates are genealogy gold.</p>
<p>My aunt M&rsquo;s many stories helped to fill in any further gaps, especially by
confirming identities through matching full names with nick names.</p>
<p>Although initially I was unable to make the connection to the greater Botha
tree using this information, the <a href="https://www.myheritage.com/">MyHeritage</a> databases, and various bits of
information I could get from older clan members, I recently picked up my notes
again (after a two year hiatus!) and was suddenly able to make a single
high-impact connection (my great-great-grandfather) that I previously missed.</p>
<p>Long story short, the moment I did this all of the fragments came together, and
I&rsquo;m now able to say with reasonable confidence that <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Appel-29">Ferdinandus Appel</a> and <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Kickers-1">Maria
Kickers</a> are my great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-grandparents.</p>
<p>DUN DUN DUUUUUUUUUN!</p>
<h2 id="i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">I don&rsquo;t want to step over the thing</h2>
<p>At the end of their <a href="https://lexfridman.com/sam-harris/">3 hour long podcast interview from May</a>, Lex Fridman asks
Sam Harris one of his standard questions (you can listen to the bit in question
<a href="https://youtu.be/4dC_nRYIDZU?t=11241">precisely here</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is the meaning of life?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In almost typical Sam Harris fashion, he replies that it&rsquo;s the wrong question.</p>
<p>Less cryptically, Sam explains that if you&rsquo;re searching for that mythical
<em>meaning of life</em> that&rsquo;s going to make everything better, you might be doing it
wrong.</p>
<p>In his words (which I have transcribed and cleaned up a little bit especially
for you):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You don&rsquo;t have to live with the illusion anymore that you need a good enough
reason and that things are going to get better when you do get those reasons.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a mirage-like quality to every future attainment and every future
breakthrough and every future peak experience that eventually you get the
lesson that you never quite arrive.</p>
<p><strong>You don&rsquo;t arrive until you cease to step over the present moment in search of
the next thing.</strong></p>
<p><strong>We&rsquo;re constantly stepping over the thing that we think we&rsquo;re seeking in the
act of seeking it.</strong> [ed: my emphasis. I loved this bit]</p>
<p>&hellip;</p>
<p>You can&rsquo;t actually become happy. You can only be happy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>His words hit home for me.</p>
<p>Dear readers, I truly wish you an abundance of recognizing the thing, and of
<em>being</em> happy.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2021 to 2022 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</guid><description> Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.
I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to 2014 (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and 2015 (no real excuse).
Much later, on Sunday January 23: It could very well still win the Most Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&amp;rsquo;s done.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition
post</a>!</p>








<figure><a href="20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to
<a href="/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/">2014</a> (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and <a href="/2015/01/21/weekly-head-voices-88-just-be-yourself-they-said/">2015</a> (no real
excuse).</p>
<p><em>Much later, on Sunday January 23:</em> It could very well still win the Most
Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Emacs and <code>M-x count-words</code> (on a temporary buffer copied over from <a href="/archive/#2021">the 2021
blog post archive</a>) tells me that I published 28 posts on this blog, and 8
technical posts over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>Just like with the running below, but for different reasons, I lost a lot of
steam during the last few months of the year.</p>
<p>In a truly surprise twist, in 2022 I will again attempt to write regularly, and
to write more, and to keep it up until the end.</p>
<h3 id="stats-addendum">Stats addendum</h3>
<p>Applying the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess log analyzer</a> to this blog&rsquo;s log files with the following
invocation:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#859900">for</span> i in {2..13..1}; <span style="color:#859900">do</span> <span style="color:#cb4b16">echo</span> cpbotha.net.access.log.<span style="color:#268bd2">$i</span>.gz; <span style="color:#859900">done</span>) | xargs zcat -f -- | goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; tells me that in 2021 cpbotha.net welcomed over 115000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>The same tool reports that <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a> clocked in at just under 165000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>Even if the real number of actual human visits is a quarter of what the tool is
reporting, I am ecstatic!</p>
<p>The three most popular cpbotha.net posts based on hits during 2021 were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">Dear USA, my data has left your building</a></li>
<li><a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">Note-taking strategy 2019</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>Thanks to Strava&rsquo;s handy training calendar shown below, we can see that I spent
125 hours last year (mostly, about 4 hours was spent on hiking just over 20km)
running a bit over 1300km.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can also see quite clearly that I lost steam in November and especially in
December.</p>
<p>This was initially due to work getting quite busy, and then later in December a
bout with Omicron (highly probably) and also less than run-friendly weather in
St. Francis.</p>
<p>I am always happy when I manage to average 100km or more per month, and I&rsquo;ll
probably try to do that again in 2022.</p>
<h3 id="possibly-tmi-read-on-at-your-own-risk">Possibly TMI, read on at your own risk</h3>
<p>Those of you who know me, will also know about my giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunion">bunion</a>, or hallux
valgus as it prefers to be called.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&amp;rsquo;s complicated." width="240px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyways, Mr Valgus is unfortunately playing an increasingly frequent role in my
attempts at running, often starting to complain at N kilometres where N is
fortunately still higher than most of my attempts, but still affecting a
worrying number of them.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to push on, until Mr Valgus overstays its welcome, at which point
it will be time to explore invasive corrective procedures.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Probably my most redeeming habit of them all, is reading books every night in
bed until I fall asleep.</p>
<p>Even if the day has been less than satisfactory, ending it with an entirely
deliberate and focused reading session tends to make up for quite a lot.</p>
<p>Although I was planning to do more book summaries in 2021, I managed to
complete only one. At least it was a good one, namely <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Seven
and a Half Lessons About the Brain&rdquo; by Lisa Feldman Barrett</a>, which I can
strongly recommend if you have not checked it out yet.</p>
<p>Thanks to strong contenders like the one above, the competition was fierce, but
in the end the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em> could go to nothing other
than Oliver Burkeman&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08FGV64B1/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</em></a>.</p>
<p>Burkeman, he of the <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">importance of being able to put <em>down</em> your work</a> and of <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">more
appearances on this blog</a>, has created a beautifully written ode to our terribly
limited lifespans (4000 weeks if you&rsquo;re lucky, you can almost hear them ticking
away&hellip;), and to our terribly limited capacity to make the most of the time
that we do get, and to really just giving up the fight to <em>get everything done</em>,
because we will never ever win the battle against the law of perpetually
filling inboxes of various kinds, and because it&rsquo;s so much better to simply
<em>disconnect</em> from the firehose (which we can&rsquo;t get rid of completely) in order to
spend time on no-excuses leisure, and especially on our loved ones.</p>
<p>My favourite fiction book by far was <em>The Anomaly</em> by Herv le Tellier, as
translated by Adriana Hunter.</p>
<p>After having just grudgingly finished Elizabeth Bear&rsquo;s Ancestral Night (first
novel in the White Space series; some interesting ideas, but just too pulpy,
clumsy and exposition-rich for my taste, in spite of space opera being a guilty
pleasure&hellip;), the light literariness and French cynicism of The Anomaly was a
<em>delightful</em> and refreshing breeze that I was unable to put down until it was
done.</p>
<p>In 2022, I&rsquo;m planning to read more than in 2021, and publish more of those
summaries.</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#mindfulness">daily meditation streak that started in 2020</a> continued for most of 2021,
until the end-of-year school vacation started. I am not yet sure how I&rsquo;ll be
able to fit this into my new 2022 work-routine.</p>
<h2 id="worst-habit-of-2021">Worst habit of 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV Award for Worst Habit of 2021 By Far goes, without a doubt, to my old
friend TwiFRaF-Yo, although this time around the main culprits were Twitter,
Reddit and YouTube.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know exactly when I fell out of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">the previous social media fast</a>, but I
fell out with a vengeance.</p>
<p>Although I subscribe almost entirely to technical communities on reddit (Emacs,
Orgmode, Org-roam, keyboards, etc.), there are enough of them to keep a person
busy.</p>
<p>If you add to that my twitter feed, where I&rsquo;ve also taken care to remove the
noise, subscribing largerly to high-signal science-, technology- , and
engineering-related feeds, there&rsquo;s a great deal of valuable-seeming information
that one feels compelled to get through every day&hellip;</p>
<p>(It feels like I&rsquo;ve told this story before&hellip;)</p>
<p>Anyways, every time I manage to disconnect (it&rsquo;s been a few weeks now, I think
Monday January 3 was the official start date of the current fast), only then am
I able to recognise (where by &ldquo;recognise&rdquo;, I mean that friends say this to me,
and this is when I&rsquo;m able to admit that they&rsquo;re right) that the net value for
me is highly probably negative.</p>
<p>While there is certainly valuable information that enters via those streams, it
costs so much attention and emotional energy that it&rsquo;s not really worth it.</p>
<p>So.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m back on the no-social-media cart until next time.</p>
<p>Just like the previous time, I&rsquo;m limiting myself to the brilliant Inoreader RSS
subscription service (which I pay for) to keep up to date with 99% long-form
blogs, and two Twitter accounts that are worth too much to me to disconnect
from (<a href="https://twitter.com/erictopol">Eric Topol</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/alper">Alper uun-Gscheidel</a>).</p>
<p>Although I sometimes think this makes me slower, because I don&rsquo;t have all of
the current happenings at my fingertips all the time, I&rsquo;m hoping this gives me
more space and time for reading, thinking and writing.</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">Systems and tools for running this human (PKM baby)</h2>
<p>In the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">2018 to 2019 transition post</a> I mentioned the &ldquo;The System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This time, for this section, I would like to limit it to tools for knowledge
management and task management (this is not my favourite term, but I&rsquo;m erring
on the side of familiarity here) .</p>
<p>All of Emacs and Orgmode and Org-roam is still going strong, although I waver
quite a bit sometimes when I see some of the shiny new things, like <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>,
which I would probably be using if it wasn&rsquo;t for Emacs.</p>
<p>However, when I sometimes dive into my notes, I can see the difference it makes
when you stick to a single tool for longer than a few years. The amount of
knowledge keeps on growing, and I am slowly getting better at linking it all
together and&hellip;  sometimes even using it.</p>
<p>The picture below shows the graph created, by the <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> package, of a
sub-section of my notes network:</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Before I got side-tracked by the pretty picture, I was planning to dedicate
this section to a new WHV award, namely the Award for the Most Unexpectedly
Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021.</p>
<p>This year the award goes to&hellip; <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper/guide">Dropbox Paper</a>!</p>
<p>Back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">WHV #233</a> I listed many of the reasons why. In the few months since then
it has become only more useful to me as the go-to mobile tool for checklists
(especially useful when we go on trips), lists of books, movies and music
recommended by people in person, and so on.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualifier features, such as its markdown DNA and its
usability on mobile for idea capturing, the fact that Paper documents show up
in Dropbox searches, which is how I usually search when I <span class="underline">really</span> need to find a
specific file (versus ripgrep searches in Orgmode), is the deal maker.</p>
<p>(My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">strange scheme for continuously converting all org files to docx</a> for
searching and reading on the iPhone is also still going strong.)</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I had a piece written here with more details about what exactly was happening
at work, but I decided to nuke that and instead keep it more personal by
mentioning that thanks to great big dollops of serendipity and people, I find
myself, with a number of levers at my disposal, right in the middle of an
organization which, after a few months of reconfiguration and preparation, has
embarked on a genuinely exciting, and importantly more unified, course.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not mention the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">discomfort and stress</a> I was
experiencing at the start of the current personal phase, most probably due to
trying to adapt quickly to my new circumstances and responsibilities.</p>
<p>In the time since then, my stress levels have returned to more acceptable
levels, but expectations remain high.</p>
<h2 id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<p>One of the most positive changes I made in the past year, was to put more
effort into making regular and active (virtual) contact with friends whom I
don&rsquo;t see in person regularly enough.</p>
<p>THANKS INTERNET YOU DA BEST.</p>
<p>This year, I want to try harder to do more of that.</p>
<p>More generally, I made a note (yes, again, one has to keep doing this until the
end) to celebrate any of my peeps and our relationships whenever there&rsquo;s a
chance.</p>
<p>Secret message for my innner INNER circle: You are my energy and my joy, I am
here to be yours.</p>
<p>Whatever else happens, these precious relationships are all we have.</p>
<h2 id="even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">Even more plans for 2022: Continue trying</h2>
<p>First off, I would really like to get this blog post here done and
published. (it wants to be too much, or rather I want it to be too much, and so
we sit here staring at each other instead of just getting on with it so I can
try again to write a good post for once)</p>
<p>Second, EAZ is back on, since Monday January 10. EAZ means no alcohol until at
least February 10. As has been the case previously, my sleep quality is
subjectively better, and it seems like my energy levels are more consistent
throughout the week.</p>
<p>I just looked back at last year&rsquo;s transition post, and especially at the <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">final
sections, including the neatly documented Life Systems 2021</a>. That guy
(<a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">apparently we share only about 2% of our atoms</a>) really seemed to have his
stuff together, on paper at the very least.</p>
<p>As I write this (22:38 on Saturday, January 22), I have just realised that <em>this</em>
&ldquo;I&rdquo; definitely needs to spend some more time thinking about &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo; (The WHV
approach to life, the universe and everything, the one with the pillars (love
and science, that&rsquo;s the easy and reliable bit) and the rules) and specifically
if and how to revise the daily life direction clusters.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll have it on your desk by Monday.</p>
<p>Until then, the one thing I&rsquo;m sure about, is that I wish you and your loved
ones the best 2022 possible.</p>








<figure><a href="stormsriver-mouth.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #236: The surprising power of consistent chipping</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/</guid><description> This 236th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the three (sorry!) weeks from Monday October 25 to Sunday November 14, 2021.
What will the beholder think? First things first: Do you notice something different about me I mean my blog?
I don&amp;rsquo;t know how most readers respond to this sort of a thing, but I can really appreciat, in a non-professional way of course, good typography on a personal blog.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This 236th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the three (sorry!)
weeks from Monday October 25 to Sunday November 14, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="facing-strand.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="what-will-the-beholder-think">What will the beholder think?</h2>
<p>First things first: Do you notice something different about me I mean my blog?</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know how most readers respond to this sort of a thing, but I can really
appreciat, in a non-professional way of course, good typography on a personal
blog.</p>
<p>Over the past few years I&rsquo;ve been tweaking the CSS here and there to make small
improvements to the WHV typography, but I&rsquo;ve never been really happy with the
font.</p>
<p>That is, until I ran into <a href="https://alexanderobenauer.com/">Alexander Obenauer&rsquo;s blog</a> and just new that I had to
have the same serif on mine.</p>
<p>The font is called <a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Newsreader">Newsreader</a>. I&rsquo;m currently enjoying the subtly new look, I
hope you do too.</p>
<h2 id="new-diagramming-tool-of-the-insert-suitable-period-here">New diagramming tool of the [insert suitable period here]</h2>
<p>Via Hacker News (henceforth just &ldquo;HN&rdquo;) I ran into this <a href="https://offbyone.us/posts/why-is-excalidraw-so-good/">entertaining and
charming review of a drawing tool called &ldquo;excalidraw&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>Searching a little further, I could see that it had become in a relatively
short timespan a darling of the otherwise hyper-critical HN community.</p>
<p>Personally, I&rsquo;m always on the lookout for any tools which I think could help me
visualize some of my ideas or plans better.</p>
<p>Excalidraw is great at boxes and arrows, which is fortunate, since about 95% of
my ideas and plans are based on different ways of connecting boxes and arrows.</p>
<p>As an aside: So far, I&rsquo;ve gotten by far the most use out of Notability on the
iPad (with 1st gen Apple Pencil), but I never produce as many diagrams as I
keep on imagining that I should be doing.</p>
<p>Upon first use, Excalidraw indeed struck me with how little friction it offers
to the act of sketching out <em>stuff</em>.</p>
<p>I especially like how the authors have somehow managed to merge super-easy
drawing on the computer with the production of diagrams that look like they&rsquo;ve
been made on a paper notebook, whilst still remaining fully vectorized.</p>
<p>Let me know if you&rsquo;ve used this for anything interesting, or if you have any
other diagramming tricks you&rsquo;d like to share.</p>
<h2 id="ok-rust-i-give-up">Ok Rust, I give up</h2>
<p>Back in July of 2018, in <a href="/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/#programming-language-addiction-update">WHV #148</a>, I wrote that after noting the fact that Rust
was an expression-oriented language (I love those) and subsequently reading the
O&rsquo;Reilly <em>Programming Rust</em> book, I had filed away the language under
&ldquo;re-evaluate whenever you reach for your trusty C++&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As a programming language enthusiast, I should have know that that &ldquo;filing
away&rdquo; was merely a postponement of the inevitable.</p>
<p>Recently, in hobby time, probably because I had not yet selected a new book to
read, and because I&rsquo;m going through a bit of a programming phase (err&hellip;), I
unfiled Rust and started going through some more of the materials.</p>
<p>My current feeling is: Hot durnit! Rust may just be the fastest functional
language I have access to!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing a number of the <a href="https://exercism.org/tracks/rust">exercism exercises</a>, and after often pulling out
a pattern match for compact yet readable solutions, I&rsquo;ve been getting a strong
wolf-in-sheep&rsquo;s-clothing feeling.</p>
<p>Rust brings a number of core functional programming principles to an
exceptionally performant programming platform.</p>
<p>Sometimes there are still more nuts and bolts than I would like to see (to be
expected from a systems language that wants to give you full control), but this
mix of low-level and subjectively high-level functional programming is still a
remarkable achievement in my book.</p>
<p><em>Of course</em> I have no real-world applications in mind, unless <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">Advent of Code</a>
counts, but Rust currently makes for great programming practice.</p>
<h2 id="keep-on-keeping-on">Keep on keeping on</h2>
<p>In WHV #214 I wrote about <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">writing down that One Main Thing that you&rsquo;d like to
get done every day</a>.</p>
<p>Day job is currently not entirely conducive to this mode of work, and that&rsquo;s
putting it lightly.</p>
<p>Still, on most days I do remember to select and then write that thing down.</p>
<p>Most recently, I was dragging such an item along with me for what felt like
weeks.</p>
<p>Every morning I did the Alt-W Ctrl-Y finger dance (that&rsquo;s Emacs for copy
paste), and I experienced the concomitant pang of internally facing
embarrassment.</p>
<p>Often there would be no progress (because meetings and other non-maker work),
but on some days I would excavate the equivalent of a generously filled
teaspoon of dirt. (<a href="https://youtu.be/4%5FC86o5dE%5Fc">Doctor Flammond&rsquo;s tunnel</a> anybody?)</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, the Thing neared completion, until one day (weirdly still to
my pleasant surprise) it was done, never to be copy-pasted again.</p>
<p>My happy little mental note was: Just keep on dragging One Main Thing with
you. It&rsquo;s not on the list because it&rsquo;s going to get completed, but rather
because it&rsquo;s the thing that you just have to keep on chipping away at,
<em>especially</em> when progress seems almost invisible.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>