<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Screenflow on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/screenflow/</link><description>Recent content in Screenflow on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2018 10:28:18 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/screenflow/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #127: Readers are leaders.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/14/weekly-head-voices-127-readers-are-leaders/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2018 10:28:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/14/weekly-head-voices-127-readers-are-leaders/</guid><description> Betty’s Bay Beach impression by Genetic Offspring Unit #1, age 11.
This week I worked on automated email analysis and storage for side-project #38465 (more on this in future editions) and on bits of UI for a wxPython desktop app (yes desktop app! some of us fortunately still get to make them!) for my current main work project. Had to make screencast to demonstrate milestone deliverable of above-mentioned main project. Making screencasts is an obscure but longstanding hobby of mine, but I needed to level up slightly, so the business bought me ScreenFlow 7.2. For the first time ever, I recorded the screencast in multiple segments and did the voice-over later. Soon these new skillz will trickle down to my publically available screencasts. On that topic, having a good microphone is crucial, not only for screen recordings but also for video meetings. I recently acquired the Samson Go Mic to complement my larger Samson C01U. The Go is brilliant: Recorded voice quality comes close to the C01U in spite of the Go’s compact form factor, and it has a hardware switch to select either of the the built-in omni-directional, for meetings, or cardioid, for more dedicated voice recording, microphone elements. Ironically, an ex-colleague posted “How to Fix Facebook—Before It Fixes Us” on Facebook, a long and worthwhile read on how FB is used to spread fake news that effectively manipulates public opinion, and what should be done to remedy this. Here is a choice quote to get you started: We still don’t know the exact degree of collusion between the Russians and the Trump campaign. But the debate over collusion, while important, risks missing what should be an obvious point: Facebook, Google, Twitter, and other platforms were manipulated by the Russians to shift outcomes in Brexit and the U.S. presidential election, and unless major changes are made, they will be manipulated again. Next time, there is no telling who the manipulators will be.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/gou1_bettys_bay_beach.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/gou1_bettys_bay_beach-1024x576.jpg"
        
            alt="Betty’s Bay Beach impression by Genetic Offspring Unit #1, age 11."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Betty’s Bay Beach impression by Genetic Offspring Unit #1, age 11.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<ul>
<li>This week I worked on automated email analysis and storage for side-project #38465 (more on this in future editions) and on bits of UI for a wxPython desktop app (yes desktop app! some of us fortunately still get to make them!) for my current main work project.</li>
<li>Had to make screencast to demonstrate milestone deliverable of above-mentioned main project. Making screencasts is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/cpbotha">an obscure but longstanding hobby of mine</a>, but I needed to level up slightly, so the business bought me <a href="https://www.telestream.net/screenflow/">ScreenFlow 7.2</a>. For the first time ever, I recorded the screencast in multiple segments and did the voice-over later. Soon these new skillz will trickle down to my publically available screencasts.</li>
<li>On that topic, having a good microphone is crucial, not only for screen recordings but also for video meetings. I recently acquired the <a href="http://www.samsontech.com/samson/products/microphones/usb-microphones/gomic/">Samson Go Mic</a> to complement my larger <a href="http://www.samsontech.com/samson/products/microphones/usb-microphones/gomic/">Samson C01U</a>. The Go is brilliant: Recorded voice quality comes close to the C01U in spite of the Go’s compact form factor, and it has a hardware switch to select either of the the built-in omni-directional, for meetings, or cardioid, for more dedicated voice recording, microphone elements.</li>
<li>Ironically, an ex-colleague posted <a href="https://washingtonmonthly.com/magazine/january-february-march-2018/how-to-fix-facebook-before-it-fixes-us/">“How to Fix Facebook—Before It Fixes Us”</a> on Facebook, a long and worthwhile read on how FB is used to spread fake news that effectively manipulates public opinion, and what should be done to remedy this. Here is a choice quote to get you started:</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>We still don’t know the exact degree of collusion between the Russians and the Trump campaign. But the debate over collusion, while important, risks missing what should be an obvious point: Facebook, Google, Twitter, and other platforms were manipulated by the Russians to shift outcomes in Brexit and the U.S. presidential election, and unless major changes are made, they will be manipulated again. Next time, there is no telling who the manipulators will be.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>In the same vein, I continuously try to spend as few as possible minutes on YouTube, but the one thing I will definitely continue watching is <a href="https://users.cg.tuwien.ac.at/zsolnai/">Károly Zsolnai-Fehér’s</a> brilliant <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCbfYPyITQ-7l4upoX8nvctg">Two Minute Papers channel</a>! Most recently, his treatment of <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1711.09784.pdf">Distilling a Neural Network Into a Soft Decision Tree</a>, a paper by Nicholas Frost and Geoffrey Hinton, caught my interest. In this, they address the problem of neural network explicability (it’s hard saying at a higher level <em>why</em> a neural network makes a particular decision) by deriving a soft decision tree from that trained neural network. The tree is not as accurate as the network, but is able to give plausible explanations for the network’s decisions. See the 4 minute long two minute paper video (hehe) here:</li>
</ul>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zjaz2mC1KhM?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<ul>
<li>I came across the following on reddit, again quite ironically, and I have since taken to saying it to my genetic offspring units (GOUs) at every possible opportunity:</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Readers are leaders!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Have a great week readers, I hope to see you again really soon!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>