<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>dscas on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/dscas/</link><description>Recent content in dscas on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2003 17:53:29 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/dscas/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Visualisation and Image Processing Platform Formerly Known as DSCAS3</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2003/12/19/the-visualisation-and-image-processing-platform-formerly-known-as-dscas3/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2003 17:53:29 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2003/12/19/the-visualisation-and-image-processing-platform-formerly-known-as-dscas3/</guid><description> The current marketing conditions and long-term strategy dictate a name change. The new name should contain at least the words “Delft”, “Visualisation”, “Image [Processing]”, and then one of “platform”, “framework”, “[software environment]”.
I’m currently looking at “devise” (Delft Visualisation and Image processing Software Environment), “devious” (“ou” not used, the rest you can easily guess) and perhaps “divine” (or “devine”, which I like more, because of the infamous Devine Brown and the fact that I would be able to use acronyms like “PIMP” for Parallel IMage Processing”) which would stand for Delft Visualisation and Image processing Network Environment, which is not an entirely correct description (the network environment is just one aspect) but acceptable nonetheless.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The current marketing conditions and long-term strategy dictate a name
change. The new name should contain at least the words “Delft”,
“Visualisation”, “Image [Processing]”, and then one of
“platform”, “framework”, “[software
environment]”.</p>
<p>I’m currently looking at “devise” (Delft Visualisation and
Image processing Software Environment), “devious”
(“ou” not used, the rest you can easily guess) and perhaps
“divine” (or “devine”, which I like more, because of
the infamous Devine Brown and the fact that I would be able to use acronyms
like “PIMP” for Parallel IMage Processing”) which would
stand for Delft Visualisation and Image processing Network Environment, which
is not an entirely correct description (the network environment is just one
aspect) but acceptable nonetheless.</p>
<p>So, what do you think? Do you have any other suggestions?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>DSCAS does 2D registration</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2003/12/09/dscas-does-2d-registration/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2003 18:28:43 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2003/12/09/dscas-does-2d-registration/</guid><description> The code is just short of being awe-inspiringly horrible, but it works and is quite usable for automatic and semi-automatic rigid registration of 2D sections for 3D reconstruction.
See the screenshot below:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The code is just short of being awe-inspiringly horrible, but it works and is
quite usable for automatic and semi-automatic rigid registration of 2D
sections for 3D reconstruction.</p>
<p>See the screenshot below:</p>
<a href="/thingies/dscas3register2d20031209.png">
<img src="/thingies/dscas3register2d20031209.png"/>
</a>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>