<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Body Budget on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/body-budget/</link><description>Recent content in Body Budget on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 17:40:32 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/body-budget/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #213: Merry Christmas!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/30/weekly-head-voices-213-merry-christmas/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 17:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/30/weekly-head-voices-213-merry-christmas/</guid><description>This edition of the WHV looks back at the week from Monday, December 21 to Sunday, December 27, 2020.
Figure 1: View of False Bay from Clarence Drive, a truly beautiful road.
Merry Christmas During this week, the most noteworthy happening was of course Christmas.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the week from Monday, December 21 to
Sunday, December 27, 2020.</p>










<figure><a href="clarence_drive_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/30/weekly-head-voices-213-merry-christmas/clarence_drive_pano_hu_34ae1bdd5cc283dc.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/30/weekly-head-voices-213-merry-christmas/clarence_drive_pano_hu_4f31bb37e31f16da.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/30/weekly-head-voices-213-merry-christmas/clarence_drive_pano_hu_da4dc4aa893ce960.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/30/weekly-head-voices-213-merry-christmas/clarence_drive_pano_hu_b31c373164b15abc.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/30/weekly-head-voices-213-merry-christmas/clarence_drive_pano_hu_4f31bb37e31f16da.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View of False Bay from Clarence Drive, a truly beautiful road."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View of False Bay from Clarence Drive, a truly beautiful road.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="merry-christmas">Merry Christmas</h2>
<p>During this week, the most noteworthy happening was of course Christmas.</p>
<p>As a family, we are wholly dedicated to the pursuit and application of Love and
Science. However, we do try to respect the religious customs of our fellow
humans.</p>
<p>In the light of this, respectfully and retrospectively, I wish you all a very
merry christmas!</p>
<p>(I have to say that my kids really adore the gifting-aspect of this
particular celebration, if you get my drift.)</p>
<h2 id="creativity-inc-dot-book-notes-published">Creativity, Inc. book notes published</h2>
<p>I finally got around to processing and publishing <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my notes on the book
<em>Creativity, Inc.</em> by Ed Catmull</a>.</p>
<p>There are a number of great nuggets in there if you are at all interested to
learn about the care and feeding of sustainable creative organizations.</p>
<p>Even if that&rsquo;s not your cup of tea, being able to take a look inside a company
like Pixar is quite fascinating.</p>
<p>BTW, books are really cheap upgrades for your brain&rsquo;s operating system.</p>
<p>BTW, I&rsquo;m planning more book notes.</p>
<h2 id="body-budgets">Body Budgets</h2>
<p>On that topic, I have just started reading <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/48930266-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Seven and a Half Lessons About the
Brain</a> by psychologist and neuro-scientist Lisa Feldman Barrett, after listening
to another <a href="https://lexfridman.com/lisa-feldman-barrett/">super-entertaining podcast with her and Lex Fridman</a>.</p>
<p>I am planning to write much more about her ideas, but for now I would like to
plant this memetic seed:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/11/23/opinion/brain-neuroscience-stress.html">Our big brains evolved to manage our body budgets</a>.</p>
<p>In short, managing the metabolic needs of a whole human is tremendously
complicated.</p>
<p>Throughout the day (every day), that big super-computer in your head is
calculating a million inputs and outputs to ensure your survival, and more
importantly, the survival of your genetic material.</p>
<p>To me, a truly interesting aspect of this is that social interaction is just
another, albeit important, variable in this complicated system of equations.</p>
<p>One of the implications of this realization is that social interaction requires
a substantial amount of metabolic energy, an equation your brain will apply
quite strictly.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re getting low on energy, your brain could very well cancel that kind
interaction you were planning, instead substituting with a quick eject, because
it predicts (the brain is a fabulous prediction machine, you&rsquo;ll see much more
of that here in the coming months) that you&rsquo;ll probably run out of energy a bit
later.</p>
<p>Related to what <a href="/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/#use-it-or-lose-it">I wrote last week concerning the use-it-or-lose-it principle</a>,
this is yet another reason to invest in one&rsquo;s physiology and its energy
efficiency:</p>
<p><em>Your body needs energy to be nice.</em></p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>