<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Slow on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/slow/</link><description>Recent content in Slow on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 19:47:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/slow/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #181: The Slow Ones.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 19:47:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/</guid><description>Welcome back everyone!
This edition of the WHV, #181, looks back at the period of time from Monday October 7 to Sunday October 13, 2019.
Compulsory running shot: Looking at Gordon's Bay from the Strand. This was on Thursday. I squeezed in another short run on Friday, which my legs definitely did not appreciate. Note to self: Laziness earlier in the week leads to skipped rest days and sore legs later. (cf. "A stitch in time saves nine." Also cf. Always Be Compounding.) Alternative WHV notification modalities. Shortly after publishing WHV #180, I decided (bolstered by the advice of my, err, advisor) to return to announcing new WHVs on Facebook and perhaps even on Twitter, in spite of TwiFRaF-YT.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>This edition of the WHV, #181, looks back at the period of time from Monday
October 7 to Sunday October 13, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_77e9f02865b47207.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_668df39896270fff.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_b72391f5381e5a66.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_2ae12fc41c639bc1.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_668df39896270fff.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Compulsory running shot: Looking at Gordon's Bay from the Strand. This was on
Thursday. I squeezed in another short run on Friday, which my legs definitely
did not appreciate. Note to self: Laziness earlier in the week leads to skipped
rest days and sore legs later. (cf. "A stitch in time saves nine." Also
cf. Always Be Compounding.)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="alternative-whv-notification-modalities">Alternative WHV notification modalities.</h2>
<p>Shortly after publishing WHV #180, I decided (bolstered by the advice of my,
err, advisor) to return to announcing new WHVs on Facebook and perhaps even on
Twitter, in spite of
<a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#twifraf-progress-report">TwiFRaF-YT</a>.</p>
<p>For the past months, the only place where you could opt in to be notified of
new WHVs was on the mailing list. (Well, that and RSS, which seems to be
becoming more niche with every passing day.)</p>
<p>Although the mailing list works for a number of people, I am interested in
adding other options that would make sense for WHV readers.</p>
<p>Readers, where else would be a good place to keep you up to date about new WHV
posts, should you like to be kept up to date?</p>
<h2 id="what-i-did-in-week-41">What I did in week 41.</h2>
<p>This was a great week for social events.</p>
<p>It was not the best week for avoiding amazing craft beer and even more amazing
wine.</p>
<p>(I knew what I was getting into when the week started. I committed to it.)</p>
<p>On Tuesday evening, I really enjoyed our local Helderberg business and nerdery
meetup.</p>
<p>Two &ldquo;lightning&rdquo; talks were given: The first on getting your podcasting game on
(microphones, syndication, oh my!), and the second on personal knowledge
management, based on the recently published <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">note-taking post on this
blog</a>.</p>
<p>Craft beer was enjoyed.</p>
<p>The next day, at a regular(ish) Top Secret Business Meeting (at the Thirsty
Scarecrow), I made use of the opportunity to drink my favourite IPA of all time
(so far), a beer which goes by the name of WARLORD, and a beer that has been
<a href="/2018/03/18/weekly-head-voices-136-slightly-more-than-nothing-much/#new-beer-warlord">documented before on these
pages</a>.</p>
<p>As the tasting ceremony started, I was greeted by this portentous sign:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_9df3cb3833e72e2f.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_6fcb5215693ddb6e.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_9d9262709756aa9c.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_64c6f6f1a80190f0.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_6fcb5215693ddb6e.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The name is BONECRUSHER, WARLORD BONECRUSHER.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Coincidence? I think not.</p>
<p>On Friday, we had lunch with friends from the Netherlands at the newly
re-opened Long Table restaurant at Haskell Winery.</p>
<p>The view from one&rsquo;s lunch table looked something like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_286fa91df2fcb999.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_36c973590ec6c78b.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_260eab87618f8b58.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_7f478114624e5f24.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_36c973590ec6c78b.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
For a whole while before the guests arrived and before I took this photo I just
sat there drinking in the view with my own eyes, like a crazy person.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>As if that was not enough, we had the exquisite pleasure of making the
acquaintance of the Haskell Anvil 2018, probably the best Chardonnay I have
ever tasted.</p>
<h3 id="running-with-fluids-and-fuel-1210-going-to-do-again">Running with fluids and fuel. 12/10 going to do again.</h3>
<p>On Sunday, I went out on a long run, partly to atone for my sins but mostly just
because I really like going on long runs.</p>
<p>What was special about this run, is that I took along extra fluids for the
first time ever.</p>
<p>Weekend runs these days are mostly longer than an hour.</p>
<p>After an hour of running on a sunny day down here, one loses quite an amount of
moisture. If this moisture is not replenished, one&rsquo;s running equipment starts
to malfunction.</p>
<p>To prevent this situation, I recently acquired a <a href="https://runnerclick.com/camelbak-circuit-vest-review/">Camelbak Circuit 1.5l
Hydration vest</a>.</p>
<p>On Sunday, I took this vest out for its maiden voyage. It had about a litre of
Game (local cheap isotonic drink) in the bladder, and two bananas stuffed in
the front pockets.</p>
<p>Subjectively, the run went better than usual and I was able to increase my
distance by a little, but gratifying, bit.</p>
<p>However, next time I&rsquo;m filling that bladder to capacity.</p>
<p>The angst-inducing sound which that thing makes when you suck out the last few
drops of drink with some distance still left to go is not something I want to
hear again soon.</p>
<h2 id="solar">Solar</h2>
<p>For the first time since <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">our house was
solarized</a>, this
thing happened on Saturday morning at 7:18:</p>
<figure style="width: 400px;">














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24.png">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24_hu_3849a9dd8612a7a7.png 480w
  
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24.png"
  

   />

</a>

</figure>
<p>The house&rsquo;s batteries were still at 24%, but the sun was already high enough to
meet our modest energy demands at that point.</p>
<p>In other words, for the first time, we had stored enough solar power the
previous day to get us 100% through the night and back into solar, without us
having to dip into the grid.</p>
<p>(The inverter is programmed not to let the lithium batteries discharge below
20%, in order to further increase their lifespan. When there&rsquo;s a real power
outage, it will go down to 10%.)</p>
<p>This should happen more often now that the days are getting longer.</p>
<p>I derive a <em>substantial</em> amount of pleasure from every single kilowatt-hour of
sunbeam-powered electricity that we generate and use.</p>
<h2 id="first-rule-of-blogging-you-dont-blog-about-blogging">First rule of blogging: You don&rsquo;t blog about blogging.</h2>
<p>According to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/oct/12/blogging-twenty-five-years-old-all-grown-up">this Guardian
article</a>,
blogging turned 25 on Monday, October 7, 2019.</p>
<p>They define the start of blogging as the birth of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Winer">Dave
Winer&rsquo;s</a> first blog post in 1994. It
turns out that Winer has posted to his blog on every single day since that very
first year.</p>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/QFKtHSlaMVI">RESTECP!</a></p>
<p>I like how the Guardian article juxtaposes blogging with modern social media.</p>
<p>Of course the truth is more complicated, but generally blogging is more about
the content, and the reasoning, albeit just as opinionated, behind it, whereas
social media is all about emotion-driven <em>engagement</em> and extremely short-term
gratification-analogues of some kind or another.</p>
<h2 id="the-slow-ones">The Slow Ones.</h2>
<p>Complementing <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">ABC</a>, I
feel another (old) theme brewing amongst the voices&hellip;</p>
<p>Deliberate, deep and slow thinking and doing, is an additional antidote to the
all-encompassing AI-optimised immediate gratification information environment
that we live in, and to humankind&rsquo;s concomitant addiction to all that is
instant.</p>
<p>In a science fiction world, we&rsquo;re going to end up with yet another
schism between humans.</p>
<p>There will be those who will hold conversations with ten others at the same
time, data streams coming in from twenty more sources in the background,
processing-processing-processing.</p>
<p>There will be a far smaller group of folks who still command the almost
forgotten art of focusing intently on a single thing for hours on end, without
swiping in any direction.</p>
<p>Communication between the two groups will become increasingly difficult.</p>
<p>Will this remain the stuff of fiction?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Slow e-mail. [Weekly Head Voices #32]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/28/slow-e-mail-weekly-head-voices-32/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2010 20:48:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/28/slow-e-mail-weekly-head-voices-32/</guid><description>(post summary: I’m teaching in Stellenbosch next week. We have another published paper. Next DeVIDE will have InfoVis. Peter Norvig spouts backyard philosophy on slow email and work-life balance.)
This week, yet another Weekly Head Voices Quickies! The handsome and sun-drenched building below, known as “The BJ” to generations of students, is part of the reason for my current posting-diet. You see, next week I have the pleasure of teaching a post-graduate Visualisation course at my old university in the beautiful town of Stellenbosch. I’ve been putting together a new course especially for this purpose, which has obviously taken up a significant portion of my time. The really pretty building under a really pretty sky where I shall be spending most of next week. (thank you Google Maps.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(post summary: I’m teaching in Stellenbosch next week. We have another published paper. Next DeVIDE will have InfoVis. Peter Norvig spouts backyard philosophy on slow email and work-life balance.)</em></p>
<p>This week, yet another Weekly Head Voices <em>Quickies</em>! The handsome and sun-drenched building below, known as “The BJ” to generations of students, is part of the reason for my current posting-diet. You see, next week I have the pleasure of teaching a post-graduate Visualisation course at my old university in the beautiful town of Stellenbosch. I’ve been putting together a new course especially for this purpose, which has obviously taken up a significant portion of my time.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/bj.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/bj.jpg"
        
            alt="The really pretty building under a really pretty sky where I shall be spending most of next week. (thank you Google Maps.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The really pretty building under a really pretty sky where I shall be spending most of next week. (thank you Google Maps.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I’m also greatly looking forward to some quality time with my SA homies. Yo homies! Oh wait, you don’t read my blog… :)</p>
<p>Also on the good news front, the paper that <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">ERCI</a> submitted to the VisWeek 2010 workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare has been accepted! This documents the extremely promising first steps that have been set on the path to comprehensive visual analysis of any imaging-based cohort study. Seeing as I’ll be present at VisWeek 2010 (whoohoo!), I’ll be presenting the work at the workshop on Sunday, October 24. Here’s the bibliographic information (I’ll link the full paper as soon as it goes online):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>M.D. Steenwijk, J. Milles, M.A. Buchem, J.H. Reiber, and C.P. Botha, <em>Integrated Visual Analysis for Heterogeneous Datasets in Cohort Studies</em>, <strong>IEEE VisWeek Workshop on Visual Analytics in Health Care</strong>, 2010.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Remember, cite it soon and cite it often! You’ll be doing my HATE-index a favour.</p>
<p>(Nerd Warning ON) On the epiphany front, I had a nice one whilst cataloguing all the various different InfoVis / Visual Analysis software toolkits available on the Interwebs: OF COURSE WE NEED YET ANOTHER ONE! I’ve been itching to start working on a new <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Projects/DeVIDE" title="DeVIDE website">DeVIDE</a> release, so <a href="http://code.google.com/p/devide/wiki/Early2011ReleasePlans" title="DeVIDE early 2011 release plans">the next one will have Python / matplotlib / VTK Titan-based InfoVis and Visual Analysis functionality</a>. (Nerd Warning OFF)</p>
<p>On the Backyard Philosophy meets Work-Life Balance meets I-need-to-wrap-this-up  front, I recently came across the following quote by Peter Norvig, director of Google Research, taken from an <a href="http://www.informationweek.com/news/global-cio/trends/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=224900261" title="Interview with Peter Norvig">interview with him in the InformationWeek</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<div id="_mcePaste">
</blockquote>
<p>&gt;   <strong>Q. How do you achieve a work-life balance? How do you keep your professional life from dominating everything?</strong>
&gt; </div></p>
<blockquote>
<div>
</blockquote>
<p>&gt;   <strong><br/> </strong>
&gt; </div></p>
<blockquote>
<div>
</blockquote>
<p>&gt;   <em>A. People get out of balance when they see their value as being able to respond quickly. If I see myself as a machine for answering email, then my work life would never stop because my email never stops. If instead I see my value as separating the important from the unimportant and making good decisions on the important, then I can go home at a reasonable hour, spend time with my family, ignore my email and phone messages all weekend long, and make sure that when I return to work, I am in the right mood to make the good decisions.</em>
&gt; </div></p>
<p>I used to think that I needed to respond to email (and other interruptions) as quickly as possible, but I’ve also very slowly been learning that that’s not really helping anyone. One should indeed rather focus on the important things, and do them well. Communication is important, but necessarily has to take second place, as time is a limited resource. Following this advice could be interpreted in a less than positive way by correspondents who expect a response right away. However, in the long run one is worth much more, to all concerned, by focusing on the important. As with all things, there is a balance that should be sought between between communication and action, between fulfilling short-term and long-term expectations.</p>
<p>Dear readers, I wish you a great week, filled with important accomplishments!</p>
<p><strong>p.s. I stand corrected. My SA homies do read my blog. I’m touched…</strong></p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>