<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Fine Dining on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/fine-dining/</link><description>Recent content in Fine Dining on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 09:39:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/fine-dining/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #184: The tai chi of you.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 09:39:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/</guid><description>Welcome travellers of the great and beautiful information universe!
(That universe was what we were promised. Thanks to the inherent and fundamental difficulties of our meat-based reality, we have ended up with something&amp;hellip; different. I remain hopeful.)
Here in this little corner, I&amp;rsquo;ll be reminiscing about the minuscule thread of personal time stretched taut between Monday, November 11 and Sunday, November 18.
pling
(that&amp;rsquo;s me plucking the thread. meat-space issues&amp;hellip;)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome travellers of the great and beautiful information universe!</p>
<p>(That universe was what we were promised. Thanks to the inherent and
fundamental difficulties of our meat-based reality, we have ended up with
something&hellip; <em>different</em>. I remain hopeful.)</p>
<p>Here in this little corner, I&rsquo;ll be reminiscing about the minuscule thread of
personal time stretched taut between Monday, November 11 and Sunday, November
18.</p>
<p><em>pling</em></p>
<p>(that&rsquo;s me plucking the thread. meat-space <em>issues</em>&hellip;)</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_606c3f258a6b0b88.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_3a6cea229427325.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_b395dc5b81a89f2b.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_f503d59cdfd80a62.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_3a6cea229427325.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
One of the views at Gåte, Quoin Rock.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="intermezzo-for-computer-nerds-wsl2">Intermezzo for computer nerds: WSL2.</h2>
<p>Microsoft released <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windowsexperience/2019/11/11/releasing-windows-10-insider-preview-build-19013-into-the-slow-ring/">Windows build 19013 onto the Windows Insider Preview slow
ring</a>, along with the shiny new WSL2.</p>
<p>WSL is a truly interesting development in the evolution of Windows that enables
users to run arbitrary Linux binaries with full Windows integration.</p>
<p>I run a true-blue Linux installation of Emacs on WSL, displaying to X410 on the
Windows side, manipulating files on the native Windows NTFS filesystem.</p>
<p>This is substantially faster for some or other reason than running native
Windows Emacs.</p>
<p>Anyways, WSL2 is the next significant jump for WSL where Microsoft is now
shipping a native Linux kernel together with Windows and exposing this kernel
via a light-weight Hyper-V utility VM with dynamic host memory allocation.</p>
<p>I was planning to wait until it got released on stable, but when MS announced
that it was available on the slow ring of the Windows Insider Previews, the
temptation was too great.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">The ThinkPad, my main development machine</a>, is
now running this hopefully relatively safe Windows preview.</p>
<p>At this point, I can report that WSL2&rsquo;s IO on its own local filesystem is
indeed much faster than WSL&rsquo;s. However, IO on the host NTFS filesystem is three
to four times slower&hellip;</p>
<p>This is indeed <em>quite</em> disappointing, as my work use-cases all involve
accessing files on the NTFS side in some or other way.</p>
<p>An unexpected bonus of WSL2 however, is the Docker integration.</p>
<p>Docker for Windows Edge is able to use WSL2 as a backend, meaning much, much
faster starting and general usage of docker containers on Windows.</p>
<p>I really hope that MS is able to improve the 9p-based NTFS IO performance of
WSL2 to at least that of WSL.</p>
<p>Far more unrealistically, I hope that MS finally retires NTFS and replaces it
with something better.</p>
<p>Windows really has been making great strides over the past
years. Unfortunately, NTFS is a gigantic ball and chain that is currently doing
a great job of holding the whole of Windows back.</p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>At the start of 2019, I wrote that I had an <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#looking-forward-1">&ldquo;additional concrete (but very
humble) running-related resolution for 2019, but I have decided to keep that
quiet until it’s in the
pocket&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>Well, it&rsquo;s in the pocket and now I can talk about it.</p>
<p>On Saturday morning I went out for my usual longer weekend run (longer is
anything greater than 10km).</p>
<p>It was cool for this time of the year, and there was almost no
wind.</p>
<p>Importantly, I had had a solid night of sleep.</p>
<p>As I was going out, Morning-Voice whispered in my head: &ldquo;It&rsquo;s highly probably
now, or never again in 2019&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I nodded in agreement.</p>
<p>My longer weekend run proceeded to morph successfully into the casual 20km run
that I had envisioned as my most concrete 2019 running goal.</p>
<p>Achievement unlocked!</p>
<p>Although I had indeed formulated the goal as &ldquo;doing a casual 20km run&rdquo;, the
<em>actual</em> goal was being fit enough to be able to do so more or less on a whim.</p>
<p>For my next trick, I&rsquo;ll try my best not to let it slip back too far.</p>
<p>OH HAI THERE LOOMING HOLIDAY SEASON!</p>
<h2 id="things-are-not-always-what-they-seem">Things are not always what they seem.</h2>
<p>After the morning run, we met with multi-decade close friends for lunch at the
restaurant Gåte at Quoin Rock.</p>
<p>That alternative &ldquo;å&rdquo;, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%85">also known as the
a-ring</a>, should give the first clue that
this place is hipper even than any of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefon">Stefon&rsquo;s
recommendations</a>.</p>
<p>I found the whole experience to be quite magical.</p>
<p>The 25 year old genius chef, Nicole Loubser, together with her team, has
constructed the most amazing culinary experience.</p>
<p>See the airport coffee and cigar below for example:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_4f0b80bef8c1827d.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_84059f263a6f246d.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_86205c6719bb0dd7.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_774ed6e5ccde909f.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_84059f263a6f246d.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The first of the 7 course lunch menu at Gåte. The macchiato is in fact tomato
soup with a pumpkin espuma on top, the ashtray is a paprika espuma with
maltodextrin on top, and the cigar is potato bread.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Our company, together with the beautiful surroundings and the party that had
entered via my mouth into my sensory system, made for a truly sublime
afternoon.</p>
<h2 id="electro-backyard-philosophy">Electro-backyard-philosophy.</h2>
<p>TPN recently and very fortunately pointed out that <a href="https://jorisvoorn.com/">Joris
Voorn</a>, probably my favourite electro artist, has a
new album out.</p>
<p>The album is of course called \\\\.</p>
<p>Below is an excerpt from the lyrics of track 8, <em>This City (feat. Lazarusman)</em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You are not alone.</p>
<p>When you have yourself.</p>
<p>How can you be alone<br>
How can you be alone when you have yourself?<br>
When you have you?</p>
<p>it is you mastering the art, the tai chi, of you</p>
<p>it is you realising that these fleeting moments are all for you</p>
<p>you have yourself<br>
you are not alone</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To my mind, these words contain echoes of both mindfulness and of
transcendental idealism, all on the background of an über hip electro beat.</p>
<p>At the almost 2 hour mark, these echoes contributed much pleasure to the mental
aspects of my run.</p>
<p>Now when I listen to it in a different state of mind, it is clear that the
music made the impact that it did due to the specific set of circumstances at
that moment.</p>
<p>This is a good demonstration of how dependent an experience can be, and how
fickle and unpredictable one&rsquo;s preferences.</p>
<p>(How do we <em>ever</em> make good choices?)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I have chosen to keep hold of the lessons,
irrespective of the subjective ephemerality of their container.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #159: Extreme.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 21:16:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/</guid><description> The view from Waterkloof Restaurant’s balcony, on a fairly perfect evening.
In theory, this edition should cover the period of time from Monday November 19 to today, Wednesday December 19, 2018.
I am very late with this post, because down here we were first busy winding down the year with all of the completion-madness that that entails, and then the vacation started starting.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/waterkloof_perfect_evening.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/waterkloof_perfect_evening-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from Waterkloof Restaurant’s balcony, on a fairly perfect evening."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from Waterkloof Restaurant’s balcony, on a fairly perfect evening.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In theory, this edition should cover the period of time from Monday November 19 to today, Wednesday December 19, 2018.</p>
<p>I am very late with this post, because down here we were first busy winding down the year with all of the completion-madness that that entails, and then the vacation started starting.</p>
<p>It hasn’t yet stopped being busy starting.</p>
<p>We are now entering what the Dutch call <a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komkommertijd">komkommertijd</a>, and, as I’ve just learned, the Germans <em>Sauregurkenzeit</em>, referring to the period when everyone has left and there’s not really anything news-worthy happening.</p>
<h2 id="extreme-dining">Extreme dining</h2>
<p>To celebrate the occasion of the official partnership between my partner and me adding another year to its growing collection, and due to my partner’s impeccable timing and ingenuity, we spent an amazing evening at what is currently South Africa’s best restaurant, at least according to <a href="https://www.timeslive.co.za/sunday-times/lifestyle/food/2018-11-20-this-eatery-in-the-western-cape-has-been-named-sas-best-restaurant/">the 2018 Eat Out Mercedes-Benz Restaurant Awards</a>.</p>
<p>I would like to share three observations:</p>
<ol>
<li>The Waterkloof experience is a superbly balanced combination of location (see the photo above), architecture and interior design, art and ambience, all acting as context for the almost other-worldly culinary adventure, itself consisting of pairings of wine and perfect little dishes, the latter again artfully manipulating appearance and taste, space and time.</li>
<li>South Africa is a country of extremes. Just the previous night, close family had been the victims in a violent but fortunately non-fatal home invasion.</li>
<li>If you ever manage to find yourself at Waterkloof, take this advice to heart: The <em>small</em> dégustation menu with wine pairing is most probably more than enough. (We selected the <em>normal</em>. By what felt like the 15th course, we were dealing with the dilemma of having to abstain from eye-wateringly beautiful culinary creations.)</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="extreme-solar">Extreme Solar</h2>
<p>For many good reasons, we are currently seriously evaluating upgrading the house with a photovoltaic solar power system.</p>
<p>It turns out, as I should have expected, that there’s a whole universe of new toys and gadgets to evaluate.</p>
<p>We are currently looking at the following main components:</p>
<ul>
<li>2 x <a href="http://www.pylontech.com.cn/pro_detail.aspx?id=121&amp;cid=23">PylonTech US3000B</a> LithiumIon batteries for a total of about 7 kWh of stored electricity.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.goodwe.co.uk/Products/index_em.html">GoodWe GW3648-EM Hybrid inverter</a>: This coordinates everything between the PV Solar panels, the grid and the batteries. When the sun is shining, it charges the batteries, and powers as much as possible of the house, only using the grid when there’s no other option. During the evening, it powers the house using the batteries, again only using the grid when absolutely required. Due to strict rules down here in Cape Town, we are limited to inverters with a maximum output of 3.6 kW, even when no feed-in (to the grid) is planned.</li>
<li>The PV Solar Panels: I am still considering options here. I would prefer monocrystalline, and as close as possible to the 4.6 kWp maximum supported by the GoodWe inverter to maximise the amount of sun in our power diet.</li>
</ul>
<p>As a first step, today we had a number of intelligent geyser controllers installed. These devices enable me to keep the geysers (we heat all of our water electrically down here…) off for most of the day, only switching them on an hour or two before hot water is usually required.</p>
<p>They look like this:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/geyserwise_tse.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/geyserwise_tse-888x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="GeyserWise TSE geyser controller. I should have done this ages ago. Who came up with the idea that a water geyser needs to maintain its high temperature 24/7?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>GeyserWise TSE geyser controller. I should have done this ages ago. Who came up with the idea that a water geyser needs to maintain its high temperature 24/7?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The rest of this exercise will be considerably more expensive, but  am really looking forward to being able to harvest most of our electricity from the lovely African sun!</p>
<p>I have one final bit of nerd-news, and it comes in the form of a…</p>
<p>WHV pro-tip #23972847376: If you are doing data science(tm), or machine learning, or visualization, or any other dataset-oriented work, I can highly recommend <a href="https://dvc.org/">DVC, or DataVersionControl</a>. We have started using this on one of our projects to manage different collections of DICOM images, and it works incredibly well.</p>
<h2 id="extreme-health">Extreme health</h2>
<p>In conclusion, I would like to mention a recent and very <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/fullarticle/2707428?resultClick=3">impressive study by the Cleveland Clinic about the correlation between cardiorespiratory fitness and all-cause mortality</a>.</p>
<p>I’ll start with this quote:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>
    In this cohort study of 122 007 consecutive patients undergoing exercise treadmill testing, cardiorespiratory fitness was inversely associated with all-cause mortality without an observed upper limit of benefit.
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let’s “unpack” that, as they say.</p>
<p>The researchers spent about 23 years measuring the cardiorespiratory fitness of just over 122 thousand subjects as they were running on a treadmill.</p>
<p>Measuring that many people gives your conclusions quite some statistical power. Also, the treadmill doesn’t lie, as people will often do, inadvertently or not, when self-reporting their fitness level.</p>
<p>What’s also interesting to me is that they didn’t observe any upper limit to the positive effect of fitness. Every additional amount of cardiorespiratory fitness, up to crazy levels, correlated with longer life.</p>
<p>The upshot of all of this is that there’s really no excuse. That one most important thing we can do to live long and prosper is to exercise.</p>
<p>It’s what Spock would have wanted.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/bettys_gravel_running.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/bettys_gravel_running-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Running on a dirt road in Betty’s Bay. I love running on dirt roads, although on this particular morning I was already tired before I started. The tiredness unfortunately did not decrease. I think there might still have been some virus involved, or, more probably, just standard bad vacation habits involving craft beer in the evening."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Running on a dirt road in Betty’s Bay. I love running on dirt roads, although on this particular morning I was already tired before I started. The tiredness unfortunately did not decrease. I think there might still have been some virus involved, or, more probably, just standard bad vacation habits involving craft beer in the evening.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>