<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>evalueserve on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/evalueserve/</link><description>Recent content in evalueserve on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 09:20:26 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/evalueserve/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #100: Happy 2016!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/03/weekly-head-voices-100-happy-2016/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 09:20:26 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/03/weekly-head-voices-100-happy-2016/</guid><description> Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res.
I wish you a truly happy 2016, filled with learning and helping other people! Neil deGrasse Tyson, exemplary human, said it best:
For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And along the way, lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/table_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/table_mountain_view.jpg"
        
            alt="Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I wish you a truly happy 2016, filled with learning and helping other people! Neil deGrasse Tyson, exemplary human, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/qccer/i_am_neil_degrasse_tyson_ask_me_anything/c3wgffy">said it best</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And along the way, lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Time is fun when you&rsquo;re having flies! I can&rsquo;t believe that four months have flown by since <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/23/weekly-head-voices-99-no-lands/">the previous WHV</a>. Since then, quite a bunch has happened. Some highlights for me:</p>
<ul>
<li>I spent a week in The Netherlands, my other home, taking part in a second hackathon with the Evalueserve peeps (the previous one was in Gurgaon in India). This was again loads of fun, and we managed to build a significant new shippable feature (measurable value!) almost from scratch.</li>
<li>In October, I went back to The Netherlands (it&rsquo;s my other home, remember) for 2.5 days to take part in the Doctorification of <a href="http://francoismalan.com/">a friend</a>. Besides the doctorification process (I&rsquo;ve been out of academia for a while, so my terminology might not be 100%) which went swimmingly, I had so many high-intensity interactions with some of my favourite people that I literally almost missed my flight back. Just picture me waking up in Delft at 8:30 with a flight leaving from Amsterdam at 10:00…</li>
<li>For a work project,  I started programming in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swift_(programming_language)">Apple&rsquo;s Swift</a>. As compiled high-performance languages go, this one has a number of modern language features which make it a truly interesting addition to one&rsquo;s programming toolbox.</li>
<li>Further on the nerd-front, I&rsquo;m trying to get more of us to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">use Signal instead of WhatsApp</a> whenever possible.</li>
<li>We spent so many weekends and the Christmas vacation doing fun outdoorsy stuff (living at the southern tip of Africa has serious perks), not least of which was a trip up Table Mountain for the first time in 15 years. See the photo up top for an impression.</li>
</ul>
<p>I have some fun changes in mind for this blog in 2016, but you&rsquo;re going to have to stick around to find out what they are, so… see you later peeps!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>