<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Gou-2 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-2/</link><description>Recent content in Gou-2 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #261: Father's day</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</guid><description>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.
Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive
The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.
&amp;ndash; Marcel Proust
Bliss It&amp;rsquo;s father&amp;rsquo;s day today.
When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250428_clarence_pano.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_9407df7811cef8cf.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_4f5b997776ce1c56.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_72fa3b251facc47.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp"
            

        
            alt="Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<blockquote>
<p>The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.</p>
<p>&ndash; Marcel Proust</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="bliss">Bliss</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s father&rsquo;s day today.</p>
<p>When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</p>
<p>Hearing that we were up, GOU #2 came out of her room, with a beautiful illustration she had made for (and of!) me. (GOU #2 has found her passion in drawing. She practises on most days, and her skill and talent are very obvious.)</p>
<p>Soon after, GOU #1 arrived home with flat whites (my favourite), fresh ciabatta and croissants from the bakery, and hugs.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m trying to say here is that when your offspring units all tell you in their different ways that they appreciate you being their dad, when you&rsquo;re fundamentally dedicated to and deeply grateful for being just that, and those very offspring units constitute the whole focus of this important life endeavour, you better hope that you are able to keep those eyes dry.</p>
<h2 id="vo-max-redux">VO₂ Max redux</h2>
<p>One of my <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">exercise goals for 2024</a> was to reach a VO₂ Max of at least (HAHAHA) 50.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t make it in 2024, but I also didn&rsquo;t do anything other than just my normal running during the year. I know that I should probably engage in some high intensity interval training of some sort if I really want to move the needle, but I run because I like running and not because I want to be fit, although I do want to be fit. (It&rsquo;s complicated being a teenager.)</p>
<p>At the start of 2025, I stated, much more softly this time, that I would maybe <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">still like to hit that 50 VO₂ Max</a>.</p>
<p>Again I realized I would have probably have to <em>do</em> something interval-ly about it, but again I kept on postponing.</p>
<p>WELL KIDS it turns out that postponing can also be a winning strategy! On Monday, May 19, my Garmin reported that I had indeed hit a VO₂ Max of 50, which, <a href="https://www8.garmin.com/manuals/webhelp/GUID-C001C335-A8EC-4A41-AB0E-BAC434259F92/EN-US/GUID-1FBCCD9E-19E1-4E4C-BD60-1793B5B97EB3.html">according to its tables</a>, places me at the bottom of the coveted top-most category for my age and gender, namely <em>Superior</em>.</p>
<p>I always knew it, but thanks anyways Garmin!</p>
<p>P.S. I do have to deflate my <em>superiority</em> a bit by reminding us all that, in addition to finding myself at the bottom of the superior range, I have also only recently entered my current age section, giving me an extra advantage. Jokes aside, 50 at 50 is not bad, so allow me to bask for a while.</p>
<h2 id="org-mode-timestamps-in-obsidian">org-mode timestamps in obsidian</h2>
<p>One feature I have really been missing in Obsidian since <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my recent break-up with Org-mode</a> is the amazing org timestamps.</p>
<p>There is no real convention in Obsidian, whilst in Org-mode timestamps <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Timestamps.html">are well-defined and quite functional</a>. My &ldquo;old&rdquo; notes are scattered with them: time ranges, scheduled times, deadlines, random timestamps inside random text notes.</p>
<p>The time logging script <a href="/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/#loggin-time">I mentioned previously</a> made use of the dataview-convention of adding timestamps to work items for example:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 (start:: 2025-05-20T07:55) - (end:: 2025-05-20T08:10)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; which did work but was no fun to work with.</p>
<p>Long story short, I could not resist for much longer, and so I hacked together a new Obsidian plugin called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian-org-timestamps">Org timestamps</a>.</p>
<p>As you can see in the comparative screenshots below, I&rsquo;ve copied the org-mode timestamp and time range format verbatim, with the additional bonus of rendering these timestamps nicely in preview mode, inspired by <a href="https://github.com/minad/org-modern">the Emacs package org-modern</a>.</p>
<p>Deviating from org-mode proper, my plugin also renders date-less timestamps &ndash; I often use these when adding entries to daily file. Speaking of which, full org timestamps can have <code>[[...]]</code> links around the date parts so that they link back to the relevant daily file.</p>








    


<figure><a href="obsidian-org-timestamps.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_e1ef46eb4edabd57.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_2719acebe5e07bc9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_f52dbf2785777e5.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>In addition to the rendering, the plugin also offers commands to move any timestamps to the nearest 5 minutes forward or backward, similar to what org-mode does with <code>shift-up/down</code>, and a feature I have always used multiple times per day.</p>
<p>Putting all of this together, my monthly time logging files now has entries that look like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 &lt;2025-05-20 07:55-08:10&gt;
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; and I can tweak those timestamps with the adjustment commands.</p>
<p>I have adapted the logging script to support both the old dataview-style and org-timestamp-style timestamps, and now the barely usable UX has become a tad less barely.</p>
<p><em>(10 minutes later&hellip;)</em></p>
<p>Because I keep on mentioning the script, I guess it&rsquo;s time to <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian_dataview_timelogging">put it online</a>, albeit extremely barely. Let me know in the comments below if you are the one other user on the planet who would like to try this.</p>
<h2 id="my-friend-this-is-the-end-again">My friend this is the end again</h2>
<p>This was one of the most stubborn WHVs I have pushed out in a very long time.</p>
<p>Before it became this hard, it used to be easier: Somehow there was always something to talk about, either interesting or entertaining, or both.</p>
<p>Although this could also just be another symptom of  me getting older, it does feel like the whole online landscape has changed quite substantially.</p>
<p>Up until recently, it was only dopamine-targeting social media which affected the way people read (or don&rsquo;t) blog posts, but these days I imagine that I&rsquo;m also detecting a whiff of AI-nihilism. Although I still feel strongly about writing each of these words by myself, the experience of the resultant output happens on the background of machines that can now generate hundreds of perfectly-written versions of this post in an instant.</p>
<p>Anyways, I plan to continue with this labour of love, even as it becomes increasingly difficult.</p>
<p>P.S. My recent reading / book-listening has taken me on fascinating journeys through neuroscience and consciousness. Before reaching this point right here, I mistakenly thought that I would share more about them in this post. Instead I&rsquo;m going to leave you with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I am not a thing in the world; I am the space in which the world is happening.</p>
<p>&ndash; Richard Lang</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2024 to 2025 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to the year 2025!
We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this traditional yearly transition blog post here to keep you busy in the meantime.
The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2025!</p>
<p>We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this <a href="/tags/transition">traditional yearly transition blog post</a> here to keep you busy in the meantime.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20241228-st-francis-light-house.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a7c8fad0a4fb3336.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_c471bba5b301f4e3.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_7e36ecc6dd88d868.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp"
            

        
            alt="The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For those of you who are new here, 1) welcome! and 2) the traditional yearly transition post is where I both ramble semi-coherently on about the year that is closest to its conclusion and also speculate a bit about the year that is closest to its inception.</p>
<p>The main audience for this post is me &ndash; writing this up and the concomitant thinking and formulating bits form an important part of my maintenance process &ndash; but to anyone else who is reading this, there is hopefully something of value (or just a bit of entertainment) for you in these words. In any case, I am super happy that you&rsquo;re here!</p>
<h2 id="life-events">Life events</h2>
<p>In 2024, <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#i-turned-50">I turned 50</a> while <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#gou-1-turned-18">GOU#1 turned 18</a>, finished high school and is now on her way to university.</p>
<p>I mention these two in the same breath, because looking back it feels like the 5 years of her high school, a substantial chunk of time in terms of her development, went by in a flash.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s almost like we blinked <a href="/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">when she was still our little girl going to high school</a> and now suddenly she is an adult, and we finally feel like actual adults (aka old people) ourselves.</p>
<p>Although these have been amazing years for us, this experience of a whole period of life flashing by, through the lense of our children&rsquo;s development into adults, is a stark reminder to strive even harder to experience the living daylights out of every single moment that we are blessed with.</p>
<p>If all goes according to plan, we will have two more blink-blink-another-high-school-journey-is-complete experiences (GOU#2 is now in her second year of that journey, GOU#3 has a few years to go before she can start) so we should probably try to blink far less often.</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>After the dip both this blog and I went through in 2023 (total of 3 WHV posts&hellip;) and a very slow blogging start in 2024, it does feel like I might slowly be getting my WHV groove back, which seems to be evidenced by 66% more WHV posting in 2024, i.e. a whole 5 WHV posts! (Contrast this with the historic average of one post every two weeks.)</p>
<p>In the introduction to <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/">WHV #255 You lift me up</a> I speculate a bit about the reasons for my hiatus (I didn&rsquo;t mention there that maybe 2023 was actually just a real downer for me) and the current potential revival.</p>
<p>In addition to the posts here, I published <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">12 technical posts over on at the vxlabs</a> and a whole bunch of short howtos / recipes in the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">brand new TiL section of my other-OTHER website</a>. WHV #255 <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">explains the motivation behind the TiL section</a>.</p>
<p>I am also quite happy about the fact that I wrote a daily entry in my private diary for a large part of 2024, and this is something that I would like to continue, hopefully for an even larger part of 2025.</p>
<p>Spending some time every day to review that day, where the review is enriched by the deliberate activitity of trying to formulate everything into a story that I can write down, helps me to make sense of everything.</p>
<p>Writing in general seems to modulate positively my experience of reality.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a lot about this idea in various posts on this blog, but allow me to surface <a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#the-describers">two relevant sections from WHV 180</a>, and especially the quote below (but you should go read those two sections):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less faulty entity.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>My secret running goal for 2024 was to do 25km of running every week. In my head this was auto-simplified to 1200km for the year (you know, the way one often calculates a month as 4 weeks), but of course we&rsquo;re talking 1300km.</p>
<p>Well, I failed at all of these goals!</p>
<p>However, I did manage to run a total of 1149.7km over the year, which comes to an average of 22.1km per week, which I am pretty OK with. I had over 100 hours of fun (I truly enjoy running) and no injuries that I can remember.</p>
<p>The training calendar below shows that August was my laziest month, but that&rsquo;s because August has the worst weather, and because I was away for a week visiting my Dutch family and getting many tens of thousands of dancing steps instead. The calendar also shows how I made a last ditch effort in December to close the gap with my goal as much as possible.</p>










<figure><a href="20250101-strava-training-calendar.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_e13adc1c4101c63a.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_2caa5fcc1a219359.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_57229ed99a10234e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You might remember <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">my three metrics-focused goals from last year&rsquo;s post</a>, namely 50 consecutive push-ups, VO<sub>2</sub> Max of at least 50 and a resting state heart rate of 50 or under&hellip;</p>
<p>Well, 50 consecutive push-ups was not that hard, Apple Health reports my average resting state heart rate for 2024 as 48 BPM (this would be mostly via my Garmin Forerunner 245 and more recently 265) but my VO<sub>2</sub> briefly peaked at 49 (some time after I turned 50) before settling back on 48. I  would have loved that 50, but <a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/blog/fitness/whats-a-good-vo2-max-for-me/">48 is not the worst for a man of my age</a>.</p>
<p>My real goal for the coming year is the same as last year: I want to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>The older I get and the more I learn, the more I understand that with exercise, the more hours I can spend every week doing it, of course maintaining balance with the rest of my life (see life systems further down), the better my meat-coated skeleton will work, and the happier the ghost driving it will be.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’re a ghost driving a meat-coated skeleton made from stardust; what do you have to be scared of?</p>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2022/10/13/ghost-stardust/">@rat_sandwich on twitter, January 31, 2013</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>P.S. of course I will again go for 25km of running per week. I think logging substantially more than 120 hours of activities in Strava will be good. I might even give that VO<sub>2</sub> Max goal another shot.</p>
<p>P.P.S. I read <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/outlive/">Peter Attia&rsquo;s book Outlive</a> a few months ago. This is a detailed and practical manual for healthy living. There&rsquo;s a lot in there, but at the core he wants you, while you still have any say in the matter, to become as fit (measured by our friend VO<sub>2</sub> Max) and as strong (measured by grip strength) as you possibly can. You see, from middle age we&rsquo;re all on a downward curve, and there&rsquo;s not much we can do about it, except ensuring that we start as high as possible.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. It&rsquo;s funny; back in school, I thought little of athleticism, because it was a jock thing, and the jocks were generally not very kind to nerd-kind (my people). Now that I&rsquo;m older and quite ironically due to my nerdy lifelong learning habits, I strive for us much athleticism as I can &ldquo;fit&rdquo; in (jock joke harr harr).</p>
<h3 id="diet">Diet</h3>
<p>During this post&rsquo;s generously long incubation, I thought it worth adding here my approach to eating.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been practising 16-8 time-restricted eating (intermittent fasting in some circles) about 95% of the time since somewhere in 2019. I first <a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">wrote about it in WHV 186</a>, and then in <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#i-really-don-t-like-breakfast">WHV 221 I came out and stated the beef I have with breakfast</a> (that pun might be too heavy for this post).</p>
<p>Anyways, while I still believe that breakfast is bad for most people, I know that the scientific world has not yet reached consensus on time-restricted eating for healthy folks.</p>
<p>However, there is considerably more consensus that lowering daily caloric intake is good for most people.</p>
<p>For me, 16-8 TRE, where I simply don&rsquo;t ingest anything besides water and black coffee from about 7 in the evening until about noon the next day, is an extremely practical and especially low-effort way to reduce caloric intake.</p>
<p>When I do eat, the portions are modest, I try to stick to natural and unprocessed where I can and I keep an eye on protein.</p>
<p>When I do break these rules, I do so with deliberation. Great food, great wine, great beer and the company of friends and family, especially when combined, constitute a perfect reason to break all of these rules.</p>
<p>In short, reduce caloric intake, increase per-calorie value and/or enjoyment!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and Tools</h2>
<p>This is the place where I summarise (read: ramble on about) the current state of my digital tools and systems. If you&rsquo;re going to skip a (nerdy) section, this is the one! You can dive back in at <a href="#life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</a>.</p>
<p>I am one of those people who <em>regularly</em> finds and uses information from notes that I made.</p>
<p>If I have the note, and I often do because I make an effort to write stuff down with the lowest possible friction but the highest possible chance of being found again, this is generally miles faster than finding the information online, even with tools like the <a href="https://kagi.com/">premium search engine Kagi</a> which I have been using regularly for a few weeks now.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-and-obsidian">Emacs and Obsidian</h3>
<p>A year ago I <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#systems-and-tools">experienced a bit of a crisis of (Emacs) faith</a>.</p>
<p>Whilst that was more of a clash between the either-or poles of Emacs and Obsidian, I am now at a place where I&rsquo;m finding increasing uses for Obisidian as an <em>additional</em> note-taking tool, working on the same collection of hundreds of org-mode and a growing number of markdown files.</p>
<p>Emacs and org-roam treat <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">markdown files as if they are native org-roam nodes</a>. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/BBazard/obsidian-orgmode-cm6">Benoit Bazard&rsquo;s fantastic new CodeMirror 6 org-mode plugin for Obsidian</a> and my <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Monitor-rclone-cron-job-with-Home-Assistant">rclone + syncthing syncing setup for iPhone</a>, I have semi-usable org database support on my phone.</p>
<p><a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> and since recently <a href="https://orgro.org/">Orgro</a> are great for editing org files in the iPhone, but they are missing the searching and discovery, let&rsquo;s call it <em>note management</em>, aspects of a tool like Obsidian.</p>
<p>Long but quite important-to-me story short, it looks like for the time being I&rsquo;ll continue to use both Emacs and Obsidian for note-taking. Because interoperability is not perfect, there will be some natural gravitational pull towards the one or the other which I have decided to explore.</p>
<p>At the moment, it looks like I might be writing more of my atomic notes as markdown files, whilst using org for the lab journal / logbook and project management type of notes.</p>
<p>On a deeper note, the Obsidian team is doing fantastic work.</p>
<p>Apart from their <a href="https://stephango.com/file-over-app"><em>file over app</em> philosophy</a>, Obsidian is <em>programmable</em> as can be witnessed by the thriving extension ecosystem.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?id=ai-chat-as-md">written a modest extension</a> to test this out from the inside. The programmability is not as extensive as that of Emacs, but it runs everywhere, even on mobile devices, and it might be extensive enough for the note-taking platform that Obsidian has become.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Emacs on and off since the late 90s, but for the past 10 years it has become an always-running and integral part of my life. It feels really strange, disconcerting if I&rsquo;m being honest, that it seems to be losing its core spot.</p>
<p>I console myself in these moments with the observation that science must trump dogma, always.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m writing this post in Emacs.</p>
<h4 id="til">TiL</h4>
<p>Thanks to Obsidian, my other, OTHER website <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">now has a &ldquo;today I learned&rdquo; (TIL) section</a> at <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">charlbotha.com/til</a>, published directly from a sub-directory of my main notes directory.</p>
<p>The benefit is that there is even less friction than usual and, perhaps more importantly, the psychological friction has also been reduced because I have convinced myself that the posts there are just notes and not true blog posts.</p>
<h3 id="honorable-tool-mentions-zotero-and-quarto">Honorable tool mentions: Zotero and Quarto</h3>
<p>After <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#omnivore-is-no-more">my distastrous recommendation of Omnivore turned into a disaster</a>, it is with some emotional trepidation but intellectual confidence (thanks to file over app and its staunchly open source nature) that I can re-recommend Zotero as a reference (of all kinds!) management tool for the long term.</p>
<p>After I last mentioned it on my blog, I have been using it quite intensively, and <a href="https://bsky.app/hashtag/zotero?author=charlbotha.com">I keep on running into delightful features</a>, like the built-in PDF reader&rsquo;s pop-up visualization of citations and image references.</p>
<p>A more recent but high power entry into my toolbelt is <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, which I will contend strikes a fantastic usability-power balance in the world of technical document and presentation authoring. I&rsquo;ve now used it, in anger, to write a fairly extensive technical document, along with the afore-mentioned Zotero and <a href="https://retorque.re/zotero-better-bibtex/">Better BibTeX</a> for reference management, and the experience was magically smooth. To seal the deal, by the end I used Quarto to generate an attractive-looking docx for interoperability with the other stakeholders, but my contact time with Word was mercifully minimised.</p>
<h3 id="my-micro-blogging-history-2008---2025">My micro-blogging history 2008 - 2025</h3>
<p>Twitter says I created my account there in December of 2008. However, <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">this blog here says I only started using it in April of 2009</a>. (Twitter first launched in July of 2006.)</p>
<p>Some years later in 2016, coincidentally right before the previous Trumpocalypse, I wrote a post naively suggesting that we should <a href="/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/">replace twitter with something better (blogs&hellip;)</a> due to the risk of Twitter possibly going bad (ahem) and to the observation then that it was (then already) doing a crappy job keeping out abusive users (AHEM).</p>
<p>That post <a href="/2016/11/20/look-mom-hacker-news-front-page/">reached the front page of Hacker News</a>, and was thus read and discussed over there (and probably in the comments here) by tens of thousands of nerds, and a surprisingly small share of the usual &ldquo;Ackchyually&rdquo;-Bros.</p>
<p>(Please allow me this little tangent: A mental model that will really ease your time on sites like HN and reddit, is that the person on the other side, especially when they come across as super confident and assertive, is probably <strong>not</strong> an expert, not even by a long shot, on the topic that they are so confidently mansplaining. In fact, they are probably the least qualified to say anything. ChatGPT avant le lettre one might say. Ok back to your regular programming&hellip;)</p>
<p>Needless to say, my specific idea of replacing twitter with&hellip; blogs and rss was not implemented by the internet, at least not at that point&hellip;</p>
<p>When Musk acquired Twitter in October of 2022, the writing started appearing on the wall, at first vaguely, but with more and more definition as the months went on. I started looking for micro-blogging alternatives that were not twitter.</p>
<p>At first Mastodon looked too complicated, but then someone setup a <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#emacs-mastodon-server-was-irresistible">mastodon server dedicated to Emacs and I was immediately sold</a>.</p>
<p>However, Mastodon indeed turned out to be too complex and fundamentally quite fragile (all but the larger instances have a just a volunteer human or two behind them), leading to the owner of my favourite instance bascially being harassed to such an extent that it was better for him to get out of this business and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@cpbotha/113340325817581254">shut the Emacs mastodon server down</a>.</p>
<p>When I saw this announcement, I was disheartened.</p>
<p>When I read that Mastodon supports message export, but not message import, meaning that my posts would languish in a sad archive file somewhere, I was convinced that I had to try something out that was not Mastodon.</p>
<p>In parallel to my Mastodon efforts, I did also try Threads and was quite enthusiastic about its scale, and the speed with which Meta managed to build it, but I didn&rsquo;t manage to get any sort of interaction there. I think that it might be more geared for the Instagram model of influencers broadcasting to large groups of followers, in contrast to a more collaborative setup. (Urgh, the recent news about Meta&rsquo;s new &ldquo;free speech&rdquo; overhaul is additional motivation for me to spend even less energy there.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, it turns out that the newer and shinier microblogging service Bluesky was conceived in 2019 with the goal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluesky">&ldquo;to find or develop an open and decentralized standard for social media that would give users more control over their data and experience&rdquo;</a>, precisely the sort of thing that has suddenly become even more painfully relevant with the advent of the Trumpocalypse part deux, now with more Musk-power.</p>
<p>Long story short, in a very short time, Bluesky has proven to be almost exactly the microblogging platform that I enjoy participating in. Lots of human interaction, no ads, many different user-contributed algorithms to choose from, including just seeing the stuff your people post, in the order that they post it &ndash; it really feels like the thing was put together with semi-normal human interaction as the central concern.</p>
<p>Up to now, it also feels like <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#bluesky-is-my-new-micro-blogging-thing-of-choice">many folks on there prefer being decent to each other</a>, something I militantly (haha) support.</p>
<p>Some mastodon folks are downright unhappy with bluesky, because they feel that it&rsquo;s not truly decentralized like mastodon.</p>
<p>Thing is, Bluesky has chosen a different spot on the usability - decentralization spectrum, and and my opinion is exactly usable and decentralised enough for what it needs to be and do at this moment in time.</p>
<p>Looking slightly further into the future, there are well-funded initiatives like <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/13/24342799/free-our-feeds-social-media-ecosystem-at-protocol-bluesky">Free our feeds</a>, ideologically and technologically supported by the Bluesky company but otherwise unconnected, which has amongst its <a href="https://freeourfeeds.com/">goals to &ldquo;build independently hosted infrastructure (a second &lsquo;relay&rsquo;) so that Bluesky users, developers and researchers always have full access to the stream of content and data no matter what the company decides to do in future&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>If you would like to know more, Faine Greenwood has written <a href="https://little-flying-robots.ghost.io/the-great-bluesky-migration-i-answer-some-of-your-questions/">this great Bluesky explainer</a>.</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</h2>
<p>My Life Systems are the guiding principles, rules, personal values and bags of tips that I have explicitly defined and refined over the years to help me be the best human that I can be.</p>
<p>Note: I write these up primarily as a reminder to myself. If it comes across as prescriptive, please remember that I&rsquo;m telling <em>me</em> how to live my life. I can do this, because I <em>am</em> the boss of me.</p>
<h3 id="core">Core</h3>
<p>You&rsquo;ll be happy to hear that the core of my Life Systems 2025 is exactly the same as the previous edition <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">Life Systems 2024</a>, except for the version number increase, and the concomitant price increase. (taking a leaf here from the Intel playbook!)</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to read <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">the 2024 write-up</a>, here is the compressed version:</p>
<p><em>Guiding principles:</em> 1. Love 2. Science. <em>Two no three rules for achieving great success in life, or just surviving, whichever comes first:</em> 1. Be useful. 2. be likable and 3. evolve. <em>Personal values:</em> 1. Be kind. 2. Be grateful. 3. Attend fully to the now. 4. Enjoy life with family and with my friends. 5. Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers. 6. Be there for my family. 7. Add value through work. 8. Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise. 9. Build and/or fix something. 10. Learn new things. 11. Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</p>
<h3 id="balance">Balance</h3>
<p>What I have been thinking about this year, especially when things get quite busy, is the sometimes tricky practice of applying balance to one&rsquo;s personal values.</p>
<p>A straight-forward example is when important work obligations start impacting my sleep or exercise schedule, in which case I have to apply balance and tone down slightly the ambition to fulfil personal value no 7.</p>
<p>It can easily get more tricky however; when something on that list of personal values, which is important to you, starts taking up more than its fair share of energy, that will come at the cost of all of the other endeavours that you value.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have a hard and fast rule for this, only the measure of remembering to <em>pay attention</em> also at that meta-level so that one can make suitable balancing adjustments when required.</p>
<h3 id="work-hard-party-hard-rest-hard">Work hard. Party hard. Rest hard.</h3>
<p>A lesson that has only become clearer for me over the years is that we humans function best when we are able to focus on one thing at a time, and when we have as few things as possible on the list that we select from.</p>
<p>This works at all scales of life, from what task do I work on during this half-hour all the way up to my main priority for today, or my three main priorities for this year.</p>
<p>The challenge in applying this lesson is three-fold:</p>
<ol>
<li>Know which thing to focus on at any time,</li>
<li>reduce switching between things and yet</li>
<li>get to all of the things that you should get to.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you have all three of these covered, then comes the truly difficult part: <strong>Attend fully to the now.</strong></p>
<p>Those of us who are lucky get about 4000 weeks of life.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not truly present in the thing that you&rsquo;ve chosen at this moment, you are not using that allotted time to its fullest extent.</p>
<p>You can never ever get that time back.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like you&rsquo;re in a Michelin-starred restaurant, and instead of going power level 9000 with all of your senses and your thoughts and your whole being into <em>experiencing</em> that food with your favourite human(s), you&rsquo;re scrolling on your phone, absent-mindedly shovelling forkfuls into your mouth.</p>
<p>Do the opposite.</p>
<p>Pick your battles, but sometimes also choose a party if you can and don&rsquo;t forget to rest like your life depends on it. Whatever you do, be the most maximally present in the thing you&rsquo;ve chosen. Presence and attention improve with regular practice.</p>
<p>In short: Work hard, party hard, rest hard.</p>
<!-- be maximally present to use that time right; do everything HARD -- came during my 2025-01-11 morning run -->
<h2 id="my-2024-to-2025-transition-wishes">My 2024 to 2025 transition wishes</h2>
<p>Humans<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> <em>at their peak</em> are a thing of beauty.</p>
<p>Above all they are truly kind.  They live and breathe the knowledge that we <em>homo sapiens</em> are at our absolute best when we connect with each other.</p>
<p>Peak humans are graceful, and they are elegant, and they are in harmony &ndash; the best sort of balance &ndash; with their surroundings, with those around them and with themselves.</p>
<p>Attaining this peak is hard. Maintaining it is nigh impossible. Best we can go for is <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">the never-ending practice</a> of these characteristics, and an eternal striving for moments to <em>become them</em>.</p>
<p>Friends, I wish you and your connected ones the willpower to strive for grace and elegance and harmony, and the presence of mind to attend fully to those perfect moments when they occur.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, you might be one of these&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 4 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-22 As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&amp;rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS! At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&amp;hellip; Short but really nice streamlit demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually played with it. Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3. In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola. Tuesday 2024-01-23 At the office nice and early (7:30). Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at react-flow and comfyui react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY! streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &amp;ldquo;things I learned&amp;rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document. Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&amp;rsquo;s a zero day vulnerability in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites. Wednesday 2024-01-24 8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW! Remember kids: Our spine&amp;rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally. This is also the reason why I&amp;rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair. Lovely working lunch with friend S at No Way José Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work: idea: make github so that people can pipx install marimo-turbo to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on. idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS &amp;hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844 (post is also embedded below) idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&amp;gt; nginx -&amp;gt; supervisord -&amp;gt; tornado systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation I would prefer to use supervisord for this This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick? ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &amp;ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&amp;rdquo; googling blog post: https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/ the kubernetes thing: https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&amp;rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via iframe.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-22">Monday 2024-01-22</h2>
<ul>
<li>As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &ldquo;When you&rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS!</li>
<li>At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&hellip;</li>
<li>Short but really nice <a href="https://streamlit.io/">streamlit</a> demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&rsquo;ve never actually played with it.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3.
<ul>
<li>In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-23">Tuesday 2024-01-23</h2>
<ul>
<li>At the office nice and early (7:30).</li>
<li>Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at <a href="https://reactflow.dev/">react-flow</a> and comfyui
<ul>
<li>react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see <a href="https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary">https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary</a>
<ul>
<li>it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster</li>
<li>marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &ldquo;things I learned&rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document.</li>
<li>Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&rsquo;s a <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/news/apple-issues-urgent-security-updates-to-fix-zero-day-flaw-update-your-iphone-and-mac-right-now">zero day vulnerability</a> in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-24">Wednesday 2024-01-24</h2>
<ul>
<li>8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot</li>
<li>dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work</li>
<li>right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW!
<ul>
<li>Remember kids: Our spine&rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally.</li>
<li>This is also the reason why I&rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lovely working lunch with friend S at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/NoWayJoseSomerset">No Way José</a></li>
<li>Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work:
<ul>
<li>idea: make github so that people can <code>pipx install marimo-turbo</code> to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on.</li>
<li>idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap
<ul>
<li>sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets</li>
<li>in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS
<ul>
<li>&hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844</a> (post is also embedded below)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&gt; nginx -&gt; supervisord -&gt; tornado
<ul>
<li>systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: <a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation">https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation</a></li>
<li>I would prefer to use supervisord for this</li>
<li>This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&rdquo; googling
<ul>
<li>blog post: <a href="https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/">https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/</a></li>
<li>the kubernetes thing: <a href="https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s">https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0" width="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><script src="https://emacs.ch/embed.js" async="async"></script>
<h3 id="til-mastodon-embeds-are-not-as-durable-as-twitter-embeds">TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds</h3>
<p>As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via <code>iframe</code>.</p>
<p>With twitter, you get more self-contained HTML which will render even when twitter or just the original tweet don&rsquo;t exist anymore.</p>
<p>This is probably just another reason to figure out how I can get more low-friction microblogging going on my own websites so that the embedding implementations of other microblogging sites become irrelevant.</p>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-25">Thursday 2024-01-25</h2>
<ul>
<li>Took a look at <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/connections/connect-networks/get-started/">cloudflare tunnels</a> to expose marimo and other dashboards to the internet
<ul>
<li>great that I can use my existing domains for this, and I can route between multiple domains to multiple locally running services</li>
<li>some more steps to setup, but it did not take more than about 5 minutes, and gives me even more options than tailscale funnels. OPTIONS MAN!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At work, quickly got react-flow&hellip; flowing. SHINY!</li>
<li>In the evening, found <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/">https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/</a> which is the new Shortcuts based way, based on the old AppleScript way, of getting a <code>message://</code> link onto the clipboard.
<ul>
<li>You <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#email-linking">might recall from this blog</a> that <code>message://</code> are the most durable and cross-platform way to link to emails from your notes (or anywhere else)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-26">Friday 2024-01-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up to cool, overcast weather, a big change from a series of 30℃ + days. Really had to resist going out for a run (normal run day + that amazing coolness), because of Wednesday&rsquo;s partially pulled back muscle not being 100% yet.</li>
<li>Worked on mystery visualization project (react-flow)</li>
<li>Lovely and energising lunch with previous colleague and friend. Happy that I reached out on Thursday although they have a packed schedule because only in country for limited time. I guess this is quite related to <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">calling up your friends</a>, with a ping of serendipity salt.</li>
<li>I was shocked by how well and fast <a href="https://ollama.ai/">ollama</a> worked on my MacBook. See embedded tweet below.</li>
<li>Almost at the end of the afternoon, friend S and I went to some more friends for the first Weiss-off, that is, a Weiss beer tasting contest. It was huge fun blind-tasting 10 different Weiss beers, ranking them, trying to identify them (so much harder than I thought!), and then having them revealed at the end.
<ul>
<li>Between the experts there (read: us), Stangen Weiss Bier came out on top, followed by Weisbier No5 and Jack Black Atlantic Weiss. The fourth place was shared by Erdinger and CBC Amber Weiss.</li>
<li>My favourite, Stellenbrau Jonkersweiss, is glaringly absent from the top. I&rsquo;ll live, probably consoled by just such a Jonkersweiss. Super happy that Amber Weiss and Atlantic are both present!</li>
<li>There was a trophy (for the taster who could blind-identify the most beers in the Weiss-off), which we have christened the <em>David Weisselhoff wisseltrofee</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">With <a href="https://twitter.com/MistralAI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@MistralAI</a>&#39;s Mistral 7B at Q4_0 on this MacBook M1 Pro 10C / 16C, <a href="https://twitter.com/ollama?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ollama</a> looks like it&#39;s easily 3 times faster than the new MLX 0.0.11 (with GGUF support).<br><br>It&#39;s subjectively (visually) faster, and the tokens/s measurements confirm this. <a href="https://t.co/9vyluimLKK">pic.twitter.com/9vyluimLKK</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1750824125419942036?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 26, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-27">Saturday 2024-01-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yesterday&rsquo;s Wonderful Weiss-off also had some, thankfully quite minor, effect the next morning, but I went out for a careful weekday distance run, which fortunately went without a hitch. Just very hot thanks.</li>
<li>Went to Buco and then to <a href="https://appletoolandgas.com/">Apple Tool and Gas</a> to find the rest of the screws I needed to repair the shower door. Friendly gentleman at Apple even sawed some of my screws to size! Shower door back in operation.</li>
<li>Updated my &ldquo;old&rdquo; M1 MBA to macOS 14.3 and then reset to transfer to GOU#1&rsquo;s iCloud. Say what you want about Apple, but that part of their stuff works <em>really</em> well.</li>
<li>Left for Betty&rsquo;s Bay at about 16:00 with GOUs #1 and #2. The rest of the family already there.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-28">Sunday 2024-01-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up in Betty&rsquo;s Bay after a longer than normal night of sleep, but Garmin body battery was still not completely happy.</li>
<li>In spite of having run yesterday and still feeling a bit tired (see body battery above), I had the best run of the month so far in Betty&rsquo;s. Go figure.</li>
<li>Spent some time with Canva &ndash; what a great resource for doing nice designs, even flow charts &ndash; but not sure where I could use this.</li>
<li>Background thought through the past weeks, and mentioned on Tuesday: I would really like to do (and promite) more TIL-style writing at work and at home. See <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/">Simon Willison&rsquo;s amazing TIL collection</a> for inspiration.</li>
<li>Ran into <a href="https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines">https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines</a> a Python library that can guarantee structured text generation from many LLMs, e.g. 100% valid JSON according to a specified schema. What makes it different from similar libraries? &ldquo;Unlike other libraries, regex-guided generation in Outlines is almost as fast as non-guided generation.&rdquo;</li>
<li>I already had <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/autogen">AutoGen</a> on my list for experimenting with multi-agent LLM applications, but now it has been joined by <a href="https://github.com/joaomdmoura/crewAI">crewAI</a> which I have also just ran into (thanks reddit!) and which seems to have significant support online.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 3 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 20:21:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-15 Discovered that we (at work) now have access to GPT-4 Turbo via Azure OpenAI: 128K context and much cheaper than the old GPT-4. Will have to upgrade our private internal assistant, code name StoneGPT. Inspired by stefanv, carefully trying out weekly planning, but in a slight deviation I&amp;rsquo;m doing this in addition to my daily planning, which I only get around to a fraction of the time in any case. I think that this sort of multi-scalar examination and planning will help. Went to Bloemhof for the welcoming of the new grade 8 learners. Was really great to see GOU#1 and GOU#2 there, on two very opposite ends of the spectrum. Tuesday 2024-01-16 MS Copilot Pro ($20) has been announced, and also Copilot 365 is now available for businesses of all sizes (not just enterprises who can commit to 300 seats): https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/ Copilot Pro not yet available in South Africa 😥 $20 per month for integration with some Office apps (which could be useful, will have to see), priority access to latest models such as GPT-4 Turbo, and custom Copilots. I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced, will stick to my perplexity.ai for now. Copilot for 365 can be purchased per seat, but minimum 1 year commitment which is $360 per person per year. Ouch. In addition to many meetings (Tuesday = meetings day), did manage to spend some quality time with a new visualization project. Slowly starting to use webcola again, but this time with d3@latest &amp;ndash; sorta works, but no dragging. Have found work-around, still need to test. Went to bed really early, because must be up at 5:30 to help GOU#2 get ready for school and get to the bus stop on time. (Slept super badly thanks.) Wednesday 2024-01-17 Up at 5:30 after a pretty restless night. GOU#2 on the bus at 6 after some serious morning prep multi-tasking, GOU#3 (age 7) so organized and independent, ready to leave for school at 7! Nice and early(ish) slightly longer weekday run before work. My hip sent me a Teams message &amp;ldquo;Hi&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; at about 80% of the route somewhere, but fortunately no follow-up. Colleagues on chat, haha. Got caught up in GEKKO Optimization Suite due to meetings with colleagues about various simulations. My initial enthusiasm was somewhat dampened upon learning that behind the Python API lies an admittedly useful but quite black-box compiled binary called apm.exe. TIL: John Lasseter drew the BSD daemon! See https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html &amp;ndash; I remember that daemon from the time when I had FreeBSD on my machine at home instead of Linux (somewhere in the 90s). You might remember that name from the Creativity Inc. book (the one about Pixar!) notes post on this blog Thursday 2024-01-18 AlphaGeometry from Google DeepMind is great work combining a symbolic math engine with a language model to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. See below for my breathless tweet. (twitter is still the uncontested ML firehose) News on our in-house GPT-wrapper front: Discovered that I now have to upgrade to the new tool_call api as the old functions one has been deprecated. Made use of the opportunity to improve our implementation of the supplied OpenAI type annotations Note to self, and to you: The *Params types are TypedDict declarations which you can use to work directly with JSON requests and responses, while the non-*Params types are pydantic models which you can use to (de)serialize JSON. Went to see a really good Mohs surgery dermatologist who will soon be removing my basal cell carcinomas. As always, AMA in the comments or via email. This is such fantastic work! Symbolic engine + language model working together to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. Also, beautiful illustrations in the paper and posts. https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-15">Monday 2024-01-15</h2>
<ul>
<li>Discovered that we (at work) now have access to GPT-4 Turbo via Azure OpenAI: 128K context and much cheaper than the old GPT-4. Will have to upgrade our private internal assistant, code name StoneGPT.</li>
<li>Inspired by stefanv, carefully trying out weekly planning, but in a slight deviation I&rsquo;m doing this <em>in addition</em> to my daily planning, which I only get around to a fraction of the time in any case. I think that this sort of multi-scalar examination and planning will help.</li>
<li>Went to Bloemhof for the welcoming of the new grade 8 learners. Was really great to see GOU#1 <em>and</em> GOU#2 there, on two very opposite ends of the spectrum.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-16">Tuesday 2024-01-16</h2>
<ul>
<li>MS Copilot Pro ($20) has been announced, and also Copilot 365 is now available for businesses of all sizes (not just enterprises who can commit to 300 seats): <a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/">https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/</a>
<ul>
<li>Copilot Pro not yet available in South Africa 😥
<ul>
<li>$20 per month for integration with some Office apps (which could be useful, will have to see), priority access to latest models such as GPT-4 Turbo, and custom Copilots. I&rsquo;m not convinced, will stick to my <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/">perplexity.ai</a> for now.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Copilot for 365 can be purchased per seat, but minimum 1 year commitment which is $360 per person per year. Ouch.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In addition to many meetings (Tuesday = meetings day), did manage to spend some quality time with a new visualization project. Slowly starting to use <a href="https://ialab.it.monash.edu/webcola/">webcola</a> again, but this time with d3@latest &ndash; sorta works, but no dragging. Have found work-around, still need to test.</li>
<li>Went to bed really early, because must be up at 5:30 to help GOU#2 get ready for school and get to the bus stop on time. (Slept super badly thanks.)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-17">Wednesday 2024-01-17</h2>
<ul>
<li>Up at 5:30 after a pretty restless night. GOU#2 on the bus at 6 after some serious morning prep multi-tasking, GOU#3 (age 7) so organized and independent, ready to leave for school at 7!</li>
<li>Nice and early(ish) slightly longer weekday run before work. My hip sent me a Teams message &ldquo;Hi&hellip;&rdquo; at about 80% of the route somewhere, but fortunately no follow-up. Colleagues on chat, haha.</li>
<li>Got caught up in <a href="#d41d8c">GEKKO Optimization Suite</a> due to meetings with colleagues about various simulations. My initial enthusiasm was somewhat dampened upon learning that behind the Python API lies an admittedly useful but quite black-box compiled binary called apm.exe.</li>
<li>TIL: John Lasseter drew the BSD daemon! See <a href="https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html">https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html</a> &ndash; I remember that daemon from the time when I had FreeBSD on my machine at home instead of Linux (somewhere in the 90s). You might remember that name from the <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/#the-story-is-more-important-than-the-technology">Creativity Inc.</a> book (the one about Pixar!) notes post on this blog</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-18">Thursday 2024-01-18</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>AlphaGeometry from Google DeepMind is great work</strong> combining a symbolic math engine with a language model to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. See below for my breathless tweet. (twitter is still the uncontested ML firehose)</li>
<li>News on our in-house GPT-wrapper front:
<ul>
<li>Discovered that I now have to upgrade to the new <code>tool_call</code> api as the old <code>functions</code> one has been deprecated. Made use of the opportunity to improve our implementation of the supplied OpenAI type annotations</li>
<li>Note to self, and to you: The <code>*Params</code> types are <code>TypedDict</code> declarations which you can use to work directly with JSON requests and responses, while the non-<code>*Params</code> types are pydantic models which you can use to (de)serialize JSON.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Went to see a really good <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mohs-surgery/about/pac-20385222">Mohs surgery</a> dermatologist who will soon be removing my basal cell carcinomas. As always, AMA in the comments or via email.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is such fantastic work! Symbolic engine + language model working together to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. Also, beautiful illustrations in the paper and posts. <a href="https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7">https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1747857845356298739?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 18, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-19">Friday 2024-01-19</h2>
<ul>
<li>Spent most of my working hours wrappng up and deploying the brand new version of our internal GPT. I read somewhere that you should <em>always</em> deploy on a Friday, as late as possible.</li>
<li>I was stressing quite a bit, as I had a great task before me:</li>
<li>Braaiing 200 boeries in the 39 degrees Celsius heat at the school in Stellenbosch, in order to feed the new grade 8 learners on the evening of their initiation.
<ul>
<li>All thanks to the fellow dad who joined me, the stress transformed completely into an enjoyable few hours taking care of this important duty, and I made a new friend!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The kids, including our very own GOU#2, were facing the challenging night before them&hellip;</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-20">Saturday 2024-01-20</h2>
<ul>
<li>woke up at 5:40 because was planning to fetch GOU#1 and GOU#2 after their eventful and successful night, but thankfully partner was willing to go!</li>
<li>me very tired the whole day, just hanging (literally) around with family, and spending too much time on twitter / threads / reddit / inoreader! (brain was not willing to do much else, at least learned new things, some of which are mentioned below)</li>
<li>Based on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39055139">this HN discussion</a> about <a href="https://delta.io/blog/delta-lake-vs-parquet-comparison/">this blog post comparing Delta Lake and Parquet</a>, learned that Delta Parquet aka Delta Tables (which I&rsquo;ve read about in the context of Azure) is just a bunch of parquet files with some json metadata!
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve been enjoying <a href="https://parquet.apache.org/">parquet</a> for years now, in the context of scipy and specifically pandas.</li>
<li>Indeed, OneLake, also part of Microsoft Fabric, has Delta Parquet at its core.</li>
<li>Apache Iceberg is a similar but more open source implemenation: <a href="https://iceberg.apache.org/">https://iceberg.apache.org/</a></li>
<li>Based on <a href="https://www.dremio.com/blog/exploring-the-architecture-of-apache-iceberg-delta-lake-and-apache-hudi/">this comparison between Iceberg, Delta Lake and Hudi</a> it looks like all of these data lake storage layers are just parquet files with metadata, and then some logic, to give database like semantics over distributed object stores. Neat!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In bed last night, falling asleep, I had the following idea:
<ul>
<li><em>My Current Life Canvas</em> is a 3D bubble (off to my right for some reason&hellip; and moving with me as I walk) the interior of which I can view using my phone via AR (have to move phone in space to view inside of bubble, with current topics arranged in familiar spots; I thought having a world map would help, because well-known and memorable locations for your topics / priorities / ideas) or any of these amazing new VR headsets, BUT you can also interact with it via computer because inside of bubble can just be projected to surface using any of the well-known <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Map_projection">map projection techniques</a>.</li>
<li>CLC does not have a regular cadence like the daily or weekly plan, but is revised or redone a few times per year. It focuses on your major life priorities at any one point in time.</li>
<li>Although this was just a dreamy idea, I do like that it offers multi-modal interaction on the spectrum from AR/VR to more conventional desktop paradigms</li>
<li>&hellip; of course there should be some kind of friendly AI floating in the bubble with you :P (Microsoft Bob?)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-21">Sunday 2024-01-21</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super enjoyable weekend long(ish) run.</li>
<li>Tried out Omnivore&rsquo;s PDF annotation support, see screenshot below. Pretty impressive, and very cool that the highlights sync into my Emacs-based notes setup via markdown. Have slightly mixed feelings, because now will have to come up with new rule for when a paper goes into Zotero (fully local, full citations, but no automatic highlights sync) and when it goes into Omnivore (good sort of cloud but not local, no full citations, automatic sync into my notes)</li>
<li>Extended family Sunday lunch at our place was great, but me not at normal energy levels yet.</li>
<li>One of my goals for this week was &ldquo;Get through the week, especially Friday braai&rdquo;. Mission successful!</li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_8552fa2e79f0c31.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_d562277b8133fec1.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_70c21750f4c22771.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_3fd7290a1dd605.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_d562277b8133fec1.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Sunday 2024-01-07</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:48:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</guid><description> Last day of my vacation. 🥹 Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder than rest in the &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; periods instead. The assault bike saddles are garbarge. Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me. Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me. &amp;hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so. After getting wlziipsrv built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&amp;hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (bug in macOS 17.2) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS! Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 and GOU#2 ❤️</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Last day of my vacation. 🥹</li>
<li>Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes
<ul>
<li>Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder  than rest in the &ldquo;rest&rdquo; periods instead.
<ul>
<li>The assault bike saddles are garbarge.</li>
<li>Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &ldquo;normal&rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me.
<ul>
<li>&hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>After getting <code>wlziipsrv</code> built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv">https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv</a></li>
<li>Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MacOS/comments/18g4vxn/cannot_remap_keys_on_macbook_pro_with_hidutils_in/">bug in macOS 17.2</a>) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS!</li>
<li>Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 <em>and</em> GOU#2 ❤️</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #247: Precious moments</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 22:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/</guid><description>Welcome back friends!
This post attempts to cover the longer thann normal period of time from Monday September 26 to Sunday October 30, 2022.
Figure 1: This is what the view looks like just after a lunch at Pearl View Guest House, which itself with spectacular views.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends!</p>
<p>This post attempts to cover the longer thann normal period of time from Monday
September 26 to Sunday October 30, 2022.</p>










<figure><a href="knysna-heads.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_c8238dc56f0e3de0.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_acc7684da5d46e95.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_f46a88b64faaa876.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_870583e22b4106b8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_acc7684da5d46e95.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: This is what the view looks like just after a lunch at Pearl View Guest House, which itself with spectacular views."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>This is what the view looks like just after a lunch at Pearl View Guest House, which itself with spectacular views.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This is the year of me struggling to make the time and the energy to write
these posts. Between work (it&rsquo;s never been this truly busy before), family
(teenagers man) and other important activities, this previously
straight-forward endeavour has become really challenging.</p>
<p>I currently have no cunning plans to remedy this issue, except to keep on
trying.</p>
<p>Anyways, my main goal with this post below morphed from &ldquo;try to write a good
post&rdquo; to &ldquo;<em>any</em> post is better than no post&rdquo;, and so it is entirely possible that
you&rsquo;ll notice some unevenness.</p>
<h2 id="wilderness-energy">Wilderness Energy</h2>
<p>So after a number of paragraphs complaining about how little free time I have
at my disposal, I shall now briefly talk about our October family break-away to
the East coast!</p>
<p>As we often do, we decided to break the road-trip in two, staying for the night
in Wilderness, literally one of my favourite places on the planet.</p>
<p>As we don&rsquo;t often do, this time we stayed an extra night because the weather,
and that balmy Wilderness energy (it sounds like a pretty hip caffeinated
drink) were simply too amazing to pass up.</p>
<p>During our surprise extra day:</p>
<ul>
<li>I ran the Waterside dirt road next to the Serpentine river, in the direction of
Hoekwil. I love running dirt roads, and this one is high up on the list.</li>
<li>We (6 famjam + 1 friend) did the canoe trip at Kaaimanskloof, something that
we&rsquo;ve always dreamed about, to the waterfall, to the train bridge and later
up the river all the way to the bend right below the Map of Africa lookout,
far up above. I shared a canoe with my most favourite middle child in the
world, aka GOU #2. (We also won the race back, even beating out the far more
energetic canoe powered by GOU #1 and her friend, by applying a certain
degree of crystallized-intelligence-guided strategy.)</li>
<li>We squeezed in a beach day.</li>
<li>We went up to Map of Africa to enjoy the brilliant sunset.</li>
</ul>
<p>After all of that I was a bit worried that we had set the pace of the whole
week, the sustaining of which I would probably not have survived.</p>
<p>Fortunately the continuation of our vacation in St Francis was, whilst <em>quite</em>
active, an energetically more sustainable affair, consisting of balmy weather,
family beach days, and zen-inducing sunsets.</p>
<p>Personally, I will <em>remember</em> this week as a great example of How To Holiday.</p>










<figure><a href="st-francis-bay-canals.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_2636366ec22c5c37.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_b307460b68aefcdf.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_5771a46dd0d8be48.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_8666c277feba0dec.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_b307460b68aefcdf.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View of the canals in St Francis Bay, the village 7km to the North of Cape St Francis."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>View of the canals in St Francis Bay, the village 7km to the North of Cape St Francis.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="goldilocks-water-for-your-moka-pot">Goldilocks water for your Moka pot</h2>
<p>At home, we rely on our <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#coffee-machine-reincarnation">trusty (new) Saeco bean-to-cup</a> machine to keep us
continously and quite fully coffee-nated.</p>
<p>However, because there is no space for Saeco on our travels, we require a
mobile, preferably compact, coffee production modality.</p>
<p>This used to be the giant coffee syringe, also known as Aeropress, which I
wrote about in <a href="/2014/07/22/weekly-head-voices-78-aeroimpressed/">WHV #78, back in 2014</a>.</p>
<p>It makes really great tasting coffee, but it can feel a little clinical.</p>
<p>More recently, as we became older (a tenacious process that never seems to stop
until the end, I am told) and our appreciation for the slower, more deliberate
rituals of life grew, we decided to switch to a Bialetti Moka pot instead.</p>
<p>You would probably recognise it. It&rsquo;s that distinctive little aluminium pot
with the octagonal base and the friendly picture on the side.</p>
<p>Instead of the one minute stir, one minute push through of the Aeropress, this
artifact sits there on its hob for about five minutes when it magically fills
up with lovely espresso.</p>
<p>(Of course it&rsquo;s not magic, it&rsquo;s just <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moka_pot">Mr Alfonso Bialetti&rsquo;s brilliant
engineering from 1933</a>!)</p>
<p>Here is our Moka pot, this time posing in <a href="/tags/stilbaai/">Stilbaai</a>, another one of my favourite
vacation destinations:</p>










<figure><a href="stilbaai-moka.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_3bafdd46cb5bf89c.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_bc0795b9133db5d8.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_ca37d8803312a579.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_84eada315ce75bc9.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_bc0795b9133db5d8.jpg"
            

         width="320px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>More recently, I chatted with friend PH at work about the ideal starting
temperature for the fresh water in one&rsquo;s Moka.</p>
<p>I had naively always preferred to start with cold water, to emulate the camping
situation, but work-friend explained that he had understood warm water to be
better for the taste.</p>
<p>I had never considered this before. Doh!</p>
<p>(Later I learned from mutual friend SvdW that they had in fact previously
studied Moka pot temperature in detail during a work trip, an experience
perhaps partially forgotten by friend PH.)</p>
<p>Serendipitously, during a meeting later that afternoon with colleagues from the
US, one of our collaborators, sporting a pretty relevant scientific background,
explained that <em>he</em> had understood (in Fahrenheit, we had to translate) that 60
°C resulted in the best coffee extraction.</p>
<p>This obviously piqued my curiousity, quite intensely, and so I went searching
that evening&hellip;</p>
<p>Imagine my delight when I ran into <a href="http://www.msc.univ-paris-diderot.fr/~phyexp/uploads/Moka/article1.pdf"><em>The physics of a stove-top espresso
machine</em></a>, a 2008 scientific article by Dr Warren D. King in the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1119/1.2870524"><em>American
Journal of Physics</em>, vol. 76, no. 6, pp. 558–565</a>, in which he documents his
mathematical modeling and experiments showing that the optimal starting
temperature for the water in a Moka pot is in fact 70 °C!</p>
<p>The short version of the story is that this will result in most of the water
going through the coffee grounds, when extraction takes place, at about 95
°C, which results in the most  flavour.</p>
<p>If you start with cold water, extraction will happen at 70 °C, which is
too low, and if you start with hot water, it will go through the grounds at too
high a temperature, resulting in bitter coffee.</p>
<h2 id="take-a-picture-with-your-mind">Take a picture with your mind</h2>
<!-- The title of this section is due to friend PK. You have to say it in his voice, "take a picture with your miiii-iiiiind!" -->
<p>Back in <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#multiplicity-of-you">WHV #242 I talked about the remembering (narrating) self, and the
experiencing self</a>. (Please read that section if you have not yet. In fact, I
think that the whole of WHV #242 could be worth your time.)</p>
<p>Kahnemann&rsquo;s poignant quote bears repeating here:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Odd as it may seem, I am my remembering self, and the experiencing self, who
does my living, is like a stranger to me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just the other day, in the middle of a perfect run on the beach, with a breeze
that was just <em>so</em>, the sun all golden and ready to set, and with my bare feet
connecting with the sand and the earth beneath it, it felt like a full sensory
connect, experiencing self for once fully in control.</p>
<p>It was perfect, until I felt this superficially pretty reasonable urge to take
a photo, just a little something to remember the perfect moment by&hellip;</p>
<p>At that instant, I saw it for what it was &ndash; sneaky, remembering self
attempting to hijack the moment, and take it away from experiencing self, the
one who at that moment was generating by far the most positive energy.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We wants it, we needs it. Must have the precious. They stole it from us. Sneaky
little hobbitses. Wicked, tricksy, false! &ndash; JRR Tolkien</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The desire to remember the perfect moment is understandable, but there is a
cost: The moment itself.</p>
<p>Resist the urge.</p>
<p>Love,<br />
Remembering Self</p>










<figure><a href="cape-st-francis-light-house.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_97ddb7d8d1f7c08b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_b9a76019323c2de.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_f7a6964a6a668463.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_9b3e177a9240de5c.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_b9a76019323c2de.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: The light house in Cape St Francis, the village 7km to the South of St Francis Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>The light house in Cape St Francis, the village 7km to the South of St Francis Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #225: Just a perfect weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</guid><description>Dear reader,
Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.
Keyboard update: K1 You&amp;rsquo;ll remember from WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the Womier K87 with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown switches.
That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear reader,</p>
<p>Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th
installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="la_autumn_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_efacf2278401042b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_395a276d16bd5112.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_9b888013a0ce8df0.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_f05d46bcd41cf24a.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_395a276d16bd5112.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="keyboard-update-k1">Keyboard update: K1</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll remember from <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the
Womier K87</a> with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown
switches.</p>
<p>That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt
Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the case that fingers also like the exercise, just like their
human owners.</p>
<p>I was not planning to buy any keyboards again soon, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was quite curious whether low profile key switches (that is, slightly less
finger travel) would be a good compromise between the fun of the Womier and the
efficiency of the Sculpt.</li>
<li>The K1 was on my list of candidates of keyboards with low-profile mechanical
switches.</li>
<li>I find it difficult to resist a good deal.</li>
</ul>
<p>You see, a friendly little bird (who also hangs out on the keyboards channel of
the zatech slack) told me about the extra-special Takealot birthday special
discount on <a href="https://www.imore.com/keychron-k1-v4-review">the Keychron K1 V4 87-key keyboard</a>.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a credit card transaction, a week of waiting for delivery and
another week of getting accustomed to the new board, and here we are, with at
least me typing these words on the new K1.</p>
<p>It took a while to get used to the keycaps, which can be a slippery sometimes
(or rather, my finger tip traction is variable), but my typing speed and
accuracy on this thing are in the neighbourhood of where they should be.</p>
<p>The thing is a great deal more <em>stylish</em> than my Womier; the Womier is that
guilty pleasure 80s disco that you really love, the K1 could work in a serious
coffee shop.</p>
<p>Also, having a keyboard which can switch this easily between wired operation
(the default for my desktop) and three different bluetooth connections is
pretty convenient. On trips where I usually only take the MacBook, I could
consider taking the K1 along when I have to do A Great Deal of Serious Typing.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I can&rsquo;t yet say if the low profile switches are indeed
the compromise that I wondered about. My subjective impression now is indeed
that my fingers don&rsquo;t get so physically tired as sometimes happens with the
Womier, but I&rsquo;ll have to switch between them a few times to get a better idea.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am certainly enjoying the experience of typing on
this thing, and I am certainly wondering about the interesting role that
different types of mechanical keyboards have begun to play in my computing
life.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-about-a-new-book-notes-post-about-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Lessons about a new book notes post about Seven and a Half Lessons about the Brain</h2>
<p>After two months of early(ish) morning typing on various keyboards, I finally
managed to wrap up <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">my book notes about Seven and a Half Lessons about the
Brain</a>, a fantastic book by neuro-scientist and psychologist Lisa Feldman
Barrett.</p>
<p>I had plans, in retrospect clearly too ambitious, to have at least two (2) book
notes posts out in Q1 of this year (after it took me months to complete <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my book
notes on Creativity, Inc.</a> by the end of last year).</p>
<p>That goal was necessarily postponed to Q2, and as we can all see now, there is
not enough time for a second post like this.</p>
<p>Either I have to change the format of the book notes to something more compact,
like a bunch of bullet lists, or I should make peace with the fact that I write
these like I write them, a little prose with quotes interspersed that can
generally be read like a mini story itself, and with the fact that they&rsquo;re
going to take as much time as they do.</p>
<p>Sometimes I have mixed feelings about the practice itself.</p>
<p>It takes fragments of hobby time spread out over weeks, fragments of time that
I could probably use for more reading, other interesting tidbits and, uhm,
extra work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it feels like a sort of a mini-rebellion doing exactly this,
assembling so many little pieces into something slightly more coherent and
significant, something that stands apart from work.</p>
<p>It seems I do know what to do.</p>
<p>Thanks for the chat!</p>
<h2 id="perfect-weekends-and-the-necessary-reminders-that-precede-them">Perfect weekends and the necessary reminders that precede them</h2>
<p>The weekend of June 4, 2021, was unexpectedly perfect, and I would like to make
note of that here for future me.</p>
<p>This is the recipe that we followed, utterly by happy accident:</p>
<ul>
<li>1x reminder during the week to really focus on the now.</li>
<li>1x absolutely perfect autumn weather package: balmy 20ish degrees Celsius,
lots of sun, very little wind.</li>
<li>3x braais, one per day, with various subsets of family.</li>
<li>2x runs: one a long weekend morning run, and the other an unplanned one
with GOU#1.</li>
<li>1x polishing and publishing of the blog post mentioned above.</li>
<li>1x unexpected Sunday evening star watching with GOU#2.</li>
</ul>
<p>One would think that daily practice would help, but it turns out that sometimes
a serendipitous reminder by a friend can help to switch one&rsquo;s brain into
exactly the right gear, right before the weekend.</p>
<p>During our Friday evening start-the-weekend ritual (it&rsquo;s a braai. surprise!), I
had my first quite visceral &ldquo;THIS, this is it, this is everything&rdquo;
experience. (so lovely)</p>
<p>From then on, brain remained in the right mode right through most of the
weekend.</p>
<p>If you ever run into me before the weekend (it&rsquo;s always before the weekend!), I
would be grateful if you could remind me that it is in fact now.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you much nowness.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #223: The potjie never left</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 22:34:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/</guid><description>Welcome friends to the two hundred and twenty third edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the period of time from Monday May 3 to Sunday May 16, 2021.
(Hah, by writing out the words like that, I&amp;rsquo;ll get paid even more for this article!)
Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome friends to the two hundred and twenty third edition of the Weekly Head
Voices, covering the period of time from Monday May 3 to Sunday May 16, 2021.</p>
<p>(Hah, by writing out the words like that, I&rsquo;ll get paid even more for this
article!)</p>










<figure><a href="verg_just_before_endurance_broke.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_7cbec36f66f46ce9.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_9c00e99c7ebe6317.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_5b4904a8b92c6eb0.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_2059833eebfe1bf7.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_9c00e99c7ebe6317.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="vxlabs-software-development-handbook-v1-is-out">vxlabs software development handbook v1 is out</h2>
<p>Well, it&rsquo;s not really a book, more of a blog post really, but it is chock full
of practical guidelines for developers.</p>
<p>It is also 100% free and open source, and can be accessed <a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/">over at the vxlabs</a>.</p>
<p>None of this will be surprising for any of you experienced developers, but it&rsquo;s
super handy having a single place that you can point folks at when you have
some specific advice in mind.</p>
<p>My personal favourite and most important guideline is <a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/#comment-your-code">&ldquo;Comment your code&rdquo;</a>. It
seems that this advice really can&rsquo;t be repeated often enough.</p>
<p>The first commit (i.e. words written) happened on December 14 of 2020, and
version 1 published on 2021-05-03. Most of this had to happen in between other
activities, but that&rsquo;s ok. This is one of the <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#interstitial-projects">interstitial projects</a> I implied
in January.</p>
<h2 id="world-in-my-eyes">World in my eyes</h2>
<p>The photo at the start of this post was taken at the entrance of Vergelegen, at
about 7km into an absolute epic Saturday late afternoon run.</p>
<p>It was epic, because the autumn weather was absolutely perfect, my running
mechanism was smooth and efficient, and there was great music piping into my
brain via the recently acquired JBL Endurance Run bluetooth earphones.</p>
<p>I mention the earphones specifically, because for the first time I had found
something that fit perfectly and even advertised being &ldquo;sweatproof&rdquo; on the box,
a characteristic that is quite important when you produce as much sweat as I
do. (TMI, but please bear with me here)</p>
<p>I was so satisfied after five or six runs that I had taken a few photos earlier
that day, as I was planning a short blog post extolling the virtues of said
gadget.</p>
<p>Probably about 60 seconds after I took the photo, running back out to the road,
thinking to myself how great these earphones were working and how far I was
still going to run and how amazing everything is, the right earphone starts
going &ldquo;GGGGGGGHHHHHRRRRRRRRGGGGGWWWWWGGGGHHHHHH&rdquo; (you have to read that with an
authentic, hard Dutch guttural) and it simply does not stop.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have you tried switching them off and on again?&rdquo; you might say.</p>
<p>Well, the sound just kept on going, switched on, or off.</p>
<p>No amount of power cycling, shaking, re-pairing or swearing made any
difference.</p>
<p>Right earphone just kept on going &ldquo;GGGGGGGHHHRRRRRGGGGHHHHH&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I finally bundled up the JBL TripSpoiler BT into my hand, and ran home, like a
person who runs without music.</p>
<p>P.S. The section title is a Depeche Mode song (one of my teenage favourites) in
which the highest mountain is contrasted with the deepest sea, albeit in a
utterly different context.</p>
<p>P.P.S. As I write this, takealot is sending me a replacement set. I&rsquo;m hoping
the new unit is an anti-lemon.</p>
<h2 id="pretty-hip-birthday-party">Pretty hip birthday party</h2>
<p>GOU #2 held her 11th party here at our facility.</p>
<p>The plans started out as a VR party (or at least that&rsquo;s what I thought), but
great forces out of my control determined that There Would Also Need to Be
Karaoke.</p>
<p>This is one time where the more technically inclined dads can shine!</p>
<p>I purchased exactly one cheap but great value Karaoke microphone (the Samson
SCR10S Karaoke Dynamic Microphone with Switch, if you must know), and then
mixed everything together using an old Windows laptop, our old burglary-proof
(when flat screens were still thick) TV with HDMI input, and a bunch of cables.</p>
<p>Friends arrived, and an extremely fun-looking and partially sugar-fuelled
teenage chaos ensued.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the VR setup ended up getting a significant chunk of the
attention. Even amongst these ultra-connected digital natives, the tech is
still new enough to garner a substantial amount of the unobtainium aka
attention.</p>
<p>(Although I never ever sing, not even in the shower, that karaoke setup has a
surprisingly strong magnetic force, if you catch my drift. GOU #2 was quite
relieved when none of her parents decided to make a guest appearance at the
main event. In my case, it&rsquo;s really for the better.)</p>
<h2 id="boomer-party">Boomer party</h2>
<p>A few days later, after we had sufficiently recovered from the teenage party,
it was time to invite long time friends of ours over for an old people party.</p>
<p>As is our wont down here, when the friends are this dear, we take time to make
a potjie.</p>
<p>The autumn weather contributed fabulously, and so we enjoyed scenes like this:</p>










<figure><a href="chicken-curry-potjie-2021.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_851d8ef19cf3be22.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_a6e81b0fbea9949a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_c7468ed7bcf7e946.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_e029c5f2d370256.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_a6e81b0fbea9949a.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: From this photo, it&rsquo;s also quite clear that I have become much taller."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: From this photo, it&rsquo;s also quite clear that I have become much taller.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Readers of this blog might recognise the visual composition above, perhaps from
<a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/">a post back in January of 2016</a>, when I initiated the pot with coincidentally
the same recipe.</p>
<p>The potjie scene seems to repeat itself (these are not the only two examples),
acting as a sort of reliable cast iron backdrop (with enamel coating!) for our
family and friendship rituals.</p>
<p>On this day, the ritual was indeed sublime.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #196: Get focused</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 22:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</guid><description> Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&amp;rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&amp;rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&amp;rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="sylvia_draws_family_20200531.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_a45ab388b85c4527.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_9e67ca7a19e8a10b.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_9bdc60a70b4a330a.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_e95086249cbd6c5.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_9e67ca7a19e8a10b.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there folks, please make yourself at home!</p>
<p>This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday May 18 to Sunday May 31 of the
extremely strange year of 2020.</p>
<p>That effort of looking back has resulted in the following three items.</p>
<h2 id="when-building-automatic-analysis-pipelines-get-your-batch-accuracy-testing-up-as-soon-as-you-can">When building automatic analysis pipelines, get your batch accuracy testing up as soon as you can</h2>
<p>A substantial part of my work hours these past two weeks went into working on a
automatic medical image analysis pipeline, with machine learning
inside™. (I mean &ldquo;AI&rdquo;, of course. And drones.)</p>
<p>I really do love this stuff, but sometimes it ends up coming down to putting
your head down and keeping it down, in order to grind out every percent or two
in improved accuracy.</p>
<p>The tip I wanted to offer here is the following: Even when you think your
pipeline is way too far from &ldquo;done&rdquo;™, get your batch accuracy testing up
and running.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a double whammy:</p>
<ol>
<li>You and your team get early and regular feedback on how your performance is
going.</li>
<li>You are forced to have the whole concept working from end-to-end. It can be
surprising how many little issues you still need to solve, and running into
them sooner rather than later is only good.</li>
</ol>
<p>By the way, the practical machine learning icon <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew%5FNg">Professor Andrew Ng&rsquo;s</a> free book
<a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/machine-learning-yearning/">Machine Learning Yearning</a> is filled to the brim with practical tips for
implementing ML in practice.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">Lazar Focus: The super tiny Windows app and website distraction blocker that you&rsquo;ve always wanted</h2>
<p>Back at the <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">start of 2018 I wrote the following about the macOS app and website
distraction blocker called Focus</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>After years of resisting these types of software tools due to my belief that I
should simply apply more grit and will power to squeeze out more focus hours,
I finally broke down and purchased the macOS app called Focus. You click its
pretty icon, and then your computer goes into focus mode: The Mail application
and a bunch of other non-focus-related apps all get killed, and a bunch of
websites (reddit, youtube, work chat, etc) are blocked for a user-configurable
block of time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even if you skipped that extract, please read the following one about the
<em>idea</em> behind such a focus app:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It usually takes a single moment of weakness for a distraction to terminate a
valuable block of focus. It takes a single moment of strength for this tool to
start a valuable block of focus.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Anyways, I was really missing this functionality on Windows, and so I busted
out my trusty <a href="https://www.lazarus-ide.org/">Lazarus IDE</a> (who <em>didn&rsquo;t</em> make apps back in the day with the old
win32 Delphi?!) and figured out the various required Windows APIs to create
this brand new super tiny but super effective app and website blocker:</p>










<figure><a href="lazar_focused_screenshot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hu_3ea9d753f10fd2a4.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hu_71d14bfb18afecb6.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hu_cc5f57817664d11a.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hu_71d14bfb18afecb6.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As shown in the screenshot, it&rsquo;s sitting at 5 MB of memory use. In the age of
Electron apps, that&rsquo;s really small.</p>
<p>When you activate focus mode, it&rsquo;ll prevent your browser (Chrome, Brave,
Firefox or Edge) from viewing any distracting website (you get to configure the
list) by redirecting to a local web page with an inspiring quote, e.g.:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Concentration can be cultivated. One can learn to exercise willpower,
discipline one&rsquo;s body and train one&rsquo;s mind. &ndash; Anil Ambani</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It will also terminate any distracting apps, and helpfully prevent you from
starting them up during your focus session.</p>
<p>The convenient progress bar shows how far you are on your way to a 25 minute
pomodoro, but that is purely for motivation, and not enforced.</p>
<p>The total focus blocks and hours at the top should also help to keep us
motivated and&hellip; <strong>LAZAR FOCUSED!</strong></p>
<p>So, because there are probably (hopefully?) at least two other people who&rsquo;ll
find this as useful as I do, and because shipping and selling software that you
made yourself is awesome especially when it&rsquo;s a hobby project, I have decided
to try and sell Lazar Focus using something like <a href="https://gumroad.com/">gumroad</a>.</p>
<p>Hopefully soon with a hobby hour or three I can finish the installer and the
website, and then make the beta available at a reduced rate.</p>
<p>Because I prefer it for apps like this when I am the buyer, I have decided to
make it available as a one-time purchase, no eval but money-back, with
time-limited upgrades (probably a year?), but with your last licensed version
obviously remaining fully functional until the end of The Windows API.</p>
<h2 id="art-fun-with-portrait-ai">Art fun with Portrait AI</h2>
<p>Ever since I spent a bit of time better curating my twitter subscriptions,
getting rid of the vitriol and adding much more STEM (shout out to <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Eric Topol</a>
&ndash; you could install twitter <em>just</em> for him and you would be great), they often
bring me shiny treasures.</p>
<p>Recently, it was <a href="https://portraitai.com/">portraitai.com</a> which brought a great deal of mirth to my home
as we made authentic looking portraits of each other. (We&rsquo;re just a bunch of
silly primates with amazing gadgets.)</p>
<p>It didn&rsquo;t seem to work all that well on me however, until I started pulling
funny faces:</p>










<figure><a href="charl_portraitai.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_60b307dd03ff58c.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_4ac89d1f2179bf4f.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_298bd39ecfd5cd80.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_b291b94c239595d1.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_4ac89d1f2179bf4f.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>With that, dear friends, I bid you kindness, happiness and health.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #193: COVID-19 part 3.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 15:33:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</guid><description> Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.
The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12 to Sunday May 2.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_7d89392b07c58b4d.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_753d6f0ee79aeca5.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_3d00f1f7a662d933.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_b5ad8d4373cf7a35.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_753d6f0ee79aeca5.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!--
2020-05-02 21:38 Boiler Room Solomun 2015 playing on the second screen while
I'm typing this.  I was hoping to understand why this has 43M views, and my
favourite boiler room of all time, Maceo Plex in Berlin in 2015, has "only"
11M.

Let me know in the comments if you read this. :)
-->
<p>The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12
to Sunday May 2.</p>
<p>This post has a strong nerd flavour. If that is not your inclination, please
use the table of contents (to your right) to navigate to the bits that you do
find interesting.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re in a rush, and can only select one section, I would recommend <a href="#the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">the
one on Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Have fun!</p>
<h2 id="covid-19-status-update">COVID-19 status update</h2>
<p>On Friday, May 1, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/lockdown-level-4-what-is-now-allowed-2020-4">the South African lockdown was slightly lifted from level 5
to level
4</a>.</p>
<p>This means that a part of the workforce will start returning to work, and that
citizens are allowed slightly more freedom of movement.</p>
<p>If safety had been the only requirement, we should probably have had to
continue with level 5 for a while longer, but that darned economy unfortunately
also has to be kept afloat.</p>
<p>In spite of this, I was super pleased to read the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Masks are obligatory.</strong> Everyone has to wear cloth face masks outside their
homes. If you don&rsquo;t yet have a cloth mask, you can wear a scarf or a t-shirt
wrapped around your mouth and nose, says Dlamini-Zuma.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This might end up being the thing that gets us through this in something that
resembles one piece.</p>
<p>The second announcement I was super happy with, was that we would be allowed
outside for exercise between 6 and 9 in the mornings.</p>
<p>So on Saturday morning I went out for my first post-level-5 run, ON THE
OUTSIDE. (It does feel strange going out on the street for the first time in
five weeks.)</p>
<p>The majority of people I saw actually had some form of face mask going on.</p>
<p>I had expected otherwise, because doing cardiorespiratory exercise with a mask
on is not easy, and people can be stubborn.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/advanced/a20842404/product-review-buff-headwear/">Buffs</a>
are these fantastically useful &ldquo;seamless tubular garments made from
high-performance microfibre&rdquo; that many runners swear by.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out you can <em>also</em> use them as as-running-proof-as-possible face
masks:</p>










<figure><a href="cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask_hu_5873ed277714d934.jpg 480w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg"
            

         width="240"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>Pro-tip: If there&rsquo;s a runner in your life, and you&rsquo;re on the lookout for a
gift, just get them a buff. You can <em>never</em> have too many buffs.</p>
<h2 id="gou-2-is-10">GOU #2 is 10</h2>
<p>My most favourite middle child in the whole world recently hit the double
digits, and she was suitably chuffed with this.</p>
<p>It must be strange experiencing your 10th birthday under these truly surreal
conditions.</p>
<p>On the other hand, when you&rsquo;re 10, you probably don&rsquo;t dwell on thoughts like
that for too long.</p>
<h2 id="miscellaneous-catch-up">Miscellaneous catch-up</h2>
<p>In the past weeks, I wrote a number of other blog posts, started a new blog,
and discovered an obscure but fantastic new blogging tool.</p>
<p>Oh, and my expensive ergonomic keyboard broke.</p>
<h3 id="fantastic-blogging-tools-and-where-to-find-them">Fantastic blogging tools and where to find them</h3>
<p>It all started when I finally got around to exploring
<a href="https://ox-hugo.scripter.co/">ox-hugo</a>, the Emacs package for writing Hugo
posts using Org mode.</p>
<p>You might not recall this, but the mere <em>existence</em> of <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/#build-and-upload-the-new-static-hotness">ox-hugo was the reason
I chose
Hugo</a>
when it was time to leave Wordpress behind.</p>
<!--
Hey there friends reading these hidden messages!

There are multiple explicit and implicit streams of connection running through
these channels and it's lovely.

Anyways, it is now 22:44 and I finished the Solomun boiler room set.

There are indeed so many stories happening in those frames, many of which will
only become apparent after more viewings.

I'm now back to the Maceo Plex set, with a smile of recognition on my face.
-->
<p>Well, it turns out that, <em>if</em> you&rsquo;re an Emacs Org mode user, ox-hugo is pretty
close to blogging nirvana.</p>
<p>In the past few days, I&rsquo;ve used it to turn arbitrary Org mode entries from my
month journal into blog posts, to send the exact same Org mode file to two
different blogs with different sets of title and metadata, and to assert
Neo-in-the-matrix-style control over what goes where and how.</p>
<p>If I have to put my finger on the core of ox-hugo&rsquo;s extreme utility, I would
say that <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi">Kaushal Modi</a>, the brains behind
ox-hugo, has managed to create a perfect coupling between Org mode on the one
hand and Hugo on the other, a coupling that maximally leverages the strengths
of each.</p>
<p>(I will probably be writing more about this, but &hellip; elsewhere. <em>[queue
suspenseful music here]</em>)</p>
<h3 id="other-mostly-very-nerdy-blog-posts">Other mostly very nerdy blog posts</h3>
<p>As part of the ox-hugo investigation, I had to figure out how to <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/04/26/cite-consistently-between-org-ref-and-ox-hugo/">cite
consistently between straight Org mode and
ox-hugo</a>
for automatic bibtex-backed bibliographies.</p>
<p>Inspired by friend <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2020/04/28/voice-capture-org-tasks-on-android/">Stéfan&rsquo;s post on voice capturing and automatically
transcribing notes to Org
mode</a>,
I figured out how to <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/2020/04/30/voice-capture-org-mode-notes-and-more-using-siri-shortcuts-on-ios/">do the same on iOS and wrote it all
up</a>.</p>
<p>If you clicked on that second link, you will have discovered my brand new blog,
the hopefully catchily titled <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">Org Mode
Exocortex</a>. I will be posting <em>ultra</em>-nerdy Emacs
Org mode content over there.</p>
<p>(Friend Stéfan is the very first guest blogger, with a re-post of his Android
speech recognition post linked above. BTW, that was my first guest blogging
experience ever. Life for the Z-list blogger does not move fast.)</p>
<p>Finally, also thanks to ox-hugo&rsquo;s motivation, I figured (haha, now I see what I
did there) out how to make and publish a new <a href="/2020/05/02/drop-in-replacement-for-hugo-figure-shortcode-with-responsive-img-srcset/"><code>figure</code> shortcode for Hugo that
automatically resizes images and gets your browser to download only the best
one</a>!</p>
<h3 id="microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-desktop-at-4-years-rip">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic Desktop at 4 years: RIP</h3>
<p>After all of that good news, I do have to report the following not-so-great news:</p>
<p>After just under four years of approximately one half of my typing, the
<a href="/2016/05/22/weekly-head-voices-107-balance/">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboard I welcomed into my home at the start of
May of 2016</a>, has developed a key
failure.</p>
<p>More specifically, the physical &ldquo;G&rdquo;, which is my &ldquo;I&rdquo; (thanks
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dvorak_keyboard_layout">Dvorak</a>), fails about
30% of the time, with that duty cycle slowly growing.</p>
<p>(You may bring your jokes about why specifically the &ldquo;I&rdquo; is failing first to
the comment section below!)</p>
<p>I opened up the keyboard following <a href="http://emmanuelcontreras.com/how-to/how-to-disassemble-microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-keyboard-and-make-it-wired/">the instructions and photos of Emmanuel
Contreras</a>.</p>
<p>(What I can add to Contreras&rsquo;s information, is that the palm rest is held fast
by no less than 12 little screws, some odd-sized. Pro-tip: When you remove all
of these, put them down in the same pattern as the holes, so that you can get
them back in later.)</p>
<p>However, one unfortunately ends up at the metal backing which is attached to
the top-plate with about 30 or more plastic pop-rivet like mechanisms.</p>
<p>Information online also seems to indicate that once a single key goes, you have
to replace the whole board.</p>
<p>Some more searching brought me to <a href="https://youtu.be/x09inK8-G1Y">this obscure but helpful YouTube
review</a> where Kevin explains that although
everyone at his company loved the keyboard, they had simply accepted it as part
of their business expense to replace them every 6 months to a year.</p>
<p>If you search through <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Microsoft-Ergonomic-Keyboard-Business-5KV-00001/product-reviews/B00CYX26BC/ref=cm_cr_arp_d_viewopt_kywd?pageNumber=1&amp;filterByKeyword=durability">the Amazon reviews for
&ldquo;durability&rdquo;</a>,
it really starts to look like a case of a fantastic keyboard marred by issues
with its durability.</p>
<p>However, if you need a relatively affordable &ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; keyboard, where with
&ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; I mean shaped in such a way that your wrists get to stay more or
less straight while typing, with really great feel and low-impact typing, the
Sculpt comes out on top.</p>
<p>Although it goes against my grain, I should probably be happy with the above
average 4 years that this one managed, and start finding a local source for its
inevitable replacement.</p>
<p>Nerds in the audience: I am very curious to hear about your keyboard
preferences in the comments. Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="two-lessons-learnt-from-how-to-take-smart-notes">Two lessons learnt from How to Take Smart Notes</h2>
<p>On March 31 I quickly read through <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/34507927-how-to-take-smart-notes">Sönke Ahrens&rsquo;s book, How to Take Smart
Notes</a>.</p>
<p>(The full title is actually &ldquo;How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to
Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking &ndash; for Students, Academics and Nonfiction
Book Writers&rdquo;)</p>
<h3 id="the-most-portable-cross-platform-ebook-format-with-self-contained-annotations-is">The most portable cross-platform ebook format with self-contained annotations is&hellip;</h3>
<p>I bought the Kindle book on Amazon, because that&rsquo;s how I&rsquo;ve been doing it for
years.</p>
<p>However, although I prefer reading novels on my Kindle e-Ink device, for
reference works it&rsquo;s a deal breaker that my highlights and notes are not in a
standards compliant format that integrates nicely with <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing personal
knowledge management system</a>.</p>
<p>My goal was to find an alternative format for these books with the following features:</p>
<ul>
<li>Before you answer PDF, which I use extensively for academic papers, typeset
books, and many other things: The alternative format should be fully
reflowable, like the source Kindle book.</li>
<li>Readable and annotations editable on all my non-Kindle devices (Windows,
Linux, macOS, iOS).</li>
<li>Most importantly: Flexible annotations, including at least highlighting and
positional notes, that are stored within the file itself, so they can never
be lost.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t expect this to be too much of a challenge.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<p>After a number of hours spent spelunking down a number of different
rabbit-holes, with epub3 being the greatest disappointment (the spec has all
the features, but the implementations largely lack good annotation support), I
ended up in a place where you probably would not expect to find me&hellip;</p>
<p>Dear readers, the best format that satisfies all requirements above
is&hellip; <code>&lt;FRITS_DRUMROLL /&gt;</code> &hellip; <strong>Microsoft DOCX</strong>!</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been DeDRM&rsquo;ing (google it) the Kindle reference books I
purchase in order to be able to read and annotate them across all my platforms.</p>
<p>For this, the iPad is pretty great.</p>
<p>Once read, the DOCX files, including all of the annotations I made, are stored
in the correct place in my synchronised file hierarchy, and are fully
searchable and accessible with standard tools.</p>
<h3 id="the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">The amazing Niklas Luhmann and his Zettelkasten</h3>
<p>The book itself, <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em>, spends well-deserved time on the
phenomenon that was the prodigiously productive German sociologist Professor
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niklas_Luhmann">Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Over his career, Prof. Luhmann wrote more than 70 books and published almost
400 research articles.</p>
<p>He made a massive impact on the world of sociology and systems theory.</p>
<p>When asked in <a href="https://www.uni-bielefeld.de/soz/luhmann-archiv/pdf/jschmidt_zettelkasten-als-uberraschungsgenerator.pdf">a 1997
interview</a>
how he managed to this productive, he answered:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Ich denke ja nicht alles allein, sondern das
geschieht weitgehend im Zettelkasten. [&hellip;]
Meine Produktivität ist im wesentlichen aus dem
Zettelkasten-System zu erklären. [&hellip;]
Der Zettelkasten kostet mich mehr Zeit als das
Bücherschreiben</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Translated this is probably something like (German readers, help me out here
please):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think everything by myself, but that largely happens in the slip box. [&hellip;]
My productivity is essentially due to that slipbox system. [..]
The slipbox costs me more time than that writing books</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <em>zettelkasten</em> he referred to were quite simply a set of wooden slipboxes,
in which he could store pieces of paper (the &ldquo;slips&rdquo;), each of which had a
single idea written on it.</p>
<p>It looked more or less exactly like this:</p>










<figure><a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu_25876075ce4fd140.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu_516f4a1013e82a40.jpg 800w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu_516f4a1013e82a40.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Photo of Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Photo of Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Over the course of his career, he managed to write about 90000 (yes, ninety
thousand) of these notes, all of which you can now <a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">browse online at the Niklas
Luhmann-Archiv</a>.</p>
<p>Importantly, he had come up with an ingenious numbering system for linking each
new note to its chain of predecessors, and also to other related chains
anywhere in the zettelkasten.</p>
<p>When it was time to write a book or a paper, he would dive into his this
collection, and then take a stroll through his amazing web of interlinked
thoughts, some of them having matured for years.</p>
<p>Putting together the publication became an exercise in harvesting index cards
from his slipboxes, instead of a positively intimidating mountain of writing,
thinking and rewriting.</p>
<p>This is such a boss-level example of the principle of
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/compounding/">compounding</a>, and one which is
definitely worth trying to follow.</p>
<p>Since reading Ahrens&rsquo;s book, I have started extending <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing note-taking
universe</a> to be more Zettelkasten-like,
when appropriate.</p>
<p>Org mode is a great basis for this, and packages like
<a href="https://github.com/jethrokuan/org-roam">org-roam</a> help us to get closer to our
90-thousand-notes-dreams.</p>
<p>On a higher level, I have been thinking and writing a great deal about how to
merge effectively the Zettelkasten one-idea-per-note approach into the full
spectrum of writing complexity that Org mode supports.</p>
<p>It is important to be mindful of the <em>mode</em> of documentation that you need to
apply at any give point.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about the Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten, <a href="https://writingcooperative.com/zettelkasten-how-one-german-scholar-was-so-freakishly-productive-997e4e0ca125">this Writing
Cooperative article in
English</a>
and <a href="https://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Missing-Link-Luhmanns-Denkmaschine-endlich-im-Netz-4364512.html">this Heise article in
German</a>
are a great start.</p>
<p>This might not be the last time that you&rsquo;ll hear me talking about Luhmann and
his Zettelkasten.</p>
<h2 id="uitzwaaien">Uitzwaaien</h2>
<p>Thank you friends for reading this and connecting with me here!</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>