<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>gou-2 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-2/</link><description>Recent content in gou-2 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #225: Just a perfect weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</guid><description> Dear reader,
Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.
Keyboard update: K1 You&amp;rsquo;ll remember from WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the Womier K87 with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown switches.
That keyboard is so much fun to type on.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear reader,</p>
<p>Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th
installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="la_autumn_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="keyboard-update-k1">Keyboard update: K1</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll remember from <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the
Womier K87</a> with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown
switches.</p>
<p>That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt
Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the case that fingers also like the exercise, just like their
human owners.</p>
<p>I was not planning to buy any keyboards again soon, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was quite curious whether low profile key switches (that is, slightly less
finger travel) would be a good compromise between the fun of the Womier and the
efficiency of the Sculpt.</li>
<li>The K1 was on my list of candidates of keyboards with low-profile mechanical
switches.</li>
<li>I find it difficult to resist a good deal.</li>
</ul>
<p>You see, a friendly little bird (who also hangs out on the keyboards channel of
the zatech slack) told me about the extra-special Takealot birthday special
discount on <a href="https://www.imore.com/keychron-k1-v4-review">the Keychron K1 V4 87-key keyboard</a>.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a credit card transaction, a week of waiting for delivery and
another week of getting accustomed to the new board, and here we are, with at
least me typing these words on the new K1.</p>
<p>It took a while to get used to the keycaps, which can be a slippery sometimes
(or rather, my finger tip traction is variable), but my typing speed and
accuracy on this thing are in the neighbourhood of where they should be.</p>
<p>The thing is a great deal more <em>stylish</em> than my Womier; the Womier is that
guilty pleasure 80s disco that you really love, the K1 could work in a serious
coffee shop.</p>
<p>Also, having a keyboard which can switch this easily between wired operation
(the default for my desktop) and three different bluetooth connections is
pretty convenient. On trips where I usually only take the MacBook, I could
consider taking the K1 along when I have to do A Great Deal of Serious Typing.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I can&rsquo;t yet say if the low profile switches are indeed
the compromise that I wondered about. My subjective impression now is indeed
that my fingers don&rsquo;t get so physically tired as sometimes happens with the
Womier, but I&rsquo;ll have to switch between them a few times to get a better idea.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am certainly enjoying the experience of typing on
this thing, and I am certainly wondering about the interesting role that
different types of mechanical keyboards have begun to play in my computing
life.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-about-a-new-book-notes-post-about-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Lessons about a new book notes post about Seven and a Half Lessons about the Brain</h2>
<p>After two months of early(ish) morning typing on various keyboards, I finally
managed to wrap up <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">my book notes about Seven and a Half Lessons about the
Brain</a>, a fantastic book by neuro-scientist and psychologist Lisa Feldman
Barrett.</p>
<p>I had plans, in retrospect clearly too ambitious, to have at least two (2) book
notes posts out in Q1 of this year (after it took me months to complete <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my book
notes on Creativity, Inc.</a> by the end of last year).</p>
<p>That goal was necessarily postponed to Q2, and as we can all see now, there is
not enough time for a second post like this.</p>
<p>Either I have to change the format of the book notes to something more compact,
like a bunch of bullet lists, or I should make peace with the fact that I write
these like I write them, a little prose with quotes interspersed that can
generally be read like a mini story itself, and with the fact that they&rsquo;re
going to take as much time as they do.</p>
<p>Sometimes I have mixed feelings about the practice itself.</p>
<p>It takes fragments of hobby time spread out over weeks, fragments of time that
I could probably use for more reading, other interesting tidbits and, uhm,
extra work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it feels like a sort of a mini-rebellion doing exactly this,
assembling so many little pieces into something slightly more coherent and
significant, something that stands apart from work.</p>
<p>It seems I do know what to do.</p>
<p>Thanks for the chat!</p>
<h2 id="perfect-weekends-and-the-necessary-reminders-that-precede-them">Perfect weekends and the necessary reminders that precede them</h2>
<p>The weekend of June 4, 2021, was unexpectedly perfect, and I would like to make
note of that here for future me.</p>
<p>This is the recipe that we followed, utterly by happy accident:</p>
<ul>
<li>1x reminder during the week to really focus on the now.</li>
<li>1x absolutely perfect autumn weather package: balmy 20ish degrees Celsius,
lots of sun, very little wind.</li>
<li>3x braais, one per day, with various subsets of family.</li>
<li>2x runs: one a long weekend morning run, and the other an unplanned one
with GOU#1.</li>
<li>1x polishing and publishing of the blog post mentioned above.</li>
<li>1x unexpected Sunday evening star watching with GOU#2.</li>
</ul>
<p>One would think that daily practice would help, but it turns out that sometimes
a serendipitous reminder by a friend can help to switch one&rsquo;s brain into
exactly the right gear, right before the weekend.</p>
<p>During our Friday evening start-the-weekend ritual (it&rsquo;s a braai. surprise!), I
had my first quite visceral &ldquo;THIS, this is it, this is everything&rdquo;
experience. (so lovely)</p>
<p>From then on, brain remained in the right mode right through most of the
weekend.</p>
<p>If you ever run into me before the weekend (it&rsquo;s always before the weekend!), I
would be grateful if you could remind me that it is in fact now.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you much nowness.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #223: The potjie never left</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 22:34:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/</guid><description> Welcome friends to the two hundred and twenty third edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the period of time from Monday May 3 to Sunday May 16, 2021.
(Hah, by writing out the words like that, I&amp;rsquo;ll get paid even more for this article!)
Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault.
vxlabs software development handbook v1 is out Well, it&amp;rsquo;s not really a book, more of a blog post really, but it is chock full of practical guidelines for developers.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome friends to the two hundred and twenty third edition of the Weekly Head
Voices, covering the period of time from Monday May 3 to Sunday May 16, 2021.</p>
<p>(Hah, by writing out the words like that, I&rsquo;ll get paid even more for this
article!)</p>








<figure><a href="verg_just_before_endurance_broke.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="vxlabs-software-development-handbook-v1-is-out">vxlabs software development handbook v1 is out</h2>
<p>Well, it&rsquo;s not really a book, more of a blog post really, but it is chock full
of practical guidelines for developers.</p>
<p>It is also 100% free and open source, and can be accessed <a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/">over at the vxlabs</a>.</p>
<p>None of this will be surprising for any of you experienced developers, but it&rsquo;s
super handy having a single place that you can point folks at when you have
some specific advice in mind.</p>
<p>My personal favourite and most important guideline is <a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/#comment-your-code">&ldquo;Comment your code&rdquo;</a>. It
seems that this advice really can&rsquo;t be repeated often enough.</p>
<p>The first commit (i.e. words written) happened on December 14 of 2020, and
version 1 published on 2021-05-03. Most of this had to happen in between other
activities, but that&rsquo;s ok. This is one of the <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#interstitial-projects">interstitial projects</a> I implied
in January.</p>
<h2 id="world-in-my-eyes">World in my eyes</h2>
<p>The photo at the start of this post was taken at the entrance of Vergelegen, at
about 7km into an absolute epic Saturday late afternoon run.</p>
<p>It was epic, because the autumn weather was absolutely perfect, my running
mechanism was smooth and efficient, and there was great music piping into my
brain via the recently acquired JBL Endurance Run bluetooth earphones.</p>
<p>I mention the earphones specifically, because for the first time I had found
something that fit perfectly and even advertised being &ldquo;sweatproof&rdquo; on the box,
a characteristic that is quite important when you produce as much sweat as I
do. (TMI, but please bear with me here)</p>
<p>I was so satisfied after five or six runs that I had taken a few photos earlier
that day, as I was planning a short blog post extolling the virtues of said
gadget.</p>
<p>Probably about 60 seconds after I took the photo, running back out to the road,
thinking to myself how great these earphones were working and how far I was
still going to run and how amazing everything is, the right earphone starts
going &ldquo;GGGGGGGHHHHHRRRRRRRRGGGGGWWWWWGGGGHHHHHH&rdquo; (you have to read that with an
authentic, hard Dutch guttural) and it simply does not stop.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have you tried switching them off and on again?&rdquo; you might say.</p>
<p>Well, the sound just kept on going, switched on, or off.</p>
<p>No amount of power cycling, shaking, re-pairing or swearing made any
difference.</p>
<p>Right earphone just kept on going &ldquo;GGGGGGGHHHRRRRRGGGGHHHHH&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I finally bundled up the JBL TripSpoiler BT into my hand, and ran home, like a
person who runs without music.</p>
<p>P.S. The section title is a Depeche Mode song (one of my teenage favourites) in
which the highest mountain is contrasted with the deepest sea, albeit in a
utterly different context.</p>
<p>P.P.S. As I write this, takealot is sending me a replacement set. I&rsquo;m hoping
the new unit is an anti-lemon.</p>
<h2 id="pretty-hip-birthday-party">Pretty hip birthday party</h2>
<p>GOU #2 held her 11th party here at our facility.</p>
<p>The plans started out as a VR party (or at least that&rsquo;s what I thought), but
great forces out of my control determined that There Would Also Need to Be
Karaoke.</p>
<p>This is one time where the more technically inclined dads can shine!</p>
<p>I purchased exactly one cheap but great value Karaoke microphone (the Samson
SCR10S Karaoke Dynamic Microphone with Switch, if you must know), and then
mixed everything together using an old Windows laptop, our old burglary-proof
(when flat screens were still thick) TV with HDMI input, and a bunch of cables.</p>
<p>Friends arrived, and an extremely fun-looking and partially sugar-fuelled
teenage chaos ensued.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the VR setup ended up getting a significant chunk of the
attention. Even amongst these ultra-connected digital natives, the tech is
still new enough to garner a substantial amount of the unobtainium aka
attention.</p>
<p>(Although I never ever sing, not even in the shower, that karaoke setup has a
surprisingly strong magnetic force, if you catch my drift. GOU #2 was quite
relieved when none of her parents decided to make a guest appearance at the
main event. In my case, it&rsquo;s really for the better.)</p>
<h2 id="boomer-party">Boomer party</h2>
<p>A few days later, after we had sufficiently recovered from the teenage party,
it was time to invite long time friends of ours over for an old people party.</p>
<p>As is our wont down here, when the friends are this dear, we take time to make
a potjie.</p>
<p>The autumn weather contributed fabulously, and so we enjoyed scenes like this:</p>








<figure><a href="chicken-curry-potjie-2021.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: From this photo, it&amp;rsquo;s also quite clear that I have become much taller."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: From this photo, it&rsquo;s also quite clear that I have become much taller.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Readers of this blog might recognise the visual composition above, perhaps from
<a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/">a post back in January of 2016</a>, when I initiated the pot with coincidentally
the same recipe.</p>
<p>The potjie scene seems to repeat itself (these are not the only two examples),
acting as a sort of reliable cast iron backdrop (with enamel coating!) for our
family and friendship rituals.</p>
<p>On this day, the ritual was indeed sublime.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #196: Get focused</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 22:27:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</guid><description> Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&amp;rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&amp;rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&amp;rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.
Well hello there folks, please make yourself at home!
This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday May 18 to Sunday May 31 of the extremely strange year of 2020.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="sylvia_draws_family_20200531.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&amp;rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&amp;rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&amp;rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there folks, please make yourself at home!</p>
<p>This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday May 18 to Sunday May 31 of the
extremely strange year of 2020.</p>
<p>That effort of looking back has resulted in the following three items.</p>
<h2 id="when-building-automatic-analysis-pipelines-get-your-batch-accuracy-testing-up-as-soon-as-you-can">When building automatic analysis pipelines, get your batch accuracy testing up as soon as you can</h2>
<p>A substantial part of my work hours these past two weeks went into working on a
automatic medical image analysis pipeline, with machine learning
inside™. (I mean &ldquo;AI&rdquo;, of course. And drones.)</p>
<p>I really do love this stuff, but sometimes it ends up coming down to putting
your head down and keeping it down, in order to grind out every percent or two
in improved accuracy.</p>
<p>The tip I wanted to offer here is the following: Even when you think your
pipeline is way too far from &ldquo;done&rdquo;™, get your batch accuracy testing up
and running.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a double whammy:</p>
<ol>
<li>You and your team get early and regular feedback on how your performance is
going.</li>
<li>You are forced to have the whole concept working from end-to-end. It can be
surprising how many little issues you still need to solve, and running into
them sooner rather than later is only good.</li>
</ol>
<p>By the way, the practical machine learning icon <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew%5FNg">Professor Andrew Ng&rsquo;s</a> free book
<a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/machine-learning-yearning/">Machine Learning Yearning</a> is filled to the brim with practical tips for
implementing ML in practice.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">Lazar Focus: The super tiny Windows app and website distraction blocker that you&rsquo;ve always wanted</h2>
<p>Back at the <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">start of 2018 I wrote the following about the macOS app and website
distraction blocker called Focus</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>After years of resisting these types of software tools due to my belief that I
should simply apply more grit and will power to squeeze out more focus hours,
I finally broke down and purchased the macOS app called Focus. You click its
pretty icon, and then your computer goes into focus mode: The Mail application
and a bunch of other non-focus-related apps all get killed, and a bunch of
websites (reddit, youtube, work chat, etc) are blocked for a user-configurable
block of time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even if you skipped that extract, please read the following one about the
<em>idea</em> behind such a focus app:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It usually takes a single moment of weakness for a distraction to terminate a
valuable block of focus. It takes a single moment of strength for this tool to
start a valuable block of focus.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Anyways, I was really missing this functionality on Windows, and so I busted
out my trusty <a href="https://www.lazarus-ide.org/">Lazarus IDE</a> (who <em>didn&rsquo;t</em> make apps back in the day with the old
win32 Delphi?!) and figured out the various required Windows APIs to create
this brand new super tiny but super effective app and website blocker:</p>








<figure><a href="lazar_focused_screenshot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As shown in the screenshot, it&rsquo;s sitting at 5 MB of memory use. In the age of
Electron apps, that&rsquo;s really small.</p>
<p>When you activate focus mode, it&rsquo;ll prevent your browser (Chrome, Brave,
Firefox or Edge) from viewing any distracting website (you get to configure the
list) by redirecting to a local web page with an inspiring quote, e.g.:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Concentration can be cultivated. One can learn to exercise willpower,
discipline one&rsquo;s body and train one&rsquo;s mind. &ndash; Anil Ambani</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It will also terminate any distracting apps, and helpfully prevent you from
starting them up during your focus session.</p>
<p>The convenient progress bar shows how far you are on your way to a 25 minute
pomodoro, but that is purely for motivation, and not enforced.</p>
<p>The total focus blocks and hours at the top should also help to keep us
motivated and&hellip; <strong>LAZAR FOCUSED!</strong></p>
<p>So, because there are probably (hopefully?) at least two other people who&rsquo;ll
find this as useful as I do, and because shipping and selling software that you
made yourself is awesome especially when it&rsquo;s a hobby project, I have decided
to try and sell Lazar Focus using something like <a href="https://gumroad.com/">gumroad</a>.</p>
<p>Hopefully soon with a hobby hour or three I can finish the installer and the
website, and then make the beta available at a reduced rate.</p>
<p>Because I prefer it for apps like this when I am the buyer, I have decided to
make it available as a one-time purchase, no eval but money-back, with
time-limited upgrades (probably a year?), but with your last licensed version
obviously remaining fully functional until the end of The Windows API.</p>
<h2 id="art-fun-with-portrait-ai">Art fun with Portrait AI</h2>
<p>Ever since I spent a bit of time better curating my twitter subscriptions,
getting rid of the vitriol and adding much more STEM (shout out to <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Eric Topol</a>
&ndash; you could install twitter <em>just</em> for him and you would be great), they often
bring me shiny treasures.</p>
<p>Recently, it was <a href="https://portraitai.com/">portraitai.com</a> which brought a great deal of mirth to my home
as we made authentic looking portraits of each other. (We&rsquo;re just a bunch of
silly primates with amazing gadgets.)</p>
<p>It didn&rsquo;t seem to work all that well on me however, until I started pulling
funny faces:</p>








<figure><a href="charl_portraitai.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>With that, dear friends, I bid you kindness, happiness and health.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #193: COVID-19 part 3.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 15:33:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</guid><description> Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.
The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12 to Sunday May 2.
This post has a strong nerd flavour. If that is not your inclination, please use the table of contents (to your right) to navigate to the bits that you do find interesting.
If you&amp;rsquo;re in a rush, and can only select one section, I would recommend the one on Niklas Luhmann.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!--
2020-05-02 21:38 Boiler Room Solomun 2015 playing on the second screen while
I'm typing this.  I was hoping to understand why this has 43M views, and my
favourite boiler room of all time, Maceo Plex in Berlin in 2015, has "only"
11M.

Let me know in the comments if you read this. :)
-->
<p>The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12
to Sunday May 2.</p>
<p>This post has a strong nerd flavour. If that is not your inclination, please
use the table of contents (to your right) to navigate to the bits that you do
find interesting.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re in a rush, and can only select one section, I would recommend <a href="#the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">the
one on Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Have fun!</p>
<h2 id="covid-19-status-update">COVID-19 status update</h2>
<p>On Friday, May 1, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/lockdown-level-4-what-is-now-allowed-2020-4">the South African lockdown was slightly lifted from level 5
to level
4</a>.</p>
<p>This means that a part of the workforce will start returning to work, and that
citizens are allowed slightly more freedom of movement.</p>
<p>If safety had been the only requirement, we should probably have had to
continue with level 5 for a while longer, but that darned economy unfortunately
also has to be kept afloat.</p>
<p>In spite of this, I was super pleased to read the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Masks are obligatory.</strong> Everyone has to wear cloth face masks outside their
homes. If you don&rsquo;t yet have a cloth mask, you can wear a scarf or a t-shirt
wrapped around your mouth and nose, says Dlamini-Zuma.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This might end up being the thing that gets us through this in something that
resembles one piece.</p>
<p>The second announcement I was super happy with, was that we would be allowed
outside for exercise between 6 and 9 in the mornings.</p>
<p>So on Saturday morning I went out for my first post-level-5 run, ON THE
OUTSIDE. (It does feel strange going out on the street for the first time in
five weeks.)</p>
<p>The majority of people I saw actually had some form of face mask going on.</p>
<p>I had expected otherwise, because doing cardiorespiratory exercise with a mask
on is not easy, and people can be stubborn.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/advanced/a20842404/product-review-buff-headwear/">Buffs</a>
are these fantastically useful &ldquo;seamless tubular garments made from
high-performance microfibre&rdquo; that many runners swear by.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out you can <em>also</em> use them as as-running-proof-as-possible face
masks:</p>








<figure><a href="cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask_hu815c169f7dc006fef835eddef66e09fe_118854_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg"
            

         width="240"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>Pro-tip: If there&rsquo;s a runner in your life, and you&rsquo;re on the lookout for a
gift, just get them a buff. You can <em>never</em> have too many buffs.</p>
<h2 id="gou-2-is-10">GOU #2 is 10</h2>
<p>My most favourite middle child in the whole world recently hit the double
digits, and she was suitably chuffed with this.</p>
<p>It must be strange experiencing your 10th birthday under these truly surreal
conditions.</p>
<p>On the other hand, when you&rsquo;re 10, you probably don&rsquo;t dwell on thoughts like
that for too long.</p>
<h2 id="miscellaneous-catch-up">Miscellaneous catch-up</h2>
<p>In the past weeks, I wrote a number of other blog posts, started a new blog,
and discovered an obscure but fantastic new blogging tool.</p>
<p>Oh, and my expensive ergonomic keyboard broke.</p>
<h3 id="fantastic-blogging-tools-and-where-to-find-them">Fantastic blogging tools and where to find them</h3>
<p>It all started when I finally got around to exploring
<a href="https://ox-hugo.scripter.co/">ox-hugo</a>, the Emacs package for writing Hugo
posts using Org mode.</p>
<p>You might not recall this, but the mere <em>existence</em> of <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/#build-and-upload-the-new-static-hotness">ox-hugo was the reason
I chose
Hugo</a>
when it was time to leave Wordpress behind.</p>
<!--
Hey there friends reading these hidden messages!

There are multiple explicit and implicit streams of connection running through
these channels and it's lovely.

Anyways, it is now 22:44 and I finished the Solomun boiler room set.

There are indeed so many stories happening in those frames, many of which will
only become apparent after more viewings.

I'm now back to the Maceo Plex set, with a smile of recognition on my face.
-->
<p>Well, it turns out that, <em>if</em> you&rsquo;re an Emacs Org mode user, ox-hugo is pretty
close to blogging nirvana.</p>
<p>In the past few days, I&rsquo;ve used it to turn arbitrary Org mode entries from my
month journal into blog posts, to send the exact same Org mode file to two
different blogs with different sets of title and metadata, and to assert
Neo-in-the-matrix-style control over what goes where and how.</p>
<p>If I have to put my finger on the core of ox-hugo&rsquo;s extreme utility, I would
say that <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi">Kaushal Modi</a>, the brains behind
ox-hugo, has managed to create a perfect coupling between Org mode on the one
hand and Hugo on the other, a coupling that maximally leverages the strengths
of each.</p>
<p>(I will probably be writing more about this, but &hellip; elsewhere. <em>[queue
suspenseful music here]</em>)</p>
<h3 id="other-mostly-very-nerdy-blog-posts">Other mostly very nerdy blog posts</h3>
<p>As part of the ox-hugo investigation, I had to figure out how to <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/04/26/cite-consistently-between-org-ref-and-ox-hugo/">cite
consistently between straight Org mode and
ox-hugo</a>
for automatic bibtex-backed bibliographies.</p>
<p>Inspired by friend <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2020/04/28/voice-capture-org-tasks-on-android/">Stéfan&rsquo;s post on voice capturing and automatically
transcribing notes to Org
mode</a>,
I figured out how to <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/2020/04/30/voice-capture-org-mode-notes-and-more-using-siri-shortcuts-on-ios/">do the same on iOS and wrote it all
up</a>.</p>
<p>If you clicked on that second link, you will have discovered my brand new blog,
the hopefully catchily titled <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">Org Mode
Exocortex</a>. I will be posting <em>ultra</em>-nerdy Emacs
Org mode content over there.</p>
<p>(Friend Stéfan is the very first guest blogger, with a re-post of his Android
speech recognition post linked above. BTW, that was my first guest blogging
experience ever. Life for the Z-list blogger does not move fast.)</p>
<p>Finally, also thanks to ox-hugo&rsquo;s motivation, I figured (haha, now I see what I
did there) out how to make and publish a new <a href="/2020/05/02/drop-in-replacement-for-hugo-figure-shortcode-with-responsive-img-srcset/"><code>figure</code> shortcode for Hugo that
automatically resizes images and gets your browser to download only the best
one</a>!</p>
<h3 id="microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-desktop-at-4-years-rip">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic Desktop at 4 years: RIP</h3>
<p>After all of that good news, I do have to report the following not-so-great news:</p>
<p>After just under four years of approximately one half of my typing, the
<a href="/2016/05/22/weekly-head-voices-107-balance/">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboard I welcomed into my home at the start of
May of 2016</a>, has developed a key
failure.</p>
<p>More specifically, the physical &ldquo;G&rdquo;, which is my &ldquo;I&rdquo; (thanks
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dvorak_keyboard_layout">Dvorak</a>), fails about
30% of the time, with that duty cycle slowly growing.</p>
<p>(You may bring your jokes about why specifically the &ldquo;I&rdquo; is failing first to
the comment section below!)</p>
<p>I opened up the keyboard following <a href="http://emmanuelcontreras.com/how-to/how-to-disassemble-microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-keyboard-and-make-it-wired/">the instructions and photos of Emmanuel
Contreras</a>.</p>
<p>(What I can add to Contreras&rsquo;s information, is that the palm rest is held fast
by no less than 12 little screws, some odd-sized. Pro-tip: When you remove all
of these, put them down in the same pattern as the holes, so that you can get
them back in later.)</p>
<p>However, one unfortunately ends up at the metal backing which is attached to
the top-plate with about 30 or more plastic pop-rivet like mechanisms.</p>
<p>Information online also seems to indicate that once a single key goes, you have
to replace the whole board.</p>
<p>Some more searching brought me to <a href="https://youtu.be/x09inK8-G1Y">this obscure but helpful YouTube
review</a> where Kevin explains that although
everyone at his company loved the keyboard, they had simply accepted it as part
of their business expense to replace them every 6 months to a year.</p>
<p>If you search through <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Microsoft-Ergonomic-Keyboard-Business-5KV-00001/product-reviews/B00CYX26BC/ref=cm_cr_arp_d_viewopt_kywd?pageNumber=1&amp;filterByKeyword=durability">the Amazon reviews for
&ldquo;durability&rdquo;</a>,
it really starts to look like a case of a fantastic keyboard marred by issues
with its durability.</p>
<p>However, if you need a relatively affordable &ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; keyboard, where with
&ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; I mean shaped in such a way that your wrists get to stay more or
less straight while typing, with really great feel and low-impact typing, the
Sculpt comes out on top.</p>
<p>Although it goes against my grain, I should probably be happy with the above
average 4 years that this one managed, and start finding a local source for its
inevitable replacement.</p>
<p>Nerds in the audience: I am very curious to hear about your keyboard
preferences in the comments. Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="two-lessons-learnt-from-how-to-take-smart-notes">Two lessons learnt from How to Take Smart Notes</h2>
<p>On March 31 I quickly read through <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/34507927-how-to-take-smart-notes">Sönke Ahrens&rsquo;s book, How to Take Smart
Notes</a>.</p>
<p>(The full title is actually &ldquo;How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to
Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking &ndash; for Students, Academics and Nonfiction
Book Writers&rdquo;)</p>
<h3 id="the-most-portable-cross-platform-ebook-format-with-self-contained-annotations-is">The most portable cross-platform ebook format with self-contained annotations is&hellip;</h3>
<p>I bought the Kindle book on Amazon, because that&rsquo;s how I&rsquo;ve been doing it for
years.</p>
<p>However, although I prefer reading novels on my Kindle e-Ink device, for
reference works it&rsquo;s a deal breaker that my highlights and notes are not in a
standards compliant format that integrates nicely with <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing personal
knowledge management system</a>.</p>
<p>My goal was to find an alternative format for these books with the following features:</p>
<ul>
<li>Before you answer PDF, which I use extensively for academic papers, typeset
books, and many other things: The alternative format should be fully
reflowable, like the source Kindle book.</li>
<li>Readable and annotations editable on all my non-Kindle devices (Windows,
Linux, macOS, iOS).</li>
<li>Most importantly: Flexible annotations, including at least highlighting and
positional notes, that are stored within the file itself, so they can never
be lost.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t expect this to be too much of a challenge.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<p>After a number of hours spent spelunking down a number of different
rabbit-holes, with epub3 being the greatest disappointment (the spec has all
the features, but the implementations largely lack good annotation support), I
ended up in a place where you probably would not expect to find me&hellip;</p>
<p>Dear readers, the best format that satisfies all requirements above
is&hellip; <code>&lt;FRITS_DRUMROLL /&gt;</code> &hellip; <strong>Microsoft DOCX</strong>!</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been DeDRM&rsquo;ing (google it) the Kindle reference books I
purchase in order to be able to read and annotate them across all my platforms.</p>
<p>For this, the iPad is pretty great.</p>
<p>Once read, the DOCX files, including all of the annotations I made, are stored
in the correct place in my synchronised file hierarchy, and are fully
searchable and accessible with standard tools.</p>
<h3 id="the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">The amazing Niklas Luhmann and his Zettelkasten</h3>
<p>The book itself, <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em>, spends well-deserved time on the
phenomenon that was the prodigiously productive German sociologist Professor
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niklas_Luhmann">Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Over his career, Prof. Luhmann wrote more than 70 books and published almost
400 research articles.</p>
<p>He made a massive impact on the world of sociology and systems theory.</p>
<p>When asked in <a href="https://www.uni-bielefeld.de/soz/luhmann-archiv/pdf/jschmidt_zettelkasten-als-uberraschungsgenerator.pdf">a 1997
interview</a>
how he managed to this productive, he answered:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Ich denke ja nicht alles allein, sondern das
geschieht weitgehend im Zettelkasten. [&hellip;]
Meine Produktivität ist im wesentlichen aus dem
Zettelkasten-System zu erklären. [&hellip;]
Der Zettelkasten kostet mich mehr Zeit als das
Bücherschreiben</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Translated this is probably something like (German readers, help me out here
please):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think everything by myself, but that largely happens in the slip box. [&hellip;]
My productivity is essentially due to that slipbox system. [..]
The slipbox costs me more time than that writing books</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <em>zettelkasten</em> he referred to were quite simply a set of wooden slipboxes,
in which he could store pieces of paper (the &ldquo;slips&rdquo;), each of which had a
single idea written on it.</p>
<p>It looked more or less exactly like this:</p>








<figure><a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu61195ac08eb6003207b1b95bfe6dfa0b_91461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu61195ac08eb6003207b1b95bfe6dfa0b_91461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu61195ac08eb6003207b1b95bfe6dfa0b_91461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Photo of Luhmann&amp;rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Photo of Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Over the course of his career, he managed to write about 90000 (yes, ninety
thousand) of these notes, all of which you can now <a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">browse online at the Niklas
Luhmann-Archiv</a>.</p>
<p>Importantly, he had come up with an ingenious numbering system for linking each
new note to its chain of predecessors, and also to other related chains
anywhere in the zettelkasten.</p>
<p>When it was time to write a book or a paper, he would dive into his this
collection, and then take a stroll through his amazing web of interlinked
thoughts, some of them having matured for years.</p>
<p>Putting together the publication became an exercise in harvesting index cards
from his slipboxes, instead of a positively intimidating mountain of writing,
thinking and rewriting.</p>
<p>This is such a boss-level example of the principle of
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/compounding/">compounding</a>, and one which is
definitely worth trying to follow.</p>
<p>Since reading Ahrens&rsquo;s book, I have started extending <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing note-taking
universe</a> to be more Zettelkasten-like,
when appropriate.</p>
<p>Org mode is a great basis for this, and packages like
<a href="https://github.com/jethrokuan/org-roam">org-roam</a> help us to get closer to our
90-thousand-notes-dreams.</p>
<p>On a higher level, I have been thinking and writing a great deal about how to
merge effectively the Zettelkasten one-idea-per-note approach into the full
spectrum of writing complexity that Org mode supports.</p>
<p>It is important to be mindful of the <em>mode</em> of documentation that you need to
apply at any give point.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about the Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten, <a href="https://writingcooperative.com/zettelkasten-how-one-german-scholar-was-so-freakishly-productive-997e4e0ca125">this Writing
Cooperative article in
English</a>
and <a href="https://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Missing-Link-Luhmanns-Denkmaschine-endlich-im-Netz-4364512.html">this Heise article in
German</a>
are a great start.</p>
<p>This might not be the last time that you&rsquo;ll hear me talking about Luhmann and
his Zettelkasten.</p>
<h2 id="uitzwaaien">Uitzwaaien</h2>
<p>Thank you friends for reading this and connecting with me here!</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>