<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>solstice on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/solstice/</link><description>Recent content in solstice on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 17:18:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/solstice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #244: Biyamiti Bat-Fan</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 17:18:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/</guid><description> Welcome to Weekly Head Voices number 244, stretching from Monday June 20 to Sunday July 24, 2022.
Winter, don&amp;rsquo;t call us, we&amp;rsquo;ll call you Shortly after the start of this period, June 21 to be exact, I was frankly and quite pleasantly surprised by the Southern Hemisphere winter solstice.
This handy Time and Date website has more details, including but not limited to:
The June solstice (winter solstice) in Cape Town is at 11:13 on Tuesday, 21 June 2022.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to Weekly Head Voices number 244, stretching from Monday June 20 to
Sunday July 24,  2022.</p>








<figure><a href="giraffe.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="winter-don-t-call-us-we-ll-call-you">Winter, don&rsquo;t call us, we&rsquo;ll call you</h2>
<p>Shortly after the start of this period, June 21 to be exact, I was frankly and
quite pleasantly surprised by the Southern Hemisphere winter solstice.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-AFRICA/cape-town">This handy Time and Date website</a> has more details, including but not limited
to:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The June solstice (winter solstice) in Cape Town is at 11:13 on Tuesday, 21
June 2022. In terms of daylight, this day is 4 hours, 32 minutes shorter than
the December solstice. In locations south of the equator, the shortest day of
the year is around this date.</p>
<p>The earliest sunset is on 12 June. The latest sunrise is on 29 June or 30 June.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some of you <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">might remember</a> that this is an important point in the year for me,
the moment when I can see the big light, namely summer, at the end of the
tunnel.</p>
<h2 id="projections">Projections</h2>
<p>I recently finished reading the book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/55411738-projections"><em>Projections: A Story of Human Emotions</em>
by Karl Deisseroth</a>.</p>
<p>As a layperson, I found this psychiatrist and world-changing scientist&rsquo;s view
of the world, and especially of the psyches of his patients, absolutely
fascinating.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Deisseroth">Deisseroth</a> writes about several different types of psychiatric disorders, but
does so via specific but (probably) fictional patients who embody the important
aspects of the disorder in question.</p>
<p>He also writes about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optogenetics">Optogenetics</a>.</p>
<p>Optogenetics is a technique, invented by Deisseroth, for controlling neurons
with lasers, <em>in vivo</em>.</p>
<p>More specifically, by inserting specific genes from algae, neurons can be
modified to activate when struck by light.</p>
<p>Using this technique, researchers are able to activate very specific subsets of
neurons in mice brains, making the mice feel anxious for example, or
comfortable, or any of the different neural components making up these mental
states.</p>
<p>From the Wikpedia artictle:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In systems neuroscience, the ability to control the activity of a genetically
defined set of neurons has been used to understand their contribution to
decision making, learning, fear memory, mating, addiction, feeding, and
locomotion.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The use of this technique has already contributed significantly to our
fundamental understanding of the brain, and the first steps have been taken
towards using it in therapy.</p>
<p>Judging by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optogenetics#Awards">the list of awards</a>, the scientific world has really noticed the
value of this work.</p>
<p>Personally, I am optimistic that there&rsquo;s much more to come.</p>
<p>P.S. Close to the end of <a href="https://lexfridman.com/karl-deisseroth/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Deisseroth</a>, Deisseroth
mentioned that he really doubts whether he has done enough&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="batting-for-biyamiti">Batting for Biyamiti</h2>
<p>I am Bat-Fan.</p>
<p>No really, I appreciate bats. (and puns)</p>
<p>They&rsquo;re little flying mammals who see and navigate the world <em>expertly</em> using
echolocation (just imagine what that <em>feels</em> like?!) . They eat large numbers of
insects, including a <a href="https://news.wisc.edu/study-bolsters-bats-reputation-as-mosquito-devourers/">debatable</a> number of mosquitoes (I did not know about the
debate until right now).</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s not to like?</p>
<p>However, during our recent freshly reinstated yearly <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/">KNP break</a>, we enjoyed
fantastic summer weather (it&rsquo;s winter down here, but that&rsquo;s Mpumalanga for
you), we spent one night in Biyamiti with a pretty active bat in the room.</p>
<p>As we went to sleep, we thought that it would probably be ok.</p>
<p>It was not.</p>
<p>In addition to the bat expertly dropping something wet in my eye (your guess is
as good as mine), during parts of the night it started doing fly-bys so close
to our faces that we could feel the discrete wind gusts caused by the flapping
of its little wings.</p>
<p>On the one hand I was quite impressed by its sheer <em>mammalian</em> skill, but on
the other we just really wanted to sleep.</p>
<p>We decided that the price of a few extra insects in the room was worth it, and
so we opened the mesh.</p>
<p>Our bat friend, in spite of apparently having built a little nest in the nook
right up in the apex of the roof, fortunately obliged by exiting to perform the
rest of its manouevres outside in the night.</p>








<figure><a href="sunset-crocodile-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: The sun sets over the Crocodile. Nothing else matters."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>The sun sets over the Crocodile. Nothing else matters.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #226: Stress practice</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 16:07:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</guid><description> Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.
Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.
As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&amp;rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (Youth Day), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth Emacs Org-mode / ox-hugo blogging machine (read this github issue for more details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this combination has saved me in the past.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the
week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys_run_pano_20210612.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (<a href="https://www.gov.za/youth-day">Youth
Day</a>), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth
Emacs Org-mode / <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo">ox-hugo</a> blogging machine (read <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo/issues/447">this github issue</a> for more
details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this
combination has saved me in the past.</p>
<h2 id="solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">Solstice tipping point is coming!</h2>
<p>The last thing we&rsquo;re supposed to do is to wish even just a little bit for time
to pass more quickly, for fairly obvious reasons.</p>
<p>However, when you&rsquo;re a few days from the darkest point in the year, it&rsquo;s hard
not to.</p>
<p>We currently have 9 hours and 56 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s just two minutes, and a few days, from the winter solstice on June 21,
when we&rsquo;ll have to make do with 9 hours and 54 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>I mention this here, because those 6 AM wake-ups feel more and more like the
middle of the night.</p>
<p>After the solstice, I&rsquo;ll start imagining the sun coming up a few moments
earlier every morning, and it will.</p>
<p>(Well, it will, eventually. Reader WIMM just pointed out via email that
although the days start getting longer, the sunrise will initially become even
a minute later, before finally becoming earlier starting from July 11. Read
more <a href="https://theconversation.com/why-the-sunrise-is-still-later-after-the-winter-solstice-shortest-day-77628">here</a> (thanks WIMM) or check the tables <a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-africa/stellenbosch?month=6&amp;year=2021">here</a>.)</p>
<p>It has been &hellip; <code>1 year and 11 months</code> &hellip; since <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/">the previous mention of winter
solstice on this blog</a>.</p>
<h2 id="avoid-the-jbl-endurance-run-bt-earphones-at-all-costs">Avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones at all costs</h2>
<p>A month ago <a href="/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/#world-in-my-eyes">I wrote about the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a> that I was
initially so happy with, which then spontaneously broke after a few hours of
running, and which I then returned for a replacement.</p>
<p>Well, the replacement set of <a href="https://eu.jbl.com/JBL+ENDURANCE+RUNBT.html?dwvar%5FJBL%20ENDURANCE%20RUNBT%5Fcolor=Black-GLOBAL-Current">proudly sweat-proof JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a>
lasted for about 9 hours of running, at which point they spontaneously broke in
exactly the same way.</p>
<p>Out of nowhere, the loud crackling sound started in the earpiece opposite to
the site with the control unit.</p>
<p>This crackling sound (similar to the disturbance you hear when speaker wires
have a connection issue) did not stop, even after un-pairing and even after
switching off the unit.</p>
<p>Connecting the charger after this would result in the charge light flickering
and fading in-and-out in a decidedly analogue fashion.</p>
<p>After experiencing the exact same problem with two different units, I am wary
wasting more time on a third set.</p>
<p>This was quite a disappointment, because mechanically this design was perfect
for me.</p>
<p>I will continue on my search for the perfect (1. secure in my large and
sometimes perspiring ears, so needs something in addition to just ear canal fit
and 2. durable, i.e. continues working <em>long</em> after the first 9 hours of
running) set of running earphones, and I&rsquo;ll keep you up to date on my findings.</p>
<p>In the meantime, please avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones.</p>
<h2 id="remote-work-culture-is-hard-work">Remote work culture is hard work</h2>
<p>During our Tuesday evening meetup, Theunis de Klerk of <a href="https://www.noldor.co.za/">Noldor</a> (the now fully
remote tech company, not <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noldor">the race of elves from Middle Earth</a>, although there is
a link here) gave an interesting and inspiring talk on how they have built and
cultivate great remote work culture.</p>
<p>This was an insightful look into an organization where the top leadership
continuously pours a great deal of thought and energy into maintaining healthy
culture, even in a fully remote environment with parts in different timezones.</p>
<p>On the one hand, it&rsquo;s great seeing working examples like this, on the other, it
can be quite a daunting prospect when you start thinking about how to apply
this in your own environment.</p>
<p>I believe that the future of knowledge work will <em>not</em> involve highly qualified
folks having to spend 8 hours per day at their desk because we still have not
learned that work is all about contributing value, and not about the number of
hours spent in captivity at one&rsquo;s desk.</p>
<p>That being said, during the current global remote working experiment, although
we are learning how to roll with value-generation, I do miss some of the almost
effortlessly and socially generated collaboration glue that at its best gets
folks almost instinctively chasing the same worthy goals.</p>
<p>(On the other hand, at its worst, it causes conflicts, grudges and ulcers, so
there&rsquo;s that&hellip;)</p>
<p>I would like to wrap this ramble up with one conclusion, and one interesting
tweet storm by Steven Sinofsky of Andreesen Horowitz:</p>
<ul>
<li>Conclusion: 1. Am I overestimating how &ldquo;easy&rdquo; social cohesion was when we
were in the office? 2. How do we go about getting back that real or imagined
social cohesion in this fully remote setting?</li>
<li><a href="https://a16z.com/2021/06/12/disruption-at-work-its-more-than-just-wfh/">Highly interesting tweet storm about the issue being larger and more
intricate than just WFH vs hybrid vs HQ</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="eternal-practice-vs-stress">Eternal practice vs stress</h2>
<p>I do need to note here (for future me) that I was consistently far grumpier
than usual for the last few days of the week under examination here.</p>
<p>When I say grumpy, I do mean quite detectably so.</p>
<p>This is definitely not my preferred state, so I&rsquo;m even meta-grumpy about that.</p>
<p>My retro- and introspection during the weekend came up with &ldquo;more stress than
usual&rdquo;, which is indeed probably a main contributor (wow, thanks work).</p>
<p>However, being grumpy or not is still fully my responsibility.</p>
<p>Increased stress at work is currently primarily due to new responsibilities and
the (often amplified by one&rsquo;s own imagination) expectations of colleagues, and
the unsurprising feeling of discomfort that is associated with finding oneself
faced with new kinds of challenges that you are not accustomed to (<em>cf.</em>
&ldquo;comfort zone&rdquo; and <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">stages 2 to 4 of the creative process</a>).</p>
<p>During the weekend I first resolved simply to be less grumpy (yes, you can do
that).</p>
<p>Fortunately, I also had a spot of insight as to how the root cause, i.e. the
work-related stress, could be better addressed in my specific case.</p>
<p>You see, I have chosen to be in this situation. I would have preferred the new
challenges without the concomitant stress, but that&rsquo;s unfortunately not how
<em>this</em> human normally works.</p>
<p>The realisation that I had was that this too is simply part of my lifelong
practice session.</p>
<p>I first talked about the idea of life being continuous pracrtice back in <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">WHV
#133</a>, and again later in <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">WHV #144</a> when I got around to reading a
reader-recommended book on the topic, titled &ldquo;Mastery&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Something I did not mention back then, probably because I only experience the
stress aspect as acutely at this moment, is that this particular framing helps
me to approach my current problems with curiosity, with an appetite for
learning and experimentation, and with the acceptance that my performance could
be far from perfect, perhaps even to the point of failure.</p>
<p>Some days will be good and some days will be bad.</p>
<p>(Even outside of the practice framing, one just has to accept that <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"><em>some days
gonna be crap</em></a>.)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, every day is a brand new opportunity to practice the
difficult new stuff, and to become gradually better at it, until one day, just
maybe, comfort slowly starts overtaking discomfort.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>