<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>github on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/github/</link><description>Recent content in github on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 21:38:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/github/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #232: Side-project Smorgasbord</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 21:38:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from a park not too far from my house.
Welcome back friends to WHV #232, looking back at the two weeks from Monday August 30 to Sunday September 13, both fortunately in the year 2021.
Give me some more of that mRNA I&amp;rsquo;m happy to report that I got my second Pfizer shot at the start of this month, at the Somerset West Town Hall.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="view_from_park.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/view_from_park_hud87debf419de22c5f031862a85d5f195_1069519_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a park not too far from my house."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a park not too far from my house.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome back friends to WHV #232, looking back at the two weeks from Monday
August 30 to Sunday September 13, both fortunately in the year 2021.</p>
<h2 id="give-me-some-more-of-that-mrna">Give me some more of that mRNA</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m happy to report that I got my second Pfizer shot at the start of this
month, at the Somerset West Town Hall.</p>
<p>The whole procedure took 30 minutes, from when I entered the front door, until
I exited after the 15 minute wait in the side-effect area with friend LM, at
which point I unfortunately jammed my shoulder on an inconveniently positioned
aloe branch, an event that under normal circumstances would not even have been
worth a mention, were it not for the fact that I was wearing my fortunately
entry-level puffer jacket, which now sports a gash with stuffing peeking out.</p>
<p>I believe that I digressed ever so slightly there.</p>
<p>Anyways&hellip;</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m super happy that all of the adults in my close family unit have now been
vaccinated, and grateful for the superbly efficient way in which this could
come to pass.</p>
<h2 id="this-blog-hopefully-immortalised-on-github">This blog hopefully immortalised on github</h2>
<p>(aka you can never escape)</p>
<p>At a recent meetup, I brought up the cheerful topic of what happens to one&rsquo;s
website(s) when one invariably gets to kick the proverbial bucket.</p>
<p>This is probably a pretty abstract concept to many folks, but as I&rsquo;m now
getting within spitting distance of my half century, it is something that I do
think about now and then.</p>
<p>The thing is, when my credit card finally decides to stop paying the monthly
Hetzner bill (at this moment, <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">these pages are served by a Hetzner VPS in
Nuremburg</a>), they will pull the plug.</p>
<p>Even if they don&rsquo;t do so immediately, cpbotha.net&rsquo;s domain registrar will for
related reasons unplug the domain as it were, rendering this site unreachable.</p>
<p>Now that I think about this some more, the shadowy company paying for all of
this has been setup in a pretty robust fashion. It&rsquo;s not quite <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accelerando">Accelerando</a>
levels of indirection, but it could remain standing and paying for hosting and
domains somewhat longer than expected.</p>
<p>In spite of that, for the one or two people who might want to read some of this
content after I&rsquo;m gone (close family members, I&rsquo;m looking right at you!), I
really wanted to have some sort of more long-term backup plan in place, in
addition to what <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/*/cpbotha.net">the wonderful Wayback Machine is already doing</a>.</p>
<p>The solution I decided upon was to spend a great many hours going through 20
years of cpbotha.net posts, mostly to fix all of the badly linked legacy
wordpress figure sections, so that the whole thing could be pushed
to&hellip; <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/cpbotha.net">github</a>!</p>
<p>Yep, you heard me right&hellip;</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve taken care of the bulk of rewriting, mostly through putting together <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/cpbotha.net/blob/main/mine/convert%5Fwp%5Ffigures.py">this
horrible script</a>, and manually reviewing the diffs, sometimes applying fixes, to
over 600 files.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/">Beautifulsoup 4</a> is amazing by the way. Wordpress on the other hand, or rather
wordpress plugins, just made so many random changes to figure markup over the
years that I&rsquo;m not really sure what to think anymore.</p>
<p>Anyways, most of the markdown content, which has been thankfully simplified, is
now on the github and should remain available for significantly longer in the
hopefully far future event of my demise.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to spend some more hours to get the whole thing also buildable on
github so that there&rsquo;s a browsable version in addition to just the markdown
sources.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I hope that I can keep this site alive, and maybe even
kicking, for at least twenty more years!</p>
<h2 id="on-always-maintaining-a-menu-of-tasty-side-projects">On always maintaining a menu of tasty side-projects</h2>
<p>Oh <a href="/tags/side-projects/">side-projects</a>&hellip;</p>
<p>As I&rsquo;ve mentioned before, we side-project for learning and for relaxation.</p>
<p>In addition to that, we also often lament the apparent cost of these
side-projects, with some of us even having whole side-project graveyards to
show for our sins.</p>
<p>On the basis of what I just said, one might think it prudent to try and avoid
these clearly nefarious side-projects, or maybe just to try and reduce their
impact as much as possible, but of course we&rsquo;ll do nothing of the sort.</p>
<p>Instead, we&rsquo;re going to double down.</p>
<p>You see, the other day I figured out that my problem with side-projects was
clearly that I didn&rsquo;t have enough of them.</p>
<p>Ideally, one has a whole menu of tasty side-projects lined up, each one a
different mix of activity types and learnings.</p>
<p>Whenever you have a bit of free time (<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2021/sep/09/study-links-too-much-free-time-to-lower-sense-of-wellbeing">not too much though!</a>), you can <em>quite</em>
simply select the most suitable side-project from your list and hammer away for
a bit.</p>
<p>Of course you will need a substantial amount of willpower, as well as the
presence of mind to actually initiate this selection action&hellip;</p>
<p>Somewhat more seriously though, always having a creative and fitting project
closely at hand that you can <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a> upon sounds like a solid strategy.</p>
<p>(err, a solid strategy for what exactly? well that&rsquo;s a topic for a future post&hellip;)</p>
<p>In the meantime:</p>
<p>LONG LIVE  YOUR GROWING MULTITUDE OF SIDE-PROJECTS!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>