<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Create Value on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/create-value/</link><description>Recent content in Create Value on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2011 21:11:46 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/create-value/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Happiness slingshot. [Weekly Head Voices #61]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/05/happiness-slingshot-weekly-head-voices-61/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2011 21:11:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/05/happiness-slingshot-weekly-head-voices-61/</guid><description>Make sure you won’t be disturbed for the next 2 minutes and 57 seconds, and then focus your full attention on this marvelous YouTube clip:
Yes people, there are apparently some brilliant human beings, the pinnacle of our society you might say, who took the time to construct a giant slingshot with which they then proceeded to shoot each other through the blue summer sky. This is the sign that we, the human race, must be doing something right.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Make sure you won’t be disturbed for the next 2 minutes and 57 seconds, and then focus your full attention on this marvelous YouTube clip:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/y_wkQBDDgvI?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Yes people, there are apparently some brilliant human beings, the pinnacle of our society you might say, who took the time to construct a giant slingshot with which they then proceeded to shoot each other through the blue summer sky. This is the sign that we, the human race, <em>must be doing something right</em>.</p>
<p>Because I need all the time that I can get to play may part in being a good human, I will now switch to Bullet Time(tm):</p>
<ul>
<li>IEEE VisWeek 2011, Mind-Blowingly Awesome Visualization Conference, took place in week 43. For the first time in years, I was NOT there. The <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">TNR</a> went and came back inspired. My fearless and revered ex-leader Frits Post received the IEEE VGTC Visualization Career Award, which is yet another official recognition of his awesomeness. I hope he still has some space on the mantelpiece next to the Eurographics Honorary Fellow award.</li>
<li>Through the <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/search?q=%23visweek" title="#visweek twitter stream">#visweek conference twitter stream</a> and some of the blogging that was going on, I was able to follow the conference at a distance. There was a Blogging about Visualization BoF (birds of a feather, a kind of informal meeting to discuss some topic of interest; also read <a href="http://bowr.de/blog/?p=291" title="Dominikus Baur's report on the visweek blogging BoF">Dominikus Baur’s blog report</a>), which motivated me to revive <a href="http://medvis.org/" title="medvis.org blog">the MedVis.org webblog</a>! We even have a <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/medvisorg" title="medvis.org twitter account">twitter account now</a>. If you have even a mild interest in medical visualisation or imaging, please subscribe via email, your RSS reader or <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/medvisorg" title="medvis.org twitter account">the twitter account</a>.</li>
<li>This blog won one of <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/2011/10/26/sa-blog-awards-2011/" title="Joe's official SA blog awards">Joe’s official SA Blog Awards</a>! Buy me a beer when you see me.</li>
<li>A real Italian explained to me that putting sugar in your espresso is entirely acceptable and even desirable. Herewith I’m going to stop feeling ashamed about my sugar-in-espresso habit. I’m not sure what I was thinking that combining two of the best substances known to humans was a sin.</li>
<li>After spending some serious quality time with <a href="http://emailga.me/" title="The Email Game">The Email Game</a>, I wrestled both of my overgrown inboxes to the ground. Lessons learnt: 1) Even the thin layer of gamification offered by The Email Game was sufficient to motivate me to start and finish a task I’ve been dreading for weeks. 2) Inbox Zero actually is more important than I’ve recently come to think. The trick is deciding when exactly you’re going to empty it.</li>
<li>Here’s a picture of a hedgehog after a bath:</li>
</ul>
<div>
<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 333px"><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/justinandelise/4234874994/"><img alt="" height="500" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2759/4234874994_9cbf4fbf35.jpg" title="Hedgehog after a bath, found on BoingBoing." width="333"/></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">It's a hedgehog. After a bath!</figcaption></figure>
</div>
<p>So recently I was having a conversation with someone in a bar. Soon the question came up: <em>What are you striving for in your work?</em></p>
<p>Imagine my surprise when I didn’t have an answer ready. I was surprised, because I usually spend a significant amount of time on introspection, pondering the usual questions:</p>
<ol>
<li>What makes me happy?</li>
<li>Why are we here?</li>
<li>What should I strive for?</li>
</ol>
<p>I mostly have answers to all of these and more, often involving coffee drinking in some form, along with a healthy dose of perspective, and harmony. However, due to general work-related business the past few months, my moments of introspection have been few and far between. As is the case with these types of philosophical guidelines, one does need to spend time regularly pondering them, else they sink quickly deeper below the surface of everyday life.</p>
<p>So I spent some time trying to remember what it was that I was striving for in work. Fortunately, not that far below the surface, I found it again:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Create value.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That’s really all there is, but it works for me.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>