<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>gaba on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gaba/</link><description>Recent content in gaba on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 11:17:09 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gaba/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #109: GABA</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 11:17:09 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/</guid><description> From now on, I would like to limit WHVs to bullets (really) or to named sections, to ease reading. DOWN WITH WALLS OF TEXT! After a multi-year, completely coincidental, break from medical imaging, I am back to The Real Business since the start of July. I am super excited about the plans we’re cooking up and executing. I can obviously not say too much, unless beer is involved, or you hang around here for muuuuuch longer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>From now on, I would like to limit WHVs to bullets (really) or to named sections, to ease reading. DOWN WITH WALLS OF TEXT!</li>
<li>After a multi-year, completely coincidental, break from <strong>medical imaging</strong>, I am back to <em>The Real Business</em> since the start of July. I am super excited about the plans we’re cooking up and executing. I can obviously not say too much, unless beer is involved, or you hang around here for muuuuuch longer. I think I am allowed to mention <strong>digital pathology</strong> and <strong>machine learning</strong> and beer.</li>
<li>Last week we <strong>road-tripped up the East Coast to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Francis_Bay">St Francis Bay</a></strong>, via Oudtshoorn and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cango_Caves">Cango Caves</a>.
<ul>
<li>Pro tip: When road tripping with more than 0 (zero) children (babies count double; sick babies +5 hit points), and you have to stay overnight somewhere, invest extra in the biggest suite you (or your children’s college fund) can afford.</li>
<li>On the beach in St Francis Bay (right in the middle of winter, you still seem to get these lovely balmy beach days), it seemed that <em>everybody</em> was surfing. Whole families, with the mom, the dad, all the kids, and grandma and grandpa, were all on various sizes of surfboards in the sea catching some waves.</li>
<li>Here’s a photo from the furthest point on what I call “Not The Ugliest Jogging Route in The World” (in St Francis Bay):</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/20160714_170901.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/20160714_170901-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<ul>
<li>Last night I accidentally discovered that I can pinpoint the exact weekend and location when and where I first tasted my <strong>favourite <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trappist_beer">trappist beer</a> (EVER)</strong>, namely Rochefort #8. It’s all written up in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/">this 2003 post</a>.</li>
<li>When Google send me an email this weekend asking me exactly <em>how</em> I would like them to use my email (yes, a few months ago I migrated my mail empire back to Google because <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">my self-hosting experiment</a> had started to cost me time and money) to show me custom advertisements, I was reminded that I do actually find the machine learning models they’re building about me quite creepy, and that perhaps I would prefer not also handing them 12 years of emails to make their models more accurate. There and then <strong>I migrated said 12 years of emails from GMail to <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/">FastMail</a></strong>. So far I’m really impressed by the product, mostly due to the speed and the user experience of the web-app. There might be a more detailed post in the near future, let me know if you’re interested.</li>
<li><em>Most surprising and interesting (to me) new scientific discovery of the week:</em> A team of scientists at Northeastern University in Boston <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/2095769-gut-bacteria-spotted-eating-brain-chemicals-for-the-first-time/">have shown</a> that <strong>one of the many kinds of bacteria living in your stomach eats exclusively <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-Aminobutyric_acid">GABA</a></strong>, a really important brain chemical (neurotransmitter) that plays a role in keeping you calm. Based on this and other work, it looks like the bacteria in your tummy, also known as your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gut_flora">gastrointestinal microbiota</a>, besides being crucially important to your digestive system and your general survival, probably also play quite an important role in your psyche. I find this slightly mind-blowing.</li>
</ul>
<p>Have a great week kids, I hope to see you on the other side.</p>
<p>P.S. Those bullets made for quite an impressive wall of text, didn’t they?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>