<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Visweek on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/visweek/</link><description>Recent content in Visweek on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 22:05:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/visweek/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #182: Can you predict what ...</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 22:05:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/</guid><description>Welcome to your home away from home folks!
This, the one hundred and eighty second edition of the WHV, looks back at the three weeks from Monday October 14 to Sunday November 3, 2019.
One of the beautiful views from our Sunday (October 20) lunch at Mont Marie in Stellenbosch. On attempting to publish the WHV on a weekly basis. Somewhere at the end of the first week, I sat down to write, but I soon realised that I didn&amp;rsquo;t have all that much to say.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to your home away from home folks!</p>
<p>This, the one hundred and eighty second edition of the WHV, looks back at the
three weeks from Monday October 14 to Sunday November 3, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_view_from_lunch.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_view_from_lunch_hu_b18df94a3176e511.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_view_from_lunch_hu_5d1d92a52979446.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_view_from_lunch_hu_25d0475ab0ceb2c4.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_view_from_lunch_hu_c6de80d9ab810760.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_view_from_lunch_hu_5d1d92a52979446.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
One of the beautiful views from our Sunday (October 20) lunch at Mont Marie in Stellenbosch.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="on-attempting-to-publish-the-whv-on-a-weekly-basis">On attempting to publish the WHV on a weekly basis.</h2>
<p>Somewhere at the end of the first week, I sat down to write, but I soon
realised that I didn&rsquo;t have all that much to say.</p>
<p>Ironically, earlier that day I had had an online discussion where I made the
statement that I preferred putting out posts regularly, rather than waiting
until until I had something &ldquo;really good&rdquo; to publish.</p>
<p>In the latter case, one tends to let things slip further and further, with that
great internal excuse that one&rsquo;s ideas and writing do not yet satisfy one&rsquo;s
otherwise unspecified but high standards.</p>
<p>In addition, one&rsquo;s performance anxiety is now fueled into a frenzy by the
illusion that surely the expectations of one&rsquo;s audience are growing greater by
the minute, and hence the next post will be measured even more strictly against
the mythical yard stick of blog posts that in reality very few people, mostly
friends, actually take the time to read.</p>
<p>So that happened.</p>
<p>As is the case with many other things in life that seem to follow the Sisyphean
ideal, I have made peace with the fact that I will just continue working at
this, until the end.</p>
<h2 id="a-call-from-the-future">A call from the future.</h2>
<p>I made three longer term technology-themed bets with friends and colleagues at
the IEEE VisWeek conference in 2009.</p>
<p>The idea was that the first of the three would play out and finally be
evaluated at VisWeek 2019 (10 years later), and the other two more or less 20
years later, to be decided at Visweek 2029.</p>
<p>Fortunately I wrote the bets up in a blog post, all the way back in 2009,
titled <a href="/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/">Futuristic Betting at VisWeek
2009</a>.</p>
<p>To my surprise, but far more to my delight, an overlapping subset of the
involved friends and colleagues recorded an hour-long video message at <a href="http://ieeevis.org/year/2019/welcome">VisWeek
2019 in Vancouver</a> and sent it to me via
the YouTubes.</p>
<p>The main message of their video was that I had lost bet #1, with which I could
agree, and that they had their doubts about my chances in bets #2 and #3, with
which I can not yet agree.</p>
<p>You can read <a href="/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/#update-on-2019-10-27">the addendum I made to the original blog
post</a> for
all of the details.</p>
<p>When I made those predictions, confident that we would be able to debate and
laugh about them at those future conferences, I ironically had no idea that my
life was going to take the turns that it did, <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">out of
academia</a> and
shortly thereafter <a href="/2013/12/14/on-leaving-the-netherlands/">out of Europe</a>.</p>
<p>Fortunately, that futuristic betting blog post seems to have functioned as a
sort of anchor in the sands of time, playing its small part in making the
connection from 2009 to 2019, from Atlantic City to Vancouver and even to
Somerset West.</p>
<p>What will happen in 2029?</p>
<h2 id="humans-predicting-the-world-in-real-time">Humans predicting the world in real-time.</h2>
<p>Based on <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2019-10/sisd-py101419.php">this recent EEG-based experimental
study</a>, it
sounds like our brains are continuously predicting the next word that someone
we&rsquo;re in conversation with is going to say.</p>
<p>Especially in noisy environments, such as IN DA CLUB, this helps us to
understand what our conversation partners are saying.</p>
<p>What struck me when I read the linked press release, and shortly thereafter
tried to assimilate <a href="https://www.eneuro.org/content/6/5/ENEURO.0128-19.2019">the full
article</a>, quite
attractively titled <em>Neural Signal to Violations of Abstract Rules Using
Speech-Like Stimuli</em>, was that is exactly what computer-based language models
do.</p>
<p><em>Language models</em> are mathematical constructs, which mostly live in software,
that attempt to predict the next word in a sentence, based on the previous
words in a sequence.</p>
<p>Recently, <a href="http://www.fit.vutbr.cz/research/groups/speech/publi/2010/mikolov_interspeech2010_IS100722.pdf">deep learning approaches overtook the more classical statistical
approaches for building such language
models</a>.</p>
<p>Given a few thousand articles in French for example, a neural network can learn
how to predict the next word in any given French sentence with high accuracy.</p>
<p>Together with the fact that the internet is now overflowing with examples of
many human languages, anyone with some spare time and GPU cycles to burn can
train up a language model, or even download a pre-trained example.</p>
<p>Such a language model can then be
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1801.06146">fine-tuned</a> for other language tasks such as
sentiment analysis and topic classification.</p>
<p>I enjoyed seeing this (growing) similarity between our built-in language
processing wetware and the rapidly developing world of deep learning.</p>
<p>Maybe you did too.</p>
<p>Just a little bit.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_clouds2.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_clouds2_hu_f9ab1fdeee786832.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_clouds2_hu_4e09c5b5100c7f99.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_clouds2_hu_ba39d0b8610f1bd9.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_clouds2_hu_7f8bffad885d6712.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/04/weekly-head-voices-182-can-you-predict-what/mont_marie_clouds2_hu_4e09c5b5100c7f99.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
My phone camera definitely needs more of that DeepFusion to capture the amazing
contrast patterns that these particular clouds were displaying at that
moment. You're going to have to take my word for it.
</figcaption>
</figure>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Happiness slingshot. [Weekly Head Voices #61]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/05/happiness-slingshot-weekly-head-voices-61/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2011 21:11:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/05/happiness-slingshot-weekly-head-voices-61/</guid><description>Make sure you won’t be disturbed for the next 2 minutes and 57 seconds, and then focus your full attention on this marvelous YouTube clip:
Yes people, there are apparently some brilliant human beings, the pinnacle of our society you might say, who took the time to construct a giant slingshot with which they then proceeded to shoot each other through the blue summer sky. This is the sign that we, the human race, must be doing something right.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Make sure you won’t be disturbed for the next 2 minutes and 57 seconds, and then focus your full attention on this marvelous YouTube clip:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/y_wkQBDDgvI?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Yes people, there are apparently some brilliant human beings, the pinnacle of our society you might say, who took the time to construct a giant slingshot with which they then proceeded to shoot each other through the blue summer sky. This is the sign that we, the human race, <em>must be doing something right</em>.</p>
<p>Because I need all the time that I can get to play may part in being a good human, I will now switch to Bullet Time(tm):</p>
<ul>
<li>IEEE VisWeek 2011, Mind-Blowingly Awesome Visualization Conference, took place in week 43. For the first time in years, I was NOT there. The <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">TNR</a> went and came back inspired. My fearless and revered ex-leader Frits Post received the IEEE VGTC Visualization Career Award, which is yet another official recognition of his awesomeness. I hope he still has some space on the mantelpiece next to the Eurographics Honorary Fellow award.</li>
<li>Through the <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/search?q=%23visweek" title="#visweek twitter stream">#visweek conference twitter stream</a> and some of the blogging that was going on, I was able to follow the conference at a distance. There was a Blogging about Visualization BoF (birds of a feather, a kind of informal meeting to discuss some topic of interest; also read <a href="http://bowr.de/blog/?p=291" title="Dominikus Baur's report on the visweek blogging BoF">Dominikus Baur’s blog report</a>), which motivated me to revive <a href="http://medvis.org/" title="medvis.org blog">the MedVis.org webblog</a>! We even have a <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/medvisorg" title="medvis.org twitter account">twitter account now</a>. If you have even a mild interest in medical visualisation or imaging, please subscribe via email, your RSS reader or <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/medvisorg" title="medvis.org twitter account">the twitter account</a>.</li>
<li>This blog won one of <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/2011/10/26/sa-blog-awards-2011/" title="Joe's official SA blog awards">Joe’s official SA Blog Awards</a>! Buy me a beer when you see me.</li>
<li>A real Italian explained to me that putting sugar in your espresso is entirely acceptable and even desirable. Herewith I’m going to stop feeling ashamed about my sugar-in-espresso habit. I’m not sure what I was thinking that combining two of the best substances known to humans was a sin.</li>
<li>After spending some serious quality time with <a href="http://emailga.me/" title="The Email Game">The Email Game</a>, I wrestled both of my overgrown inboxes to the ground. Lessons learnt: 1) Even the thin layer of gamification offered by The Email Game was sufficient to motivate me to start and finish a task I’ve been dreading for weeks. 2) Inbox Zero actually is more important than I’ve recently come to think. The trick is deciding when exactly you’re going to empty it.</li>
<li>Here’s a picture of a hedgehog after a bath:</li>
</ul>
<div>
<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 333px"><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/justinandelise/4234874994/"><img alt="" height="500" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2759/4234874994_9cbf4fbf35.jpg" title="Hedgehog after a bath, found on BoingBoing." width="333"/></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">It's a hedgehog. After a bath!</figcaption></figure>
</div>
<p>So recently I was having a conversation with someone in a bar. Soon the question came up: <em>What are you striving for in your work?</em></p>
<p>Imagine my surprise when I didn’t have an answer ready. I was surprised, because I usually spend a significant amount of time on introspection, pondering the usual questions:</p>
<ol>
<li>What makes me happy?</li>
<li>Why are we here?</li>
<li>What should I strive for?</li>
</ol>
<p>I mostly have answers to all of these and more, often involving coffee drinking in some form, along with a healthy dose of perspective, and harmony. However, due to general work-related business the past few months, my moments of introspection have been few and far between. As is the case with these types of philosophical guidelines, one does need to spend time regularly pondering them, else they sink quickly deeper below the surface of everyday life.</p>
<p>So I spent some time trying to remember what it was that I was striving for in work. Fortunately, not that far below the surface, I found it again:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Create value.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That’s really all there is, but it works for me.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>HappinessException [Weekly Head Voices #44]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/04/07/happinessexception-weekly-head-voices-44/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 20:30:41 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/04/07/happinessexception-weekly-head-voices-44/</guid><description>Just slightly before this week is over, here’s a super quick WHV looking back on last week, #13 of the year 2011. Let’s start the show with this delightful body-motion-art music video, brought to my attention by the intriguing TNR:
The most noteworthy items of my week were the following:
The VisWeek 2011 deadline, together with EuroVis our most important yearly paper deadline, smashed through our lives on Thursday. I had the distinct privilege of participating in two excellent submissions, and once again came to the realisation that I absolutely love writing papers, even when chasing deadlines as serious as this. As I’ve mentioned before, it’s quite the kick crafting that perfect gooseflesh-inducing sentence. Now cross yer fingers that both of these get accepted! I attended the early retirement party of one of my group’s professors. He gave a superbly humorous talk, amongst other topics on the changing culture at my employer (issue #1: Too Much Management and related to that issue #2: Research Institute Thinks it Should Act Like a Commercial Entity and Predictably Does So Embarrassingly Badly). This, as well as his compressed review of 30 years of academia, constituted serious food for thought. On Saturday I had the privilege of giving a talk, in Dutch (!!), to an audience of more than 200 clinical physicists at the yearly conference of the Dutch Society of Clinical Physics. I presented an overview of our surgical planning and guidance research, including the absolute latest results of the VisCAS survey that we’re working on (when I say “we”, I of course mean that one of my MedVis Ninjas is doing most of the hard work). If you’re also lucky enough to find yourself in Bergen, Norway for EuroVis 2011 in May/June, you’ll even be able to come and admire our poster on the topic! For my truly backyard philosophical conclusion, I’d like to refer to an interesting piece in this weekend’s Volkskrant on Pascal Bruckner, a real-deal non-backyard philosopher, and his refreshing view on our eternal quest for happiness. Bruckner makes the point that happiness used to be the exception, implying that then it was already quite an achievement just being able to survive.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Just slightly before <em>this</em> week is over, here’s a super quick WHV looking back on last week, #13 of the year 2011. Let’s start the show with this delightful body-motion-art music video, brought to my attention by the intriguing <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">TNR</a>:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/r-qhj3sJ5qs?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>The most noteworthy items of my week were the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>The VisWeek 2011 deadline, together with EuroVis our most important yearly paper deadline, smashed through our lives on Thursday. I had the distinct privilege of participating in two excellent submissions, and once again came to the realisation that I absolutely love writing papers, even when chasing deadlines as serious as this. As I’ve mentioned before, it’s quite the kick crafting that perfect gooseflesh-inducing sentence. Now cross yer fingers that both of these get accepted!</li>
<li>I attended the early retirement party of one of my group’s professors. He gave a superbly humorous talk, amongst other topics on the changing culture at my employer (issue #1: Too Much Management and related to that issue #2: Research Institute Thinks it Should Act Like a Commercial Entity and Predictably Does So Embarrassingly Badly). This, as well as his compressed review of 30 years of academia, constituted serious food for thought.</li>
<li>On Saturday I had the privilege of giving a talk, in Dutch (!!), to an audience of more than 200 clinical physicists at the yearly conference of the <a href="http://nvkf.nl/" title="NVKF website">Dutch Society of Clinical Physics</a>.  I presented an overview of our surgical planning and guidance research, including the absolute latest results of the <a href="http://viscas.medvis.org/" title="VisCAS website">VisCAS</a> survey that we’re working on (when I say “we”, I of course mean that <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/People/ThomasKroes" title="Thomas Kroes website">one of my MedVis Ninjas</a> is doing most of the hard work). If you’re also lucky enough to find yourself in Bergen, Norway for EuroVis 2011 in May/June, you’ll even be able to come and admire our poster on the topic!</li>
</ul>
<p>For my truly backyard philosophical conclusion, I’d like to refer to an interesting piece in this weekend’s Volkskrant on Pascal Bruckner, a real-deal non-backyard philosopher, and his refreshing view on our eternal quest for happiness. Bruckner makes the point that happiness used to be the exception, implying that then it was already quite an achievement just being able to survive.</p>
<p>These days, because we have access to infinite amounts of fat and sugar, and other important foodstuffs such as beer, and our survival has become almost a given, we have come to believe that it is our duty to be happy. Even worse than that, we have come to expect it of each other, finding it strange when someone is temporarily not in the throes of passion or happiness. Paradoxically, or maybe not, this expectation leads to much unhappiness, or as Bruckner puts it, the more we have, the more discontent we get.</p>
<p>Being French <em>and</em> a philosopher, he makes use of his unique prerogative by concluding with a quote by Voltaire from Candide:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>l’homme est né pour vivre dans les convulsions de l’inquiétude ou dans la lethargie de l’ennui.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(go look it up on Google Translate, you have-it-all human! don’t forget to leave a comment on this blog.)</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>On the importance of taking notes. [Weekly Head Voices #38]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2011 22:39:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/</guid><description>Post summary: Part one is about friends graduating from Evil School, part two is rather short mentioning vague bits of good news and part three is 100% time management and productivity boosting goodness! Feel free to skip, skim or reorder!
One On Thursday, February 10, 2011, my dear friend Mister Krekel graduated from Evil School after years of hard work and evil-doing, and will henceforth go through life as the formidable Doctor Krekel. Please do watch out. Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Part one is about friends graduating from Evil School, part two is rather short mentioning vague bits of good news and part three is 100% time management and productivity boosting goodness! Feel free to skip, skim or reorder!</em></p>
<h2 id="one">One</h2>
<p>On Thursday, February 10, 2011, my dear friend Mister Krekel graduated from Evil School after years of hard work and evil-doing, and will henceforth go through life as the formidable Doctor Krekel. Please do watch out.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_school_by_fmalan.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_school_by_fmalan.jpg"
        
            alt="Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The joyous transition took place in the Evil School’s Academiegebouw in Leiden, and this time yours truly (I’m referring to me in a round-about fashion) even had the great honour of playing a part in the formal proceedings. If you’re curious as to what exactly this ritual constitutes, see <a href="/2010/05/29/augmentation-weekly-head-voices-23/" title="previous edition of the WHV also on PhD defences in Leiden">this previous edition of the WHV</a> on the graduation of another terribly evil colleague. I believe that the bunch of us now constitute a bona fide Axis of Evil. No, the evil jokes can unfortunately not stop yet.</p>
<p>The Party was held in a secret cafe nearby. You will notice that I’ve capitalised Party, as it was not your average run of the mill Evil School graduation affair, but a social event of note. Here in Holland, the PhD defence and graduation are a combined affair, and so the whole day is dedicated to just one person. It is actually very special: People take time off from work, sometimes even temporarily put aside their differences, and travel from all over to attend the festivities. It’s like a wedding, except that there’s only one of you. I can only recommend it very highly. At the Party, everyone had clearly read the memo, and they were there with that singular goal in mind: Celebrate the freshly minted Evil Doctor. Presents were given, speeches were held, photos were shown, beer was imbibed and, flying in the face of all advice concerning the mixing of alcohol, cameras and social networking, the <a href="http://fpixel.wordpress.com/" title="link to the evil photographer">best evil photographer in town</a>, who’s coincidentally also in Evil School, took the most amazing photos that you should be able to see on Facebook if you’re one of the privileged few to belong to The Network, also known as <em>The Friends of the Axis of Evil</em>.</p>
<h2 id="two">Two</h2>
<p>On the good news front, you&rsquo;ll see (or not) on the <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/program.php" title="list of eurovis 2011 conditional accepts">list of EuroVis 2011 conditional accepts</a>, that a paper by cool colleagues from far away, to which I contributed a small part, has been conditionally accepted, and hence has a significant chance of being presented at said event in Bergen, Norway (May 31 to June 3). We also have plans to submit a poster (or two), so there&rsquo;s an even more significant chance that I will make an appearance at this fantastic conference! We&rsquo;re also cooking up various odds and ends that will hopefully crystallise sufficiently by the end of March to be submissible for VisWeek 2011. Cross yer fingers.</p>
<h2 id="three">Three</h2>
<p>Today&rsquo;s backyard time management section is in fact more about planning than it is about notes. However, my Pro-Tips involve combining them in an easy to implement productivity booster. When people start out in research, one of the first bits of advice they get is keeping some kind of lab journal. I think this advice applies to more than just research: If you do any kind of independent or project work, jotting down your activities, thoughts and results during the day is useful in helping to structure your thought processes, and also very helpful when you have to backtrack a complex multi-day procedure. During my Ph.D., I filled a number of real cardboard-and-paper books with notes. More recently, I&rsquo;ve started using Google Documents for the same purpose. Besides all the other advantages, having to document explicitly your work output keeps you productive and on your toes.</p>
<h3 id="pro-tip-1">Pro Tip #1</h3>
<p><em>Keep a lab journal, even if you don&rsquo;t work in a lab.</em></p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="/2011/01/09/2011-a-cyber-suburban-odyssey-weekly-head-voices-35/" title="2011 start post">mentioned before</a> that my resolutions for 2011 included more concrete planning. This has manifested in a work-in-progress planning for the whole year, including milestones, awards won, and so forth, but much more practically, it has manifested in a little lab-journal-compatible trick. Every morning when I sit down to begin the day, I spend a few minutes thinking and then start the day&rsquo;s journal entry by writing down, as concretely as possible, the tasks that I plan to complete by the end of the day. This also ensures that I spend effort on the <em>important</em> things, and not only on the urgent things. So, that brings us to:</p>
<h3 id="pro-tip-2">Pro Tip #2</h3>
<p><em>At the start of each day, write down in your lab journal exactly and
concretely what you plan to accomplish by the end of that day.</em></p>
<p>These pro tips appear to be quite straight-forward, but together they help one
to focus, and to keep tabs on one&rsquo;s <em>effective</em> productivity. In other words,
just being terribly busy the whole day gets you nothing; the trick is being
terribly busy in all the right directions.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Somebody is clearly pushing the boundaries of awesomeness… cowboys AND aliens!</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/In-m2RJw3hE?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Futuristic Betting at VisWeek 2009.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2009 12:26:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/</guid><description>So I went to IEEE VisWeek 2009, and it was far more awesome and enjoyable than even my most optimistic expectations. Besides contributing to the tweetstorm (see #visweek) but not being able to liveblog due to higher priority activities, attending paper presentations and chatting with as many cool people as possible (much higher priority activities), this year I&amp;rsquo;ve also made a number of elaborate bets with a subset of said cool people concerning the future of our technology. If all goes according to plan, the bets&amp;rsquo;ll end up being visionary, if not, they might be slightly embarrassing and we&amp;rsquo;ll have a good laugh at VisWeek 2019.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>So I went to IEEE VisWeek 2009, and it was far more awesome and enjoyable than
even my most optimistic expectations. Besides contributing to the tweetstorm
(see <a href="http://twitter.com/#search?q=%23visweek" title="link to visweek hashtag search">#visweek</a>) but not being able to liveblog due to higher priority
activities, attending paper presentations and chatting with as many cool people
as possible (much higher priority activities), this year I&rsquo;ve also made a
number of elaborate bets with a subset of said cool people concerning the
future of our technology. If all goes according to plan, the bets&rsquo;ll end
up being visionary, if not, they might be slightly embarrassing and we&rsquo;ll
have a good laugh at VisWeek 2019.</p>
<p>Because these bets only realise in 10 or 20 years, I&rsquo;ve told my betting
partners that I would write it up on my blog so that we could check in that
much time, and that they would then owe me copious amounts of beer. This also
gives them the opportunity to check my wording for suitability, as we might
have to cleave hairs when the time comes.</p>
<h2 id="bet-1-huds">Bet #1: HUDs.</h2>
<p><em>Bet #1: At VisWeek 2019, I and at least one other person will be wearing a HUD
pretty much all the time, OR I will have at least one bionic eye.</em></p>
<figure>
<a href="http://www.popsci.com/gear-amp-gadgets/article/2009-06/heads-display-embedded-glasses">
<img src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/interactive-data-eyeglasses.jpg" style="margin: 0px;"/>
</a>
<figcaption>Courtesy of Fraunhofer-Gesellschaft.</figcaption>
</figure> 
<p>I made this bet with the infamous Dr. Bob Laramee, proprietor of the <a href="http://www.winslam.com/rlaramee/star/index.html" title="5-star webpage">5-star
webpage</a>. This came up in a conversation about having some form of
non-intrusive display device always available with which things could be looked
up, relatively unobtrusively, during for example a conversation.</p>
<p>I do expect that sometime within the next 10 years, HUDs (heads-up display)
will be offered as an option with every new set of spectacles. This is
definitely not a push-over bet, but that makes it all the more exciting.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure how the bionic eye clause slipped in there, honestly!</p>
<h2 id="bet-2-the-future-of-cars">Bet #2: The future of cars.</h2>
<p><em>Bet #2: 19.5 years from now, there will be more cars with alternative propulsion systems than there are cars with fossil-fuel based internal combustion engines.</em></p>
<p>This one was made with Dr Helmut Doleisch, linked view data analysis guru and
now CEO of <a href="http://www.simvis.at/" title="SimVis website">SimVis</a> (hey man, BUY THEIR SOFTWARE!). He is concerned with all
the vested interests in fossil-fuel combustion, whereas I think that 19.5 years
is more than enough time to introduce non-fossil fuel based propulsion systems
on the road, so much so that less than 50% of cars on the road will have need
of fossil fuel.</p>
<p>Brazil with its 190 million inhabitants is an interesting example in this
regard: A large number of their cars already run on either gasoline or
sugarcane ethanol &mdash; clearly a great step in the direction of non-fossil
fuel options.</p>
<h2 id="bet-3-the-future-of-conferences">Bet #3: The future of conferences.</h2>
<p><em>Bet #3: In 2029, distributed conferences with tele-presence will be common.</em></p>
<p>In this case, the beer-donor is Dr Stefan Bruckner, master of all things volume
visualisation and father of the VolumeShop software system. My contention is
that in 20 years, conferences where attendees take part via tele-presence
systems, whatever they may be, will be common-place.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve called one of the models I envision of this &ldquo;clustered telepresence&rdquo;,
which would entail that groups of attendees would indeed gather physically, but
that these remote clusters would be connected by advanced tele-presence
systems, involving advanced displays (think very large, or perhaps even some
form of mobile volumetric displays) and distributed and mobile sound.</p>
<p>During the discussion preceding the making of this bet, valid concerns were
raised with regard to the efficacy of remote socialising, especially
beer-drinking. I agree that this is an issue of utmost importance, but still
contend that technology and efficiency concerns will conspire to address this
problem in a way that is at least good enough to fool, to a sufficient extent,
all parties involved.</p>
<h2 id="update-on-2019-10-27">Update on 2019-10-27</h2>
<p>On Friday, October 25, Dr DataVis Bob of Bet #1, Dr Helmut Doleisch of Bet #2
and <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/">Prof Noeska Smit</a> (representing both me and Prof
Bruckner of Bet
#3), the former three all present at VisWeek 2019, recorded a three-part video
message to me, and to the world, in which they declared that I had definitely
lost bet #1.</p>
<p>I do agree fully with their judgement.</p>
<p>As far as they could establish, there was no-one else at VisWeek 2019 with any
form of HUD&hellip;  WHICH THEY COULD DETECT!</p>
<p>However, I was definitely not present at VisWeek.</p>
<p>Even if I had been there, I don&rsquo;t own any of the spectacle-integrated HUDs that
I predicted in 2009, and I still have both my own organic eyes.</p>
<p><strong>Anyways, the fact of the matter is that I now owe Dr Bob an unspecified
amount of beer.</strong></p>
<p>More seriously, a few years after my 2009 prediction of HUDs in spectacles,
Google released <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_glass">Google Glass</a>. At
that point, I thought that things were going to go my way.</p>
<p>However, after the initial hype,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_glass#Criticism">criticism</a> started
piling up, and the project was shelved a few years later.</p>
<p>That being said, recent developments such as Microsoft&rsquo;s augmented reality
<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/hololens">Hololens</a>, the great deal of R&amp;D
effort Apple is pouring into augmented reality in all of their hardware, and
other movements in the technology landscape, lead me to think that this
discussion about omni-present non-intrusive personal displays is not completely
over.</p>
<h3 id="bets-2-and-3">Bets #2 and #3</h3>
<p>There are still 9.5 years left for bet #2.</p>
<p>I have asked Dr Helmut if we could amend the bet to specify cars in the EU.</p>
<p>Even if he agrees, there&rsquo;s indeed not that much time in car-years for more than
half of the cars on roads in the EU to have non-fossil-fuel propulsion systems.</p>
<p>However, if the bet were too easy, it would not be as much fun, now would it?</p>
<p>For bet #3 I am also still going to hang on.</p>
<p>The ongoing deterioration of our environment is one of multiple factors putting
more weight behind the movement for better tele-conferencing.</p>
<p>In addition to that, people keep on comparing face-to-face meetings with
terrible tele-conference setups.</p>
<p>Of course face-to-face is better than your laptop&rsquo;s sub-par camera, woefully
inadequate sound and embarrassing lack of robot legs!</p>
<p>I am really curious as to the limits and parameters of human immersion.</p>
<p>Who knows what clever tricks can be done to fool the highly gullible human
psyche into believing that it&rsquo;s actually present and interacting with other
humans somewhere thousands of kilometres away?</p>
<p>Anyways, I digress.</p>
<p>More importantly than everything I have written in this update, receiving this
video message from the future, made by friends who live and work a world away,
absolutely made my day.</p>
<p>Friends, I almost felt like I was sitting there with you at VisWeek 2019. Thank
you!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>