<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Science on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/categories/science/</link><description>Recent content in Science on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 16:23:34 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/categories/science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Science: Really not just for scientists.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/24/science-really-not-just-for-scientists/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 16:23:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/24/science-really-not-just-for-scientists/</guid><description> The public’s unwillingness to learn basic scientific concepts and scientists’ inability to communicate those concepts lead the public to reject promising research (such as genetic modification), ignore serious problems (such as global warming) and embrace dangerous nonsense (such as anti-vaccination rhetoric).
— Proposition from the Ph.D. thesis of Dr Wynand Winterbach, via Francois Malan on Facebook.
(This important message was brought to you by cpbotha.net, trawling facebook for interesting tidbits so you don’t have to!)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>The public’s unwillingness to learn basic scientific concepts and scientists’ inability to communicate those concepts lead the public to reject promising research (such as genetic modification), ignore serious problems (such as global warming) and embrace dangerous nonsense (such as anti-vaccination rhetoric).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>— Proposition from the <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4233/uuid:863253bb-a341-4445-96fd-4e83dc31baca">Ph.D. thesis</a> of Dr Wynand Winterbach, via <a href="http://francoismalan.com/">Francois Malan</a> on Facebook.</p>
<p>(This important message was brought to you by cpbotha.net, trawling facebook for interesting tidbits so you don’t have to!)</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The new MedVis Book is out!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2013/12/24/the-new-medvis-book-is-out/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2013 12:28:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2013/12/24/the-new-medvis-book-is-out/</guid><description>For the past 2.5 years, I have been helping my friend Prof. Bernhard Preim to write the new Medical Visualization textbook. A crazy number of hours of studying scientific literature (a quick count in the bbl file yields 1880 cited references!!), trying to fit everything into a coherent conceptual framework and then trying to write all of it down as a more or less readable story has finally led to more than 1000 pages of Medical Visualization reading pleasure.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>For the past 2.5 years, I have been helping my friend <a href="http://isgwww.cs.uni-magdeburg.de/~bernhard/" title="bernhard's website">Prof. Bernhard Preim</a> to write the new Medical Visualization textbook. A crazy number of hours of studying scientific literature (a quick count in the bbl file yields 1880 cited references!!), trying to fit everything into a coherent conceptual framework and then trying to write all of it down as a more or less readable story has finally led to more than 1000 pages of Medical Visualization reading pleasure.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>
<p><a href="http://medvisbook.com/"><img alt="" class="alignnone" height="922" src="http://medvisbook.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/cover_full_20130729.jpg" width="1650"/></a></p>
<p>The title has been changed to <em>Visual Computing for Medicine</em> to reflect the significant rework, and also the broader treatment of the field. The book itself is 836 pages with hundreds of colour figures. Five chapters (190+ pages) are <a href="http://medvisbook.com/online-chapters/" title="medvisbook online chapters">available exclusively online</a>, free to download.</p>
<p>Go to <a href="http://medvisbook.com/" title="medvisbook website">the book website</a> (run by us) to read more <a href="http://medvisbook.com/about/" title="about the book">about the contents</a> of the book, and to find out <a href="http://medvisbook.com/where-to-buy/" title="where to buy">where you can get your very own copy</a>!</p>
<p>P.S. It was a huge pleasure working on the book together with Bernhard. (We’ve been collaborating quite intensively since the end of 2007 somewhere, when we started setting up the <a href="http://www.vcbm.org/" title="VCBM website">Eurographics Workshops on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine</a>, which have since then been held in 2008, 2010, 2012 and will be held again in 2014 in Vienna.) Just for the record, he definitely put a great deal more work into the book than I did. The exact ratio will remain our secret.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Startups vs. Academic Research Groups: FIGHT!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/07/24/startups-vs-academic-research-groups-fight/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2012 21:34:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/07/24/startups-vs-academic-research-groups-fight/</guid><description>There are many similarities between startups, defined here as (relatively) young and agile companies with a few bright people trying to change the world by working on some cool idea(s), and academic research groups, defined here as (relatively) young and agile units within academic institutes with a few bright people trying to change the world by working on some cool idea(s). Err, yes.
Fortunately there are also many differences, so I have something to write about here. For some years now I’ve been running the TU Delft Medical Visualization research group, an experience that shall serve as the primary source of information for this piece. I’ve also had some experience of startup culture, first as one of two (and later three) engineers in a new business unit of Crusader Systems (now CSense) designing an embedded image processing product called FrothMaster, then at Stone Three as employee #1, then later at Treparel as a co-founder and architect, and more recently as scientific advisor to Clinical Graphics and co-founder of TimeScapers. In spite of this healthy dose of exposure, I’ve never actually run a startup as my main activity, so I will have to extrapolate and sometimes revert to wild guesses. I am trusting that some of the startup-involved readers will pipe up in the comments!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>There are many similarities between startups, defined here as (relatively) young and agile companies with a few bright people trying to change the world by working on some cool idea(s), and academic research groups, defined here as (relatively) young and agile units within academic institutes with a few bright people trying to change the world by working on some cool idea(s). Err, yes.</p>
<p>Fortunately there are also many differences, so I have something to write about here. For some years now I’ve been running the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/MedVis" title="TU Delft MedVis Group">TU Delft Medical Visualization research group</a>, an experience that shall serve as the primary source of information for this piece. I’ve also had <em>some</em> experience of startup culture, first as one of two (and later three) engineers in a new business unit of Crusader Systems (now <a href="http://www.csensesystems.com/cms/tiki-index.php" title="CSense website">CSense</a>) designing an embedded image processing product called FrothMaster, then at <a href="http://www.stonethree.com/" title="Stone Three website">Stone Three</a> as employee #1, then later at <a href="http://www.treparel.com/" title="Treparel Website">Treparel</a> as a co-founder and architect, and more recently as scientific advisor to <a href="http://www.clinicalgraphics.com/" title="Clinical Graphics website">Clinical Graphics</a> and co-founder of <a href="http://timescapers.com/" title="TimeScapers website">TimeScapers</a>. In spite of this healthy dose of exposure, I’ve never actually run a startup as my main activity, so I will have to extrapolate and sometimes revert to wild guesses. I am trusting that some of the startup-involved readers will pipe up in the comments!</p>
<p>An academic research group works more or less as follows: Someone, usually a member of faculty (in this case me) at some university has a number of (crackpot) research ideas. Said someone pours buckets of sweat into further developing these ideas into over-detailed research proposals, which are then all rejected by the national and international research funding agencies that they are sent to. Somehow, said someone manages to keep going at this, resulting in proposals that describe projects that have nothing to do any more with the original research ideas, but are works of buzz-word art.</p>
<p>At some point, to the complete surprise of said someone, a number of proposals get approved. This means that buckets of money are handed over to the hosting university. Doh. Faculty member can now put in official requests to make use of these funds to employ a number of bright Ph.D. candidates for 4 years each, to buy toys for said candidates and to pay for visits to parties, I mean conferences, all around the world. Ph.D. candidates work on research project, supervised by faculty member, and each publishes on average 4 good research papers, followed by a thesis, at which case they usually have to be kicked out.</p>
<p>Some of the freshly-minted doctors decide to stay in academia, eventually breaking out of their postdoc cocoons as beautiful faculty members themselves, most often at other academic institutes. Some of the rest even decide to start startups!</p>
<p>At a startup, the main goal is to develop a new product or service, and then sell so much of it that the company turns a huge and sustainable profit. Alternatively, the startup’s product or service and/or people are so sexy that a much larger company decides to buy the whole thing up for a very large bundle of cash, instantly making the founders quite rich. This is called an “exit”. Initial funding strategies vary greatly. Startups can have any mix of bootstrapping (generating little bits of income to feed itself hopefully leading to more income), self financing, venture capital or angel investment. A startup is “<a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/ramenprofitable.html" title="link to Paul Graham's ramen profitability definition">ramen profitable</a>” when it is just able to pay for the founders’ living expenses.</p>
<p><strong>Financing:</strong> Here we see the first significant difference. In academia, a competition upfront determines whether you get financing or not for a particular research idea. Only when you have sufficient financing to appoint people and buy equipment for the duration of the project (generally 2 to 4 years), the relevant project is allowed to start. Faculty salaries are paid by the hosting institute. A startup can start whenever at least one founder is able to get by on their own resources for a few months. The startup is able to get by on very little, but does need to generate income throughout its lifetime, and that income ideally needs to increase steadily so that the company can grow.</p>
<p><strong>Risk:</strong> The second big difference is related to this. At a startup, all the rewards go to the startup, for a largest part to its founders and to a lesser extent to its employees. People work their behinds off, because the payoff could be huge and your chunk is considerable. If your idea happens to change the world (see Dropbox), also the non-monetary kick can be life-changing. However, the risk is also all yours. If your idea bombs and your company blows up into a million pieces, you get to keep each and every piece! Even worse, you actually have to deal with the fallout in some or other fashion. In practice, this could mean bankruptcy of the company, but it could even go as far as directly impacting on the financial status of the founders.</p>
<p>In academia, there is certainly some risk in exploring in new territory, but it is accepted that not all ideas pan out equally well. You’re allowed to fail now and then, as long as you do OK on average. If you fail all the time of course, you’ll probably have a harder time finding new grants and collaborators to continue with your research, but you’ll still have the job. On the other hand, your reward in case of a successful project is that the relevant publications get mentioned by other researchers in their articles. You now have made what is called “impact”, and your <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H-index" title="wikipedia page on h-index">h-index</a> will hopefully start reflecting this soon, making it ever so slightly easier for you to get that next research grant. On a less cynical note, you sometimes are privy to the real kick of scientific discovery, where you’ve managed to cook up something that other scientists (and maybe in 20 years some real people) get really excited about. This latter aspect is in my opinion the actual driver, and the aspect that can make the science business so addictive.</p>
<p><strong>Focus:</strong> A startup needs to have laser sharp focus. You need to pick one thing, service, expertise, product or concept, and become the absolute best at that. This seems to be a recurring theme looking at successful startups. If you do decide to go do something else, you have to call it a “<a href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/start/2012/05/the-pivot-the-moment-where-startups-change-or-die.php" title="readwriteweb explaining the pivot">pivot</a>“, but you cant’t do too many of those, else people think you don’t know what you’re doing. In academia, you should definitely also have a research focus, but the requirements are far less stringent.</p>
<p>Research groups usually have a number of independent research projects, all more or less exploring some general research avenue, but a good devil’s advocate could claim that having different projects constitutes a lack of real focus. In my group for example, I currently have 6 major projects, ranging from surgical planning, through anatomical modelling and neuro-imaging to population imaging, as well as a small number of less major projects. This range is both a blessing and a curse. I have the luxury of exploring and finding cross-links between related but discrete research lines. Also, we have a higher chance of striking gold and a lower risk of striking out with this spread. However, sometimes I think that picking one idea and working on that for a few years would help us to build up more expertise concentration.</p>
<p><strong>Overheads:</strong> Usually an academic research group is embedded within a hosting university. This grants certain advantages, such as infrastructure, and thousands of highly skilled colleagues, but it also means extra overhead. One of the most time-consuming components of this is teaching, an activity with which I have a love-hate relationship. Students who put in the minimum of effort  drain a huge deal of energy per each of their completely useless kilograms. Dedicated students  on the other hand are energising and in some cases decide to join the research group, further bolstering its capabilities.</p>
<p>In a startup, there is usually no hosting institution, and hence no such kind of overhead. I think this generally contributes significantly to the work satisfaction experienced by startuppers, as the level of self-determination is perceived to be much greater due to the lack of any externally imposed constraints. The impression I get from colleagues at my academic institute, is that the constraints or parameters imposed by the hosting institute, including administration, politics and in some cases teaching, can negatively impact on work satisfaction.</p>
<p><strong>Goals:</strong> This one is interesting to think about. I think in both cases the idealistic goal is to discover or create something big that changes the world for the better. Taking a more cynical look at the day to day activities, one could think that the major goal of a research group is to setup larger and larger research programmes involving more and more people and more ambitious research goals, until finally the people at the top lose touch with the work on the ground. The cynical startup founder wants to get rich, either via a fabulous exit or market success, and then do it all again, perhaps at a larger scale.</p>
<p>I think it’s even more important to look past both lofty idealism and cynicism, and instead focus on something that can sustain you indefinitely: <em>Doing something meaningful</em>. Even if that world-changing breakthrough (startup or academia) is not yet in sight, and the bags of cash or the 50-person research group are a really long way off, coming home after work with the conviction that what you’ve done today in some way positively impacts the little world around you will definitely help to keep that spring in your step.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>You have beautiful ize. [Weekly Head Voices #62]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/19/you-have-beautiful-ize-weekly-head-voices-62/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2011 21:29:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/19/you-have-beautiful-ize-weekly-head-voices-62/</guid><description>I completely lack the genes that usually cause human males to have a thing for cars, but I do love Top Gear. This trailer for a fictional 60s detective show, made by Jeremy Clarkson, James May and Richard Hammond, encapsulates many of the reasons why:
Moustaches, guns, girls, cars and Hammond karate-chopping the porter at Playboy Club London for absolutely no reason whatsoever at 41 seconds can be nothing but 100% pure AWESOME.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I completely lack the genes that usually cause human males to have a thing for cars, but I do love Top Gear. This trailer for a fictional 60s detective show, made by Jeremy Clarkson, James May and Richard Hammond, encapsulates many of the reasons why:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qLp4FhDAfQk?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Moustaches, guns, girls, cars and Hammond karate-chopping the porter at Playboy Club London for absolutely no reason whatsoever at 41 seconds can be nothing but 100% pure AWESOME.</p>
<p>It’s crazily busy at the moment, for a large part due to the extra load of having to teach and revamp, AT THE SAME TIME, the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4086" title="TU Delt DataVis course">TU Delft’s postgraduate Data Visualization course</a>. I’ve chucked out the written exam and the structured lab work, and exchanged it for paper reading, class discussion and four independent projects, inspired by positive experience with my <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4307" title="TU Delft postgraduate MedVis course">Medical Visualization Ninja Training Course</a> (third year in the running, Ninjas all over the place!), the <a href="/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/" title="infovis in stellenbosch">postgraduate InfoVis course I gave at Stellenbosch</a> and of course the teaching materials of esteemed colleagues at UBC, Harvard, Berkeley and Stanford. With a bit of luck, we will soon deliver a whole class of new-style DataVis Ninjas.</p>
<p>At a recent conference, I ran into an erudite half-British colleague from the far North, who in a few minutes almost managed to turn my world into rubble. You see, I’ve always proudly promoted the use of the -ise forms of certain words, such as visualise, realise, colonise and so forth, these being examples of British English. (Obviously, I adapt when American English is required.)</p>
<p>It turns out that, as is the case with life in general, it’s unfortunately not as simple as that.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_and_British_English_spelling_differences#-ise.2C_-ize_.28-isation.2C_-ization.29" title="wikipedia article on britsh vs english spelling">It turns out</a> that many of the -ise words are originally from the Greek or the Latin with “-ize” endings, and therefore the Oxford spelling prefers their use, although it accepts the “-ise” forms as well. On the other hand, the Cambridge University Press, as well as the mainstream media and most of the public in Britain and the former colonies, has a strong preference for the “-ise” forms. Certain other words like for example advertise, advise and surprise always take the “-ise” form in British English.</p>
<p>So now I’m faced with this conundrum. It would otherwise not have been such an issue, but the words “visualise” and “visualisation” come up quite often during my work day. Sticking to “-ise” is easier and still correct when in British English mode, but “-ize” for those few words of Greek  and Latin origin could perhaps be considered more correct, and has the great advantage of allowing me to standardise on “visualize” as the canonical form of that important term. However, then I would run the risk of confusing the “-ize” and the true “-ise” words in Oxford English, potentially leading to painful embarrassment at the many cocktail parties that I frequent.</p>
<p>So you see, the Universe is just full of mysteries. Another mystery that has plagued humankind for decades, is what would happen if Stephen Hawking and Albert Einstein got involved in a rap battle. Well humankind, wonder no more:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zn7-fVtT16k?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Ok kids, thank you for tuning in again. Have a great week, I hope to see you again soon!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>EuroVis 2011</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/26/eurovis-2011/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2011 11:25:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/26/eurovis-2011/</guid><description>I’ve written before about EuroVis, the most important European scientific conference on visualisation. In 2009, it took place in Berlin, in 2010 it was in Bordeaux, and, an a surprise non-twist of alliteration, the 2011 edition was held in Bergen, Norway. With 216 attendees and a practically perfect organization, this year’s edition has been described as the biggest and the best EuroVis ever. In a bid to save some time (I still owe you a mega-edition of the Weekly (actually Monthly) Head Voices), I’m going to give my biased account in bullet-list form:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve written before about EuroVis, the most important European scientific conference on visualisation. In <a href="/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/" title="blog post on eurovis 2009">2009, it took place in Berlin</a>, in <a href="/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/" title="blog coverage of eurovis 2010">2010 it was in Bordeaux</a>, and, an a surprise non-twist of alliteration, the <strong>2011 edition was held in Bergen, Norway.</strong> With 216 attendees and a practically perfect organization, this year’s edition has been described as the biggest and the best EuroVis ever. In a bid to save some time (I still owe you a mega-edition of the Weekly (actually Monthly) Head Voices), I’m going to give my biased account in bullet-list form:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>On Tuesday evening, we were welcomed by the very charismatic vice mayor of Bergen in the Tårnsalen of the Lysverket building of the Bergen Art Museum. It seems the photo I took of the inside of the art deco tower, built in 1938, is quite a popular shot. The food was divine, thank you very much.

  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/tarnsalen.jpg">
      <img
          
              
              src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/tarnsalen-1024x612.jpg"
          
              alt="Art Deco tower from the inside in the Tårnsalen, Lysverket."/> </a><figcaption>
              <p>Art Deco tower from the inside in the Tårnsalen, Lysverket.</p>
          </figcaption>
  </figure>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The next morning, during the conference opening, the following Bergen (rainiest city in Europe) joke was told: <em>A visitor asks a local boy in exasperation “Does it rain like this all the time?” and the little boy answers “I don’t know, I’m only 12 years old!”</em>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/speakers.php#mcCloud" title="conference keynote page">conference keynote</a> was given by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_McCloud" title="Wikipedia page on Scott McCloud">Scott McCloud</a>, American cartoonist and comic theorist, on aspects of visual communication. This was most probably the best presentation I’ve ever had the privilege of experiencing. Besides brilliant oratorship, his slides are somehow more a visual stream of consciousness affair than discrete quanta of information. When I grow up, I’m going to present like that.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As per usual, I get to award the <strong>Weekly Head Voices Best Paper awards</strong>, and they go to the following papers:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.mevis-research.de/~crieder/pdf/EuroVis2011_paper175.pdf" title="fulltext of Rieder 2011 eurovis paper">A Shader Framework for Rapid Prototyping of GPU-Based Volume Rendering</a> by Christian Rieder, Stephan Palmer, Florian Link and Horst K. Hahn. Rieder and his colleagues have constructed a full GPU-based volume rendering pipeline in MeVisLab of which the various shader based components are modifiable at runtime. This means that you can prototype your GPU-based volume rendering ideas in no time flat!</li>
<li><a href="http://www.ii.uib.no/vis/publications/publication/2011/lampe11curveDensity" title="curve density estimates website">Curve Density Estimates</a> by Ove Daae Lampe and Helwig Hauser. Back to basics and really important work on the effective visualisation of complex curves at any resolution, with smooth scaling between levels.</li>
<li><a href="http://vgl.serc.iisc.ernet.in/pdf/pub/MultifieldComparisonMeasureEUROVIS2011.pdf" title="fulltext gradient-based comparison metric paper">A Gradient-Based Comparison Measure for Visual Analysis of Multifield Data</a> by Suthambhara Nagaraj, Vijay Natarajan and Ravi S. Nanjundiah. Another back-to-basics paper in which the authors show how to find the agreement between hundreds of scalar fields and visualise this agreement, thus enabling comparison.</li>
</ul>
<p>The slightly less prestigious EuroVis 2011 Best Paper awards went to:</p>
<ol>
<li>Uncertainty-Aware Exploration of Continuous Parameter Spaces Using Multivariate Prediction  by Wolfgang Berger, Harald Piringer, Peter Filzmoser, Eduard Gröller. I was unfortunately in the other session, but was told by numerous colleagues that this was indeed an award-winning presentation as well.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.sci.utah.edu/publications/anderson11/Anderson_eurovis2011.pdf" title="fulltext of Anderson's paper">A User Study of Visualization Effectiveness Using EEG and Cognitive Load</a> by Erik Anderson, Kristin Potter, Laura Matzen, Jason Shepherd, Gilbert Preston, Claudio Silva. This was presented in the Evaluation session which I had the privilege of chairing. It is indeed a very compelling idea to measure the effectiveness of a visualisation through cognitive load and this paper documents the first very important steps in this direction.</li>
<li>A Gradient-Based Comparison Measure for Visual Analysis of Multifield Data by Suthambhara Nagaraj, Vijay Natarajan and Ravi S. Nanjundiah. This was also amongst the more prestigious WHV best paper award winners, see above!</li>
</ol>
<p>The rest of the conference featured the following bullets:</p>
<ul>
<li>During the social event on Thursday evening, Frits Post (my boss), was elevated to the rank of Eurographics Honorary Fellow, recognizing his service to and standing in the visualisation community. Including this newest addition, there are only <a href="http://www.eg.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=90&amp;Itemid=52" title="list of EG honorary fellows">five (5!) EG Honorary Fellows</a> in the world today. I am very proud!</li>
<li>During the first session of the morning after the social event, I had the exquisite privilege of presenting the work of my Brazilian colleagues: <a href="http://www.lcad.icmc.usp.br/~nonato/pubs/plp.pdf" title="fulltext PLP paper">Piecewise Laplacian-based Projection for Interactive Data Exploration and Organization</a> by Fernando V. Paulovich, Danilo M. Eler, Jorge Poco, Charl P. Botha, Rosane Minghim, Luis G. Nonato. I really do like presenting at events like these, and it’s been a while. Do read and cite the paper, it documents a practical way of reducing any set of high-dimensional data points to the visual space, and enabling interaction with those points on the visual space!</li>
<li>The <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/speakers.php#groller" title="capstone page">capstone of the conference</a> was presented by the legendary Prof. E. Gröller, also known by the whole community as <em>Meister</em>. In typical style, the title of his talk was only announced during the talk itself. The title was <em>The Haunted Swamps of Heuristics</em>. In this philosophical and visionary contribution, it was argued that algorithms and parameters are too deeply intertwined to focus only on the former, but that it was more important to study, in detail, the exact behaviour of the latter. More broadly speaking, we need to accept the fact that there is a great deal of uncertainty also in the parameter spaces of our algorithms, but that this uncertainty can and should be dealt with correctly.</li>
</ul>
<p>That thought-provoking capstone and this blog post will share the same concluding quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Doubt is not a pleasant condition, but certainty is absurd. — Voltaire / Gröller</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I hope to see you in the comments below! You could also opt to click on my shiny new +1 button, or my slightly older but no less shiny retweet or facebook share buttons.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Schloss Dagstuhl: Computer Scientist Heaven</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/19/schloss-dagstuhl-computer-scientist-heaven/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2011 19:56:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/19/schloss-dagstuhl-computer-scientist-heaven/</guid><description>Somewhere in a remote but picturesque location in southern Germany, there’s a special castle called Schloss Dagstuhl. Every week, the castle fills up with a smallish group of Exceptionally Privileged Computer Scientists, who can only go there Because They Have Been Invited. Every week hosts a different field; In my case this was the Scientific Visualization seminar, one of the oldest participating groups. Everything has been setup just so to guarantee a perfect computer sciencey week for all guests. Because I’ve already been boring too many people with this story in person, I thought it prudent to write it up. Let’s hope it’s not a first (and second!) rule of Fight Club situation, in which case posting frequency over here might drop quite drastically. Schloss Dagstuhl, picture courtesy of Wikipedia.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Somewhere in a remote but picturesque location in southern Germany, there’s a special castle called Schloss Dagstuhl. Every week, the castle fills up with a smallish group of Exceptionally Privileged Computer Scientists, who can only go there Because They Have Been Invited. Every week hosts a different field; In my case this was the Scientific Visualization seminar, one of the oldest participating groups. Everything has been setup <em>just so</em> to guarantee a perfect computer sciencey week for all guests. Because I’ve already been boring too many people with this story in person, I thought it prudent to write it up. Let’s hope it’s not a first (and second!) rule of Fight Club situation, in which case posting frequency over here might drop <em>quite</em> drastically.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Dagstuhl_DSC02285.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Dagstuhl_DSC02285-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Schloss Dagstuhl, picture courtesy of Wikipedia."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Schloss Dagstuhl, picture courtesy of Wikipedia.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>To begin with, the meals are exquisite, three times a day, every day. As we all know, the path to a computer scientist’s heart is through buying them new gadgets, but feeding them well is a great backup plan. Another very nice touch is the fact that seating is deliberately randomised, meaning that your introvert self is forced to sit at the table with a different group of guests during each lunch and dinner, in turn meaning that even if you try otherwise, you will probably get to have a good conversation with every one of the fifty attendees.</p>
<p>In the case of our seminar, the working day consists of presentations in blocks of three or four, followed by a longer block of discussion on all the preceding presentations, panel style. Attendees were all asked not just to give a standard scientific presentation, but to discuss open problems and future challenges in their respective sub-fields. I (and many others, judging by the aggregated post-meeting feedback) really enjoyed this format. The presentations made one think, and the discussion blocks were long enough to really get into the details. You can check out abstracts and slides on <a href="http://www.dagstuhl.de/mat/index.en.phtml?11231" title="site with Dagstuhl SciVis 2011 materials">the seminar website</a>.</p>
<p>After a full day of quite intensive discussion, there were breakout sessions during which four subgroups started working on the various chapters of a new Springer book that should appear sometime early in next year. The book will deal with multi-field, uncertainty, biomedical and scalable visualization, and it has the makings of being a keeper.</p>
<p>The other extremely important magic bit about this castle is the abundance of real coffee machines (ones that grind coffee beans for every cup), snack corners and, uhm, beer fridges. You can’t really go anywhere, as you’re in the middle of nowhere, so after dinner the conversations tend to continue till late in the night, conversant stamina enhanced by said coffee and beer facilities. Evil science plans were made, good old-fashioned deep conversations were had and the early next morning consequences were flatly ignored. I haven’t laughed quite so much in a long time, but <em>that</em> part of the programme prefers, and has the right, to remain completely silent.</p>
<p>If you ever get <em>the</em> invitation, don’t hesitate for a second to accept: You shall return an exhausted but terribly happy computer nerd.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>On the importance of taking notes. [Weekly Head Voices #38]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2011 22:39:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/</guid><description>Post summary: Part one is about friends graduating from Evil School, part two is rather short mentioning vague bits of good news and part three is 100% time management and productivity boosting goodness! Feel free to skip, skim or reorder!
One On Thursday, February 10, 2011, my dear friend Mister Krekel graduated from Evil School after years of hard work and evil-doing, and will henceforth go through life as the formidable Doctor Krekel. Please do watch out. Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Part one is about friends graduating from Evil School, part two is rather short mentioning vague bits of good news and part three is 100% time management and productivity boosting goodness! Feel free to skip, skim or reorder!</em></p>
<h2 id="one">One</h2>
<p>On Thursday, February 10, 2011, my dear friend Mister Krekel graduated from Evil School after years of hard work and evil-doing, and will henceforth go through life as the formidable Doctor Krekel. Please do watch out.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_school_by_fmalan.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_school_by_fmalan.jpg"
        
            alt="Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The joyous transition took place in the Evil School’s Academiegebouw in Leiden, and this time yours truly (I’m referring to me in a round-about fashion) even had the great honour of playing a part in the formal proceedings. If you’re curious as to what exactly this ritual constitutes, see <a href="/2010/05/29/augmentation-weekly-head-voices-23/" title="previous edition of the WHV also on PhD defences in Leiden">this previous edition of the WHV</a> on the graduation of another terribly evil colleague. I believe that the bunch of us now constitute a bona fide Axis of Evil. No, the evil jokes can unfortunately not stop yet.</p>
<p>The Party was held in a secret cafe nearby. You will notice that I’ve capitalised Party, as it was not your average run of the mill Evil School graduation affair, but a social event of note. Here in Holland, the PhD defence and graduation are a combined affair, and so the whole day is dedicated to just one person. It is actually very special: People take time off from work, sometimes even temporarily put aside their differences, and travel from all over to attend the festivities. It’s like a wedding, except that there’s only one of you. I can only recommend it very highly. At the Party, everyone had clearly read the memo, and they were there with that singular goal in mind: Celebrate the freshly minted Evil Doctor. Presents were given, speeches were held, photos were shown, beer was imbibed and, flying in the face of all advice concerning the mixing of alcohol, cameras and social networking, the <a href="http://fpixel.wordpress.com/" title="link to the evil photographer">best evil photographer in town</a>, who’s coincidentally also in Evil School, took the most amazing photos that you should be able to see on Facebook if you’re one of the privileged few to belong to The Network, also known as <em>The Friends of the Axis of Evil</em>.</p>
<h2 id="two">Two</h2>
<p>On the good news front, you&rsquo;ll see (or not) on the <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/program.php" title="list of eurovis 2011 conditional accepts">list of EuroVis 2011 conditional accepts</a>, that a paper by cool colleagues from far away, to which I contributed a small part, has been conditionally accepted, and hence has a significant chance of being presented at said event in Bergen, Norway (May 31 to June 3). We also have plans to submit a poster (or two), so there&rsquo;s an even more significant chance that I will make an appearance at this fantastic conference! We&rsquo;re also cooking up various odds and ends that will hopefully crystallise sufficiently by the end of March to be submissible for VisWeek 2011. Cross yer fingers.</p>
<h2 id="three">Three</h2>
<p>Today&rsquo;s backyard time management section is in fact more about planning than it is about notes. However, my Pro-Tips involve combining them in an easy to implement productivity booster. When people start out in research, one of the first bits of advice they get is keeping some kind of lab journal. I think this advice applies to more than just research: If you do any kind of independent or project work, jotting down your activities, thoughts and results during the day is useful in helping to structure your thought processes, and also very helpful when you have to backtrack a complex multi-day procedure. During my Ph.D., I filled a number of real cardboard-and-paper books with notes. More recently, I&rsquo;ve started using Google Documents for the same purpose. Besides all the other advantages, having to document explicitly your work output keeps you productive and on your toes.</p>
<h3 id="pro-tip-1">Pro Tip #1</h3>
<p><em>Keep a lab journal, even if you don&rsquo;t work in a lab.</em></p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="/2011/01/09/2011-a-cyber-suburban-odyssey-weekly-head-voices-35/" title="2011 start post">mentioned before</a> that my resolutions for 2011 included more concrete planning. This has manifested in a work-in-progress planning for the whole year, including milestones, awards won, and so forth, but much more practically, it has manifested in a little lab-journal-compatible trick. Every morning when I sit down to begin the day, I spend a few minutes thinking and then start the day&rsquo;s journal entry by writing down, as concretely as possible, the tasks that I plan to complete by the end of the day. This also ensures that I spend effort on the <em>important</em> things, and not only on the urgent things. So, that brings us to:</p>
<h3 id="pro-tip-2">Pro Tip #2</h3>
<p><em>At the start of each day, write down in your lab journal exactly and
concretely what you plan to accomplish by the end of that day.</em></p>
<p>These pro tips appear to be quite straight-forward, but together they help one
to focus, and to keep tabs on one&rsquo;s <em>effective</em> productivity. In other words,
just being terribly busy the whole day gets you nothing; the trick is being
terribly busy in all the right directions.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Somebody is clearly pushing the boundaries of awesomeness… cowboys AND aliens!</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/In-m2RJw3hE?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Future is Sick [Weekly Head Voices #36]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/23/the-future-is-sick-weekly-head-voices-36/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2011 21:12:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/23/the-future-is-sick-weekly-head-voices-36/</guid><description>Post summary: Conference, VXLabs, SIP, boots, backyard philosophy on you the consumer, dramatic reading. Read on for more!
Just before the weekend I spent two days at the Dutch Bio-Medical Engineering Conference in Egmond aan Zee, in a ginormous seaside hotel. Probably because I attempted to keep up with the young ones during their nightly escapades, I’m currently dealing quite badly with a serious cold, which is why this is the first sick blog post of 2011. Besides all those germs, I also brought you this photo of said seaside right after sunset: Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Conference, VXLabs, SIP, boots, backyard philosophy on you the consumer, dramatic reading. Read on for more!</em></p>
<p>Just before the weekend I spent two days at the Dutch Bio-Medical Engineering Conference in Egmond aan Zee, in a ginormous seaside hotel. Probably because I attempted to keep up with the young ones during their nightly escapades, I’m currently dealing quite badly with a serious cold, which is why this is the first sick blog post of 2011.  Besides all those germs, I also brought you this photo of said seaside right after sunset:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/egmond_aan_zee_bme2011.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/egmond_aan_zee_bme2011.jpg"
        
            alt="Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The conference was an energetic and motivating affair, at which yours truly even got to chair a session, during which I tried, in spite of not getting to bed all that early the night before, to Keep Things Extremely Punctual As Well As Mildly Entertaining. I succeeded in the former, you’ll have to ask the audience about the latter.</p>
<p>The absolute highlight, for me at least, was the capstone on Friday by <a href="https://depts.washington.edu/biointel/" title="Prof. Satava's website">Professor Richard Satava</a>, a surgeon with an amazing vision of the future. Bordering on science fiction but for a large part backed by his own and other groups’ research, his superbly delivered presentation touched on surgical operating rooms completely staffed by robots (some elements remotely controlled by a surgeon), cell engineering, surgery robots that heal troops at the scene of the crime (hehe), genetic engineering, cloning and a healthy dash of trans-humanism. By the end the whole room was collectively straining at the leash to go and genetically upgrade anything and anyone they could find. With a room full of BME researchers, that’s more dangerous than it sounds. :)</p>
<p>Other note-worthy items of the past two weeks can be summarised in the following neat bullet list:</p>
<ul>
<li>I’ve started a new blog, called VXLabs, for matters that are too nerdy even for this blog. If you’re interested, you can start by reading the <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/01/22/htc-desire-z-an-in-depth-and-nerdy-review/" title="in-depth and nerdy review of the HTC Desire Z at VXLabs">HTC Desire Z (my lovely new smartphone) review</a> I’ve recently gotten around to writing. If you’re nerdy enough, you might consider subscribing VXLabs as well!</li>
<li>There are far cheaper ways than Skype to call telephones around the world. With SIP software, such as SIPDroid on Android, you can use cheap SIP servers that even offer free calls to many destinations. See <a href="http://www.backsla.sh/betamax" title="table of betamax providers">this page</a> for a list of just the betamax (German VOIP company) providers and the free countries that they support.</li>
<li>I was approached by a company producing Ugg-like boots to review their boots, get a free pair in the process, and get a good deal for my readers. This is probably because I went on about those BEAUTIFUL Timberland boots in one of my previous posts. Although I was flattered that the gentleman in question thought my widely-read (haha) opinion would be good for his brand and he called this a <em>fashion blog</em> (!!), I declined, stating that my readership probably is more into Timberlands than Uggs. That’s true, readership? Right?!</li>
<li><strong>Micro Backyard Philosophy</strong>: After one of those late nights refreshing my Twitter, Facebook, Google Reader and GMail for the Nth time, I got to thinking about how the internet sometimes turns us into 100% consumers, leaving <strong>no room for creativity</strong>. It’s insidious, because we believe that the internet will give us exactly what we crave if we just know how to search for it, and that it should do so with that next press on the refresh button, when in fact this is hardly ever the case, especially when that which you crave is in fact to create. Remember this the next time it’s getting late and you think Just One More Refresh. Don’t push that button. <strong>Sit back and think about what you really want to do</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it boys and girls, thank you very much for reading this far! You go and have yourselves a fabulous and especially creative week. If you get lonely waiting for the next edition of the Weekly Head Voices, marvel at this dramatic reading of a bad user game review, creativity at its finest:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Z2Z23SAFVA?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>An Inside Job. [Weekly Head Voices #33]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 14:10:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</guid><description>Hiatus: temporarily over.
My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to that, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am. :)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hiatus: temporarily over.</p>
<p>My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to <em>that</em>, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am. :)</p>
<p>In this post, I’m going to touch upon the highlights of the past seven weeks (40 to 46) and I’m going to do so with bullets, seeing as I’m in a bullety-kind of mood.</p>
<ul>
<li>I spent a week in Stellenbosch teaching Information Visualisation! Read all about it in <a href="/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/" title="stbvis2010 blog post">this special blog post</a>.</li>
<li>The week after that my mom came to visit us. She really has the best genes.</li>
<li>I met my new work laptop: A Dell Latitude E6410 with Core i5 M540 2.53GHz CPU, 4G ram, 500G HDD, NVidia NVS 3100m GPU with 512 MB video mem. It’s a 14″ latop (15.4″ is a completely useless format, flame me in the comments), but due to the materials used quite heavy. I like it!</li>
<li>Another one of our STW NIG research proposals has been granted. I conceived and developed this one together with colleagues from the LUMC Departments of Anatomy, of Surgery and of Orthopaedics. The title is <em>High-definition Atlas-based surgical planning for Pelvic Surgery</em> and we get to combine high-resolution human histology, mega-volume rendering, , biomechanical modelling and surgical simulation. With this grant we can appoint two more Ph.D. students (one in my group, one at the LUMC) for four years to work on this!!</li>
<li>The week after that I went to Salt Lake City (Utah, US and A) to attend the conference previously known as <a href="http://vis.computer.org/VisWeek2010/" title="IEEE VisWeek 2010 website">IEEE Visualization</a>. It was AWESOME! (blog post half-written, will soon publish).</li>
<li>The week after that I had a really cool dream: I was playing high-speed catch with a bunch of people outside. The ball was randomly changing shape between rock, papers and scissors. If you wanted to catch it, you didn’t only have to be at the right place at the right time, but your hand also had to be in the right complementary configuration to catch the shape-shifting ball.</li>
<li>Now that we’re talking about dreams: <em>I finally saw <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1375666/" title="IMDB page for Inception">Inception</a> and was completely blown away.</em> It’s not about being complicated, it’s about being a well-told story and a fantastically filmed movie. What I positively adored, is the fact that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan" title="Wikipedia page about Christopher Nolan">Nolan</a> doesn’t require much: He only needs you to believe that dreams can be shared, without giving away too many of the details of the mechanism, and then builds a marvellous story on that canvas. My absolute favourite scene was the waking up on the plane, just before the landing, almost at the end of the film. I loved the way in which the characters looked at each other, and the possible interpretations of their expressions.</li>
<li>On the topic of the Underworld gig in the Heineken Music Hall: I hope I have my voice back before my morning lecture tomorrow morning. Thank you Fantastic Friends!</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it kids. If you’ve come this far, you’re now mostly up to date. Please leave me a comment, it’s good for my serotonin! I hope you have a great week. To get you off to a  good start, here’s a music video showing what an infectious idea could look like…</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<div class="embed-vimeo" style="text-align: center;">
<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="473" mozallowfullscreen="" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/15391189" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="840"></iframe>
</div>
</div>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Teaching InfoVis in Stellenbosch</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 11:42:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/</guid><description>In week 40 (that’s Monday October 4 to Friday October 8 for those of you not so much into week numbers) I had the privilege of giving a week-long Information Visualisation course to a group of post-graduate students (a mix of B.A. Honours in either Socio-informatics or in Decision-making and Values Studies) at the Centre for KDD of the University of Stellenbosch in the building previously-known-as “The BJ”.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In week 40 (that’s Monday October 4 to Friday October 8 for those of you not so much into week numbers) I had the privilege of giving a week-long Information Visualisation course to a group of post-graduate students (a mix of B.A. Honours in either Socio-informatics or in Decision-making and Values Studies) at the <a href="http://www.informatics.sun.ac.za/" title="Centre for KDD website">Centre for KDD</a> of the University of Stellenbosch in the building previously-known-as “The BJ”.</p>
<p>With this post, I want to summarise, extremely compactly, my impressions:</p>
<ul>
<li>In spite of the odd publication at an InfoVis venue, and in spite of putting significant effort into broadening my horizons also into InfoVis, I’m strictly speaking still a Scientific Visualisation (SciVis) guy. In this context, developing and giving an InfoVis course was a fantastically educational experience. I aspire to be equally fluent in SciVis and InfoVis when I grow up.</li>
<li>I designed a course based on a mix of lecturing, paper reading and discussion and hands-on exercises. I can now highly recommend this combination. Next time I will put more effort into involving everyone more actively in the discussion. What also seemed to work well was the course website that students could add their work to during class.</li>
<li>I sourced almost all of my material from generous InfoVis colleagues, primarily Dr. Tamara Munzner, but also Dr. John Stasko, Prof.dr. Jarke van Wijk and Dr. Maneesh Agrawala. Thank you!</li>
<li>Having spent 7 years at the Stellenbosch Engineering Faculty (1500 guys all wearing t-shirts in jeans; furthermore, social skills are frowned upon) and the past 10 years at the TU Delft, a kind of Ultra-Engineering-Faculty, spending the week at The BJ interacting with socially adept and skilled communicators was a truly interesting experience.</li>
<li>I was otherwise also impressed with the level of cooperation between the students and their willingness to work hard (and long).</li>
<li>Laptop-use during lectures in a relatively small class: It’s an interesting phenomenon, having to deal with your own little <a href="http://mariandoerk.de/visualbackchannel/" title="visual backchannel paper at infovis 2010">communication backchannel</a>. Banning laptop use is obviously not an option as there are too many possible advantages, but I’m not sure yet what a good solution would be towards making sure that the laptops are being used to augment learning.</li>
<li>Most students chose <a href="http://vis.stanford.edu/protovis/" title="ProtoVis website">ProtoVis</a> (from <a href="http://stbvis2010.medvis.org/syllabus/p-infovis-design" title="list of software toolkits stbvis2010 students could use">a list of 8 possibilities</a>, and they were free to use anything else too) to implement their final mini-projects with. This was probably due to their previous web-programming experience, and also that ProtoVis requires more or less zero setup.</li>
</ul>
<p>Conclusion: Much learned, hopefully the students did too. :) All in all a positive and energising experience!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>