<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Obsidian on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/obsidian/</link><description>Recent content in Obsidian on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/obsidian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #261: Father's day</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</guid><description>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.
Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive
The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.
&amp;ndash; Marcel Proust
Bliss It&amp;rsquo;s father&amp;rsquo;s day today.
When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250428_clarence_pano.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_9407df7811cef8cf.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_4f5b997776ce1c56.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_72fa3b251facc47.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp"
            

        
            alt="Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<blockquote>
<p>The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.</p>
<p>&ndash; Marcel Proust</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="bliss">Bliss</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s father&rsquo;s day today.</p>
<p>When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</p>
<p>Hearing that we were up, GOU #2 came out of her room, with a beautiful illustration she had made for (and of!) me. (GOU #2 has found her passion in drawing. She practises on most days, and her skill and talent are very obvious.)</p>
<p>Soon after, GOU #1 arrived home with flat whites (my favourite), fresh ciabatta and croissants from the bakery, and hugs.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m trying to say here is that when your offspring units all tell you in their different ways that they appreciate you being their dad, when you&rsquo;re fundamentally dedicated to and deeply grateful for being just that, and those very offspring units constitute the whole focus of this important life endeavour, you better hope that you are able to keep those eyes dry.</p>
<h2 id="vo-max-redux">VO₂ Max redux</h2>
<p>One of my <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">exercise goals for 2024</a> was to reach a VO₂ Max of at least (HAHAHA) 50.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t make it in 2024, but I also didn&rsquo;t do anything other than just my normal running during the year. I know that I should probably engage in some high intensity interval training of some sort if I really want to move the needle, but I run because I like running and not because I want to be fit, although I do want to be fit. (It&rsquo;s complicated being a teenager.)</p>
<p>At the start of 2025, I stated, much more softly this time, that I would maybe <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">still like to hit that 50 VO₂ Max</a>.</p>
<p>Again I realized I would have probably have to <em>do</em> something interval-ly about it, but again I kept on postponing.</p>
<p>WELL KIDS it turns out that postponing can also be a winning strategy! On Monday, May 19, my Garmin reported that I had indeed hit a VO₂ Max of 50, which, <a href="https://www8.garmin.com/manuals/webhelp/GUID-C001C335-A8EC-4A41-AB0E-BAC434259F92/EN-US/GUID-1FBCCD9E-19E1-4E4C-BD60-1793B5B97EB3.html">according to its tables</a>, places me at the bottom of the coveted top-most category for my age and gender, namely <em>Superior</em>.</p>
<p>I always knew it, but thanks anyways Garmin!</p>
<p>P.S. I do have to deflate my <em>superiority</em> a bit by reminding us all that, in addition to finding myself at the bottom of the superior range, I have also only recently entered my current age section, giving me an extra advantage. Jokes aside, 50 at 50 is not bad, so allow me to bask for a while.</p>
<h2 id="org-mode-timestamps-in-obsidian">org-mode timestamps in obsidian</h2>
<p>One feature I have really been missing in Obsidian since <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my recent break-up with Org-mode</a> is the amazing org timestamps.</p>
<p>There is no real convention in Obsidian, whilst in Org-mode timestamps <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Timestamps.html">are well-defined and quite functional</a>. My &ldquo;old&rdquo; notes are scattered with them: time ranges, scheduled times, deadlines, random timestamps inside random text notes.</p>
<p>The time logging script <a href="/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/#loggin-time">I mentioned previously</a> made use of the dataview-convention of adding timestamps to work items for example:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 (start:: 2025-05-20T07:55) - (end:: 2025-05-20T08:10)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; which did work but was no fun to work with.</p>
<p>Long story short, I could not resist for much longer, and so I hacked together a new Obsidian plugin called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian-org-timestamps">Org timestamps</a>.</p>
<p>As you can see in the comparative screenshots below, I&rsquo;ve copied the org-mode timestamp and time range format verbatim, with the additional bonus of rendering these timestamps nicely in preview mode, inspired by <a href="https://github.com/minad/org-modern">the Emacs package org-modern</a>.</p>
<p>Deviating from org-mode proper, my plugin also renders date-less timestamps &ndash; I often use these when adding entries to daily file. Speaking of which, full org timestamps can have <code>[[...]]</code> links around the date parts so that they link back to the relevant daily file.</p>








    


<figure><a href="obsidian-org-timestamps.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_e1ef46eb4edabd57.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_2719acebe5e07bc9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_f52dbf2785777e5.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>In addition to the rendering, the plugin also offers commands to move any timestamps to the nearest 5 minutes forward or backward, similar to what org-mode does with <code>shift-up/down</code>, and a feature I have always used multiple times per day.</p>
<p>Putting all of this together, my monthly time logging files now has entries that look like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 &lt;2025-05-20 07:55-08:10&gt;
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; and I can tweak those timestamps with the adjustment commands.</p>
<p>I have adapted the logging script to support both the old dataview-style and org-timestamp-style timestamps, and now the barely usable UX has become a tad less barely.</p>
<p><em>(10 minutes later&hellip;)</em></p>
<p>Because I keep on mentioning the script, I guess it&rsquo;s time to <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian_dataview_timelogging">put it online</a>, albeit extremely barely. Let me know in the comments below if you are the one other user on the planet who would like to try this.</p>
<h2 id="my-friend-this-is-the-end-again">My friend this is the end again</h2>
<p>This was one of the most stubborn WHVs I have pushed out in a very long time.</p>
<p>Before it became this hard, it used to be easier: Somehow there was always something to talk about, either interesting or entertaining, or both.</p>
<p>Although this could also just be another symptom of  me getting older, it does feel like the whole online landscape has changed quite substantially.</p>
<p>Up until recently, it was only dopamine-targeting social media which affected the way people read (or don&rsquo;t) blog posts, but these days I imagine that I&rsquo;m also detecting a whiff of AI-nihilism. Although I still feel strongly about writing each of these words by myself, the experience of the resultant output happens on the background of machines that can now generate hundreds of perfectly-written versions of this post in an instant.</p>
<p>Anyways, I plan to continue with this labour of love, even as it becomes increasingly difficult.</p>
<p>P.S. My recent reading / book-listening has taken me on fascinating journeys through neuroscience and consciousness. Before reaching this point right here, I mistakenly thought that I would share more about them in this post. Instead I&rsquo;m going to leave you with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I am not a thing in the world; I am the space in which the world is happening.</p>
<p>&ndash; Richard Lang</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #260: I'm not your guy, buddy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</guid><description>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.
The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. GOU #3 (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining. It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250322_palmiet_hike.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_94326a752c7d0837.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_3039937a478d9ff0.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_95661b4813429562.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&rsquo;s Bay. <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #3</a> (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining.  It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</p>
<p>A week or two later, GOU #3 recovered by being an absolute trooper through the whole of the slightly more substantial and absolutely brilliant 6.5km family hike all around the little <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/rreQJ7uyT1SFSKfJ7">Sea Farm private reserve&rsquo;s peninsula</a>. I tell myself, and others, that this is partially due to involving her in the progress of the event, by showing her at regular intervals on Google Maps exactly where we found ourselves, and how we were making progress around the peninsula.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, we will both have better answers to the question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why am I in such a rush to get through life when I want so much to enjoy it?</p>
<p>&ndash; Jan Chozen Bays</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(With that in mind, you might also find <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237</a> interesting!)</p>
<h2 id="the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-migrates-again">The whole cpbotha.net-hive migrates again</h2>
<p>Slightly more than five years after <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">the previous migration of the whole so-called cpbotha.net-hive from WebFaction (RIP) to Hetzner</a>, I got an offer I could not refuse, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/mackuba.eu/post/3ll7dgrep7c25">on Bluesky (!)</a>, for a <a href="https://www.netcup.com/en/server/vps/vps-1000-g11-12m-iv">netcup VPS</a> with double the number of vCPUs, double the RAM and 5x the storage, all for about 25% cheaper every month.</p>
<p>On the weekend of March 28 I managed to port the six websites in question across (3 easy static ones, including this blog, and 3 slightly more tricky wordpress ones).</p>
<p>I am most grateful that as part of this porting effort I have now finally been able to dockerize the binaries I built years ago of the super obscure <a href="https://github.com/ma-tech/WlzIIPSrv">WlzIIPSrv fork of the C++ IIP image slice server</a> and will in future be able to migrate much more easily if I ever need to do so again. WlzIIPSrv is the software that serves the pannable and zoomable histology slices when you browse a <a href="https://visible-orbit.org/slices/dk2904l-registered/">visible-orbit.org (wordpress site also hosted on this new server) stack like this one</a>.</p>
<p>Although this migration is a significant and positive technical event for me, most of you will probably not even notice that this site responds a tad (or three) more snappily than it used to.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am celebrating that this is officially the first blog post coming to you from this shiny new server!</p>
<h2 id="productivity-devolution">Productivity (d)evolution</h2>
<h3 id="just-get-it-done-with-kanban">Just get it done with Kanban</h3>
<p>Someone once called using Trello for task management &ldquo;the time management connoisseur equivalent of lying in the gutter with a cheap bottle of wine in a brown paper bag&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(So, by the way, that someone was me! See <a href="/2014/11/27/weekly-head-voices-86-beardy/#note-taking-and-todo-system-chaos-nerd-warning">the previous admission on this blog, in WHV #86 from 2014</a>, original source of my statement is <a href="https://noeskasmit.com/comparison-of-task-managers-rtm-astrid-wunderlist-todoist/#comment-71">this comment on Noeska&rsquo;s blog</a>.)</p>
<p>I mention this now, because my current system, the one which has to act as replacement for <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my almighty Emacs Org-mode</a>, is a monthly Kanban board with columns for &ldquo;todo&rdquo;, &ldquo;today / next&rdquo;, &ldquo;doing&rdquo; and &ldquo;done&rdquo;, and task cards that I can move, quite satisfyingly, from column to column, which is essentially a less full-featured but fully local version of my old Trello-based system.</p>
<p>While the 2014-org-mode-me mind really cannot comprehend this, the current system, based on the plugins <a href="https://github.com/mgmeyers/obsidian-kanban">obsidian-kanban</a> and <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/tasks/Introduction">obsidian-tasks</a>, is working just fine for the moment.</p>
<h3 id="pomodori-made-from-100-xbar">pomodori made from 100% xbar</h3>
<p>You might recall from the previous WHV that I was still <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#productivity-hack-of-the-year">using Emacs as an over-powered pomodoro timer</a>.</p>
<p>Well, even that started itching a bit too much, and now I&rsquo;ve just re-implemented the whole thing, along with the productivity boosting auto-DnD setting, by <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/xbar-pomodoro-timer-with-DnD-for-macOS">modifying an existing self-contained macOS xbar script</a> which you can use if you too wish to work harder.</p>
<h3 id="loggin-time">Loggin&rsquo; time</h3>
<p>Together with the pomodoro timing, I was also using org-mode to maintain detailed time logs for work, using the built-in org-clock functionality.</p>
<p>Because of above-mentioned itch, I now have a semi-usable replacement which I put together as an <a href="https://blacksmithgu.github.io/obsidian-dataview/api/code-reference/#dvviewpath-input">Obsidian Dataview custom view</a>, in other words, a bunch of javascript that piggy-backs on the dataview parser and groups bullet items with start and end timestamps under their parent tasks and container headings, as projects, in order to spit out daily and monthly timelog breakdowns.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve only been testing this since the start of April. Although it&rsquo;s giving me all of the data that I need, the UX is just barely over the threshold of usable-by-me.</p>
<p>Perhaps in the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll find some time to write more about this tool to hear what others think.</p>
<h2 id="the-bozo-explosion">The Bozo explosion</h2>
<p>My great friend Dave told me about this phenomenon, of which I then had to go find the source.</p>
<p>It turns out the originator is none other than Steve Jobs, with the idea being injected into the internet hive-mind by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_Kawasaki">Guy Kawasaki</a>, a Guy who worked for Jobs at Apple (I see what I&rsquo;m doing here) from 1983 until about 1986.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a short but great post by Guy Kawasaki titled <a href="https://guykawasaki.com/what-i-learned-from-steve-jobs/">What I Learned From Steve Jobs</a> which is definitely worth a few minutes of your time.</p>
<p>Here I want to focus on point 9, namely &ldquo;A players hire A+ players&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve personally seen this a number of times with the smartest and best leaders I&rsquo;ve ever had the privilege of interacting with. They, the A players, actively seek and appoint colleagues who are smarter or better than they are, the A+ players. They absolutely revel in the opportunity of being challenged by the best people they can find. This turns into a positive feedback loop, with more and more similarly capable people seeking out their peers.</p>
<p>The opposite of this happens when you start with B players. B players easily feel threatened by more capable folks, and so they tend to recruit C players so that they can maintain the pecking order. Those C players will accordingly recruit D players and so on. This process of course leads to what Jobs coined as &ldquo;the Bozo explosion&rdquo;, which sounds frighteningly similar to what is currently happening in some parts of the world today.</p>
<p>Next time when you&rsquo;re evaluating a new opportunity, do make some time to ensure that the folks involved have the A player mentality.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>For future me, here&rsquo;s a list of other notable events from the period under review:</p>
<ul>
<li>Two 50th celebrations.</li>
<li>Various very special eating and drinking occasions with treasured friends, some from afar, and family.</li>
<li>Three family hikes.</li>
<li>1 Sting concert (with my life partner) which exceeded all my expectations.</li>
<li>My first running race (Spookhill challenge).</li>
<li>Visits with Parisian friends and family to the breathtaking <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeitz_Museum_of_Contemporary_Art_Africa">Zeitz Museum of Contemporary Art Africa (MOCAA)</a> and the Two Oceans aquarium.</li>
<li>Far too many marshmallow eggs.</li>
</ul>
<p>&hellip; and with that, I would like to leave you with this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The trick is to learn how to want the things you already have.</p>
<p>&ndash; William B. Irvine</p>
</blockquote>








    


<figure><a href="zeitz_mocaa_ocular.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7e8591922bb9e2d9.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_426183b3ab1ebea9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7a603b5cd15f6d27.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp"
            

        
            alt="Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!-- "not your guy, buddy" from the South Park episode "Canada on strike" https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1211261/characters/nm0005295/ --> ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #259: Backbone</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</guid><description> Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!
(I just learned that the English connoisseur comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved connaisseur (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little oi.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







    


<figure><a href="bettys_sunset.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_84d7d5fb2023d1f3.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_94ef9e4fb9dd976e.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_b061658b14bcf3ec.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!</p>
<p>(I <em>just</em> learned that the English <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/connoisseur"><em>connoisseur</em> comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling</a>. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved <em>connaisseur</em> (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little <em>oi</em>.)</p>
<h2 id="how-do-you-do-fellow-humans">How do you do, fellow humans?</h2>
<p>This Sunday morning I browsed through all of my Obsidian daily entries, starting from Monday January 20, the day after <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/">The 2024 to 2025 transition post</a> appeared, because the urge to write here has become quite persistent of late, an urge that is clearly quite oblivious to my feeling that it has become increasingly more tricky to make the time to sit down and focus on just this one thing.</p>
<p>I, very briefly I should add, considered feeding all of those daily posts to one of our artificial friends to extract highlights, but for the time-being, I really like that every word you read here was produced by my laborious and messy (fluids-based, for the most part) biology-based process.</p>
<p>This means that I read every single stupid word I wrote in those daily entries, re-experienced various emotions, some of them transformed by the ever-changing self, while I read them, and let those ideas all simmer for a while in the wetware mostly enclosed by my skull, before sitting down here and producing a new set of emotions whilst typing out a bunch of new words on this (mechanical) keyword.</p>
<p>Blood, sweat and tears my friends, blood sweat and tears.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Since my last entry here, I&rsquo;ve been reading a lot more, something that I&rsquo;m really happy about.</p>
<p>Besides the deep-seated and strong instinct that reading good books makes me a better human, it also turns out to be an <em>excellent</em> doom-scrolling suppressant, by virtue of simply pushing that activity out of one&rsquo;s daily schedule.</p>
<p>Apart from that motivation, what has made a huge difference in my reading volume was adding audiobooks as well as Zotero on my laptop to the reading modality mix.</p>
<p>Where I previously would only read on my Kindle e-reader, I&rsquo;ve discovered that picking the right medium for the right book means I can comfortably use these three channels during different phases of the day.</p>
<p>In the evening right before closing my eyes, I usually read fiction on the Kindle. After 10 to 20 minutes of reading, my eyes start closing of their own accord and my brain shuts down. Current Kindle book: <a href="https://www.gregegan.net/MORPHOTROPHIC/MORPHOTROPHIC.html">Morphotrophic by Greg Egan</a>. <a href="/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/#permutation-city">Egan has previously appeared on this blog</a> for a much older creation which I really loved.</p>
<p>During the day in the car on short commutes, I prefer to read non-fiction books like <a href="https://www.ynharari.com/book/nexus/">Nexus by Yuval Harari</a> (which I loved by the way). With Nexus at 1.5x speed, which is still very comfortable, it was around 17 hours of listening time which went by a lot faster than I expected. I&rsquo;m currently on [<em>Behave: The Biology of Humans at Our Best and Worst</em> by Robert M. Sapolsky] which is super entertaining and extremely successful at repeatedly blowing my mind.</p>
<p>Some non-fiction books deserve even closer attention, like <a href="https://www.abriefhistoryofintelligence.com/">Max Bennett&rsquo;s <em>A Brief History of Intelligence</em></a>, which I started reading on my Kindle but then completed on my laptop, using the fantastic epub reader in Zotero. With this tool I can make highlights and notes to my heart&rsquo;s content.</p>








    


<figure><a href="screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_fd5d3cc24c0400cb.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_ded6f76846ff592d.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_a10ae5587078729c.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>On the topic of Zotero, the two features that would make it even more perfect for me are <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/pull/836">the iOS epub support</a>, so I can open annotated epubs on the go, and <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/issues/597">iOS webpage snapshot support</a>, so that I can save <a href="https://github.com/gildas-lormeau/SingleFile">SingleFile</a> snapshots of web pages from my phone like on desktop, and not just the link.</p>
<h3 id="thanks-for-nothing-amazon">Thanks for nothing Amazon</h3>
<p>On that topic, <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/02/psa-amazon-kills-download-transfer-via-usb-option-for-kindles-this-week/">on February 26 Amazon killed the Kindle &ldquo;download &amp; transfer via USB&rdquo; feature</a>, the exact feature that I&rsquo;ve always used to make copies of Kindle titles for my own use, most often for highlighting and further study, sometimes leading to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/book/">book notes posts</a>.</p>
<p>Although I really appreciated the convenience of e.g. hearing about a book, and then being able to purchase and start reading that book within minutes, this user-hostile move by Amazon is the last straw for me.  All the way back in 2016, <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2016/08/21/amazon-owns-your-ebooks/">friend Stéfan warned us all about the Kindle Swindle</a>, i.e. the way that Amazon restricts ebook rights far more than necessary, and is in essence able to &ldquo;switch off&rdquo; all ebooks that you have bought.</p>
<p>For me personally, this latest move just means that I will drastically reduce my spending on Kindle books, and anything else from Amazon, as far as possible.</p>
<h2 id="101-productivity-hacks-for-stubborn-people">101 productivity hacks for stubborn people</h2>
<p>Also known as The Productivity Section!</p>
<h3 id="a-bientôt-monsieur-org">A bientôt monsieur Org</h3>
<p>In the 24/25 year transition post I talked about <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#emacs-and-obsidian">my apparently eternally brewing personal tension between Emacs and Obsidian</a>.</p>
<p>It looks like I might have found myself in the third <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_stages_of_grief">stage of grief</a>, namely <em>bargaining</em>, when I wrote that I would explore the interplay between the two poles of Emacs and Obsidian.</p>
<p>Well, as I write this, it feels like I might have reached the fifth and final stage, namely <em>acceptance</em>, acceptance of the fact that orgmode (note, not Emacs, but orgmode), although far more powerful and flexible, is probably always going to be the silo that it currently is, in contrast to markdown (note, not necessarily Obsidian) which, while functionality-wise is but a shadow of orgmode, is hugely more accessible and inter-operates with everyone and their dogs.</p>
<p>You see, since writing that transition post, I&rsquo;ve been creating more and more markdown notes, to the extent that I keep on running into the inconvenience of orgmode nexus nodes which I can in theory link to from markdown, but with links that are not as fully featured as markdown to markdown links.</p>
<p>It really does seem like &ldquo;interplay&rdquo; is turning into &ldquo;dominance&rdquo;, if you&rsquo;ll excuse my multiple layers of innuendo here.</p>
<p>And so after a really good 10 year run as orgmode-disciple, as chronicled by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">10+ years of vxlabs posts on the topic</a>, a bunch of <a href="/tags/orgmode/">appearances on this blog</a> and even <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">the orgmode-exocortex</a>, it&rsquo;s time to read the writing on the wall, writing that upon closer inspection has turned out to be in markdown format after all.</p>
<h3 id="productivity-hack-of-the-year">Productivity hack of the year</h3>
<p>In a textbook case of <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2024/06/07/report-death/">greatly exaggerated rumours of someone&rsquo;s demise</a>, my orgmode isn&rsquo;t completely dead yet&hellip;</p>
<p>By far the most effective productivity hack I&rsquo;ve implemented in many months, in terms of actual focus hours gained, has been the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar">orgmode-based pomodoro timer I hacked together and wrote about in my other OTHER website TIL section</a>.</p>
<p>While it was already helpful to have a boring text-based pomodoro-timer display a countdown on my macOS menubar, I had wildly underestimated how much impact the addition of <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar#double-bonus-macos-do-not-disturb-during-pomodoro">the automatic do-not-disturb mode</a> would have.</p>
<p>When I start the 25 minute pomodoro focus timer, my script automatically activates the so-called do-not-disturb &ldquo;focus&rdquo; across all of my (Apple) devices. For those 25 minutes, absolutely nothing pings or alerts, and only calls by my my inner-inner circle can get through. When the 25 minutes are up, DnD is disabled across all devices, and I can see to any emergencies that might have occurred.</p>
<p>(🍅 These particular paragraphs are being typed within such an interruption-proof pomodoro BTW.)</p>
<h2 id="how-are-the-children">How are the children?</h2>
<p>Why thank you for asking!</p>
<p>Here I would like to mention that Genetic Offspring Unit #1 (GOU#1) has now experienced the first few weeks of industrial engineering at university (which is the same as the first few weeks of most of the engineering disciplines) and seems to be loving it to bits.</p>
<p>It brings me great joy that, in spite of the fact that she is a wonderfully well-adjusted and socially graceful human, her engineering DNA is shining through brilliantly. This way of thinking suits her, she just seems to get it, and she&rsquo;s really <em>enjoying the work</em>.</p>
<p>P.S. It also brings me joy, but also a tiny bit of concern, that she really enjoys and also sometimes makes dad jokes <em>AT ME</em>.</p>
<h2 id="spiritual-hygiene-backbone">Spiritual hygiene backbone</h2>
<p>All of that reading I wrote about a few paragraphs back somehow happens even when my days seem to fall apart due to general life chaos, various distractions many of my own (unintentional design) and/or due to will power failure on my part.</p>
<p>So on those days, when I finally fall asleep reading, I console myself with the affirmation that the day was not <em>complete</em> chaos, at least I&rsquo;ve done some reading&hellip;</p>
<p>The same goes for my running.</p>
<p>A seemingly low-level function somewhere in my system <em>needs</em> to take me out running an average of three times a week.</p>
<p>Even when I don&rsquo;t want to, I often find myself standing outside in my shoes and ready to go.</p>
<p>It does help that I&rsquo;ve programmed myself with the mantra &ldquo;If you&rsquo;re wondering whether you should go run the answer is YES&rdquo;.</p>
<p>During my many low-power moments, that mantra often nudges me over the edge.</p>
<p>My daily writing habit also seems to be getting stronger.</p>
<p>I might be tired, or distracted, but <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#multiplicity-of-you">one of the voices</a> often gets me to write with mind-tricks like &ldquo;oh just a bullet or two man, surely you can manage that?&rdquo; to which my simple mind succumbs, and before I know it, I&rsquo;ve written a few more bullets, and maybe even a paragraph or two.</p>
<p>Unbeknownst to simple mind (shhhht), retro- and introspection have now been performed, and prepared for future review.</p>
<p>I have now come to realise that these three habits, namely reading, running and writing, and their various positive feedback loops, together form a pretty decent <em>spiritual hygiene backbone</em>.</p>
<p>Especially when the rest feels like it wants to flop around or even fall apart, this backbone is a robust, reliable and, quite importantly, <em>simple</em> construct that defines my desired internal structure, enabling me to maintain focus and humanity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>