<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Meetings on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/meetings/</link><description>Recent content in Meetings on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 22:15:07 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/meetings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #227: Reality bending security blanket</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 22:15:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.
This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.
Groundhog Lockdown On the above-mentioned Sunday, president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4, one level more serious from where we were.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="backyard_walk_s_and_i.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hu_a68b691dbdf99b45.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hu_be557d50d4d8e5ff.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hu_407681b3046b5494.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hu_d96757f16cdef4a2.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hu_be557d50d4d8e5ff.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from
Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.</p>
<h2 id="groundhog-lockdown">Groundhog Lockdown</h2>
<p>On the above-mentioned Sunday, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/level-4-lockdown-for-south-africa-for-14-days-2021-6">president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4</a>,
one level more serious from where we were.</p>
<p>For us this means that schools are closing a week earlier for the July
vacation, and hence will have to open a week earlier, and hence will have a
severe effect on the breakaway we had planned, an effect of the
<em>cancellation</em> variety.</p>
<p>Although frustrating (some of us really need that precious time away to keep
calm and carry on afterwards), we don&rsquo;t really have anything to complain about
if that is our biggest problem.</p>
<p>Gauteng province has been hit really hard by the third wave of COVID, and
specifically this new Delta variant.</p>
<p>This modified lockdown level 4 explicitly prohibits travel into and out of the
province in order to help stem the disease&rsquo;s spread.</p>
<p>In other news, our vaccination is making progress, albeit at a slower pace than
most people had hoped.</p>
<p>In a few days they are going to start with the over 50s. No, this does not
include me yet, although I am close.</p>
<h2 id="amazon-document-culture">Amazon document culture</h2>
<p>Last week, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=27545331">Hacker News discussed</a> a really interesting <a href="https://www.justingarrison.com/blog/2021-03-15-the-document-culture-of-amazon/">blog post by an Amazon
employee about Amazon&rsquo;s document culture</a>.</p>
<p>In short, at Amazon, a meeting can only happen if a document has been written
detailing what is to be discussed during the meeting.</p>
<p>At the start of the meeting, everyone gets from 10 minutes to half an hour,
depending on what makes sense for the document under discussion, to read the
document, and only then the meeting starts.</p>
<p>This approach has many advantages, discussed in the blog post.</p>
<p>What I personally like about doing it this way, is that the convenor of the
meeting has to pay a price for that meeting, namely sitting down and spending
time to structure their thoughts on paper well enough so it will satisfy the
expectations of the participants.</p>
<p>Furthermore, by dedicating quiet time to reading the document, one has a
slightly better guarantee that everyone is up to date with the background, and,
more interesting to me, is that it sets a more deliberate and thoughtful mood
for the whole meeting.</p>
<p>Of course I tried this out at the first high-level meeting that I could, where
I had to present a plan to the participants.</p>
<p>It felt a bit strange initiating this silent reading at the start, but my
perception is that it contributed to a higher quality discussion afterwards.</p>
<p>In this case it was easy, because the goal of the meeting was to present a plan
that was already a document. However, this is something I will definitely want
to repeat.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, the document will be all that is required.</p>
<h2 id="your-choice">Your choice</h2>
<p>In <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">WHV #226</a> I wrote that I had chosen to be in the situation that was causing
stress due to its new challenges.</p>
<p>Friend SvdW (jokingly? chidingly?) commented via private communications
channels that that &ldquo;choice&rdquo; had surprised him, seeing that <a href="https://philosophybreak.com/articles/free-will-illusion-sam-harris/">we have no free
will</a>.</p>
<p>He is right of course, but in this case it <em>is</em> in fact all about the illusion,
about being subjectively convinced that one is the agent and the author of
one&rsquo;s current situation.</p>
<p>This did remind me something I wrote in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#productivity-system-tuneup">WHV #185</a> about how this same framing
can be effective against procrastination:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have chosen to
take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having decided
to commit, i.e. active.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the cases where you believe that you <em>are</em> probably the agent of your
situation, it can really help to verbalise that to yourself in the way
described above.</p>
<p>This can sometimes be tricky, because so much of it has to do with potentially
subjective-reality-bending framing, which could get in the way of addressing
problems external to oneself.</p>
<p>If you apply This One Trick, and you do a great job, how real were those
external problems in the first place?</p>
<p>On days like these, I get a feeling, albeit an extremely faint one, for why
Descartes constructed the mental security blanket of <em>cogito ergo sum</em>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>