<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>eaz on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/eaz/</link><description>Recent content in eaz on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 22:28:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/eaz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #197: How to ship side-projects</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 22:28:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/</guid><description> Hello friends!
Weekly Head Voices #197 looks back at the week from Monday June 1 to Sunday June 7.
Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect.
Work-work is quite high intensity at the moment.
I really would not mind a bit of respite any time soon now.
In the meantime, let me look back, and by the crazy laws of metaphysics also inwards, at the previous week:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello friends!</p>
<p>Weekly Head Voices #197 looks back at the week from Monday June 1 to Sunday June 7.</p>








<figure><a href="morgenster.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Work-work is quite high intensity at the moment.</p>
<p>I really would not mind a bit of respite any time soon now.</p>
<p>In the meantime, let me look back, and by the crazy laws of metaphysics
also inwards, at the previous week:</p>
<h2 id="on-slipping-and-shipping-a-side-project">On slipping and shipping a side-project</h2>
<p>I have <a href="/2018/05/13/weekly-head-voices-142-theory-of-mind/#the-side-project-dilemma">written</a> <a href="/2018/09/03/weekly-head-voices-152-a-small-but-highly-trained-team-of-11-year-olds/#au-revoir">before</a> about nerds and their side-projects.</p>
<p>You might recall that I said that they mostly don&rsquo;t ever see the light of day,
although they still have indirect benefits.</p>
<p>In any case, the two I linked to above both failed, so at least that&rsquo;s nice for
consistency.</p>
<p>However, on Friday I went and bucked the trend ever so slightly by
soft-launching the Lazar Focus app and website distraction blocker for Windows.</p>
<p>I <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">mentioned LF last week</a>, but it now has a website, called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">lazarfocused.com</a>,
and it has a <a href="https://gumroad.com/l/yExQgr">product page on gumroad</a>.</p>
<p>It has a <em>substantially</em> smaller number of bugs thanks to brilliant beta
testing by multi-modal medical visualization expert and productivity app
<em>connoisseuse</em> <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/">Noeska</a>.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re on Windows, this is exactly the little app you need to block
distractions, only when you say so of course, so that you can focus on all of
The Important Stuff™ you undoubtedly would rather get done, so that you
can get back to goofing off.</p>
<p>AMIRITE?!</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re one of those people who don&rsquo;t need any help to help focusing and to
stay in the zone, but you work with people who might, the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/06/06/the-philosophy-behind-lazar-focus/">philosophy behind
Lazar Focus</a> blog post is a good introduction to share with them. (Also, could I
interview you? :)</p>
<h2 id="dry-january-finally-ends--or-maybe-not--with-rochefort">Dry January finally ends (or maybe not) with Rochefort</h2>
<p>This year, I <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">started Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) on January 6</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m happy to report that this was interrupted only once for a superb glass of
my favourite Chardonnay (that&rsquo;s the Haskell Anvil, see <a href="/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/#what-i-did-in-week-41">WHV #181</a> for the first
encounter) with besties, right at the source.</p>
<p>Other than that, I remained in EAZ until Saturday, June 6, when the St
Bernhardus Abt 12 and the Trappistes Rochefort #8 and #10 that a friend had
brought for me all the way from The Netherlands and that had been waiting
patiently for me in the cupboard, had just been sitting there waiting for long
enough.</p>
<p>(By the way, the St Bernhardus Abt 12 is a taste clone of the Westvleteren, the
pretty expensive king of the Trappist beers, as a drunk gentleman once
explained to me in the Doerak in Delft late one evening. He was right, as my
companion and I subsequently confirmed when we acquired both beers for a
comparative tasting on the spot.)</p>
<p>The time, but far more pertinently the opportunity, had come to end (or was it
merely to interrupt&hellip;) EAZ 2020.</p>
<p>Friends, that Rochefort is simply packed with a multitude of sweet, warm
memories of days and evenings in my other home, with my other family.</p>








<figure><a href="rochefort_8_action_shot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Just in case you needed reminding, the Rochefort 8 looks like this. Memories of a lifetime not pictured."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Just in case you needed reminding, the Rochefort 8 looks like this. Memories of a lifetime not pictured.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>(Going even further back, I have <a href="/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/">mentioned before</a> that this blog contains <a href="/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/">a
written record of my very first encounter with Rochefort</a>, all the way back in
2003, right in the town of La Roche-en-Ardenna, about 30 minutes away from
Rochefort itself. Reading that post now, it really was a sort of WHV avant la
lettre!)</p>
<h2 id="the-last-bit">The last bit</h2>
<p>Ok folks, it is now 22:17 on Thursday evening, and I&rsquo;m at that super difficult
&ldquo;HOW IN THOR&rsquo;S NAME DO I CONCLUDE THIS THING?!&quot;-stage, a problem which I seem
to be solving with the &ldquo;I KNOW LET&rsquo;S BREAK THE FOURTH WALL / SIMPLY TALK
ABOUT HOW WE DON&rsquo;T KNOW HOW TO END THIS THING&rdquo;-manoeuvre.</p>
<p>On the bright side, I think we did <em>just</em> make the deadline with this edition
of the WHV, narrowly avoiding postponement and a larger-than-normal next post.</p>
<p>Have a brilliant rest of the week and weekend. I look forward to seeing you
again, here and anywhere!</p>
<p>P.S. I still don&rsquo;t know how to ship side-projects.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2019 to 2020 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 11:03:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/</guid><description> Welcome to 2020 folks!
In retrospect, I really should have written this post during the vacation, when it is substantially easier to wax all optimistic about the year to come.
As it stands, we&amp;rsquo;re slightly more than a week of work into the new year, and most of that vacation naiveté has been brought summarily crashing down to earth as part of a sort of planetary body check.
Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s better this way after all.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2020 folks!</p>
<p>In retrospect, I really should have written this post during the vacation, when
it is substantially easier to wax all optimistic about the year to come.</p>
<p>As it stands, we&rsquo;re slightly more than a week of work into the new year, and
most of that vacation naiveté has been brought summarily crashing down to earth
as part of a sort of planetary body check.</p>
<p>Perhaps it&rsquo;s better this way after all. Let&rsquo;s keep it real.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu6ac8123094a27124c09a4d85d8cf5b05_1834769_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu6ac8123094a27124c09a4d85d8cf5b05_1834769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu6ac8123094a27124c09a4d85d8cf5b05_1834769_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu6ac8123094a27124c09a4d85d8cf5b05_1834769_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu6ac8123094a27124c09a4d85d8cf5b05_1834769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
A sample of the view as I was walking to the main beach in Betty's Bay,
listening to a super entertaining <a
href="https://www.wnycstudios.org/podcasts/radiolab/articles/man-against-horse">radiolab
podcast about a recent 50 mile race between humans and horses</a>. (Hint: A human won!)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>During the vacation, I did manage to find all (most?) of <a href="/tags/transition/">the previous (year)
transition posts</a> all the way back to 2010 and retro-tag
them, for your and my reading pleasure, but mostly because I like to keep
things orderly around here.</p>
<p>The rest of this post is a very brief and spotty review of 2019, followed by my
far-more-grounded-than-usual (see above) hopes and dreams for 2020.</p>
<h2 id="learnings-and-events-that-i-found-important-through-the-lens-of-this-blog">Learnings and events that I found important, through the lens of this blog.</h2>
<p>I now find <a href="/tags/sleep/">sleep</a> <em>at least</em> as important as healthy eating (and
<a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">not
eating</a>)
and exercise for human wellness. I started writing about sleep in the <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 to
2018 transition post</a> after
reading about Matthew Walker for the first time in a Guardian interview.</p>
<p>In 2019 I got around to reading his book as well, and I now I&rsquo;m even more
scared of losing sleep over anything.</p>
<p>(For a giggle, contrast this with <a href="/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/#earlyish-morning-sessions">my early morning work sessions in WHV
#161</a>. On
second thought, in Summer time one could probably get this working again.)</p>
<p>Our home is <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">now solar
powered</a>. In fact,
this post is for the largest part made using power directly from the sun!</p>
<p><a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">Stone Three
Healthcare</a>,
a new med-tech company I am officially part of, was officially launched after
a great incubation period.</p>
<p>Exciting times lie ahead.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/#life-is-but-a-dream">Reality is just a different type of
dreaming</a>,
and other implications of brain-based reality simulation.</p>
<p>We are still feeling <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/#loss">the loss of a clan mother</a>.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">ABC stands for Always Be
Compounding</a>.</p>
<p>Maybe <em>that</em> will be my main theme for 2020.</p>
<h2 id="blogging-stats">Blogging Stats.</h2>
<p>In 2019 I published 35 posts on this blog, slightly down from 2019&rsquo;s 36 posts.</p>
<p>(I also published 12 more nerdy posts over on vxlabs, slightly up from 2019&rsquo;s 11 posts.)</p>
<p>The static log analyzer tool I installed in March of 2019 (awstats, if you have
to know) reports 37403 unique visitors reading just under 160000 pages between
them.</p>
<p>It could be that all of that is due to my small group of friends voraciously
re-reading everything on here, each time with a new dynamically assigned IP
address.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be (voracious) readers, thank you for reading the things
I write!</p>
<h2 id="technical-changes-to-the-site-with-implications-for-the-writing-process">Technical changes to the site, with implications for the writing process.</h2>
<p>In March of this year, I <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">ported this whole site from wordpress to the Hugo
static site generator</a>.</p>
<p>Although this has resulted in a significantly faster and more secure site, the
real benefits only dawned on me a few weeks in.</p>
<p>With Hugo, my main input modality is the humble text editor, where I write the
<a href="https://commonmark.org/help/">markdown</a>, that is semi-structured plaintext
with a few tricks, of each post before converting it to its final published
form.</p>
<p>In contrast to the WYSIWYG of Wordpress and especially of its new-fangled
Gutenberg visual editor, the latter which was probably the biggest reason for
me to make the jump, I see only text and the markdown heading structure when I
write posts, with very few other distractions.</p>
<p>This has magically resulted in me applying significantly more focus and
discipline to how I write these posts, which has further resulted in an
unexpected increase in writing satisfaction.</p>
<p>(I am carefully optimistic that it might even contribute ever so slightly to
post quality.)</p>
<p>In November of 2019, I also moved all 20 years of super valuable (to me) reader
comments <a href="/2019/11/10/we-now-have-self-hosted-isso-comments/">away from the Disqus silo and into a self-hosted open-source
commenting system called
isso</a>.</p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>In 2019, Strava says I ran 1086km, down from over 1200km in 2018.</p>
<p>I am happy with this.</p>
<p>At the start of 2019, <a href="/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/#running-inspiration">I slowed down a bit
(again)</a>
to help save my ankles.</p>
<p>That seemed to have worked, because I had no mentionable injuries for the rest
of the year, and <em>that</em> makes me happier than more distance would have.</p>
<p>For the sake of this retrospective, I do have to note that I did attain my
secret-until-unlock extra 2019 running goal, namely <a href="/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/#running">the casual 20km
jog</a> on one
not-too-hot Saturday morning in November.</p>
<p>For 2020, my main goal is simply to continue running throughout the year (see
ABC above) without injury.</p>
<p>The secret additional milestone has not yet been formulated.</p>
<p>(I still enjoy running the most on barefoot or sandals, but for the longer
runs, I am really happy to have made the <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#escalante">Altra connection in
September</a>.)</p>
<h2 id="plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">Plans and life directions for 2020.</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#other-plans-for-2019">January 6, 2019 transition WHV were definitely more
ambitious</a>
than I currently feel.</p>
<p>Traditionally, Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) starts around this time and then
continues for a month or more.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s a great tradition, so Monday, January 6, 2020 marks the date this time
around.</p>
<p>Other than EAZ and my humble running goals, it is probably relevant to mention
my recently started experimental daily list of life directions.</p>
<p>At the start of 2012, <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">I wrote the following about life
goals</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Don&rsquo;t set life goals, but rather set life directions. Instead of defining the
point that you want to go towards, define your preferred direction. If you do
it right, you&rsquo;ll pass those points as you go along in any case, except you
won&rsquo;t land in the depressing goal vacuum right after reaching the point that
you&rsquo;ve been moving towards for so long, because you&rsquo;re motoring along in a
direction, and that&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s important.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(I should have added then that life goals, especially the new year&rsquo;s resolution
variety, are also incredibly easy to fail at.)</p>
<p>Finally applying this advice concretely to my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019">note-taking / PKM
system</a>, I have recently added an
&ldquo;Experiment: Articulate your directions / systems&rdquo; heading to <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">the daily
planning template</a>.</p>
<p>In other words, every(ish) morning during day planning, I <em>attempt</em> to write
down (again&hellip;) my current life directions.</p>
<p>This is a neat trick to force me to be reminded multiple times per week of
these guidelines.</p>
<p>It also gives me the opportunity to adapt the wording, or even the list
itself. Your surroundings change continuously, and so do you.</p>
<p>The most recent version is as follows:</p>
<ol start="0">
<li>nurture your clan.</li>
<li>grow the business.</li>
<li>keep on writing, also for publication.</li>
<li>keep on programming, also for publication.</li>
<li>keep on learning, and sharpen tools.</li>
<li>optimise physiology.</li>
</ol>
<p>All of these are
<a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding"><em>compounding</em></a>.</p>
<p>None of them are concrete goals which I can quantitatively attain.</p>
<p>They are all <em>directions of movement</em>, along which any decision or action can
be measured.</p>
<p>If that action furthers one or more of the six directions above, we are good to
go.</p>
<p>If not, it&rsquo;s probably time to go to bed.</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2020">Wishes for 2020.</h2>
<p>Dear readers, <strong>thank you for being here</strong>.</p>
<p>I wish you a brilliant 2020.</p>
<p>I look forward to all of our meetings, both here on these pages, and everywhere
else where they may happen.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2018 to 2019 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 15:39:34 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</guid><description> The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house-1024x646.jpg"
        
            alt="The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to this, the most recent (as of this writing) instance of the venerable WHV year transition post tradition!</p>
<p>You can find previous editions here:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 to 2018</a> – short post, can be summarised as: “Sorry I stopped blogging for a while, I did run a bit, I’m going to blog more.”</li>
<li><a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">2016 to 2017</a> – substantial post (1800 words) with: “education will improve stupid politics; running, blogging, meditation; we made a new baby!!; kindness and gratefulness; life changes the whole time, deal with it.”</li>
<li><a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">2011 to 2012</a> – transition post disguised as WHV with: “stop doing life goals, disconnect more, list of miscellaneous life tips, because in 2011 I am not-even-40-yet Mr Wisdom”.</li>
<li><a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">2009 to 2010</a> – super short but sweet, I am clearly still new at this.</li>
</ul>
<p>Putting that list together just reminded me of an interesting observation: The more I try to take notes and document everything I see, the more I notice the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiscale_modeling">multiscalar</a> nature of my subjective experience being exposed.</p>
<p>I make detailed daily notes, all of them grouped in monthly text files.</p>
<p>At a slightly higher scale, the frequency of these WHV blog posts is somewhere between a post per week down to a post every three weeks.</p>
<p>When I write each blog post, I look back through the previous weeks, at a daily scale, and perform an extremely lossy summarisation.</p>
<p>When I write the year transitions, I perform an extremely lossy summarisation of the weekly-scale WHV posts.</p>
<p>The list above links together the various yearly transition posts, thus creating a lovely ball of multi-scalar confusion, which should not be confused with a lemur ball, shown below:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball-1024x682.jpg"
        
            alt="At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>WARNING: This post has grown into a long ramble over the past few days. I hope that you enjoy reading the ramble as much as I did thinking of you while writing it.</p>
<h2 id="focus-quantity-and-quality">Focus: Quantity and Quality.</h2>
<p>This post has been taking a while.</p>
<p>I am now back here at the start, after having been almost at the end, because I did not want you to have the idea that my 2018 did not have aspects I am not that happy with, or that I don’t use multiple negations in confusing ways often enough.</p>
<p><em>(As an aside, a friend and I have been exchanging photos of the less glamorous but entirely normal aspects of our vacations via WhatsApp: Plastic on the beach, the washing line, filthy toilets, truly terrible interior decor, and so on. What started as a joke has turned into an unintended but interesting psychological experiment in</em> <strong><em>reverse image crafting</em></strong><em>, strongly underlining the effect that this sort of communication can have.)</em></p>
<p>Back to my main story: During retrospection, I have the tendency to focus (sorry, couldn’t resist) on the good parts, because this is what I remember the best.</p>
<p>However, for the purpose of this post, I did want to spend some words on one of the (multiple!) issues that I struggled with in 2018.</p>
<p>Either I am getting worse at focusing, or I am getting better at noticing when I lose focus, or a combination of both.</p>
<p>At the very least <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">five of the posts I wrote in 2018 dealt in some way with</a> <em><a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">focus</a></em>.</p>
<p>The mentioned posts specifically and my thinking generally take the form of some analysis but mostly tools and tricks to try and improve the frequency, intensity and length of periods of focus.</p>
<p>(What you don’t read in the posts because of above-mentioned memory bias, is that there is usually a significant amount of inwardly-directed regret and disappointment involved.)</p>
<p>Even more subtle is the problem of selecting That One Most Suitable Thing to focus on. What’s going to have the most impact? What do I have capacity for at the moment? Can I trust my own subjective assessment of my current capacity, or is Lazy-Me being sneaky?</p>
<p>By the time I have made a decision, it’s probably wrong. <em>Sometimes</em> it’s a good decision, but by then the little block of time I had has flown away or has been blown to smithereens by the latest interruption, and so the quality of the decision is moot.</p>
<p>I would have expected that at this advanced age focus would come naturally and easily, and that I would know exactly what to do. However, I have had to accept that <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#slippery-slippery-focus">focus will probably remain this slippery</a> and require constant attention (haha I see what I did there) until the very end.</p>
<p>Besides eating well, sleeping well, exercising regularly and taking time to meditate (just in case!), our old friend <a href="https://cpbotha.net/?s=pomodoro">the pomodoro technique</a> is still the best tool in the box.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging.</h2>
<p>During 2018, 36 blog posts were published here, most of which were Weekly Head Voices. Those of you who have a math degree or two will not need much time to calculate that the “W” in “WHV” is at the moment mostly a little inside joke.</p>
<p>However, I did publish 14 more posts than I did in 2017, so there is hope for this year!</p>
<p>The wordpress.com statistics plugin reports just over 19000 visitors (unique IP numbers) who were responsible for just over 26000 page views for the whole year.</p>
<p>Because many people use some form of ad and/or tracking blocking these days, their visits won’t be counted, as the wordpress.com statistics relies on a tiny image which is hosted by wordpress.com, access to which is (rightfully) blocked by many blocker plugins.</p>
<p>In order to get a better idea of how many ad-blocker people read my stuff, I installed the <a href="https://wp-statistics.com/">wp-statistics</a> plugin, which locally tallies up all visits and hence is not blocked by blockers, at the start of March. For the period from March 2018 until the end of the year, it is reporting just over 74000 visitors and somewhere north of 390000 page hits.</p>
<p>Although to me this seems on the high side, I do think we can safely say that there were somewhere between 19000 and 74000 unique hosts, which to me is a very pleasant surprise.</p>
<p>However, I am by far the happiest due to all of the interactions I had with friends, mostly old and some new, on this blog. Most recently, the comments section of <a href="/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/">WHV #156</a> blew up in such a brilliant way!</p>
<p>More generally speaking, even when there are no comments, I know that throughout the year I am connecting with various subsets of my peeps through the posts on this blog. This acts as tremendous motivation to keep on writing. If even a single friend reads, it has been more than worth it.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, there is now a</em> <a href="https://t.me/headvoices"><em>telegram group, quite surprisingly called “headvoices”</em></a><em>, that you can join to receive a summary whenever a new post is published, and for general chitchat. Although so far only two of my most avant-garde friends have joined, this new form of blog-related communication excites me!)</em></p>
<h3 id="looking-forward">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>Surprisingly, I again will aim to write one WHV post per week.</p>
<p>I will probably fail again, but I believe that this is one of those cases of “aim for the stars, reach the moon”.</p>
<p>As mentioned above, writing these letters and writing them regularly is really important to me.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, I should probably have declared <strong>email bankruptcy</strong> years ago. I am</em> <strong><em>just</em></strong> <em>managing to keep head above water, but writing letters to friends like we used to do in the old days is becoming increasingly difficult. What is your feeling currently re email and how it has changed over the past few years?)</em></p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>Strava says I ran 1286km in 2018.</p>
<p>Seeing that I had set myself a private goal of 1000km for 2018 (2016 was 440km and <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 was 880km</a>), I am quite happy with this.</p>
<p>(As an aside, I spent 119 hours running, spread out over a total of 149 runs, which means 2.86 runs every week of the year.)</p>
<p>I did 770 of those 1286 kilometres in sandals, and a further 35km on barefoot.</p>
<p>More importantly, I had to learn the humbling lesson that no amount of stubborn, brute-force exercise could work around the fact I am flat footed (arch-challenged?), resulting in easily overworked posterior tibial tendons.</p>
<p>As I pushed my weekly distance up, my feet complained more loudly, until I was forced to go back to normal-person-running-shoes.</p>
<p>After a few weeks eating humble pie in running shoes, things are going much better, and I recently did my first short and careful run in sandals.</p>
<p>(Similar to the observation confirmed by <a href="https://veronikach.com/progress-reports/my-goals-for-2018-final-progress-report/">the pattern recognition heroine veronikach in her end-of-2018 post</a>, I too ran slower this year in order to run better. I did this for the largest part due to my temporarily busted ankles, but also because more experienced athletes at work recommended heart rate training. For the past few hundreds of kilometres, I have regulated my running speed to try and keep my heart rate within the 75% to 85% of maximum range, mostly ending up closer to 85% than 80%. This has increased the occurrence of those addictive perfect runs, and it has helped to keep my ankles out of trouble.)</p>
<h3 id="looking-forward-1">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>In 2019, I would be happy to <em>maintain</em> my 2018 monthly running quota, to remain injury-free, and to maximise my running zen.</p>
<p>(“Running slow” explained above can contribute substantially to the latter two goals.)</p>
<p>I do have an additional concrete (but very humble) running-related resolution for 2019, but I have decided to keep that quiet until it’s in the pocket. :)</p>
<h2 id="other-plans-for-2019">Other plans for 2019.</h2>
<h3 id="experiment-alcohol-zero">Experiment Alcohol Zero #2.</h3>
<p>Yesterday, which at the time of writing is January 4, 2019, was the first day of EAZ #2.</p>
<p>It has been two years since <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#experiment-alcohol-zero">the previous EAZ in 2016</a>. The previous experiment coincided with a significant jump in my running performance, the effects of which did not fade away after the end of the experiment.</p>
<p>This time around, the plan is to run EAZ for at least as long as in 2016, but hopefully a few days or weeks longer.</p>
<p>(I should probably call this EA&lt;0.5, as that is what my current favourite “alcohol-free” beer, Devil’s Peak Zero to Hero, claims.)</p>
<h3 id="ship-more-side-projects">Ship more side-projects.</h3>
<p>Most nerds I know have <em>side-projects</em>.</p>
<p>These are the technical artifacts, systems and machines one builds, because one can’t stop building stuff, even after work ends.</p>
<p>Like most nerds, I have a number of these that started with high momentum (new programming language, new tools, new problem, EXCITING! … 3 hours later … NOVELTY COMPLETELY WORN OFF doh.) and are now lying around gathering dust.</p>
<p>Inspired by a colleague who managed to ship <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/656740/Cosmonator/">a brilliant shooter game side-project on Steam</a> last year, I made myself the promise to ship more side-projects.</p>
<p>After that, I managed to ship two side-projects, one small and the other quite tiny.</p>
<p>This was a satisfying experience that I would like to continue in 2019.</p>
<p>(P.S. the problem with shipping side-projects, is that you now have more things that you actually have to look after. Next year I’ll think up a resolution for unmaintained shipped side-projects.)</p>
<h3 id="mindful-more">Mindful more.</h3>
<p>This is a simple one.</p>
<p>I used to spend a few minutes every second morning before work doing simple mindfulness breathing and focus exercises.</p>
<p>It was worth the modest time investment many times over, in terms of focus, and especially in terms of seeing life in perspective.</p>
<p>In the second half of 2018 I let this habit slip for some or other reason. I think it’s because I convinced myself that running time could also count as meditation time.</p>
<p>In 2019, I’m going to #bringbackthemeditation.</p>
<h3 id="learn-more">Learn more.</h3>
<p>During 2018, I started taking a more structured approach to the books I wanted to read, and the courses I wanted to follow, by tracking these in my <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">sneaky longer term goals which form part of my daily planning routine</a>.</p>
<p>More structure meant more books read to completion, and more courses followed, resulting in an Ever So Slightly Improved Me.</p>
<p>I am planning to continue and extend this practice in 2019.</p>
<h3 id="evolve-the-system">Evolve The System.</h3>
<p>The System.</p>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
<p>One step, and then another, and then another, until the lights finally go out.</p>
<h3 id="try-to-grow-a-tree">Try to grow a tree.</h3>
<p>I grew up with a fuerte avocado tree that gave us hundreds of the divine fruit every season.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 40 odd years, and my mom (HI MOM!) gave us a beautiful baby fuerte avocado tree for Christmas!







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree-805x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>We are currently trying to nurture it through its first few weeks of life in our garden.</p>
<p>With the summer sun, and the new environment, it’s a bit touch and go at the moment, but we’re really rooting for that baby tree! (bad pun quota exhausted now?!)</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This is it my friends.</p>
<p>You have made it to the end, an endeavour for which I am truly grateful.</p>
<p>I wish you a 2019 filled with growth, health and happiness.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2017 to 2018 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 11:46:06 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/</guid><description> My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis.
Does anything still work around here?
So much dust…
Is this thing on?
Testing… 123… tesssting… sound check sound check.
OH HI MARK.
(HELLO ALL MY OTHER FRIENDS WHO ARE NOT MARK!)
It’s been 4 months since the previous post (a Weekly Head Voices), due to reasons involving work (fortunately challenging and fun), genetic offspring units but especially the youngest one who is currently developing at a frightening speed, the South African climate, and my brain suddenly starting to refuse work any later than about 19:00 every day.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2827-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2827-PANO-1024x404.jpg"
        
            alt="My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Does anything still work around here?</p>
<p>So much dust…</p>
<p>Is this thing on?</p>
<p>Testing… 123… tesssting… sound check sound check.</p>
<p>OH HI MARK.</p>
<p>(HELLO ALL MY OTHER FRIENDS WHO ARE NOT MARK!)</p>
<p>It’s been 4 months since the previous post (a Weekly Head Voices), due to reasons involving work (fortunately challenging and fun), genetic offspring units but especially the youngest one who is currently developing at a frightening speed, the South African climate, and my brain suddenly starting to refuse work any later than about 19:00 every day.</p>
<p>My brain has good reasons I have to admit, having absorbed <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/sep/24/why-lack-of-sleep-health-worst-enemy-matthew-walker-why-we-sleep">this Guardian interview with Matthew Walker</a>, director of the Center for Human Sleep Science at the University of California, Berkeley. In short, the possible effects of sleeping anything less than 7 hours per night are simply terrifying. It made me, I mean my brain, really rethink its approach to grabbing-one-more-hour-from-sleep-because-this-stuff-is-really-super-interesting.</p>
<p>Anyhow, following the probably better and more beefy example set by my previous transition post, <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">2016-to-2017 that is</a>, I thought that a new edition would be the best way to get back into slightly more regular posting.</p>
<h1 id="2017-the-100-partial-and-spotty-review">2017: The 100% partial and spotty review</h1>
<p>I wrote 21 posts on this blog in 2017, 12 of which were Weekly Head Voices, which means I was about 23% (12 / 52) successful in terms of posting frequency with the WHV.</p>
<p>The most popular post over here was <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">Deep Work: A welcome kick in the butt</a>, published on January 9, which garnered just over 20 thousand views. From there my stats went all downhill. :)</p>
<p>More importantly than reader stats, each post, especially <a href="https://cpbotha.net/category/weekly-head-voices/">the Weekly Head Voices ones</a>, brought so much connection and satisfaction, which raises the question: Why am I not doing this more? (See my reasons above for not having posted for 4 months, I would have to guess.)</p>
<p>In 2017, I ran just over 800km, which, in contrast to my blogging frequency, is a nice improvement over the 440km I did in 2016. Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) of February last year contributed significantly to my average distance and speed. Those gains were maintained and slightly extended in spite of EAZ concluding in March of last year.</p>
<p>To get an idea of what I was up to work-wise in 2017, you could consider browsing <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/">the posts I wrote on my nerd-blog during 2017</a>.  This will give you a bad idea, but it’s probably better than no idea, if you really needed to know.</p>
<p>Life-wise, I might have mentioned <a href="/category/weekly-head-voices/">The Weekly Head voices posts</a> before. There aren’t that many of them for 2017, but the ones that there are, are not too bad.</p>
<h1 id="2018-again-not-much-planned-at-least-not-in-public">2018: Again not much planned, at least not in public.</h1>
<p>Following the shining example of <a href="http://www.veronikach.com/progress-reports/year-of-blogging/">Dr Cheplygina</a>, I would love to become a fully paid-up member of the <em>True</em> Weekly Bloggers Club.</p>
<p>For the past 6 months I sort of went Facebook cold turkey (because reasons, mostly to do with attention-abuse and above-mentioned time scarcity). That, in addition to my unplanned blogging hiatus, feels (yes, I have those, albeit in extremely limited quantities) like it’s caused a bit of a disconnect between me and friends around the world.</p>
<p>I have very recently returned to facebook via the mobile website, and only after extremely liberal application of the “unfollow” button to whittle my feed down to just the people I have a healthy connection with. This will help me te maintain connections with the friends who use that as platform.</p>
<p><strong>My reciprocation will have to take the form of weekly updates on this blog.</strong></p>
<p>I look forward to it, and I look forward even more to welcoming you here!








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2669.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2669-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from our cabin at Storms River Mouth Rest Camp. 12/10 will go again."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from our cabin at Storms River Mouth Rest Camp. 12/10 will go again.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>