<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>West Coast on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/west-coast/</link><description>Recent content in West Coast on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 21:44:02 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/west-coast/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #230: Follow your blisters</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</guid><description> Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&amp;rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &amp;ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&amp;rdquo; (I didn&amp;rsquo;t and I don&amp;rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="van_breda_cottage_angles.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_b81e281e98679d6a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_1e9bab3660c89449.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_cecd63736e6ae3a2.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_f936d96a4cce0835.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_1e9bab3660c89449.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV covers the three weeks from Monday July 26 to Sunday August 15.</p>
<h2 id="why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">Why I don&rsquo;t like dark mode anymore</h2>
<p>As you might know, I spent most of my working (and sometimes hobby, we&rsquo;ll get
back to that further down) hours in front of this screen or some other screen.</p>
<p>Up to now, I was really convinced that I preferred dark mode everywhere, until
recently two events transpired:</p>
<p>I started noticing more eye-strain than usual, even on my 27&quot; screen, something
which had a perceptible effect on my productivity. This I resignedly ascribed
to my advancing age, although I did find the suddenness quite surprising,
especially since I recently had my glasses updated.</p>
<p>Then, after years with only the admittedly brilliant <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">zenburn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/fniessen/emacs-leuven-theme">Leuven (dark)</a>
Emacs themes checking all of the boxes for me, I finally ran into a really
interesting and usable theme called <a href="https://github.com/kunalb/poet">Poet</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s interesting, because it uses variable pitched fonts for everything but
code, tables and elements of the fixed width domain, where most Emacs fonts
stick to the traditional all-fixed-width approach.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="20210822-poet-theme-screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_61bc38e25939896c.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_741ea773817f7739.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_19248625c7c1a3e8.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_4cb0af8349c12ee4.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_741ea773817f7739.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can probably understand that for someone who uses Emacs almost primarily
for technical notes and other writing, this book-like appearance could work
really well.</p>
<p>The theme was even more interesting for me personally, as it suddenly became
clear as day that I experienced almost no eye-strain when using Emacs with this
lighter theme than when I used any of my other usually dark-themed tools!</p>
<p>It became obvious that poet-theme&rsquo;s lighter background was much easier on my
eyes than dark mode in vscode. (No, this specific advantage can&rsquo;t be ascribed
to Emacs itself I&rsquo;m afraid.)</p>
<p>Reading pages such as <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/digital-eye-strain/is-dark-mode-better-for-eyes/">this</a> explains that dark mode leads to pupils having to
dilate more to let in more light, which there is less of with dark themes.</p>
<p>This leads to, just like with cameras and any other optics with lenses and
apertures, a shortened depth of field, and hence more difficulty focusing on
the screen!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/dark-mode/">This article by the well-known Nielsen Norman Group</a> nicely summarises research
on this topic. In short:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In people with normal vision (or corrected-to-normal vision), visual
performance tends to be better with light mode, whereas some people with
cataract and related disorders may perform better with dark mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Up until recently, I did not experience a qualitative difference in vision
between dark and light, but I sit here relieved that my eye-strain issue has
been resolved by an Emacs theme!</p>
<h2 id="know-how-to-put-down-your-work">Know how to put down your work</h2>
<p>The following take from <a href="https://twitter.com/brandsrock/status/1426163442256330753">a recent tweet by mike joubert</a> struck me
(tweet-take-strike! words are funny&hellip;):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly valuable skill isn&rsquo;t the capacity to push yourself harder, but to
stop and recuperate despite the discomfort of knowing that work remains
unfinished, emails unanswered, other people&rsquo;s demands unfulfilled.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">article, titled <em>The three-or-four-hours rule for getting creative work
done</em></a>, is itself a good read about the observation that creative types (amongst
which I count engineers) have at their best three to four hours of focus time
per day &mdash; so it is crucially important that their days are structured such
that there is an <strong>uninterrupted</strong> block of three to four hours inside of which
that lovely focus has the possibility of appearing.</p>
<p>The tweet-extract focuses on the similarly important but more subtle art of
being able to put one&rsquo;s work down, completely, when that block of time is over,
even when it feels like the work is far from complete.</p>
<p>I especially like that it also explicitly mentions the illusions created by
one&rsquo;s perception of &ldquo;other people&rsquo;s demands&rdquo;, something that ironically becomes
even harder to walk away from when one is more tired at the end of the work
day.</p>
<p>For me, becoming better at putting work down has pleasant echoes of running
slower to run faster, of emptiness in art and more broadly, <a href="https://zenhabits.net/work-less/">choosing fewer f*cks
to give</a>.</p>
<h2 id="follow-your-blisters">Follow your blisters</h2>
<p>On the topic of choosing your ducks&hellip;</p>
<p>I initially did not like <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/what-you-should-follow-instead-of-your-passion">this HBR</a> post when it first crossed my stream, because
it smacks a bit too much of the current social media style of &ldquo;wisdom&rdquo;, namely
&ldquo;everything you need to know in 280 characters&rdquo;, or &ldquo;this 1 minute tiktok video
will change your life&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the title is pretty clickbaity: <em>What You Should
Follow Instead of Your Passion</em>.</p>
<p>However, the core message of the post, which I could not help reading, did
stick with me, and after a few days I realised that I would have to go find the
article again in order to talk about it here.</p>
<p>The core message is to replace <em>find your passion</em> with <strong><em>Find your blisters.</em></strong></p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s point is that folks often get the wrong idea with <em>passion</em> as
something that is simply always delightful, whilst the thing you should
actually be looking for, is that activity that you simply are unable to stop
doing, even when you try, and especially even when you don&rsquo;t directly derive
pleasure from it, for example because you feel that you&rsquo;re not that good at it.</p>
<p>They give the personal example of writing.</p>
<p>Although they&rsquo;ve been at it for years, it&rsquo;s still a difficult and laborious
process, and they are often not happy with the results.</p>
<p>However, they have been unable to stop from returning to writing projects again
and again over the years.</p>
<p>Ironically, even although they find that they are still bad at it, they have in
fact become really good, simply because they have been pushing through and
practising more than almost anyone else over the years.</p>
<p>I really like this down-to-earth view.</p>
<p>One can indeed source almost unlimited amounts of energy from one&rsquo;s &ldquo;blisters&rdquo;,
but true benefits will for a large part be brought about by a <a href="/tags/practice/">lifetime of often
challenging practice</a>.</p>










<figure><a href="flowers_everywhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_77f0491ce2bb652a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_c88a425b4a6e1547.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_26051671c6ea88b0.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_c1d1549ff9af473f.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_c88a425b4a6e1547.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #185: Starship GOU #1.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 22:35:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</guid><description>Welcome back friends!
It&amp;rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.
Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file two weeks ago, but then I didn&amp;rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).
In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more
precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.</p>
<p>Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file
two weeks ago, but then I didn&rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then
everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).</p>
<p>In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time
right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look
back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_hu_2b5d558db2c4f36b.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_hu_eccba70dba2f273.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_hu_9d2deb6913c1f7c5.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_hu_58c70f4a7a287b8.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_hu_eccba70dba2f273.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view from a Friday afternoon arrival run along the Langebaan Lagoon in the West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="lecturing-old-school">Lecturing, old school.</h2>
<p>On Thursday, November 21, I gave a two hour lecture titled &ldquo;IoMT in Healthcare
Innovation&rdquo; at the <a href="https://www.usb.ac.za/">University of Stellenbosch Business
School</a>.</p>
<p>IoMT expands to the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/bernardmarr/2018/01/25/why-the-internet-of-medical-things-iomt-will-start-to-transform-healthcare-in-2018/#46f18c694a3c">&ldquo;Internet of Medical
Things&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>My knowledge of IoT is spotty, and before giving this lecture I didn&rsquo;t even
know that the term &ldquo;IoMT&rdquo; existed.</p>
<p>Fortunately, it turns out that a lot of what we&rsquo;re currently doing at Stone
Three Healthcare (connecting patients with specialist care through
diagnostic-grade streaming of auscultation (and soon other modalities) device
data) can in fact be classified as IoMT.</p>
<p>Phew.</p>
<p>I would like to make the following observations based on this experience:</p>
<ol>
<li>I still really love getting up in front of a group of people to present
something. There are so many things that could go wrong, but when they go
right, the experience is great.</li>
<li>A two hour lecture is quite long, for both the students, even when they&rsquo;re
as advanced as this, <em>and</em> for the lecturer, especially when he is as out of
practice as this.
<ul>
<li>If there&rsquo;s a next time, I will either insert my own 15 minute break, or I
will get the class to break out into some sort of topic-strengthening
activity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I had somehow forgotten how much time lecture preparation could take up,
even when you just had to present your own day-to-day reality.
<ul>
<li>BIG UP TO THE LECTURERS IN THE WHV AUDIENCE!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="productivity-system-tuneup">Productivity system tuneup.</h2>
<p>Last Sunday morning, as the family took a last swim at Kraalbaai before we had
to return home, I tried to apply some serious thinking (well, I did this by
stringing together a series of normal thinking moments) to the problem of
increasing my efficiency and focus at work.</p>
<p>At that moment, the scenery outside looked like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hu_3a7a1c7804b0f98a.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hu_e0822a7dcd61b85c.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hu_c5f7184e7274d5e2.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hu_bd599ba3f52a8f93.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hu_e0822a7dcd61b85c.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view of the Preekstoel from Kraalbaai beach, West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Regular readers will know that coming up with new ways to increase and maintain
focus is a life-long endeavour, which my subconscious self enjoys inventing
interesting new ways to subvert.</p>
<p>Conscious me has made peace with the fact that it has no choice but to keep on
working at its end of the bargain, until the very end.</p>
<p>With the opposing forces involved, my focus seems to oscillate with varying
frequencies between terrible and not too bad.</p>
<p>Anyways, having had a few days of fresh air and majestic scenery to jog the
neural circuitry, I applied myself, again, to the problem at hand.</p>
<p>I thought that sketching could help, so I was scribbling using a rather
impressive electronic pencil-analogue on a glass screen.</p>
<p>After several focused minutes (SEVERAL MINUTES, I TELL YOU!), I had a mindmap
with &ldquo;increase efficiency&rdquo; in a little oval at the center, arrows pointing
outwards into three terribly familiar habits, each in a rectangle <em>this</em> time,
and finally more connecting lines to lists of pretty plausible sounding reasons
for the three well-known habits.</p>
<p>The three rectangles were:</p>
<ol>
<li>Morning planning.</li>
<li>Inbox 0.</li>
<li>Pomodoro always.</li>
</ol>
<p>Over the years, these three items have made pretty regular appearances, in
various different forms, on this blog.</p>
<p>(I laughed when I just looked up <a href="/2010/09/20/an-indecent-proposal-weekly-head-voices-31/">this old 2010
post</a> and found a
pretty effective focus technique in the comments.)</p>
<p>Anyways, although the little thinking and drawing session documented here
seemingly did not result in any new revelations, the act of going through the
whole thought process, and documenting the results (again), seemed to have
contributed to a pretty great week in terms of focus.</p>
<p>I wrote down a little mantra for myself (definitely not fit for publication),
weaving together the three points above and the reasoning behind them, almost
like the affirmation in Wreckit Ralph&rsquo;s bad guy support group:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m bad, and that&rsquo;s good. I will never be good, and that&rsquo;s not bad. There&rsquo;s
no one I&rsquo;d rather be than me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have <em>chosen</em>
to take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having <em>decided</em>
to <em>commit</em>, i.e. active.</p>
<p>My humble focus mantra is following in this tradition.</p>
<p>(I really hope that my subversive sub-conscious is not paying attention right
now&hellip;)</p>
<h2 id="starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">Starship GOU #1, taxiing on the runway.</h2>
<p>Wednesday, December 4, was officially <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU
#1&rsquo;s</a> last day of primary school.</p>
<p>Although she seemed to navigate this emotional event with her customary
even-keeled demeanour, some of the moments were really just too big to let go by
without a good cry or two.</p>
<p>I was also happy to observe the level of retrospection and sunny candour she
applied to her informal post hoc analyses of above-mentioned crying moments.</p>
<p>I really hope that she strengthens and maintains this important human ability.</p>
<p>From our perspective as parents, it feels like the stakes are being raised
quite significantly.</p>
<p>The thing is, our oldest is now quite obviously becoming an adult.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like that scene at the end of the brilliant 2015 movie <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2096673/">Inside
Out</a>, where the protagonist&rsquo;s brain
console is suddenly upgraded to one with at least 9000 new knobs and dials.</p>
<p>Up to now, we (the parents) were GOU #1&rsquo;s only control system.</p>
<p>Now it is becoming quite clear that she is increasingly forming her own
opinions, and making her own decisions.</p>
<p>In most cases, the physical constraints of a 13 year old living in her parent&rsquo;s
house still afford us some level of control.</p>
<p>However, relying on that would be missing the point entirely.</p>
<p>You see, we find ourselves in the moment of truth, when the past 13 years of
mostly gentle programming has to start executing all by itself.</p>
<p>Our little GOU #1, our first co-created human intelligence, is preparing to go
out into the world.</p>
<p>She has not taken off yet, so we do our best to apply the final touches to her
already promising software.</p>
<p>We exhort her regularly: <em>Be useful. Use your (rational) brain. Be kind. Find
the kindness in others.</em></p>
<p>In the darkness, when we are at our weakest, stripped down to our core, we do
what all parents do:</p>
<p>We worry, and we hope with a passion, the intensity of which it is difficult to
describe, that our offspring units do manage to <a href="/2012/03/04/rhythm-of-the-night-weekly-head-voices-66/#life-philosophy-that-works">generate their own motivation,
to manufacture meaning, and to create
love</a>.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu_544a14b8bf3123b3.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu_22f84d9f00678acb.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu_74c3b741c254cf38.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu_cde918a2f22a10a3.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu_22f84d9f00678acb.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
This could be a runway, but it is the entrance to Vergelegen Wine Estate. At
this point, I was in fact running on this way.
</figcaption>
</figure>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #80: There can be only one.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/08/07/weekly-head-voices-80-there-can-be-only-one/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2014 19:42:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/08/07/weekly-head-voices-80-there-can-be-only-one/</guid><description>Week 31 of 2014, which was otherwise pretty uneventful except for bunches of hard work, ended with a trip up to the West Coast to go see the flowers.
YES PEOPLE SPRING IS JUST AROUND THE CORNER!
I made you a photo of this ominous looking Portal To Soooooomething: These look like the gates to some far-off fantasy plane. Instead, it’s the Geelbek Restaurant in the West Coast National Park, which does serve mysteriously delicious chocolate cake.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Week 31 of 2014, which was otherwise pretty uneventful except for bunches of hard work, ended with a trip up to the West Coast to go see the flowers.</p>
<p>YES PEOPLE SPRING IS JUST AROUND THE CORNER!</p>
<p>I made you a photo of this ominous looking Portal To <em>Soooooomething</em>: <figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/wpid-gates_to_somewhere_geelbek_restaurant.jpg" title=""><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/wpid-gates_to_somewhere_geelbek_restaurant-300x225.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">These look like the gates to some far-off fantasy plane. Instead, it’s the Geelbek Restaurant in the West Coast National Park, which does serve mysteriously delicious chocolate cake.</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>Just so you don’t think it was overcast and non-Springy everywhere, I can assure you that those funny clouds were <em>only</em> over the respawning portal. Everywhere else it looked like this 360 degree photosphere I made for you (hey, we live in the future, I can show you 360 degree pannable photos; go on, pan and zoom with your mouse, or just wave your hands if you have your VR helmet on):</p>
<iframe frameborder="0" height="315" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" scrolling="no" src="https://maps.google.com/maps?layer=c&amp;panoid=MtsQV45TJD8AAAQfCSmvhA&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;source=embed&amp;output=svembed&amp;cbp=13%2C16.972399999999993%2C%2C0%2C0" width="560"></iframe>
<div>
<small><a href="https://www.google.com/maps/views/" style="color:#0000FF; text-align:left">Views</a>: <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/views/view/102438662851504788261/gphoto/6044908835702411618" style="color:#0000FF; text-align:left">Grootvlei Guest Farm – On The Dunes</a> by <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/views/profile/102438662851504788261" style="color:#0000FF; text-align:left">Charl Botha</a></small>
</div>
<p>(I made the photosphere at the <a href="http://www.grootvleiguestfarm.co.za/gallery_on_the_dunes.htm">Grootvlei Guest Farm – On the Dunes House</a>.)</p>
<p>Because clever people told me so, or more probably because I misunderstood them, I thought that I needed to do my Big Thinking Tasks (BTIs, for example trying to get the architecture of a new system down) in the morning. However, by the time afternoon came around, I would be too tired to take care of the MITs (Most Irritating Tasks, usually admin), and hence would postpone them till the day after, when they would just get postponed again, ad infinitum.</p>
<p>I recently started taking care of a few MITs first thing in the morning. This way, I actually get them done, and the BTIs still (mostly) fit.</p>
<p>Just to clarify things, <a href="http://zenhabits.net/purpose-your-day-most-important-task/">MITs are also used by zenhabits</a>, except there they call them Most Important Tasks. Whoops. For the sake of exposition, and to make everything more muddy, let’s call them zMITs, and my MITs iMITs (“i” is for irritating, as in iPhone, iPad, and so forth). In any case, zMITs are also to be done first thing in the morning, and at least one of the zMITs should advance your goals, let’s call it the zOMG.</p>
<p>Putting all of this together, I should probably start off my day by taking care of my zOMG, then a few iMITs, some zMITs and then finally the BTIs. YEAH!</p>
<p>I’m going through a little reading revival. After finishing Remote last week, I’m time-slicing between the following books at the moment:</p>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
<i>PostgreSQL: Up and Running</i> – I shouldn’t be telling you this, but there is just so much wow in Postgres. I’m currently using the text analysis functionality, and noticing that my SQL needs some advancing, hence the book.
  </li>
<li>
<i>A Tour of C++ by Bjarne Stroustroup</i> – Everybody’s talking about C++11 and C++14. I was curious about the newer features, and Dr Stroustroup seems to know his way around the language. (In my hobby projects, C++ and Lua are playing an increasingly important role.)
  </li>
<li>
<i>Programming in Scala</i> – I don’t have serious plans with this at the moment, but felt I needed to be sufficiently informed to have vigorous arguments about its utility.
  </li>
<li>
<i>Thinking, Fast and Slow by Daniel Kahneman</i> – fascinating book about how the human brain functions in two parts: fast, efficient and intuitive, vs. slow, energy-heavy and rational.
  </li>
<li>
<i>The Psychology of Influence by Robert Cialdini</i> – another fascinating book about how exactly humans influence each other.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>I’m all out of fiction at the moment. If you have recommendations of so-called Hard SF and/or Space Opera, I’m all ears!</p>
<p>Talking about Science Fiction, I ran into this marvellous clip showcasing the awesome products of <a href="https://www.clinicalgraphics.com/">Clinical Graphics</a>:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HvjkDiJ92BE?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Damnit I’m so proud of Dr Krekel and his team!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>