<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Backyard Philosophy on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/backyard-philosophy/</link><description>Recent content in Backyard Philosophy on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 21:27:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/backyard-philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #259: Backbone</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</guid><description> Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!
(I just learned that the English connoisseur comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved connaisseur (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little oi.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







    


<figure><a href="bettys_sunset.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_84d7d5fb2023d1f3.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_94ef9e4fb9dd976e.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_b061658b14bcf3ec.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!</p>
<p>(I <em>just</em> learned that the English <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/connoisseur"><em>connoisseur</em> comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling</a>. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved <em>connaisseur</em> (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little <em>oi</em>.)</p>
<h2 id="how-do-you-do-fellow-humans">How do you do, fellow humans?</h2>
<p>This Sunday morning I browsed through all of my Obsidian daily entries, starting from Monday January 20, the day after <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/">The 2024 to 2025 transition post</a> appeared, because the urge to write here has become quite persistent of late, an urge that is clearly quite oblivious to my feeling that it has become increasingly more tricky to make the time to sit down and focus on just this one thing.</p>
<p>I, very briefly I should add, considered feeding all of those daily posts to one of our artificial friends to extract highlights, but for the time-being, I really like that every word you read here was produced by my laborious and messy (fluids-based, for the most part) biology-based process.</p>
<p>This means that I read every single stupid word I wrote in those daily entries, re-experienced various emotions, some of them transformed by the ever-changing self, while I read them, and let those ideas all simmer for a while in the wetware mostly enclosed by my skull, before sitting down here and producing a new set of emotions whilst typing out a bunch of new words on this (mechanical) keyword.</p>
<p>Blood, sweat and tears my friends, blood sweat and tears.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Since my last entry here, I&rsquo;ve been reading a lot more, something that I&rsquo;m really happy about.</p>
<p>Besides the deep-seated and strong instinct that reading good books makes me a better human, it also turns out to be an <em>excellent</em> doom-scrolling suppressant, by virtue of simply pushing that activity out of one&rsquo;s daily schedule.</p>
<p>Apart from that motivation, what has made a huge difference in my reading volume was adding audiobooks as well as Zotero on my laptop to the reading modality mix.</p>
<p>Where I previously would only read on my Kindle e-reader, I&rsquo;ve discovered that picking the right medium for the right book means I can comfortably use these three channels during different phases of the day.</p>
<p>In the evening right before closing my eyes, I usually read fiction on the Kindle. After 10 to 20 minutes of reading, my eyes start closing of their own accord and my brain shuts down. Current Kindle book: <a href="https://www.gregegan.net/MORPHOTROPHIC/MORPHOTROPHIC.html">Morphotrophic by Greg Egan</a>. <a href="/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/#permutation-city">Egan has previously appeared on this blog</a> for a much older creation which I really loved.</p>
<p>During the day in the car on short commutes, I prefer to read non-fiction books like <a href="https://www.ynharari.com/book/nexus/">Nexus by Yuval Harari</a> (which I loved by the way). With Nexus at 1.5x speed, which is still very comfortable, it was around 17 hours of listening time which went by a lot faster than I expected. I&rsquo;m currently on [<em>Behave: The Biology of Humans at Our Best and Worst</em> by Robert M. Sapolsky] which is super entertaining and extremely successful at repeatedly blowing my mind.</p>
<p>Some non-fiction books deserve even closer attention, like <a href="https://www.abriefhistoryofintelligence.com/">Max Bennett&rsquo;s <em>A Brief History of Intelligence</em></a>, which I started reading on my Kindle but then completed on my laptop, using the fantastic epub reader in Zotero. With this tool I can make highlights and notes to my heart&rsquo;s content.</p>








    


<figure><a href="screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_fd5d3cc24c0400cb.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_ded6f76846ff592d.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_a10ae5587078729c.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>On the topic of Zotero, the two features that would make it even more perfect for me are <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/pull/836">the iOS epub support</a>, so I can open annotated epubs on the go, and <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/issues/597">iOS webpage snapshot support</a>, so that I can save <a href="https://github.com/gildas-lormeau/SingleFile">SingleFile</a> snapshots of web pages from my phone like on desktop, and not just the link.</p>
<h3 id="thanks-for-nothing-amazon">Thanks for nothing Amazon</h3>
<p>On that topic, <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/02/psa-amazon-kills-download-transfer-via-usb-option-for-kindles-this-week/">on February 26 Amazon killed the Kindle &ldquo;download &amp; transfer via USB&rdquo; feature</a>, the exact feature that I&rsquo;ve always used to make copies of Kindle titles for my own use, most often for highlighting and further study, sometimes leading to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/book/">book notes posts</a>.</p>
<p>Although I really appreciated the convenience of e.g. hearing about a book, and then being able to purchase and start reading that book within minutes, this user-hostile move by Amazon is the last straw for me.  All the way back in 2016, <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2016/08/21/amazon-owns-your-ebooks/">friend Stéfan warned us all about the Kindle Swindle</a>, i.e. the way that Amazon restricts ebook rights far more than necessary, and is in essence able to &ldquo;switch off&rdquo; all ebooks that you have bought.</p>
<p>For me personally, this latest move just means that I will drastically reduce my spending on Kindle books, and anything else from Amazon, as far as possible.</p>
<h2 id="101-productivity-hacks-for-stubborn-people">101 productivity hacks for stubborn people</h2>
<p>Also known as The Productivity Section!</p>
<h3 id="a-bientôt-monsieur-org">A bientôt monsieur Org</h3>
<p>In the 24/25 year transition post I talked about <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#emacs-and-obsidian">my apparently eternally brewing personal tension between Emacs and Obsidian</a>.</p>
<p>It looks like I might have found myself in the third <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_stages_of_grief">stage of grief</a>, namely <em>bargaining</em>, when I wrote that I would explore the interplay between the two poles of Emacs and Obsidian.</p>
<p>Well, as I write this, it feels like I might have reached the fifth and final stage, namely <em>acceptance</em>, acceptance of the fact that orgmode (note, not Emacs, but orgmode), although far more powerful and flexible, is probably always going to be the silo that it currently is, in contrast to markdown (note, not necessarily Obsidian) which, while functionality-wise is but a shadow of orgmode, is hugely more accessible and inter-operates with everyone and their dogs.</p>
<p>You see, since writing that transition post, I&rsquo;ve been creating more and more markdown notes, to the extent that I keep on running into the inconvenience of orgmode nexus nodes which I can in theory link to from markdown, but with links that are not as fully featured as markdown to markdown links.</p>
<p>It really does seem like &ldquo;interplay&rdquo; is turning into &ldquo;dominance&rdquo;, if you&rsquo;ll excuse my multiple layers of innuendo here.</p>
<p>And so after a really good 10 year run as orgmode-disciple, as chronicled by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">10+ years of vxlabs posts on the topic</a>, a bunch of <a href="/tags/orgmode/">appearances on this blog</a> and even <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">the orgmode-exocortex</a>, it&rsquo;s time to read the writing on the wall, writing that upon closer inspection has turned out to be in markdown format after all.</p>
<h3 id="productivity-hack-of-the-year">Productivity hack of the year</h3>
<p>In a textbook case of <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2024/06/07/report-death/">greatly exaggerated rumours of someone&rsquo;s demise</a>, my orgmode isn&rsquo;t completely dead yet&hellip;</p>
<p>By far the most effective productivity hack I&rsquo;ve implemented in many months, in terms of actual focus hours gained, has been the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar">orgmode-based pomodoro timer I hacked together and wrote about in my other OTHER website TIL section</a>.</p>
<p>While it was already helpful to have a boring text-based pomodoro-timer display a countdown on my macOS menubar, I had wildly underestimated how much impact the addition of <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar#double-bonus-macos-do-not-disturb-during-pomodoro">the automatic do-not-disturb mode</a> would have.</p>
<p>When I start the 25 minute pomodoro focus timer, my script automatically activates the so-called do-not-disturb &ldquo;focus&rdquo; across all of my (Apple) devices. For those 25 minutes, absolutely nothing pings or alerts, and only calls by my my inner-inner circle can get through. When the 25 minutes are up, DnD is disabled across all devices, and I can see to any emergencies that might have occurred.</p>
<p>(🍅 These particular paragraphs are being typed within such an interruption-proof pomodoro BTW.)</p>
<h2 id="how-are-the-children">How are the children?</h2>
<p>Why thank you for asking!</p>
<p>Here I would like to mention that Genetic Offspring Unit #1 (GOU#1) has now experienced the first few weeks of industrial engineering at university (which is the same as the first few weeks of most of the engineering disciplines) and seems to be loving it to bits.</p>
<p>It brings me great joy that, in spite of the fact that she is a wonderfully well-adjusted and socially graceful human, her engineering DNA is shining through brilliantly. This way of thinking suits her, she just seems to get it, and she&rsquo;s really <em>enjoying the work</em>.</p>
<p>P.S. It also brings me joy, but also a tiny bit of concern, that she really enjoys and also sometimes makes dad jokes <em>AT ME</em>.</p>
<h2 id="spiritual-hygiene-backbone">Spiritual hygiene backbone</h2>
<p>All of that reading I wrote about a few paragraphs back somehow happens even when my days seem to fall apart due to general life chaos, various distractions many of my own (unintentional design) and/or due to will power failure on my part.</p>
<p>So on those days, when I finally fall asleep reading, I console myself with the affirmation that the day was not <em>complete</em> chaos, at least I&rsquo;ve done some reading&hellip;</p>
<p>The same goes for my running.</p>
<p>A seemingly low-level function somewhere in my system <em>needs</em> to take me out running an average of three times a week.</p>
<p>Even when I don&rsquo;t want to, I often find myself standing outside in my shoes and ready to go.</p>
<p>It does help that I&rsquo;ve programmed myself with the mantra &ldquo;If you&rsquo;re wondering whether you should go run the answer is YES&rdquo;.</p>
<p>During my many low-power moments, that mantra often nudges me over the edge.</p>
<p>My daily writing habit also seems to be getting stronger.</p>
<p>I might be tired, or distracted, but <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#multiplicity-of-you">one of the voices</a> often gets me to write with mind-tricks like &ldquo;oh just a bullet or two man, surely you can manage that?&rdquo; to which my simple mind succumbs, and before I know it, I&rsquo;ve written a few more bullets, and maybe even a paragraph or two.</p>
<p>Unbeknownst to simple mind (shhhht), retro- and introspection have now been performed, and prepared for future review.</p>
<p>I have now come to realise that these three habits, namely reading, running and writing, and their various positive feedback loops, together form a pretty decent <em>spiritual hygiene backbone</em>.</p>
<p>Especially when the rest feels like it wants to flop around or even fall apart, this backbone is a robust, reliable and, quite importantly, <em>simple</em> construct that defines my desired internal structure, enabling me to maintain focus and humanity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2024 to 2025 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to the year 2025!
We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this traditional yearly transition blog post here to keep you busy in the meantime.
The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2025!</p>
<p>We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this <a href="/tags/transition">traditional yearly transition blog post</a> here to keep you busy in the meantime.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20241228-st-francis-light-house.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a7c8fad0a4fb3336.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_c471bba5b301f4e3.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_7e36ecc6dd88d868.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp"
            

        
            alt="The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For those of you who are new here, 1) welcome! and 2) the traditional yearly transition post is where I both ramble semi-coherently on about the year that is closest to its conclusion and also speculate a bit about the year that is closest to its inception.</p>
<p>The main audience for this post is me &ndash; writing this up and the concomitant thinking and formulating bits form an important part of my maintenance process &ndash; but to anyone else who is reading this, there is hopefully something of value (or just a bit of entertainment) for you in these words. In any case, I am super happy that you&rsquo;re here!</p>
<h2 id="life-events">Life events</h2>
<p>In 2024, <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#i-turned-50">I turned 50</a> while <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#gou-1-turned-18">GOU#1 turned 18</a>, finished high school and is now on her way to university.</p>
<p>I mention these two in the same breath, because looking back it feels like the 5 years of her high school, a substantial chunk of time in terms of her development, went by in a flash.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s almost like we blinked <a href="/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">when she was still our little girl going to high school</a> and now suddenly she is an adult, and we finally feel like actual adults (aka old people) ourselves.</p>
<p>Although these have been amazing years for us, this experience of a whole period of life flashing by, through the lense of our children&rsquo;s development into adults, is a stark reminder to strive even harder to experience the living daylights out of every single moment that we are blessed with.</p>
<p>If all goes according to plan, we will have two more blink-blink-another-high-school-journey-is-complete experiences (GOU#2 is now in her second year of that journey, GOU#3 has a few years to go before she can start) so we should probably try to blink far less often.</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>After the dip both this blog and I went through in 2023 (total of 3 WHV posts&hellip;) and a very slow blogging start in 2024, it does feel like I might slowly be getting my WHV groove back, which seems to be evidenced by 66% more WHV posting in 2024, i.e. a whole 5 WHV posts! (Contrast this with the historic average of one post every two weeks.)</p>
<p>In the introduction to <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/">WHV #255 You lift me up</a> I speculate a bit about the reasons for my hiatus (I didn&rsquo;t mention there that maybe 2023 was actually just a real downer for me) and the current potential revival.</p>
<p>In addition to the posts here, I published <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">12 technical posts over on at the vxlabs</a> and a whole bunch of short howtos / recipes in the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">brand new TiL section of my other-OTHER website</a>. WHV #255 <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">explains the motivation behind the TiL section</a>.</p>
<p>I am also quite happy about the fact that I wrote a daily entry in my private diary for a large part of 2024, and this is something that I would like to continue, hopefully for an even larger part of 2025.</p>
<p>Spending some time every day to review that day, where the review is enriched by the deliberate activitity of trying to formulate everything into a story that I can write down, helps me to make sense of everything.</p>
<p>Writing in general seems to modulate positively my experience of reality.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a lot about this idea in various posts on this blog, but allow me to surface <a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#the-describers">two relevant sections from WHV 180</a>, and especially the quote below (but you should go read those two sections):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less faulty entity.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>My secret running goal for 2024 was to do 25km of running every week. In my head this was auto-simplified to 1200km for the year (you know, the way one often calculates a month as 4 weeks), but of course we&rsquo;re talking 1300km.</p>
<p>Well, I failed at all of these goals!</p>
<p>However, I did manage to run a total of 1149.7km over the year, which comes to an average of 22.1km per week, which I am pretty OK with. I had over 100 hours of fun (I truly enjoy running) and no injuries that I can remember.</p>
<p>The training calendar below shows that August was my laziest month, but that&rsquo;s because August has the worst weather, and because I was away for a week visiting my Dutch family and getting many tens of thousands of dancing steps instead. The calendar also shows how I made a last ditch effort in December to close the gap with my goal as much as possible.</p>










<figure><a href="20250101-strava-training-calendar.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_e13adc1c4101c63a.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_2caa5fcc1a219359.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_57229ed99a10234e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You might remember <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">my three metrics-focused goals from last year&rsquo;s post</a>, namely 50 consecutive push-ups, VO<sub>2</sub> Max of at least 50 and a resting state heart rate of 50 or under&hellip;</p>
<p>Well, 50 consecutive push-ups was not that hard, Apple Health reports my average resting state heart rate for 2024 as 48 BPM (this would be mostly via my Garmin Forerunner 245 and more recently 265) but my VO<sub>2</sub> briefly peaked at 49 (some time after I turned 50) before settling back on 48. I  would have loved that 50, but <a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/blog/fitness/whats-a-good-vo2-max-for-me/">48 is not the worst for a man of my age</a>.</p>
<p>My real goal for the coming year is the same as last year: I want to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>The older I get and the more I learn, the more I understand that with exercise, the more hours I can spend every week doing it, of course maintaining balance with the rest of my life (see life systems further down), the better my meat-coated skeleton will work, and the happier the ghost driving it will be.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’re a ghost driving a meat-coated skeleton made from stardust; what do you have to be scared of?</p>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2022/10/13/ghost-stardust/">@rat_sandwich on twitter, January 31, 2013</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>P.S. of course I will again go for 25km of running per week. I think logging substantially more than 120 hours of activities in Strava will be good. I might even give that VO<sub>2</sub> Max goal another shot.</p>
<p>P.P.S. I read <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/outlive/">Peter Attia&rsquo;s book Outlive</a> a few months ago. This is a detailed and practical manual for healthy living. There&rsquo;s a lot in there, but at the core he wants you, while you still have any say in the matter, to become as fit (measured by our friend VO<sub>2</sub> Max) and as strong (measured by grip strength) as you possibly can. You see, from middle age we&rsquo;re all on a downward curve, and there&rsquo;s not much we can do about it, except ensuring that we start as high as possible.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. It&rsquo;s funny; back in school, I thought little of athleticism, because it was a jock thing, and the jocks were generally not very kind to nerd-kind (my people). Now that I&rsquo;m older and quite ironically due to my nerdy lifelong learning habits, I strive for us much athleticism as I can &ldquo;fit&rdquo; in (jock joke harr harr).</p>
<h3 id="diet">Diet</h3>
<p>During this post&rsquo;s generously long incubation, I thought it worth adding here my approach to eating.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been practising 16-8 time-restricted eating (intermittent fasting in some circles) about 95% of the time since somewhere in 2019. I first <a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">wrote about it in WHV 186</a>, and then in <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#i-really-don-t-like-breakfast">WHV 221 I came out and stated the beef I have with breakfast</a> (that pun might be too heavy for this post).</p>
<p>Anyways, while I still believe that breakfast is bad for most people, I know that the scientific world has not yet reached consensus on time-restricted eating for healthy folks.</p>
<p>However, there is considerably more consensus that lowering daily caloric intake is good for most people.</p>
<p>For me, 16-8 TRE, where I simply don&rsquo;t ingest anything besides water and black coffee from about 7 in the evening until about noon the next day, is an extremely practical and especially low-effort way to reduce caloric intake.</p>
<p>When I do eat, the portions are modest, I try to stick to natural and unprocessed where I can and I keep an eye on protein.</p>
<p>When I do break these rules, I do so with deliberation. Great food, great wine, great beer and the company of friends and family, especially when combined, constitute a perfect reason to break all of these rules.</p>
<p>In short, reduce caloric intake, increase per-calorie value and/or enjoyment!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and Tools</h2>
<p>This is the place where I summarise (read: ramble on about) the current state of my digital tools and systems. If you&rsquo;re going to skip a (nerdy) section, this is the one! You can dive back in at <a href="#life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</a>.</p>
<p>I am one of those people who <em>regularly</em> finds and uses information from notes that I made.</p>
<p>If I have the note, and I often do because I make an effort to write stuff down with the lowest possible friction but the highest possible chance of being found again, this is generally miles faster than finding the information online, even with tools like the <a href="https://kagi.com/">premium search engine Kagi</a> which I have been using regularly for a few weeks now.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-and-obsidian">Emacs and Obsidian</h3>
<p>A year ago I <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#systems-and-tools">experienced a bit of a crisis of (Emacs) faith</a>.</p>
<p>Whilst that was more of a clash between the either-or poles of Emacs and Obsidian, I am now at a place where I&rsquo;m finding increasing uses for Obisidian as an <em>additional</em> note-taking tool, working on the same collection of hundreds of org-mode and a growing number of markdown files.</p>
<p>Emacs and org-roam treat <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">markdown files as if they are native org-roam nodes</a>. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/BBazard/obsidian-orgmode-cm6">Benoit Bazard&rsquo;s fantastic new CodeMirror 6 org-mode plugin for Obsidian</a> and my <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Monitor-rclone-cron-job-with-Home-Assistant">rclone + syncthing syncing setup for iPhone</a>, I have semi-usable org database support on my phone.</p>
<p><a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> and since recently <a href="https://orgro.org/">Orgro</a> are great for editing org files in the iPhone, but they are missing the searching and discovery, let&rsquo;s call it <em>note management</em>, aspects of a tool like Obsidian.</p>
<p>Long but quite important-to-me story short, it looks like for the time being I&rsquo;ll continue to use both Emacs and Obsidian for note-taking. Because interoperability is not perfect, there will be some natural gravitational pull towards the one or the other which I have decided to explore.</p>
<p>At the moment, it looks like I might be writing more of my atomic notes as markdown files, whilst using org for the lab journal / logbook and project management type of notes.</p>
<p>On a deeper note, the Obsidian team is doing fantastic work.</p>
<p>Apart from their <a href="https://stephango.com/file-over-app"><em>file over app</em> philosophy</a>, Obsidian is <em>programmable</em> as can be witnessed by the thriving extension ecosystem.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?id=ai-chat-as-md">written a modest extension</a> to test this out from the inside. The programmability is not as extensive as that of Emacs, but it runs everywhere, even on mobile devices, and it might be extensive enough for the note-taking platform that Obsidian has become.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Emacs on and off since the late 90s, but for the past 10 years it has become an always-running and integral part of my life. It feels really strange, disconcerting if I&rsquo;m being honest, that it seems to be losing its core spot.</p>
<p>I console myself in these moments with the observation that science must trump dogma, always.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m writing this post in Emacs.</p>
<h4 id="til">TiL</h4>
<p>Thanks to Obsidian, my other, OTHER website <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">now has a &ldquo;today I learned&rdquo; (TIL) section</a> at <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">charlbotha.com/til</a>, published directly from a sub-directory of my main notes directory.</p>
<p>The benefit is that there is even less friction than usual and, perhaps more importantly, the psychological friction has also been reduced because I have convinced myself that the posts there are just notes and not true blog posts.</p>
<h3 id="honorable-tool-mentions-zotero-and-quarto">Honorable tool mentions: Zotero and Quarto</h3>
<p>After <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#omnivore-is-no-more">my distastrous recommendation of Omnivore turned into a disaster</a>, it is with some emotional trepidation but intellectual confidence (thanks to file over app and its staunchly open source nature) that I can re-recommend Zotero as a reference (of all kinds!) management tool for the long term.</p>
<p>After I last mentioned it on my blog, I have been using it quite intensively, and <a href="https://bsky.app/hashtag/zotero?author=charlbotha.com">I keep on running into delightful features</a>, like the built-in PDF reader&rsquo;s pop-up visualization of citations and image references.</p>
<p>A more recent but high power entry into my toolbelt is <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, which I will contend strikes a fantastic usability-power balance in the world of technical document and presentation authoring. I&rsquo;ve now used it, in anger, to write a fairly extensive technical document, along with the afore-mentioned Zotero and <a href="https://retorque.re/zotero-better-bibtex/">Better BibTeX</a> for reference management, and the experience was magically smooth. To seal the deal, by the end I used Quarto to generate an attractive-looking docx for interoperability with the other stakeholders, but my contact time with Word was mercifully minimised.</p>
<h3 id="my-micro-blogging-history-2008---2025">My micro-blogging history 2008 - 2025</h3>
<p>Twitter says I created my account there in December of 2008. However, <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">this blog here says I only started using it in April of 2009</a>. (Twitter first launched in July of 2006.)</p>
<p>Some years later in 2016, coincidentally right before the previous Trumpocalypse, I wrote a post naively suggesting that we should <a href="/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/">replace twitter with something better (blogs&hellip;)</a> due to the risk of Twitter possibly going bad (ahem) and to the observation then that it was (then already) doing a crappy job keeping out abusive users (AHEM).</p>
<p>That post <a href="/2016/11/20/look-mom-hacker-news-front-page/">reached the front page of Hacker News</a>, and was thus read and discussed over there (and probably in the comments here) by tens of thousands of nerds, and a surprisingly small share of the usual &ldquo;Ackchyually&rdquo;-Bros.</p>
<p>(Please allow me this little tangent: A mental model that will really ease your time on sites like HN and reddit, is that the person on the other side, especially when they come across as super confident and assertive, is probably <strong>not</strong> an expert, not even by a long shot, on the topic that they are so confidently mansplaining. In fact, they are probably the least qualified to say anything. ChatGPT avant le lettre one might say. Ok back to your regular programming&hellip;)</p>
<p>Needless to say, my specific idea of replacing twitter with&hellip; blogs and rss was not implemented by the internet, at least not at that point&hellip;</p>
<p>When Musk acquired Twitter in October of 2022, the writing started appearing on the wall, at first vaguely, but with more and more definition as the months went on. I started looking for micro-blogging alternatives that were not twitter.</p>
<p>At first Mastodon looked too complicated, but then someone setup a <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#emacs-mastodon-server-was-irresistible">mastodon server dedicated to Emacs and I was immediately sold</a>.</p>
<p>However, Mastodon indeed turned out to be too complex and fundamentally quite fragile (all but the larger instances have a just a volunteer human or two behind them), leading to the owner of my favourite instance bascially being harassed to such an extent that it was better for him to get out of this business and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@cpbotha/113340325817581254">shut the Emacs mastodon server down</a>.</p>
<p>When I saw this announcement, I was disheartened.</p>
<p>When I read that Mastodon supports message export, but not message import, meaning that my posts would languish in a sad archive file somewhere, I was convinced that I had to try something out that was not Mastodon.</p>
<p>In parallel to my Mastodon efforts, I did also try Threads and was quite enthusiastic about its scale, and the speed with which Meta managed to build it, but I didn&rsquo;t manage to get any sort of interaction there. I think that it might be more geared for the Instagram model of influencers broadcasting to large groups of followers, in contrast to a more collaborative setup. (Urgh, the recent news about Meta&rsquo;s new &ldquo;free speech&rdquo; overhaul is additional motivation for me to spend even less energy there.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, it turns out that the newer and shinier microblogging service Bluesky was conceived in 2019 with the goal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluesky">&ldquo;to find or develop an open and decentralized standard for social media that would give users more control over their data and experience&rdquo;</a>, precisely the sort of thing that has suddenly become even more painfully relevant with the advent of the Trumpocalypse part deux, now with more Musk-power.</p>
<p>Long story short, in a very short time, Bluesky has proven to be almost exactly the microblogging platform that I enjoy participating in. Lots of human interaction, no ads, many different user-contributed algorithms to choose from, including just seeing the stuff your people post, in the order that they post it &ndash; it really feels like the thing was put together with semi-normal human interaction as the central concern.</p>
<p>Up to now, it also feels like <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#bluesky-is-my-new-micro-blogging-thing-of-choice">many folks on there prefer being decent to each other</a>, something I militantly (haha) support.</p>
<p>Some mastodon folks are downright unhappy with bluesky, because they feel that it&rsquo;s not truly decentralized like mastodon.</p>
<p>Thing is, Bluesky has chosen a different spot on the usability - decentralization spectrum, and and my opinion is exactly usable and decentralised enough for what it needs to be and do at this moment in time.</p>
<p>Looking slightly further into the future, there are well-funded initiatives like <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/13/24342799/free-our-feeds-social-media-ecosystem-at-protocol-bluesky">Free our feeds</a>, ideologically and technologically supported by the Bluesky company but otherwise unconnected, which has amongst its <a href="https://freeourfeeds.com/">goals to &ldquo;build independently hosted infrastructure (a second &lsquo;relay&rsquo;) so that Bluesky users, developers and researchers always have full access to the stream of content and data no matter what the company decides to do in future&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>If you would like to know more, Faine Greenwood has written <a href="https://little-flying-robots.ghost.io/the-great-bluesky-migration-i-answer-some-of-your-questions/">this great Bluesky explainer</a>.</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</h2>
<p>My Life Systems are the guiding principles, rules, personal values and bags of tips that I have explicitly defined and refined over the years to help me be the best human that I can be.</p>
<p>Note: I write these up primarily as a reminder to myself. If it comes across as prescriptive, please remember that I&rsquo;m telling <em>me</em> how to live my life. I can do this, because I <em>am</em> the boss of me.</p>
<h3 id="core">Core</h3>
<p>You&rsquo;ll be happy to hear that the core of my Life Systems 2025 is exactly the same as the previous edition <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">Life Systems 2024</a>, except for the version number increase, and the concomitant price increase. (taking a leaf here from the Intel playbook!)</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to read <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">the 2024 write-up</a>, here is the compressed version:</p>
<p><em>Guiding principles:</em> 1. Love 2. Science. <em>Two no three rules for achieving great success in life, or just surviving, whichever comes first:</em> 1. Be useful. 2. be likable and 3. evolve. <em>Personal values:</em> 1. Be kind. 2. Be grateful. 3. Attend fully to the now. 4. Enjoy life with family and with my friends. 5. Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers. 6. Be there for my family. 7. Add value through work. 8. Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise. 9. Build and/or fix something. 10. Learn new things. 11. Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</p>
<h3 id="balance">Balance</h3>
<p>What I have been thinking about this year, especially when things get quite busy, is the sometimes tricky practice of applying balance to one&rsquo;s personal values.</p>
<p>A straight-forward example is when important work obligations start impacting my sleep or exercise schedule, in which case I have to apply balance and tone down slightly the ambition to fulfil personal value no 7.</p>
<p>It can easily get more tricky however; when something on that list of personal values, which is important to you, starts taking up more than its fair share of energy, that will come at the cost of all of the other endeavours that you value.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have a hard and fast rule for this, only the measure of remembering to <em>pay attention</em> also at that meta-level so that one can make suitable balancing adjustments when required.</p>
<h3 id="work-hard-party-hard-rest-hard">Work hard. Party hard. Rest hard.</h3>
<p>A lesson that has only become clearer for me over the years is that we humans function best when we are able to focus on one thing at a time, and when we have as few things as possible on the list that we select from.</p>
<p>This works at all scales of life, from what task do I work on during this half-hour all the way up to my main priority for today, or my three main priorities for this year.</p>
<p>The challenge in applying this lesson is three-fold:</p>
<ol>
<li>Know which thing to focus on at any time,</li>
<li>reduce switching between things and yet</li>
<li>get to all of the things that you should get to.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you have all three of these covered, then comes the truly difficult part: <strong>Attend fully to the now.</strong></p>
<p>Those of us who are lucky get about 4000 weeks of life.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not truly present in the thing that you&rsquo;ve chosen at this moment, you are not using that allotted time to its fullest extent.</p>
<p>You can never ever get that time back.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like you&rsquo;re in a Michelin-starred restaurant, and instead of going power level 9000 with all of your senses and your thoughts and your whole being into <em>experiencing</em> that food with your favourite human(s), you&rsquo;re scrolling on your phone, absent-mindedly shovelling forkfuls into your mouth.</p>
<p>Do the opposite.</p>
<p>Pick your battles, but sometimes also choose a party if you can and don&rsquo;t forget to rest like your life depends on it. Whatever you do, be the most maximally present in the thing you&rsquo;ve chosen. Presence and attention improve with regular practice.</p>
<p>In short: Work hard, party hard, rest hard.</p>
<!-- be maximally present to use that time right; do everything HARD -- came during my 2025-01-11 morning run -->
<h2 id="my-2024-to-2025-transition-wishes">My 2024 to 2025 transition wishes</h2>
<p>Humans<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> <em>at their peak</em> are a thing of beauty.</p>
<p>Above all they are truly kind.  They live and breathe the knowledge that we <em>homo sapiens</em> are at our absolute best when we connect with each other.</p>
<p>Peak humans are graceful, and they are elegant, and they are in harmony &ndash; the best sort of balance &ndash; with their surroundings, with those around them and with themselves.</p>
<p>Attaining this peak is hard. Maintaining it is nigh impossible. Best we can go for is <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">the never-ending practice</a> of these characteristics, and an eternal striving for moments to <em>become them</em>.</p>
<p>Friends, I wish you and your connected ones the willpower to strive for grace and elegance and harmony, and the presence of mind to attend fully to those perfect moments when they occur.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, you might be one of these&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #256: Word</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/24/weekly-head-voices-256-word/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 21:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/24/weekly-head-voices-256-word/</guid><description>The title of this post is another nerd-dad joke I probably should not have made, but which I simply could not resist.
Whatever the case may be, I&amp;rsquo;m happy that it&amp;rsquo;s out, just like this, the otherwise extremely modest 256th edition of the Weekly Head Voices!
A scene from our Saturday family and friends hike in Jonkershoek.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The title of this post is another nerd-dad joke I probably should not have made, but which I simply could not resist.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I&rsquo;m happy that it&rsquo;s out, just like this, the otherwise extremely modest 256th edition of the Weekly Head Voices!</p>








    


<figure><a href="panoramic_jonkershoek_yellowwood.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/24/weekly-head-voices-256-word/panoramic_jonkershoek_yellowwood_hu_bc0dc874fd6e2c48.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/24/weekly-head-voices-256-word/panoramic_jonkershoek_yellowwood_hu_b744cfd190403525.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/24/weekly-head-voices-256-word/panoramic_jonkershoek_yellowwood_hu_5b6adc06092ded60.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/24/weekly-head-voices-256-word/panoramic_jonkershoek_yellowwood_hu_3bd7a34e512b7b3a.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/24/weekly-head-voices-256-word/panoramic_jonkershoek_yellowwood_hu_b744cfd190403525.webp"
            

        
            alt="A scene from our Saturday family and friends hike in Jonkershoek."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>A scene from our Saturday family and friends hike in Jonkershoek.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Today I only have three things (ok it turns out I have four!) I would like to mention.</p>
<h2 id="shielding-you-from-the-equal-odds-rule">Shielding you from the equal-odds rule</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve often read about this phenomenon, and internalised the idea, but today I found its original source.</p>
<p>It was in fact Dean Simonton&rsquo;s research that brought us /the equal-odds rule/:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Simonton found that the probability of producing a highly recognized work product, such as an influential research article, is roughly the same for all contributors, whether eminent or not. This is what Simonton called the equal-odds principle. What distinguishes highly eminent scholars is the overall volume of works they produce. By sheer dint of productivity, those who reach professional eminence stack the odds in their favor of producing another masterpiece</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(The quote above is from Simonton&rsquo;s 2010 book Learning and Cognition: The Design of the Mind (p.224), but I retrieved it from the <a href="https://sarneckalab.blogspot.com/2017/12/simontons-equal-odds-rule.html">Sarnecka Lab Blog&rsquo;s post on the topic</a>.)</p>
<p>I think we can extend this to fields outside of academia. People who appear to produce a great deal of fantastic work do so by producing a greater amount of work in total than their peers.</p>
<p>According to Simonton, the ratio of great work to non-great work is similar for everyone. Those who succeed, are just producing that much more.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s a long story to explain that many of the posts on this blog are going to be just meh, and some just bad, but I have to make them all and put them here so that there can be good ones in between.</p>
<p>(Now that I write this, I&rsquo;m sure I must have mentioned this before on this blog&hellip; can you help me find the post(s) in question?)</p>
<p>In any case, to help you work around this glitch in the creativity matrix, and to give new readers a more gentle introduction, I decided during my run this morning to start explicitly tagging posts that I personally really like.</p>
<p>I have only just started with this, and it will probably take a while to go through all of my older posts, but you can henceforth keep an eye out for the tag <a href="/tags/my-selection/">&ldquo;my selection&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p><em>P.S. or rather &ldquo;pssst!&rdquo;: This edition did not get the tag. <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/">Last week&rsquo;s post #255</a> did!</em></p>
<h2 id="making-til-go-fast">Making TiL go fast</h2>
<p>During the weekend I noticed that the super recently <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">announced TIL (Things I Learned) section</a> on my other website was not as fast I expected.</p>
<p>Turns out I was right.</p>
<p>The debugging and working-arounding were the source of an hour of two of entertainment, and <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/11/23/speed-up-obsidian-quartz-page-loads/">a new blog post at the vxlabs</a>.</p>
<h2 id="something-he-can-never-have">Something he can never have</h2>
<p>On the Saturday hike, I recounted this story to a friend, but it&rsquo;s always tricky when at that point you&rsquo;re unable to remember the two amazing dramatis personae.</p>
<p>Today I went searching to find the exact details, and was delighted to find that <a href="https://genius.com/Kurt-vonnegut-joe-heller-annotated">Kurt Vonnegut himself had written a poem about his experience with his friend Joseph Heller</a> at some billionaire&rsquo;s party.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Joe Heller</p>
<p>True story, Word of Honor:<br>
Joseph Heller, an important and funny writer<br>
now dead,<br>
and I were at a party given by a billionaire<br>
on Shelter Island.<br>
I said, &ldquo;Joe, how does it make you feel<br>
to know that our host only yesterday<br>
may have made more money<br>
than your novel &lsquo;Catch-22&rsquo;<br>
has earned in its entire history?&rdquo;<br>
And Joe said, &ldquo;I’ve got something he can never have.&rdquo;<br>
And I said, &ldquo;What on earth could that be, Joe?&rdquo;<br>
And Joe said, &ldquo;The knowledge that I&rsquo;ve got enough.&rdquo;<br>
Not bad! Rest in peace!&quot;</p>
<p>&ndash; Kurt Vonnegut</p>
<p><em>The New Yorker</em>, May 16th, 2005</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #254: Ratio</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 15:02:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/</guid><description>Hello there WHV enjoyers, and welcome back! &amp;hellip;ish.
The last official WHV, by name, was WHV #253, published on September 2, 2023, although the 2023 to 2024 transition post certainly deserves its honorary WHV title.
In the meantime, I have been experimenting with the Daily Head Voices / lifelogs, which was fun, but ultimately not sufficiently meaty to fill the WHV vacuum.
We are clearly going through a pretty significant WHV-hiatus.
Although I&amp;rsquo;m still not sure what the new stable state is going to be, I have some extremely modest plans, and in addition to those I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to dust off and revive the draft of WHV #254 which was just lying there on my disc since September of last year, all languishing.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello there WHV enjoyers, and welcome back! &hellip;ish.</p>
<p>The last official WHV, by name, was <a href="/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/">WHV #253, published on September 2, 2023</a>, although the <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/">2023 to 2024 transition post</a> certainly deserves its honorary WHV title.</p>
<p>In the meantime, I have been experimenting with the <a href="/categories/lifelog/">Daily Head Voices / lifelogs</a>, which was fun, but ultimately not sufficiently meaty to fill the WHV vacuum.</p>
<p>We are clearly going through a pretty significant WHV-hiatus.</p>
<p>Although I&rsquo;m still not sure what the new stable state is going to be, I have <em>some</em> extremely modest plans, and in addition to those I&rsquo;ve decided to dust off and revive the draft of WHV #254 which was just lying there on my disc since September of last year, all languishing.</p>










<figure><a href="wilderness-view-from-the-views.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_3a2af3333e208e2c.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_81aa06121ae775ec.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_e50b29cbe418a449.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_51f1e144bf2c94d8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_81aa06121ae775ec.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: The view from our return-journey lunch at The Views in Wilderness was awe-inspiring."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>The view from our return-journey lunch at The Views in Wilderness was awe-inspiring.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="easter-break-on-the-garden-route">Easter break on the Garden Route</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m typing these words on my laptop in the family car, moving back home along the N2 after an absolutely fabulous Easter break-away on the Garden Route.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I have not yet figured out a safe way to drive and type at the same time, so my partner is graciously helping out with the driving bits during this shift.</p>
<p>GOU#1&rsquo;s exchange family &ldquo;sister&rdquo; from Germany is currently visiting, and so we have been doing our best to show her some of the best this amazing country has to offer.</p>
<p>Although this makes for a fairly jam-packed holiday programme (almost no time to work on hobby projects), it really has been loads of fun.</p>
<p>Some highlights (ask me in the comments if you&rsquo;re curious about anything):</p>
<ul>
<li>Ebb &amp; Flow rest camp in Wilderness - one of my favourite running routes next to the Serpentine river</li>
<li>Sun-down at Salinas Beach restaurant in Wilderness</li>
<li><a href="https://knysnaelephantpark.co.za">Elephant encounters at the Knysna Elephant Park</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.sanparks.org/parks/garden-route/camps/storms-river-mouth">Storms River Mouth rest camp (Tsitsikamma)</a> - beauty all round, hikes over the hanging bridges up past the view point, also the start of the Otter trail at the other end of the camp</li>
<li>Lunch at The Views in Wilderness</li>
<li>St Francis, beautiful as always, with specific mention of Etienne&rsquo;s surfing lessons at the main beach for our teenagers, and the super entertaining St Francis Bay canal sunset cruise</li>
<li>We were absolutely blessed with balmy later summer weather, except for one rainy morning in Storms</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="two-mention-worthy-personal-knowledge-tools">Two mention-worthy personal knowledge tools</h2>
<p>As is traditional around these parts, we have this nerdy section surprise here to talk about software tools that I really like, after which there will be some backyard philosophy sections.</p>
<h3 id="miniflux">miniflux</h3>
<p>My yearly <a href="https://www.inoreader.com">inoreader</a> rss reader subscription was up for renewal.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a really fantastic product that I&rsquo;ve been using (and paying for) for years as <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#mobile">a core part of my personal knowledge management approach</a>, but the renewal email and especially the price tag was a good reminder to review my options, especially since I already have an old Linux laptop serving <a href="https://pi-hole.net">Pi-hole</a> for family-wide ad-blocking, and <a href="https://www.home-assistant.io">Home Assistant</a> to track energy production and usage stats of some of our devices at home.</p>
<p>A few minutes of searching fortunately led me to <a href="https://miniflux.app">miniflux</a>, &ldquo;a minimalist and opinionated feed reader&rdquo;. After a few more minutes, I had the docker-compose up and running (miniflux and postgres containers), and after some more minutes I had a <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/en-gb/products/tunnel/">CloudFlare tunnel</a> up so that I can easily access my miniflux&rsquo;s web UI from anywhere via an automatic Cloudflare-supplied SSL certificate. Finally, through the magic of OPML, it was straight-forward to move my 130+ feed subscriptions from inoreader to miniflux.</p>










<figure><a href="screenshot-miniflux.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_ef74d383072aa1b5.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_4c429f2130b9c515.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_34a9379b4036d398.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_6bf961f84eb46697.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_4c429f2130b9c515.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: miniflux often looks like this"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>miniflux often looks like this</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been using this setup for the past week or two and so far it looks like a strong keeper!</p>
<p>miniflux has extensive keyboard support on the desktop, but it works great on mobile, which is where I mostly use it.</p>
<p>I really like its minimalism: It shows me a paged view of all my feeds (page size configurable), via which I can easily jump to the source page, or use miniflux&rsquo;s built-in reader mode, and also easily toggle the whole page as read before moving on to the next.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re in the market for a self-hosted RSS reader, take this as a strong recommendation for miniflux. Even if you don&rsquo;t want to self-host, <a href="https://miniflux.app/hosting.html">their $15 / year hosted offering</a> is probably worth a look.</p>
<h3 id="omnivore">omnivore</h3>
<p>After years of eschewing &ldquo;read-it-later&rdquo; apps like Pocket and friends for the more straight-forward but often klunky  <a href="/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">&ldquo;just print to PDF and store&rdquo; approach</a>, I had to give <a href="https://omnivore.app/">omnivore</a> a go, as it offered native support to sync article highlights into Obsidian&rsquo;s markdown, and I thought that I would be able to use this for my Emacs setup as well.</p>
<p>I was indeed able to co-opt the Obsidian integration to get saved article highlights into my Emacs setup, but in the process fell completely for the omnivore app as a whole.</p>
<p>On mobile, which is where I use this most, I am able to import any web-page or post into omnivore with two taps.</p>
<p>On average, it does a great job of extracting the article contents and rendering it in a far more consistent and reading-friendly way.</p>
<p>One can make different coloured highlights in any article, and even add a note to each highlight.</p>
<p>Finally, it also imports PDFs with aplomb, and offers most of its functionality there. There are additional subtle delights, like the fact that you can double-tap on one column of a multi-column PDF, at which point omnivore will zoom to bring only that column into maximum width view.</p>










<figure><a href="screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom_hu_7e164320f45eb29e.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom_hu_f767113c0785ef74.jpg 800w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom_hu_f767113c0785ef74.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Vertically partial screenshot of Omnivore during PDF column zoom. Maps of Bounded Reality is a piece by the great Daniel Kahneman (1934-03-05 - 2024-03-27, rest in peace) which gives an overview of his and Amos Tversky&rsquo;s groundbreaking work making sense of human behaviour." width="320px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Vertically partial screenshot of Omnivore during PDF column zoom. Maps of Bounded Reality is a piece by the great Daniel Kahneman (1934-03-05 - 2024-03-27, rest in peace) which gives an overview of his and Amos Tversky&rsquo;s groundbreaking work making sense of human behaviour.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For me the only downside of omnivore is that it violates <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#high-level-overview">both my single search interface and plain old files on local drives characteristics</a>. However, both of these violations are partially mitigated by the aforementioned note-syncing feature. I don&rsquo;t really want to have <strong>all</strong> of my saved articles to be part of my database, so here I should make syncable highlights when something is important enough to go into the primary notes database.</p>
<p>After some months of use, I strongly recommend omnivore as your web-resource-ingestion-and-assimilation tool!</p>
<h2 id="the-three-or-four-hours-rule-for-getting-creative-work-done">The three-or-four hours rule for getting creative work done</h2>
<p>Last year, I listened to a short piece by Oliver Burkeman, who has <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">featured on this blog a number of times</a>, which made an impression on me. I made a note of it in the pre-hiatus draft of this post, and then promptly forgot about it.</p>
<p>The core of Burkeman&rsquo;s three-or-four hours rule, which you can <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">read more about on his website</a>, is summarised in the following quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; use whatever freedom you do have over your schedule not to &ldquo;maximise your
time&rdquo; or &ldquo;optimise your day&rdquo;, in some vague way, but specifically to ringfence
three or four hours of undisturbed focus (ideally when your energy levels are
highest).</p>
<p>Stop assuming that the way to make progress on your most important projects is
to work for longer. And drop the perfectionistic notion that emails, meetings,
digital distractions and other interruptions ought ideally to be whittled away
to practically nothing.</p>
<p>Just focus on protecting four hours – and don&rsquo;t worry if the rest of the day is
characterised by the usual scattered chaos.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have definitely suffered from the &ldquo;maximise your time&rdquo; bug and can attest to its negative effects.</p>
<p>Burkeman suggests to worry only about a core few high-focus hours (he says 3 or 4, I think sometimes depending on your context, even 1 could work) and let the rest be what it wants to be.</p>
<p>I think this is a far better approach which strongly complements <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">the one main thing philosophy</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. There&rsquo;s another important tenet of Burkeman&rsquo;s approach, which he talks about in his post linked above, and which also <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">featured in WHV #230, namely: Know how to put down your work</a> (although I just noticed that back then I did not mention the chaos part&hellip;). In summary: Guard your focus hours, let &ldquo;the chaos&rdquo; fill the rest, but become really good at detaching and walking away at the end of the work day. Thank you <a href="http://noeskasmit.com">Noeska</a> for the reminder!</p>
<h2 id="the-magic-relationship-ratio-is-5-to-1">The Magic Relationship Ratio is 5 to 1</h2>
<p>I really enjoyed the <a href="https://lexfridman.com/shannon-curry/">fascinating podcast between Lex Fridman and Dr Shannon Curry</a>, a clinical and forensic psychologist, titled &ldquo;Johnny Depp &amp; Amber Heard Trial, Marriage, Dating &amp; Love&rdquo;, much of it in fact about human relationships (<a href="https://www.podcastworld.io/episodes/366-shannon-curry-johnny-depp-amber-heard-trial-marriage-dat-sz9ltosy">textual summary here</a>).</p>
<p>Among the many practical and science-based topics that Dr Curry talked about, she mentioned the <a href="https://www.gottman.com/blog/the-magic-relationship-ratio-according-science/">&ldquo;5 to 1magic relationship ratio&rdquo;</a>, which refers to the observation that the interactions between happy couples tend to consist of at least 5 positive interactions for each negative interaction.</p>
<p>It should come as no surprise that being able to spend decades together in a permanent state of happiness, by definition continuously facing various internal and external stressors in an often resource-constrained environment, is probably not realistic.</p>
<p>Thus I really like that this observation runs with the knowledge that almost no-one is going to get this right, and that the smart approach is instead to accept that and focus on what you can attain, namely, that more practical but still ambitious 5 to 1 ratio.</p>
<h2 id="ratio">Ratio</h2>
<p>This is the part of the post where I try to tie up some of the threads, or at least justify the title.</p>
<p>Burkeman&rsquo;s three-or-four hours rule is all about working towards a practical and healthy <em>ratio</em> between focus time and the rest of the daily chaos, instead of being continuously disappointed because it&rsquo;s not really possible to fill all of your days with pure focus hours.</p>
<p>The 5 to 1 ratio is the same: We make peace with reality, and work towards a healthy ratio between positive and negative interactions.</p>
<p>The third <em>ratio</em> I want to mention here refers to the Dutch word &ldquo;ratio&rdquo; (<a href="https://nl.bab.la/uitspraak/nederlands/ratio">pronunciation)</a>, one of whose definitions is &ldquo;reason&rdquo; or &ldquo;logic&rdquo;, or more idiomatically, the noun corresponding to adjective &ldquo;rationeel&rdquo;, which is the same as the English &ldquo;rational&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As with all things language, the use of this word implies subtle little differences. Whatever the case may be, I was delighted when I discovered that the Dutch had adopted the original Latin for this. To me it felt like that meant there was a special place for and focus on <em>ratio</em> in their world.</p>
<p>With that trifecta (a neologism, I just learned, for contrast!) of <em>ratio</em> examples, I think that I can now conclude this post with the earnest wish, for you and for me, that we are able to instantiate, maintain and propagate superb levels of <em>ratio</em>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2023 to 2024 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 15:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2024 everyone, and especially to this traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: View from first morning of the Cape of Good Hope hiking trail with family and friends. The 3-in-1 hill climb in the summer sun at the end of day 2 almost took me out.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2024 everyone, and especially to this <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="2023-12-16-cape-point-hike.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_e736f7a9c5849337.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_5d2baa1368199c5d.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_92dc0cc764247a73.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_878bfcc0c607f876.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_5d2baa1368199c5d.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from first morning of the Cape of Good Hope hiking trail with family and friends. The 3-in-1 hill climb in the summer sun at the end of day 2 almost took me out."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>View from first morning of the Cape of Good Hope hiking trail with family and friends. The 3-in-1 hill climb in the summer sun at the end of day 2 almost took me out.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="overview-and-a-warning">Overview, and a warning</h2>
<p>While the year transition posts down here are usually an optimistic and upbeat affair, I have to warn you that this year&rsquo;s edition is a bit different.</p>
<p>Most of the possibly depressing stuff is in the first section, all about aging and cancer and mortality, which you probably could have guessed based on the title, and if not, now on the summary here. Consider strongly skipping the section if you prefer a more optimistic reading of this post.</p>
<p>After the aforementioned <em>harshing of the vibe</em>, I give an extremely spotty review of the physical (running and exercise), the cerebral (writing) and the virtual (systems and tools) aspects of the past year.</p>
<p>I conclude the post with some backyard philosophical ramblings on my continuing efforts at being a good human, and my wishes for you and your loved ones.</p>
<h2 id="aging-is-rough">Aging is rough</h2>
<p>For me, 2023 was the year of really getting in touch with my mortality.</p>
<p>In August of 2023, I <em>started</em> my 50th revolution around the sun.</p>
<p>My birthday might have been enough of a reminder, but the message was made unquestionably clear with <a href="/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/">my prostate cancer</a> diagnosis in February. No thanks to mother nature, and all thanks to science and modern healthcare, the surgical treatment was swift and as effective as we are able to measure.</p>
<p>Love, by all of my friends and family supporting me throughout all of this, and science, see modern healthcare above, got me through this whole adventure with only a small number of scars to show for it. Besides the physical scars, my previously strong trust in my physical robustness took a really big knock.</p>
<p>Much more recently, as in a day or two ago, the pathology results for two recently excised suspicious skin growths came back from the pathology lab.</p>
<p>Both are basal cell carcinoma (BCC), but while the one was completely excised, the other was not, and was also classified as morpheaform BCC, the rarest and more aggressive form of the three.</p>
<p>To the best of my current knowledge, we just need to remove the rest and I should be mostly derisked, but dangit, I had really hoped not to have to think about any form of cancer again for a little while longer.</p>
<p>So, people, please take the following advice as seriously as you possibly can:</p>
<ul>
<li>The sun, especially down here, is amazing but also quite dangerous. Lotion up as often as possible, wear that stupid hat, spend more time in the shade.</li>
<li>All of you, especially younger readers: Use hearing protection at music events. Last year before Lowlands I acquired <a href="https://eargasm.com/products/eargasm-high-fidelity-earplugs">Eargast High Fidelity Earplugs</a>, only about 20 years too late! (like skin canccer, tinnitus is another one of those things you have to start actively preventing decades before it possibly starts)</li>
<li>Over 40? Get your PSA tested.</li>
</ul>
<p>On a more philosophical and hopefully not too depressing note: It has become viscerally clear to me that once one is past reproductive age, one has irrevocably entered the domain of borrowed time.</p>
<p>If you think about evolution and more specifically selection, you can see that survival traits, by the power of math, could only really be encouraged in the young. After the reproductive phase, with <em>genes already passed on</em>, there could be no <em>effective</em> reward or punishment for respectively beneficial and detrimental traits.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the antagonistic pleiotropic (AP) hypothesis posits that there are genes which control more than one trait &ldquo;where at least one of these traits is beneficial to the organism&rsquo;s fitness early on in life and at least one is detrimental to the organism&rsquo;s fitness later on due to a decline in the force of natural selection&rdquo; (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antagonistic_pleiotropy_hypothesis">AP - wikipedia</a>, <a href="https://www.nature.com/scitable/knowledge/library/the-evolution-of-aging-23651151/">The Evolution of Aging - Nature</a>)</p>
<p>An interesting recent example is <a href="https://alzres.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13195-020-00740-0">this 2021 study of apolipoprotein E (APOE ε4)</a>, which is the strongest genetic risk factor for late onset Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease, but at the same time is also associated with cognitive benefits earlier in life.</p>
<p>From the discussion in the linked paper:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>These results taken together provide support for the antagonistic pleiotropic hypothesis as cognitive performance was better at younger ages in APOE ε4 heterozygotes and both heterozygous and homozygous APOE ε4 carriers also had higher risk of dementia at older ages.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So&hellip; about &ldquo;mother&rdquo; nature.</p>
<p>Nature is beautiful, but absolutely ruthless.</p>
<p>The mental model of &ldquo;natural&rdquo; being beneficial for us humans is at best only coincidentally and very partially useful. For the most part, it&rsquo;s wrong and quite dangerous.</p>
<p>In the end, we can only rely on science, and on each other, to survive and flourish.</p>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>In last year&rsquo;s transition post, I was <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#running">hoping for an average of 25km per week in 2023</a> which would have meant about 1200km for the year.</p>
<p>However, I did not plan on being taken out of the&hellip; running for 6 weeks by my prostate before being allowed to start slowing picking it up again.</p>
<p>In spite of that, I was super happy to see a bit later in the year that 1000km was still in reach, and so I went for that.</p>
<p>Something that looks like it could be my gluteus medius attempted to sabotage my efforts during the final weeks, but on December 30 I pushed through with a last run of the year. 1000km in the pocket!</p>










<figure><a href="strava-fitness-2023.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_fda5ac701be2142f.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_c8669b3c69d1229.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_e07f5d05f7cfd8af.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_9f954c3d4f0bafc3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_c8669b3c69d1229.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: The smooth part of the curve from the start of April until mid-May was for surgery and recovery. I&rsquo;m happy with the gradual build-up after that and the big push at the end of the year!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>The smooth part of the curve from the start of April until mid-May was for surgery and recovery. I&rsquo;m happy with the gradual build-up after that and the big push at the end of the year!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Regular running is the mechanical backbone of my life.</p>
<p>Even when the stress is great and it feels like stuff is falling apart, those clockwork runs bring peace and perspective. When it&rsquo;s going really great, they bring exhilaration and they feel like a celebration of life!</p>
<p>Although I am hopeful that the current injury resolves itself, which it should if it is in fact my gluteus medius, I might start looking into cross-training this year. It would be great to have an alternative exercise modality to tide me over when injuries happen and to keep me out of the sun a part of the time.</p>
<p>My only running-specific desire is to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>For you numbers-people, that&rsquo;s probably not the most interesting goal.</p>
<p>As a hopefully more satisfying alternative, I would like to offer my super-secret exercise goal for 2024:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be able to do 50 consecutive push-ups,</li>
<li>have a VO₂ Max of at least 50 and</li>
<li>a resting state heart rate of 50 or under.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>For reasons that I&rsquo;ve now mentioned often enough, I produced only a small number of longer blog posts in 2023, namely the <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/">transition post</a>, three (3) weekly head voices posts (including the cancer one), and the <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/">2023 note-taking strategy post</a> which I&rsquo;m really happy with.</p>
<p>Besides that, there were a few short technical postlets over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>On November 14, faced by this barren landscape of almost no blogging, I thought it was worth trying to break through the concomitant writer&rsquo;s block by putting out a <em>daily</em> bullet list of life minutiae: Experiences, learnings and observations that might be interesting to Someone on the Internet.</p>
<p>By reducing the expectation to a straight-forward list of daily miscellanea it would in theory be substantially easier and faster to produce said list.</p>
<p>Further, I deliberately did so on my favourite mastodon server, namely <a href="https://emacs.ch/">emacs.ch</a>, because I trusted that the obscurity of mastodon would mean that not many people would actually see my daily lifelogs, which would further reduce posting friction.</p>
<p>In a surprising turn of events, all of this seemed to work!</p>
<p>As I <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/issues/26868">can&rsquo;t directly link to a mastodon search yet</a>, you will have to go to <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha">my profile</a> or to <a href="https://emacs.ch/tags/lifelog">the #lifelog tag</a> and browse back if you are interested in the first 30 (thirty!) posts, starting on November 14.</p>
<p>On <a href="/2023/12/18/daily-head-voices-on-monday-2023-12-18/">December 18 I decided to move the Daily Head Voices back here</a> because reasons (which you can read about in that post). Since then I have really been enjoying keeping them going during the Christmas break, and I&rsquo;ve also made some tweaks to the technical setup in order to be able to publish them more efficiently.</p>
<p>Although I would really like to work on more substantial posts in the future, recent experience has shown that it might be a while before I can make the space that that requires. The <a href="/categories/lifelog/">lifelog posts</a> are an enjoyable way for me to keep the writing pipes open in the meantime!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and tools</h2>
<p>A core part of my functioning is <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human">the system of software tools and other tricks</a> that I use to work and live better. Other names that people use to describe this thing include second brain, <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">exocortex</a>, or just a really big pile of lists.</p>
<p>Shortly after my pretty detailed <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/">Note-taking strategy 2023</a> blog post, I underwent what I can only describe as some form of Emacs crisis of faith.</p>
<p>During this period, I experienced deep doubt in my current system, and came pretty close to jumping ship.</p>
<p>My crisis was largely due to three things:</p>
<ol>
<li>The shiny webkit-based rendering engines in many of the competitors, enabling useful-looking visualizations and interesting new visual interaction approaches.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins">vibrant extension community of the local-first Obsidian note-taking tool</a> where many enthusiasts were tapping into the enormous javascript / typescript library ecosystem, and shiny webkit-rendering mentioned above.</li>
<li>Emacs and org-mode&rsquo;s comparatively weak mobile support. (yes, I&rsquo;ve tried, and purchased were relevant, <a href="#d41d8c">beorg</a>, plain.org, organice, orgro and probably many more.)</li>
</ol>
<p>After months of cogitation, I fortunately convinced myself to first test the waters before jumping, where my usual style is just to throw <strong>everything</strong> out and start over, and extremely quickly ran into the glaring weakness that is Obsidian&rsquo;s lack of first class support for the humble timestamp&hellip;</p>
<p>This is something that we Orgmode users take for granted, but man, the Orgmode timestamp is actually pretty amazing.</p>
<p>This textual analogue of an inverted ice bucket seemed to shock me out of my daze, and suddenly I was again able to make peace with Old Reliable BFG9000, aka Emacs and Org.</p>
<p>As part of my atonement, and also to mitigate some of their perceived deficiencies, I coded up and published the following software upgrades to Emacs, Org-mode and Org-roam:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/braindump4000">braindump4000</a>: Convert any Org-mode database into a hyperlinked website, and also an Obsidian vault, so that you can browse it on your phone using the Obsidian app.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">org-roam-canvas</a>: Expose your whole org-roam database in such a way that you can embed org-roam notes as part of an Obsidian canvas. (see screenshots on the github)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity">org-roam-similarity</a>: Use AI-based similarity (i.e. learned document embeddings / vectors) to interactively list similar org-roam notes to the one that you are working on. This is something that I&rsquo;ve been dreaming about for years, and this is also something that I&rsquo;ve been using quite regularly and successfully to surface relevant information from the depths of my notes!</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-to-apple-notes">org-roam-to-apple-notes</a>: This was quite painful thanks to Apple&rsquo;s super bad AppleScript support of Apple Notes, but it has turned out to be quite useful. On macOS, you can export your whole org-roam database, or just the note that you&rsquo;re currently working on, straight into Apple Notes. Although I implemented base64 embedding of images as this was <em>rumoured</em> to work, images don&rsquo;t work because Apple.</li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_c599996d6ef5a83.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_bc73da04581f6dbb.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_e15f6dbc1a62ed46.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_910a12b14db41a96.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_bc73da04581f6dbb.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: A screenshot of org-roam-similarity showing similar notes in org-roam-buffer."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>A screenshot of <code>org-roam-similarity</code> showing similar notes in <code>org-roam-buffer</code>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I write this, it really feels like my faith has been fully restored.</p>
<h3 id="ai">AI</h3>
<p>2023 was the year when, through the astounding success and utility of large language models like ChatGPT and friends, as well as latent diffusion models like StableDiffusion, Dall-E and Midjourney, and many more examples of generative AI, we could finally start using the term &ldquo;AI&rdquo; almost completely unironically!</p>
<p>Thanks to Day Job, <a href="/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/#genai">I had the opportunity to go quite deep</a>, giving a number of pretty detailed talks on the nuts and bolts of transformer-based language models.</p>
<p>The reason I&rsquo;m mentioning it here though, is just to make a public note of the fact that I have been exploring and integrating these new tools into all of my workflows as much as makes sense, attempting to push the barriers here and there.</p>
<p>Like the preternaturally productive <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2023/Mar/27/ai-enhanced-development/">Simon Willison writes</a>, the current generation of AI coding assistance tools are enabling me to take on personal projects I previously would not have due to the time required, and to get those projects to a usable state far more quickly.</p>
<p>My own programming ability is still the driving force (this is the part in my brain that models and simulates software systems in wetware so that I can implement and debug them), but the AI takes care of so much boiler plate, and also helps quickly exploring multiple high probability solutions to the little problems that one invariably runs into.</p>
<p>Besides <a href="https://github.com/features/copilot">Github Copilot</a> which I use in VS Code and also in Emacs via <a href="https://github.com/copilot-emacs/copilot.el">copilot.el</a> to write, sort of ironically, better Emacs Lisp code more quickly, I am trying to integrate at least one AI assistant into my general daily workflow.</p>
<p>My current flavour is <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/">perplexity</a>, an LLM-based system that focuses on answering questions, using background web searches coupled with a current generation LLM.</p>
<p>Although perplexity works really well as a question answering tool, I am waiting for something that combines its talents with a more refined version of the already impressive but sometimes a bit wild <a href="https://github.com/KillianLucas/open-interpreter">Open Interpreter</a> (which I have obviously played with), and for that true AI assistant Jarvis-like tool to be always within reach&hellip;</p>
<p><a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2023/09/new-ray-ban-meta-smart-glasses/">Meta&rsquo;s new Ray Ban AI-powered smart glasses</a> look like a very interesting hardware step in this direction, and might even mean that while I lost <a href="/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/#bet-1-huds">that 2009 bet about HUDs</a> with regard to its timing, I was at least thinking in the right direction!</p>
<p>Please excuse the rambling; I am really quite excited about the now near future role of AI assistants in human culture!</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2024">Life systems 2024</h2>
<p>As <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">January 2022 Charl remarked</a>, <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">our January 2021 self really seemed to have everything figured out and organized</a>, at least in terms of life directions. Furthermore, if we&rsquo;re being honest with ourselves, <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#things-i-would-like-to-work-on-in-2023">January 2023</a> was also quite fuzzy&hellip;</p>
<p>Surprisingly to me however, this year, after spending some thinking time during the vacation, I have compiled a pretty organized-looking and hopefully practical list of personal values, which I will hereby add to the famous <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">WHV approach to life, the universe and everything (WALUE)</a>.</p>
<p>You might recall that our guiding principles were two-fold: 1. Love. 2. Science. (in that order)</p>
<p>.. while the <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">The WHV’s Two no Three Rules for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</a> were 1. Be useful, 2. be likable and 3. evolve.</p>
<p>Over the years I added six personal directions on top of all that, and then later, in a seemingly well-motivated but eventually unsuccessful attempt to apply those directions more successfully, I grouped them into two clusters, namely 1. Grow, learn, build, enjoy. (motion) and 2. Be useful. Be likeable. Be kind. (self-checks).</p>
<p>Well, <strong>this</strong> year I&rsquo;m replacing those two clusters with the following re-expanded list of my more concrete personal values and priorities.  In all cases, it should be possible to use these to check the desirability of any choice or activity.</p>
<ol>
<li>Be kind.</li>
<li>Be grateful.</li>
<li>Attend fully to the now.</li>
<li>Enjoy life with family and with my friends.</li>
<li>Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers.</li>
<li>Be there for my family.</li>
<li>Add value through work.</li>
<li>Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise.</li>
<li>Build or/or fix something.</li>
<li>Learn new things.</li>
<li>Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</li>
</ol>
<p>In summary, the shiny new 2024 life systems edition consists of the same old a) two guiding principles and the same old b) two no three rules, but now we&rsquo;ve added these c) 11 shiny new personal values all for the same low, low price.</p>
<p>There are no real surprises in this list, but hopefully keeping it close will help to bias daily action in the right directions.</p>
<p>P.S. Please don&rsquo;t forget the <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#learning-at-the-burning">PERMA</a> when thinking about your personal well-being.</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2024">Wishes for 2024</h2>
<p>Dear fellow human,</p>
<p>This is the end of this blog post.</p>
<p>Thank you for being here.</p>
<p>I wish you and your loved ones a year of learning, kindness, gratitude, health and happiness.</p>










<figure><a href="stilbaai-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_f4c4eedfe584fe5a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_8c04e2966d04c4f1.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_1a92a7bd1be2fa3d.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_2021f04e9c9f0447.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_8c04e2966d04c4f1.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Tuesday 2024-01-02: Culture of doubt</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/03/daily-head-voices-on-tuesday-2024-01-02/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/03/daily-head-voices-on-tuesday-2024-01-02/</guid><description> Religion is a culture of faith; science is a culture of doubt. &amp;ndash; Richard Feynman
Went to the beach at just after 11:00. Brilliant weather which for Betty&amp;rsquo;s is quite special, so the place was absolutely packed. Finally created org-capture-template to do the Daily Head Voices post setup more easily and more consistently, see below for the relevant element. Thought a bit about writing and then self-hosting the tool that scans the cpbotha.net RSS feed and then performs actions, e.g. sending to Telegram, when new posts appear Initial thought was Go, because small and self-contained (like my discord scihub bot and my eureka-alert RSS feed generator), but Python means much higher development velocity. Because it&amp;rsquo;s a script that will run every few minutes and then stop, RAM is less of an issue, and the official docker images https://hub.docker.com/_/python/ mean I don&amp;rsquo;t yet have to upgrade the ancient Ubuntu 18.04 on my VPS. Next thought was rather to spend this time writing. Zapier free tier is working fine for now, will get back to self-hosting it later. org-roam-node-find calls org-roam-node-read calls org-roam-node-read--completions calls org-roam-node-list, which always reads the full list of nodes from the sqlite database. Whyyyyy? When I do a semantic search using org-roam-similarity, I already have the small list of IDs. I only want to offer the user this small list, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to read the full list every time, and then remove everything except the list I already have &amp;ndash; so much wasted effort. I&amp;rsquo;m really hoping d12frosted&amp;rsquo;s vulpea has something better&amp;hellip; org-capture-template to create DHV after prompting for date ;; select region around your private day notes, then C-c c l (&amp;#34;l&amp;#34; &amp;#34;Lifelog&amp;#34; entry (file+olp+datetree lifelog-org) &amp;#34;* TODO Daily Head Voices on %&amp;lt;%A&amp;gt; %&amp;lt;%Y-%m-%d&amp;gt; :PROPERTIES: :EXPORT_FILE_NAME: index.md :EXPORT_HUGO_BUNDLE: lifelog-%&amp;lt;%Y%m%d&amp;gt; :EXPORT_HUGO_TAGS: lifelog :END: :LOGBOOK: - Created \&amp;#34;TODO\&amp;#34; %U :END: %i &amp;#34; ;; - with org 9.6.6 :time-prompt is only honoured when target is ;; &amp;#34;file+olp+datetree&amp;#34; ;; - I would have preferred just target &amp;#34;file&amp;#34; for this, but need ;; time-prompt as I often only create post after the day :empty-lines 1 :jump-to-captured &amp;#39;t :time-prompt &amp;#39;t :tree-type &amp;#39;month)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Religion is a culture of faith; science is a culture of doubt. &ndash; Richard Feynman</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Went to the beach at just after 11:00. Brilliant weather which for Betty&rsquo;s is quite special, so the place was absolutely packed.</li>
<li>Finally created <code>org-capture-template</code> to do the Daily Head Voices post setup more easily and more consistently, see below for the relevant element.</li>
<li>Thought a bit about writing and then self-hosting the tool that scans the cpbotha.net RSS feed and then performs actions, e.g. sending to Telegram, when new posts appear
<ul>
<li>Initial thought was Go, because small and self-contained (like my discord scihub bot and my eureka-alert RSS feed generator), but Python means much higher development velocity. Because it&rsquo;s a script that will run every few minutes and then stop, RAM is less of an issue, and the official docker images <a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/python/">https://hub.docker.com/_/python/</a> mean I don&rsquo;t yet have to upgrade the ancient Ubuntu 18.04 on my VPS.</li>
<li>Next thought was rather to spend this time writing. Zapier free tier is working fine for now, will get back to self-hosting it later.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><code>org-roam-node-find</code> calls <code>org-roam-node-read</code> calls <code>org-roam-node-read--completions</code> calls <code>org-roam-node-list</code>, which always reads the full list of nodes from the sqlite database. Whyyyyy? When I do a semantic search using <code>org-roam-similarity</code>, I already have the small list of IDs. I only want to offer the user this small list, I <strong>don&rsquo;t</strong> want to read the full list every time, and then remove everything except the list I already have &ndash; so much wasted effort. I&rsquo;m really hoping d12frosted&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/d12frosted/vulpea">vulpea</a> has something better&hellip;</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="org-capture-template-to-create-dhv-after-prompting-for-date">org-capture-template to create DHV after prompting for date</h2>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; select region around your private day notes, then C-c c l</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;l&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;Lifelog&#34;</span> <span style="color:#953800">entry</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">file+olp+datetree</span> <span style="color:#953800">lifelog-org</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;* TODO Daily Head Voices on %&lt;%A&gt; %&lt;%Y-%m-%d&gt;
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">:PROPERTIES:
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">:EXPORT_FILE_NAME: index.md
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">:EXPORT_HUGO_BUNDLE: lifelog-%&lt;%Y%m%d&gt;
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">:EXPORT_HUGO_TAGS: lifelog
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">:END:
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">:LOGBOOK:
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- Created \&#34;TODO\&#34; %U
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">:END:
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">%i
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#57606a">;; - with org 9.6.6 :time-prompt is only honoured when target is</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#57606a">;;   &#34;file+olp+datetree&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#57606a">;; - I would have preferred just target &#34;file&#34; for this, but need</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#57606a">;;   time-prompt as I often only create post after the day</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#6639ba">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">1</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">:jump-to-captured</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;t</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">:time-prompt</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;t</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">:tree-type</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;month</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div> ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #253: Weekend Warrior</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 16:38:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/</guid><description>Welcome back everyone!
It&amp;rsquo;s clear to me that I have to get back in the WHV saddle, but preaching sure is easier than practising, and so I thought it might be a good idea to try and bullet-list myself back into it.
(When I say &amp;ldquo;bullet-list&amp;rdquo; I mean &amp;ldquo;helpfully named hierarchical sections&amp;rdquo;, because Emacs tends to frown quite disapprovingly at mere bullet lists. Here I am after the intention of the bullet-list, namely to just get on with it.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s clear to me that I have to get back in the WHV saddle, but preaching sure
is easier than practising, and so I thought it might be a good idea to try and
<a href="/tags/bullet-lists/">bullet-list</a> myself back into it.</p>
<p>(When I say &ldquo;bullet-list&rdquo; I mean &ldquo;helpfully named hierarchical sections&rdquo;,
because <a href="/tags/emacs/">Emacs</a> tends to frown quite disapprovingly at mere bullet lists. Here I
am after the <em>intention</em> of the bullet-list, namely to <em>just get on with it</em>.)</p>










<figure><a href="bilthoven_manege.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_2e0173759a9b3934.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_1740715dbd8e6fe0.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_3893d5e642d52f69.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_31349c7dd6e8518e.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_1740715dbd8e6fe0.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Manege from a late summer stroll in NL. Smells, sounds, weather took me back so hard."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Manege from a late summer stroll in NL. Smells, sounds, weather took me back so hard.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It is important to mention that this post attempts to cover time up to
Wednesday, August 23, 2023.</p>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>My running habit has been steadily returning to its pre-op state, both in terms of
fitness but, more importantly, in terms of joy.</p>
<p>Also, my sixth pair of Altra Escalantes (version 3.0) recently arrived. I
wanted black ones, as I usually recycle old Altras after their recommended
700km or so into super comfortable office shoes, but my supplier was out of
stock and so I ended up with these surprisingly attractive blue and red ones:</p>










<figure><a href="altra_escalante_v3_no6.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/altra_escalante_v3_no6_hu_c8d1293b0b36ab.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/altra_escalante_v3_no6_hu_a5aea862418ea2ec.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/altra_escalante_v3_no6_hu_230eb4b8efe70307.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/altra_escalante_v3_no6_hu_a5aea862418ea2ec.jpg"
            

         width="50%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>In more good news, it turns out that it&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.webmd.com/fitness-exercise/news/20230719/your-heart-benefits-even-if-you-exercise-as-a-weekend-warrior">entirely OK if you spend all of your
minimum of 2.5 weekly hours of exercise during the weekend</a>.</p>
<p>Personally, I usually manage to fit in two shorter runs during the week, and a
longer run during the weekend, for a desired total of 25km per week, but I have
always wondered if it was in fact required to exercise on every day of the week
for maximal health benefit.</p>
<p>P.S. My main motivation is the unqualified joy of the run and not so much the
health benefits, although the benefits sure are nice!</p>
<p>P.P.S. <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#running">25km per week was my resolution for 2023</a>, but that plan was quite rudely
torpedoed by my <a href="/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/">prostate cancer adventure a few months ago</a>, so now I just try
to make it week by week.</p>
<h2 id="genai">GenAI</h2>
<p>For the past months, I&rsquo;ve been going deeper and deeper into generative AI, and
more specifically large language models (LLMs), down to the nuts and bolts and
let&rsquo;s-get-Llama-2-70-billion-quantized-and-running-on-my-PC levels.</p>
<p>Here are a few things that I really liked learning about:</p>
<ul>
<li>Although it has indeed been a longer journey, the current GenAI explosion /
hype seems to have been ignited in the third quarter of 2022, with the open
source release of Stable Diffusion in August, and the birth of ChatGPT in
November.</li>
<li>For the largest part, the most powerful LLMs have been trained, on hundreds
of billions to trillions of words, how to predict the next / missing word of
an incomplete document. After enough of this, they appear to gain some sort
of reasoning capability, including being able to answer theory of mind
questions.
<ul>
<li>There are striking similarities to how humans interpret speech.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Almost all of the currently famous models (Stable Diffusion, Whisper, all
current LLMs) are based on a specific type of neural network called a
Transformer, introduced in the paper <em>Attention Is All You Need</em>, published by
Ashish Vaswani and fellow Google researchers in 2017.</li>
</ul>
<p>For many more details about these, and other hopefully interesting
observations, please come to one of my GenAI talks!</p>
<p>GenAI developments are continuing at a truly impressive pace, and now I hope
that we (personally) can also start showing some practical and useful
applications!</p>
<p>P.S. Read the brilliant Lyn Alden&rsquo;s latest newsletter <a href="https://www.lynalden.com/august-2023-newsletter/">Six AI Themes to Consider</a>
in which she discusses how AIs (actually LLMs) are already starting to use
bitcoin (lightning) to pay for services (soon other AIs and also humans) in
order to complete their tasks.</p>
<h2 id="lowlands-2023">Lowlands 2023</h2>
<p>One could say that the WHV series owes its life to a certain 3-day festival in
the Netherlands as <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">it was born in the sweet afterglow of the 2009 edition</a>.</p>
<p>However, due to the strict WHALLSALL privacy policy, you will find only
<a href="/tags/lowlands/">pleasant echoes of the experience</a> in a number of posts on this blog.</p>
<p>This time it felt even more special, because it&rsquo;s the first time that I was
able to go since <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/">all the way back in 2019</a>.</p>
<p>I was pleasantly shocked by the warm <em>familiarity</em> of my other home, starting all
the way from the airport in Cape Town, joining hundreds of Dutchies returning
home after their vacations in SA, to arriving in NL and letting that lovely
language permeate my neural network, all through the festival chaos and
sometimes extremely close proximity to tens of thousands of locals, to walking
and cycling under the late summer sun, to spending the highest possible quality
time with my friends there.</p>
<p>Again I am left overflowing with gratitude.</p>
<p>Thank you other home, and eternal thank you friends!</p>
<h2 id="i-am-a-function">I am a function</h2>
<p>Back in <a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">WHV #70 from 2014</a>, based on some reading about the turnover of matter
in humans, I came to the following conclusion:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Now I see us all as nothing more than the continuously changing patterns that
form briefly in the grains of sand of the universe. Winds blow grains of sand
around, now taking part in one pattern and then in another. At some point, your
body has contained parts of your best friend, and of your worst enemy. The
patterns change continually; sometimes they fade away, and sometimes new
patterns emerge.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the intervening years, reader KvG first introduced me to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Watts">Alan Watts</a>, noting
that they saw similar themes in our writing.</p>
<p>I am wording it carefully here, as I obviously can&rsquo;t really compare my backyard
philosophical attempts to the work of Alan Watts, which I have now come to know
better.</p>
<p>That story was required to bring us to this, the concluding quote of this post:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You are a function of what the whole universe is doing in the same way that a
wave is a function of what the whole ocean is doing. &ndash; Alan Watts</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I really love that.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2022 to 2023 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 16:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2023 everyone, and to the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis
I wish all of you all of the best for this shiny new year twenty-twenty-three!
(By the way, this, the first day of the year, is the earliest that the yearly transition post has ever appeared!)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2023 everyone, and to the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="20221220-cape-st-francis-walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_9aeb90d9d01a11e9.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_8678af152961e9a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_d62854548d79e21e.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_4e0ce1b965a24760.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_8678af152961e9a.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I wish all of you all of the best for this shiny new year twenty-twenty-three!</p>
<p>(By the way, this, the first day of the year, is the earliest that the
yearly transition post has ever appeared!)</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Over the past year, I published fifteen posts on this blog, 14 of which were
&ldquo;weekly&rdquo; head voices posts (#237 to #250), and one <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/">the 2022 transition post</a>.</p>
<p>In an ideal world where I get to divide up my time between family and friends,
blogging, running and Emacs, I might be able to get close to the mythical 52
WHVs per year.</p>
<p>However, for me 2022 was definitely The Year of a Whole Lot of Work.</p>
<p>You might remember <a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">WHV #239 Embarrassing finitude</a>, in which I observed that you
only get to choose a really small number (probably only two: family and
friends, and one additional project) of significant priorities that you can
effectively contribute to over any given stretch of time.</p>
<p>I mostly remember that I&rsquo;ve made peace with this limitation, and I am realising
that (good) Work might be a crucial and substantial component of a long and
good life.</p>
<h3 id="some-stats">Some stats</h3>
<p>Invoking the goaccess log analysis tool using the incantation below reports that
this site was visited by just over 126 thousand unique visitor IP numbers in
the year up to December 27.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#6639ba">export</span> <span style="color:#953800">DOMAIN</span><span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>cpbotha.net
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0550ae">(</span><span style="color:#cf222e">for</span> i in <span style="color:#0550ae">{</span>1..11<span style="color:#0550ae">}</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">do</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> <span style="color:#953800">$DOMAIN</span>.access.log.<span style="color:#953800">$i</span>.gz<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">done</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> <span style="color:#953800">$DOMAIN</span>.access.log<span style="color:#0550ae">)</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> xargs zcat -f -- <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format<span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The most popular posts also over 2022 were the very old <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">2013 usa my data has
left your building</a>, the still quite relevant <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">2016 migrating from gmail to
fastmail</a> and my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">2019 note-taking strategy post</a>.</p>
<p>From this it&rsquo;s clear that I really have to get around to completing that
started-month-ago-but-languishing 202x note-taking strategy update, as my
system has evolved quite substantially.</p>
<p>I did also publish five posts on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>, this site&rsquo;s nerdy sibling, which
in its turn attracted just over 147 thousand unique visitor IPs over the year.</p>
<p>The most popular posts from vxlabs were the following, in descending order:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/06/12/typescript-development-with-emacs-tree-sitter-and-lsp-in-2022/">TypeScript development with Emacs, tree-sitter and LSP in 2022</a> - with
tree-sitter having been merged with Emacs core in the meantime, this post
also needs a substantial update. Emacs is developing faster than ever!</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/12/06/wsl2-io-measurements/">Comparing WSL1 and WSL2 filesystem I/O performance on local and host files</a> &ndash;
still reasonably accurate, still relevant.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/11/21/using-kubernetes-for-development-containers/">Using Kubernetes for development containers</a> - I&rsquo;m surprised that this is
relatively popular. I thought that it would be super niche.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="selected-learnings-from-2022">Selected learnings from 2022</h3>
<p>I went through all of 2022&rsquo;s WHVs to make an <em>extremely critical</em> (haha)
selection of learnings that bear mention in this yearly overview.</p>
<p>Because I think all of them are worthy of a retrospection, they are
chronologically ordered.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237 Don&rsquo;t step over the thing</a> &ndash; <em>We’re constantly stepping over the thing that
we think we’re seeking in the act of seeking it.</em> &hellip; <em>You can’t actually
become happy. You can only be happy.</em>
<ul>
<li>Related: <a href="/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/#take-a-picture-with-your-mind">WHV #247 Take a picture with your mind</a> &ndash; Your narrating self, the
one that needs to take all of those photos, can also take you out of the
thing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">WHV #239 Embarrassing finitude</a> &ndash; I&rsquo;m going to summarise that post section
here with &ldquo;pick your battles&rdquo;, or for the more poetically inclined readers
&ldquo;choose your f*cks&rdquo;. Our time is extremely limited - it is best to make
extremely deliberate and economical choices about the things that we spend
our time and energy on at any point.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/">WHV #242 Multiplicity of me</a> &ndash; If you skip everything else, read this
one. It&rsquo;s like &ldquo;happiness for dummies, in 24 hours&rdquo;.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/#part-time--role--model">WHV #243 Part-time role model</a> &ndash; Some motivation to never stop trying to be the
best you, also when, inevitably, you&rsquo;ll only have occasional success.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">WHV #246 Call up your friends</a> &ndash; Do call up that friend you&rsquo;re thinking
up. Write thank-you notes. Send birthday messages. Make the connection!</li>
<li><a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#self-discipline">WHV #249 Self-discipline</a> &ndash; Take care of this personal engine and it will
take you places.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/#happiness-is-a-joke">WHV #250 Durable, blissful contentment</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="quo-vadis-2023">Quo vadis 2023</h3>
<p>Writing on this here blog, and specifically the WHVs, is important to me for
the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>They enable learning, through retro- and introspection.</li>
<li>Each successful post is an exercise in applied and externalised self-discipline.</li>
<li>I enjoy practising the dying art of writing.</li>
<li>They help to form a connection with other humans, both friends and strangers.</li>
</ul>
<p>The reason for this retro-retrospection here, is that I am evaluating the
(smouldering) results and implications of the tension between post regularity
on the one hand, and self-perceived post substance on the other, over the past
year.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve erred on the side of post substance, when regularity might have been the
better option.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not that I was able to control it that deftly; what we have here is merely
the result of trying to publish posts of a reasonable quality at a reasonable
cadence.</p>
<p>My current feeling is that I would like to increase regularity, in spite of
past performance.</p>
<p>To make this happen, I have to learn to be satisfied with somewhat less, and
more importantly, I have to come up with improvements to my blogging workflow
that enable a more predictable flow of material.</p>
<p>A new year won&rsquo;t be a true new year without overly ambitious resolutions, now
will it?</p>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>This year, I averaged 20km of running per week for a total of 1044km (118 runs,
just under 99 hours) over the whole year.</p>
<p>Last year I did 25km per week, which is what I would have liked for this year
as well, but this is fine. <em>Any</em> kilometres are better than no kilometres!</p>










<figure>
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_51b4310156cb6775.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_9b2d56329fea834b.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_44ff53ded7296414.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_b6f0d925e5348190.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_9b2d56329fea834b.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Random drop-outs in graph below. At least finished strong in last week of year."/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Random drop-outs in graph below. At least finished strong in last week of year.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I did three quick spot checks in my daily journals to see if I could determine
any specific reasons for the low / no-exercise weeks, but nothing jumped out.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to have to blame work for this one too.</p>
<p>Anyways, what I <em>can</em> say, without any hesitation, is that running made a massive
positive contribution to my physical and mental well-being this year.</p>
<p>The effects can generally be immediately felt (that beautiful bit when it feels
like all one&rsquo;s limbs are finally working together, rhythmically even, is
exhilarating), and usually signal another start of a cascade of positive
physiological and life-style factors.</p>
<p>Running resolutions for 2023: 0) Much enjoy. 1) Don&rsquo;t get injured. 2) Try <em>again</em> for the 25km/w average.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>I really enjoyed the following books:</p>
<h3 id="fiction">Fiction</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/54906250-project-hail-mary">Project Hail Mary by Andy Weir</a> - feel good edge of seat stranded in space but
have to save the earth human-alien-buddy movie -book. Great for engineers who
know how to suspend disbelief.
<ul>
<li>I could not remember that I had ever bought this book, but enjoyed the
living daylights out of it. Only later discovered that it was GOU #1 (who
shares my Kindle account)! 🥰 we enjoyed the same book!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57357418-termination-shock">Termination Shock by Neal Stephenson</a> - this is such a disciplined, detailed,
diligent piece of science fiction by someone who clearly has <em>practised</em> this
art and honed their craft to perfection. I enjoyed the story (it does require
some reader stamina) and appreciated the massive skills of the artist.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/#permutation-city">Permutation City by Greg Egan</a> - click on the link to the left to go to my
mini-review in WHV #240.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="non-fiction">Non-fiction</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/#projections">Projections: A Story of Human Emotions by Karl Deisseroth</a> - click on the link
to the left to go to my mini-review in WHV #244.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59516276-the-unseen-body">The Unseen
Body: A Doctor&rsquo;s Journey Through the Hidden Wonders of Human Anatomy by
Jonathan Reisman</a> - Join the doctor on a fascinating journey through each
and every organ in the human body, robustly spiced by his stories of travels
to some of the most remote corners of the globe, and of his experience
various medical emergencies.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="resolutions">Resolutions</h3>
<p>Somewhere in the second half of 2022, I somehow lost my <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#reading">reading-before-sleep
habit</a>.</p>
<p>I plan to reinstate this habit, and to install the new habit of reading more
books on my phone (vs being limited to my Kindle, which is not always with me).</p>
<p>Armed with these two life-hacks, I hope to finish reading 20 books in 2023.</p>
<p>Please send me your recommendations in the comments below!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human">Systems and tools for running this human</h2>
<p>As per tradition, I quote from previous transition posts my explanation of &ldquo;The
System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Similar to <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">last year</a>, Emacs, Orgmode and Org-roam are still going very strong,
and constitute the lion&rsquo;s share of my personal knowledge management system.</p>
<p>In fact, with the imminent Emacs 29 release, a recent build of which I&rsquo;m typing
this draft into (English is hard folks&hellip;), Emacs has only become <em>more</em>
compelling.</p>
<p>Amongst <a href="https://blog.phundrak.com/emacs-29-what-can-we-expect">many other improvements</a>, tree-sitter, eglot and use-package are now all
part of core.</p>
<h3 id="byeeeeee-dropbox">Byeeeeee Dropbox!</h3>
<p>However&hellip;</p>
<p>The time has finally come for me to drop (again) Dropbox.</p>
<p>Although I have been a paying customer for many years (see <a href="/2010/02/28/weekly-head-voices-15-auto-tune-my-cloud/">WHV #15</a> from
February of 2010 for a report close to the start of our commercial
relationship), in the end it was their intransigence and inscrutability around
the Dropbox Paper 2020 migration that broke the camel&rsquo;s back.</p>
<p>They have been promising since before 2020 that they would migrate all existing
users to the new 2020 edition of Dropbox Paper.</p>
<p>However, now all you can find about this are frustrated forum posts from
long-time customers. My direct support request to be migrated was promptly
answered, and then closed with the following message:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As much as I would like to help, currently, the latest version of Paper release
is available to new users only.</p>
<p>Our team is currently in the process of working on this new feature in order to
build the best Paper experience for all our users.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I still really love that tool (winner of the WHV Award for the Most
Unexpectedly Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021!), but the interaction above
only served as a reminder of the pitfalls of a relationship like this.</p>
<p>During the writing of my yet-to-appear 202x note-taking approach blog post, it
bugged me that I had to come up with a good explanation for why I allowed
Dropbox Paper to break my rule of everything-needs-to-be-a-file-I-could-sync.</p>
<p>Although my yearly Dropbox Paper subscription is only up for renewal in June of
&lsquo;23, I decided to bite the bullet and <a href="/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/#hell-freezes-over--again">migrate everything out to an extremely
frightening mix of OneDrive, syncthing and unison</a>.</p>
<p>As I write this, it&rsquo;s been just over two months with nary a hiccup.</p>
<p>In June, I&rsquo;ll let that Dropbox subscription lapse.</p>
<p>Dropbox Paper, RIP.</p>
<p>(With <a href="https://1writerapp.com/">1writer</a> and also <a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> on the iPhone, and <a href="https://syncthing.net/">syncthing</a> on my main desktop
at home, plus Apple Notes for the truly ephemeral stuff, I have a pretty
capable mobile response to Paper.)</p>
<h3 id="resolutions">Resolutions</h3>
<ol>
<li>I would really like to publish a blog post titled <em>Note-taking approach
2023</em>. Ideally, it should be full of information about my current PKM system.</li>
<li>Write more notes, including both journals and <a href="/tags/zettelkasten/">Zettelkasten-style</a> notes.</li>
<li>Stretch goal: Maybe get another useful patch into Emacs.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>2022 was my first year back in employment, after <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">eight years of freelancing</a>.</p>
<p>In this year, I have only become more deeply involved and invested in the
current <a href="https://stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> adventure.</p>
<p>As I mentioned previously, I have the privilege of working closely together
with extremely capable folks, in a high-trust setting.</p>
<p>Many of my colleagues are smarter than I am in their respective fields. Due to
that, and the fact that we are both growing and innovating, I am constantly
learning.</p>
<p>My personal responsibilities span the spectrum from programming, through
mentor- and leadership to management and org-level technical decisions. On the
other dimension, I am exposed to everything from software plumbing to data
science, engineering and visualization. (This is what&rsquo;s known as a
PiM-situation. PiM = pig in mud)</p>
<p>The work is hard, but it&rsquo;s varied, it&rsquo;s challenging, it&rsquo;s together with a group
of humans I like, and it feels meaningful.</p>
<p>I have written all these words to try and explain that although it&rsquo;s clear from
this post that Work(tm) took up significantly more time and space this year, it
has contributed substantially to my well-being.</p>
<p>Freelancing was less stressful &ndash; I could focus on the engineering tasks at
hand and usually deliver. Now I have more responsibility, which brings
substantially more stress but also more satisfaction.</p>
<p>Furthermore, in terms of maintaining the plasticity of my neural network,
something I do have to pay more and more attention to thanks to the advancing
years, the variation and challenges of my current work setting are great.</p>
<p>That being said, I definitely have to get better at controlling stress.</p>
<h2 id="things-i-would-like-to-work-on-in-2023">Things I would like to work on in 2023</h2>
<p>In addition to the blogging, running, reading and systems resolutions mentioned
above, I would like to work on the following bigger themes in 2023:</p>
<ol>
<li>Work(tm).</li>
<li>Self-discipline, <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#self-discipline">as featured in WHV #249</a>. I will implement this by writing
really stern messages to me in my diary.</li>
<li>Creating, restoring and maintaining good habits that <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a>: Reading,
writing, running, mindfulness practice.</li>
</ol>
<p>&hellip; and then finally, my central theme for 2023 will be:</p>
<h3 id="4-dot-expansiveness">4. Expansiveness</h3>
<p>Sometimes, most probably when you&rsquo;re out in nature, you experience your senses
really opening up.</p>
<p>It is as if the usually clearly defined borders between you and your
surroundings start to fade away.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve talked about this phenomenon before, in <a href="/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/#the-strange-continuum-of-consciousness">WHV #217&rsquo;s The Strange Continuum
of Consciousness</a> and in other places.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a great feeling, and it usually happens when you are fully present in that
moment.</p>
<p>For a while, you can get pleasantly lost in the infinite and fractal detail in
the moment and its participants.</p>
<p>For a while, you can truly appreciate the beauty of your surroundings, of the food
and drink you might be enjoying, and of the humans in your company.</p>
<p>In 2023, let us be expansive!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #247: Precious moments</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 22:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/</guid><description>Welcome back friends!
This post attempts to cover the longer thann normal period of time from Monday September 26 to Sunday October 30, 2022.
Figure 1: This is what the view looks like just after a lunch at Pearl View Guest House, which itself with spectacular views.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends!</p>
<p>This post attempts to cover the longer thann normal period of time from Monday
September 26 to Sunday October 30, 2022.</p>










<figure><a href="knysna-heads.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_c8238dc56f0e3de0.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_acc7684da5d46e95.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_f46a88b64faaa876.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_870583e22b4106b8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/knysna-heads_hu_acc7684da5d46e95.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: This is what the view looks like just after a lunch at Pearl View Guest House, which itself with spectacular views."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>This is what the view looks like just after a lunch at Pearl View Guest House, which itself with spectacular views.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This is the year of me struggling to make the time and the energy to write
these posts. Between work (it&rsquo;s never been this truly busy before), family
(teenagers man) and other important activities, this previously
straight-forward endeavour has become really challenging.</p>
<p>I currently have no cunning plans to remedy this issue, except to keep on
trying.</p>
<p>Anyways, my main goal with this post below morphed from &ldquo;try to write a good
post&rdquo; to &ldquo;<em>any</em> post is better than no post&rdquo;, and so it is entirely possible that
you&rsquo;ll notice some unevenness.</p>
<h2 id="wilderness-energy">Wilderness Energy</h2>
<p>So after a number of paragraphs complaining about how little free time I have
at my disposal, I shall now briefly talk about our October family break-away to
the East coast!</p>
<p>As we often do, we decided to break the road-trip in two, staying for the night
in Wilderness, literally one of my favourite places on the planet.</p>
<p>As we don&rsquo;t often do, this time we stayed an extra night because the weather,
and that balmy Wilderness energy (it sounds like a pretty hip caffeinated
drink) were simply too amazing to pass up.</p>
<p>During our surprise extra day:</p>
<ul>
<li>I ran the Waterside dirt road next to the Serpentine river, in the direction of
Hoekwil. I love running dirt roads, and this one is high up on the list.</li>
<li>We (6 famjam + 1 friend) did the canoe trip at Kaaimanskloof, something that
we&rsquo;ve always dreamed about, to the waterfall, to the train bridge and later
up the river all the way to the bend right below the Map of Africa lookout,
far up above. I shared a canoe with my most favourite middle child in the
world, aka GOU #2. (We also won the race back, even beating out the far more
energetic canoe powered by GOU #1 and her friend, by applying a certain
degree of crystallized-intelligence-guided strategy.)</li>
<li>We squeezed in a beach day.</li>
<li>We went up to Map of Africa to enjoy the brilliant sunset.</li>
</ul>
<p>After all of that I was a bit worried that we had set the pace of the whole
week, the sustaining of which I would probably not have survived.</p>
<p>Fortunately the continuation of our vacation in St Francis was, whilst <em>quite</em>
active, an energetically more sustainable affair, consisting of balmy weather,
family beach days, and zen-inducing sunsets.</p>
<p>Personally, I will <em>remember</em> this week as a great example of How To Holiday.</p>










<figure><a href="st-francis-bay-canals.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_2636366ec22c5c37.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_b307460b68aefcdf.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_5771a46dd0d8be48.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_8666c277feba0dec.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/st-francis-bay-canals_hu_b307460b68aefcdf.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View of the canals in St Francis Bay, the village 7km to the North of Cape St Francis."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>View of the canals in St Francis Bay, the village 7km to the North of Cape St Francis.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="goldilocks-water-for-your-moka-pot">Goldilocks water for your Moka pot</h2>
<p>At home, we rely on our <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#coffee-machine-reincarnation">trusty (new) Saeco bean-to-cup</a> machine to keep us
continously and quite fully coffee-nated.</p>
<p>However, because there is no space for Saeco on our travels, we require a
mobile, preferably compact, coffee production modality.</p>
<p>This used to be the giant coffee syringe, also known as Aeropress, which I
wrote about in <a href="/2014/07/22/weekly-head-voices-78-aeroimpressed/">WHV #78, back in 2014</a>.</p>
<p>It makes really great tasting coffee, but it can feel a little clinical.</p>
<p>More recently, as we became older (a tenacious process that never seems to stop
until the end, I am told) and our appreciation for the slower, more deliberate
rituals of life grew, we decided to switch to a Bialetti Moka pot instead.</p>
<p>You would probably recognise it. It&rsquo;s that distinctive little aluminium pot
with the octagonal base and the friendly picture on the side.</p>
<p>Instead of the one minute stir, one minute push through of the Aeropress, this
artifact sits there on its hob for about five minutes when it magically fills
up with lovely espresso.</p>
<p>(Of course it&rsquo;s not magic, it&rsquo;s just <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moka_pot">Mr Alfonso Bialetti&rsquo;s brilliant
engineering from 1933</a>!)</p>
<p>Here is our Moka pot, this time posing in <a href="/tags/stilbaai/">Stilbaai</a>, another one of my favourite
vacation destinations:</p>










<figure><a href="stilbaai-moka.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_3bafdd46cb5bf89c.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_bc0795b9133db5d8.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_ca37d8803312a579.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_84eada315ce75bc9.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/stilbaai-moka_hu_bc0795b9133db5d8.jpg"
            

         width="320px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>More recently, I chatted with friend PH at work about the ideal starting
temperature for the fresh water in one&rsquo;s Moka.</p>
<p>I had naively always preferred to start with cold water, to emulate the camping
situation, but work-friend explained that he had understood warm water to be
better for the taste.</p>
<p>I had never considered this before. Doh!</p>
<p>(Later I learned from mutual friend SvdW that they had in fact previously
studied Moka pot temperature in detail during a work trip, an experience
perhaps partially forgotten by friend PH.)</p>
<p>Serendipitously, during a meeting later that afternoon with colleagues from the
US, one of our collaborators, sporting a pretty relevant scientific background,
explained that <em>he</em> had understood (in Fahrenheit, we had to translate) that 60
°C resulted in the best coffee extraction.</p>
<p>This obviously piqued my curiousity, quite intensely, and so I went searching
that evening&hellip;</p>
<p>Imagine my delight when I ran into <a href="http://www.msc.univ-paris-diderot.fr/~phyexp/uploads/Moka/article1.pdf"><em>The physics of a stove-top espresso
machine</em></a>, a 2008 scientific article by Dr Warren D. King in the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1119/1.2870524"><em>American
Journal of Physics</em>, vol. 76, no. 6, pp. 558–565</a>, in which he documents his
mathematical modeling and experiments showing that the optimal starting
temperature for the water in a Moka pot is in fact 70 °C!</p>
<p>The short version of the story is that this will result in most of the water
going through the coffee grounds, when extraction takes place, at about 95
°C, which results in the most  flavour.</p>
<p>If you start with cold water, extraction will happen at 70 °C, which is
too low, and if you start with hot water, it will go through the grounds at too
high a temperature, resulting in bitter coffee.</p>
<h2 id="take-a-picture-with-your-mind">Take a picture with your mind</h2>
<!-- The title of this section is due to friend PK. You have to say it in his voice, "take a picture with your miiii-iiiiind!" -->
<p>Back in <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#multiplicity-of-you">WHV #242 I talked about the remembering (narrating) self, and the
experiencing self</a>. (Please read that section if you have not yet. In fact, I
think that the whole of WHV #242 could be worth your time.)</p>
<p>Kahnemann&rsquo;s poignant quote bears repeating here:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Odd as it may seem, I am my remembering self, and the experiencing self, who
does my living, is like a stranger to me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just the other day, in the middle of a perfect run on the beach, with a breeze
that was just <em>so</em>, the sun all golden and ready to set, and with my bare feet
connecting with the sand and the earth beneath it, it felt like a full sensory
connect, experiencing self for once fully in control.</p>
<p>It was perfect, until I felt this superficially pretty reasonable urge to take
a photo, just a little something to remember the perfect moment by&hellip;</p>
<p>At that instant, I saw it for what it was &ndash; sneaky, remembering self
attempting to hijack the moment, and take it away from experiencing self, the
one who at that moment was generating by far the most positive energy.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We wants it, we needs it. Must have the precious. They stole it from us. Sneaky
little hobbitses. Wicked, tricksy, false! &ndash; JRR Tolkien</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The desire to remember the perfect moment is understandable, but there is a
cost: The moment itself.</p>
<p>Resist the urge.</p>
<p>Love,<br />
Remembering Self</p>










<figure><a href="cape-st-francis-light-house.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_97ddb7d8d1f7c08b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_b9a76019323c2de.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_f7a6964a6a668463.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_9b3e177a9240de5c.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/cape-st-francis-light-house_hu_b9a76019323c2de.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: The light house in Cape St Francis, the village 7km to the South of St Francis Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>The light house in Cape St Francis, the village 7km to the South of St Francis Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #242: Multiplicity of me</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 20:51:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</guid><description>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.
If you like backyard philosophy, you&amp;rsquo;re in the right place.
Even if you only like bullet lists, you&amp;rsquo;re going to be ok.
Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from
Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.</p>
<p>If you like backyard philosophy, you&rsquo;re in the right place.</p>
<p>Even if you only like bullet lists, you&rsquo;re going to be ok.</p>










<figure><a href="afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_41bd9f5429550d06.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_cd29c721e76c2270.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_968c3008cb01b577.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_454f8c3e3a4ec58f.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_cd29c721e76c2270.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo by friend WvdL.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="learning-at-the-burning">Learning at the Burning</h2>
<p>There&rsquo;s an unwritten rule that you should not make any life decisions for at
least three weeks after the (Afrika)Burn.</p>
<p>Apparently people have, inspired by the sometimes weird experiences of the
event, made some major but unfortunately quite regrettable decisions in its
afterglow.</p>
<p>Anyways, I did not come back with anything like that.</p>
<p>Without sounding (too much) like Zaphod eating the fairy cake powering the
Total Perspective Vortex and walking away pretty much unscathed, through the
week&rsquo;s ups (mostly) and downs I learned a bunch, and I did come back with some
internal changes, but they were at their most extreme a strong reminder (kick
in the butt might even be appropriate) of a partially buried perspective or
two.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it is now exactly three weeks after the thing, and although that
dusty afterglow has definitely waned, it feels like I&rsquo;ve just merged back into
reality without any major incidents, just a slight tweak (or gentle kick in the
butt) here and there, for the better.</p>
<p>(Because inquiring minds might want to know, yes, we again brought the
BURNIVERSITY. We&rsquo;re probably one of the smallest theme camps, but we were
intense, and it feels like our interactions were too.)</p>
<p>Anyways, here are some completely random words, some of them loosely based (or
not at all, or something in between) on a recent conversation with friend PK,
and some of them from friend DW:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA</a> is a good framework for your well-being, and that of your loved ones:
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion</li>
<li>Engagement</li>
<li>Relationships</li>
<li>Meaning</li>
<li>Accomplishment</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>That thing you&rsquo;re stressing about is most probably not worth such a high
personal cost, and health-risk.</li>
<li>Just do the work.</li>
<li><a href="https://typesense.org/blog/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-just-showing-up-everyday/">Just showing up every day is a super power</a>. Pick your thing(s), show up to
them every single day, profit.</li>
<li>Chopping onions is the physical manifestation of your love for the people for
whom you are cooking. Give it (chopping onions, making food, loving) your
<em>whole</em> attention, and see what happens. Thank you DW, for this wisdom, and
for the food.
<ul>
<li>(Dear reader, between you and me, man that guy was burning so bright&hellip;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Practice will boost your powers of attention. This will deeply improve you,
and how you interact with others.</li>
<li>Kindness is still the most important super power.</li>
<li>Check up on yourself every day, about all of these completely random words.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="multiplicity-of-you">Multiplicity of you</h2>
<p><a href="/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/#homo-deus">In 2018, I talked about <em>Homo Deus</em></a>, a book by Yuval Harari in which he
discusses several thought-provoking ideas, one of which I highlighted then and
would like to discuss again now:</p>
<p>Your experience of being a single identity, a single <em>I</em>, is most probably an
illusion, as your brain most probably houses more &ldquo;me&quot;s than you would think.</p>
<p>Research by the Nobel prize-winner Daniel Kahneman and his various
collaborators showed that we house at the very least two major selves, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow#Two_selves">namely
the remembering / narrating self and the experiencing self</a>.</p>
<p>The experiencing self is the one who actually does the living and the
<em>experiencing</em> of each moment, while the narrating self is the one who
continuously stitches together your whole story, often bending the truth to fit
its (your) opinions of yourself and those around you.</p>
<p>The narrating self is the one who dominates, for better or for worse.</p>
<p>Kahnemann himself pointed out the irony of this the best:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Odd as it may seem, I am my remembering self, and the experiencing self, who
does my living, is like a stranger to me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(You might have heard of <a href="https://positivepsychology.com/what-is-peak-end-theory/">Peak-End Theory</a>, or the phenomenon that humans tend to
judge an experience based largley on the single peak moment, and on how they
felt at the end. You can thank your remembering self for this, and you can
imagine how this could really complicate your decision making.)</p>
<p>Harari discusses Kahneman&rsquo;s selves, but continues into more research with
people who for various reasons have separated brain hemispheres.</p>
<p>When you show one brain hemisphere one version of reality, and the other
another, it is as if there are multiple narrating selves in the same person who
come up with stories that they are convinced are the truth, although in this
case these stories conflict diametrically with other thanks to the design of
the experiment.</p>
<p>From this and other data, Harari concludes that humans generally house multiple
identities.</p>
<p>What I want to to get at, is that it helps to remember (always) that &ldquo;you&rdquo; are
in fact a collection of sometimes competing &ldquo;you&quot;s.</p>
<p>As if that were not challenging enough, your narrating self takes
responsibility for all of these feelings, and tries to weave it all into a
consistent story, although that is often extremely difficult or even
impossible.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.samharris.org/blog/the-illusion-of-the-self2">an 2012 interview with Sam Harris</a>, Bruce Hood had the following to say about
this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>By rejecting the notion of a core self and considering how we are a multitude
of competing urges and impulses, I think it is easier to understand why we
suddenly go off the rails. It explains why we act, often unconsciously, in a
way that is inconsistent with our self image &ndash; or the image of our self as we
believe others see us.</p>
<p>That said, the self illusion is probably an inescapable experience we need for
interacting with others and the world, and indeed we cannot readily abandon or
ignore its influence, but we should be skeptical that each of us is the
coherent, integrated entity we assume we are.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because this thought has become much more prominent for me in quite a positive
way, I would like to take it even further, by reminding you to practise
reminding yourself of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Although your perception is generally tied to your narrating self (the one
that&rsquo;s going to remember this blog post), the complete &ldquo;you&rdquo; in fact
constitutes the whole playing field, the consciousness and its physical
medium, in which <em>all</em> of these selves live and move around. In the words of
Harris, &ldquo;you can drop back into that&rdquo; and just <em>be</em> the consciousness, <em>be</em> that
which contains it all.</li>
<li>While your own selves truly live in this conciousness, high definition
versions of your surroundings and everyone you interact with are also
running in this same (your) neural network.
<ul>
<li>This means that you have a surprising amount of control of how you
experience life.</li>
<li>When you hear a dog barking, this is really nothing more than clusters of
neurons firing in your brain, but you visualize the dog <em>over there</em>. When
you feel the wind blowing over your skin, there&rsquo;s just another set of
neurons firing not far away from the barking dog. It&rsquo;s all inside your
head, and the borders between &ldquo;inside&rdquo; and &ldquo;outside&rdquo; are far more blurry
than you might think.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>All of your selves are <em>you</em>. Treat them like you would a group of your closest
friends. You can hold them up to the group&rsquo;s standards, but you have to
forgive, and you have to be kind.</li>
</ul>
<p>Folks, I wish you all (and all the yous), and all of your people, peace and
love.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>