<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>backyard philosophy on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/backyard-philosophy/</link><description>Recent content in backyard philosophy on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 20:51:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/backyard-philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #242: Multiplicity of me</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 20:51:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</guid><description> This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.
If you like backyard philosophy, you&amp;rsquo;re in the right place.
Even if you only like bullet lists, you&amp;rsquo;re going to be ok.
Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL.
Learning at the Burning There&amp;rsquo;s an unwritten rule that you should not make any life decisions for at least three weeks after the (Afrika)Burn.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from
Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.</p>
<p>If you like backyard philosophy, you&rsquo;re in the right place.</p>
<p>Even if you only like bullet lists, you&rsquo;re going to be ok.</p>








<figure><a href="afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu7277cd24f1de9911fddc15a072d08f47_9215095_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo by friend WvdL.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="learning-at-the-burning">Learning at the Burning</h2>
<p>There&rsquo;s an unwritten rule that you should not make any life decisions for at
least three weeks after the (Afrika)Burn.</p>
<p>Apparently people have, inspired by the sometimes weird experiences of the
event, made some major but unfortunately quite regrettable decisions in its
afterglow.</p>
<p>Anyways, I did not come back with anything like that.</p>
<p>Without sounding (too much) like Zaphod eating the fairy cake powering the
Total Perspective Vortex and walking away pretty much unscathed, through the
week&rsquo;s ups (mostly) and downs I learned a bunch, and I did come back with some
internal changes, but they were at their most extreme a strong reminder (kick
in the butt might even be appropriate) of a partially buried perspective or
two.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it is now exactly three weeks after the thing, and although that
dusty afterglow has definitely waned, it feels like I&rsquo;ve just merged back into
reality without any major incidents, just a slight tweak (or gentle kick in the
butt) here and there, for the better.</p>
<p>(Because inquiring minds might want to know, yes, we again brought the
BURNIVERSITY. We&rsquo;re probably one of the smallest theme camps, but we were
intense, and it feels like our interactions were too.)</p>
<p>Anyways, here are some completely random words, some of them loosely based (or
not at all, or something in between) on a recent conversation with friend PK,
and some of them from friend DW:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA</a> is a good framework for your well-being, and that of your loved ones:
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion</li>
<li>Engagement</li>
<li>Relationships</li>
<li>Meaning</li>
<li>Accomplishment</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>That thing you&rsquo;re stressing about is most probably not worth such a high
personal cost, and health-risk.</li>
<li>Just do the work.</li>
<li><a href="https://typesense.org/blog/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-just-showing-up-everyday/">Just showing up every day is a super power</a>. Pick your thing(s), show up to
them every single day, profit.</li>
<li>Chopping onions is the physical manifestation of your love for the people for
whom you are cooking. Give it (chopping onions, making food, loving) your
<em>whole</em> attention, and see what happens. Thank you DW, for this wisdom, and
for the food.
<ul>
<li>(Dear reader, between you and me, man that guy was burning so bright&hellip;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Practice will boost your powers of attention. This will deeply improve you,
and how you interact with others.</li>
<li>Kindness is still the most important super power.</li>
<li>Check up on yourself every day, about all of these completely random words.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="multiplicity-of-you">Multiplicity of you</h2>
<p><a href="/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/#homo-deus">In 2018, I talked about <em>Homo Deus</em></a>, a book by Yuval Harari in which he
discusses several thought-provoking ideas, one of which I highlighted then and
would like to discuss again now:</p>
<p>Your experience of being a single identity, a single <em>I</em>, is most probably an
illusion, as your brain most probably houses more &ldquo;me&quot;s than you would think.</p>
<p>Research by the Nobel prize-winner Daniel Kahneman and his various
collaborators showed that we house at the very least two major selves, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow#Two_selves">namely
the remembering / narrating self and the experiencing self</a>.</p>
<p>The experiencing self is the one who actually does the living and the
<em>experiencing</em> of each moment, while the narrating self is the one who
continuously stitches together your whole story, often bending the truth to fit
its (your) opinions of yourself and those around you.</p>
<p>The narrating self is the one who dominates, for better or for worse.</p>
<p>Kahnemann himself pointed out the irony of this the best:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Odd as it may seem, I am my remembering self, and the experiencing self, who
does my living, is like a stranger to me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(You might have heard of <a href="https://positivepsychology.com/what-is-peak-end-theory/">Peak-End Theory</a>, or the phenomenon that humans tend to
judge an experience based largley on the single peak moment, and on how they
felt at the end. You can thank your remembering self for this, and you can
imagine how this could really complicate your decision making.)</p>
<p>Harari discusses Kahneman&rsquo;s selves, but continues into more research with
people who for various reasons have separated brain hemispheres.</p>
<p>When you show one brain hemisphere one version of reality, and the other
another, it is as if there are multiple narrating selves in the same person who
come up with stories that they are convinced are the truth, although in this
case these stories conflict diametrically with other thanks to the design of
the experiment.</p>
<p>From this and other data, Harari concludes that humans generally house multiple
identities.</p>
<p>What I want to to get at, is that it helps to remember (always) that &ldquo;you&rdquo; are
in fact a collection of sometimes competing &ldquo;you&quot;s.</p>
<p>As if that were not challenging enough, your narrating self takes
responsibility for all of these feelings, and tries to weave it all into a
consistent story, although that is often extremely difficult or even
impossible.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.samharris.org/blog/the-illusion-of-the-self2">an 2012 interview with Sam Harris</a>, Bruce Hood had the following to say about
this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>By rejecting the notion of a core self and considering how we are a multitude
of competing urges and impulses, I think it is easier to understand why we
suddenly go off the rails. It explains why we act, often unconsciously, in a
way that is inconsistent with our self image &ndash; or the image of our self as we
believe others see us.</p>
<p>That said, the self illusion is probably an inescapable experience we need for
interacting with others and the world, and indeed we cannot readily abandon or
ignore its influence, but we should be skeptical that each of us is the
coherent, integrated entity we assume we are.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because this thought has become much more prominent for me in quite a positive
way, I would like to take it even further, by reminding you to practise
reminding yourself of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Although your perception is generally tied to your narrating self (the one
that&rsquo;s going to remember this blog post), the complete &ldquo;you&rdquo; in fact
constitutes the whole playing field, the consciousness and its physical
medium, in which <em>all</em> of these selves live and move around. In the words of
Harris, &ldquo;you can drop back into that&rdquo; and just <em>be</em> the consciousness, <em>be</em> that
which contains it all.</li>
<li>While your own selves truly live in this conciousness, high definition
versions of your surroundings and everyone you interact with are also
running in this same (your) neural network.
<ul>
<li>This means that you have a surprising amount of control of how you
experience life.</li>
<li>When you hear a dog barking, this is really nothing more than clusters of
neurons firing in your brain, but you visualize the dog <em>over there</em>. When
you feel the wind blowing over your skin, there&rsquo;s just another set of
neurons firing not far away from the barking dog. It&rsquo;s all inside your
head, and the borders between &ldquo;inside&rdquo; and &ldquo;outside&rdquo; are far more blurry
than you might think.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>All of your selves are <em>you</em>. Treat them like you would a group of your closest
friends. You can hold them up to the group&rsquo;s standards, but you have to
forgive, and you have to be kind.</li>
</ul>
<p>Folks, I wish you all (and all the yous), and all of your people, peace and
love.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #241: Best intentions</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 22:05:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/</guid><description> Welcome back folks to the Weekly Head Voices!
Edition 241 (this one) covers the four weeks from Monday March 21 to Sunday April 17 of the year 2022.
This time, my excuse for being so late is our autumn vacation trip to Augrabies and the Kgalagagi Transfrontier park.
The Knersvlakte-Augrabies-Kgalagadi-Calvinia vacation trip The super short summary is as follows:
My extremely resourceful partner had managed to book a few nights in rest camps in Kgalagadi about a year ago.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks to the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>Edition 241 (this one) covers the four weeks from Monday March 21 to Sunday
April 17 of the year 2022.</p>
<p><em>This</em> time, my excuse for being so late is our autumn vacation trip to Augrabies
and the Kgalagagi Transfrontier park.</p>








<figure><a href="augrabies-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu071790dcf2447618c4dba76f9e592767_994406_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-knersvlakte-augrabies-kgalagadi-calvinia-vacation-trip">The Knersvlakte-Augrabies-Kgalagadi-Calvinia vacation trip</h2>
<p>The super short summary is as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>My extremely resourceful partner had managed to book a few nights in rest
camps in Kgalagadi about a year ago. That&rsquo;s generally how early you need to
be for this.</li>
<li>As the vacation came closer, we accidentally configured a really cool road
trip (&ldquo;sloertoer&rdquo; as I recently learned) to sandwich the Kgalagadi bit in the
middle.
<ul>
<li>On the way there, we stayed at <a href="https://letsatsi.ncfamouslodges.com/">Letsatsi Lodge in Vanrhynsdorp</a>, and we spent
two nights at the Augrabies falls. The falls were absolutely
spectacular. Besides the panorama above, <a href="https://youtu.be/DW8SFHUP_18">this clip</a> of the falls at sunset
should give you a taste of what we experienced.
<ul>
<li>On the last night, our braai was attacked by a swarm of locusts. This was
so intense that the rest of the clan had to move indoors. I remained
outside with the braai and the locusts, witnessing thousands of the
beasts burn themselves up in the flames.
<ul>
<li>This event seemed like a great excuse to look up the difference between
grasshoppers and locusts. Maybe you already knew this, but I did
not. Grasshoppers <em>transform</em> into locusts. The transformation is both
physical, modulated by serotonin (which is also a super important
neurotransmitter in humans) and social; grasshoppers are loners, while
locusts are born, live and die as a swarm.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>On the journey&rsquo;s final leg back home from Nossob, we spent a night in the
Blou Nartjie in Calvinia.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Kgalagadi was magic.
<ul>
<li>On the one morning where we were able to get up early enough to exit as the
Tweerivieren gates opened (this is The Way), we were lucky enough to spend
some close-up alone time with two cheetah close to Kamfersboom. Ironically,
this happened much later in the morning as we were on our way back to the
camp. You never know&hellip;</li>
<li>On other drives we spotted lion, leopard (lazing in a tree, a lot further
away than the cheetah who were almost at touching distance), springbok,
lots of gemsbok (surprise!), meerkat and fox.</li>
<li>The balmy evenings outside, with intensely brilliant starry skies, were
unexpectedly good.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>








<figure><a href="kgalagadi-tfp-sign.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hua1f48337906a4fdbacd477fcc942e2df_1525223_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Red Karahari sand!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Red Karahari sand!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-period-after-the-trip">The period after the trip</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m writing this sentence here during the last few hours of the Easter weekend.</p>
<p>As I wrote in my mostly private and personal diary this morning: &ldquo;Man, these
days were really good for a reset, spending time on meta-work (emacs config,
planning config, and so on) and family.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(On the topic of keeping diaries and on the topic of deciding to publish some
of the private bits, here is another extract: &ldquo;Reviewing the past 4 weeks of
notes for hopefully soon-to-be-published WHV 241 also reminded me of so many
bits of peace and wisdom. I&rsquo;ve said this before, it&rsquo;s like I&rsquo;m up and down the
scale of human, and the high performing / balanced human needs to write
encouraging messages to the more frequently active normal / inferior me.&rdquo;)</p>
<p>Moving on&hellip;</p>
<p>In the time since the vacation trip, I&rsquo;ve been exceptionally privileged and
grateful to have a small selection of close friends visit in various
configurations.</p>
<p>In some cases I could offer only my ears although I desperately wanted to help
more, and in other cases they were less complicated life-affirming
celebrations.</p>
<p>In all cases, this is what I&rsquo;m here for.</p>
<p>(Later, I would really like to talk more about how easily and how often I
manage to forget that when I get caught up stress.)</p>
<h2 id="a-smidgen-of-nerd-news">A smidgen of nerd news</h2>
<p>It turns out that my <a href="/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/#new-diagramming-tool-of-the-insert-suitable-period-here">favourite quickly-sketch-out-your-idea tool excalidraw</a> is
a cinch to run locally, if you already have node and yarn installed, and who
doesn&rsquo;t these days?!</p>
<p>As you can see from the docs, it&rsquo;s just a <code>git clone</code>, <code>yarn</code> and <code>yarn start</code> away.</p>
<p>I thought this was going to be important during our Kgalagadi trip, because
patchy internet, so I got it going one evening in Twee Rivieren.</p>
<p>(Narrator: After that, he never used it, but he could have!)</p>
<p>Other than that, I had <a href="https://github.com/FuPeiJiang/VD.ahk/pull/10">fun helping to fix up an open source AutoHotkey library
for using Windows API calls to switch desktops quickly</a>.</p>
<p>I use this library in my simple but fast tool, called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/vxdesktops.ahk">vxdesktops.ahk, for
hotkey-based switching between virtual desktops on Windows</a>. I put this together
when I saw yet another screencast of someone showing off how quickly they could
switch using <a href="/2014/09/23/weekly-head-voices-82-tiles-and-platitutes/">i3wm</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-surprising-effectiveness-of-assuming-best-intentions">The surprising effectiveness of assuming best intentions</h2>
<p>With a small group of friends, we have for a while now been applying the idea
of always assuming best intentions, and always <em>having</em> the best intentions.</p>
<p>I knew that this is how I would generally like to operate, but I was still
pleasantly surprised by how this has turned so many potentially difficult
conversations into constructive and educational interactions that have enriched
us all.</p>
<p>So recently, <a href="https://rickmanelius.com/article/assume-positive-intent">a 2017 blog post by Rick Manelius, titled Assume Positive Intent</a>,
was again featured on HN where it caught my attention.</p>
<p>He makes the case for <em>always</em> assuming positive intent, also outside of groups
of friends where you can explicitly agree upon this principle.</p>
<p>Of course he excludes low trust environments from this mode, but generally in
business, and other interactions with strangers in non-low-trust environments,
assuming positive intent will work well (and be far less tiring) far more often
than it won&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>My humble suggestion here would be to try the explicit configuration of
bilaterally best intentioned environments wherever possible because this is
really an amazing way to connect with fellow humans, and to assume positive
intent everywhere else where it makes sense.</p>
<p>I hope to be able to write more eloquently about this in a future post.</p>
<p>Thank you for joining me here!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #240: I am just a copy of a copy of a copy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 21:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</guid><description> Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three weeks instead of one.
I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking
back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of
the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three
weeks instead of one.</p>
<p>I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about
alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more
resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough
time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</p>
<p>(Some more famous bloggers that I follow manage to put out a paragraph or two
every single day. It would be interesting to try an experiment like that.)</p>
<p>Anyways, switching out of meta mode back to the mishmash of on-topics for edition
240:</p>
<h2 id="blood-flowers">Blood flowers</h2>
<p>During a recent karma-restoring family beach walk, we came across the following
pretty striking flowers:</p>








<figure><a href="blood-flowers.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Blood flowers in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Blood flowers in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The <a href="http://pza.sanbi.org/haemanthus-coccineus">PlantZAfrica website tells us</a> that these are examples of <em>Haemanthus
coccineus</em>, also known as &ldquo;March flower&rdquo; (no idea why) or &ldquo;blood flower&rdquo;, the
latter which is more in line with the meaning of its Greek genus (haima =
blood, anthos = flower), and its Latin species.</p>
<p>We are not the first or only people to find it quite striking:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It was probably the first flower to be collected from Table Mountain and,
probably also the first illustration of a South African flower to appearin a
European publication. The illustration was by the Flemish botanis de L&rsquo;Obel
in 1605. &ndash; PlantZAfrica</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, as if the name &ldquo;Blood Flower&rdquo; is not metal enough, it turns out
<em>Haemanthus coccineus</em> lives fully underground in the form of a large bulb for
the dry summer months, only revealing its brilliant red flower when the rainy
season is about to start.</p>
<h2 id="fantastic-karma-and-how-to-destroy-it">Fantastic karma and how to destroy it</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s Friday evening. We&rsquo;ve just had a brilliant edition of our Friday evening
family braai tradition, and everyone starts retiring to their various
individual relaxation activities.</p>
<p>I decide that it&rsquo;s a great idea to forge ahead with the <a href="https://github.com/vega/react-vega/tree/master/packages/react-vega">react-vega</a> and <a href="https://redux-toolkit.js.org/rtk-query/overview">RTK
Query</a> visualization functionality I had ended my work week with.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d successfully worked with a previous version of the former, and my
confidence in RTKQ&rsquo;s quality was trending upwards due to recent experience in
one of our products.</p>
<p>I had already made a start with this new instance, and surely my first fully
backend-data-driven visualization was only an hour or two away, giving me a
final Friday evening boost.</p>
<p>Well friends, in hindsight I should have stopped right there and then.</p>
<p>Sure, it was the sort of gamble that had often paid off in the past &ndash; who does
not like to start their weekend with the dopamine rush that comes with the
solving of a little technical puzzle, especially one that results in pretty
pictures?! &ndash; but in this case it was doomed to failure.</p>
<p>The later it got, the less able I was to debug the issue, and the less
emotional control I was able to exert over my growing frustration.</p>
<p>(I am still less than happy with the new react-vega&rsquo;s limited documentation,
error handling and examples.)</p>
<p>I went to bed far later than normal, frustrated, and with no solution in sight.</p>
<p>All of this continued to affect my Saturday (grumpy with capital G&hellip; no wait,
all capitals&hellip;), until I finally made the conscious decision to disconnect
from the technical problem completely.</p>
<p>Anyways, I&rsquo;m writing this down as a reminder to me to be really, really careful
with the work-to-weekend transition.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-1-make-my-home-smart-but-do-it-really-slowly">Techno interlude #1: Make my home smart, but do it really slowly</h2>
<p>I finally got around to hooking up one (1) of the <a href="https://shelly.cloud/products/shelly-1-smart-home-automation-relay/">Shelly 1 smart relays</a> I
bought at the end of 2020.</p>
<p>My whole family is now able to open the main yard gate using&hellip; THEIR PHONES.</p>
<p>Noteworthy here is how easily the Shelly switches can be flashed, over the air
(OTA) no less, with the third party <a href="https://github.com/mongoose-os-apps/shelly-homekit">shelly-homekit firmware</a> to make them
natively Apple homekit compatible.</p>
<p>You can read about the how and the what in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/03/05/connecting-the-shelly-1-to-an-et-systems-gate-motor-for-apple-homekit-control/">this vxlabs post</a>.</p>
<p>Shortly after that post appeared, we held a <a href="https://fb.me/e/30MWR7Rq3">&ldquo;home automation&rdquo;-themed Helderberg
Software Developers and Entrepreneurs meetup</a>. Thanks to current interest in the
topic, and the three absolutely brilliant speakers who were willing to take us
along on their HA adventure, it was the biggest and most active we&rsquo;ve had in
years, by far!</p>
<p>In another probably surprising move, we are currently moving the meetup group
away from meetup.com and onto facebook as a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/helderberg.swdev.entrep.meetups/">group</a> (join if you&rsquo;re on fb!) from
where we can easily setup events.</p>
<p>Since 2019, meetup.com has been charging a pretty ridiculous $50 / 6-months fee
for a 100% free meetup with 0 commercial intent. In return for that, they
handle attendance (ish, we ofen had &gt;50% no-shows) and supply a bit of
discoverability.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, we now fortunately also have a snazzy website at
<a href="https://helderberg.dev/">https://helderberg.dev/</a> where you&rsquo;ll always be able to find the meetup, no
matter the events platform <em>du jour</em>.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-2-make-emacs-more-prettier">Techno interlude #2: Make Emacs More Prettier</h2>
<p>In spite of general business, I did have to make time for some <code>init.el</code>
wrangling, as is the privilege and sworn duty of every Emacs user.</p>
<p>This time, I refined my font and specifically <code>variable-pitch</code> setup.</p>
<p>I settled on the <a href="https://www.figma.com/blog/the-birth-of-inter/">Inter font</a> because I liked the look of <a href="https://obsidian.md/">obsidian.md</a>, where it&rsquo;s
the default. Then I discovered that it was designed (based on the Roboto font)
by Figma designer Rasmus Andersson as &ldquo;a font meant to make it easier to read
text on computer screens&rdquo; (hey, that&rsquo;s exactly what I need!), and is now also
the default on github, mozilla, and notion. Pretty good typographic company
right there.</p>
<p>The other small change I made which was much more satisfying than I expected,
was setting the default font size based on the estimated pixel density of the
current screen.</p>
<p>This means that my Emacs will render its default fonts at sizes that make sense
on whichever display I&rsquo;m using it.</p>
<p>Yes, I know that we should have been able to specify <a href="https://github.com/kickingvegas/12pt-should-be-the-same-everywhere/blob/master/absoluteMeasurementDPI.md">resolution invariant font
sizes by now</a>, but until that future arrives, my Emacs config will just have to
compensate.</p>
<p>The screenshot below shows an example of variable-pitch rendering on the left
(org-roam entry at the bottom, automatic topic backlinks at the top) and in the
centre (a slightly earlier draft of this post) and fixed-pitch on the right,
the relevant parts of my <code>init.el</code> showing the font and (<a href="https://github.com/humanoid-colors/emacs-humanoid-themes">humanoid</a>) theme setup.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Emacs screenshot. No, I don&amp;rsquo;t like dark themes."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Emacs screenshot. No, <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">I don&rsquo;t like dark themes</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="permutation-city">Permutation City</h2>
<p>When I saw a recommendation for <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156784.Permutation_City">Permutation City, a 1994 sci-fi novel by the
Australian author Greg Egan</a>, I was hesitant.</p>
<p>Would a novel, written more than 25 years ago, about uploading digital copies
of humans to virtual reality (I wrote a bit about that in <a href="/2020/07/01/weekly-head-voices-199-a-bit-stubborn/#a-totally-unexpected-ramble-on-cycles-patterns-and-teleportation">WHV #199</a> back in
2020), still be up to date with the latest ideas on the topic, seeing that
several adjacent fields of research have been advancing at a break-neck pace in
recent decades?</p>
<p>Weeeeell&hellip;.</p>
<p>It turns out great sci-fi has no problem reaching ahead through a quarter
century of modern technological development and then blowing my mind several
times.</p>
<p>With Permutation City, Egan has written the book I would have wanted to write,
in my wildest fantasies of course, about humans, and copies of humans, and the
philosophically indistinguishable self-awareness and consciousness of the
copies, and of their copies, and so on, literally ad infinitum.</p>
<p>Fortunately this is my first Egan novel, and even more fortunately it turns out
that he has produced a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/32699.Greg_Egan">considerable collection of stories</a> which I now have the
privilege to proceed to assimilate!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #238: Live deep and suck out all the marrow of life</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 21:24:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/</guid><description> Welcome everyone to the 238th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the week from Monday, January 31 to Sunday, February 6, 2022.
I would like to get you started with some flowers, after which there is a possibly boring bit about improving my keyboard, followed by a final bit with a quote which I think is a bit more than just a two-bit quote.
Figure 1: Photo taken by GOU #1 at Vergelegen Wine Estate during a solidly Thing-level (see WHV #237) Sunday lunch with my inner inner circle.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome everyone to the 238th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one
covering the week from Monday, January 31 to Sunday, February 6, 2022.</p>
<p>I would like to get you started with some flowers, after which there is a
possibly boring bit about improving my keyboard, followed by a final bit with a
quote which I think is a bit more than just a two-bit quote.</p>








<figure><a href="vergelegen-sunflowers.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/vergelegen-sunflowers_hu9fead7a3f6340f98938310326f8faad7_3059019_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo taken by GOU #1 at Vergelegen Wine Estate during a solidly Thing-level (see WHV #237) Sunday lunch with my inner inner circle."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo taken by <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> at Vergelegen Wine Estate during a solidly Thing-level (see <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237</a>) Sunday lunch with my inner inner circle.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="womier-k87-keyboard-customization-unlocked">Womier K87 keyboard: Customization unlocked!</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/#yet-another--new-keyboard-yank">WHV #235 that I was quite happy with my new Varmilo
VA87m mechanical keyboard</a> and that I was also quite surprised to learn that I
might prefer <em>linear</em> switches over <em>tactile</em>, thanks to the super smooth Cherry MX
Speed Silver switches.</p>
<p>Furthermore, its stabilisers were exceptionally smooth, and quiet. It taught me
that one did not have to live with rattly stabilisers.</p>
<p>As is often the case with new knowledge, this made me re-evaluate my
relationship with my other keyboard, the Womier K87 (aka &ldquo;RGB-with-unicorns&rdquo;),
which was introduced here in <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204</a>.</p>
<p>You see, that board came with both <em>tactile</em> switches (Gateron browns), and with
rattly <a href="https://switchandclick.com/stabilizer-guide/">stabilisers</a>.</p>
<p>&hellip; and so it came to pass that I ordered 90 Cherry MX Red switches from
<a href="https://www.ctrlshiftesc.co.za/">Ctrl.Shift.Esc</a>, as well as a super cheap (R109 when I ordered, it seems the
price has just doubled!) 100g tube of SPANJAARD silicone paste.</p>
<p>The red switches are quintessentially linear. They have a more conventional
actuation distance of 2mm versus the perhaps too-quick-for-me 1.2mm of the
speed silvers.</p>
<p>Plus, they were in stock.</p>
<p>I selected the SPANJAARD silicone paste as a cheap local alternative after
reading more than I ever wanted to know about lubricants and greases for
respectively the switches themselves and the stabilisers.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m just kidding, this is exactly the sort of thing I love knowing everything
about.)</p>
<p>On the evening of Monday, January 31, our dinner table looked like this:</p>








<figure><a href="womier-red-switches-in-progress.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/womier-red-switches-in-progress_hu06a89d3565099197aa98ca55e791c386_3364266_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Brown switches out, reds are in. I kept those three browns top right for comparison. The white cap puller was much faster for me than the wire one above the keycaps."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Brown switches out, reds are in. I kept those three browns top right for comparison. The white cap puller was much faster for me than the wire one above the keycaps.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Shortly after that, I was typing on the &ldquo;new&rdquo; board, entirely unconvinced that
the switch (haha) had been worthwhile.</p>
<p>As I&rsquo;m typing this, it&rsquo;s a more than a week later, and I am now entirely
convinced.</p>
<p>Based on how they feel, and an improvement of my typing speed and accuracy on
these switches relative to brown, I am hereby joining team linear!</p>
<p>With regard to the rattly stabs: On February 2 I removed the spacebar,
backspace and return keys, disassembled the stabilisers, and coated the wire
ends in as much silicone paste as I could. Although not quite at Varmilo
levels, the three respective stabilisers have improved massively, and have
convincingly crossed my satisfaction threshold.</p>
<h2 id="live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life">Live deep and suck out all the marrow of life</h2>
<p>I used to encourage friend PK, and probably others (and probably most often
just myself), but he usually just <em>got it</em>, with the following: &ldquo;Please remember
to squeeze out every last drop from that experience&rdquo;.</p>
<p>There was a distinctly visual, almost palpable, element to this wish.</p>
<p>You have to imagine somehow grabbing the moment in question, and then wringing
it out like a wet towel to extract every last iota of juicy experience.</p>
<p>As I&rsquo;m desperately scrambling here for the right words to describe precisely
the intention, you can image how happy I was to run into the following quote by
Henry David Thoreau just the other day:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I went to the woods because I wished to live deliberately, to front only the
essential facts of life, and see if I could not learn what it had to teach, and
not, when I came to die, discover that I had not lived. I did not wish to live
what was not life, living is so dear; nor did I wish to practise resignation,
unless it was quite necessary. I wanted <strong>to live deep and suck out all the
marrow of life</strong>, to live so sturdily and Spartan-like as to put to rout all that
was not life, to cut a broad swath and shave close, to drive life into a
corner, and reduce it to its lowest terms&hellip; &ndash; Henry David Thoreau (<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/2690-i-went-to-the-woods-because-i-wished-to-live">ref</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(I just spent some time on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_David_Thoreau">Thoreau&rsquo;s wikipedia page</a>. It turns out it was not
just this quote, he was an impressive human.)</p>
<p>Folks, remember to squeeze out every last drop from <em>your</em> experience!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #237: Don't step over the thing</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 22:29:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/</guid><description> Well hello there and welcome to the first Weekly Head Voices of the year 2022!
Figure 1: So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay.
Where we usually pretend that a WHV covers a certain period of time since the previous one, this one will simply engage in some excessive but pretty skillful hand-waving and say that if you read it and the 2021 to 2022 year transition post, you should be more or less up to date with the state of this nation up to Sunday, January 30, 2022.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well hello there and welcome to the first Weekly Head Voices of the year 2022!</p>








<figure><a href="stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&rsquo;s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Where we usually pretend that a WHV covers a certain period of time since the
previous one, this one will simply engage in some excessive but pretty skillful
hand-waving and say that if you read it and the <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/">2021 to 2022 year transition
post</a>, you should be more or less up to date with the state of this nation up to
Sunday, January 30, 2022.</p>
<h2 id="eaz-and-sleep">EAZ and sleep</h2>
<p><a href="/tags/eaz/">EAZ (Experiment Alcohol Zero - no alcohol for at least a month but usually
more)</a> is still going strong, and it&rsquo;s getting harder for me to ignore the fact
that it&rsquo;s (again) having a drastic impact on my sleep quality.</p>
<p>Where I normally am quite chuffed to wake up feeling that I&rsquo;ve had a solid
night of sleep, these days it feels like I&rsquo;m almost guaranteed a great night of
shut-eye as long as I can get to bed on time.</p>
<h2 id="gou-updates">GOU updates</h2>
<p>In other much more important news, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> has left the nest.</p>
<p>Ok fortunately only sort of&hellip; She now spends her weeks in the school&rsquo;s
dormitory.</p>
<p>They are extremely well looked-after, and she gets to participate even more
fully in school activities where previously this was a bit constrained by the 1
to 1.5 hour travel time (school bus in traffic) involved.</p>
<p>We do miss her quite a lot in the weeks.</p>
<p>In her absence, GOU #2 (2IC, IOW) has quickly taken on a new role, which is
interesting to see.</p>
<p>GOU #3 has just started with Grade R (first year of &ldquo;big school&rdquo;), and it looks
like she&rsquo;s taken to it like a fish to water.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a lot more fun now with both #2 and #3 in the car in the mornings,
although we could probably do without all the karma loss I suffer in traffic
every morning. The 4km from my house to school can easily take up to 25
minutes, during which I&rsquo;m obviously surrounded by people who clearly can&rsquo;t
drive.</p>
<h2 id="the-apple-doesn-t-fall-far-from-the-tree">The apple doesn&rsquo;t fall far from the tree</h2>
<p>At the start of 2019 I decided for some or other reason that I really wanted to
know how my branch of the Botha family connected to the rest of the tree.</p>
<p>Botha is a pretty common surname down here.</p>
<p>Many Botha&rsquo;s probably know that we are the descendants of <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Both-15">Friedrich Both</a>, a
soldier who came to the Cape from Wagenheim (from the Thuringen region of
Germany) in 1678 to assist the Dutch colonists.</p>
<p>OR ARE WE?</p>
<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23948326/">A 2013 study by Greeff and Erasmus, titled <em>Appel Botha: The abc of a three
hundred year old divorce case</em></a>, showed that Theunis Botha, the first of four
sons of Friedrich Both and his Dutch wife, Maria Kickers (divorced from Jan
Cornelisz because they could not have children), was in fact the extra-marital
product of Maria&rsquo;s relationship with Ferdinandus Appel!</p>
<p>DUN DUN DUUUUUUUN!</p>
<p>According to the study, Theunis Appel is responsible for roughly half (38000) of all
of the Botha&rsquo;s (78000) living in 2013.</p>
<p>Returning to my branch all the way down here: My uncle E was so kind to send me
notes he made of the gravestones on one of the farms my ancestors lived on,
including full names and dates of birth and death of a number of said
ancestors. As you might realise, full names and birth / death dates are genealogy gold.</p>
<p>My aunt M&rsquo;s many stories helped to fill in any further gaps, especially by
confirming identities through matching full names with nick names.</p>
<p>Although initially I was unable to make the connection to the greater Botha
tree using this information, the <a href="https://www.myheritage.com/">MyHeritage</a> databases, and various bits of
information I could get from older clan members, I recently picked up my notes
again (after a two year hiatus!) and was suddenly able to make a single
high-impact connection (my great-great-grandfather) that I previously missed.</p>
<p>Long story short, the moment I did this all of the fragments came together, and
I&rsquo;m now able to say with reasonable confidence that <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Appel-29">Ferdinandus Appel</a> and <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Kickers-1">Maria
Kickers</a> are my great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-grandparents.</p>
<p>DUN DUN DUUUUUUUUUN!</p>
<h2 id="i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">I don&rsquo;t want to step over the thing</h2>
<p>At the end of their <a href="https://lexfridman.com/sam-harris/">3 hour long podcast interview from May</a>, Lex Fridman asks
Sam Harris one of his standard questions (you can listen to the bit in question
<a href="https://youtu.be/4dC_nRYIDZU?t=11241">precisely here</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is the meaning of life?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In almost typical Sam Harris fashion, he replies that it&rsquo;s the wrong question.</p>
<p>Less cryptically, Sam explains that if you&rsquo;re searching for that mythical
<em>meaning of life</em> that&rsquo;s going to make everything better, you might be doing it
wrong.</p>
<p>In his words (which I have transcribed and cleaned up a little bit especially
for you):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You don&rsquo;t have to live with the illusion anymore that you need a good enough
reason and that things are going to get better when you do get those reasons.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a mirage-like quality to every future attainment and every future
breakthrough and every future peak experience that eventually you get the
lesson that you never quite arrive.</p>
<p><strong>You don&rsquo;t arrive until you cease to step over the present moment in search of
the next thing.</strong></p>
<p><strong>We&rsquo;re constantly stepping over the thing that we think we&rsquo;re seeking in the
act of seeking it.</strong> [ed: my emphasis. I loved this bit]</p>
<p>&hellip;</p>
<p>You can&rsquo;t actually become happy. You can only be happy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>His words hit home for me.</p>
<p>Dear readers, I truly wish you an abundance of recognizing the thing, and of
<em>being</em> happy.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #233: Atomic party sections</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.
Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.
(Don&rsquo;t) Stress for success (aka 4000 weeks at 60%) It&rsquo;s really quite busy at work, perhaps even verging on the slightly too busy territory.
I&rsquo;m consistently putting in stretches of focused, high intensity work to help push us into calmer waters.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering
the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="don-t--stress-for-success--aka-4000-weeks-at-60">(Don&rsquo;t) Stress for success (aka 4000 weeks at 60%)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s really quite busy at work, perhaps even verging on the slightly too busy
territory.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m consistently putting in stretches of focused, high intensity work to help
push us into calmer waters.</p>
<p>However, in spite of all of this, my stress levels seem to have have subsided
to quite an extent over the last few weeks.</p>
<p>This could be ascribed to me slowly moving out of <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">new challenge discomfort
territory</a>, because I&rsquo;m either getting better at what I&rsquo;m supposed to be doing,
or, if you want to be cynical, I just care a little less.</p>
<p>Maybe these two are the same.</p>
<p>I like to think that it could also be the growing effect of <em>Four Thousand
Weeks: Time and How to Use It</em>, <a href="/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/#how-i-m-putting-down-my-work">the book I mentioned in WHV-231</a> that so
eloquently and quite urgently makes the case that because life is so stupidly
short, and you&rsquo;re not even going to get close to Getting your Things Done, and
that working hard so that you can relax at some future point in time is a
terribly imprudent approach forced upon us by our instrumentalist society, you
should instead do your best extracting every bit of enjoyment from every moment
that you get, when you get it.</p>
<p>Every morning is an opportunity for a mini coffee and breakfast party, and
every evening is an opportunity for a mini dinner party, both of these with the
people, big and small, I hold the most dear.</p>
<p>Every day I do need to work, but there is ample opportunity for curiosity, for
learning, and for offering a helping hand.</p>
<p>There is generally also time to go out for a wide-open-perception run in the
sun.</p>
<p>All of this is available to you if you can just learn how to keep your own set
of instrumentalising demons safely locked up in their cages. (these are the
gremlins who keep on bugging you to try to finish one more thing.)</p>
<p>As Burkeman writes on page 144:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To the philosophers of the ancient world, leisure wasn&rsquo;t the means to some
other end; on the contrary, it was the end to which everything else worth doing
was a means.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Back in <a href="/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/#flip-it">WHV #222, I tried to say something similar, just far less eloquently</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve completed only a pinch over 60% of the book. I might have more to say when
it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">Dropbox Paper (aka mobile note-taking evolving)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s no secret around these parts that <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#mobile">the mobile aspects of my otherwise
pretty respectable note-taking game are weak</a>. (In short: Emacs Org mode is
amazing and can do <em>anything</em>, <strong>except</strong> when on my iPhone. Moar shorter: iPhone =
Org mode Kryptonite)</p>
<p>Somehow, in spite of being so deep in with Dropbox, and in spite of using
<a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper">Dropbox Paper</a> for other things, I overlooked it when evaluating solutions for
mobile note capture all the way back in 2019.</p>
<p>This weekend, because I had to scrounge around for an important bit of
information I <em>knew</em> I had stored somewhere (it turned out to be in my Apple
Notes doh), I spent some time trying to find a tool that would give me
mobile-editable notes that would turn up more readily in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that Dropbox Paper documents turn up in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Who would have guessed?!</p>
<p>In addition to that, Paper has:</p>
<ul>
<li>markdown support</li>
<li>syntax highlighting of triple-backtick source code blocks</li>
<li>LaTeX math!</li>
<li>embedding of arbitrary media which gets automatically uploaded to dropbox on
drag and drop</li>
<li>easy linking to other Paper docs</li>
<li>checklists</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Cue sound of another personal knowledge management puzzle piece snapping into place&hellip;</em></p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m not allowed to talk about it here, because the blog post in question
happened <em>after</em> this blog post&rsquo;s legally allowed observed timespan, but shortly
in the future, I will also solve the issue of being able to search through and
preview all of my Org mode notes on the iPhone.</p>
<p>Post is on vxlabs if you&rsquo;re from the (near) future.</p>
<h2 id="a-truly-spectacular-long-weekend-in-betty-s">A truly spectacular long weekend in Betty&rsquo;s</h2>
<p>The second week ended with a weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay that was so spectacular
that it deserves its own section in this blog post.</p>
<p>Well this is it. The section dedicated to the weekend. I hope you like it.</p>
<h2 id="the-section-at-the-end">The section at the end</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this.</p>
<p>I wish you continuous and consistent atomic party moments.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #231: Two thousand four hundred fourty-four</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW
This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to Sunday August 29, 2021.
Orbital mechanics that are important to me Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.
That&amp;rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.
Let me try again:
Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="pano_from_watsonia.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &ldquo;run&rdquo; with bestie DW</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to
Sunday August 29, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="orbital-mechanics-that-are-important-to-me">Orbital mechanics that are important to me</h2>
<p>Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.</p>
<p>Let me try again:</p>
<p>Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for
another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</p>
<p>As is our custom here, I get to increase the mathematical encoding (this is a
fantastically consistent and useful approach to the structured modelling of
reality) of my time as an alive unit by one.</p>
<p>When I was younger, it was possible to use this number to impress one&rsquo;s
friends. Sometimes, the number of an older sibling or even a parent could also
be used to increase social standing, if one&rsquo;s own number was still quite small.</p>
<p>Ironically, as the number gets bigger, we prefer not to talk or even think
about it too much.</p>
<p>Thanks to math, the number could in theory be transformed into &ldquo;number of
revolutions remaining&rdquo;, but fortunately our complex physiologies and
environments greatly complicate the estimation of the required term for that
transformation, in this case greatly comforting us with uncertainty.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS&hellip;</p>
<p>I had an amazing birthday.</p>
<p>From morning video chats with homies, to working lunches that turned into
superbly relaxed lunches with old friends, surprise visits by far-off friends
the day before, birthday mountain runs with a bestie, and so many (voice)
messages on various platforms from friends everywhere, my birthday was a
friendship-and-life-affirming business.</p>
<p>Friends, thank you for working together like that. You are all breath-taking!</p>
<p>P.S. Experiencing this acted as a beautiful reminder to send that message,
write that email or make that call whenever you can find an excuse!</p>
<h2 id="how-i-m-putting-down-my-work"><em>How</em> I&rsquo;m putting down my work</h2>
<p>In the previous edition of the WHV, I talked about <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">the important skill of being
able to put down one&rsquo;s work</a>.</p>
<p>Here I would just like to mention how I&rsquo;ve been trying to practise this in my
life, especially because it really seems to have helped me since we last spoke.</p>
<p>Ok, get ready!</p>
<p>You Won&rsquo;t Believe This One Trick&hellip;</p>
<p>At 17:00, 17:30 at the latest, I explicitly switch off any tools that I use for
work, and disconnect from all dayjob-related systems.</p>
<p>Work email closed, development enviroments exited, docker containers all stopped.</p>
<p>For good measure, I roll a tumbleweed or two across my office floor, blowing
air out through my pursed lips.</p>
<p>The thing is, my brain has the tendency to continue cogitating on the last
thing I kept it busy with.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I used to have the tendency to still try and solve that problem
before bed, only resulting in me later lying in said bed, unable to get my
brain to stop cogitating, leading to bad sleep, contributing to subpar
performance the next day.</p>
<p>I have to qualify here that putting down work tools does not exclude me from
picking up hobby programming projects later in the evening, after &ldquo;The Making
of The Dinner, With Wine&rdquo; and &ldquo;The Chilling With The Family&rdquo; stages.</p>
<p>Although programming plays a substantial part of dayjob, I have never stopped
enjoying and being relaxed by this activity in the recreational setting.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, making a point of putting down work on time, starting
the gradual wind-down, has drastically reduced the number and severity of
<em>Trying Unsuccessfully to Solve All Work Problems In The Dark, From One&rsquo;s Bed</em> for
me.</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/">Oliver Burkeman</a>, author of <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">the putting-down-your-work post</a>, also wrote a
book titled <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2021/aug/16/four-thousand-weeks-time-and-how-to-use-it-by-oliver-burkeman-review">Four Thousand Weeks: Time and How to Use It</a>, which my mom got me
for my birthday (THANKS MOM!).</p>
<p>As soon as I&rsquo;m done with <a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">Seligman&rsquo;s book flourish</a>, I&rsquo;ll start with this book,
which will hopefully filter through to this blog.</p>
<p>In the meantime, here&rsquo;s the blurb which is already food  for thought:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The average human lifespan is absurdly, insultingly brief.</p>
<p>If you live to be 80, youll have had about 4,000 weeks. But thats no reason for despair.</p>
<p>Confronting our radical finitude  and how little control we really have  is the key to a fulfilling and meaningfully productive life.</p>
</blockquote>








<figure><a href="helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&amp;rsquo;ve been treated with."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&rsquo;ve been treated with.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #230: Follow your blisters</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="van_breda_cottage_angles.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&amp;rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &amp;ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&amp;rdquo; (I didn&amp;rsquo;t and I don&amp;rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV covers the three weeks from Monday July 26 to Sunday August 15.</p>
<h2 id="why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">Why I don&rsquo;t like dark mode anymore</h2>
<p>As you might know, I spent most of my working (and sometimes hobby, we&rsquo;ll get
back to that further down) hours in front of this screen or some other screen.</p>
<p>Up to now, I was really convinced that I preferred dark mode everywhere, until
recently two events transpired:</p>
<p>I started noticing more eye-strain than usual, even on my 27&quot; screen, something
which had a perceptible effect on my productivity. This I resignedly ascribed
to my advancing age, although I did find the suddenness quite surprising,
especially since I recently had my glasses updated.</p>
<p>Then, after years with only the admittedly brilliant <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">zenburn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/fniessen/emacs-leuven-theme">Leuven (dark)</a>
Emacs themes checking all of the boxes for me, I finally ran into a really
interesting and usable theme called <a href="https://github.com/kunalb/poet">Poet</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s interesting, because it uses variable pitched fonts for everything but
code, tables and elements of the fixed width domain, where most Emacs fonts
stick to the traditional all-fixed-width approach.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="20210822-poet-theme-screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can probably understand that for someone who uses Emacs almost primarily
for technical notes and other writing, this book-like appearance could work
really well.</p>
<p>The theme was even more interesting for me personally, as it suddenly became
clear as day that I experienced almost no eye-strain when using Emacs with this
lighter theme than when I used any of my other usually dark-themed tools!</p>
<p>It became obvious that poet-theme&rsquo;s lighter background was much easier on my
eyes than dark mode in vscode. (No, this specific advantage can&rsquo;t be ascribed
to Emacs itself I&rsquo;m afraid.)</p>
<p>Reading pages such as <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/digital-eye-strain/is-dark-mode-better-for-eyes/">this</a> explains that dark mode leads to pupils having to
dilate more to let in more light, which there is less of with dark themes.</p>
<p>This leads to, just like with cameras and any other optics with lenses and
apertures, a shortened depth of field, and hence more difficulty focusing on
the screen!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/dark-mode/">This article by the well-known Nielsen Norman Group</a> nicely summarises research
on this topic. In short:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In people with normal vision (or corrected-to-normal vision), visual
performance tends to be better with light mode, whereas some people with
cataract and related disorders may perform better with dark mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Up until recently, I did not experience a qualitative difference in vision
between dark and light, but I sit here relieved that my eye-strain issue has
been resolved by an Emacs theme!</p>
<h2 id="know-how-to-put-down-your-work">Know how to put down your work</h2>
<p>The following take from <a href="https://twitter.com/brandsrock/status/1426163442256330753">a recent tweet by mike joubert</a> struck me
(tweet-take-strike! words are funny&hellip;):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly valuable skill isn&rsquo;t the capacity to push yourself harder, but to
stop and recuperate despite the discomfort of knowing that work remains
unfinished, emails unanswered, other people&rsquo;s demands unfulfilled.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">article, titled <em>The three-or-four-hours rule for getting creative work
done</em></a>, is itself a good read about the observation that creative types (amongst
which I count engineers) have at their best three to four hours of focus time
per day &mdash; so it is crucially important that their days are structured such
that there is an <strong>uninterrupted</strong> block of three to four hours inside of which
that lovely focus has the possibility of appearing.</p>
<p>The tweet-extract focuses on the similarly important but more subtle art of
being able to put one&rsquo;s work down, completely, when that block of time is over,
even when it feels like the work is far from complete.</p>
<p>I especially like that it also explicitly mentions the illusions created by
one&rsquo;s perception of &ldquo;other people&rsquo;s demands&rdquo;, something that ironically becomes
even harder to walk away from when one is more tired at the end of the work
day.</p>
<p>For me, becoming better at putting work down has pleasant echoes of running
slower to run faster, of emptiness in art and more broadly, <a href="https://zenhabits.net/work-less/">choosing fewer f*cks
to give</a>.</p>
<h2 id="follow-your-blisters">Follow your blisters</h2>
<p>On the topic of choosing your ducks&hellip;</p>
<p>I initially did not like <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/what-you-should-follow-instead-of-your-passion">this HBR</a> post when it first crossed my stream, because
it smacks a bit too much of the current social media style of &ldquo;wisdom&rdquo;, namely
&ldquo;everything you need to know in 280 characters&rdquo;, or &ldquo;this 1 minute tiktok video
will change your life&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the title is pretty clickbaity: <em>What You Should
Follow Instead of Your Passion</em>.</p>
<p>However, the core message of the post, which I could not help reading, did
stick with me, and after a few days I realised that I would have to go find the
article again in order to talk about it here.</p>
<p>The core message is to replace <em>find your passion</em> with <strong><em>Find your blisters.</em></strong></p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s point is that folks often get the wrong idea with <em>passion</em> as
something that is simply always delightful, whilst the thing you should
actually be looking for, is that activity that you simply are unable to stop
doing, even when you try, and especially even when you don&rsquo;t directly derive
pleasure from it, for example because you feel that you&rsquo;re not that good at it.</p>
<p>They give the personal example of writing.</p>
<p>Although they&rsquo;ve been at it for years, it&rsquo;s still a difficult and laborious
process, and they are often not happy with the results.</p>
<p>However, they have been unable to stop from returning to writing projects again
and again over the years.</p>
<p>Ironically, even although they find that they are still bad at it, they have in
fact become really good, simply because they have been pushing through and
practising more than almost anyone else over the years.</p>
<p>I really like this down-to-earth view.</p>
<p>One can indeed source almost unlimited amounts of energy from one&rsquo;s &ldquo;blisters&rdquo;,
but true benefits will for a large part be brought about by a <a href="/tags/practice/">lifetime of often
challenging practice</a>.</p>








<figure><a href="flowers_everywhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &amp;ldquo;blommetjieskyk&amp;rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #227: Reality bending security blanket</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 22:15:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.
This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.
Groundhog Lockdown On the above-mentioned Sunday, president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4, one level more serious from where we were.
For us this means that schools are closing a week earlier for the July vacation, and hence will have to open a week earlier, and hence will have a severe effect on the breakaway we had planned, an effect of the cancellation variety.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="backyard_walk_s_and_i.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from
Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.</p>
<h2 id="groundhog-lockdown">Groundhog Lockdown</h2>
<p>On the above-mentioned Sunday, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/level-4-lockdown-for-south-africa-for-14-days-2021-6">president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4</a>,
one level more serious from where we were.</p>
<p>For us this means that schools are closing a week earlier for the July
vacation, and hence will have to open a week earlier, and hence will have a
severe effect on the breakaway we had planned, an effect of the
<em>cancellation</em> variety.</p>
<p>Although frustrating (some of us really need that precious time away to keep
calm and carry on afterwards), we don&rsquo;t really have anything to complain about
if that is our biggest problem.</p>
<p>Gauteng province has been hit really hard by the third wave of COVID, and
specifically this new Delta variant.</p>
<p>This modified lockdown level 4 explicitly prohibits travel into and out of the
province in order to help stem the disease&rsquo;s spread.</p>
<p>In other news, our vaccination is making progress, albeit at a slower pace than
most people had hoped.</p>
<p>In a few days they are going to start with the over 50s. No, this does not
include me yet, although I am close.</p>
<h2 id="amazon-document-culture">Amazon document culture</h2>
<p>Last week, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=27545331">Hacker News discussed</a> a really interesting <a href="https://www.justingarrison.com/blog/2021-03-15-the-document-culture-of-amazon/">blog post by an Amazon
employee about Amazon&rsquo;s document culture</a>.</p>
<p>In short, at Amazon, a meeting can only happen if a document has been written
detailing what is to be discussed during the meeting.</p>
<p>At the start of the meeting, everyone gets from 10 minutes to half an hour,
depending on what makes sense for the document under discussion, to read the
document, and only then the meeting starts.</p>
<p>This approach has many advantages, discussed in the blog post.</p>
<p>What I personally like about doing it this way, is that the convenor of the
meeting has to pay a price for that meeting, namely sitting down and spending
time to structure their thoughts on paper well enough so it will satisfy the
expectations of the participants.</p>
<p>Furthermore, by dedicating quiet time to reading the document, one has a
slightly better guarantee that everyone is up to date with the background, and,
more interesting to me, is that it sets a more deliberate and thoughtful mood
for the whole meeting.</p>
<p>Of course I tried this out at the first high-level meeting that I could, where
I had to present a plan to the participants.</p>
<p>It felt a bit strange initiating this silent reading at the start, but my
perception is that it contributed to a higher quality discussion afterwards.</p>
<p>In this case it was easy, because the goal of the meeting was to present a plan
that was already a document. However, this is something I will definitely want
to repeat.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, the document will be all that is required.</p>
<h2 id="your-choice">Your choice</h2>
<p>In <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">WHV #226</a> I wrote that I had chosen to be in the situation that was causing
stress due to its new challenges.</p>
<p>Friend SvdW (jokingly? chidingly?) commented via private communications
channels that that &ldquo;choice&rdquo; had surprised him, seeing that <a href="https://philosophybreak.com/articles/free-will-illusion-sam-harris/">we have no free
will</a>.</p>
<p>He is right of course, but in this case it <em>is</em> in fact all about the illusion,
about being subjectively convinced that one is the agent and the author of
one&rsquo;s current situation.</p>
<p>This did remind me something I wrote in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#productivity-system-tuneup">WHV #185</a> about how this same framing
can be effective against procrastination:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have chosen to
take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having decided
to commit, i.e. active.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the cases where you believe that you <em>are</em> probably the agent of your
situation, it can really help to verbalise that to yourself in the way
described above.</p>
<p>This can sometimes be tricky, because so much of it has to do with potentially
subjective-reality-bending framing, which could get in the way of addressing
problems external to oneself.</p>
<p>If you apply This One Trick, and you do a great job, how real were those
external problems in the first place?</p>
<p>On days like these, I get a feeling, albeit an extremely faint one, for why
Descartes constructed the mental security blanket of <em>cogito ergo sum</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #226: Stress practice</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 16:07:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</guid><description> Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.
Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.
As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&amp;rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (Youth Day), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth Emacs Org-mode / ox-hugo blogging machine (read this github issue for more details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this combination has saved me in the past.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the
week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys_run_pano_20210612.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (<a href="https://www.gov.za/youth-day">Youth
Day</a>), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth
Emacs Org-mode / <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo">ox-hugo</a> blogging machine (read <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo/issues/447">this github issue</a> for more
details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this
combination has saved me in the past.</p>
<h2 id="solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">Solstice tipping point is coming!</h2>
<p>The last thing we&rsquo;re supposed to do is to wish even just a little bit for time
to pass more quickly, for fairly obvious reasons.</p>
<p>However, when you&rsquo;re a few days from the darkest point in the year, it&rsquo;s hard
not to.</p>
<p>We currently have 9 hours and 56 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s just two minutes, and a few days, from the winter solstice on June 21,
when we&rsquo;ll have to make do with 9 hours and 54 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>I mention this here, because those 6 AM wake-ups feel more and more like the
middle of the night.</p>
<p>After the solstice, I&rsquo;ll start imagining the sun coming up a few moments
earlier every morning, and it will.</p>
<p>(Well, it will, eventually. Reader WIMM just pointed out via email that
although the days start getting longer, the sunrise will initially become even
a minute later, before finally becoming earlier starting from July 11. Read
more <a href="https://theconversation.com/why-the-sunrise-is-still-later-after-the-winter-solstice-shortest-day-77628">here</a> (thanks WIMM) or check the tables <a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-africa/stellenbosch?month=6&amp;year=2021">here</a>.)</p>
<p>It has been &hellip; <code>1 year and 11 months</code> &hellip; since <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/">the previous mention of winter
solstice on this blog</a>.</p>
<h2 id="avoid-the-jbl-endurance-run-bt-earphones-at-all-costs">Avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones at all costs</h2>
<p>A month ago <a href="/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/#world-in-my-eyes">I wrote about the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a> that I was
initially so happy with, which then spontaneously broke after a few hours of
running, and which I then returned for a replacement.</p>
<p>Well, the replacement set of <a href="https://eu.jbl.com/JBL+ENDURANCE+RUNBT.html?dwvar%5FJBL%20ENDURANCE%20RUNBT%5Fcolor=Black-GLOBAL-Current">proudly sweat-proof JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a>
lasted for about 9 hours of running, at which point they spontaneously broke in
exactly the same way.</p>
<p>Out of nowhere, the loud crackling sound started in the earpiece opposite to
the site with the control unit.</p>
<p>This crackling sound (similar to the disturbance you hear when speaker wires
have a connection issue) did not stop, even after un-pairing and even after
switching off the unit.</p>
<p>Connecting the charger after this would result in the charge light flickering
and fading in-and-out in a decidedly analogue fashion.</p>
<p>After experiencing the exact same problem with two different units, I am wary
wasting more time on a third set.</p>
<p>This was quite a disappointment, because mechanically this design was perfect
for me.</p>
<p>I will continue on my search for the perfect (1. secure in my large and
sometimes perspiring ears, so needs something in addition to just ear canal fit
and 2. durable, i.e. continues working <em>long</em> after the first 9 hours of
running) set of running earphones, and I&rsquo;ll keep you up to date on my findings.</p>
<p>In the meantime, please avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones.</p>
<h2 id="remote-work-culture-is-hard-work">Remote work culture is hard work</h2>
<p>During our Tuesday evening meetup, Theunis de Klerk of <a href="https://www.noldor.co.za/">Noldor</a> (the now fully
remote tech company, not <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noldor">the race of elves from Middle Earth</a>, although there is
a link here) gave an interesting and inspiring talk on how they have built and
cultivate great remote work culture.</p>
<p>This was an insightful look into an organization where the top leadership
continuously pours a great deal of thought and energy into maintaining healthy
culture, even in a fully remote environment with parts in different timezones.</p>
<p>On the one hand, it&rsquo;s great seeing working examples like this, on the other, it
can be quite a daunting prospect when you start thinking about how to apply
this in your own environment.</p>
<p>I believe that the future of knowledge work will <em>not</em> involve highly qualified
folks having to spend 8 hours per day at their desk because we still have not
learned that work is all about contributing value, and not about the number of
hours spent in captivity at one&rsquo;s desk.</p>
<p>That being said, during the current global remote working experiment, although
we are learning how to roll with value-generation, I do miss some of the almost
effortlessly and socially generated collaboration glue that at its best gets
folks almost instinctively chasing the same worthy goals.</p>
<p>(On the other hand, at its worst, it causes conflicts, grudges and ulcers, so
there&rsquo;s that&hellip;)</p>
<p>I would like to wrap this ramble up with one conclusion, and one interesting
tweet storm by Steven Sinofsky of Andreesen Horowitz:</p>
<ul>
<li>Conclusion: 1. Am I overestimating how &ldquo;easy&rdquo; social cohesion was when we
were in the office? 2. How do we go about getting back that real or imagined
social cohesion in this fully remote setting?</li>
<li><a href="https://a16z.com/2021/06/12/disruption-at-work-its-more-than-just-wfh/">Highly interesting tweet storm about the issue being larger and more
intricate than just WFH vs hybrid vs HQ</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="eternal-practice-vs-stress">Eternal practice vs stress</h2>
<p>I do need to note here (for future me) that I was consistently far grumpier
than usual for the last few days of the week under examination here.</p>
<p>When I say grumpy, I do mean quite detectably so.</p>
<p>This is definitely not my preferred state, so I&rsquo;m even meta-grumpy about that.</p>
<p>My retro- and introspection during the weekend came up with &ldquo;more stress than
usual&rdquo;, which is indeed probably a main contributor (wow, thanks work).</p>
<p>However, being grumpy or not is still fully my responsibility.</p>
<p>Increased stress at work is currently primarily due to new responsibilities and
the (often amplified by one&rsquo;s own imagination) expectations of colleagues, and
the unsurprising feeling of discomfort that is associated with finding oneself
faced with new kinds of challenges that you are not accustomed to (<em>cf.</em>
&ldquo;comfort zone&rdquo; and <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">stages 2 to 4 of the creative process</a>).</p>
<p>During the weekend I first resolved simply to be less grumpy (yes, you can do
that).</p>
<p>Fortunately, I also had a spot of insight as to how the root cause, i.e. the
work-related stress, could be better addressed in my specific case.</p>
<p>You see, I have chosen to be in this situation. I would have preferred the new
challenges without the concomitant stress, but that&rsquo;s unfortunately not how
<em>this</em> human normally works.</p>
<p>The realisation that I had was that this too is simply part of my lifelong
practice session.</p>
<p>I first talked about the idea of life being continuous pracrtice back in <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">WHV
#133</a>, and again later in <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">WHV #144</a> when I got around to reading a
reader-recommended book on the topic, titled &ldquo;Mastery&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Something I did not mention back then, probably because I only experience the
stress aspect as acutely at this moment, is that this particular framing helps
me to approach my current problems with curiosity, with an appetite for
learning and experimentation, and with the acceptance that my performance could
be far from perfect, perhaps even to the point of failure.</p>
<p>Some days will be good and some days will be bad.</p>
<p>(Even outside of the practice framing, one just has to accept that <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"><em>some days
gonna be crap</em></a>.)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, every day is a brand new opportunity to practice the
difficult new stuff, and to become gradually better at it, until one day, just
maybe, comfort slowly starts overtaking discomfort.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>