<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>backyard philosophy on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/backyard-philosophy/</link><description>Recent content in backyard philosophy on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 21:53:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/backyard-philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #233: Atomic party sections</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</guid><description> Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.
Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.
(Don&amp;rsquo;t) Stress for success (aka 4000 weeks at 60%) It&amp;rsquo;s really quite busy at work, perhaps even verging on the slightly too busy territory.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering
the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="don-t--stress-for-success--aka-4000-weeks-at-60">(Don&rsquo;t) Stress for success (aka 4000 weeks at 60%)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s really quite busy at work, perhaps even verging on the slightly too busy
territory.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m consistently putting in stretches of focused, high intensity work to help
push us into calmer waters.</p>
<p>However, in spite of all of this, my stress levels seem to have have subsided
to quite an extent over the last few weeks.</p>
<p>This could be ascribed to me slowly moving out of <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">new challenge discomfort
territory</a>, because I&rsquo;m either getting better at what I&rsquo;m supposed to be doing,
or, if you want to be cynical, I just care a little less.</p>
<p>Maybe these two are the same.</p>
<p>I like to think that it could also be the growing effect of <em>Four Thousand
Weeks: Time and How to Use It</em>, <a href="/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/#how-i-m-putting-down-my-work">the book I mentioned in WHV-231</a> that so
eloquently and quite urgently makes the case that because life is so stupidly
short, and you&rsquo;re not even going to get close to Getting your Things Done, and
that working hard so that you can relax at some future point in time is a
terribly imprudent approach forced upon us by our instrumentalist society, you
should instead do your best extracting every bit of enjoyment from every moment
that you get, when you get it.</p>
<p>Every morning is an opportunity for a mini coffee and breakfast party, and
every evening is an opportunity for a mini dinner party, both of these with the
people, big and small, I hold the most dear.</p>
<p>Every day I do need to work, but there is ample opportunity for curiosity, for
learning, and for offering a helping hand.</p>
<p>There is generally also time to go out for a wide-open-perception run in the
sun.</p>
<p>All of this is available to you if you can just learn how to keep your own set
of instrumentalising demons safely locked up in their cages. (these are the
gremlins who keep on bugging you to try to finish one more thing.)</p>
<p>As Burkeman writes on page 144:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To the philosophers of the ancient world, leisure wasn&rsquo;t the means to some
other end; on the contrary, it was the end to which everything else worth doing
was a means.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Back in <a href="/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/#flip-it">WHV #222, I tried to say something similar, just far less eloquently</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve completed only a pinch over 60% of the book. I might have more to say when
it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">Dropbox Paper (aka mobile note-taking evolving)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s no secret around these parts that <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#mobile">the mobile aspects of my otherwise
pretty respectable note-taking game are weak</a>. (In short: Emacs Org mode is
amazing and can do <em>anything</em>, <strong>except</strong> when on my iPhone. Moar shorter: iPhone =
Org mode Kryptonite)</p>
<p>Somehow, in spite of being so deep in with Dropbox, and in spite of using
<a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper">Dropbox Paper</a> for other things, I overlooked it when evaluating solutions for
mobile note capture all the way back in 2019.</p>
<p>This weekend, because I had to scrounge around for an important bit of
information I <em>knew</em> I had stored somewhere (it turned out to be in my Apple
Notes doh), I spent some time trying to find a tool that would give me
mobile-editable notes that would turn up more readily in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that Dropbox Paper documents turn up in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Who would have guessed?!</p>
<p>In addition to that, Paper has:</p>
<ul>
<li>markdown support</li>
<li>syntax highlighting of triple-backtick source code blocks</li>
<li>LaTeX math!</li>
<li>embedding of arbitrary media which gets automatically uploaded to dropbox on
drag and drop</li>
<li>easy linking to other Paper docs</li>
<li>checklists</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Cue sound of another personal knowledge management puzzle piece snapping into place&hellip;</em></p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m not allowed to talk about it here, because the blog post in question
happened <em>after</em> this blog post&rsquo;s legally allowed observed timespan, but shortly
in the future, I will also solve the issue of being able to search through and
preview all of my Org mode notes on the iPhone.</p>
<p>Post is on vxlabs if you&rsquo;re from the (near) future.</p>
<h2 id="a-truly-spectacular-long-weekend-in-betty-s">A truly spectacular long weekend in Betty&rsquo;s</h2>
<p>The second week ended with a weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay that was so spectacular
that it deserves its own section in this blog post.</p>
<p>Well this is it. The section dedicated to the weekend. I hope you like it.</p>
<h2 id="the-section-at-the-end">The section at the end</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this.</p>
<p>I wish you continuous and consistent atomic party moments.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #231: Two thousand four hundred fourty-four</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW
This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to Sunday August 29, 2021.
Orbital mechanics that are important to me Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.
That&amp;rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.
Let me try again:
Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="pano_from_watsonia.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &ldquo;run&rdquo; with bestie DW</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to
Sunday August 29, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="orbital-mechanics-that-are-important-to-me">Orbital mechanics that are important to me</h2>
<p>Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.</p>
<p>Let me try again:</p>
<p>Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for
another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</p>
<p>As is our custom here, I get to increase the mathematical encoding (this is a
fantastically consistent and useful approach to the structured modelling of
reality) of my time as an alive unit by one.</p>
<p>When I was younger, it was possible to use this number to impress one&rsquo;s
friends. Sometimes, the number of an older sibling or even a parent could also
be used to increase social standing, if one&rsquo;s own number was still quite small.</p>
<p>Ironically, as the number gets bigger, we prefer not to talk or even think
about it too much.</p>
<p>Thanks to math, the number could in theory be transformed into &ldquo;number of
revolutions remaining&rdquo;, but fortunately our complex physiologies and
environments greatly complicate the estimation of the required term for that
transformation, in this case greatly comforting us with uncertainty.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS&hellip;</p>
<p>I had an amazing birthday.</p>
<p>From morning video chats with homies, to working lunches that turned into
superbly relaxed lunches with old friends, surprise visits by far-off friends
the day before, birthday mountain runs with a bestie, and so many (voice)
messages on various platforms from friends everywhere, my birthday was a
friendship-and-life-affirming business.</p>
<p>Friends, thank you for working together like that. You are all breath-taking!</p>
<p>P.S. Experiencing this acted as a beautiful reminder to send that message,
write that email or make that call whenever you can find an excuse!</p>
<h2 id="how-i-m-putting-down-my-work"><em>How</em> I&rsquo;m putting down my work</h2>
<p>In the previous edition of the WHV, I talked about <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">the important skill of being
able to put down one&rsquo;s work</a>.</p>
<p>Here I would just like to mention how I&rsquo;ve been trying to practise this in my
life, especially because it really seems to have helped me since we last spoke.</p>
<p>Ok, get ready!</p>
<p>You Won&rsquo;t Believe This One Trick&hellip;</p>
<p>At 17:00, 17:30 at the latest, I explicitly switch off any tools that I use for
work, and disconnect from all dayjob-related systems.</p>
<p>Work email closed, development enviroments exited, docker containers all stopped.</p>
<p>For good measure, I roll a tumbleweed or two across my office floor, blowing
air out through my pursed lips.</p>
<p>The thing is, my brain has the tendency to continue cogitating on the last
thing I kept it busy with.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I used to have the tendency to still try and solve that problem
before bed, only resulting in me later lying in said bed, unable to get my
brain to stop cogitating, leading to bad sleep, contributing to subpar
performance the next day.</p>
<p>I have to qualify here that putting down work tools does not exclude me from
picking up hobby programming projects later in the evening, after &ldquo;The Making
of The Dinner, With Wine&rdquo; and &ldquo;The Chilling With The Family&rdquo; stages.</p>
<p>Although programming plays a substantial part of dayjob, I have never stopped
enjoying and being relaxed by this activity in the recreational setting.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, making a point of putting down work on time, starting
the gradual wind-down, has drastically reduced the number and severity of
<em>Trying Unsuccessfully to Solve All Work Problems In The Dark, From One&rsquo;s Bed</em> for
me.</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/">Oliver Burkeman</a>, author of <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">the putting-down-your-work post</a>, also wrote a
book titled <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2021/aug/16/four-thousand-weeks-time-and-how-to-use-it-by-oliver-burkeman-review">Four Thousand Weeks: Time and How to Use It</a>, which my mom got me
for my birthday (THANKS MOM!).</p>
<p>As soon as I&rsquo;m done with <a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">Seligman&rsquo;s book flourish</a>, I&rsquo;ll start with this book,
which will hopefully filter through to this blog.</p>
<p>In the meantime, here&rsquo;s the blurb which is already food  for thought:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The average human lifespan is absurdly, insultingly brief.</p>
<p>If you live to be 80, you’ll have had about 4,000 weeks. But that’s no reason for despair.</p>
<p>Confronting our radical finitude  and how little control we really have  is the key to a fulfilling and meaningfully productive life.</p>
</blockquote>








<figure><a href="helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&amp;rsquo;ve been treated with."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&rsquo;ve been treated with.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #230: Follow your blisters</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="van_breda_cottage_angles.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&amp;rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &amp;ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&amp;rdquo; (I didn&amp;rsquo;t and I don&amp;rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV covers the three weeks from Monday July 26 to Sunday August 15.</p>
<h2 id="why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">Why I don&rsquo;t like dark mode anymore</h2>
<p>As you might know, I spent most of my working (and sometimes hobby, we&rsquo;ll get
back to that further down) hours in front of this screen or some other screen.</p>
<p>Up to now, I was really convinced that I preferred dark mode everywhere, until
recently two events transpired:</p>
<p>I started noticing more eye-strain than usual, even on my 27&quot; screen, something
which had a perceptible effect on my productivity. This I resignedly ascribed
to my advancing age, although I did find the suddenness quite surprising,
especially since I recently had my glasses updated.</p>
<p>Then, after years with only the admittedly brilliant <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">zenburn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/fniessen/emacs-leuven-theme">Leuven (dark)</a>
Emacs themes checking all of the boxes for me, I finally ran into a really
interesting and usable theme called <a href="https://github.com/kunalb/poet">Poet</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s interesting, because it uses variable pitched fonts for everything but
code, tables and elements of the fixed width domain, where most Emacs fonts
stick to the traditional all-fixed-width approach.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="20210822-poet-theme-screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can probably understand that for someone who uses Emacs almost primarily
for technical notes and other writing, this book-like appearance could work
really well.</p>
<p>The theme was even more interesting for me personally, as it suddenly became
clear as day that I experienced almost no eye-strain when using Emacs with this
lighter theme than when I used any of my other usually dark-themed tools!</p>
<p>It became obvious that poet-theme&rsquo;s lighter background was much easier on my
eyes than dark mode in vscode. (No, this specific advantage can&rsquo;t be ascribed
to Emacs itself I&rsquo;m afraid.)</p>
<p>Reading pages such as <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/digital-eye-strain/is-dark-mode-better-for-eyes/">this</a> explains that dark mode leads to pupils having to
dilate more to let in more light, which there is less of with dark themes.</p>
<p>This leads to, just like with cameras and any other optics with lenses and
apertures, a shortened depth of field, and hence more difficulty focusing on
the screen!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/dark-mode/">This article by the well-known Nielsen Norman Group</a> nicely summarises research
on this topic. In short:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In people with normal vision (or corrected-to-normal vision), visual
performance tends to be better with light mode, whereas some people with
cataract and related disorders may perform better with dark mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Up until recently, I did not experience a qualitative difference in vision
between dark and light, but I sit here relieved that my eye-strain issue has
been resolved by an Emacs theme!</p>
<h2 id="know-how-to-put-down-your-work">Know how to put down your work</h2>
<p>The following take from <a href="https://twitter.com/brandsrock/status/1426163442256330753">a recent tweet by mike joubert</a> struck me
(tweet-take-strike! words are funny&hellip;):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly valuable skill isn&rsquo;t the capacity to push yourself harder, but to
stop and recuperate despite the discomfort of knowing that work remains
unfinished, emails unanswered, other people&rsquo;s demands unfulfilled.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">article, titled <em>The three-or-four-hours rule for getting creative work
done</em></a>, is itself a good read about the observation that creative types (amongst
which I count engineers) have at their best three to four hours of focus time
per day &mdash; so it is crucially important that their days are structured such
that there is an <strong>uninterrupted</strong> block of three to four hours inside of which
that lovely focus has the possibility of appearing.</p>
<p>The tweet-extract focuses on the similarly important but more subtle art of
being able to put one&rsquo;s work down, completely, when that block of time is over,
even when it feels like the work is far from complete.</p>
<p>I especially like that it also explicitly mentions the illusions created by
one&rsquo;s perception of &ldquo;other people&rsquo;s demands&rdquo;, something that ironically becomes
even harder to walk away from when one is more tired at the end of the work
day.</p>
<p>For me, becoming better at putting work down has pleasant echoes of running
slower to run faster, of emptiness in art and more broadly, <a href="https://zenhabits.net/work-less/">choosing fewer f*cks
to give</a>.</p>
<h2 id="follow-your-blisters">Follow your blisters</h2>
<p>On the topic of choosing your ducks&hellip;</p>
<p>I initially did not like <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/what-you-should-follow-instead-of-your-passion">this HBR</a> post when it first crossed my stream, because
it smacks a bit too much of the current social media style of &ldquo;wisdom&rdquo;, namely
&ldquo;everything you need to know in 280 characters&rdquo;, or &ldquo;this 1 minute tiktok video
will change your life&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the title is pretty clickbaity: <em>What You Should
Follow Instead of Your Passion</em>.</p>
<p>However, the core message of the post, which I could not help reading, did
stick with me, and after a few days I realised that I would have to go find the
article again in order to talk about it here.</p>
<p>The core message is to replace <em>find your passion</em> with <strong><em>Find your blisters.</em></strong></p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s point is that folks often get the wrong idea with <em>passion</em> as
something that is simply always delightful, whilst the thing you should
actually be looking for, is that activity that you simply are unable to stop
doing, even when you try, and especially even when you don&rsquo;t directly derive
pleasure from it, for example because you feel that you&rsquo;re not that good at it.</p>
<p>They give the personal example of writing.</p>
<p>Although they&rsquo;ve been at it for years, it&rsquo;s still a difficult and laborious
process, and they are often not happy with the results.</p>
<p>However, they have been unable to stop from returning to writing projects again
and again over the years.</p>
<p>Ironically, even although they find that they are still bad at it, they have in
fact become really good, simply because they have been pushing through and
practising more than almost anyone else over the years.</p>
<p>I really like this down-to-earth view.</p>
<p>One can indeed source almost unlimited amounts of energy from one&rsquo;s &ldquo;blisters&rdquo;,
but true benefits will for a large part be brought about by a <a href="/tags/practice/">lifetime of often
challenging practice</a>.</p>








<figure><a href="flowers_everywhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &amp;ldquo;blommetjieskyk&amp;rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #227: Reality bending security blanket</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 22:15:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.
This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.
Groundhog Lockdown On the above-mentioned Sunday, president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4, one level more serious from where we were.
For us this means that schools are closing a week earlier for the July vacation, and hence will have to open a week earlier, and hence will have a severe effect on the breakaway we had planned, an effect of the cancellation variety.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="backyard_walk_s_and_i.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/backyard_walk_s_and_i_hud53395ab9ad0e52aa68396f98a5f295f_1900088_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a walk by life partner and genetic progenitor unit, photo by partner.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This 227th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the two weeks from
Monday June 14 to Sunday June 27.</p>
<h2 id="groundhog-lockdown">Groundhog Lockdown</h2>
<p>On the above-mentioned Sunday, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/level-4-lockdown-for-south-africa-for-14-days-2021-6">president Ramaphosa announced lockdown level 4</a>,
one level more serious from where we were.</p>
<p>For us this means that schools are closing a week earlier for the July
vacation, and hence will have to open a week earlier, and hence will have a
severe effect on the breakaway we had planned, an effect of the
<em>cancellation</em> variety.</p>
<p>Although frustrating (some of us really need that precious time away to keep
calm and carry on afterwards), we don&rsquo;t really have anything to complain about
if that is our biggest problem.</p>
<p>Gauteng province has been hit really hard by the third wave of COVID, and
specifically this new Delta variant.</p>
<p>This modified lockdown level 4 explicitly prohibits travel into and out of the
province in order to help stem the disease&rsquo;s spread.</p>
<p>In other news, our vaccination is making progress, albeit at a slower pace than
most people had hoped.</p>
<p>In a few days they are going to start with the over 50s. No, this does not
include me yet, although I am close.</p>
<h2 id="amazon-document-culture">Amazon document culture</h2>
<p>Last week, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=27545331">Hacker News discussed</a> a really interesting <a href="https://www.justingarrison.com/blog/2021-03-15-the-document-culture-of-amazon/">blog post by an Amazon
employee about Amazon&rsquo;s document culture</a>.</p>
<p>In short, at Amazon, a meeting can only happen if a document has been written
detailing what is to be discussed during the meeting.</p>
<p>At the start of the meeting, everyone gets from 10 minutes to half an hour,
depending on what makes sense for the document under discussion, to read the
document, and only then the meeting starts.</p>
<p>This approach has many advantages, discussed in the blog post.</p>
<p>What I personally like about doing it this way, is that the convenor of the
meeting has to pay a price for that meeting, namely sitting down and spending
time to structure their thoughts on paper well enough so it will satisfy the
expectations of the participants.</p>
<p>Furthermore, by dedicating quiet time to reading the document, one has a
slightly better guarantee that everyone is up to date with the background, and,
more interesting to me, is that it sets a more deliberate and thoughtful mood
for the whole meeting.</p>
<p>Of course I tried this out at the first high-level meeting that I could, where
I had to present a plan to the participants.</p>
<p>It felt a bit strange initiating this silent reading at the start, but my
perception is that it contributed to a higher quality discussion afterwards.</p>
<p>In this case it was easy, because the goal of the meeting was to present a plan
that was already a document. However, this is something I will definitely want
to repeat.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, the document will be all that is required.</p>
<h2 id="your-choice">Your choice</h2>
<p>In <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">WHV #226</a> I wrote that I had chosen to be in the situation that was causing
stress due to its new challenges.</p>
<p>Friend SvdW (jokingly? chidingly?) commented via private communications
channels that that &ldquo;choice&rdquo; had surprised him, seeing that <a href="https://philosophybreak.com/articles/free-will-illusion-sam-harris/">we have no free
will</a>.</p>
<p>He is right of course, but in this case it <em>is</em> in fact all about the illusion,
about being subjectively convinced that one is the agent and the author of
one&rsquo;s current situation.</p>
<p>This did remind me something I wrote in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#productivity-system-tuneup">WHV #185</a> about how this same framing
can be effective against procrastination:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have chosen to
take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having decided
to commit, i.e. active.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the cases where you believe that you <em>are</em> probably the agent of your
situation, it can really help to verbalise that to yourself in the way
described above.</p>
<p>This can sometimes be tricky, because so much of it has to do with potentially
subjective-reality-bending framing, which could get in the way of addressing
problems external to oneself.</p>
<p>If you apply This One Trick, and you do a great job, how real were those
external problems in the first place?</p>
<p>On days like these, I get a feeling, albeit an extremely faint one, for why
Descartes constructed the mental security blanket of <em>cogito ergo sum</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #226: Stress practice</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 16:07:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</guid><description> Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.
Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.
As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&amp;rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (Youth Day), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth Emacs Org-mode / ox-hugo blogging machine (read this github issue for more details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this combination has saved me in the past.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the
week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys_run_pano_20210612.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu9c9be7fbcab668463ece1d5d7459b225_1143636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (<a href="https://www.gov.za/youth-day">Youth
Day</a>), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth
Emacs Org-mode / <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo">ox-hugo</a> blogging machine (read <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo/issues/447">this github issue</a> for more
details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this
combination has saved me in the past.</p>
<h2 id="solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">Solstice tipping point is coming!</h2>
<p>The last thing we&rsquo;re supposed to do is to wish even just a little bit for time
to pass more quickly, for fairly obvious reasons.</p>
<p>However, when you&rsquo;re a few days from the darkest point in the year, it&rsquo;s hard
not to.</p>
<p>We currently have 9 hours and 56 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s just two minutes, and a few days, from the winter solstice on June 21,
when we&rsquo;ll have to make do with 9 hours and 54 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>I mention this here, because those 6 AM wake-ups feel more and more like the
middle of the night.</p>
<p>After the solstice, I&rsquo;ll start imagining the sun coming up a few moments
earlier every morning, and it will.</p>
<p>(Well, it will, eventually. Reader WIMM just pointed out via email that
although the days start getting longer, the sunrise will initially become even
a minute later, before finally becoming earlier starting from July 11. Read
more <a href="https://theconversation.com/why-the-sunrise-is-still-later-after-the-winter-solstice-shortest-day-77628">here</a> (thanks WIMM) or check the tables <a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-africa/stellenbosch?month=6&amp;year=2021">here</a>.)</p>
<p>It has been &hellip; <code>1 year and 11 months</code> &hellip; since <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/">the previous mention of winter
solstice on this blog</a>.</p>
<h2 id="avoid-the-jbl-endurance-run-bt-earphones-at-all-costs">Avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones at all costs</h2>
<p>A month ago <a href="/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/#world-in-my-eyes">I wrote about the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a> that I was
initially so happy with, which then spontaneously broke after a few hours of
running, and which I then returned for a replacement.</p>
<p>Well, the replacement set of <a href="https://eu.jbl.com/JBL+ENDURANCE+RUNBT.html?dwvar%5FJBL%20ENDURANCE%20RUNBT%5Fcolor=Black-GLOBAL-Current">proudly sweat-proof JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a>
lasted for about 9 hours of running, at which point they spontaneously broke in
exactly the same way.</p>
<p>Out of nowhere, the loud crackling sound started in the earpiece opposite to
the site with the control unit.</p>
<p>This crackling sound (similar to the disturbance you hear when speaker wires
have a connection issue) did not stop, even after un-pairing and even after
switching off the unit.</p>
<p>Connecting the charger after this would result in the charge light flickering
and fading in-and-out in a decidedly analogue fashion.</p>
<p>After experiencing the exact same problem with two different units, I am wary
wasting more time on a third set.</p>
<p>This was quite a disappointment, because mechanically this design was perfect
for me.</p>
<p>I will continue on my search for the perfect (1. secure in my large and
sometimes perspiring ears, so needs something in addition to just ear canal fit
and 2. durable, i.e. continues working <em>long</em> after the first 9 hours of
running) set of running earphones, and I&rsquo;ll keep you up to date on my findings.</p>
<p>In the meantime, please avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones.</p>
<h2 id="remote-work-culture-is-hard-work">Remote work culture is hard work</h2>
<p>During our Tuesday evening meetup, Theunis de Klerk of <a href="https://www.noldor.co.za/">Noldor</a> (the now fully
remote tech company, not <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noldor">the race of elves from Middle Earth</a>, although there is
a link here) gave an interesting and inspiring talk on how they have built and
cultivate great remote work culture.</p>
<p>This was an insightful look into an organization where the top leadership
continuously pours a great deal of thought and energy into maintaining healthy
culture, even in a fully remote environment with parts in different timezones.</p>
<p>On the one hand, it&rsquo;s great seeing working examples like this, on the other, it
can be quite a daunting prospect when you start thinking about how to apply
this in your own environment.</p>
<p>I believe that the future of knowledge work will <em>not</em> involve highly qualified
folks having to spend 8 hours per day at their desk because we still have not
learned that work is all about contributing value, and not about the number of
hours spent in captivity at one&rsquo;s desk.</p>
<p>That being said, during the current global remote working experiment, although
we are learning how to roll with value-generation, I do miss some of the almost
effortlessly and socially generated collaboration glue that at its best gets
folks almost instinctively chasing the same worthy goals.</p>
<p>(On the other hand, at its worst, it causes conflicts, grudges and ulcers, so
there&rsquo;s that&hellip;)</p>
<p>I would like to wrap this ramble up with one conclusion, and one interesting
tweet storm by Steven Sinofsky of Andreesen Horowitz:</p>
<ul>
<li>Conclusion: 1. Am I overestimating how &ldquo;easy&rdquo; social cohesion was when we
were in the office? 2. How do we go about getting back that real or imagined
social cohesion in this fully remote setting?</li>
<li><a href="https://a16z.com/2021/06/12/disruption-at-work-its-more-than-just-wfh/">Highly interesting tweet storm about the issue being larger and more
intricate than just WFH vs hybrid vs HQ</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="eternal-practice-vs-stress">Eternal practice vs stress</h2>
<p>I do need to note here (for future me) that I was consistently far grumpier
than usual for the last few days of the week under examination here.</p>
<p>When I say grumpy, I do mean quite detectably so.</p>
<p>This is definitely not my preferred state, so I&rsquo;m even meta-grumpy about that.</p>
<p>My retro- and introspection during the weekend came up with &ldquo;more stress than
usual&rdquo;, which is indeed probably a main contributor (wow, thanks work).</p>
<p>However, being grumpy or not is still fully my responsibility.</p>
<p>Increased stress at work is currently primarily due to new responsibilities and
the (often amplified by one&rsquo;s own imagination) expectations of colleagues, and
the unsurprising feeling of discomfort that is associated with finding oneself
faced with new kinds of challenges that you are not accustomed to (<em>cf.</em>
&ldquo;comfort zone&rdquo; and <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">stages 2 to 4 of the creative process</a>).</p>
<p>During the weekend I first resolved simply to be less grumpy (yes, you can do
that).</p>
<p>Fortunately, I also had a spot of insight as to how the root cause, i.e. the
work-related stress, could be better addressed in my specific case.</p>
<p>You see, I have chosen to be in this situation. I would have preferred the new
challenges without the concomitant stress, but that&rsquo;s unfortunately not how
<em>this</em> human normally works.</p>
<p>The realisation that I had was that this too is simply part of my lifelong
practice session.</p>
<p>I first talked about the idea of life being continuous pracrtice back in <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">WHV
#133</a>, and again later in <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">WHV #144</a> when I got around to reading a
reader-recommended book on the topic, titled &ldquo;Mastery&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Something I did not mention back then, probably because I only experience the
stress aspect as acutely at this moment, is that this particular framing helps
me to approach my current problems with curiosity, with an appetite for
learning and experimentation, and with the acceptance that my performance could
be far from perfect, perhaps even to the point of failure.</p>
<p>Some days will be good and some days will be bad.</p>
<p>(Even outside of the practice framing, one just has to accept that <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"><em>some days
gonna be crap</em></a>.)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, every day is a brand new opportunity to practice the
difficult new stuff, and to become gradually better at it, until one day, just
maybe, comfort slowly starts overtaking discomfort.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #225: Just a perfect weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</guid><description> Dear reader,
Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.
Keyboard update: K1 You&amp;rsquo;ll remember from WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the Womier K87 with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown switches.
That keyboard is so much fun to type on.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear reader,</p>
<p>Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th
installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="la_autumn_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="keyboard-update-k1">Keyboard update: K1</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll remember from <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the
Womier K87</a> with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown
switches.</p>
<p>That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt
Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the case that fingers also like the exercise, just like their
human owners.</p>
<p>I was not planning to buy any keyboards again soon, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was quite curious whether low profile key switches (that is, slightly less
finger travel) would be a good compromise between the fun of the Womier and the
efficiency of the Sculpt.</li>
<li>The K1 was on my list of candidates of keyboards with low-profile mechanical
switches.</li>
<li>I find it difficult to resist a good deal.</li>
</ul>
<p>You see, a friendly little bird (who also hangs out on the keyboards channel of
the zatech slack) told me about the extra-special Takealot birthday special
discount on <a href="https://www.imore.com/keychron-k1-v4-review">the Keychron K1 V4 87-key keyboard</a>.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a credit card transaction, a week of waiting for delivery and
another week of getting accustomed to the new board, and here we are, with at
least me typing these words on the new K1.</p>
<p>It took a while to get used to the keycaps, which can be a slippery sometimes
(or rather, my finger tip traction is variable), but my typing speed and
accuracy on this thing are in the neighbourhood of where they should be.</p>
<p>The thing is a great deal more <em>stylish</em> than my Womier; the Womier is that
guilty pleasure 80s disco that you really love, the K1 could work in a serious
coffee shop.</p>
<p>Also, having a keyboard which can switch this easily between wired operation
(the default for my desktop) and three different bluetooth connections is
pretty convenient. On trips where I usually only take the MacBook, I could
consider taking the K1 along when I have to do A Great Deal of Serious Typing.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I can&rsquo;t yet say if the low profile switches are indeed
the compromise that I wondered about. My subjective impression now is indeed
that my fingers don&rsquo;t get so physically tired as sometimes happens with the
Womier, but I&rsquo;ll have to switch between them a few times to get a better idea.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am certainly enjoying the experience of typing on
this thing, and I am certainly wondering about the interesting role that
different types of mechanical keyboards have begun to play in my computing
life.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-about-a-new-book-notes-post-about-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Lessons about a new book notes post about Seven and a Half Lessons about the Brain</h2>
<p>After two months of early(ish) morning typing on various keyboards, I finally
managed to wrap up <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">my book notes about Seven and a Half Lessons about the
Brain</a>, a fantastic book by neuro-scientist and psychologist Lisa Feldman
Barrett.</p>
<p>I had plans, in retrospect clearly too ambitious, to have at least two (2) book
notes posts out in Q1 of this year (after it took me months to complete <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my book
notes on Creativity, Inc.</a> by the end of last year).</p>
<p>That goal was necessarily postponed to Q2, and as we can all see now, there is
not enough time for a second post like this.</p>
<p>Either I have to change the format of the book notes to something more compact,
like a bunch of bullet lists, or I should make peace with the fact that I write
these like I write them, a little prose with quotes interspersed that can
generally be read like a mini story itself, and with the fact that they&rsquo;re
going to take as much time as they do.</p>
<p>Sometimes I have mixed feelings about the practice itself.</p>
<p>It takes fragments of hobby time spread out over weeks, fragments of time that
I could probably use for more reading, other interesting tidbits and, uhm,
extra work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it feels like a sort of a mini-rebellion doing exactly this,
assembling so many little pieces into something slightly more coherent and
significant, something that stands apart from work.</p>
<p>It seems I do know what to do.</p>
<p>Thanks for the chat!</p>
<h2 id="perfect-weekends-and-the-necessary-reminders-that-precede-them">Perfect weekends and the necessary reminders that precede them</h2>
<p>The weekend of June 4, 2021, was unexpectedly perfect, and I would like to make
note of that here for future me.</p>
<p>This is the recipe that we followed, utterly by happy accident:</p>
<ul>
<li>1x reminder during the week to really focus on the now.</li>
<li>1x absolutely perfect autumn weather package: balmy 20ish degrees Celsius,
lots of sun, very little wind.</li>
<li>3x braais, one per day, with various subsets of family.</li>
<li>2x runs: one a long weekend morning run, and the other an unplanned one
with GOU#1.</li>
<li>1x polishing and publishing of the blog post mentioned above.</li>
<li>1x unexpected Sunday evening star watching with GOU#2.</li>
</ul>
<p>One would think that daily practice would help, but it turns out that sometimes
a serendipitous reminder by a friend can help to switch one&rsquo;s brain into
exactly the right gear, right before the weekend.</p>
<p>During our Friday evening start-the-weekend ritual (it&rsquo;s a braai. surprise!), I
had my first quite visceral &ldquo;THIS, this is it, this is everything&rdquo;
experience. (so lovely)</p>
<p>From then on, brain remained in the right mode right through most of the
weekend.</p>
<p>If you ever run into me before the weekend (it&rsquo;s always before the weekend!), I
would be grateful if you could remind me that it is in fact now.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you much nowness.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #222: Scotty, we need more power!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 14:07:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/</guid><description> Welcome back everyone!
It&amp;rsquo;s now early(ish) Friday morning of the weekend after, but I would like to get the 222d edition of the WHV out, namely the one covering the two weeks from Monday, April 19 to Sunday, May 2, 2021.
My excuse for skipping a week is that the second week was spent on vacation. Exhibit A is shown below:
Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s now early(ish) Friday morning of the weekend after, but I would like to
get the 222d edition of the WHV out, namely the one covering the two weeks from
Monday, April 19 to Sunday, May 2, 2021.</p>
<p>My excuse for skipping a week is that the second week was spent on
vacation. Exhibit A is shown below:</p>








<figure><a href="st_francis_beach_run_202104.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu56cda6ac1a19ad77b512a8eda60b2857_609367_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu56cda6ac1a19ad77b512a8eda60b2857_609367_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu56cda6ac1a19ad77b512a8eda60b2857_609367_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu56cda6ac1a19ad77b512a8eda60b2857_609367_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu56cda6ac1a19ad77b512a8eda60b2857_609367_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The rest of this post has (imagine the following in Bill Hader&rsquo;s Stefon voice):</p>
<ul>
<li>migraines and science</li>
<li>scifi ipads</li>
<li>VR</li>
<li>a life tip</li>
</ul>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="brain-glitch">Brain glitch</h2>
<p>I lost almost half a work day to a <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/conditions/ocular-migraine.htm">visual migraine</a>.</p>
<p>Looking at my notes, it seems that these only started during the past few
years, although it could be that I just didn&rsquo;t record the previous ones.</p>
<p>It starts out with bright spots in the middle of your field of vision, which
slowly grow until they form jiggly circles. This is not ideal, but at least you
can now look through their centres. Haha.</p>
<p>It looks eerily identical to the illustration on the linked website.</p>
<p>After half an hour to about an hour, sometimes a headache will hit, and
sometimes not. This time it was unusually intense, and I had no choice but to
detach from work for a while.</p>
<p>Looking back at my notes now, I really appreciate the time-stamped entries as
the migraine developed all the way to its end.</p>
<p>Lesson reaffirmed: Take good notes, no matter what.</p>
<h3 id="fascinating-scientific-review-of-migraine-and-metabolism">Fascinating scientific review of migraine and metabolism</h3>
<p>After a related chat with a friend who reported that in his case blood sugar
played a role (he can&rsquo;t skip breakfast, and can&rsquo;t eat too sweet), my
permanently foraging internet tentacles entirely coincidentally dredged up this
publication in Nature Reviews Neurology titled &ldquo;The metabolic face of
migraine - from pathophysiology to treatment&rdquo; (<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31586135/">pubmed</a>, <a href="https://orbi.uliege.be/bitstream/2268/247255/1/Gross%20et%20al%20Metabolic%20face%20of%20migraine-Nat%20Rev%20Neurol%202019.pdf">PDF fulltext</a>).</p>
<p>The article is pretty dense, but here are some interesting observations:</p>
<p>The first is from box 1: In some humans, when brain energy demands outstrip
metabolic reserves, rendering them vulnerable to disruption of cortical
homeostatis (energy balance), there is a whole cascade of events that,
according to the article&rsquo;s authors, might be started by the pannexin channels
in neurons. (These channels act as sensors of cortical homeostasis.)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s quite straight-forward then that (haha):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The final result of this cascade is trigeminovascular activation and calcitonin
gene-related peptide release in the extradural space, which leads to headache.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Following from there, they postulate two alternate pathways that cause
respectively migraine with and without aura (visual effects).</p>
<p>In other words, when your brain requires more energy than you have available,
and you are one of the many genetic variants who suffer from this mechanism,
you could be in for some migraine when your body reacts to the imbalance.</p>
<p>On top of that, the authors present one more good reason <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#skip-you-some-breakfast-for-great-good">to become fat-adapted</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>These increases in lipolysis and ketogenesis can also be interpreted as
counter-​regulatory responses to a cerebral energy deficit. Given that ketone
bodies are an efficient alternative fuel for the brain when glucose
availability is low, their elevation would be expected to restore brain energy
homeostasis. However, the Western carbohydrate-​laden diet means that in most
people in Western countries the brain is not keto-​adapted so does not have the
enzymatic composition and transporters to make use of ketone bodies produced
during an energy crisis.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Box 2 in the article provides the following quite intriguing &ldquo;Suggested
approach to improving mitochondrial function and energy metabolism in
migraine&rdquo; (emphasis mine, so that you can skim over if you want):</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>Individualize supplementation of micronutrients. To ensure that all
micronutrients needed for mitochondrial function are available, laboratory
tests can be used to individualize supplementation with minerals,
hydrophobic and lipophilic vitamins and trace mineralsthat are deficient.</li>
<li>Reduce oxidative stress and increase antioxidants. Measurement of oxidative
and/or nitrosative stress levels and antioxidant status in individuals could
detect a potential mismatch between oxidative stress levels and antioxidant
capacity and enable therapeutic adjustments to be made, although studies are
needed to prove that such an approach improves migraine
management. Strategies to reduce oxidative stress could include <strong><strong>elimination
or reduction of processed food, food with a high glycaemic index and</strong></strong>
<strong><strong>alcohol, use of green or blue light filtering glasses, interruption of
hormone-based contraception, lifestyle changes</strong></strong> and addition of
antioxidants,such as polyphenols, coenzyme Q10, α-lipoic acid or
β-hydroxybutyrate mineral salts, to the diet.</li>
<li><strong><strong>Stabilize blood glucose levels</strong></strong>. An oral glucose tolerance testshould be
undertaken in patients with migraine and clinical features that suggest
glucose intolerance or a family history of glucose intolerance. Patients
with reactive hyperinsulinaemia and reactive hypoglycaemia are likely to
benefit from stabilization of blood glucose levels, which can often be
achieved with dietary adjustments.</li>
<li>Provide an <strong><strong>alternative energy substrate for the brain</strong></strong>. For patients with
compromised energy metabolism, an alternative source of fuel for the brain,
in addition to glucose and lactate, might be beneficial. This source can be
generated with a ketogenic diet and/or use of exogenous ketogenic
substances, such asmedium-chain triglycerides or exogenous ketone body
salts. Further placebo-controlled trials are needed to validate ketogenic
therapies in migraine.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="4-20-ipad-pro-supercomputers-straight-outta-scifi">4/20 iPad Pro supercomputers straight outta SciFi</h2>
<p>On 4/20 I tuned into a liveblog (I think it was <a href="https://live.arstechnica.com/apples-april-20-2021-spring-loaded-event/">the one by Ars Technica</a>) of
Apple&rsquo;s release event.</p>
<p>Apple is currently evolving the computing landscape quite substantially, so I
find it immensely interesting to see what they are bringing next.</p>
<p>They did a whole bunch this time, but what struck me as the most significant,
is that they introduced two new iPad Pro tablets with M1 chips.</p>
<p>You know, that same M1 chip powering <a href="/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/">the super fast and energy-efficient laptop
on which I&rsquo;m typing up this post</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to sticking a desktop-class processor (err, desktop-class
performance, but mobile-level battery efficiency) back into a mobile device
that you can also buy with 2 terabytes of built-in storage (I find this a bit
surreal), the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2021/4/21/22395449/apple-ipad-pro-2021-liquid-retina-xdr-mini-led-explainer">new Liquid Retina XDR display on the top-end iPad Pro</a> has 10000
of a new kind of micro-led just for the back-lighting and thus is able to offer
1000 nits of full-screen brightness and adaptively up to 1600 nits on portions
of the screen, all of that with a contrast ratio of 1 to&hellip;. ONE MILLION.</p>
<p>As I was reading this, and later listening as the excitement led (&hellip;) me to
tune in to the video stream, one of my inner voices marvelled at the sheer
technological innovation on display (sorry can&rsquo;t stop) here.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m curious to see how this new class of supercomputer-level tablet device is
going to change how we humans interact with the digital world.</p>
<h2 id="oculus-quest-2">Oculus Quest 2</h2>
<p>On that topic&hellip;</p>
<p>On the weekend that we returned from vacation, we welcomed an <a href="https://www.theverge.com/21437674/oculus-quest-2-review-features-photos">Oculus Quest 2 VR
headset</a> into the family.</p>
<p>In the early 2000s, <a href="https://graphics.tudelft.nl/">the TU Delft Graphics research lab</a> that I was part of had
an AR / VR research line, so I got some exposure to state-of-the-art equipment
then.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 15 years, and the self-contained Oculus Quest 2 at $299 is
mind-blowingly good.</p>
<p>Specifically the head tracking is phenomenal.</p>
<p>Graphics elements in VR are rock-solid in virtual space as you move your head
(and yourself) around. The resolution is high enough that you could even work
on a document if you would like. With the most recent firmware update, Quest 2
now does 120 Hz.</p>
<p>In short, when you put on the headset, immersion is total.</p>
<p>No more outside world.</p>
<p>You can double tap on the side of the helmet to switch on reality (viewing your
surroundings through the 4 cameras mounted on the outside), and double tap to
switch reality off and go back into VR.</p>
<p>Facebook (they own Oculus) has some interesting work-focused ideas with this:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/5_bVkbG1ZCo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>When I saw that video for the first time, before having tried out the Quest 2,
I thought &ldquo;haha look at fb faking VR&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s pretty much spot-on.</p>
<p>(We&rsquo;re not playing office-office with the kids though, beat saber is much more
fun in 3D!)</p>
<h2 id="flip-it">Flip it</h2>
<p>During a recent chat with a busy friend, seeing if we could have coffee
somewhere, I reminded us both (you have to imagine this in Afrikaans, but
failing that in English with a thick Afrikaans accent):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Remember that the moments of relaxation and humanity are the anchors. All of
the rest should flow around that.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is so easy to forget.</p>
<p>We (and I also mean I) postpone the chat, or the run, or time with the family,
because of work.</p>
<p>It should be the other way round!</p>








<figure><a href="st_francis_sunset_watch_202104.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hua10bf591581d94392300ebf8596c4e8a_1503636_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hua10bf591581d94392300ebf8596c4e8a_1503636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hua10bf591581d94392300ebf8596c4e8a_1503636_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hua10bf591581d94392300ebf8596c4e8a_1503636_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hua10bf591581d94392300ebf8596c4e8a_1503636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Awesome ritual in St Francis where people make a whole celebration of the sunset. We were there thanks to GOU#1&amp;rsquo;s tip."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Awesome ritual in St Francis where people make a whole celebration of the sunset. We were there thanks to GOU#1&rsquo;s tip.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #212: Use it, or lose it</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 10:57:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/</guid><description> Well hello there folks, and welcome to the 212th edition of the Weekly Head Voices!
This one covers the two weeks from Monday December 7 to Sunday December 20, 2020. My end-of-year vacation started at some point during the period under investigation, so there&amp;rsquo;s not all that much to report here, except perhaps for a small philosophy message brought to you by the world of science.
Figure 1: View of the bridge over the mouth of the Steenbras River, taken from our anniversary hike up Steenbras Gorge to the Crystal Pools and back.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well hello there folks, and welcome to the 212th edition of the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This one covers the two weeks from Monday December 7 to Sunday December
20, 2020. My end-of-year vacation started at some point during the period under
investigation, so there&rsquo;s not all that much to report here, except perhaps for
a small philosophy message brought to you by the world of science.</p>








<figure><a href="bridge_steenbras_gorge.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu5c74236a4b331276fc52fb72c11f4c2b_2185026_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu5c74236a4b331276fc52fb72c11f4c2b_2185026_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu5c74236a4b331276fc52fb72c11f4c2b_2185026_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu5c74236a4b331276fc52fb72c11f4c2b_2185026_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/bridge_steenbras_gorge_hu5c74236a4b331276fc52fb72c11f4c2b_2185026_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View of the bridge over the mouth of the Steenbras River, taken from our anniversary hike up Steenbras Gorge to the Crystal Pools and back."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View of the bridge over the mouth of the Steenbras River, taken from our anniversary hike up Steenbras Gorge to the Crystal Pools and back.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="my-advent-of-code-comes-to-an-end">My Advent of Code comes to an end</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/#advent-of-code-2020">WHV #211 that I was really enjoying the Advent of Code 2020</a>.</p>
<p>As I hinted there, I was happy to reach my modest goal of the double digits (i.e. day 10).</p>
<p>On day 20 however (which is of course December 20), the puzzle took up so much
of my time that I decided, with significant difficulty (remember these puzzles
are like cat nip for nerds), to drop out.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s been great fun, and I learned so much <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a> in such a short period, but at
some point one has to make the call whether the time cost is justified by the
fun and the learning.</p>
<p>P.S. It took about two days to finally let go. :)</p>
<h2 id="use-it-or-lose-it">Use it, or lose it</h2>
<p>I am currently reading the fascinating book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/51778153-livewired"><em>Livewired: The Inside Story of the
Ever-Changing Brain</em></a> by neuro-scientist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David%5FEagleman">David Eagleman</a>.</p>
<p>As you can probably deduce from the title, this book is about how the brain
never stops rewiring itself.</p>
<p>Even now as you&rsquo;re reading these words, your brain is making and breaking
connections, and changing chemical balances, as it crunches through and
sometimes integrates the ideas that are invoked by this weird trick we humans
do, called <em>speech</em>, and the even weirder trick, called <em>writing</em>.</p>
<p>(Writing: Your retinae count the photons coming from the screen on which you&rsquo;re
reading this, construct patterns of darkness and light, convert those patterns
to words, and then string together those words into living, breathing
simulations of reality in your giant neural network.)</p>
<p>Besides functioning as an awe-inspiring exploration of the inner workings of
the brain and the nervous system, also for me with a little bit of existing
background, the book explains the phenomenon that inside the brain there is a
never-ending struggle between brain regions, between neurons and between the
thoughts that they store.</p>
<p>If you are blindfolded for a few days, your audio cortex will start annexing
parts of your visual cortex. If you&rsquo;re blindfolded for long enough (don&rsquo;t do
this), your visual cortex could be repurposed completely.</p>
<p>Neurons compete for incoming data, memories compete for neurons; it&rsquo;s a
continual fight for existence.</p>
<p>When a new, more important or more stressful memory arrives, it can push out,
into eternal oblivion, an older, less interesting memory.</p>
<p>If an input data stream like sight or hearing stops, another strong input
stream will take over those neurons. When you stop practising long division, or
algebraic simplification, you&rsquo;ll first start to get slower, and then later lose
that ability.</p>
<p>Those neurons have been repurposed.</p>
<p>(The book posits a really interesting hypothesis for why humans dream so
visually: Your eyes are closed for a large part of the day. Your visual cortex
would take a beating every night, i.e. be taken over by other parts of your
brain, if you didn&rsquo;t use it so actively during dreaming every night.)</p>
<p>You can probably see where this is going.</p>
<p>In the brain, just like in the rest of your human physiology, efficiency is
everything.</p>
<p>The moment you stop practising a certain function, like math, or absorbing
technical documents, or programming, or driving, or running, or being kind,
your system will start to try to repurpose as much as possible of the required
subsystems for other functions that you <em>are</em> actively deploying.</p>
<p>In short: <em>Use it, or lose it.</em></p>
<p>You&rsquo;re going to have to keep on practising all of the things you find important
until the day all of it stops for the last time.</p>
<p>This may seem quite harsh, but man, does it keep us honest.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #207: Kogelberg</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 15:58:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/</guid><description> The 207th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, which in theory should cover the week from Monday October 5 to Sunday October 11, 2020, is in fact only here to remind future me of that time when I took the Thursday October 8 off from work to go run the Kogelberg Trail with friends PK, TvD and EW.
(Ok, well maybe there is also a backyard philosophy thing hidden at the end of the post&amp;hellip;)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The 207th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, which in theory should cover the
week from Monday October 5 to Sunday October 11, 2020, is in fact only here to
remind future me of that time when I took the Thursday October 8 off from work
to go run the <a href="https://www.hikingsouthafrica.co.za/kogelberg-trail/">Kogelberg Trail</a> with friends PK, TvD and EW.</p>
<p>(Ok, well maybe there is also a backyard philosophy thing hidden at the end
of the post&hellip;)</p>








<figure><a href="kogelberg_5005.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: About halfway through the first climb"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: About halfway through the first climb</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="random-notes-on-the-kogelberg-trail-adventure">Random notes on the Kogelberg Trail adventure</h2>
<ul>
<li>Taking the day off to go run in the mountains: These two separately pleasant
actions are even greater when applied together.</li>
<li>Based on the predictions a week or so before the time, we were going to run
in a bit of rain. As the date came closer, the predicted start time of the
rain kept on creeping later and later. The day itself was mostly gorgeous
sunshine with very little wind.</li>
<li>According to the Cape Nature peeps at the starting point, we were the first
people to run the route since before the lockdown when they, err, locked down
the nature reserve. This was noticeable by the overgrown vegetation we had to
fight through for a kilometre or two, just after the first climb. Other than
that, it felt pretty special!</li>
<li>I like running with a GPX of the route on my Apple Watch (<a href="http://www.workoutdoors.net/">WorkOutDoors</a> is
amazing for following a route with maps while you&rsquo;re running, especially if
you&rsquo;re directionless like me), but I could not find one available online
before the time.
<ul>
<li>So I started a Strava Pro trial so I could use their amazing <a href="https://www.strava.com/heatmap">global heatmap</a>
to draw the crowd-sourced GPX in about 6 clicks. I&rsquo;m probably going to keep
the Strava Pro: Being able to make routes like this of any place that you
might find yourself in is amazing.</li>
<li>You can download a GPX of the route we actually ran, as logged by my
iPhone, by clicking on the following link: <a href="./kogelberg_trail_cpbotha_20201008.zip">Kogelberg Trail GPX</a>. The whole
thing is just under 24km.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Below is a video impression somewhere just past halfway. Don&rsquo;t miss the waterfall!</p>
<video controls>
<source src="kogelberg_trail_impression_20201008.mp4" type="video/mp4">
Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
<h2 id="find-a-place-in-the-universe-that-is-your-consciousness">Find a place in the universe that is your consciousness</h2>
<p>On the morning of October 7, about halfway through a 10 minute mindfulness
practice with <a href="https://wakingup.com/">the Waking Up app</a>, Sam Harris says something like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Take a negative emotion, and examine it. Remember, you can find a place in
consciousness that is not implicated, to stand on and be able to do this.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>His words really struck home at that moment.</p>
<p>By the end of the session, analysing a particular negative thought, I
experienced quite viscerally (haha, sorry) the phenomenon of relatively easily
finding a non-implicated mental space to stand, from where I could take apart
that negative emotion piece by piece, without being drawn into it at all.</p>
<p>Now it feels like all of those practice sessions exploring the <em>experience</em> of
consciousness, as the whole of the reality simulation being run over the
trillions of neural connections in the human brain, were not in vain.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #204: What is your purpose?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 22:22:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</guid><description> Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September 13, 2020.
Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.
Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.
Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices,
examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September
13, 2020.</p>
<p>Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more
subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being
outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.</p>








<figure><a href="guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with Microsoft Research&amp;rsquo;s Image Composite Editor, and the power of math."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/product/computational-photography-applications/image-composite-editor/">Microsoft Research&rsquo;s Image Composite Editor</a>, and the power of math.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="sleep-update">Sleep update</h2>
<p>With our teenager back in school, we have to get up at 5:45, mercifully only
for two days of the week with the school in COVID-19-mode.</p>
<p>On other days we get to sleep in until 6:45. LUXURY!</p>
<p>(The lock-down also saved us from a few months of 5:45 wake-ups 5 time per
week during the darkest part of the winter, so there&rsquo;s that.)</p>
<p>This, together with increased pressure at work, has again brought into sharp
focus my sleep hygiene.</p>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t been doing too badly during the past months, but the current period
seemed to require a tad more attention to good sleep.</p>
<p>After reading the disappointing news that the promised first-party (Apple, in
other words) sleep-tracking in the new WatchOS 6 release was not going to be
much more than tracking time in bed, I searched around for the best third-party
sleep tracking app.</p>
<p>Well folks, after a few weeks of testing, I think that <a href="http://autosleep.tantsissa.com/">AutoSleep</a> is it!</p>
<p>(Beware, there&rsquo;s a straight rip-off app in the Google Play store. It&rsquo;s not even
in the same reality as the real thing, although the scammers have stolen a
bunch of visual elements and even copy from the real autosleep website. Oh
Android&hellip;)</p>
<p>The app appears to be almost too full of complicated-looking visual gizmos, so
much so that initially I was not as positive about it. See below for an example
of my sleep history overview:</p>








<figure><a href="autosleep_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot_huce0efa54e288cea4a99599142a3b63a7_817330_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot.png"
            

         width="240px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>However, after using it for a while, and coming to grips with the various
pieces of feedback, this app has turned out to be a great tool in my quest for
sleep hygiene nirvana.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I did have to change my watch charging habits by charging my watch
in the evening hours, so that I can sleep with it on my wrist, and I also have
to remember to tap the &ldquo;lights out&rdquo; button when I attempt to start my sleep
(you don&rsquo;t have to do this, but it gives more accurate tracking that way).</p>
<p>Now I have measurements to show how important the wind-down routine is (if I
can fit in some book-reading in bed, I can fall asleep after that in almost no
time); how some nights when it feels like I&rsquo;m quite restless, I actually do get
quite an amount of sleep; and finally how a drink or two on a weekend night can
affect my average heart rate through the night (+5 beats, oof), and more.</p>
<h2 id="wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 and nativecomp Emacs workflow update</h2>
<p>The following is for my more nerdy readers.</p>
<p>After running into <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/WSL/issues/4619#issuecomment-678652118">this comment</a> on a github issue I am subscribed to, I learned
that you can use the versatile <a href="http://www.dest-unreach.org/socat/">socat</a> tool to forward connections from a unix
socket on WSL2, via the WSL bridge and a WSL1 instance, to a TCP port on
localhost.</p>
<p>The upshot of this is that I now have a robust X11 connection from WSL2 to X410
running on my Windows laptop.</p>
<p>This is possible without socat, but you either need to forward ports using SSH
(which I&rsquo;ve done), or punch holes in the firewall, and then, as if that&rsquo;s not
bad enough, deal with a connection that breaks every time the laptop goes into
suspend.</p>
<p>With the socat X11 connection in place, I decided that it was time to go
further around the WSL2 bend and replace my complicated rsync-based scripts for
copying source code from the Windows host to the WSL2-native filesystem with a
second instance of dropbox running directly on WSL2, with a severe selective
sync configuration.</p>
<p>By the way, after <a href="https://dropbox.tech/infrastructure/rewriting-the-heart-of-our-sync-engine">Dropbox rewrote their sync engine (in Rust)</a>, nothing else
even comes close in terms of performance.</p>
<p>Thanks to this perfect storm of socat-X11-boosted WSL2 and MULTI-dropbox, I
decided that it was finally time to commit to <a href="https://akrl.sdf.org/gccemacs.html">the new nativecomp Emacs &ldquo;capable
of compiling and running Emacs Lisp as native code&rdquo;</a>, so I busted out my
slightly modified version of <a href="https://masteringemacs.org/article/speed-up-emacs-libjansson-native-elisp-compilation">Mickey Petersen&rsquo;s</a> Dockerfile and compiled me one.</p>
<p>This very post is being written on native-compiled Emacs Lisp, running on WSL2,
displaying via socat to X410.</p>
<p><code>#feelsgoodman</code></p>
<p>(P.S. I&rsquo;ve been running like this for about three weeks, with nary an
issue. The future is now.)</p>
<h2 id="keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">Keyboard update: Unicorns-with-RGB</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/#my-attempt-at-dipping-my-toes-carefully-into-the-world-of-mechanical-keyboards">WHV #200 how I carefully started dipping my toes in the
clickity-clackety waters of mechanical keyboards</a> by acquiring a cheap keyboard
with hot-swappable <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile-clicky/outemu-blue/">Outemu blue switches</a>.</p>
<p>What I did not tell you then, was that shortly after acquiring that keyboard, I
had already ordered the <a href="https://youtu.be/e9gRESbY-e8">Womier K87 all-acrylic RGB-overload keyboard</a> from
Banggood.</p>
<p>My reason for ordering that specific board was not so much the lighting (WHICH
IS FREAKING SPECTACULAR BUT BACK THEN I DID NOT KNOW THIS), but rather because
it was the most affordable mechanical keyboard with universal(-ish)
hotswappable switches.</p>
<p>You see, the Outemu board can only take Outemu switches, while with a board
with universal sockets, you have access to a whole smorgas(key)bord of
different switches!</p>
<p>The Womier finally arrived after slightly more than a month, with <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile/gateron-brown/">Gateron brown
switches</a> installed as I had requested.</p>
<p>Probably due to both the brown switches (rated 45g actuation force but probably
less, tactile but not clicky) and due to the board&rsquo;s far more solid
composition, my typing comfort and speed on this thing are close to what I
usually have on my Microsoft Sculpt ergonomic.</p>
<p>Because of this, I don&rsquo;t swap back to the Sculpt nearly as often.</p>
<p>Together with the fact that the keyboard has an impressive and varied
collection of intricate animated lighting patterns thanks to the RGB LED behind
each and every single key, and a whole bunch of extra LEDs in the acrylic body,
this leads to a great deal of typing fun.</p>
<p><code>#feelsbrightman</code></p>
<h2 id="running-update">Running update</h2>
<p>Back in <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">WHV #177</a> I embraced the space and acquired my first pair of Altras, a
pair of road shoes named Escalante 1.0, for a good price, because the 1.5 had
already been released.</p>
<p>Recently I was again in the fortunate position to buy a pair of 1.5s for a good
price, as, you guessed it, the 2.0 had already been released.</p>
<p>The new babies look like this:</p>








<figure><a href="altra_escalante_1.5.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Running in them has been super enjoyable.</p>
<p>(The 1.0s are at about 700km, which is usually a good time to retire them from
running. Now they are just for cocktail parties and business meetings.)</p>
<p>On a more philosophical note, with the aforementioned improving weather, the
aforementioned increased pressure at work, and the non-aforementioned abundance
of mountains all around me, I have taken to randomly taking a few hours off
from aforementioned work to go run in the now aforementioned mountains.</p>
<p><code>#feelslifeaffirmingman</code></p>
<h2 id="what-is-your-purpose">What is your purpose?</h2>
<p>We have a great tradition here at the WHV of revising our official and utterly
complete life philosophy based on discussions with wise friends.</p>
<p>See for example <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">WHV #124</a> where I had to add a third rule to <em>WHV&rsquo;s Two Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em>.</p>
<p>Quite poetically, the additional rule was &ldquo;Evolve&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(FYI, the current official WHV approach to life, the universe and everyhing is
summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.)</p>
<p>During the beautifully-surrounded lunch discussion with longest-time friend
(LTF, henceforth), as depicted in the panoramic photo at the start of this
post, we also spent some time talking about life directions vs. goals.</p>
<p>As you know, I am <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">not a fan of life goals, instead opting for life directions</a>.</p>
<p>LTF agreed with some of my reasoning, but made the valid point that goals were
required to measure and maintain velocity along one&rsquo;s chosen directions, or
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">systems</a>.</p>
<p>In principle we agree on this point also, but I believe that the conversation
will have to continue, as we still need to define and then articulate a
closed-form solution to the directions vs goals issue, or rather a guideline
that can be used to determine the correct relative dosage.</p>
<p>Probably more important was LTF&rsquo;s contribution of the concept of &ldquo;purpose&rdquo;.</p>
<p>One could argue that life directions form one&rsquo;s purpose, but that would be
missing an opportunity I think.</p>
<p>As LTF later quipped:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Purpose = the reason you get up in the morning. Goals = help you go to sleep at
night.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At least in my case, I have a number of life directions, but I think a purpose
is a higher-level, mostly singular, desired outcome of your life&rsquo;s work.</p>
<p>Ideally, <em>life directions</em> should be set in order to orient one towards
fulfilling one&rsquo;s <em>purpose</em>, with continuously evolving <em>goals</em> punctuating the way
there.</p>
<p>What is <em>your</em> purpose?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>