<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Exercise on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/exercise/</link><description>Recent content in Exercise on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:50:41 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/exercise/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Sunday 2024-01-07</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:48:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</guid><description> Last day of my vacation. 🥹 Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder than rest in the &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; periods instead. The assault bike saddles are garbarge. Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me. Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me. &amp;hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so. After getting wlziipsrv built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&amp;hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (bug in macOS 17.2) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS! Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 and GOU#2 ❤️</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Last day of my vacation. 🥹</li>
<li>Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes
<ul>
<li>Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder  than rest in the &ldquo;rest&rdquo; periods instead.
<ul>
<li>The assault bike saddles are garbarge.</li>
<li>Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &ldquo;normal&rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me.
<ul>
<li>&hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>After getting <code>wlziipsrv</code> built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv">https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv</a></li>
<li>Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MacOS/comments/18g4vxn/cannot_remap_keys_on_macbook_pro_with_hidutils_in/">bug in macOS 17.2</a>) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS!</li>
<li>Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 <em>and</em> GOU#2 ❤️</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Saturday 2024-01-06</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-06/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:47:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-06/</guid><description> Researching assault-style airbikes as an alternative cardio modality, for when I would like a workout that&amp;rsquo;s not running (for when my joints need some rest) and that&amp;rsquo;s not in the sun so much An assault-style airbike uses a big fan as the front wheel, and engages your arms and upper body as well. Seems to be an important staple in the crossfit world. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if I&amp;rsquo;m the right person for it, but it sure looks convincing! Here&amp;rsquo;s a not-too-crazy beginner cardio workout example on youtube: https://youtu.be/6OMfabFyVFI?si=SId44AGsPX9U2YZJ Really special braai with a group of besties, hosted by SnR. According to the highly scientific DHV-scale, the evening has been classified as &amp;ldquo;life-affirming&amp;rdquo; and also &amp;ldquo;the absolute best possible way to spend those hours&amp;rdquo;. So much thank you!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Researching assault-style airbikes as an alternative cardio modality, for when I would like a workout that&rsquo;s not running (for when my joints need some rest) and that&rsquo;s not in the sun so much
<ul>
<li>An assault-style airbike uses a big fan as the front wheel, and engages your arms and upper body as well. Seems to be an important staple in the crossfit world. I&rsquo;m not sure if I&rsquo;m the right person for it, but it sure looks convincing!</li>
<li>Here&rsquo;s a not-too-crazy beginner cardio workout example on youtube: <a href="https://youtu.be/6OMfabFyVFI?si=SId44AGsPX9U2YZJ">https://youtu.be/6OMfabFyVFI?si=SId44AGsPX9U2YZJ</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Really special braai with a group of besties, hosted by SnR. According to the highly scientific DHV-scale, the evening has been classified as &ldquo;life-affirming&rdquo; and also &ldquo;the absolute best possible way to spend those hours&rdquo;. So much thank you!</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #188: Exercise Canary.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 20:29:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/</guid><description>As I mentioned in the last WHV, I am in the midst of trying to end this year on a strong and especially regular note.
So, more on time than the rest of the rest of the year, you are now reading the 188th edition of the Weekly Head Voices. This will most probably be the last WHV of the year 2019, looking back at the week from Monday December 23 to Sunday December 29.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>As <a href="/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/">I mentioned in the last
WHV</a>, I am in the
midst of trying to end this year on a strong and especially <em>regular</em> note.</p>
<p>So, more on time than the rest of the rest of the year, you are now reading the
188th edition of the Weekly Head Voices. This will most probably be the last
WHV of the year 2019, looking back at the week from Monday December 23 to
Sunday December 29.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_59397d04b7c51d36.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_15f2b94a18ffd728.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_ed5374261cfa5852.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_e250dd95cfe03186.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_15f2b94a18ffd728.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Vacation oscillates between lazing and running.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="topol-tweets-for-your-vacation">Topol-Tweets™ for your vacation.</h2>
<p><a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">I may have implied before that Prof. Eric Topol&rsquo;s twitter stream is
brilliant</a>.</p>
<p>During the past few days he posted two high impact (meta-)analyses on topics
that I currently find interesting.</p>
<h3 id="time-restricted-eating">Time-restricted eating.</h3>
<p>The first is a New England Journal of Medicine systematic review of
<a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">time-restricted
eating</a>
and intermittent fasting:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">How ironic for <a
href="https://twitter.com/NEJM?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@NEJM</a> to publish a
systematic review on time-restricting eating and fasting for <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ChristmasDay?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ChristmasDay</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/diet?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#diet</a>
<a href="https://t.co/BLbVxUsZJt">https://t.co/BLbVxUsZJt</a> by de Cabo and
Mattson <a
href="https://twitter.com/HopkinsMedicine?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@HopkinsMedicine</a>
<a href="https://t.co/o5FHhbIISv">pic.twitter.com/o5FHhbIISv</a></p>&mdash;
Eric Topol (@EricTopol) <a
href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol/status/1209957610268397568?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December
25, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>I was able to download the full-text PDF via a free subscription to NEJM which
gives you three free articles per month.</p>
<p>However, I feel it&rsquo;s my civilly disobedient duty to inform you that the PDF is
now also available via
<a href="https://sci-hub.se/10.1056/nejmra1905136">Sci-Hub</a>. (Future readers, if that
link disappears, try <a href="https://whereisscihub.now.sh/">Where Is Sci-Hub</a>.)</p>
<p>Anyways, you can read the full article, or read the twitter discussion embedded
above.</p>
<p>The TL;DR is that fasting&rsquo;s benefits have been clinically shown &ldquo;for many
health conditions such as obesity, diabetes mellitus, CVD, cancers&rdquo; mostly for
&ldquo;overweight young and middle-age adults&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Although long term benefits in otherwise healthy humans still have to be shown,
texts like the following (and more parts of the article&rsquo;s introduction) make me
hopeful:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Periodic flipping of the metabolic switch not only provides the ketones that
are necessary to fuel cells during the fasting period but also elicits highly
orchestrated systemic and cellular responses that carry over into the fed
state to bolster mental and physical performance, as well as disease
resistance.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="amount-and-intensity-of-leisure-time-physical-activity-and-lower-cancer-risk">Amount and Intensity of Leisure-Time Physical Activity and Lower Cancer Risk.</h3>
<p>The second Topol-Tweet I wanted to single out was this gigantic study with data
pooled from 9 cohorts, totalling more than 750000 people, in which the data
showed that 2.5 to 5 hours per week of moderate-intensity [leisure-time]
activity was associated with significantly lower risk for seven different types
of cancer:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Exercise (leisure time
physical activity) and its intensity are associated with a lower incidence of
many types of <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/cancer?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#cancer</a>,
from 9 cohorts, &gt; 750,000 people <a
href="https://t.co/BBMQTCIrDm">https://t.co/BBMQTCIrDm</a> <a
href="https://twitter.com/ASCO?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ASCO</a> <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/openaccess?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#openaccess</a>
by <a href="https://twitter.com/theNCI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@theNCI</a>&#39;s
Charles Matthews and colleagues <a
href="https://t.co/u91xolRuWO">pic.twitter.com/u91xolRuWO</a></p>&mdash; Eric
Topol (@EricTopol) <a
href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol/status/1210348149849518080?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December
26, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>This <a href="https://ascopubs.org/doi/pdf/10.1200/JCO.19.02407">the full-text PDF of this Journal of Oncology article is fortunately
available thanks to open
access</a>!</p>
<p>Intriguingly, the study also found that (page 8):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There was evidence of nonlinear u-shaped associations with vigorous-intensity
activity for colon and endometrial cancer such that the protective
associations observed at intermediate activity levels were eroded at higher
levels of activity (ie, 30 v0 MET hours/week).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This either does mean that too much exercise indeed brings us right back to no
protective effect from colon and endometrial cancer relative to no exercise, or
that the data in this case (n = 309881) is still somehow misleading the
analysis.</p>
<h2 id="the-middle-aged-exercise-canary">The (middle-aged) Exercise Canary™.</h2>
<p>On Friday, during the second part of my morning run, the first part being
together with GOU #1 (running with your genetic offspring is amazing on more
than one level), I had an exercise-related realisation which I thought was
worth sharing with you peeps.</p>
<p>Another important but indirect reason to exercise (I&rsquo;m extrapolating from
running here, please correct me if you can) is the following:</p>
<p>Performing some activity at the edge of one&rsquo;s athletic capability, be it
endurance or intensity, enables one to detect with much more sensitivity than
normal, anything negatively impacting one&rsquo;s functioning and hence the status of
one&rsquo;s health.</p>
<p>For example, when I&rsquo;ve lost an hour of sleep for whatever reason, or I&rsquo;ve had
as little as a drink or two the previous day, or, as is often the case, I&rsquo;ve
sinned on both dimensions, my legs, lungs and other grit-related organs will
notify me in no uncertain terms, during my run, that they are not happy.</p>
<p>On a rest day, I <em>might</em> experience a spot of brain fog, but mental performance
is already so complicated that it could be a host of other contributing
factors.</p>
<p>A gaggle of cognitive biases (you heard it here first) means that I usually
ascribe it to everything <em>but</em> my behaviour the previous day.</p>
<p>Fortunately friends, <em>the exercise canary does not lie.</em></p>
<p>Unlike when we were still invincible, here at middle-age I prefer being
reminded early and regularly of the consequences of my daily life choices.</p>
<h2 id="friendly-wishes">Friendly wishes.</h2>
<p>Highly valued reader peeps, I wish you much wisdom and kindness as we round out
the last few days of 2019, and usher in the brave new 2020.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting, either on this blog in the
soon-to-be-written traditional 2019-2020 transition post, or at whichever
other point we might become entangled.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #135: It’s all rainbows and unicorns, no really!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/03/11/weekly-head-voices-135-its-all-rainbows-and-unicorns-no-really/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 20:04:08 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/03/11/weekly-head-voices-135-its-all-rainbows-and-unicorns-no-really/</guid><description> This rainbow unicorn, floating serenely on a cloudy background, is winking right at you. Down below, we are celebrating GOU #3’s second birthday. Photo taken with the expert assistance of GOU#1, age 11 going on 32.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/rainbow_unicorn_2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/rainbow_unicorn_2.jpg"
        
            alt="This rainbow unicorn, floating serenely on a cloudy background, is winking right at you. Down below, we are celebrating GOU #3’s second birthday. Photo taken with the expert assistance of GOU#1, age 11 going on 32."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>This rainbow unicorn, floating serenely on a cloudy background, is winking right at you. Down below, we are celebrating GOU #3’s second birthday. Photo taken with the expert assistance of GOU#1, age 11 going on 32.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Hi there friends, welcome back to the weekly (!!!) head voices! I missed you.</p>
<h1 id="software-release-frazzle">Software Release Frazzle</h1>
<p>Releasing desktop software, even for a small group of people, can get tricky quickly yo!</p>
<p>Yes, people still write desktop software, and we do love doing it. However, compared to web-apps, there are some additional challenges.</p>
<p>One can’t easily roll-out an incremental fix while no-one is watching, because every release is a significant event where users have to go to the effort of downloading and installing your baby.</p>
<p>It’s a fairly new product, so our release process is still being refined. Long story short, we caught a bug on the release platform (we develop cross-platform, but deploy for a single platform) shortly before release and so we really had to scramble to fix. This, together with the fact that the preparations for the release were already generally intense, left me quite frazzled by Wednesday evening after dinner.</p>
<p>Lesson learned: In a cross-platform development, don’t allow <em>any</em> dependency version discrepancies between platforms, no matter if it causes developer inconvenience.</p>
<h1 id="unicorns-and-rainbows">Unicorns and rainbows</h1>
<p>GOU #3 turned 2 on Thursday.</p>
<p>The littlest genetic offspring unit seems to be verbally well developed. She’s already using words like “eintlik” (“eigenlijk” in Dutch, “actually” in English) in fairly well-structured sentences. I have taught her to say phrases like “universiteit” and “lekker internet”, which she does with a smile.</p>
<p>She is able to express her wants and needs at a level which exceeds that of some 30 year olds.</p>
<p>Anyways, yesterday we held a birthday party for her.</p>
<p>It was a fabulously enjoyable affair with far too many delectable delicacies, and more than sufficient amounts of craft beer and good wine (expensive local Chardonnay is my current preference, if you must know).</p>
<p>It was beautiful to see so much of the family together in one place, all connecting like we humans should be doing as often as we can, but often don’t.</p>
<p>Thank you little GOU #3, for everything.</p>
<h1 id="your-complimentary-grab-bag-of-interesting-cocktail-party-conversational-tidbits">Your complimentary grab-bag of interesting cocktail party conversational tidbits</h1>
<h2 id="trump--brexit-voters-were-scared">Trump / Brexit voters were scared.</h2>
<p>In my <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#the-bad-with-a-hopefully-slightly-positive-outlook-at-the-end">2016 to 2017 transition post</a>, I lamented the observation that for both Brexit and the Trumpocalypse, a lower level of education was the strongest indicator for a vote for leave and for Trump respectively.</p>
<p>A new study by the Queensland University of Technology has now shown that in both cases <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2018-03/quot-2be030818.php">the vote for Brexit / Trump was also driven by fear</a>. It also makes the scary point that the respective campaigns deliberately targeted this fear, which is more than worrisome.</p>
<p>Use this tidbit with care, or right before you were planning to leave the party anyways.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-defend-your-exercise-addiction">How to defend your exercise addiction</h2>
<p><a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acel.12750/full">A recent study published in Aging Cell</a>, showed that older people who exercised regularly (in this case cycling), had the same levels of T-cells as 20 year olds. In other words, their immune systems are as effective as people a fraction of their age.</p>
<p>One of the co-authors of the study, 82-year old Prof Norman Lazarus (who himself cycles 100km at a time), <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/health-43308729">summarised it neatly in the media as follows</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>If exercise was a pill, everyone would be taking it.</strong> It has wide-ranging benefits for the body, the mind, for our muscles and our immune system.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(I like how he casually takes aim at our pill-obsession.)</p>
<h2 id="the-carmack-productivity-method-cpm">The Carmack Productivity Method (CPM)</h2>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Carmack">John Carmack</a> is the modern-day genius who was the lead programmer of genre- and era-defining games like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfenstein_3D">Wolfenstein 3D</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(1993_video_game)">DOOM</a> (“one of the most significant and influential titles in video game history”) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quake_(video_game)">Quake</a>. During working on these projects, he invented a number of important computer graphics techniques.</p>
<p>It turns out that Carmack is not only a genius, but a productivity and focus <em>monster</em>.</p>
<p>In <a href="http://bookofhook.blogspot.co.za/2013/03/smart-guy-productivity-pitfalls.html">this 2013 blog post</a>, a colleague of Carmack at id Software describes how Carmack would apparently play CDs while he was working. If he was checking his email, or if he was interrupted by a colleague, or he needed to go to the bathroom, in other words, if he was not focusing on the core of his work, he would pause the CD player.</p>
<p>By the end of the day, he knew exactly how much focused work he had done by how far he had gotten through his playlist.</p>
<p>Compared to the interrupt-driven way programmers work today (thanks internet!) this sounds like an amazingly visceral way to recognise and signal interruptions in your flow: THE MUSIC SIMPLY STOPS.</p>
<p>Would you be able to implement something like this for your work?</p>
<h1 id="à-bientôt">À bientôt</h1>
<p>Thank you very much for stopping by! Have a productive week, and don’t forget to exercise.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>