<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>research on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/research/</link><description>Recent content in research on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 14:10:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>An Inside Job. [Weekly Head Voices #33]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 14:10:36 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</guid><description> Hiatus: temporarily over.
My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to that, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hiatus: temporarily over.</p>
<p>My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to <em>that</em>, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am. :)</p>
<p>In this post, I’m going to touch upon the highlights of the past seven weeks (40 to 46) and I’m going to do so with bullets, seeing as I’m in a bullety-kind of mood.</p>
<ul>
<li>I spent a week in Stellenbosch teaching Information Visualisation! Read all about it in <a href="/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/" title="stbvis2010 blog post">this special blog post</a>.</li>
<li>The week after that my mom came to visit us. She really has the best genes.</li>
<li>I met my new work laptop: A Dell Latitude E6410 with Core i5 M540 2.53GHz CPU, 4G ram, 500G HDD, NVidia NVS 3100m GPU with 512 MB video mem. It’s a 14″ latop (15.4″ is a completely useless format, flame me in the comments), but due to the materials used quite heavy. I like it!</li>
<li>Another one of our STW NIG research proposals has been granted. I conceived and developed this one together with colleagues from the LUMC Departments of Anatomy, of Surgery and of Orthopaedics. The title is <em>High-definition Atlas-based surgical planning for Pelvic Surgery</em> and we get to combine high-resolution human histology, mega-volume rendering, , biomechanical modelling and surgical simulation. With this grant we can appoint two more Ph.D. students (one in my group, one at the LUMC) for four years to work on this!!</li>
<li>The week after that I went to Salt Lake City (Utah, US and A) to attend the conference previously known as <a href="http://vis.computer.org/VisWeek2010/" title="IEEE VisWeek 2010 website">IEEE Visualization</a>. It was AWESOME! (blog post half-written, will soon publish).</li>
<li>The week after that I had a really cool dream: I was playing high-speed catch with a bunch of people outside. The ball was randomly changing shape between rock, papers and scissors. If you wanted to catch it, you didn’t only have to be at the right place at the right time, but your hand also had to be in the right complementary configuration to catch the shape-shifting ball.</li>
<li>Now that we’re talking about dreams: <em>I finally saw <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1375666/" title="IMDB page for Inception">Inception</a> and was completely blown away.</em> It’s not about being complicated, it’s about being a well-told story and a fantastically filmed movie. What I positively adored, is the fact that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan" title="Wikipedia page about Christopher Nolan">Nolan</a> doesn’t require much: He only needs you to believe that dreams can be shared, without giving away too many of the details of the mechanism, and then builds a marvellous story on that canvas. My absolute favourite scene was the waking up on the plane, just before the landing, almost at the end of the film. I loved the way in which the characters looked at each other, and the possible interpretations of their expressions.</li>
<li>On the topic of the Underworld gig in the Heineken Music Hall: I hope I have my voice back before my morning lecture tomorrow morning. Thank you Fantastic Friends!</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it kids. If you’ve come this far, you’re now mostly up to date. Please leave me a comment, it’s good for my serotonin! I hope you have a great week. To get you off to a  good start, here’s a music video showing what an infectious idea could look like…</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<div class="embed-vimeo" style="text-align: center;">
<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="473" mozallowfullscreen="" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/15391189" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="840"></iframe>
</div>
</div>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #9: Windows 7 Geek-o-Rama.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2009 20:35:02 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/</guid><description> I’ve unfortunately not been involved in any quantum entanglement accidents recently — teaching duties are mostly to be blamed for my two-week silence. Besides spending at least a whole work-day every week on our Data Visualisation practical, I’ve been lecturing and also been preparing a new lecture block on information visualisation with a dash of visual data analysis. Due to my not secretly being an infovis expert, this latter activity has taken up quite a chunk of my time and effort.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve unfortunately not been involved in any quantum entanglement accidents recently — teaching duties are mostly to be blamed for my two-week silence.  Besides spending at least a whole work-day every week on our <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4086p" title="datavis practical website">Data Visualisation practical</a>, I’ve been lecturing and also been preparing a new lecture block on information visualisation with a dash of visual data analysis.  Due to my not secretly being an infovis expert, this latter activity has taken up quite a chunk of my time and effort.  On the other hand, the exercise has forced me to acquire a significant amount of new infovis brain juice which I’ll probably soon be applying to <em>impressive</em> effect.</p>
<p>In any case.</p>
<p>On the geek front, I have to say that I’m <strong>really liking Windows 7</strong>.  Partly eye-candy, partly the SuperBar, partly the revamped file manager: I’m a happy camper both on the NetBook (just installed 4GB of SDHC especially for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ReadyBoost" title="wikipedia page on readyboost">ReadyBoost</a>) and on the quad core workstation.  Feel free to discuss this in the comments, even, or especially, my black turtleneck-wearing friends! :)  Unrelated to the big 7, it turns out that if you use large removable (USB) drives between computers with different operating systems, NTFS is your best bet.  Even more unrelated, I’ve also discovered that one can implement complete independent Windows applications using <a href="http://www.autohotkey.com/" title="AutoHotkey website">AutoHotkey</a>.  Before I knew what I was doing, I had re-implemented most of my <a href="http://cpbotha.net/software/envedit/" title="envedit website">envedit</a> application in AutoHotKey, with GUI and all (you can find my efforts in <a href="http://code.google.com/p/envedit/source/browse/trunk/ahk/envedit.ahk" title="source of envedit.ahk">SVN</a>, AHK’s a strange little language).  The resultant stand-alone app is 400k, which compares favourably to the 4MB envedit installation.  To conclude this week’s edition of I Really Like Geeking Out, I broke down and bought 20G of extra Google storage for slightly less than EUR 5 per year.  I’m not using it (yet), but I somehow get a kick from seeing this at the bottom of my GMail interface (click the image for a slightly larger version):</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png" title=""><img alt="gmail_storage_screenie" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-701" data-attachment-id="701" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":""}' data-image-title="gmail_storage_screenie" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie-300x88.png" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png" data-orig-size="533,158" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/gmail_storage_screenie/" height="88" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie-300x88.png" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie-300x88.png 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png 533w" title="gmail_storage_screenie" width="300"/></a>
</p>
<p>With regard to research, things have been going just swimmingly.  There are a number of really cool articles being lovingly incubated as we speak.  Some mathematical visualization and some time-varying VDA will go to Eurovis, whilst one other submission is already being carefully groomed for the Vis deadline in March next year.</p>
<p>In other news that absolutely made my day on Monday, November 9, 2009: After being in the oven for almost two years, our pathological shoulder segmentation article should soon appear at a news-stand near you:</p>
<div>
<blockquote>
<p>
      Peter R Krekel, Edward R Valstar, Frits H Post, Piet M Rozing, and Charl P Botha. 2009. <em><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Krekel2010" title="Link to paper website.">Combined Surface and Volume Processing for Fused Joint Segmentation</a>.</em> The International Journal for Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery.
    </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
<strong>Mr Cricket, that was just marvelous!</strong>
</p>
<p>
    Finally, I’m ecstatic to report that due to an unfair dose of serendipity, not in the least brought about by the involvement of <a href="http://gpsgek.nl/" title="website of said extremely resourceful individual">one extremely resourceful individual</a>, <strong>Longitudinal Medical Visualisation</strong> (google should take you to the right place) looks like it might be getting off the ground in a Really Big Way soon.  Stay tuned kids, stay tuned.
  </p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>