<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Prostate on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/prostate/</link><description>Recent content in Prostate on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 22:40:37 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/prostate/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 2 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/15/daily-head-voices-2024-01-08_14/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 22:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/15/daily-head-voices-2024-01-08_14/</guid><description>Inspired by the impressive power (and philosophy) of One Punch Man&amp;rsquo;s Consecutive Normal Punches, I present: A Series of Consecutive Normal Daily Head Voices!
Monday 2024-01-08 First day back at work 😱 &amp;hellip; but the most lovely lunch run (not literally) and chat with colleague E. Single cable life at work is there, but it&amp;rsquo;s complicated: Thunderbolt3 cable from macbook to Thinkpad dock, dock thunderbolt3 to displayport-mini (adapter), displayport-mini to displayport to monitor. Had blood drawn for my quarterly PSA test. (prostate-specific antigen; regular test to check that prostate cancer stays gone) Double Commander (currently at 1.1.8) on macOS is even better than I remember it, and is only a brew install --cask double-commander away. Tuesday 2024-01-09 marimo looks really good! From the github: a reactive notebook for Python. It allows you to rapidly experiment with data and models, code with confidence in your notebook&amp;rsquo;s correctness, and productionize notebooks as pipelines or interactive web apps. I still have to play with it, but it sounds like an Observable for Python. Wednesday 2024-01-10 Shorter weekday run because hip and because sun. Hip only started complaining by the end, a little later than my last short run. 🎉 Tried to find reclining high-back office chairs with footrest in South Africa, starting from: https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/ Spectacular failure! Google Bard, Bing Chat, Perplexity come up with plausible looking links that go to different sites, but nowhere any chairs to be found perplexity is probably the least bad because it more often admits to just not finding any links in SA See e.g. https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c and https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5 Because of work, started to spend some quality time with d3.js again. I hope to be doing some nice interactive visualization soon! Thursday 2024-01-11 PSA is 0.006! 🥳 if you&amp;rsquo;ve ever worked with d3.js, you will have used bl.ocks.org quite often. To my surprise, none of these links work anymore, and instead redirect you to the source gist, where they used to show you the live visualization. I could not find much official news about this sunsetting, but was consoled by the discovery of the open source bl.ocks.org clone at https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/ via https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513 Tune of the evening: RÜFÜS DU SOL - On My Knees (Adriatique Remix) Friday 2024-01-12 Short week-day run, no hip issues! Very nice focused day at home: First half wrapping up a code review. Second half diving back into d3.js. So much old memories I have to unearth. In between hacked in an idle mode for org-roam-similarity, in the process discovered that on this M1 Pro, CPU is much faster (2x) and uses much less RAM than the hardware accelerated PyTorch MPS version Lovely weekend-starter braai with family. Ran into the final sections (and private comments the source org file) of WHV #208 &amp;ndash; besides the nostalgic music bits, really enjoyed reading some of the older journals. Publish or not, strong motivation to keep on writing journals. (now-you is often a very different person than then-you. interesting to keep in touch!) Saturday 2024-01-13 one of the highlights of the day was phone-call by and substantial conversation with bestie PK rest of day quite laid-back with the whole family, which was great thinking a lot about stefanv&amp;rsquo;s week planner instead of day planner, and the implications of this seemingly reduced planning effort (my daily planning is mostly only theoretical) greater family braai (GFB) Sunday 2024-01-14 Overslept a bit, woke up at 9 AM. This has not happened in ages. Slightly longer weekend run at 10 with new running hat and SPF50 on me face and neck. Hip issue did not manifest, am touching wood! Because I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about more visual ways to plan my week, worked on org-roam-canvas, making it a whole lot faster.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Inspired by the impressive power (and philosophy) of One Punch Man&rsquo;s <em>Consecutive Normal Punches</em>, I present: A Series of Consecutive Normal Daily Head Voices!</p>
<h2 id="monday-2024-01-08">Monday 2024-01-08</h2>
<ul>
<li>First day back at work 😱</li>
<li>&hellip; but the most lovely lunch run (not literally) and chat with colleague E.</li>
<li>Single cable life at work is there, but it&rsquo;s complicated: Thunderbolt3 cable from macbook to Thinkpad dock, dock thunderbolt3 to displayport-mini (adapter), displayport-mini to displayport to monitor.</li>
<li>Had blood drawn for my quarterly PSA test. (prostate-specific antigen; regular test to check that prostate cancer stays gone)</li>
<li>Double Commander (currently at 1.1.8) on macOS is even better than I remember it, and is only a <code>brew install --cask double-commander</code> away.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-09">Tuesday 2024-01-09</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/marimo-team/marimo">marimo</a> looks really good! From the github: <em>a reactive notebook for Python. It allows you to rapidly experiment with data and models, code with confidence in your notebook&rsquo;s correctness, and productionize notebooks as pipelines or interactive web apps</em>. I still have to play with it, but it sounds like an <a href="https://observablehq.com/">Observable</a> for Python.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-10">Wednesday 2024-01-10</h2>
<ul>
<li>Shorter weekday run because hip and because sun. Hip only started complaining by the end, a little later than my last short run. 🎉</li>
<li>Tried to find reclining high-back office chairs with footrest in South Africa, starting from: <a href="https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/">https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/</a>
<ul>
<li>Spectacular failure! Google Bard, Bing Chat, Perplexity come up with plausible looking links that go to different sites, but nowhere any chairs to be found</li>
<li>perplexity is probably the least bad because it more often admits to just not finding any links in SA</li>
<li>See e.g. <a href="https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c">https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c</a> and <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5">https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Because of work, started to spend some quality time with <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a> again. I hope to be doing some nice interactive visualization soon!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-11">Thursday 2024-01-11</h2>
<ul>
<li>PSA is 0.006! 🥳</li>
<li>if you&rsquo;ve ever worked with d3.js, you will have used bl.ocks.org quite often. To my surprise, none of these links work anymore, and instead redirect you to the source gist, where they used to show you the live visualization. I could not find much official news about this sunsetting, but was consoled by the discovery of the open source bl.ocks.org clone at <a href="https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/">https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/</a> via <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513">https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513</a></li>
<li>Tune of the evening: <a href="https://youtu.be/IAmmkJZ55vM?si=WjEjD8MLge7sCo0E">RÜFÜS DU SOL - On My Knees (Adriatique Remix)</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-12">Friday 2024-01-12</h2>
<ul>
<li>Short week-day run, no hip issues!</li>
<li>Very nice focused day at home: First half wrapping up a code review. Second half diving back into d3.js. So much old memories I have to unearth.</li>
<li>In between hacked in an idle mode for <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity">org-roam-similarity</a>, in the process discovered that on this M1 Pro, CPU is much faster (2x) and uses much less RAM than the hardware accelerated PyTorch MPS version</li>
<li>Lovely weekend-starter braai with family.</li>
<li>Ran into the final sections (and private comments the source org file) of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/#thank-you-joris">WHV #208</a> &ndash; besides the nostalgic music bits, really enjoyed reading some of the older journals. Publish or not, strong motivation to keep on writing journals. (now-you is often a very different person than then-you. interesting to keep in touch!)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-13">Saturday 2024-01-13</h2>
<ul>
<li>one of the highlights of the day was phone-call by and substantial conversation with bestie PK</li>
<li>rest of day quite laid-back with the whole family, which was great</li>
<li>thinking a lot about stefanv&rsquo;s week planner instead of day planner, and the implications of this <em>seemingly</em> reduced planning effort (my daily planning is mostly only theoretical)</li>
<li>greater family braai (GFB)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-14">Sunday 2024-01-14</h2>
<ul>
<li>Overslept a bit, woke up at 9 AM. This has not happened in ages.</li>
<li>Slightly longer weekend run at 10 with new running hat and SPF50 on me face and neck. Hip issue did not manifest, am touching wood!</li>
<li>Because I&rsquo;ve been thinking about more visual ways to plan my week, worked on <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">org-roam-canvas</a>, making it a <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas/commit/a67ad1ee59c93a2998a0c2975ed7d567e7f02c8d">whole lot faster</a>.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #252: My prostate cancer post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 14:01:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/</guid><description> Figure 1: A dazzle of zebras
Welcome back everyone!
My excuse this time for the multi-month WHV blogging hiatus is that I was dealing with prostate cancer.
I was diagnosed in February, but I wanted to wait for calmer waters before writing anything.
Extremely fortunately, those calmer waters have arrived, and now I can talk openly.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="dazzle-of-zebra.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_553474bf4e68c1b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_1d0de5a264e5fb60.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_d2d6dbd49b798c55.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_fa1286d2e3011625.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_1d0de5a264e5fb60.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A dazzle of zebras"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>A dazzle of zebras</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome  back everyone!</p>
<p>My excuse this time for the multi-month WHV blogging hiatus is that I was
dealing with prostate cancer.</p>
<p>I was diagnosed in February, but I wanted to wait for calmer waters before
writing anything.</p>
<p>Extremely fortunately, those calmer waters have arrived, and now I can talk
openly.</p>
<p>I wanted to write up this whole story firstly because this blog has a long
history of stories about significant life events, but also just in case it
could help anyone else who might find themselves in a similar boat and would
like to talk. If you are such a person, please <a href="https://cpbotha.net/about/">email me</a> or leave a comment down
below.</p>
<p>On to the story:</p>
<h2 id="discovery">Discovery</h2>
<p>In January my GP randomly tacked on a PSA (Prostate Specific Antigen) test to
the <a href="https://apob.app/about">Apolipoprotein B (ApoB) blood test</a>, which at that point still was the main
topic of our interest.</p>
<p>The tacked-on PSA came back at 6.5ug/L, which is <em>convincingly</em> above the range
for my age, and hence was suddenly promoted to The Main Topic of Interest.</p>
<p>Three weeks later a repeat test at the urologist came back even a tad higher,
and so I was scheduled for a prostate biopsy two weeks after that.</p>
<p>This procedure, fortunately under general anaesthesia, is where the urologist
sticks a number of needles into one&rsquo;s prostate in order to gather actual tissue
samples that can be studied by the pathology lab.</p>
<p>Those biopsy results came back with&hellip;</p>
<p>Prostate cancer.</p>
<p>ULP&hellip; although my science brain had deduced that this was probably going to
be the outcome (low <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/c-reactive-protein-test/about/pac-20385228">CRP</a> = probably no prostatitis, few other indications of
<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/benign-prostatic-hyperplasia/symptoms-causes/syc-20370087">BPH)</a>, my human brain was in panic.</p>
<p>To be more specific about the diagnosis, it was <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/diagnosis-staging/tests/understanding-your-pathology-report/prostate-pathology/prostate-cancer-pathology.html">Gleason score 3+4 aka grade
group 2 (on the favourable side of &ldquo;intermediate risk&rdquo;)</a> prostate cancer. 9
out of the 13 biopsy cores (samples) were cancerous, with both lobes of the
prostate involved.</p>
<p>Cue some more shock here&hellip;</p>
<p>After that initial shock came the more cognitive realisation (thanks science
brain!) that as cancers and cancer gradings go, this was quite&hellip; <em>reasonable</em>.</p>
<p>That being said, the <em>existential dread</em> caused by this disease, which was
entirely willing and able to kill me, was quite visceral.</p>
<p>By the way, you know that thing about the atheists and the foxholes?</p>
<p>Contrary to the wisdom of the foxhole, I found <em>immense</em> peace in my science, and
endless strength in my family and my friends.</p>
<h2 id="surgery">Surgery</h2>
<p>My urologist explained that for someone at my age, with this diagnosis, he
would recommend in no uncertain terms to have the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prostatectomy">prostate removed</a>, preferably
via <em>robot-assisted laparoscopic prostatectomy</em>, aka my new friend Wreck-it RALP
(silent H).</p>
<p>In my <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">previous career as academic in The Netherlands</a>, a significant part of my
research was computer-assisted surgery. Although I did most of my work in
orthopaedics with the academic hospital in Leiden, the Da Vinci surgical robot
(previous generation!) was very much on our radar.</p>
<p>Little did I know that a decade or so later I would experience its successor,
the Da Vinci X, very much first hand.</p>
<p>(It&rsquo;s hard for me to put in words how grateful I am now for all of the
thousands of hours of research and development that have gone into
robot-assisted surgery&hellip; thank you colleagues!)</p>
<p>On March 30, my partner and I left home at 4 AM to report at the hospital
at 5.</p>
<p>First that horrible open-at-the-back hospital wear, and then the warm enema
they brought in shortly after admission, were pretty clear signs that things
were getting <em>uncomfortably</em> real.</p>
<p>My experience of the surgery itself was of course sublime &ndash; oblivion is indeed
bliss!  &ndash; thanks to the anaesthetist&rsquo;s magic.</p>
<p>The main procedure was performed by <a href="https://caperoboticsurgery.co.za/">Dr Conray Moolman</a>, a urological surgeon who
specialises in RALP, with hundreds of prostatectomies under the belt.</p>
<p>(Why yes, I am in fact now <em>expected</em> to brandish this level of punnery, thanks
for asking.)</p>
<p>Having the operation done by someone with his level of experience is a best
case scenario for me personally, but the role of that experience in the
surgical outcome is underlined by much of the literature on robotic
prostatectomy.</p>
<p>As you can see in the handy Wikipedia illustration below, the surgeon has to
cut out the prostate and some of the surrounding tissue, and then attach the
remaining urethra to the bladder neck.</p>
<p>The poor urethra is just expected to stretch to the occasion.</p>










<figure><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prostatectomy#/media/File:Prostate_Removal.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/fb/Prostate_Removal.png"
         width="50%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>All of this happens via the Da Vinci X&rsquo;s many robotic arms, a number of them
inserted into my abdominal cavity through the five incisions (four small and
one larger) in my abdomen.</p>










<figure><a href="davinci-table.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_9d81c6c80d2fd942.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_3657f00e43b134d5.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_acd23c8750a659c7.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_3657f00e43b134d5.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>One of the main challenges for the surgeon here is that, along with the whole
prostate, they need to remove as little as possible of the surrounding nerves,
which would result in certain post-operative functional deficits, but enough of
the surrounding tissue to include cancer cells that may have progressed to
there.</p>
<h2 id="post-op">Post-op</h2>
<p>I was able to walk a little bit on the same afternoon, with the expert help of
the physiotherapist, and in spite of the interference of my new and fortunately
temporary augmentation the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foley_catheter">Foley catheter</a>, which had to remain in place for at
least a week to give the new bladder-urethra hook-up time to heal.</p>
<p>A few days later, the first fantastic bit of news was that the post-op
pathology report, completed a few days later, showed that <a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/positive-surgical-margins-following-radical-prostatectomy-20090617171">&ldquo;all margins were
clear&rdquo;</a>, meaning that it was highly probable that all prostate cancer cells
had been taken care of.</p>
<p>I was able to return to work just over two weeks after surgery.</p>
<p>The first post-op PSA test 6 weeks afterwards showed a new PSA level of 0.01.</p>
<p>I have not been able to find out if that amount is just what the test shows at
its lower end, or if there is somehow some residual PSA left in my system.</p>
<p>My urologist seems happy with this result, which is important.</p>
<p>For the first year, I&rsquo;ll have to repeat this blood test every three months to
ensure that there&rsquo;s really nothing there. I am keeping my fingers crossed.</p>
<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</h2>
<p>As I write this, exactly three months after the prostatectomy, I am looking out
over the Crocodile river, at the end of <a href="/tags/knp/">our traditional winter KNP break-away</a>.</p>
<p>Shortly after the 6-week PSA test, I had to have another small surgical
procedure due to a urethral stricture which developed most probably due to the
catheter. Fortunately the stricture was very distal (ahem), far away from the
critical new urethra-bladder-neck junction.</p>
<p>I am almost back up to pre-surgical strength, although I do have to go to the
bathroom substantially more regularly (also at night) due to the remaining
nerves (most of them, fortunately!) still having to learn new tricks, but
probably more due to the urethral sphincter being exactly the part that is
newly sutured to the bladder neck. Other than that, my running fitness took
quite a hit, and is now in the slow process of building up again.</p>
<p>On the mental side, my confidence in my own health and physical resilience has
taken a bit of a knock. This is something I really need to work on.</p>
<p><strong><strong>Through all of this, support from work, friends and family has been absolutely
phenomenal.</strong></strong></p>
<p>Amongst many other lessons, this has shown me how much even that random
WhatsApp from a friend who I haven&rsquo;t seen in ages can mean, and so I have
resolved to send that random supportive message through whichever medium,
whenever there&rsquo;s an opportunity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Monthly [Weekly Head Voices #50]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/07/02/the-monthly-weekly-head-voices-50/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2011 15:00:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/07/02/the-monthly-weekly-head-voices-50/</guid><description>HEY!
I’m still here, and it seems I really have to catch up on my backlog of WHVs, all the more as I was starting to notice the beginnings of BPP (Backlogged Posting Paralysis, of course). So I’ve spent a few minutes gathering a selection of life snippets of the past six weeks (week 21 through week 26) and will now proceed blasting them out this old Web 1.0 exhaust. I wasn’t completely idle blog-wise, however. I did write a post about my EuroVis 2011 and my Schloss Dagstuhl SciVis seminar adventures.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>HEY!</p>
<p>I’m still here, and it seems I really have to catch up on my backlog of WHVs, all the more as I was starting to notice the beginnings of BPP (Backlogged Posting Paralysis, of course). So I’ve spent a few minutes gathering a selection of life snippets of the past six weeks (week 21 through week 26) and will now proceed blasting them out this old Web 1.0 exhaust. I wasn’t completely idle blog-wise, however. I did write a <a href="/2011/06/26/eurovis-2011/" title="eurovis 2011 post">post about my EuroVis 2011</a> and my <a href="/2011/06/19/schloss-dagstuhl-computer-scientist-heaven/" title="dagstuhl scivis 2011 post">Schloss Dagstuhl SciVis seminar</a> adventures.</p>
<p>Before the blasting commences, I would like to present some relaxing visual input brought to you via my cell phone camera, which at the time of capturing found itself in my hand, itself being inside the chapel in <a href="http://maps.google.nl/maps?q=Herberg+Op+Hodenpijl,+Rijksstraatweg,+Schipluiden&amp;hl=en%E2%89%AA=51.987252,4.321012&amp;spn=0.002355,0.005348&amp;sll=51.986948,4.321007&amp;sspn=0.004711,0.010697&amp;t=h&amp;z=18" title="google maps of herberg op hodenpijl">Herberg op Hodenpijl</a>, a short westward cycle from my house:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/herberg_op_hodenpijl2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/herberg_op_hodenpijl2-1024x608.jpg"
        
            alt="Herberg op Hodenpijl chapel roof detail."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Herberg op Hodenpijl chapel roof detail.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The picturesque surroundings are home to the chapel, which hosted an art exhibition at that point, and an organic restaurant and grocer. Most (all?) of the produce comes from a small farm across the road that you can also visit. The goats are really friendly. You could do worse than popping by on a sunny day.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/herberg_op_hodenpijl1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/herberg_op_hodenpijl1-1024x608.jpg"
        
            alt="Herberg op Hodenbijl chapel roof detail."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Herberg op Hodenbijl chapel roof detail.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The rest of this post has been categorised, with nice headings, so that you can skim through it even faster.</p>
<h4 id="health-and-well-being">Health and well-being</h4>
<ul>
<li>In a recent cooking insert on the television, <a href="http://dewerelddraaitdoor.vara.nl/Video-detail.628.0.html?&amp;tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=22570&amp;tx_ttnews%5BbackPid%5D=626&amp;tx_ttnews%5Bcat%5D=148&amp;cHash=ab10fe812f48fd43e838df03ffa6cf31" title="DWDD video clip">two chefs prepared <em>Loup farci en croûte</em></a>, or sea bass filled with julienne vegetables in a pastry of a thousand layers. Take a look at the video clip: The chefs put an amazing amount of effort into preparing this visually beautiful and apparently delectable dish.</li>
<li>My <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">TNR</a> and since recently also business partner, who can often be found hurtling down mountains on various and high-speed forms of personal transportation, and when he’s not is involved in a number of other extreme sports activities, managed to break two fingers on his right hand cycling over the flat and otherwise uneventful piece of earth between the computer science and physics buildings on our campus. Go figure.</li>
<li>In a <a href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/news/fullstory_112161.html" title="medlineplus article on coffee vs prostate cancer">recent study</a> with 48000 (yes, that’s fourty eight thousand) men followed over a period of 22 years, a strong correlation was found between drinking six cups of coffee per day and a lowered risk of prostate cancer. Also men (but can you still call them men?) drinking fewer than 6 cups of coffee per day had a lower risk. The study did correct for other lifestyle factors. The linked summary also mentions other studies in which coffee drinking has been associated with lower risk of Parkinson disease, type 2 diabetes and liver cancer. I guess I can worry less about this addiction than, euhm, the other ones.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="nerd-news">Nerd News</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dropbox has recently activated functionality they call shareable links, meaning that you can request a unique <a href="http://db.tt/some_code">http://db.tt/some_code</a> link for any file or directory anywhere in your dropbox and share it with anyone else (also non-dropbox users), who is then able to download said file or directory given the link. There’s a page on the website where you can manage all of your shared links, for example deactivating ones you don’t want people to access anymore. Read the <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/help/167" title="dropbox help on sharable links">help on shareable</a> links for more information.</li>
<li>As you <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/" title="blog post on the importance of taking notes">might know</a>, I keep a lab journal documenting in some detail my daily work activities. I also maintain a personal journal, mostly for dumping stuff that might be interesting for this blog. I used to do all of this in Google Docs, but for the past few weeks I’ve experimenting using <a href="http://www.tiddlywiki.com/" title="tiddlywiki website">TiddlyWiki</a> (this is a single file JavaScript-heavy wiki implementation) on my Dropbox for all my journaling and personal knowledge base needs. It’s been going swimmingly for at least two reasons: 1) It’s available also when I’m offline. 2) The idea of being able to break out into a new wiki page (called a tiddler) at the drop of a hat takes some getting used to, but fits the non-linear nature of my journal and personal knowledge base entries much better than the mostly linear google docs.</li>
<li>I’ve settled on using the free <a href="http://www.tonido.com/" title="tonido website">tonido personal cloud software</a> to make all the files on my home server available via the internets. This means I can get to all of my music, photos are whatever no matter where I am. Pretty neat! (I have too much to fit on my 50G dropbox account. There’s also the PogoPlug software, but the free version has its limitations.)</li>
<li>Just a few days before Google+ (Google’s new social networking religion, in case you’ve been sleeping for the past week) hit the internets, I installed the Google +1 button on this blog, see right at the bottom of every post. So now you know what to do with every post: Click my +1 button, then click my facebook like button, then leave me some snarky comment right here. Easy as 123, and I’m a happy camper.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="comedy">Comedy</h4>
<p>Whilst flipping through channels one Saturday night,  I flipped right into the stand-up comedian <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demetri_Martin" title="demetri martin wikipedia page">Demetri Martin</a>. I made a note of it in my journal, and now here we are. Watch him present his research findings on his large pad, with his pointer:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vaGa3kjRS7o?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>That’s it for now dear readers. I really do hope to be back soon, and I hope to do so with a slightly more focused contribution. See you on <a href="http://plus.google.com/" title="google plus">Google+</a>!</p>
<p><strong>UPDATE 2011-07-23 note-taking strategy</strong></p>
<p>To you I might appear fickle, but I guarantee that it’s just hyperactivity. I’ve since adjusted my note-taking strategy again. As you will have seen in the comments, Pieter Kitslaar subtly influenced me to go searching for a note-taking solution that syncs between phone and everywhere else. Fortunately, I ran into the <a href="http://simplenoteapp.com/" title="simplenote universe">SimpleNote universe</a> and I’m now officially in <strong>note-taking heaven</strong>. I have <a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=com.teragadgets.android.notes" title="flick note market page">Flick Note</a> on my Android, the SyncPad extension on Chrome (for sometimes) and <a href="http://www.resoph.com/" title="resoph notes website">ResophNotes</a> on Windows and on Linux with Wine. All apps work exactly as I would expect a super-fast and efficient note-taking app to work, with real-time incremental searching, hotkeys <strong>everywhere</strong>, and best of all, offline use and transparent syncing. <strong>ResophNotes is especially cool, definitely give it a shot.</strong></p>
<p>So I’m using this SimpleNote setup for all my personal knowledge base and general note-taking needs. For detailed work and lab journaling, I’m now using linear OpenDocument files on my Dropbox, which solves the offline problem I had with Google Docs, which I do still adore for collaborative work.</p>
<p>Lemme know in the comments what you think!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>