<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Software on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/software/</link><description>Recent content in Software on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2007 16:17:02 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/software/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Spotify2AppleMusic Chrome Extension</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/software/spotify2applemusic-chrome-extension/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 19:57:29 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/software/spotify2applemusic-chrome-extension/</guid><description> Spotify2AppleMusic is a Chrome Extension with which you can easily copy any shared Spotify playlist into a new playlist in your Apple Music library.
You can post any questions / compliments to the Spotify2AppleMusic email / web discussion group. If you have questions, please search the group using the search box at the top of the group page before posting.
Tips The extension is free, but tips are greatly appreciated!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/spotify2applemusic/gehbfaolompeeapflihekomijnhgccbk"><img data-attachment-id="3262" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/software/spotify2applemusic-chrome-extension/attachment/128/" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/128.png" data-orig-size="128,128" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="128" data-image-description="" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/128.png" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/128.png" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/128.png" alt="" width="128" height="128" class="size-full wp-image-3262" /></a></p>
<p><a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/spotify2applemusic/gehbfaolompeeapflihekomijnhgccbk">Spotify2AppleMusic</a> is a Chrome Extension with which you can easily copy any shared Spotify playlist into a new playlist in your Apple Music library.</p>
<p>You can post any questions / compliments to the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/spotify2applemusic">Spotify2AppleMusic email / web discussion group</a>. If you have questions, please search the group using the search box at the top of <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/spotify2applemusic">the group page</a> before posting.</p>
<h1 id="tips">Tips</h1>
<p>The extension is free, but tips are greatly appreciated!</p>
<p>30% of what you donate will go to a local South African charity. I tend to choose ones with an educational theme.</p>
<p>The rest will go towards my (expensive) coffee habit and the yearly Apple Developer subscription I now need to keep this extension alive.</p>
<h2 id="paypal-with-4-easy-options">Paypal with 4 easy options:</h2>
<h2 id="paypal-with-an-amount-of-your-choosing">Paypal with an amount of your choosing:</h2>
<h2 id="ethereum-address">Ethereum address</h2>
<p>TBD. Mail me if you need this, which will expedite the process of me putting the address up here.</p>
<h1 id="top-contributors">Top contributors</h1>
<p>None so far.</p>
<h1 id="charities-contributed-to">Charities contributed to</h1>
<p>From this app, none.</p>
<h1 id="planned-improvements">Planned improvements</h1>
<ul>
<li>Improve algorithm that matches Apple Music tracks to Spotify tracks. It’s now quite rigid, and hence sometimes misses songs it could have matched. </ul></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Latest VTK Windows binaries</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/software/latest-vtk-windows-binaries/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2008 18:31:29 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/software/latest-vtk-windows-binaries/</guid><description> This page will always link to my latest blog post with VTK Windows binaries, so you know you have the most recent ones. The latest post is:
Python 2.6 enabled VTK 5.4 Windows binaries You might still be interested in the older Python 2.5 builds:
Python 2.5 enabled VTK 5.4 Windows binaries. However, if you’re really serious about VTK, ITK and perhaps even a kitchen sink, and you would like the choice between 32bit and 64bit on both Windows and Linux, you should really be looking at the DeVIDE Runtime Environment, or DRE.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This page will always link to my latest blog post with VTK Windows binaries, so you know you have the most recent ones.  The latest post is:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/08/13/python-2-6-enabled-vtk-5-4-windows-binaries/" title="Link to Python 2.6 VTK 5.4.2 windows binaries posting.">Python 2.6 enabled VTK 5.4 Windows binaries</a></li>
</ul>
<p>You might still be interested in the older Python 2.5 builds:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/05/23/python-25-enabled-vtk-54-windows-binaries/" title="Link to Python 2.5 enabled VTK 5.4  Windows binaries post">Python 2.5 enabled VTK 5.4 Windows binaries.</a></li>
</ul>
<p>However, if you’re really serious about VTK, ITK and perhaps even a kitchen sink, and you would like the choice between 32bit and 64bit on both Windows and Linux, you should really be looking at the <a href="http://visualization.tudelft.nl/Projects/DeVIDE" title="DeVIDE website">DeVIDE Runtime Environment, or DRE</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>pam_pwdfile</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/software/pam_pwdfile/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2007 22:13:40 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/software/pam_pwdfile/</guid><description> Timo Weingärtner has graciously offered to take over the maintenance of pam_pwdfile. Its development will henceforth be hosted at https://github.com/tiwe-de/libpam-pwdfile.
Old page contents follows PAM, or pluggable authentication modules, is a very effective method by which applications can abstract the way that they authenticate and authorize users. Using PAM for example, a whole system can be switched from normal /etc/passwd to shadow passwords without recompiling a single binary, as was the case with older *ix systems.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Timo Weingärtner has graciously offered to take over the maintenance of pam_pwdfile. Its development will henceforth be hosted at <a href="https://github.com/tiwe-de/libpam-pwdfile" title="pam-pwdfile github">https://github.com/tiwe-de/libpam-pwdfile</a>.</p>
<h1 id="old-page-contents-follows">Old page contents follows</h1>
<p>PAM, or pluggable authentication modules, is a very effective method by which applications can abstract the way that they authenticate and authorize users. Using PAM for example, a whole system can be switched from normal /etc/passwd to shadow passwords without recompiling a single binary, as was the case with older *ix systems. Linux being my OS of choice, I have had most contact with Linux-PAM, as maintained by Andrew Morgan. Please see the Linux PAM pages at <a href="http://www.us.kernel.org/pub/linux/libs/pam/">http://www.us.kernel.org/pub/linux/libs/pam/</a>.</p>
<p>We required a Linux PAM module for authenticating using arbitrary password files containing username:crypted_password pairs, and this was not yet available for Linux PAM. As is the way with nicely open operating systems, I was able to put one together quickly, and you can get the source here. Since then, patches for extending functionality have also been contributed and integrated with pam_pwdfile. You can use this module to have different sets of passwords for each of the PAM-based services on your systems.</p>
<p>This module is available as part of Debian, where it is known as <a href="http://packages.debian.org/unstable/admin/libpam-pwdfile.html">libpam-pwdfile</a>{.external}. It also exists in the FreeBSD ports collection.</p>
<p>Warwick Duncan has written a very useful utility (command-line and CGI) to manage password files that can be used by pam_pwdfile. You can read all about chpwdfile and download it from the <a href="http://eclipse.che.uct.ac.za/chpwdfile/">chpwdfile homepage</a>{.external}! (Hmmm, it seems that the chpwdfile site has dropped off the edge of the internet. I’ve mirrored the source tarball of chpwdfile <a href="http://cpbotha.net/files/mirror/chpwdfile-0.24.tar.gz">here</a>{.external}. Remember that you can also use the apache htpasswd utility to manage your password files from the command line.)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>dri_resume</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/software/dri_resume/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2007 15:57:43 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/software/dri_resume/</guid><description> IMPORTANT NOTE: My patches have finally found their way into the XFree86 CVS (post 4.3) as well as DRI CVS. The version in DRI CVS has been greatly cleaned-up by Michel Daenzer and will probably propagate its way back into XFree86. What all of this means is that all current releases of XFree86 and X.org include the Radeon suspend/resume functionality, and as is the case with software, most users won’t even know it’s there.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><strong>IMPORTANT NOTE</strong>: My patches have finally found their way into the XFree86 CVS (post 4.3) as well as DRI CVS. The version in DRI CVS has been greatly cleaned-up by Michel Daenzer and will probably propagate its way back into XFree86. What all of this means is that all current releases of XFree86 and X.org include the Radeon suspend/resume functionality, and as is the case with software, most users won’t even know it’s there.</p>
<p>In short: <strong>This page is only here for reference purposes. The work documented here has been absorbed into the relevant repositories.</strong></p>
<p>Below follows the original text of this webpage:</p>
<hr>
<p>With the software available at this page, you can suspend from / resume to DRI-capable (i.e. hardware 3D-accelerated) XFree86 for the Radeon, even with 3D apps running.</p>
<p>Suspending / resuming DRI-capable XFree86 used to be impossible, until I made the infamous <a href="http://cpbotha.net/software/dri_reinit/" title="dri_reinit page">dri_reinit</a> kludge which allowed this if no 3D apps were running at the time. However, what you find on this page is a new solution and the best solution at the moment if all you’re interested in is suspending/resuming DRI-capable XFree86. It most definitely allows suspending / resuming even with running 3D applications.</p>
<p>In order to make this code work, you first have to make changes to your agpgart similar to those in the <a href="/files/dri_reinit/agpgart-i845-resume.patch">agpgart-i845-resume.patch</a>{.external}. If you have an Intel 845 chipset, you’re in luck as you can just use this patch. If not, have a look at what it does (simply makes sure that the resume hook calls the configure hook) and do the same for your chipset. IMPORTANT: This patch (and code similar to it) has been making its way into kernels everywhere. 2.4.20 will have it integrated, Florent’s v14 swsusp patch has something similar already included for all intel chipsets, 2.5.xx has it integrated AFAIK. The bottom-line is: check your source before blindly making changes. If this is confusing you, you can ask me for help.</p>
<p>Thomas Grossmann has contributed an agpgart patch for via chipsets. You can download it by clicking <a href="/files/dri_resume/contrib/agpgart-via-resume.patch">here</a>{.external}.</p>
<p>Once you’ve done this, you can either download my modified binary Radeon drivers or you can patch and build your own XFree86. In the binary case, you have three versions to choose from: one for 4.2 XFree86 and two for 4.3 or later XFree86.</p>
<h2 id="head-803192bb2f51215eb848dcddd9706905dfa5677e">Binaries</h2>
<p>If you’re running a 4.2.x series XFree86, get <a href="/files/dri_resume/radeon-cpbotha-20021012-linux.i386.tar.bz2">this package</a>{.external} (patched 20021012 DRI CVS snapshot, equivalent to v5; v6 or later CAN’T be installed over an existing 4.2.x installation) and install it over an existing XFree86 4.2.x installation with the included install.sh shell script.</p>
<p>If you’re running a 4.3 (or later) XFree86, I have two different sets of binary drivers on offer.</p>
<ul>
<li>The first set (my preferred) is built from DRI CVS (20030405). Download the tarball <a href="/files/dri_resume/radeon-cpbotha-20030405-linux.DRI.i386.tar.bz2">here</a>{.external}. This fixes a number of bugs that still exist in stock 4.3.0.</li>
<li>The second set is built from stock XFree86 version 4.3.0. Get it <a href="/files/dri_resume/radeon-cpbotha-20030302-linux.xfree86-4.3.0.i386.tar.bz2">here</a>{.external}.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="head-e6884c23c0b7b7976cc439bc754c85a21eaf48ef">Important notes</h2>
<p><strong>NOTE1:</strong> You have to switch VTs away from X (with e.g. chvt) at suspend time and switch back at resume time for this to work.</p>
<p><strong>NOTE2:</strong> Unlike the driReinit patch, you do NOT have to check for the use-count on the radeon module before suspending, just go ahead.</p>
<p><strong>NOTE3:</strong> It seems that the swsusp code doesn’t correctly restore all MTRRs: in your suspend/resume script, do something similar to what I do at the end of my script. Replace the addresses and sizes with what you see when you do a “cat /proc/mtrr” on your system. This is not crucial and you should only do it if you see a 2D slow down during full screen repainting (at virtual desktop switches for instance). It also seems (from the changelog) that swsusp v17 is restoring MTRRs now. I haven’t been able to test this yet.</p>
<p><strong>NOTE4:</strong> I am using this code along with kernel 2.4.21-pre3, swsuspv16 and ACPI20030109.</p>
<h2 id="head-a80ddf968c653a435811e74a11ec657c0fe521de">Source</h2>
<p>If you prefer patching the source yourself, or you have a 8500 (r200 – the patch will work for this as well, but my binaries don’t include it), download and apply <a href="/files/dri_resume/xfree86-dri-resume-v8.patch">xfree86-dri-resume-v8.patch</a> to your XFree86 source before building. It should work on both XFree86 and DRI source trees.</p>
<p>My modifications have been submitted to XFree86: they should be merged any day now…</p>
<ul>
<li>Changes in v8: Nothing, just applies cleanly to XFree86 4.3.0 RC 1</li>
<li>Changes in v7: Merged with XFree86 CVS main tree.</li>
<li>Changes in v6: Merged with post XFree86 4.2.99 merge DRI tree.</li>
<li>Changes in v5: Adapted IOCTL changes in DRI tree.</li>
<li>Changes in v4: Suspending/resuming XVideo is now supported.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>dri_reinit</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/software/dri_reinit/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2007 15:56:32 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/software/dri_reinit/</guid><description> This work evolved into the dri_resume code and was subsequently absorbed into the XFree86 code-base. This page is here for reference purposes.
This used to be the home of my driReInitKludge. However, Michel Dänzer made a far better patch based on my work and has since started a new branch in DRI CVS for the development of this functionality.
So, I’m now using this page to distribute binaries of this XFree86 DRI reinit-0-0-1-branch.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><strong>This work evolved into the <a href="/software/dri_resume">dri_resume</a> code and was subsequently absorbed into the XFree86 code-base. This page is here for reference purposes.</strong></p>
<p>This used to be the home of my driReInitKludge. However, Michel Dänzer made a far better patch based on my work and has since started a new branch in DRI CVS for the development of this functionality.</p>
<p>So, I’m now using this page to distribute binaries of this XFree86 DRI reinit-0-0-1-branch. What makes these drivers different from the normal DRI Radeon drivers is that they re-initialise DRI across each VT switch, meaning that you can do all kinds of neat tricks with X, including (but not limited to) suspending to disc and resuming whilst running DRI (i.e. 3D-accelerated X). There is only one caveat and that is that you should NOT suspend if X is running a 3D application at the time. This is very easy to check for.</p>
<p>Before these changes, DRI XFree86 would break if you attempted suspend/resume, with no exceptions.</p>
<p>In order for suspending/resuming to work, you will have to modify your agpgart driver as well. <a href="/files/dri_reinit/agpgart-i845-resume.patch">agpgart-i845-resume.patch</a>{.external} shows how to do this for the i845 chipset. You’ll have to do something similar for your own chipset. This makes sure that your AGP chipset is in a somewhat sane state when you resume. You might be able to get away without patching your agpgart by adjusting your suspend script so that it removes the radeon and agpgart modules just before suspending (i.e. after chvt’ing away from X) and re-inserts them when resuming, before chvt’ing back to X.</p>
<p>Get the binary drivers <a href="/files/dre_reinit/radeon-reinit-20020804-linux.i386.tar.bz2">here</a> and install it over an existing XFree86 4.2.0 installation with the included install.sh shell script.</p>
<p>Once you have the patch installed, check the use-count of the radeon module with lsmod. In X it should be 1, switched away to a VT it should be 0.</p>
<p>Once you are running with the modified binaries, change your suspend script so that it checks for the use count of the radeon module and does not suspend if it’s more than 0. This would mean that X could not release the DRM because some 3D app was running at the time. Example:</p>
<pre>OLDCON=`fgconsole`
# make sure we are on a text VT
chvt 1
# we can't go to sleep if the radeon DRM is still in use
RADEON_USECOUNT=`lsmod | grep radeon | awk {'print $3'}`
if [ $RADEON_USECOUNT -gt 0 ]; then
beep; beep; beep
echo "Radeon DRM in use, not going to suspend!"
chvt $OLDCON
exit 1
fi
# continue with suspend

# do this if you did NOT patch your agpgart (untested)
#rmmod radeon
#rmmod agpgart
.
.
.
# then the RESUME

# do this if you did NOT patch your agpgart (untested)
#modprobe agpgart
#modprobe radeon

chvt $OLDCON</pre>
<p>If you’re interested in the source, perhaps for historical reasons, you could browse the <a href="/files/dri_reinit/" title="dri_reinit download dir">download directory</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>vtkFlRenderWindowInteractor</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/software/vtkflrenderwindowinteractor/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2007 21:36:31 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/software/vtkflrenderwindowinteractor/</guid><description> vtkFlRenderWindowInteractor is a VTK class (actually FLTK too, but it helps to think of it as VTK) that enables VTK to render to and interact with your FLTK application. It is based on code by David Pont (the code was then called FlvtkInteractorWindow) which in its turn was partly based on the wxVTK code by David D. Marshall and Brian Todd. I reworked the code extensively to be simpler, more robust and bug-free(tm).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>vtkFlRenderWindowInteractor is a VTK class (actually FLTK too, but it helps to think of it as VTK) that enables VTK to render to and interact with your FLTK application. It is based on code by David Pont (the code was then called FlvtkInteractorWindow) which in its turn was partly based on the wxVTK code by David D. Marshall and Brian Todd. I reworked the code extensively to be simpler, more robust and bug-free(tm). It should always be available from <a href="http://cpbotha.net/software/vtkFlRenderWindowInteractor" title="vtkFlRenderWindowInteractor home page">http://cpbotha.net/vtkFlRenderWindowInteractor.html</a> .</p>
<p>The main idea behind this class is to be as simple and robust as possible. It fulfils one purpose and that’s to enable you to write applications with FLTK and VTK. It is possible to have multiple VTK renderings (all active) in your FLTK application, each with its own independent working VTK interactorstyle. You can also add custom interactorstyles, just like with any standard VTK interactor. Picking also works fine, thank you.</p>
<p>This code has been successfully tested on Linux, Irix, Windows and many of the other platforms supported by ITK, as the vtkFlRWI is extensively used in the InsightApplications component of ITK.</p>
<p><strong>Downloads</strong></p>
<p>The current version is 1.02. You can download a source and example tarball by clicking <a href="http://cpbotha.net/files/vtkFlRenderWindowInteractor/vtkFlRenderWindowInteractor-1.02.tar.gz">here</a>{.external}. Read the <a href="http://code.google.com/p/vtkflrenderwindowinteractor/source/browse/trunk/changelog?r=78" title="Changelog for release 1.02"><span class="external">changelog</span></a> for a detailed description of changes.</p>
<p>The vtkFlRenderWindowInteractor project development is hosted by Google Code.  Go to <a href="http://code.google.com/p/vtkflrenderwindowinteractor/" title="Google Code project page">our project page</a> to checkout the latest development source or to file a bug!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>im2avi</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/software/im2avi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2007 14:37:22 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/software/im2avi/</guid><description> NOTE: All the linux machines that I work with are still running Debian Stable (aka Woody aka Linux 1958) and im2avi happily works on these machines. Some users have reported getting it to run on newer machines, some users have reported not being able to. At some stage, I’ll spend some time on a newer Linux distribution and update everything to run out of the box on such machines. Until then, you are primarily on your own.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>NOTE: All the linux machines that I work with are still running Debian Stable (aka Woody aka Linux 1958) and im2avi happily works on these machines. Some users have reported getting it to run on newer machines, some users have reported not being able to. At some stage, I’ll spend some time on a newer Linux distribution and update everything to run out of the box on such machines. Until then, you are primarily on your own.</p>
<p>im2avi is a small program for making AVIs from sequences of images. It makes use of <a href="http://avifile.sourceforge.net/" title="link to avifile website">avifile</a> for encoding video streams, so im2avi has access to all the codecs that avifile supports, including e.g. DivX ;) or Cinepak. It uses the <a href="http://www.imagemagick.org/www/Magick++/" title="ImageMagick++ website">ImageMagick++ library</a> to load the images, so it supports a wide range of formats. im2avi was developed on linux, but should run on most OSen that support avifile, ImageMagick and fltk.</p>
<p>My primary use for im2avi is to make “screen movies” for presentations and such-like. To capture the actual frames, I use <a href="http://xvidcap.sourceforge.net/" title="xvidcap website">xvidcap</a>. I write the frames to the default xwd-format (which im2avi can easily read) and then make msmpeg4 AVIs. For an examples of the output, see the movies on my <a href="http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/publications/botha2003/" title="ShellSplatting webpage">ShellSplatting page</a>.</p>
<p>NOTE: It seems xvidcap now has its own built-in encoding support, so you might want to try that first!</p>
<p>im2avi adds value in offering an easy to use UI frontend to avifile and ImageMagick++. im2avi is distributed under the GPL v2 or later.</p>
<p>You can download version 0.4 (released 20030620) by clicking <a href="http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/~cpbotha/files/im2avi/im2avi-0.4.tar.gz" title="im2avi download link">here</a>. Please read the included README file. The changelog is also available <a href="http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/~cpbotha/thingies/changelog.im2avi" title="im2avi changelog">here</a>.</p>
<p>To see a screenshot, click &lt;a href=&ldquo;<a href="http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/~cpbotha/screenshots/im2avi-0.2.jpg%22">http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/~cpbotha/screenshots/im2avi-0.2.jpg&quot;</a> title=&rdquo;&quot; data-rel=&ldquo;lightbox-image-0&rdquo; data-rl_title=&quot;&quot; data-rl_caption=&quot;&quot;&gt;here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>envedit</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/software/envedit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2007 14:29:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/software/envedit/</guid><description> envedit is a Windows Environment Editor. Use it to edit / set all your user and system environment variables, such as the PATH. I made this tool as the built-in Windows editor (Start | Control Panel | System | Advanced | Environment Variables) is definitely one of the worst user interface examples ever created.
envedit is different from other environment editor tools in that it offers two free-form edit windows. Changes to the complete text will be parsed and applied to the Windows environment keys in the registry.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>envedit is a Windows Environment Editor. Use it to edit / set all your user and system environment variables, such as the PATH. I made this tool as the built-in Windows editor (Start | Control Panel | System | Advanced | Environment Variables) is definitely one of the worst user interface examples ever created.</p>
<p>envedit is different from other environment editor tools in that it offers two free-form edit windows. Changes to the complete text will be parsed and applied to the Windows environment keys in the registry. See the screenshot below:</p>
<img title="envedit screenshot" src="/files/envedit/envedit-6.3.20-screenshot.png" alt="envedit screenshot" width="512" height="478" align="middle" />
<h3 id="quickstart">Quickstart</h3>
<p>Download the binary installer (setup) and run it to install the tool. You should now have an envedit icon on your desktop.</p>
<p>Before you begin, always make a backup of your user and system environments by using <em>File | Save to file [Ctrl-S]</em> for both the user and system environments.</p>
<p>The selected environment (USER or SYSTEM) is shown with a blue background. All actions will be performed on the selected environment. After making changes, go to preview mode (<em>Environment | Preview [F7]</em>) and check your changes before selecting <em>Environment | Apply [F8]</em>. To undo changes (you can only do this if you haven’t applied yet), use <em>Environment | Synchronise [F5]</em>.</p>
<p>You can also try <em>Tools | Path Edit current variable [F3]</em> to bring up the path editor, which will allow you to edit the ;-separated paths line by line, and to make use of the directory and file selection dialogs to replace or insert directory and file paths. When invoking this function, your cursor has to be on a non-empty line in the user or system text edit box.</p>
<h3 id="download">****Download</h3>
<p>The latest release of envedit is 6.3.20. See the <a href="http://cpbotha.net/files/envedit/changelog.txt" title="envedit changelog">changelog</a> if you’re interested in the changes since previous versions.</p>
<p>You can download a binary installer (setup exe, this is the easiest), a zip file containing the binaries, or the source code.</p>
<ul>
<li>Binary installer: <a href="http://cpbotha.net/files/envedit/envedit-6.3.20-setup.exe" title="binary installer">envedit-6.3.20-setup.exe</a> (if you don’t know what to download, just get this one)</li>
<li>ZIPped binaries: <a href="http://cpbotha.net/files/envedit/envedit-6.3.20.zip" title="zipped binaries">envedit-6.3.20.zip</a></li>
<li>Source code: <a href="http://cpbotha.net/files/envedit/envedit-6.3.20-source.zip" title="source code">envedit-6.3.20-source.zip</a> (Python 2.3 or 2.4, Tkinter)</li>
</ul>
<p>The source code is released under a BSD open-source license, which also means that the binaries are freeware.</p>
<h3 id="dependencies">Dependencies</h3>
<p>The binary installer includes all its dependencies and should run on a clean Windows installation, i.e. you don’t have to install any other frameworks whatsoever.</p>
<h3 id="development">Development</h3>
<p>We have a <a href="http://envedit.googlecode.com/" title="Google Code projecct site for envedit">Google Code Project Site</a> where you can SVN the latest source or file any bugs that you may come across.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>