<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>icemirb on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/icemirb/</link><description>Recent content in icemirb on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 22:38:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/icemirb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #171: ICEMiRB.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 22:38:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/</guid><description> Down here, you never know what sort of fantastic beasts you could run into. I met this particular fullmetal creature right about here.
Dear friends,
In this post, I do a particularly lossy review of my trip through time, from Monday May 6 to Sunday May 19, 2019.
First we talk about sleep, then a long part on technical tricks, then a slightly more backyard philosophical piece on human tool sharpening, and finally the announcement of a new academic event somewhere in the far or near or medium term future.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="fullmetal_baboon.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
<p>Down here, you never know what sort of fantastic beasts you could run into. I
met this particular fullmetal creature <a
href="https://goo.gl/maps/KpcQGa6hEcbd87mF7">right about here</a>.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>In this post, I do a particularly lossy review of my trip through time, from
Monday May 6 to Sunday May 19, 2019.</p>
<p>First we talk about sleep, then a long part on technical tricks, then a
slightly more backyard philosophical piece on human tool sharpening, and
finally the announcement of a new academic event somewhere in the far or near
or medium term future.</p>
<h1 id="sleep">Sleep.</h1>
<p>If you were one of the people who found themselves in my company for more than
about 10 nanoseconds during the past weeks, I probably tried to get you to
listen to <a href="/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/#the-easiest-but-most-high-impact-measure-you-can-take-to-not-die-too-soon-go-to-bed-on-time">the 6-hour long podcast between Peter Attia and Matthew Walker on
the topic of
sleep</a>.</p>
<p>Usually I&rsquo;m able to get something sufficiently out of my system by writing
about here. I do this quite deliberately to try and spare my innocent
bystanders.</p>
<p>This time, either it didn&rsquo;t really help, or I underestimate how much I would
have blabbed about it had I not let off some of the sleep steam here.</p>
<p>IN ANY CASE&hellip;</p>
<p>During the past weeks I have been paying more attention than usual to sleep, in
terms of quality, quantity and consistency.</p>
<p>Because I also decided to take more notes than usual during the day, I could
see quite acutely the effects of good sleep vs bad sleep on my performance and
energy levels the next day.</p>
<p>If sleep was good the night before, my exercise the next day seemed to take
much less effort, I still seemed to have more than enough energy at the end of
the afternoon, and, most importantly, I had almost no trouble with that
ever-important f-word:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>FOCUS.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Conversely, if I let sleep-onset slip by as little as half an hour, my brain
would be in three thousand pieces by three &lsquo;o clock the next afternoon.</p>
<p>It is starting to dawn on me that all of those evenings where I tried to borrow
an hour or even two from my sleep had a far greater cost the day after than I
ever realised.</p>
<p><strong>I can only conclude, that to experience the highest quality and intensity
waking hours, one simply has no choice but to pay the full 33% sleep tax.</strong></p>
<h2 id="damnit-coffee">Damnit coffee.</h2>
<p>Caffeine has a quarter life of 12 hours.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re positively buzzing at 1PM, 25% of that caffeine is still active in
your system at 1AM and absolutely will interfere with your sleep quality.</p>
<p>I have compromised by having my last shot before lunch, or in extreme cases
right after.</p>
<h1 id="til-things-i-learned">TIL: Things I learned.</h1>
<p>This WHV is one week late, because it seemed like nothing happened in the first week.</p>
<p>However, it seems I did learn quite few new technical tricks. In the
subsections below, I share a selection of these with you.</p>
<h2 id="remarkjs-is-great-for-quickly-building-technical-presentations">remarkjs is great for quickly building technical presentations.</h2>
<p>At <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Helderberg-Software-Developers-and-Entrepreneurs/">my favourite local
meetup</a>,
I was planning to give a talk on <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a>, the static website
generator which is powering this site, and which I&rsquo;m increasingly using instead
of wordpress.</p>
<p>Because every new project is an opportunity to check and perhaps upgrade one&rsquo;s
tools (see below for how this can also sometimes backfire), I set aside the
trusty <a href="https://revealjs.com/">reveal.js</a> and <a href="https://github.com/yjwen/org-reveal">ox-reveal Emacs orgmode
interface</a> I usually bust out, and paddled
out onto rough internet seas, on the lookout for an alternative solution.</p>
<p>(Now that I think back, I had no good reason to search for an alternative,
except that my pre-configured reveal.js style and formatting never made me
really happy.)</p>
<p>Fortunately, after not too long I ran into <a href="https://remarkjs.com">remark</a>, an
HTML- and markdown-based presentation tool that seems simpler than reveal, but
still quite attractive, as you&rsquo;ll be able to see on the demo site above.</p>
<p>At this point, I was pleasantly surprised that this distraction had not cost
more than about 30 minutes.</p>
<p>At least, that <em>was</em> the case until I ran into <a href="https://github.com/torgeir/remark-mode.el">remark-mode for
Emacs</a>!</p>
<p>As you can see from the screenshot, this enables a pretty smooth
generate-as-you-type workflow.</p>
<p>Also noteworthy, is the great built-in presenter mode. Press <code>C</code> to clone the
window into a new linked presentation which you can move off to the external
display, and then press <code>P</code> to switch to presenter mode where you can see all
of the comments you have left in the markdown.</p>
<p>I made two small fixes in <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/remark-mode.el">my own
fork</a> to enable seeding with your
own HTML template, and to enable the generate-as-you-type to work also on
straight <code>.md</code> files. I prefer keeping my presentations as <code>.md</code> (vs <code>.remark</code>)
as most of the search logic I have built in Emacs assumes <code>.org</code> and <code>.md</code>
files for my notes.</p>
<p>By choosing remarkjs instead of my existing revealjs workflow I did manage to
exhaust the short block of time I had allocated to prepare for the talk, and so
the talk morphed into a more spontaneous affair, dealing with orgmode, remarkjs
and in the end, also a bit of hugo.</p>
<h2 id="pybtex-is-a-pure-python-bibtex-parser-and-renderer">pybtex is a pure-Python bibtex parser and renderer.</h2>
<p>One of the sites getting the wordpress-to-hugo upgrade treatment was my
internet persona placeholder, the almost completely unknown
<a href="https://charlbotha.com/">charlbotha.com</a>.</p>
<p>The upgrade of this tiny site would have gone quite easily, were it not for the
fact that I was using the wordpress papercite plugin to publish a list of all
of the publications, including fulltexts in most cases, that I&rsquo;ve had the
pleasure to be involved in over the years.</p>
<p>I could not find any tool which could give me exactly the sort of publication
lists that papercite was able to.</p>
<p>To me it was clear that yet another tool was required. (&ldquo;my god, it&rsquo;s full of biases!&quot;)</p>
<p>Fortunately, <a href="https://mentat.za.net">@stefanvdwalt</a> very quickly pointed me at
the Python package <a href="https://pybtex.org">pybtex</a> when he saw that I was
careening off into the dark side with <a href="https://citation.js.org">citation.js</a>.</p>
<p>A few hours later I had built a script which was able to eat my
Zotero-generated bibtex file and spit out different lists of publications with
linked PDFs straight into a Hugo-edible markdown file.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://charlbotha.com/publications/">charlbotha.com/publications</a> for the
result.</p>
<p>P.S. Making it available to a broader audience is on my todo-list.</p>
<h2 id="asciidoc-is-one-of-your-best-choices-to-write-software-manuals">asciidoc is one of your best choices to write software manuals.</h2>
<p>We are currently working hard towards the release of version 2.0 of our
flagship FDA-certified cardiology product,
<a href="https://www.telesensi.com">TeleSensi</a>.</p>
<p>Because updating the user manual with every release is not as fun as it could
be, I had the idea to convert the doc-format source file to some text-based
document authoring system.</p>
<p>Again, in spite of past positive experience writing manuals with
<a href="http://docutils.sourceforge.net">reStructuredText</a> and LaTeX, I made use of
the opportunity to try out
<a href="https://asciidoctor.org/docs/what-is-asciidoc/">asciidoc</a>.</p>
<p>In <em>this</em> case, I am happy to report that the choice of asciidoc ended up
beating all of the alternatives by a mile.</p>
<p>I started by <a href="https://pandoc.org">pandoc</a>-ing the docx to asciidoc, and then
manually (ha ha, it&rsquo;s a joke we writers tell) fine-tuned the document until, in
a few hours, the new manual looked significantly better than the original.</p>
<p>Long story short, our manual is now part of the software source repository and
hence version-locked, it can be automatically built for new releases, and parts
of the manual can be linked programmatically to form parts of our compliance
documentation.</p>
<p>With the manual now essentially being a software construct, there are many more
tricks we can do (and already do, but I&rsquo;m not allowed to say much more).</p>
<h2 id="you-can-build-self-contained-installers-with-legacy-non-modular-apps-and-recent-modular-java">You can build self-contained installers with legacy non-modular apps and recent modular Java.</h2>
<p>In a rather surprising (to me) turn of events, I had to convert some legacy
(read: non-modular) Java code from a product component to a self-contained
installer on Windows and macOS so that our users never even have to <em>think</em>
about JREs.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s possible that the following magical recipe could help you, should you ever
find yourself in a similar predicament:</p>
<ul>
<li>Install <a href="https://adoptopenjdk.net">AdoptOpenJDK</a> 11 (LTS)</li>
<li>Retrieve and extract this <a href="https://mail.openjdk.java.net/pipermail/openjfx-dev/2018-September/022500.html">backport of the new
javapackager</a>
from the yet to be released Java 13 into your OpenJDK 11.</li>
<li>Build your legacy <a href="https://imagej.net/Uber-JAR">uber-JAR</a> with the freshly
installed OpenJDK11.</li>
<li>Use <code>jdeps</code> to determine the list of modular dependencies of your uber-JAR.</li>
<li>Armed with this knowledge, build a mini java-runtime using <code>jlink</code>.</li>
<li>Now feed your uber-jar and the freshly created java-runtime to <code>jpackager</code> in
order to construct a fully self-contained executable or platform-specific
installation package.</li>
</ul>
<p>Much, but not all, of that comes from <a href="https://medium.com/@adam_carroll/java-packager-with-jdk11-31b3d620f4a8">this blog
post</a>.</p>
<h2 id="you-can-easily-dired-jump-to-the-currently-ivy-readd-file-in-emacs">You can easily dired-jump to the currently ivy-read&rsquo;d file in Emacs.</h2>
<p>I mix and match <a href="https://github.com/abo-abo/swiper">ivy</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm">helm</a> in my Emacs.</p>
<p>When you&rsquo;re helming for a file, you can usually press <code>F5</code> to open dired
(Emacs&rsquo;s built-in filemanager) on that file&rsquo;s directory.</p>
<p>This is quite convenient, and something I was missing in ivy, which I use for
example as part of <code>find-file-in-project</code>.</p>
<p>Weeeeell, by adding the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; for any ivy-read, press M-o to get action menu,</span>
<span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; then &#39;d&#39; to start dired with that file selected</span>
(<span style="color:#268bd2">ivy-add-actions</span>
 <span style="color:#268bd2">t</span> <span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; add for all types</span>
 <span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; (cdr x) gets the full filename, not just relative</span>
 `((<span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;d&#34;</span> ,(<span style="color:#cb4b16">lambda</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">x</span>) (<span style="color:#268bd2">dired-jump</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">nil</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">cdr</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">x</span>))) <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;dired&#34;</span>)
   ))
</code></pre></div><p>&hellip; you get to select <code>d</code> from the <code>M-o</code> action menu to <code>dired-jump</code> (a
wonderful command by itself, usually bound to <code>C-x C-j</code>) to the currently
focused file.</p>
<h1 id="sharpening-these-rocks">Sharpening these rocks.</h1>
<p>All of that brings us to this.</p>
<p>I spent quite a few hours last week performing meta-work: That is, not doing
the work itself, but rather sharpening the tools required to do that work.</p>
<p>As with all important matters, there&rsquo;s an XKCD comic about this topic too:</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://xkcd.com/1205/">
<img src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/is_it_worth_the_time.png" alt="xkcd on
tool sharpening">
</a>
<figcaption>
Incredibly useful visualization by XKCD: How much time will your tool
sharpening save per event, and how frequently does that event occur? The
cross-indexed block is how much time this could save you over 5 years.
</figure>
<p>Besides the mostly defensible tricks mentioned in the previous section, I did
also invest hours in attempting to update the mobile and email-based parts of
my personal knowledge management strategy (because
<a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">Windows</a>), but these hours led to a less than
satisfactory solution.</p>
<p>If I have to be honest, it feels like those hours were wasted, although it was
impossible to say beforehand that the effort to outcome ratio was going to be
that bad.</p>
<p>(To make it all a bit more interesting, a few days later some of the dead-ends
explored during those wasted hours led to coincidental improvements of other
frequently occurring (on the order of 5 times per day) components of my
workflow.)</p>
<p>Some folks double down on their workflows, rather taking the small hits and
spending the time doing their actual work.</p>
<p>I find it difficult to resist an opportunity for streamlining.</p>
<p>Sometimes this pays off, not in the least because of the compounding effects of
frequently applicable optimisations, and other times I fall down the rabbit
hole.</p>
<p>In my dreams, I am able to reach a sort of workflow optimisation pinnacle,
where all inefficiencies have been excised from the system. In reality, goal
posts like to move it move it, and so the scramble never ends.</p>
<p>How do you approach this?</p>
<h1 id="icemirb">ICEMiRB</h1>
<p><em>The International Conference on Emacs, Minimal Running and Blogging</em>, or
ICEMiRB, is a new meeting of minds and legs that the aforementioned and
indomitable <a href="https://mentat.za.net">@stefanvdwalt</a> and I are currently bouncing
around.</p>
<p>I actually just want the t-shirt, but the more I think about this, the more I
think it&rsquo;s something that one day really has to happen.</p>
<p>Please let me know in the comments if you would be interested in taking part.</p>
<p>I imagine we will go all out in terms of the various forms of attendance and
participation that we accommodate.</p>
<p>Have a beautiful week folks, I hope to see you again soon!</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>@stefanvdwalt just reminded me that Mindfulness is to be the fourth main topic
of the ICEMiRB.</p>
<p>Because the acronym is already of substantial girth (yes, we know that
Mindfulness and Minimal could co-habit the same part of the
acronym. coincidence?!), we will try to settle for one of two conference
taglines:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ICEMiRB - A Mindful(TM) Conference.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>or</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ICEMiRB - The Mindfulness is silent.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>or not.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>