<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Masks4all on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/masks4all/</link><description>Recent content in Masks4all on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 15:33:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/masks4all/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #193: COVID-19 part 3.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 15:33:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</guid><description> Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.
The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12 to Sunday May 2.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_7d89392b07c58b4d.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_753d6f0ee79aeca5.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_3d00f1f7a662d933.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_b5ad8d4373cf7a35.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu_753d6f0ee79aeca5.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!--
2020-05-02 21:38 Boiler Room Solomun 2015 playing on the second screen while
I'm typing this.  I was hoping to understand why this has 43M views, and my
favourite boiler room of all time, Maceo Plex in Berlin in 2015, has "only"
11M.

Let me know in the comments if you read this. :)
-->
<p>The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12
to Sunday May 2.</p>
<p>This post has a strong nerd flavour. If that is not your inclination, please
use the table of contents (to your right) to navigate to the bits that you do
find interesting.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re in a rush, and can only select one section, I would recommend <a href="#the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">the
one on Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Have fun!</p>
<h2 id="covid-19-status-update">COVID-19 status update</h2>
<p>On Friday, May 1, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/lockdown-level-4-what-is-now-allowed-2020-4">the South African lockdown was slightly lifted from level 5
to level
4</a>.</p>
<p>This means that a part of the workforce will start returning to work, and that
citizens are allowed slightly more freedom of movement.</p>
<p>If safety had been the only requirement, we should probably have had to
continue with level 5 for a while longer, but that darned economy unfortunately
also has to be kept afloat.</p>
<p>In spite of this, I was super pleased to read the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Masks are obligatory.</strong> Everyone has to wear cloth face masks outside their
homes. If you don&rsquo;t yet have a cloth mask, you can wear a scarf or a t-shirt
wrapped around your mouth and nose, says Dlamini-Zuma.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This might end up being the thing that gets us through this in something that
resembles one piece.</p>
<p>The second announcement I was super happy with, was that we would be allowed
outside for exercise between 6 and 9 in the mornings.</p>
<p>So on Saturday morning I went out for my first post-level-5 run, ON THE
OUTSIDE. (It does feel strange going out on the street for the first time in
five weeks.)</p>
<p>The majority of people I saw actually had some form of face mask going on.</p>
<p>I had expected otherwise, because doing cardiorespiratory exercise with a mask
on is not easy, and people can be stubborn.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/advanced/a20842404/product-review-buff-headwear/">Buffs</a>
are these fantastically useful &ldquo;seamless tubular garments made from
high-performance microfibre&rdquo; that many runners swear by.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out you can <em>also</em> use them as as-running-proof-as-possible face
masks:</p>










<figure><a href="cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask_hu_5873ed277714d934.jpg 480w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg"
            

         width="240"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>Pro-tip: If there&rsquo;s a runner in your life, and you&rsquo;re on the lookout for a
gift, just get them a buff. You can <em>never</em> have too many buffs.</p>
<h2 id="gou-2-is-10">GOU #2 is 10</h2>
<p>My most favourite middle child in the whole world recently hit the double
digits, and she was suitably chuffed with this.</p>
<p>It must be strange experiencing your 10th birthday under these truly surreal
conditions.</p>
<p>On the other hand, when you&rsquo;re 10, you probably don&rsquo;t dwell on thoughts like
that for too long.</p>
<h2 id="miscellaneous-catch-up">Miscellaneous catch-up</h2>
<p>In the past weeks, I wrote a number of other blog posts, started a new blog,
and discovered an obscure but fantastic new blogging tool.</p>
<p>Oh, and my expensive ergonomic keyboard broke.</p>
<h3 id="fantastic-blogging-tools-and-where-to-find-them">Fantastic blogging tools and where to find them</h3>
<p>It all started when I finally got around to exploring
<a href="https://ox-hugo.scripter.co/">ox-hugo</a>, the Emacs package for writing Hugo
posts using Org mode.</p>
<p>You might not recall this, but the mere <em>existence</em> of <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/#build-and-upload-the-new-static-hotness">ox-hugo was the reason
I chose
Hugo</a>
when it was time to leave Wordpress behind.</p>
<!--
Hey there friends reading these hidden messages!

There are multiple explicit and implicit streams of connection running through
these channels and it's lovely.

Anyways, it is now 22:44 and I finished the Solomun boiler room set.

There are indeed so many stories happening in those frames, many of which will
only become apparent after more viewings.

I'm now back to the Maceo Plex set, with a smile of recognition on my face.
-->
<p>Well, it turns out that, <em>if</em> you&rsquo;re an Emacs Org mode user, ox-hugo is pretty
close to blogging nirvana.</p>
<p>In the past few days, I&rsquo;ve used it to turn arbitrary Org mode entries from my
month journal into blog posts, to send the exact same Org mode file to two
different blogs with different sets of title and metadata, and to assert
Neo-in-the-matrix-style control over what goes where and how.</p>
<p>If I have to put my finger on the core of ox-hugo&rsquo;s extreme utility, I would
say that <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi">Kaushal Modi</a>, the brains behind
ox-hugo, has managed to create a perfect coupling between Org mode on the one
hand and Hugo on the other, a coupling that maximally leverages the strengths
of each.</p>
<p>(I will probably be writing more about this, but &hellip; elsewhere. <em>[queue
suspenseful music here]</em>)</p>
<h3 id="other-mostly-very-nerdy-blog-posts">Other mostly very nerdy blog posts</h3>
<p>As part of the ox-hugo investigation, I had to figure out how to <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/04/26/cite-consistently-between-org-ref-and-ox-hugo/">cite
consistently between straight Org mode and
ox-hugo</a>
for automatic bibtex-backed bibliographies.</p>
<p>Inspired by friend <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2020/04/28/voice-capture-org-tasks-on-android/">Stéfan&rsquo;s post on voice capturing and automatically
transcribing notes to Org
mode</a>,
I figured out how to <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/2020/04/30/voice-capture-org-mode-notes-and-more-using-siri-shortcuts-on-ios/">do the same on iOS and wrote it all
up</a>.</p>
<p>If you clicked on that second link, you will have discovered my brand new blog,
the hopefully catchily titled <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">Org Mode
Exocortex</a>. I will be posting <em>ultra</em>-nerdy Emacs
Org mode content over there.</p>
<p>(Friend Stéfan is the very first guest blogger, with a re-post of his Android
speech recognition post linked above. BTW, that was my first guest blogging
experience ever. Life for the Z-list blogger does not move fast.)</p>
<p>Finally, also thanks to ox-hugo&rsquo;s motivation, I figured (haha, now I see what I
did there) out how to make and publish a new <a href="/2020/05/02/drop-in-replacement-for-hugo-figure-shortcode-with-responsive-img-srcset/"><code>figure</code> shortcode for Hugo that
automatically resizes images and gets your browser to download only the best
one</a>!</p>
<h3 id="microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-desktop-at-4-years-rip">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic Desktop at 4 years: RIP</h3>
<p>After all of that good news, I do have to report the following not-so-great news:</p>
<p>After just under four years of approximately one half of my typing, the
<a href="/2016/05/22/weekly-head-voices-107-balance/">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboard I welcomed into my home at the start of
May of 2016</a>, has developed a key
failure.</p>
<p>More specifically, the physical &ldquo;G&rdquo;, which is my &ldquo;I&rdquo; (thanks
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dvorak_keyboard_layout">Dvorak</a>), fails about
30% of the time, with that duty cycle slowly growing.</p>
<p>(You may bring your jokes about why specifically the &ldquo;I&rdquo; is failing first to
the comment section below!)</p>
<p>I opened up the keyboard following <a href="http://emmanuelcontreras.com/how-to/how-to-disassemble-microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-keyboard-and-make-it-wired/">the instructions and photos of Emmanuel
Contreras</a>.</p>
<p>(What I can add to Contreras&rsquo;s information, is that the palm rest is held fast
by no less than 12 little screws, some odd-sized. Pro-tip: When you remove all
of these, put them down in the same pattern as the holes, so that you can get
them back in later.)</p>
<p>However, one unfortunately ends up at the metal backing which is attached to
the top-plate with about 30 or more plastic pop-rivet like mechanisms.</p>
<p>Information online also seems to indicate that once a single key goes, you have
to replace the whole board.</p>
<p>Some more searching brought me to <a href="https://youtu.be/x09inK8-G1Y">this obscure but helpful YouTube
review</a> where Kevin explains that although
everyone at his company loved the keyboard, they had simply accepted it as part
of their business expense to replace them every 6 months to a year.</p>
<p>If you search through <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Microsoft-Ergonomic-Keyboard-Business-5KV-00001/product-reviews/B00CYX26BC/ref=cm_cr_arp_d_viewopt_kywd?pageNumber=1&amp;filterByKeyword=durability">the Amazon reviews for
&ldquo;durability&rdquo;</a>,
it really starts to look like a case of a fantastic keyboard marred by issues
with its durability.</p>
<p>However, if you need a relatively affordable &ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; keyboard, where with
&ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; I mean shaped in such a way that your wrists get to stay more or
less straight while typing, with really great feel and low-impact typing, the
Sculpt comes out on top.</p>
<p>Although it goes against my grain, I should probably be happy with the above
average 4 years that this one managed, and start finding a local source for its
inevitable replacement.</p>
<p>Nerds in the audience: I am very curious to hear about your keyboard
preferences in the comments. Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="two-lessons-learnt-from-how-to-take-smart-notes">Two lessons learnt from How to Take Smart Notes</h2>
<p>On March 31 I quickly read through <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/34507927-how-to-take-smart-notes">Sönke Ahrens&rsquo;s book, How to Take Smart
Notes</a>.</p>
<p>(The full title is actually &ldquo;How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to
Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking &ndash; for Students, Academics and Nonfiction
Book Writers&rdquo;)</p>
<h3 id="the-most-portable-cross-platform-ebook-format-with-self-contained-annotations-is">The most portable cross-platform ebook format with self-contained annotations is&hellip;</h3>
<p>I bought the Kindle book on Amazon, because that&rsquo;s how I&rsquo;ve been doing it for
years.</p>
<p>However, although I prefer reading novels on my Kindle e-Ink device, for
reference works it&rsquo;s a deal breaker that my highlights and notes are not in a
standards compliant format that integrates nicely with <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing personal
knowledge management system</a>.</p>
<p>My goal was to find an alternative format for these books with the following features:</p>
<ul>
<li>Before you answer PDF, which I use extensively for academic papers, typeset
books, and many other things: The alternative format should be fully
reflowable, like the source Kindle book.</li>
<li>Readable and annotations editable on all my non-Kindle devices (Windows,
Linux, macOS, iOS).</li>
<li>Most importantly: Flexible annotations, including at least highlighting and
positional notes, that are stored within the file itself, so they can never
be lost.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t expect this to be too much of a challenge.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<p>After a number of hours spent spelunking down a number of different
rabbit-holes, with epub3 being the greatest disappointment (the spec has all
the features, but the implementations largely lack good annotation support), I
ended up in a place where you probably would not expect to find me&hellip;</p>
<p>Dear readers, the best format that satisfies all requirements above
is&hellip; <code>&lt;FRITS_DRUMROLL /&gt;</code> &hellip; <strong>Microsoft DOCX</strong>!</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been DeDRM&rsquo;ing (google it) the Kindle reference books I
purchase in order to be able to read and annotate them across all my platforms.</p>
<p>For this, the iPad is pretty great.</p>
<p>Once read, the DOCX files, including all of the annotations I made, are stored
in the correct place in my synchronised file hierarchy, and are fully
searchable and accessible with standard tools.</p>
<h3 id="the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">The amazing Niklas Luhmann and his Zettelkasten</h3>
<p>The book itself, <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em>, spends well-deserved time on the
phenomenon that was the prodigiously productive German sociologist Professor
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niklas_Luhmann">Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Over his career, Prof. Luhmann wrote more than 70 books and published almost
400 research articles.</p>
<p>He made a massive impact on the world of sociology and systems theory.</p>
<p>When asked in <a href="https://www.uni-bielefeld.de/soz/luhmann-archiv/pdf/jschmidt_zettelkasten-als-uberraschungsgenerator.pdf">a 1997
interview</a>
how he managed to this productive, he answered:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Ich denke ja nicht alles allein, sondern das
geschieht weitgehend im Zettelkasten. [&hellip;]
Meine Produktivität ist im wesentlichen aus dem
Zettelkasten-System zu erklären. [&hellip;]
Der Zettelkasten kostet mich mehr Zeit als das
Bücherschreiben</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Translated this is probably something like (German readers, help me out here
please):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think everything by myself, but that largely happens in the slip box. [&hellip;]
My productivity is essentially due to that slipbox system. [..]
The slipbox costs me more time than that writing books</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <em>zettelkasten</em> he referred to were quite simply a set of wooden slipboxes,
in which he could store pieces of paper (the &ldquo;slips&rdquo;), each of which had a
single idea written on it.</p>
<p>It looked more or less exactly like this:</p>










<figure><a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu_25876075ce4fd140.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu_516f4a1013e82a40.jpg 800w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu_516f4a1013e82a40.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Photo of Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Photo of Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Over the course of his career, he managed to write about 90000 (yes, ninety
thousand) of these notes, all of which you can now <a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">browse online at the Niklas
Luhmann-Archiv</a>.</p>
<p>Importantly, he had come up with an ingenious numbering system for linking each
new note to its chain of predecessors, and also to other related chains
anywhere in the zettelkasten.</p>
<p>When it was time to write a book or a paper, he would dive into his this
collection, and then take a stroll through his amazing web of interlinked
thoughts, some of them having matured for years.</p>
<p>Putting together the publication became an exercise in harvesting index cards
from his slipboxes, instead of a positively intimidating mountain of writing,
thinking and rewriting.</p>
<p>This is such a boss-level example of the principle of
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/compounding/">compounding</a>, and one which is
definitely worth trying to follow.</p>
<p>Since reading Ahrens&rsquo;s book, I have started extending <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing note-taking
universe</a> to be more Zettelkasten-like,
when appropriate.</p>
<p>Org mode is a great basis for this, and packages like
<a href="https://github.com/jethrokuan/org-roam">org-roam</a> help us to get closer to our
90-thousand-notes-dreams.</p>
<p>On a higher level, I have been thinking and writing a great deal about how to
merge effectively the Zettelkasten one-idea-per-note approach into the full
spectrum of writing complexity that Org mode supports.</p>
<p>It is important to be mindful of the <em>mode</em> of documentation that you need to
apply at any give point.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about the Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten, <a href="https://writingcooperative.com/zettelkasten-how-one-german-scholar-was-so-freakishly-productive-997e4e0ca125">this Writing
Cooperative article in
English</a>
and <a href="https://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Missing-Link-Luhmanns-Denkmaschine-endlich-im-Netz-4364512.html">this Heise article in
German</a>
are a great start.</p>
<p>This might not be the last time that you&rsquo;ll hear me talking about Luhmann and
his Zettelkasten.</p>
<h2 id="uitzwaaien">Uitzwaaien</h2>
<p>Thank you friends for reading this and connecting with me here!</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #192: COVID-19 part 2.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 11:09:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/</guid><description> A scene from Stilbaai, my number one favourite new vacation destination, taken on the morning after the lockdown had been announced. We were extremely fortunate to spend our last day of freedom in a place like this. Greetings, fellow humans!
It&amp;rsquo;s 16:15 (UTC+2) on Sunday afternoon as I sit here writing this.
The post seems to be mostly planned out, with fragments of text strewn around the editor window right below this sentence.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu_150980dcea0e6037.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu_a0aab4c43ab48a7c.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu_20e690f79b823b8e.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu_da03ecf481d5e618.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu_a0aab4c43ab48a7c.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
A scene from Stilbaai, my number one favourite new vacation destination, taken
on the morning after the lockdown had been announced. We were extremely
fortunate to spend our last day of freedom in a place like this.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Greetings, fellow humans!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s 16:15 (UTC+2) on Sunday afternoon as I sit here writing this.</p>
<p>The post seems to be mostly planned out, with fragments of text strewn around
the editor window right below this sentence.</p>
<p>With sheer luck, I&rsquo;ve managed to find music that interacts well with my current
mood trajectory (finding <em>the right music</em> seems like a truly hard problem),
and at this moment I&rsquo;m still hopeful that I might also have found <a href="/tags/pomodoro/">one whole
pomodoro</a> to work with here.</p>
<p>We are living through some of the most surrealistic times I have ever
experienced.</p>
<p>For friends, for other curious observers and for posterity I think it&rsquo;s now an
even better idea than usual to write down at least some of my observations.</p>
<p>On that note, the older I get, the more clearly I see how the idea of a unified
&ldquo;I&rdquo; going through life is nothing more than an illusion, albeit seemingly
well-made.</p>
<p>In 2014 I <a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">wrote about us being patterns continuously shifting in the sands of
the universe</a>.</p>
<p>Back then, at least if I can go by my writing, it was a dawning
realisation. Now it has become Captain Obvious territory.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS</p>
<p>In this post, I look back at the period of time from Wednesday March 25 to
Sunday April 11.</p>
<h2 id="lockdown-extension">Lockdown extension.</h2>
<p>The South African national lockdown started at midnhight on Thursday, March 26
and would continue for three weeks until April 16.</p>
<p>Of course this virus wasn&rsquo;t magically going to give up and go home after
exactly three weeks.</p>
<p>Just like everyone else, we were only buying time, and I&rsquo;m super happy that we
started when we did.</p>
<p>We know <em>much</em> more now than we knew then. In three weeks more, we&rsquo;ll know even
more.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I&rsquo;ve never before seen the whole of South Africa work
together this well.</p>
<p>There is certaintly some dissent, but by and large the measures seem to be
working, and the curve looks like it is flattening for us.</p>
<p>(There will <em>of course</em> be those, as there always are, who will claim that it
was all much ado about nothing&hellip;)</p>
<p>Although we sort of saw it coming, it was still quite something hearing on
Friday evening, April 10, that the national lockdown would be extended to April
30.</p>
<h2 id="masks4all">#Masks4All</h2>
<p>On March 30, I &ldquo;joined&rdquo; the twitter #masks4all campaign by doing my little bit
to try and convince people everywhere that if <strong>all</strong> of us started wearing
home-made (the good stuff is for the healthcare workers yo!) masks as a rule,
it would contribute substantially to preventing the virus from spreading.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">South Africans, how do
we get our leaders and their advisors to look into <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Masks4All?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Masks4All</a>
as a way to end this lockdown *safely* and get the economy back into action
again? See e.g. <a href="https://t.co/iCMNAwAJhr">https://t.co/iCMNAwAJhr</a>
for a summary. <a
href="https://twitter.com/DrZweliMkhize?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@DrZweliMkhize</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/PresidencyZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@PresidencyZA</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/nicd_sa?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nicd_sa</a></p>&mdash;
Charl Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a
href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1244511197921185792?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March
30, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>I find this extra important, because it could play a really important role,
together with physical distancing, hand-washing and more, in how we end the
lockdown safely and get our already-less-than-robust economy back up and
running.</p>
<p>At the start it felt like no-one was listening, and I was getting anxious.</p>
<p>SOMEONE WAS WRONG ON THE INTERNET, AND THIS TIME IT WAS SERIOUS!</p>
<p>It really did not help that the <a href="https://www.westerncape.gov.za/gc-news/147/54065">official line of the Western Cape Health
Department on March 29 was warning <em>against</em> masks and
gloves</a>. (I&rsquo;ve archived the
statement in case anyone loses it.)</p>
<p>The point that many people were utterly missing at that point but that is
hopefully now embarrassingly obvious, is that the mask is not there to protect
the wearer, it&rsquo;s there to help protect <em>everyone else</em> from being infected by the
wearer.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a week or so (an eternity in COVID-19 time) to April 10, and South
Africa&rsquo;s very own and very respected health minister Dr Zweli Mkhize started
tweeting the new official line that the department of health now also
recommends that everyone wears cloth masks:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Cloth face mask
recommendations: <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MasksCOVID19?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#MasksCOVID19</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ClothFaceMask?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ClothFaceMask</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/COVID_19_ZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@COVID_19_ZA</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/HealthZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@HealthZA</a> <a
href="https://t.co/ptNsa4oUFl">pic.twitter.com/ptNsa4oUFl</a></p>&mdash; Dr
Zweli Mkhize (@DrZweliMkhize) <a
href="https://twitter.com/DrZweliMkhize/status/1248613456934129667?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April
10, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>See the great <a href="https://masks4all.co/">#masks4all.co</a> for more information.</p>
<p>My (microscopic little) work here is done.</p>
<h2 id="work-exercise-and-the-future-in-captivity">Work, exercise and the future, in captivity.</h2>
<h3 id="remote-work">Remote work.</h3>
<p>In <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#outlook">the previous
WHV</a>, I might have
mentioned remote work once or twice.</p>
<p>Well, since then it feels like I&rsquo;ve spent at least three and a half years
working remotely, hard.</p>
<p>I underestimated the amount of automatic, implicit, in-person communication
that happens when you&rsquo;re at the office.</p>
<p>All of that currently has to happen via various video meetings, instant
messenging, emails, and then many more instant messages during the rest of the
day.</p>
<p>In its new form, all of this communication takes quite an amount of time and
energy. It feels like I can only bunker down late morning to start on the
actual work.</p>
<p>(Microsoft Teams is our tool for all of this. Whilst it&rsquo;s not perfect, it has
been serving us quite well.)</p>
<p>In spite of the feeling that communication is taking up significantly more time
and energy, my perception is that, over-all, we engineers get a lot more done
in this new configuration.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I am hopeful that continued practice will reduce the perceived
additional communication effort.</p>
<h3 id="exercise">Exercise.</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s not allowed to leave the house even for exercise, and so my running has
taken quite a hit.</p>
<p>I have had to resort to running circles around the house for half an hour at a
time, which, in spite of me usually really enjoying the monotony of
road-running, is quite a challenge.</p>
<p>On the other hand, there are people who are stuck in apartments and <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/mar/21/man-runs-marathon-on-7-metre-balcony-during-french-lockdown">then run
42km on the
balcony</a>,
and there&rsquo;s even the South African <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/southafrica/comments/fzvtak/south_african_runner_from_george_runs_100_miles/">Eddie Mouton who ran 160km in his
yard</a>.</p>
<p>The elliptical trainer which we bought on July 31 of 2007 (it&rsquo;s the FINNLO
crosstrainer 3252), and for the almost 13 years since then has been nothing
more than an overpriced clothing and towel hanger, has seen more actual
exercise use in the past weeks than during its whole lifetime up to now.</p>
<p>One great upshot of all of this is that we more often train together, or at
least close enough for a high-five now and then.</p>
<h3 id="the-future">The future.</h3>
<p>As I alluded to in the previous <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#outlook">WHV
#191</a>, and
especially as the lockdown has now been extended, giving us even more time to
practise and build habits, I would really like to know how much of what we
learn and experience now is going to stick in the post-covid-19-era?</p>
<p>Noticing how we have to pay much more attention to how exactly we communicate,
realising how much work can actually be fit into a day without too many
interruptions, and seeing how quickly nature uses this time to recover from our
normally incessant onslaught, all lead me to think that we should not stop
analysing and discussing the changes that COVID-19 has brought.</p>
<p>Do you think we&rsquo;ll just flip back to the old normal as soon as we (hopefully)
get through this, or do you think we can look forward to a slightly upgraded
humanity?</p>
<h2 id="thats-all-folks">That&rsquo;s all folks!</h2>
<p>Because this post had already grown substantially larger than I had intended, I
just removed two whole subsections, the beefiest one about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niklas_Luhmann">Niklas
Luhmann</a> and <a href="https://writingcooperative.com/zettelkasten-how-one-german-scholar-was-so-freakishly-productive-997e4e0ca125">his amazing
Zettelkästen / external
brain</a>.</p>
<p>Do not fear, they&rsquo;ll probably make an appearance in a subsequent WHV, or
perhaps even separate posts.</p>
<p>As some of you might have read previously on this blog, the struggle in my head
between these longer form mish-mash-life-snapshot WHV posts on the one hand and
more topic-focused shorter posts on the other has been going on for years, and
will hopefully continue for years more.</p>
<p>(I say hopefully, because that means I might still be posting as well.)</p>
<p>This specific thought is still developing, but I might be starting an
experiment where I do try to write some shorter, more focused posts.</p>
<p>I will keep you up to date!</p>
<p>Ok reader, whoever and wherever you are, I wish you the very best that humanity
has to offer!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>