<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Academia on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/academia/</link><description>Recent content in Academia on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 14:06:05 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/academia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dear Academia, I hope we can still be friends.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 14:06:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/</guid><description>After many great years in academia, I finally decided in October of last year to resign from my position as tenured assistant professor. As of February of this year, I proudly walk the earth as an independent engineer.
It has taken me two years of thinking to reach this decision.
I started re-evaluating my life in academia two years ago after a review-for-promotion (See the &amp;ldquo;oral defence&amp;rdquo; bullet. :)) process that resulted in a &amp;ldquo;not quite yet&amp;rdquo; judgement. It took this long to make my decision, because it was actually going quite well. I had tenure, the holy grail (well, the first of a number of them) for many academics. I had built up and was heading the TU Delft Medical Visualization research group. I was fortunate to attract the best postgraduate students and Ph.D. candidates. My research proposals were successful, so I had money to explore exciting new research avenues. My h-index was (slowly) going in the right direction. Even my teaching was more than occasionally positively received. :)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>After many great years in academia, I finally decided in October of last year
to resign from my position as tenured assistant professor. As of February of
this year, I proudly walk the earth as an independent engineer.</p>
<p>It has taken me two years of thinking to reach this decision.</p>
<p>I started re-evaluating my life in academia two years ago after
a <a href="/2010/09/20/an-indecent-proposal-weekly-head-voices-31/">review-for-promotion (See the &ldquo;oral defence&rdquo;
bullet. :))</a> process
that resulted in a &ldquo;not quite yet&rdquo; judgement. It took this long to make my
decision, because it was actually going quite well. I had
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenure_(academic)">tenure</a>, the holy grail (well,
the first of a number of them) for many academics. I had built up and was
heading the TU Delft Medical Visualization research group. I was fortunate to
attract the best postgraduate students and Ph.D. candidates. My research
proposals were successful, so I had money to explore exciting new research
avenues. My h-index was (slowly) going in the right direction. Even my teaching
was more than occasionally positively received. :)</p>
<p>However, after all this thinking I was finally able to admit to myself that I
am a much better engineer than an academic. All of these years, I had been
applying my engineering talent to the design problem that is academia. This was
successful to a certain extent, but I would never be able to compete with a
Real Academic(tm).</p>
<p><em>More importantly, life is short. It makes sense, and is much more enjoyable,
to spend the largest possible part of it running at full efficiency.</em></p>
<p>Quickly after this realisation, came the next one: I had sub-consciously been
working on a fairly respectable engineering-oriented CV and a great network. I
now had the freedom to work for &hellip; <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">me</a>. I could get back
to designing and building advanced technical artefacts that people actually
use, and I could do so completely on my own terms.</p>
<p>It was definitely not easy to leave academia. The hardest part is leaving
behind the relationships I was privileged to have with my colleagues (friends),
in Delft and the rest of the world. Of course we will still have contact, but
it will never be the same as the 15:30 sugar fix, the caffeine-driven and
super-esoteric debates in the kitchen, the ultra-weird lunch discussions, or
the awesome conversations and beer-drinking at scientific (haha) conferences.</p>
<p>That being said, the wave of creative energy I have been riding on for the past
month, even after correcting for novelty, is a good sign that my choice was a
suitable one. I am happy and relieved to call myself an engineer again.</p>
<p>So Academia, it&rsquo;s really not you, it&rsquo;s me. :)</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Startups vs. Academic Research Groups: FIGHT!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/07/24/startups-vs-academic-research-groups-fight/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2012 21:34:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/07/24/startups-vs-academic-research-groups-fight/</guid><description>There are many similarities between startups, defined here as (relatively) young and agile companies with a few bright people trying to change the world by working on some cool idea(s), and academic research groups, defined here as (relatively) young and agile units within academic institutes with a few bright people trying to change the world by working on some cool idea(s). Err, yes.
Fortunately there are also many differences, so I have something to write about here. For some years now I’ve been running the TU Delft Medical Visualization research group, an experience that shall serve as the primary source of information for this piece. I’ve also had some experience of startup culture, first as one of two (and later three) engineers in a new business unit of Crusader Systems (now CSense) designing an embedded image processing product called FrothMaster, then at Stone Three as employee #1, then later at Treparel as a co-founder and architect, and more recently as scientific advisor to Clinical Graphics and co-founder of TimeScapers. In spite of this healthy dose of exposure, I’ve never actually run a startup as my main activity, so I will have to extrapolate and sometimes revert to wild guesses. I am trusting that some of the startup-involved readers will pipe up in the comments!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>There are many similarities between startups, defined here as (relatively) young and agile companies with a few bright people trying to change the world by working on some cool idea(s), and academic research groups, defined here as (relatively) young and agile units within academic institutes with a few bright people trying to change the world by working on some cool idea(s). Err, yes.</p>
<p>Fortunately there are also many differences, so I have something to write about here. For some years now I’ve been running the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/MedVis" title="TU Delft MedVis Group">TU Delft Medical Visualization research group</a>, an experience that shall serve as the primary source of information for this piece. I’ve also had <em>some</em> experience of startup culture, first as one of two (and later three) engineers in a new business unit of Crusader Systems (now <a href="http://www.csensesystems.com/cms/tiki-index.php" title="CSense website">CSense</a>) designing an embedded image processing product called FrothMaster, then at <a href="http://www.stonethree.com/" title="Stone Three website">Stone Three</a> as employee #1, then later at <a href="http://www.treparel.com/" title="Treparel Website">Treparel</a> as a co-founder and architect, and more recently as scientific advisor to <a href="http://www.clinicalgraphics.com/" title="Clinical Graphics website">Clinical Graphics</a> and co-founder of <a href="http://timescapers.com/" title="TimeScapers website">TimeScapers</a>. In spite of this healthy dose of exposure, I’ve never actually run a startup as my main activity, so I will have to extrapolate and sometimes revert to wild guesses. I am trusting that some of the startup-involved readers will pipe up in the comments!</p>
<p>An academic research group works more or less as follows: Someone, usually a member of faculty (in this case me) at some university has a number of (crackpot) research ideas. Said someone pours buckets of sweat into further developing these ideas into over-detailed research proposals, which are then all rejected by the national and international research funding agencies that they are sent to. Somehow, said someone manages to keep going at this, resulting in proposals that describe projects that have nothing to do any more with the original research ideas, but are works of buzz-word art.</p>
<p>At some point, to the complete surprise of said someone, a number of proposals get approved. This means that buckets of money are handed over to the hosting university. Doh. Faculty member can now put in official requests to make use of these funds to employ a number of bright Ph.D. candidates for 4 years each, to buy toys for said candidates and to pay for visits to parties, I mean conferences, all around the world. Ph.D. candidates work on research project, supervised by faculty member, and each publishes on average 4 good research papers, followed by a thesis, at which case they usually have to be kicked out.</p>
<p>Some of the freshly-minted doctors decide to stay in academia, eventually breaking out of their postdoc cocoons as beautiful faculty members themselves, most often at other academic institutes. Some of the rest even decide to start startups!</p>
<p>At a startup, the main goal is to develop a new product or service, and then sell so much of it that the company turns a huge and sustainable profit. Alternatively, the startup’s product or service and/or people are so sexy that a much larger company decides to buy the whole thing up for a very large bundle of cash, instantly making the founders quite rich. This is called an “exit”. Initial funding strategies vary greatly. Startups can have any mix of bootstrapping (generating little bits of income to feed itself hopefully leading to more income), self financing, venture capital or angel investment. A startup is “<a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/ramenprofitable.html" title="link to Paul Graham's ramen profitability definition">ramen profitable</a>” when it is just able to pay for the founders’ living expenses.</p>
<p><strong>Financing:</strong> Here we see the first significant difference. In academia, a competition upfront determines whether you get financing or not for a particular research idea. Only when you have sufficient financing to appoint people and buy equipment for the duration of the project (generally 2 to 4 years), the relevant project is allowed to start. Faculty salaries are paid by the hosting institute. A startup can start whenever at least one founder is able to get by on their own resources for a few months. The startup is able to get by on very little, but does need to generate income throughout its lifetime, and that income ideally needs to increase steadily so that the company can grow.</p>
<p><strong>Risk:</strong> The second big difference is related to this. At a startup, all the rewards go to the startup, for a largest part to its founders and to a lesser extent to its employees. People work their behinds off, because the payoff could be huge and your chunk is considerable. If your idea happens to change the world (see Dropbox), also the non-monetary kick can be life-changing. However, the risk is also all yours. If your idea bombs and your company blows up into a million pieces, you get to keep each and every piece! Even worse, you actually have to deal with the fallout in some or other fashion. In practice, this could mean bankruptcy of the company, but it could even go as far as directly impacting on the financial status of the founders.</p>
<p>In academia, there is certainly some risk in exploring in new territory, but it is accepted that not all ideas pan out equally well. You’re allowed to fail now and then, as long as you do OK on average. If you fail all the time of course, you’ll probably have a harder time finding new grants and collaborators to continue with your research, but you’ll still have the job. On the other hand, your reward in case of a successful project is that the relevant publications get mentioned by other researchers in their articles. You now have made what is called “impact”, and your <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H-index" title="wikipedia page on h-index">h-index</a> will hopefully start reflecting this soon, making it ever so slightly easier for you to get that next research grant. On a less cynical note, you sometimes are privy to the real kick of scientific discovery, where you’ve managed to cook up something that other scientists (and maybe in 20 years some real people) get really excited about. This latter aspect is in my opinion the actual driver, and the aspect that can make the science business so addictive.</p>
<p><strong>Focus:</strong> A startup needs to have laser sharp focus. You need to pick one thing, service, expertise, product or concept, and become the absolute best at that. This seems to be a recurring theme looking at successful startups. If you do decide to go do something else, you have to call it a “<a href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/start/2012/05/the-pivot-the-moment-where-startups-change-or-die.php" title="readwriteweb explaining the pivot">pivot</a>“, but you cant’t do too many of those, else people think you don’t know what you’re doing. In academia, you should definitely also have a research focus, but the requirements are far less stringent.</p>
<p>Research groups usually have a number of independent research projects, all more or less exploring some general research avenue, but a good devil’s advocate could claim that having different projects constitutes a lack of real focus. In my group for example, I currently have 6 major projects, ranging from surgical planning, through anatomical modelling and neuro-imaging to population imaging, as well as a small number of less major projects. This range is both a blessing and a curse. I have the luxury of exploring and finding cross-links between related but discrete research lines. Also, we have a higher chance of striking gold and a lower risk of striking out with this spread. However, sometimes I think that picking one idea and working on that for a few years would help us to build up more expertise concentration.</p>
<p><strong>Overheads:</strong> Usually an academic research group is embedded within a hosting university. This grants certain advantages, such as infrastructure, and thousands of highly skilled colleagues, but it also means extra overhead. One of the most time-consuming components of this is teaching, an activity with which I have a love-hate relationship. Students who put in the minimum of effort  drain a huge deal of energy per each of their completely useless kilograms. Dedicated students  on the other hand are energising and in some cases decide to join the research group, further bolstering its capabilities.</p>
<p>In a startup, there is usually no hosting institution, and hence no such kind of overhead. I think this generally contributes significantly to the work satisfaction experienced by startuppers, as the level of self-determination is perceived to be much greater due to the lack of any externally imposed constraints. The impression I get from colleagues at my academic institute, is that the constraints or parameters imposed by the hosting institute, including administration, politics and in some cases teaching, can negatively impact on work satisfaction.</p>
<p><strong>Goals:</strong> This one is interesting to think about. I think in both cases the idealistic goal is to discover or create something big that changes the world for the better. Taking a more cynical look at the day to day activities, one could think that the major goal of a research group is to setup larger and larger research programmes involving more and more people and more ambitious research goals, until finally the people at the top lose touch with the work on the ground. The cynical startup founder wants to get rich, either via a fabulous exit or market success, and then do it all again, perhaps at a larger scale.</p>
<p>I think it’s even more important to look past both lofty idealism and cynicism, and instead focus on something that can sustain you indefinitely: <em>Doing something meaningful</em>. Even if that world-changing breakthrough (startup or academia) is not yet in sight, and the bags of cash or the 50-person research group are a really long way off, coming home after work with the conviction that what you’ve done today in some way positively impacts the little world around you will definitely help to keep that spring in your step.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #11: iCalmDown.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/01/31/weekly-head-voices-11-icalmdown/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2010 23:51:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/01/31/weekly-head-voices-11-icalmdown/</guid><description>My Tall Philosophical Neighbour (henceforth TPN) blogged today about the iCalmDown, which, as you know, is the latest Apple product released with perhaps a tad too much fanfare this past week. Yes, I do realise that I’m most privileged to have a tall neighbour who’s both philosophical and manages to blog with more regularity than many. In any case, in a cut-and-dried case of keepin’ up with the Joneses, or the TBN in this case, you are now holding in your hands the eleventh edition of the Weekly Head Voices, documenting a selection of events taking place in week 4 of 2010. Please let me know if you’re reading this on your iCalmDown! SuSE engineers consider this dog to be &amp;quot;quite pretty&amp;quot; and also &amp;quot;so cute and cuddly&amp;quot;.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>My Tall Philosophical Neighbour (henceforth TPN) <a href="http://tokkiebytes.wordpress.com/2010/01/30/apple-brings-the-net-to-the-toilet/" title="link to TPN's iCalmDown blog post">blogged today</a> about the iCalmDown, which, as you know, is the latest Apple product released with perhaps a tad too much fanfare this past week. Yes, I do realise that I’m most privileged to have a tall neighbour who’s <em>both</em> philosophical and manages to blog with more regularity than many. In any case, in a cut-and-dried case of keepin’ up with the Joneses, or the TBN in this case, you are now holding in your hands the eleventh edition of the Weekly Head Voices, documenting a selection of events taking place in week 4 of 2010. Please let me know if you’re reading this on your iCalmDown!










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/01/ugly_dog.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/01/ugly_dog.jpg"
        
            alt="SuSE engineers consider this dog to be &quot;quite pretty&quot; and also &quot;so cute and cuddly&quot;."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>SuSE engineers consider this dog to be &quot;quite pretty&quot; and also &quot;so cute and cuddly&quot;.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>First I have to get some <strong>negative emotions</strong> off my chest: I’m currently <strong>test-driving the TU Delft’s new standard SuSE Enterprise Linux Edition (SLED) 11 image</strong> at work. After two days of using the system and documenting my experiences, I had to switch back to my usual Ubuntu desktop, as my eyes had started bleeding profusely. The SLED desktop takes the concept of “ugly” to places even it feels very dirty having ever visited. Okay, so I might be ever so slightly exaggerating, but there really is almost no comparison with a modern Ubuntu system!</p>
<p>During this past week my <strong>productivity has again made the transition from reactive to proactive</strong>. This is a usual phenomenon after any long vacation, but it sure is a nice feeling being able to start on things long before they become urgent. It gives me some room to strategise and think about the Big Picture. In the same vein, I (once again) realised that I should spend mornings on the creative and heavier-weight items on my todo list, and reserve the afternoons for meetings (which definitely require creativity, but of a different kind) and more routine tasks. For the past months I have followed the policy of scheduling meetings in the afternoons as far as possible, so my mornings are reserved for tasks that require a few hours contiguously. Luxury!</p>
<p>At the start of an evening with two friends (in line with my anonymisation policy, let’s call them Science Entrepreneur Friend, or SEF, and Extremely Clever Yet Very Social Scientist Friend, or ECYVSSF) that ended with me having so much fun that I managed to get caught on the infamous Dutch nachtnet (trains that take party-goers home at ungodly hours), SEF pointed out that my “to learn and to create” snippet of the <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/01/24/weekly-head-voices-10-loose-bits-sink-chips/" title="Link to previous post.">previous post</a> reminded him of something of <strong>Wilhelm von Humboldt</strong>. After some searching I found the [relevant quote][3]:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To inquire and to create;—these are the grand centres around which all human pursuits revolve, or at least to these objects do they all more or less directly refer. Before inquiry can fathom the very essence of things, or penetrate to the limits of reason, it presupposes, in addition to profundity, a rich diversity and genial warmth of soul—the harmonious exertion of all the human faculties combined.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thank you SEF !</p>
<p>This same evening was characterised by, besides too many Pelgrim Trippels (a strong beer brewed in Rotterdam), much heated discussion on the interaction between <strong>science</strong>, that is how we attain and disseminate new knowledge about the reality around us, and <strong>academia</strong>, that is the interesting ecosphere where science mostly takes place, where scientists work in strange and strict hierarchical castes, and the focus on science can easily be lost due to the practicalities and politics of academia.</p>
<p>For all its faults, it is exactly this strange system that makes it possible for me to work closely together with a number of exceptionally bright people, an energising activity that is arguably very much in the spirit of inquiry and of creativity.</p>
<p>On that positive note, have a brilliant week everyone!</p>
<p>[3]: <a href="http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&amp;staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=589&amp;chapter=45502&amp;layout=html&amp;Itemid=27">http://oll.libertyfund.org/?option=com_staticxt&amp;staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=589&amp;chapter=45502&amp;layout=html&amp;Itemid=27</a> &ldquo;Link to chapter 8 of Von Humboldt&rsquo;s &ldquo;The Sphere and Duties of Government&rdquo;&rdquo;</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>