<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Kgalagadi on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/kgalagadi/</link><description>Recent content in Kgalagadi on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 22:05:14 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/kgalagadi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #241: Best intentions</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 22:05:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/</guid><description>Welcome back folks to the Weekly Head Voices!
Edition 241 (this one) covers the four weeks from Monday March 21 to Sunday April 17 of the year 2022.
This time, my excuse for being so late is our autumn vacation trip to Augrabies and the Kgalagagi Transfrontier park.
The Knersvlakte-Augrabies-Kgalagadi-Calvinia vacation trip The super short summary is as follows:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks to the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>Edition 241 (this one) covers the four weeks from Monday March 21 to Sunday
April 17 of the year 2022.</p>
<p><em>This</em> time, my excuse for being so late is our autumn vacation trip to Augrabies
and the Kgalagagi Transfrontier park.</p>










<figure><a href="augrabies-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu_b68ee6581e7e6b51.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu_1e991a7788e16538.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu_d7051693ec93fd32.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu_9df164a2cd4f86e4.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/augrabies-pano_hu_1e991a7788e16538.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-knersvlakte-augrabies-kgalagadi-calvinia-vacation-trip">The Knersvlakte-Augrabies-Kgalagadi-Calvinia vacation trip</h2>
<p>The super short summary is as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>My extremely resourceful partner had managed to book a few nights in rest
camps in Kgalagadi about a year ago. That&rsquo;s generally how early you need to
be for this.</li>
<li>As the vacation came closer, we accidentally configured a really cool road
trip (&ldquo;sloertoer&rdquo; as I recently learned) to sandwich the Kgalagadi bit in the
middle.
<ul>
<li>On the way there, we stayed at <a href="https://letsatsi.ncfamouslodges.com/">Letsatsi Lodge in Vanrhynsdorp</a>, and we spent
two nights at the Augrabies falls. The falls were absolutely
spectacular. Besides the panorama above, <a href="https://youtu.be/DW8SFHUP_18">this clip</a> of the falls at sunset
should give you a taste of what we experienced.
<ul>
<li>On the last night, our braai was attacked by a swarm of locusts. This was
so intense that the rest of the clan had to move indoors. I remained
outside with the braai and the locusts, witnessing thousands of the
beasts burn themselves up in the flames.
<ul>
<li>This event seemed like a great excuse to look up the difference between
grasshoppers and locusts. Maybe you already knew this, but I did
not. Grasshoppers <em>transform</em> into locusts. The transformation is both
physical, modulated by serotonin (which is also a super important
neurotransmitter in humans) and social; grasshoppers are loners, while
locusts are born, live and die as a swarm.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>On the journey&rsquo;s final leg back home from Nossob, we spent a night in the
Blou Nartjie in Calvinia.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Kgalagadi was magic.
<ul>
<li>On the one morning where we were able to get up early enough to exit as the
Tweerivieren gates opened (this is The Way), we were lucky enough to spend
some close-up alone time with two cheetah close to Kamfersboom. Ironically,
this happened much later in the morning as we were on our way back to the
camp. You never know&hellip;</li>
<li>On other drives we spotted lion, leopard (lazing in a tree, a lot further
away than the cheetah who were almost at touching distance), springbok,
lots of gemsbok (surprise!), meerkat and fox.</li>
<li>The balmy evenings outside, with intensely brilliant starry skies, were
unexpectedly good.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="kgalagadi-tfp-sign.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hu_c44581243df350c8.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hu_9e23f14b3afa03b4.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hu_278561f17b58b7b2.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hu_ee81534d5bf68b36.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/04/20/weekly-head-voices-241-best-intentions/kgalagadi-tfp-sign_hu_9e23f14b3afa03b4.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Red Karahari sand!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Red Karahari sand!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="the-period-after-the-trip">The period after the trip</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m writing this sentence here during the last few hours of the Easter weekend.</p>
<p>As I wrote in my mostly private and personal diary this morning: &ldquo;Man, these
days were really good for a reset, spending time on meta-work (emacs config,
planning config, and so on) and family.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(On the topic of keeping diaries and on the topic of deciding to publish some
of the private bits, here is another extract: &ldquo;Reviewing the past 4 weeks of
notes for hopefully soon-to-be-published WHV 241 also reminded me of so many
bits of peace and wisdom. I&rsquo;ve said this before, it&rsquo;s like I&rsquo;m up and down the
scale of human, and the high performing / balanced human needs to write
encouraging messages to the more frequently active normal / inferior me.&rdquo;)</p>
<p>Moving on&hellip;</p>
<p>In the time since the vacation trip, I&rsquo;ve been exceptionally privileged and
grateful to have a small selection of close friends visit in various
configurations.</p>
<p>In some cases I could offer only my ears although I desperately wanted to help
more, and in other cases they were less complicated life-affirming
celebrations.</p>
<p>In all cases, this is what I&rsquo;m here for.</p>
<p>(Later, I would really like to talk more about how easily and how often I
manage to forget that when I get caught up stress.)</p>
<h2 id="a-smidgen-of-nerd-news">A smidgen of nerd news</h2>
<p>It turns out that my <a href="/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/#new-diagramming-tool-of-the-insert-suitable-period-here">favourite quickly-sketch-out-your-idea tool excalidraw</a> is
a cinch to run locally, if you already have node and yarn installed, and who
doesn&rsquo;t these days?!</p>
<p>As you can see from the docs, it&rsquo;s just a <code>git clone</code>, <code>yarn</code> and <code>yarn start</code> away.</p>
<p>I thought this was going to be important during our Kgalagadi trip, because
patchy internet, so I got it going one evening in Twee Rivieren.</p>
<p>(Narrator: After that, he never used it, but he could have!)</p>
<p>Other than that, I had <a href="https://github.com/FuPeiJiang/VD.ahk/pull/10">fun helping to fix up an open source AutoHotkey library
for using Windows API calls to switch desktops quickly</a>.</p>
<p>I use this library in my simple but fast tool, called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/vxdesktops.ahk">vxdesktops.ahk, for
hotkey-based switching between virtual desktops on Windows</a>. I put this together
when I saw yet another screencast of someone showing off how quickly they could
switch using <a href="/2014/09/23/weekly-head-voices-82-tiles-and-platitutes/">i3wm</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-surprising-effectiveness-of-assuming-best-intentions">The surprising effectiveness of assuming best intentions</h2>
<p>With a small group of friends, we have for a while now been applying the idea
of always assuming best intentions, and always <em>having</em> the best intentions.</p>
<p>I knew that this is how I would generally like to operate, but I was still
pleasantly surprised by how this has turned so many potentially difficult
conversations into constructive and educational interactions that have enriched
us all.</p>
<p>So recently, <a href="https://rickmanelius.com/article/assume-positive-intent">a 2017 blog post by Rick Manelius, titled Assume Positive Intent</a>,
was again featured on HN where it caught my attention.</p>
<p>He makes the case for <em>always</em> assuming positive intent, also outside of groups
of friends where you can explicitly agree upon this principle.</p>
<p>Of course he excludes low trust environments from this mode, but generally in
business, and other interactions with strangers in non-low-trust environments,
assuming positive intent will work well (and be far less tiring) far more often
than it won&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>My humble suggestion here would be to try the explicit configuration of
bilaterally best intentioned environments wherever possible because this is
really an amazing way to connect with fellow humans, and to assume positive
intent everywhere else where it makes sense.</p>
<p>I hope to be able to write more eloquently about this in a future post.</p>
<p>Thank you for joining me here!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>