<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>rain on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/rain/</link><description>Recent content in rain on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2011 14:09:51 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/rain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Opportunity Cost [Weekly Head Voices #52]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/07/17/opportunity-cost-weekly-head-voices-52/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2011 14:09:51 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/07/17/opportunity-cost-weekly-head-voices-52/</guid><description> On Thursday July 14, 2011, it rained for 20.5 hours straight, and it did so from all directions at the same time (yes, apparently also in the upwards direction as my wet socks will attest). The last time it rained this much on one day, was on July 17, 1954, as confirmed by the paper this weekend. I believe I might also have broken several swearing records (in terms of duration, variation, originality and vehemence) whilst struggling through the water on my bicycle, on my way to my work.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>On Thursday July 14, 2011, it rained for 20.5 hours straight, and it did so from all directions at the same time (yes, apparently also in the upwards direction as my wet socks will attest). The last time it rained this much on one day, was on July 17, 1954, as confirmed by the paper this weekend. I believe I might also have broken several swearing records (in terms of duration, variation, originality and vehemence) whilst struggling through the water on my bicycle, on my way to my work.</p>
<p>I think the Dutch climate is just trying to remind us that it’s just <em>really not nice</em>, and that this “summer” that others speak of is merely a figment of their imagination. Probably for the purpose of wound-focused salt-rubbing, the weather every so often does have its moments, like this morning in my garden when I managed to photograph some bees doing their thing in the few minutes that the sun timidly managed to appear before being assertively occluded by infinitely high stacks of angry-looking clouds:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/bee_on_flower1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/bee_on_flower1-894x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Profile of bee on flower. Note the strong jawline. Cell-phone camera seems to have at least some idea with regard to macro mode."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Profile of bee on flower. Note the strong jawline. Cell-phone camera seems to have at least some idea with regard to macro mode.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/bee_on_flower2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/bee_on_flower2-1024x949.jpg"
        
            alt="Different bee on different flower. Hard to see the jawline, but wingspan is quite impressive."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Different bee on different flower. Hard to see the jawline, but wingspan is quite impressive.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Besides complaining about the weather, I did want to discuss briefly with you an interesting economic concept, a concept that I’ve decreed will henceforth go through life as a  backyard philosophical idea. The idea that I’m on about is called <strong><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opportunity_cost" title="wikipedia page on opportunity cost">opportunity cost</a></strong>, and refers to the cost that one incurs engaging in an activity, measured in terms of the best alternative that one could have engaged in otherwise. For example, if you’re sitting around refreshing your Twitter / Google+ / Facebook  <em>instead of</em> implementing a new and improved type of internet-connected sliced bread, potentially worth ONE BILLION DOLLARS, the opportunity cost of your social networking addiction at that point is, you guessed it, ONE BILLION DOLLARS. I really like the idea that Friedrich von Wieser named this phenomenon (that I have previously unknowingly <a href="/2011/05/22/just-one-thing-weekly-head-voices-49/" title="just one thing blog post">touched upon</a>) and will henceforth apply it liberally. So if I walk away from a conversation, mumbling something along the lines of ONE BILLION DOLLARS, you know why. Seriously though, it is good to keep this idea in mind in everything that you do, especially since cost can be measured in ways other than hard currency.</p>
<p>… and now for something completely different:</p>
<p>I have recently received the joyous news that a certain musical genius and his mind-blowing audio-visual spectacle are planning to be present at a <a href="http://www.last.fm/festival/1647011+A+Campingflight+to+Lowlands+Paradise+2011" title="LL 2011">certain festival</a> that is soon to take place:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WWai4UZ0OqI?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Just sayin’.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Time does wait for electronic true love [Weekly Head Voices #30]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/12/time-does-wait-for-electronic-true-love-weekly-head-voices-30/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 15:06:55 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/12/time-does-wait-for-electronic-true-love-weekly-head-voices-30/</guid><description> I probably shouldn’t be spending deadline-chasing time writing this post, but I can’t not, you know? I do have some Sunday pomodoros behind me, so the FNSF (and other involved parties) will probably not mind too much. Also, to shave off a few more seconds, I’ll temporarily switch to the Swimgeek Quick Update-style bullet list.
Before the first bullet however, you really have to see the DTV Shredder in action, the vehicle I’ve decided to equip my evil footsoldiers with, right after I manage to purchase a suitable volcanic island and install my evil lair:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I probably shouldn’t be spending deadline-chasing time writing this post, but I can’t not, you know? I do have some Sunday <a href="http://www.pomodorotechnique.com/" title="Pomodoro Technique website">pomodoros</a> behind me, so the <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviation page">FNSF</a> (and other involved parties) will probably not mind too much. Also, to shave off a few more seconds, I’ll temporarily switch to the <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/" title="SwimGeek's blog">Swimgeek Quick Update-style</a> bullet list.</p>
<p>Before the first bullet however, you really have to see the DTV Shredder in action, the vehicle I’ve decided to equip my evil footsoldiers with, right after I manage to purchase a suitable volcanic island and install my evil lair:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ws8zIHW6Ghk?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>(found via <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2010/09/12/what-happens-when-you-leave-a-skateboard-and-a-tank-alone-in-a-d/" title="engadget post on the DTV Shredder">engadget</a>.)</p>
<p>Here come the bullets:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Due to the completion of the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/TI1100A" title="TI 1100-a website">TI 1100-a project</a> by the end of the previous week, I was expecting this week to be of the more relaxed persuasion. I couldn’t have been more wrong. It turns out that a number of deadlines were simply in stealth mode, waiting for the right moment to pounce. Colour me surprised.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="Link to WHV abbreviations page">extremely resourceful  / capable individual (ERCI)</a> mentioned in <a href="/2009/09/13/weekly-head-voices-3-powerless-meat-zen-xi-leaves-nfbi-motek/" title="Weekly Head Voices #3">WHV #3</a> and <a href="/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/" title="Weekly Head Voices #9">#9</a> completed his M.Sc. under the entertaining supervision of the <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">FSNF</a> and myself, defended his thesis (title: <em>Integrated Visual Analysis for Heterogeneous Datasets in Cohort Studies — Application to Neuropsychiatric SLE</em>) this past week, and managed to acquire his whole degree <em>Cum Laude</em>. Congratulations Ir. ERCI, we hope to see much more of you during the coming years *wink wink*!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It turns out that combining a Goretex raincoat, a <a href="http://www.senzumbrellas.com/" title="Senz Umbrellas website">Senz aerodynamic storm-proof umbrella</a> (truly awesome tech, designed by a TU Delft spinoff) and a set of <a href="http://rainlegs.com/" title="RainLegs website">RainLegs</a> (you look like the missing fifth member of the <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CS9OO0S5w2k" title="YMCA original by the Village People">Village People</a>, but your legs remain dry) results in a pretty effective counter-measure against the soul-demolishing Dutch Autumn rain, if one is able to live with wet feet. A Facebook friend with some serious tropical storm experience also recommended a pair of those big Timberland boots, a suggestion that for some or other reason resonated with me, and not only because it would solve my wet feet problem. He meant these really pretty yellow boots with the macho-looking soles:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg"
        
            alt="These are the Timberland boots you were looking for."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>These are the Timberland boots you were looking for.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>On Thursday, my <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kindle-DX-Wireless-Reader-3G-Global/dp/B002GYWHSQ/" title="website Kindle DX graphite">Kindle DX Graphite</a> was delivered by the friendly UPS dude. It was love at first sight (with the Kindle and not the UPS dude), and since then my feelings have only deepened. You see, the Kindle DX embodies the fusion of two of my greatest fetishes: Reading and high-tech gadgets. Ostensibly I bought it to try paperlessify my academic review work (papers, student theses, proposals, all printed out numerous times and finally thrown out for recycling) and as soon as firmware 3.0 has been released for the KDX Graphite and I get some time I’ll write a critical blog post concerning its performance in this role, but for now I’m just euphoric with the thing as general reading platform. <a href="http://calibre-ebook.com/" title="Calibre website">Calibre</a>, once you get used to its idiosyncrasies, is fantastic as a cross-platform library manager.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Specific events of the past week, as well as interesting conversations with the FSNF and others, have again pointed out that terminal over-booking might be necessarily associated with a post-Ph.D. academic career. During your Ph.D., you have the exquisite luxury of focusing on one (perhaps three) important things for extended periods of time. Thereafter, right after the defence-afterglow has subsided, if you decide to stay in academia, your calendar and task-manager explode in a messy deluge of meetings, administration and forced work during the evenings and weekends, because this is the only way to get more than half of your stuff done. I have it from trustworthy sources that this only gets worse the further along you get in your career. As I’ve invested heavily in optimising my own time utilisation and efficiency, and now have a strategy that, although there’s significant room for improvement, doesn’t work <em>too</em> badly, I’m planning to put together <em>The Great Academic Time Management Post</em>. If you already disagree with this or with what you think the contents of the post might turn out to be, please vent in the comments!</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it for this episode. My big red pomodoro timer is looking at me in a decidedly unfriendly way… The rest of you have a great week!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>