<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Tron2 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/tron2/</link><description>Recent content in Tron2 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2011 11:13:58 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/tron2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2011: A Cyber-Suburban Odyssey [Weekly Head Voices #35]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/09/2011-a-cyber-suburban-odyssey-weekly-head-voices-35/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2011 11:13:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/09/2011-a-cyber-suburban-odyssey-weekly-head-voices-35/</guid><description>In spite of last year’s Space Odyssey also not quite panning out as Kubrick and Clarke might have hoped, I had a great year. Sure, it had its fair share of curve-balls, but in terms of personal growth (am I even allowed to use that term? I hope the cliché police are still on vacation) I am most satisfied. My traditional year-end vacation, as per usual filled with family, friends (slightly less than usual due to genetic offspring #2 related constraints), sun, sand, beer and deep thought, helped wonderfully in my subconscious processing (the most important kind) and integration of the past year’s events. A boat peacefully floating on the calm waters of the New Harbour in Hermanus. The sky was more blue and the water more azure than you can imagine. Accompanied by S+R, I was experiencing what can only be called a perfect day.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In spite of last year’s Space Odyssey also not quite panning out as Kubrick and Clarke might have hoped, I had a great year. Sure, it had its fair share of curve-balls, but in terms of personal growth (am I even allowed to use that term? I hope the cliché police are still on vacation) I am most satisfied. My traditional year-end vacation, as per usual filled with family, friends (slightly less than usual due to genetic offspring #2 related constraints), sun, sand, beer and deep thought, helped wonderfully in my subconscious processing (the most important kind) and integration of the past year’s events.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/hermanus_new_harbour.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/hermanus_new_harbour.jpg"
        
            alt="A boat peacefully floating on the calm waters of the New Harbour in Hermanus. The sky was more blue and the water more azure than you can imagine. Accompanied by S&#43;R, I was experiencing what can only be called a perfect day."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>A boat peacefully floating on the calm waters of the New Harbour in Hermanus. The sky was more blue and the water more azure than you can imagine. Accompanied by S+R, I was experiencing what can only be called a perfect day.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I’m still working on my New Year’s resolutions, because I think it’s important to have excuses spend time thinking about one’s ways. There’s something in there about more concrete planning (I’m working on a secret list of milestones for 2011), and also about spending more time each day on the <a href="http://www.pickthebrain.com/blog/important-vs-urgent-5-ways-to-focus-on-what-really-matters/" title="important vs urgent"><em>important</em> tasks as opposed to the <em>urgent</em> tasks</a>. How about you?</p>
<p>May your journey in 2011 be at least as cool as the cyber-suburban odyssey I have planned! To get you in the right frame of mind, here’s a track from the Daft Punk soundtrack of the new <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1104001/" title="IMDB page for the Tron: Legacy movie">Tron: Legacy movie</a>:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_6Afc2uzw4g?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>P.S. I’m so old, I still vividly remember the <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0084827/" title="IMDB page of the first tron">first Tron movie</a>. It played a significant role in the shaping of my young character.</p>
<p>P.P.S. I’ve put my beloved E71 in storage and am now the proud owner of a charge-me-3-times-per-day-please <a href="http://www.htc.com/www/product/desirez/overview.html" title="HTC Desire Z product page">HTC Desire Z</a> micro-laptop with built-in phone. I’m going to try and write a post about it soon. Short story: In spite of the battery, I’m in love again.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. Go and memorise <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_common_misconceptions" title="Wikipedia's list of common misconceptions">Wikipedia’s list of common misconceptions</a>. Go around correcting as many people as you can. Make new friends!</p>
<p>P.P.P.P.S. For the fetishists amongst you, here is the yearly my-feet-on-vacation photo:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/chapmans_peak_hotel.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/chapmans_peak_hotel.jpg"
        
            alt="My feet having a good time at the almost-Infinity pool on the roof of the Chapman&#39;s Peak hotel (you really have to go there)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>My feet having a good time at the almost-Infinity pool on the roof of the Chapman's Peak hotel (you really have to go there).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>