<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Begging the Question on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/begging-the-question/</link><description>Recent content in Begging the Question on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2002 16:44:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/begging-the-question/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Slashdot Idiots</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2002/04/03/slashdot-idiots/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2002 16:44:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2002/04/03/slashdot-idiots/</guid><description>Today on Slashdot:
I&amp;rsquo;m guessing that everyone here has a valid criticism of Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s attacks on, and approach towards the Open Source model. To me, that begs the question of what we think would be an &amp;ldquo;appropriate&amp;rdquo; reaction from Microsoft towards the Open Source model… Article here.
This always makes me grind my teeth. No, you illiterate pseudo-intellectual idiot, you can not use that phrase like that. Let me quote from the website of Prof. Paul Brians (and the same information is available from a million other places):</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Today on Slashdot:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m guessing that everyone here has a valid criticism of Microsoft&rsquo;s attacks on, and approach towards the Open Source model. To me, that <strong>begs the question</strong> of what we think would be an &ldquo;appropriate&rdquo; reaction from Microsoft towards the Open Source model… Article <a href="http://slashdot.org/askslashdot/02/04/02/2346210.shtml?tid=109">here</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This always makes me grind my teeth. No, you illiterate pseudo-intellectual idiot, you can not use that phrase like that. Let me quote from <a href="https://brians.wsu.edu/2016/05/19/begs-the-question/">the website of Prof. Paul Brians</a> (and the same information is available from a million other places):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>An argument which improperly assumes as true the very point the speaker is trying to argue for is said in formal logic to &ldquo;beg the question.&rdquo; Here is an example of a question-begging argument: &ldquo;This painting is trash because it is obviously worthless.&rdquo; The speaker is simply asserting the worthlessness of the work, not presenting any evidence to demonstrate that this is in fact the case. Since we never use &ldquo;begs&rdquo; with this odd meaning (&ldquo;to improperly take for granted&rdquo;) in any other phrase, many people mistakenly suppose the phrase implies something quite different: that the argument demands that a question about it be asked -– raises the question. <strong>If you&rsquo;re not comfortable with formal terms of logic, it&rsquo;s best to stay away from this phrase, or risk embarrassing yourself.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>(P.S. in 2018: That last bolded sentence has been replaced with: <em>Although using the expression in its original sense is now rare, using it in the newer sense will cause irritation among traditionalists</em>. Oi.)</p>
<p>(P.P.S. in 2024: 2002-me was a lot angrier than I am now, but I still do prefer that people raise questions, unless they indeed know exactly what they are doing.)</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>