<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Ntfs on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/ntfs/</link><description>Recent content in Ntfs on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 09:39:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/ntfs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #184: The tai chi of you.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 09:39:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/</guid><description>Welcome travellers of the great and beautiful information universe!
(That universe was what we were promised. Thanks to the inherent and fundamental difficulties of our meat-based reality, we have ended up with something&amp;hellip; different. I remain hopeful.)
Here in this little corner, I&amp;rsquo;ll be reminiscing about the minuscule thread of personal time stretched taut between Monday, November 11 and Sunday, November 18.
pling
(that&amp;rsquo;s me plucking the thread. meat-space issues&amp;hellip;)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome travellers of the great and beautiful information universe!</p>
<p>(That universe was what we were promised. Thanks to the inherent and
fundamental difficulties of our meat-based reality, we have ended up with
something&hellip; <em>different</em>. I remain hopeful.)</p>
<p>Here in this little corner, I&rsquo;ll be reminiscing about the minuscule thread of
personal time stretched taut between Monday, November 11 and Sunday, November
18.</p>
<p><em>pling</em></p>
<p>(that&rsquo;s me plucking the thread. meat-space <em>issues</em>&hellip;)</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_606c3f258a6b0b88.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_3a6cea229427325.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_b395dc5b81a89f2b.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_f503d59cdfd80a62.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/gate_torso_hu_3a6cea229427325.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
One of the views at Gåte, Quoin Rock.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="intermezzo-for-computer-nerds-wsl2">Intermezzo for computer nerds: WSL2.</h2>
<p>Microsoft released <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windowsexperience/2019/11/11/releasing-windows-10-insider-preview-build-19013-into-the-slow-ring/">Windows build 19013 onto the Windows Insider Preview slow
ring</a>, along with the shiny new WSL2.</p>
<p>WSL is a truly interesting development in the evolution of Windows that enables
users to run arbitrary Linux binaries with full Windows integration.</p>
<p>I run a true-blue Linux installation of Emacs on WSL, displaying to X410 on the
Windows side, manipulating files on the native Windows NTFS filesystem.</p>
<p>This is substantially faster for some or other reason than running native
Windows Emacs.</p>
<p>Anyways, WSL2 is the next significant jump for WSL where Microsoft is now
shipping a native Linux kernel together with Windows and exposing this kernel
via a light-weight Hyper-V utility VM with dynamic host memory allocation.</p>
<p>I was planning to wait until it got released on stable, but when MS announced
that it was available on the slow ring of the Windows Insider Previews, the
temptation was too great.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">The ThinkPad, my main development machine</a>, is
now running this hopefully relatively safe Windows preview.</p>
<p>At this point, I can report that WSL2&rsquo;s IO on its own local filesystem is
indeed much faster than WSL&rsquo;s. However, IO on the host NTFS filesystem is three
to four times slower&hellip;</p>
<p>This is indeed <em>quite</em> disappointing, as my work use-cases all involve
accessing files on the NTFS side in some or other way.</p>
<p>An unexpected bonus of WSL2 however, is the Docker integration.</p>
<p>Docker for Windows Edge is able to use WSL2 as a backend, meaning much, much
faster starting and general usage of docker containers on Windows.</p>
<p>I really hope that MS is able to improve the 9p-based NTFS IO performance of
WSL2 to at least that of WSL.</p>
<p>Far more unrealistically, I hope that MS finally retires NTFS and replaces it
with something better.</p>
<p>Windows really has been making great strides over the past
years. Unfortunately, NTFS is a gigantic ball and chain that is currently doing
a great job of holding the whole of Windows back.</p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>At the start of 2019, I wrote that I had an <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#looking-forward-1">&ldquo;additional concrete (but very
humble) running-related resolution for 2019, but I have decided to keep that
quiet until it’s in the
pocket&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>Well, it&rsquo;s in the pocket and now I can talk about it.</p>
<p>On Saturday morning I went out for my usual longer weekend run (longer is
anything greater than 10km).</p>
<p>It was cool for this time of the year, and there was almost no
wind.</p>
<p>Importantly, I had had a solid night of sleep.</p>
<p>As I was going out, Morning-Voice whispered in my head: &ldquo;It&rsquo;s highly probably
now, or never again in 2019&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I nodded in agreement.</p>
<p>My longer weekend run proceeded to morph successfully into the casual 20km run
that I had envisioned as my most concrete 2019 running goal.</p>
<p>Achievement unlocked!</p>
<p>Although I had indeed formulated the goal as &ldquo;doing a casual 20km run&rdquo;, the
<em>actual</em> goal was being fit enough to be able to do so more or less on a whim.</p>
<p>For my next trick, I&rsquo;ll try my best not to let it slip back too far.</p>
<p>OH HAI THERE LOOMING HOLIDAY SEASON!</p>
<h2 id="things-are-not-always-what-they-seem">Things are not always what they seem.</h2>
<p>After the morning run, we met with multi-decade close friends for lunch at the
restaurant Gåte at Quoin Rock.</p>
<p>That alternative &ldquo;å&rdquo;, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%85">also known as the
a-ring</a>, should give the first clue that
this place is hipper even than any of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefon">Stefon&rsquo;s
recommendations</a>.</p>
<p>I found the whole experience to be quite magical.</p>
<p>The 25 year old genius chef, Nicole Loubser, together with her team, has
constructed the most amazing culinary experience.</p>
<p>See the airport coffee and cigar below for example:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_4f0b80bef8c1827d.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_84059f263a6f246d.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_86205c6719bb0dd7.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_774ed6e5ccde909f.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/nothing_is_what_it_seems_hu_84059f263a6f246d.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The first of the 7 course lunch menu at Gåte. The macchiato is in fact tomato
soup with a pumpkin espuma on top, the ashtray is a paprika espuma with
maltodextrin on top, and the cigar is potato bread.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Our company, together with the beautiful surroundings and the party that had
entered via my mouth into my sensory system, made for a truly sublime
afternoon.</p>
<h2 id="electro-backyard-philosophy">Electro-backyard-philosophy.</h2>
<p>TPN recently and very fortunately pointed out that <a href="https://jorisvoorn.com/">Joris
Voorn</a>, probably my favourite electro artist, has a
new album out.</p>
<p>The album is of course called \\\\.</p>
<p>Below is an excerpt from the lyrics of track 8, <em>This City (feat. Lazarusman)</em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You are not alone.</p>
<p>When you have yourself.</p>
<p>How can you be alone<br>
How can you be alone when you have yourself?<br>
When you have you?</p>
<p>it is you mastering the art, the tai chi, of you</p>
<p>it is you realising that these fleeting moments are all for you</p>
<p>you have yourself<br>
you are not alone</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To my mind, these words contain echoes of both mindfulness and of
transcendental idealism, all on the background of an über hip electro beat.</p>
<p>At the almost 2 hour mark, these echoes contributed much pleasure to the mental
aspects of my run.</p>
<p>Now when I listen to it in a different state of mind, it is clear that the
music made the impact that it did due to the specific set of circumstances at
that moment.</p>
<p>This is a good demonstration of how dependent an experience can be, and how
fickle and unpredictable one&rsquo;s preferences.</p>
<p>(How do we <em>ever</em> make good choices?)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I have chosen to keep hold of the lessons,
irrespective of the subjective ephemerality of their container.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>