<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Knp on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/knp/</link><description>Recent content in Knp on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 13:45:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/knp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #262: Beast machine</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/10/12/weekly-head-voices-262-beast-machine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 13:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/10/12/weekly-head-voices-262-beast-machine/</guid><description>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, which proudly started coming at you from the Southern bank of the Crocodile river, looking over the water into Kruger National Park, right before being ignominiously ignored for an extended period of time and then finally being revived on the road (literally, I&amp;rsquo;m sitting in the passenger seat with my laptop on my&amp;hellip; err.. .lap, thanks driver-spouse!) back from St Francis, covers the period of time up to when it eventually, hopefully, finally gets published.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, which proudly started coming at you from the Southern bank of the Crocodile river, looking over the water into Kruger National Park, right before being ignominiously ignored for an extended period of time and then finally being revived on the road (literally, I&rsquo;m sitting in the passenger seat with my laptop on my&hellip; err.. .lap, thanks driver-spouse!) back from St Francis, covers the period of time up to when it eventually, hopefully, finally gets published.</p>








    


<figure><a href="elefriend92.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/10/12/weekly-head-voices-262-beast-machine/elefriend92_hu_f87aa94e87f185d4.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/10/12/weekly-head-voices-262-beast-machine/elefriend92_hu_2cd229878339741.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/10/12/weekly-head-voices-262-beast-machine/elefriend92_hu_36b108ea0b5c3bd2.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/10/12/weekly-head-voices-262-beast-machine/elefriend92_hu_c28b4a09a41c4191.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/10/12/weekly-head-voices-262-beast-machine/elefriend92_hu_2cd229878339741.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<blockquote>
<p>Never be so focused on what you&rsquo;re looking for that you overlook the thing you actually find.</p>
<p>&ndash; Ann Patchett</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="first-rule-of-blogging">First rule of blogging</h2>
<p>Some of my blogging friends often joked: <em>The first rule of blogging is you don&rsquo;t blog about blogging</em>. I really love that, but today we really can&rsquo;t ignore the elephant in the room right here.</p>
<p>Friends, I still find myself in the midst of a pretty serious case of writer&rsquo;s block.</p>
<p>I am back here writing this (months later on the road, not on the river bank anymore), because I am unable to suppress the almost continuous desire to write something on this thing that is interesting or entertaining enough for you to read. However, actually producing something that to my mind satisfies those requirements feels like it has become difficult almost to the point of impossibility.</p>
<p>After spending a great number of mental cycles on the tools and techniques part of a possible solution, I have so far come up with <em>(&hellip;checks notes&hellip;)</em> exactly zero solutions.</p>
<p>The currently best candidate for the psychological part of the solution is to reframe this as <em>really</em> writing for an audience of one, namely future me. Although I&rsquo;ve often alluded to that idea on here, in practice I am thinking specifically about various of you, the readers who I personally know and love, a focus which ironically might be contributing to my predicament.</p>
<p>I hope that I can succeed in convincing myself at exactly the right moments that my audience is really only future me, so that I might be able to produce more regularly.</p>
<h2 id="rays-of-light">Rays of light</h2>
<p>Kind reader NS left <a href="/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/#isso-2860">the sweetest comment on the previous WHV</a> (yes, I think you should go read it now). We have never met in person, but they landed on my blog via a Stack Overflow answer of mine some years ago, and have been reading the Weekly Head Voices occasionally since then.</p>
<p>This also caused a little musical connection: Back in 2016, friend and colleague (and music connoisseur) FvdL introduced me te Jamie XX&rsquo;s album In Colour (I found the guilty party in my notes), an introduction that <a href="/2016/02/02/weekly-head-voices-103-chips/#music">landed in WHV #103</a> by way of which it became one of reader NS&rsquo;s favourite albums.</p>
<p>In a great twist of coincidence, I got to see Jamie XX doing <a href="https://youtu.be/P0GpUQpMBZY?si=cyaeO6_-PJ7YIrUW">his latest set</a> at <a href="/tags/lowlands/">Lowlands</a> in August with a bunch of besties.</p>
<p>NS&rsquo;s comment was a beautiful and quite timely reminder of why this here blog writing endeavour is worth every drop of blood, sweat and tears. (Even although I&rsquo;ll be &ldquo;writing it for future me&rdquo;&hellip;)</p>
<p>Maybe the universe wanted to make doubly sure, because around the same time I received an emailed blog comment from afar, from old friend CS. Thank you universe, thank you friend CS.</p>
<h2 id="consciousness-and-the-controlled-hallucination">Consciousness and the controlled hallucination</h2>
<p>Previously on this blog I wondered about the strangeness of going through life essentially as a brain locked up in a dark skull (<a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/#life-is-but-a-dream">WHV #174</a>), all the while slowly, incrementally building up a fantastic high-definition simulation (hallucination&hellip;) of the real-world outside based on the thin streams of photons entering one&rsquo;s eyes, and sound waves one&rsquo;s ears.</p>
<p>Somewhat later (<a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#the-describers">WHV #180</a>) I learned from the book <em>Stumbling on Happiness</em> by Daniel Gilbert that this idea was introduced by Immanuel Kant as <em>transcendental idealism</em>.</p>
<p>In her book <em>Seven and a Half Lessons About the Brain</em>, Lisa Feldman Barrett explains that indeed your brain predicts almost <em>everything</em> you do (read <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/#your-brain-predicts--almost--everything-you-do">the summary right here on this blog</a>). In fact, &ldquo;If your brain has predicted well, then your neurons are already firing in a pattern that matches the incoming sense data&rdquo;!</p>
<p>In his book <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Being_You:_A_New_Science_of_Consciousness">Being You</a>, the neuroscientist and professor of cognitive and computational neuroscience at the university of sussex <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anil_Seth">Anil Seth</a> expands on this idea at length, also calling the way we experience reality through our perception a <em>controlled hallucination</em>.</p>
<p>Where this idea might be strange at first glance, the more one reads and thinks about it, the more it makes complete sense that our complete high-definition experience of everything around us, and even inside us, is our brain using the exact same mechanism for simulating reality that it uses during less controlled hallucinations such as dreams.</p>
<p>In other words, our subjective experience by definition is produced by, and runs entirely inside, the brain. Mostly we are unable to distinguish our dreams from reality. Many aspects of hallucinations brought on by certain psychedelics can&rsquo;t be distinguished from reality either.</p>
<p>At a higher level, we go through life with a frankly quite limited set of senses, but we are treated with an incredibly detailed subjective experience. This can only work because we are in fact continuously and incrementally enriching an incredibly detailed model of reality with the limited sense inputs at our disposal.</p>
<p>From a slightly higher level, the simulation is enormous and complex in space and time, based on years of accumulated and integrated sense data.</p>
<p>There are folks like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Donald_D._Hoffman">Donald D. Hoffman</a>, cognitive psychologist and author of the book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/41817484-the-case-against-reality">The Case Against Reality: How Evolution Hid the Truth from Our Eyes</a>, who argue that what we experience could even be quite far removed from objective reality.</p>
<p>Moving on to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hard_problem_of_consciousness">&ldquo;hard problem of consciousness&rdquo;</a> and back to professor Seth, I really liked to read about what he calls &ldquo;the beast machine&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Consciousness and selfhood arises from the body&rsquo;s need to interpret and control a fantastically complex plethora of inputs and outputs: Energy, temperature, danger and then, probably the <em>raison d&rsquo;etre</em> for our large brains, relationships now and in the future with a complex and changing network of fellow humans.</p>
<p>We <em>experience</em> all of this as feelings, as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qualia">qualia</a>, which encourage us to take the action that will help ensure our continued survival.</p>
<p>You know you&rsquo;re going to feel hungry in a few hours, so you&rsquo;re already starting to think about what you can rustle up to eat. You think that such and so would be really happy if did this or that, and so you factor that into your plans. Generally, your subjective experience as a conscious being is what enables you to navigate the incredibly complex and changing information landscape with success.</p>
<p>Based on Seth&rsquo;s work, consciousness is emergent from and tied to being a living, self-regulating organism.</p>
<p>Now, as physicalists, we merely have to figure out the actual physiological mechanism of <em>how</em> consciousness is brought about exactly.</p>
<h3 id="ps-orchestrated-objective-reduction-orch-or-hypothesis">P.S. Orchestrated Objective Reduction (Orch OR) hypothesis</h3>
<p>I was really surprised (and a bit scared to be honest) to hear how many hardcore physicists were focusing on different aspects of consciousness.</p>
<p>For example, Roger Penrose (!) together with Stuart Hameroff proposed that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orchestrated_objective_reduction">consciousness originates from quantum processes within microtubules inside neurons</a>.</p>
<p>While the hypothesis is controversial, there is ample substance for discussion.</p>
<h3 id="ps-what-is-it-like-to-be-a-bat">P.S. What is it like to be a bat?</h3>
<p>In any consciousness readings, you&rsquo;re bound to run into the paper <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/What_Is_It_Like_to_Be_a_Bat%3F">&ldquo;What Is It Like to Be a Bat?&rdquo; by Thomas Nagel</a>.</p>
<p>Nagel describes consciousness as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>an organism has conscious mental states if and only if there is something that it is like to be that organism &ndash; something it is like <em>for</em> the organism</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="the-end">The end</h2>
<p>Dear reader(s), I wish that your consciousness hallucination is as pleasant as possible, and that it keeps you in the greenest of pastures.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We must always change, renew, rejuvenate ourselves; otherwise, we harden.</p>
<p>&ndash; Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #252: My prostate cancer post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 14:01:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/</guid><description> Figure 1: A dazzle of zebras
Welcome back everyone!
My excuse this time for the multi-month WHV blogging hiatus is that I was dealing with prostate cancer.
I was diagnosed in February, but I wanted to wait for calmer waters before writing anything.
Extremely fortunately, those calmer waters have arrived, and now I can talk openly.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="dazzle-of-zebra.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_553474bf4e68c1b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_1d0de5a264e5fb60.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_d2d6dbd49b798c55.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_fa1286d2e3011625.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_1d0de5a264e5fb60.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A dazzle of zebras"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>A dazzle of zebras</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome  back everyone!</p>
<p>My excuse this time for the multi-month WHV blogging hiatus is that I was
dealing with prostate cancer.</p>
<p>I was diagnosed in February, but I wanted to wait for calmer waters before
writing anything.</p>
<p>Extremely fortunately, those calmer waters have arrived, and now I can talk
openly.</p>
<p>I wanted to write up this whole story firstly because this blog has a long
history of stories about significant life events, but also just in case it
could help anyone else who might find themselves in a similar boat and would
like to talk. If you are such a person, please <a href="https://cpbotha.net/about/">email me</a> or leave a comment down
below.</p>
<p>On to the story:</p>
<h2 id="discovery">Discovery</h2>
<p>In January my GP randomly tacked on a PSA (Prostate Specific Antigen) test to
the <a href="https://apob.app/about">Apolipoprotein B (ApoB) blood test</a>, which at that point still was the main
topic of our interest.</p>
<p>The tacked-on PSA came back at 6.5ug/L, which is <em>convincingly</em> above the range
for my age, and hence was suddenly promoted to The Main Topic of Interest.</p>
<p>Three weeks later a repeat test at the urologist came back even a tad higher,
and so I was scheduled for a prostate biopsy two weeks after that.</p>
<p>This procedure, fortunately under general anaesthesia, is where the urologist
sticks a number of needles into one&rsquo;s prostate in order to gather actual tissue
samples that can be studied by the pathology lab.</p>
<p>Those biopsy results came back with&hellip;</p>
<p>Prostate cancer.</p>
<p>ULP&hellip; although my science brain had deduced that this was probably going to
be the outcome (low <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/c-reactive-protein-test/about/pac-20385228">CRP</a> = probably no prostatitis, few other indications of
<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/benign-prostatic-hyperplasia/symptoms-causes/syc-20370087">BPH)</a>, my human brain was in panic.</p>
<p>To be more specific about the diagnosis, it was <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/diagnosis-staging/tests/understanding-your-pathology-report/prostate-pathology/prostate-cancer-pathology.html">Gleason score 3+4 aka grade
group 2 (on the favourable side of &ldquo;intermediate risk&rdquo;)</a> prostate cancer. 9
out of the 13 biopsy cores (samples) were cancerous, with both lobes of the
prostate involved.</p>
<p>Cue some more shock here&hellip;</p>
<p>After that initial shock came the more cognitive realisation (thanks science
brain!) that as cancers and cancer gradings go, this was quite&hellip; <em>reasonable</em>.</p>
<p>That being said, the <em>existential dread</em> caused by this disease, which was
entirely willing and able to kill me, was quite visceral.</p>
<p>By the way, you know that thing about the atheists and the foxholes?</p>
<p>Contrary to the wisdom of the foxhole, I found <em>immense</em> peace in my science, and
endless strength in my family and my friends.</p>
<h2 id="surgery">Surgery</h2>
<p>My urologist explained that for someone at my age, with this diagnosis, he
would recommend in no uncertain terms to have the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prostatectomy">prostate removed</a>, preferably
via <em>robot-assisted laparoscopic prostatectomy</em>, aka my new friend Wreck-it RALP
(silent H).</p>
<p>In my <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">previous career as academic in The Netherlands</a>, a significant part of my
research was computer-assisted surgery. Although I did most of my work in
orthopaedics with the academic hospital in Leiden, the Da Vinci surgical robot
(previous generation!) was very much on our radar.</p>
<p>Little did I know that a decade or so later I would experience its successor,
the Da Vinci X, very much first hand.</p>
<p>(It&rsquo;s hard for me to put in words how grateful I am now for all of the
thousands of hours of research and development that have gone into
robot-assisted surgery&hellip; thank you colleagues!)</p>
<p>On March 30, my partner and I left home at 4 AM to report at the hospital
at 5.</p>
<p>First that horrible open-at-the-back hospital wear, and then the warm enema
they brought in shortly after admission, were pretty clear signs that things
were getting <em>uncomfortably</em> real.</p>
<p>My experience of the surgery itself was of course sublime &ndash; oblivion is indeed
bliss!  &ndash; thanks to the anaesthetist&rsquo;s magic.</p>
<p>The main procedure was performed by <a href="https://caperoboticsurgery.co.za/">Dr Conray Moolman</a>, a urological surgeon who
specialises in RALP, with hundreds of prostatectomies under the belt.</p>
<p>(Why yes, I am in fact now <em>expected</em> to brandish this level of punnery, thanks
for asking.)</p>
<p>Having the operation done by someone with his level of experience is a best
case scenario for me personally, but the role of that experience in the
surgical outcome is underlined by much of the literature on robotic
prostatectomy.</p>
<p>As you can see in the handy Wikipedia illustration below, the surgeon has to
cut out the prostate and some of the surrounding tissue, and then attach the
remaining urethra to the bladder neck.</p>
<p>The poor urethra is just expected to stretch to the occasion.</p>










<figure><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prostatectomy#/media/File:Prostate_Removal.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/fb/Prostate_Removal.png"
         width="50%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>All of this happens via the Da Vinci X&rsquo;s many robotic arms, a number of them
inserted into my abdominal cavity through the five incisions (four small and
one larger) in my abdomen.</p>










<figure><a href="davinci-table.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_9d81c6c80d2fd942.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_3657f00e43b134d5.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_acd23c8750a659c7.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_3657f00e43b134d5.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>One of the main challenges for the surgeon here is that, along with the whole
prostate, they need to remove as little as possible of the surrounding nerves,
which would result in certain post-operative functional deficits, but enough of
the surrounding tissue to include cancer cells that may have progressed to
there.</p>
<h2 id="post-op">Post-op</h2>
<p>I was able to walk a little bit on the same afternoon, with the expert help of
the physiotherapist, and in spite of the interference of my new and fortunately
temporary augmentation the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foley_catheter">Foley catheter</a>, which had to remain in place for at
least a week to give the new bladder-urethra hook-up time to heal.</p>
<p>A few days later, the first fantastic bit of news was that the post-op
pathology report, completed a few days later, showed that <a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/positive-surgical-margins-following-radical-prostatectomy-20090617171">&ldquo;all margins were
clear&rdquo;</a>, meaning that it was highly probable that all prostate cancer cells
had been taken care of.</p>
<p>I was able to return to work just over two weeks after surgery.</p>
<p>The first post-op PSA test 6 weeks afterwards showed a new PSA level of 0.01.</p>
<p>I have not been able to find out if that amount is just what the test shows at
its lower end, or if there is somehow some residual PSA left in my system.</p>
<p>My urologist seems happy with this result, which is important.</p>
<p>For the first year, I&rsquo;ll have to repeat this blood test every three months to
ensure that there&rsquo;s really nothing there. I am keeping my fingers crossed.</p>
<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</h2>
<p>As I write this, exactly three months after the prostatectomy, I am looking out
over the Crocodile river, at the end of <a href="/tags/knp/">our traditional winter KNP break-away</a>.</p>
<p>Shortly after the 6-week PSA test, I had to have another small surgical
procedure due to a urethral stricture which developed most probably due to the
catheter. Fortunately the stricture was very distal (ahem), far away from the
critical new urethra-bladder-neck junction.</p>
<p>I am almost back up to pre-surgical strength, although I do have to go to the
bathroom substantially more regularly (also at night) due to the remaining
nerves (most of them, fortunately!) still having to learn new tricks, but
probably more due to the urethral sphincter being exactly the part that is
newly sutured to the bladder neck. Other than that, my running fitness took
quite a hit, and is now in the slow process of building up again.</p>
<p>On the mental side, my confidence in my own health and physical resilience has
taken a bit of a knock. This is something I really need to work on.</p>
<p><strong><strong>Through all of this, support from work, friends and family has been absolutely
phenomenal.</strong></strong></p>
<p>Amongst many other lessons, this has shown me how much even that random
WhatsApp from a friend who I haven&rsquo;t seen in ages can mean, and so I have
resolved to send that random supportive message through whichever medium,
whenever there&rsquo;s an opportunity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #244: Biyamiti Bat-Fan</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 17:18:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/</guid><description>Welcome to Weekly Head Voices number 244, stretching from Monday June 20 to Sunday July 24, 2022.
Winter, don&amp;rsquo;t call us, we&amp;rsquo;ll call you Shortly after the start of this period, June 21 to be exact, I was frankly and quite pleasantly surprised by the Southern Hemisphere winter solstice.
This handy Time and Date website has more details, including but not limited to:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to Weekly Head Voices number 244, stretching from Monday June 20 to
Sunday July 24,  2022.</p>










<figure><a href="giraffe.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu_c46f9551e2078a83.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu_698ee08c6d552be1.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu_aa238c6874e141ea.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu_f5d7b3c73ba15777.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu_698ee08c6d552be1.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="winter-don-t-call-us-we-ll-call-you">Winter, don&rsquo;t call us, we&rsquo;ll call you</h2>
<p>Shortly after the start of this period, June 21 to be exact, I was frankly and
quite pleasantly surprised by the Southern Hemisphere winter solstice.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-AFRICA/cape-town">This handy Time and Date website</a> has more details, including but not limited
to:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The June solstice (winter solstice) in Cape Town is at 11:13 on Tuesday, 21
June 2022. In terms of daylight, this day is 4 hours, 32 minutes shorter than
the December solstice. In locations south of the equator, the shortest day of
the year is around this date.</p>
<p>The earliest sunset is on 12 June. The latest sunrise is on 29 June or 30 June.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some of you <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">might remember</a> that this is an important point in the year for me,
the moment when I can see the big light, namely summer, at the end of the
tunnel.</p>
<h2 id="projections">Projections</h2>
<p>I recently finished reading the book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/55411738-projections"><em>Projections: A Story of Human Emotions</em>
by Karl Deisseroth</a>.</p>
<p>As a layperson, I found this psychiatrist and world-changing scientist&rsquo;s view
of the world, and especially of the psyches of his patients, absolutely
fascinating.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Deisseroth">Deisseroth</a> writes about several different types of psychiatric disorders, but
does so via specific but (probably) fictional patients who embody the important
aspects of the disorder in question.</p>
<p>He also writes about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optogenetics">Optogenetics</a>.</p>
<p>Optogenetics is a technique, invented by Deisseroth, for controlling neurons
with lasers, <em>in vivo</em>.</p>
<p>More specifically, by inserting specific genes from algae, neurons can be
modified to activate when struck by light.</p>
<p>Using this technique, researchers are able to activate very specific subsets of
neurons in mice brains, making the mice feel anxious for example, or
comfortable, or any of the different neural components making up these mental
states.</p>
<p>From the Wikpedia artictle:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In systems neuroscience, the ability to control the activity of a genetically
defined set of neurons has been used to understand their contribution to
decision making, learning, fear memory, mating, addiction, feeding, and
locomotion.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The use of this technique has already contributed significantly to our
fundamental understanding of the brain, and the first steps have been taken
towards using it in therapy.</p>
<p>Judging by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optogenetics#Awards">the list of awards</a>, the scientific world has really noticed the
value of this work.</p>
<p>Personally, I am optimistic that there&rsquo;s much more to come.</p>
<p>P.S. Close to the end of <a href="https://lexfridman.com/karl-deisseroth/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Deisseroth</a>, Deisseroth
mentioned that he really doubts whether he has done enough&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="batting-for-biyamiti">Batting for Biyamiti</h2>
<p>I am Bat-Fan.</p>
<p>No really, I appreciate bats. (and puns)</p>
<p>They&rsquo;re little flying mammals who see and navigate the world <em>expertly</em> using
echolocation (just imagine what that <em>feels</em> like?!) . They eat large numbers of
insects, including a <a href="https://news.wisc.edu/study-bolsters-bats-reputation-as-mosquito-devourers/">debatable</a> number of mosquitoes (I did not know about the
debate until right now).</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s not to like?</p>
<p>However, during our recent freshly reinstated yearly <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/">KNP break</a>, we enjoyed
fantastic summer weather (it&rsquo;s winter down here, but that&rsquo;s Mpumalanga for
you), we spent one night in Biyamiti with a pretty active bat in the room.</p>
<p>As we went to sleep, we thought that it would probably be ok.</p>
<p>It was not.</p>
<p>In addition to the bat expertly dropping something wet in my eye (your guess is
as good as mine), during parts of the night it started doing fly-bys so close
to our faces that we could feel the discrete wind gusts caused by the flapping
of its little wings.</p>
<p>On the one hand I was quite impressed by its sheer <em>mammalian</em> skill, but on
the other we just really wanted to sleep.</p>
<p>We decided that the price of a few extra insects in the room was worth it, and
so we opened the mesh.</p>
<p>Our bat friend, in spite of apparently having built a little nest in the nook
right up in the apex of the roof, fortunately obliged by exiting to perform the
rest of its manouevres outside in the night.</p>










<figure><a href="sunset-crocodile-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu_559869ac1444d9f8.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu_43de18ed1789dc75.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu_151556b2257c03e.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu_28c6820c3044f7aa.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu_43de18ed1789dc75.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: The sun sets over the Crocodile. Nothing else matters."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>The sun sets over the Crocodile. Nothing else matters.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #172: ABC.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 20:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/</guid><description> YARRRRGGGHHHH it&amp;rsquo;s now more than a month after the previous WHV saw the light of day.
This draft, intially intended to see the light of day not much more than a week after 171, has been languishing in a cold jail of electrons up in the cloud somewhere for the past weeks, while life was doing its thing, you know, inexorably marching ahead.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="reflection_strand_beach.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu_d10e2687378ecdd7.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu_9cffd88baa84eaf0.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu_ff429f214291dbe5.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu_3ef93aa1dc11f3b5.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/reflection_strand_beach_hu_9cffd88baa84eaf0.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>YARRRRGGGHHHH it&rsquo;s now more than a month after the previous WHV saw the light
of day.</p>
<p>This draft, intially intended to see the light of day not much more than a week
after 171, has been languishing in a cold jail of electrons up in the cloud
somewhere for the past weeks, while life was doing its thing, you know,
inexorably marching ahead.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I&rsquo;m happy that we are here now.</p>
<h2 id="the-dark-forest">The Dark Forest.</h2>
<p>I just searched this blog to check: To my surprise, I have somehow not gushed
about the Dark Forest trilogy by Cixin Liu before.</p>
<p>I read Ken Liu&rsquo;s translation of <em>The Three-Body Problem</em> in 2014, and it blew
my mind.</p>
<p>It could be that I deliberately reserved gushing until finishing the rest of
the trilogy.</p>
<p>During the past weeks I finished <em>The Dark Forest</em> and finally <em>Death&rsquo;s End</em>.</p>
<p>This is hardcore science fiction, with enough mind-bending physics ideas to,
well, bend your mind, and an insightful peek into at least one Chinese world
view through the eyes of the author.</p>
<p>Most haunting, however, is this work&rsquo;s dark answer to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermi_paradox">the Fermi
paradox</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-books-will-stop-working">The books will stop working.</h2>
<p>I bought The Dark Forest trilogy as Kindle ebooks from Amazon, adding to quite
a stack of previous Kindle ebook purchases.</p>
<p>As you might have heard, Microsoft are shutting off their DRM servers, and have
<a href="https://boingboing.net/2019/06/28/jun-17-2004.html">warned their customers that &ldquo;The books will stop
working&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>Stéfan <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2016/08/21/amazon-owns-your-ebooks/">has also warned about
this</a> in the
context of Amazon.</p>
<p>Today I saw that Charlie Stross, a super successful author himself, as a rule
<a href="https://twitter.com/cstross/status/1144336012015034368">breaks the DRM on any ebooks that he
buys</a>.</p>
<p>I find all of this a bit chilling.</p>
<h2 id="circadian-brevity">Circadian brevity.</h2>
<p>We have been privy to some of those magical sunny winter days that this part of
the world is renowned for.</p>
<p>However, the days are significantly shorter, and this does tend to have a sort
of narrowing effect on one&rsquo;s days.</p>
<p>More concretely, for these past few weeks (excluding the KNP break mentioned
below) it really felt like each work day consisted exclusively of waking up,
preparing for school and work, leaving for school and work, doing work and/or
school, getting back home for dinner and bath-time, and then going to bed.</p>
<p>Somehow, there&rsquo;s almost no time for anything else.</p>
<p>The optimist in me notes that this is probably really just the shorter days. In
a few months, spring will bring longer days, and longer days have the potential
of bearing much more variety.</p>
<p>The cynic on the other hand is making the scary case that this could just be
one of the many new and irreversible artefacts of inexorably approaching old
age.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the stakes are even higher than normal for
maintaining focus throughout the day.</p>
<h2 id="knp">KNP</h2>
<p>Our (almost) <a href="/tags/knp/">yearly break under the reassuring sun in the Kruger National
Park</a> was just what the doctors ordered to remedy some of all that
darkness.</p>
<p>The sun and the soft winter warmth were amazing as always.</p>
<p>However, I had significant troubles (all of them in my head of course. Wait,
what isn&rsquo;t? HA HA) <a href="/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/#you-are-turning-into-a-cyborg">disconnecting from
work</a>.</p>
<p>&hellip; only to realise the day <em>after</em> bestie PK&rsquo;s birthday that I&rsquo;d forgotten to
call due to being <em>half</em> disconnected. (Correction: I was reminded by said
bestie. I think in the Book of Etiquette my faux pas is thus at least a -3 on a
scale of 1 to 10.)</p>
<p>Dang it. I&rsquo;m not very good at this.</p>
<p>However, word on the street is that &ldquo;grit&rdquo; is hip again, so I kept at it. (I&rsquo;m
also stubborn.)</p>
<p>By the last day of our break, I think I finally managed to reach the desired
state of disconnectedness.</p>
<p>On this day, we arrived at <a href="http://www.krugerpark.co.za/Kruger_National_Park_Bush_Lodges_&amp;_Camps-travel/shimuwini-camp.html">the Shimuwini
camp</a>,
where a troupe of elephants decided to join us for dinner on the bank of the
Letaba river, about 50 metres from our front porch.</p>
<p>Magical.</p>
<video controls>
  <source src="elephants_grazing_shimuwini.mp4" type="video/mp4">
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
<h2 id="solar-powerrrrrrrr">Solar powerrrrrrrr</h2>
<p>Well well well well well.</p>
<p>At one point I was starting to think that it would forever be all talk and no
solar action around here.</p>
<p>However, thanks to <a href="http://redengineering.co.za/">RED Engineering</a>, the
brilliant and well-organized installer (#4 on my list&hellip;) who was also patient
enough to field my never-ending stream of questions, this post and hopefully
many more in the future are 100% solar powered.</p>
<p>(I just checked on the dashboard. Very much overcast today, but plant is
generating enough to power the house.)</p>
<p>When the final bits and bobs have been sorted (most important remaining
challenge is getting the GoodWe GW5048D-ES to successfully talk to the
PylonTech US3000 battery cluster BMS), I&rsquo;ll write a post with more details
about the system and its performance.</p>
<p>Until then, these are the specifications:</p>
<ul>
<li>Panels: 18 x <a href="./canadian_solar_cs3u_specs.pdf">Canadian Solar KuMax high efficiency polycrystalline CS3U
355Wp</a></li>
<li>Inverter: <a href="https://www.goodwe.com/Products/index_spec/id/22.html">GoodWe
GW5048D-ES</a></li>
<li>Batteries: 2 x <a href="http://www.pylontech.com.cn/pro_detail.aspx?id=121&amp;cid=23">PylonTech US3000 lithium iron phosphate
batteries</a> for a
total of 7kWh of storage.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="always-be-compounding">Always Be Compounding!</h2>
<p>I think it was during <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/155-mental-models/">a recent podcast with Shane
Parrish</a> where I heard about
the idea of applying compounding to aspects of one&rsquo;s life.</p>
<p>In short, if <a href="https://fs.blog/2016/03/five-percent-better/">you can become 5% wiser and better every year, you&rsquo;ll be about
twice as wise as you are now in a mere 15
years</a>.</p>
<p>The fundamental principle is one of modest, incremental progress, but, and this
is the secret sauce, <em>consistently</em> applied, without letting up.</p>
<p>If you can write a blog post every week (ahem..) you&rsquo;ll have hundreds of blog
posts in a few years, and something significant to look back on.</p>
<p>(If you&rsquo;re able to write on a specific topic, that&rsquo;s even better. Stéfan
recently Signalled me this very relevant post titled <a href="https://matthewrocklin.com/blog/work/2019/06/25/write-short-blogposts">&ldquo;Write Short
Blogposts&rdquo;</a>.)</p>
<p>If you can write a book chapter every month, you&rsquo;ll have written a book when
the year is over.</p>
<p>If you are able to pick a worthwhile activity or topic, and then to <em>keep on</em>
making incremental contributions to that activity or topic, you&rsquo;ll become
<em>the</em> expert on that topic before you know it.</p>
<p>I think you get the idea.</p>
<p>I find this such a powerful concept, so much so that I&rsquo;ve resolved to integrate
it with my daily checklist.</p>
<p>For me, step one is to have a list of worthwhile directions available, and step
two is to execute, just a little bit, on any of them as regularly as possible.</p>
<h2 id="gou2-tells-it-like-it-is">GOU#2 tells it like it is.</h2>
<p>Recently, GOU#2 (age 9) and her classmates compiled a father&rsquo;s day book, where
each child had to draw a picture illustrating what makes their dad special.</p>
<p>My heart melted when I finally reached her page:</p>
<figure>
<a href="sylvia_kunswerk_blog.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hu_f7df7a654d75b2c4.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hu_380945a01fbb24f7.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hu_f0ef2be2c9512ee.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hu_2a0cfbdd8227c556.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/sylvia_kunswerk_blog_hu_380945a01fbb24f7.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<p>Because the meta is strong down here, I could not resist posting this artwork
as well.</p>
<p>Folks, have an excellent week. I wish you happiness, health and compounding.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #147: The yearly post-Mpumalanga post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 20:50:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/</guid><description> The Lilac-Breasted Roller. I met this enchanting and almost surrealistically pretty creature for the first time two weeks ago.
Time period covered by this post: Monday June 18 to Sunday July 8.
Reason for extended absence: Holiday-based recharge.
Holiday rating: 13/10. Math is irrelevant.
It’s relatively quiet from the European side of my family. I trust (partly confirmed by the grapevine) that my peeps over there are having themselves a wonderful rest.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/lilac_breasted_roller.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/lilac_breasted_roller-1024x377.jpg"
        
            alt="The Lilac-Breasted Roller. I met this enchanting and almost surrealistically pretty creature for the first time two weeks ago."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Lilac-Breasted Roller. I met this enchanting and almost surrealistically pretty creature for the first time two weeks ago.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>Time period covered by this post:</strong> Monday June 18 to Sunday July 8.</p>
<p><strong>Reason for extended absence:</strong> Holiday-based recharge.</p>
<p><strong>Holiday rating:</strong> 13/10. Math is irrelevant.</p>
<p>It’s relatively quiet from the European side of my family. I trust (partly confirmed by the grapevine) that my peeps over there are having themselves a wonderful rest.</p>
<p>Over here on the tip of the African continent, we migrated temporarily about 1800km to the North-East, to Mpumalanga, where winter is a rather theoretical concept.</p>
<p>The week was amazing.</p>
<p>It’s hard to explain the emotions evoked by the rugged beauty of the surroundings, and by the African sun, albeit slightly gentler than usual, beating down on one’s back.</p>
<div class="gallery galleryid-3205 gallery-columns-2 gallery-size-medium" data-carousel-extra='{"blog_id":1,"permalink":"https:\/\/cpbotha.net\/2018\/07\/10\/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post\/"}' id="gallery-9">
<figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon landscape">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-9" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843.jpg" title=""><img alt="" class="attachment-medium size-medium" data-attachment-id="3206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"5.6","credit":"","camera":"Canon PowerShot SX260 HS","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1530003714","copyright":"","focal_length":"43.736","iso":"100","shutter_speed":"0.0025","title":"","orientation":"1"}' data-image-title="IMG_5843" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-1024x768.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-300x225.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843.jpg" data-orig-size="4000,3000" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/img_5843/" height="225" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-300x225.jpg 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-768x576.jpg 768w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-1200x900.jpg 1200w" width="300"/></a>
</div></figure><figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon landscape">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-9" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919.jpg" title=""><img alt="" class="attachment-medium size-medium" data-attachment-id="3207" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"5.6","credit":"","camera":"Canon PowerShot SX260 HS","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1530092144","copyright":"","focal_length":"40.31","iso":"100","shutter_speed":"0.004","title":"","orientation":"1"}' data-image-title="IMG_5919" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-1024x768.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-300x225.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919.jpg" data-orig-size="4000,3000" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/img_5919/" height="225" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-300x225.jpg 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-768x576.jpg 768w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-1200x900.jpg 1200w" width="300"/></a>
</div></figure>
</div>
<p>Added to that, every evening we were embroiled in a non-competitive competition to outcook the previous evening’s culinary adventure.</p>
<p>All of this made for a rather primal holiday experience filled with wild animals, eating, old-fashioned human contact (including a serendipitous meeting with friends I had last seen 20 years ago), thinking and running.</p>
<p>This weekend we’ll hopefully return to the usual WHV programming, with more, you know, content.</p>
<p>Until then, I would like to leave you with the following sunset.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/zen_potjie.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/zen_potjie-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Potjie, overflowing with Zen."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Potjie, overflowing with Zen.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #107: Balance.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/05/22/weekly-head-voices-107-balance/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2016 20:01:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/05/22/weekly-head-voices-107-balance/</guid><description> That’s how the African sun sets in Mpumalanga.
… and this is more or less what it looks like when a cheetah decides to grace you with its presence. We had it all to ourselves (this is quite unusual in the Kruger National Park with an animal of this level of celebrity) and were able to follow it until it wandered further away from the road, probably on the lookout for some dinner.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/mpumalanga_sunset-1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/mpumalanga_sunset-1-1024x429.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>That’s how the African sun sets in Mpumalanga.</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/cheetah1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/cheetah1-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>… and this is more or less what it looks like when a cheetah decides to grace you with its presence. We had it all to ourselves (this is quite unusual in the <a href="/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/">Kruger National Park</a> with an animal of this level of celebrity) and were able to follow it until it wandered further away from the road, probably on the lookout for some dinner.</p>
<p>It was a brilliant week-long getaway with the newest little member of the family. The time is just long enough to allow for a complete switch-off (see the “you are turning into a cyborg” section of <a href="/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/">one of the previous KNP posts</a>) with the balmy weather and the wild animal tracking just adding to the fun.</p>
<p>On the nerd front, I convinced <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">my employer</a> to get me a new Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic desktop. As I spend 8 hours or more monkey-typing on some sort of keyboard every day, having one that works well is quite important. I might have found a new favourite in the Sculpt Ergonomic. It looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/ms_sculpt_ergonomic-1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/ms_sculpt_ergonomic-1.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>It’s probably the most strangely shaped keyboard I have ever worked on, but it has grown on me quite quickly. The strange shape helps keep my arms and wrists in an even better posture than with the Comfort Curve 3000 (my previous favourite), and the chiclet keys combine just the right amounts of finger travel economy and tactile feedback in my opinion. My only gripe is that the escape key, which as Emacs user I quite often use, is smaller than the other keys and has a completely different feel.</p>
<p>(An extremely brief final aside on the nerd front: I briefly tried Evernote <em>again</em> as <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">my current note-taking strategy</a> does not support a good web-clipper, and my all-singing all-dancing non-linear knowledge management prototype, now in its seventh complete rewrite, is not ready yet. They’ve updated the Evernote look, but even with 5 or 6 clipped web pages in total in my database, I had trouble getting the android app to sync up with the web version.)</p>
<p>During my compulsive daily RSS feed / twitter / Google+ reading, I came across <a href="http://nautil.us/issue/36/aging/the-wisdom-of-the-aging-brain">this interesting summary of recent research on changes in the aging brain</a>. It’s the type of article that interests one especially when one is in possession of such an aging brain, and perhaps also when it reflects one’s own experiences, all completely hypothetically of course.</p>
<p>In any case, in yet another one of those examples of youth being wasted on the young it’s long been known that <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg20227023-000-the-five-ages-of-the-brain-adulthood/">your brain is at its maximum processing capacity and speed during one’s early twenties</a>. In my early twenties, the <em>last</em> thing I was thinking about was my mental performance peaking. It’s a sobering counterpoint that my brain’s processing speed has been steadily declining since my late twenties.</p>
<p>As a sort of a consolation prize, it is starting to look like our brains, when we succeed in keeping them healthy, develop more balanced patterns of activity as we get older. We work smarter rather than harder, unlike those twenty year olds who refuse to get off my lawn.</p>
<p>The article mentions the hypothesis that there might be something that could be called the <em>neuro-circuitry of wisdom</em>, consisting of _the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (responsible for rationality, discipline, and self-preservation), the ventromedial prefrontal cortex (associated with “kind, supportive, social, and emotional behavior needed for survival of species”), the anterior cingulate (which mediates conflicts between parts of the prefrontal cortex), and the striatum with amygdala (part of the reward circuitry) _. With age, brain activity between all of these regions reaches a sort of balance, leading to the owner of said brain demonstrating feats of wisdom which will probably be witnessed by exactly no-one, almost like trees falling in the forest, or almost like the posts on this blog, minus the wisdom.</p>
<p>Here’s to hoping that, as we all near our inevitable final sunsets, we do in fact become ever so slightly wiser, and ever so slightly more capable of contributing peace and kindness to our surroundings; even, or perhaps especially, when no-one is watching.</p>
<p>(I just reminded me of Reggie Watts… see below.)</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ej_BHc1UaDA?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #94: Into the wild.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/07/19/weekly-head-voices-94-into-the-wild/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2015 15:12:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/07/19/weekly-head-voices-94-into-the-wild/</guid><description> This WHV deals with the weeks from Monday June 29 to Sunday July 19. I skipped an edition or two whilst away on vacation, as I was quite busy with, you know, being on vacation. So, about that vacation: Last year I explained about the Kruger National Park, or KNP. Well, we went again this year, and again it was lovely. It helps that in the Mpumalanga and Limpopo provinces, “winter” at this time of year seems to mean “lovely balmy days with temperatures between 25 and 30 degrees Celsius”. What completely and utterly seals the deal, is being surrounded by this particular permutation of natural vastness. You should go there to see for yourself, but here’s a taste: Elephants in some of the vastness that is KNP. EXTREME-NERDERY BULLET: If you’re a Dvorak typist using Java-based tools on the Mac (e.g. Eclipse, IntelliJ, AppCode, and everything by JetBrains) you might have noticed that keyboard shortcuts fall on the spectrum somewhere between extremely wonky and plain infuriating. Besides that you now know that this subset of persons is not limited to just you, here’s an SO answer that I wrote up based on information in the JetBrains bug threads. In short, a long-standing (as in years) bug in Java on Mac means you have to use an open-source tool called Karabiner instead of Mac’s built-in Dvorak support. Here, have a photo of a stealthy leopard to recover: This leopard was stalking something, but then disappeared. A Sunday lunch at the Thirsty Scarecrow led to at least two new discoveries. Citizen Beer, a craft beer brewery I have not ran into yet (it’s not for lack of trying, really) makes a pretty delicious amber ale called Alliance (their wonderfully-named Saboteur IPA is not too shabby either):</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul class="org-ul">
<li>
    This WHV deals with the weeks from Monday June 29 to Sunday July 19. I skipped an edition or two whilst away on vacation, as I was quite busy with, you know, being on vacation. So, about that vacation:
  </li>
<li>
    Last year <a href="/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/">I explained about the Kruger National Park, or KNP</a>. Well, we went again this year, and again it was lovely. It helps that in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mpumalanga">Mpumalanga</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limpopo">Limpopo</a> provinces, “winter” at this time of year seems to mean “lovely balmy days with temperatures between 25 and 30 degrees Celsius”. What completely and utterly seals the deal, is being surrounded by this particular permutation of natural vastness. You should go there to see for yourself, but here’s a taste:
  </li>
</ul>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-knp_elephant_scene_2015.jpg" title="">
<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 100%">
<img alt="elephant scene in the KNP" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-knp_elephant_scene_2015-825x510.jpg"/>
<figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Elephants in some of the vastness that is KNP.</figcaption></figure>
</a>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
<b>EXTREME-NERDERY BULLET:</b> If you’re a Dvorak typist using Java-based tools on the Mac (e.g. Eclipse, IntelliJ, AppCode, and everything by JetBrains) you might have noticed that keyboard shortcuts fall on the spectrum somewhere between extremely wonky and plain <i>infuriating</i>. Besides that you now know that this subset of <i>persons</i> is not limited to just you, <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/31119280/532513">here’s an SO answer that I wrote up</a> based on information in the JetBrains bug threads. In short, a long-standing (as in years) bug in Java on Mac means you have to use an open-source tool called <a href="https://pqrs.org/osx/karabiner/">Karabiner</a> instead of Mac’s built-in Dvorak support.
  </li>
<li>
    Here, have a photo of a stealthy leopard to recover:
  </li>
</ul>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-1" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-knp_leopard_2015.jpg" title="">
<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 100%">
<img src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-knp_leopard_2015-825x510.jpg"/>
<figcaption class="wp-caption-text">This leopard was stalking something, but then disappeared.</figcaption></figure>
</a>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
    A Sunday lunch at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/thethirstyscarecrow">the Thirsty Scarecrow</a> led to at least two new discoveries. <a href="https://twitter.com/CitizenBeer">Citizen Beer</a>, a craft beer brewery I have not ran into yet (it’s not for lack of trying, really) makes a pretty delicious amber ale called <i>Alliance</i> (their wonderfully-named <i>Saboteur</i> IPA is not too shabby either):
  </li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-2" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-thirsty_scarecrow_citizen_beer_alliance.jpg" title=""><img alt="thirsty_scarecrow_citizen_beer_alliance.jpg" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-thirsty_scarecrow_citizen_beer_alliance-218x300.jpg"/></a>
</p>
</div>
<p>Very important discovery number 2: You <em>can</em> (and should) deep-fry Oreos!</p>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-thirsty_scarecrow_deepfried_oreos.jpg" title=""><img alt="thirsty_scarecrow_deepfried_oreos.jpg" src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-thirsty_scarecrow_deepfried_oreos-300x298.jpg"/></a>
</p>
</div>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
    I’m still terrible at these bullets, but I imagine they’re better than being faced by a wall of text. What do you think?
  </li>
</ul>
<p>Right peeps, that’s it for this edition. I wish you a fantastic and especially meaningful week. If at any point you need a little pick-me-up, my baby giraffe is standing by:</p>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-4" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-knp_baby_giraffe_2015.jpg" title="">
<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 100%">
<img src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/07/wpid-knp_baby_giraffe_2015-825x510.jpg"/><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">A baby giraffe, because we all need one once in a while.</figcaption></figure>
</a>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>