<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>birthday on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/birthday/</link><description>Recent content in birthday on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 09:08:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/birthday/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #231: Two thousand four hundred fourty-four</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW
This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to Sunday August 29, 2021.
Orbital mechanics that are important to me Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.
That&amp;rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.
Let me try again:
Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="pano_from_watsonia.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &ldquo;run&rdquo; with bestie DW</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to
Sunday August 29, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="orbital-mechanics-that-are-important-to-me">Orbital mechanics that are important to me</h2>
<p>Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.</p>
<p>Let me try again:</p>
<p>Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for
another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</p>
<p>As is our custom here, I get to increase the mathematical encoding (this is a
fantastically consistent and useful approach to the structured modelling of
reality) of my time as an alive unit by one.</p>
<p>When I was younger, it was possible to use this number to impress one&rsquo;s
friends. Sometimes, the number of an older sibling or even a parent could also
be used to increase social standing, if one&rsquo;s own number was still quite small.</p>
<p>Ironically, as the number gets bigger, we prefer not to talk or even think
about it too much.</p>
<p>Thanks to math, the number could in theory be transformed into &ldquo;number of
revolutions remaining&rdquo;, but fortunately our complex physiologies and
environments greatly complicate the estimation of the required term for that
transformation, in this case greatly comforting us with uncertainty.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS&hellip;</p>
<p>I had an amazing birthday.</p>
<p>From morning video chats with homies, to working lunches that turned into
superbly relaxed lunches with old friends, surprise visits by far-off friends
the day before, birthday mountain runs with a bestie, and so many (voice)
messages on various platforms from friends everywhere, my birthday was a
friendship-and-life-affirming business.</p>
<p>Friends, thank you for working together like that. You are all breath-taking!</p>
<p>P.S. Experiencing this acted as a beautiful reminder to send that message,
write that email or make that call whenever you can find an excuse!</p>
<h2 id="how-i-m-putting-down-my-work"><em>How</em> I&rsquo;m putting down my work</h2>
<p>In the previous edition of the WHV, I talked about <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">the important skill of being
able to put down one&rsquo;s work</a>.</p>
<p>Here I would just like to mention how I&rsquo;ve been trying to practise this in my
life, especially because it really seems to have helped me since we last spoke.</p>
<p>Ok, get ready!</p>
<p>You Won&rsquo;t Believe This One Trick&hellip;</p>
<p>At 17:00, 17:30 at the latest, I explicitly switch off any tools that I use for
work, and disconnect from all dayjob-related systems.</p>
<p>Work email closed, development enviroments exited, docker containers all stopped.</p>
<p>For good measure, I roll a tumbleweed or two across my office floor, blowing
air out through my pursed lips.</p>
<p>The thing is, my brain has the tendency to continue cogitating on the last
thing I kept it busy with.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I used to have the tendency to still try and solve that problem
before bed, only resulting in me later lying in said bed, unable to get my
brain to stop cogitating, leading to bad sleep, contributing to subpar
performance the next day.</p>
<p>I have to qualify here that putting down work tools does not exclude me from
picking up hobby programming projects later in the evening, after &ldquo;The Making
of The Dinner, With Wine&rdquo; and &ldquo;The Chilling With The Family&rdquo; stages.</p>
<p>Although programming plays a substantial part of dayjob, I have never stopped
enjoying and being relaxed by this activity in the recreational setting.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, making a point of putting down work on time, starting
the gradual wind-down, has drastically reduced the number and severity of
<em>Trying Unsuccessfully to Solve All Work Problems In The Dark, From One&rsquo;s Bed</em> for
me.</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/">Oliver Burkeman</a>, author of <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">the putting-down-your-work post</a>, also wrote a
book titled <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2021/aug/16/four-thousand-weeks-time-and-how-to-use-it-by-oliver-burkeman-review">Four Thousand Weeks: Time and How to Use It</a>, which my mom got me
for my birthday (THANKS MOM!).</p>
<p>As soon as I&rsquo;m done with <a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">Seligman&rsquo;s book flourish</a>, I&rsquo;ll start with this book,
which will hopefully filter through to this blog.</p>
<p>In the meantime, here&rsquo;s the blurb which is already food  for thought:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The average human lifespan is absurdly, insultingly brief.</p>
<p>If you live to be 80, you’ll have had about 4,000 weeks. But that’s no reason for despair.</p>
<p>Confronting our radical finitude  and how little control we really have  is the key to a fulfilling and meaningfully productive life.</p>
</blockquote>








<figure><a href="helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&amp;rsquo;ve been treated with."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&rsquo;ve been treated with.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #177: Streakers.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 22:26:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</guid><description> A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly challenging post-Sunday-lunch run. This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to Sunday September 8, 2019.
On friendship, 25 years later. The birthday mentioned previously, along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends for more than 25 years now.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="lourensriver_at_vergelegen.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly
challenging post-Sunday-lunch run.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to
Sunday September 8, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="on-friendship-25-years-later">On friendship, 25 years later.</h2>
<p>The birthday <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/#celebration">mentioned
previously</a>,
along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two
small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends
for more than 25 years now.</p>
<p>In the bigger scheme of things, it&rsquo;s not <em>that</em> long, but what I would like to
mention here is how much such friendships can grow into the most honest of
human connections.</p>
<p>It is as if with the passing years, one is able to shed all of the unnecessary
baggage one tends to carry around as a beginner human.</p>
<p>What is left, is pure human warmth, unconditional support and, perhaps most
significantly, the effortless loss of self.</p>
<p><em>You</em> fade away, quite happily so, when one of your friends gets up in the
light to tell a story.</p>
<p>For a while at least, one&rsquo;s only representative in the conversation is one&rsquo;s
undivided recognition of and attention to the other.</p>
<p>This is certainly not reserved for 25+ year friendships, although this
pre-requisite seems to facilitate the process to the point of effortlessness.</p>
<h2 id="nested-headings-of-miscellany-nhom-nhom">Nested Headings of Miscellany (NHoM-NHoM).</h2>
<h3 id="org-pdf-tools-for-constructing-unifying-notes">org-pdf-tools for constructing unifying notes.</h3>
<p>Recently, I had to work through a stack of regulatory documents in PDF format.</p>
<p>The challenge was that the documents described different aspects of a single,
complicated procedure, but were severely lacking in overview-engendering
outlines or, even better, diagrams.</p>
<p>I did what I mostly do when faced with any research-related complexity: BUST
OUT SOME MORE OF THAT EMACS!</p>
<p>I found the Emacs package
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/">org-pdftools</a>, which I then
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/pull/4">PRd to work on my newer
Orgmode</a> (github makes
this sort of collaboration so easy!) and then integrated into my workflow.</p>
<p>org-pdftools enables one to link to specific annotated extracts, created
on-demand inside Emacs, from one&rsquo;s orgmode notes.</p>
<p>I used this to synthesise an overview document explaining the whole process,
linking to different parts of multiple PDFs explaining each aspect in more
detail.</p>
<p>Being able to jump effortlessly from a central overview document to specific
positions in reference PDFs is a huge boon to the research process.</p>
<h3 id="escalante">Escalante!</h3>
<p>One friend of work pointed me at an online source of affordable Altras.</p>
<p>I have secretly been pining for a pair of these shoes.</p>
<p>I was planning to use them for the longer runs when I can feel that my feet
need a little more support than my sandals are able to provide.</p>
<p>However, my feet have really gotten used to the wide open spaces of sandals, or
even better, of going barefoot.</p>
<p>Altras are zero-drop shoes, with <em>ginormous</em> toe boxes. Their motto is &ldquo;Embrace
the Space&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It seems like I have found some shoes with the right motto&hellip;</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://altrarunning.com/">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/altra-foot-space.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>Friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation had shoes that were semi-affordable, contrary to my
expectation.</p>
<p>When I pointed friend #2 from work at friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation, he pointed me
at an even <em>more</em> affordable source.</p>
<p>I <em>could</em> have continued with this iterative process, but I was unable to delay
this purchase any longer.</p>
<p>My new pair of Altra Escalante 1.0s arrived the next day.</p>
<p>(Yes, I know, 1.5 and 2.0 are available. However, <a href="https://runrepeat.com/altra-escalante">the stellar reviews of
1.0</a> have not changed, and did I say
&ldquo;affordable&rdquo;?!)</p>
<p>On Friday I broke them in, and on Sunday I made a slightly longer than normal
run (see in-progress photo above) to see how they did.</p>
<p>Anyways, in spite of the rest of me taking quite a beating on the second run, I
can happily report that the shoes did a marvellous job of balancing support
on the one hand and foot-freedom on the other.</p>
<h2 id="life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">Life optimisation tip #73: Streak more.</h2>
<p>As I was scrolling aimlessly through my facebook feed during my last session
before the Great Social Media Fast of September 2019 (see next section), I
quite ironically ran into a truly interesting post by a Swedish visualization
colleague (SVC).</p>
<p>In this post, he talked about his hobby and progress as a <em>run streaker</em>.</p>
<p>It turns out that there are runners with the <em>excellent</em> additional hobby of
<em>streaking</em>, which in <em>this</em> context refers to the act of running every single
day of their lives, and trying to do these daily runs for the longest
continuous streak possible.</p>
<p>The streakers know of each other, almost like Highlander, and are in a friendly
competition, very much unlike Highlander.</p>
<p>SVC now has a single uninterrupted streak, spanning multiple years, of daily
running behind him. He has friends in his city who have also been streaking for
multiple years now.</p>
<p>I find this fantastic, both specifically as a running and fitness feat, and
more generally as a brilliant human optimisation trick.</p>
<p>The longer your streak, the harder it&rsquo;s going to become to break that
streak. Add in the friendly competition element, and you have become an
accomplishment machine.</p>
<p>I see great potential here in the context of
<a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">compounding</a>
more consistently, and for longer.</p>
<p>What else could we streak folks?</p>
<h2 id="the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">The Great Social Media Fast of 2019.</h2>
<p>Twitter, Facebook, Reddit and friends&hellip; hot durnit.</p>
<p>Because I recently re-acquired the habit of checking reddit and twitter
multiple times during the day, I again examined the mechanisms driving this
undesirable behaviour.</p>
<p>The insidiousness, at least for me, lies in the fact that TwiFRaF (twitter,
facebook, reddit and friends) always has something looking like new information
on tap, where with tap, I mean firehose.</p>
<p>At any given moment during the day, when brain desires new input, or is just
tired and would like to take a break, TwiFRaF firehoses are ready to spew
something that appears to be new information but is only a very convincing
analogue.</p>
<p>Brain thinks it&rsquo;s getting what it wanted, plus a tiny and uninspired spurt of
discovery-dopamine here and there, which helps to keep up the illusion.</p>
<p>Any chance of real curiousity taking its natural course is cancelled.</p>
<p>Instead of pondering a question, and then going out on a slow and deliberate
search for information and later enlightenment, the firehose is opened, because
it&rsquo;s easier.</p>
<p>Furthermore, brain is unnecessarily exhausted trawling through a mix of mostly
generic rubbish with, granted, an interesting nugget every blue moon.</p>
<p>Hot durnit.</p>
<p>Fortunately, I like experiments, and Cold Turkey is my middle name!</p>
<p>So, on Saturday I decided to cut out TwiFRaF completely.</p>
<p>Initially I thought it would be an experiment until the end of September, but
now I&rsquo;m thinking that streaking might be an even better option.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;ll see.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #176: Cycle of life.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 13:35:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/</guid><description> Oh hai there friends.
Alles komt tot een einde. This WHV covers the weeks from Monday July 29 to Sunday August 25.
This period had more than its fair share of lows and highs.
Loss. On Saturday, August 3 we lost one of our clan mothers, quite unexpectedly.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to find the words to describe the sudden emptiness left behind by a loved one.
It was a painful reminder of how much of our experience, and of our selves, are built upon our bonds with those around us.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Oh hai there friends.</p>
<figure>
<a href="journeys_end.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hude3a04e51fa4f1e0dd8ccb6de321cf03_1430997_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hude3a04e51fa4f1e0dd8ccb6de321cf03_1430997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hude3a04e51fa4f1e0dd8ccb6de321cf03_1430997_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hude3a04e51fa4f1e0dd8ccb6de321cf03_1430997_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/journeys_end_hude3a04e51fa4f1e0dd8ccb6de321cf03_1430997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>Alles komt tot een einde.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This WHV covers the weeks from Monday July 29 to Sunday August 25.</p>
<p>This period had more than its fair share of lows and highs.</p>
<h2 id="loss">Loss.</h2>
<p>On Saturday, August 3 we lost one of our clan mothers, quite unexpectedly.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to find the words to describe the sudden <em>emptiness</em> left behind by
a loved one.</p>
<p>It was a painful reminder of how much of our experience, and of our <em>selves</em>,
are built upon our bonds with those around us.</p>
<p>It was also a reminder of how much more deliberately and intently we should
dive into and <em>merge</em> with the atoms of each and every moment that we get to
spend with our fellow humans.</p>
<h2 id="reunion">Reunion.</h2>
<p>This year I again had the exquisite pleasure of bringing a short summer visit
to my Dutch family.</p>
<p>Although I sometimes wish that I had eidetic memory so that I could savour this
experience more accurately, I do seem to be looking back at a perfect few days.</p>
<p>The weather was typically Dutch: a tad grey, with some rain now and then. So
when the sun made a brief appearance now and then, our enjoyment was only
intensified.</p>
<p>Each hour and each minute was squeezed for every drop of experience and
togetherness that it had to offer.</p>
<p>Each moment was filled to the brim with our shared <em>humanness</em>.</p>
<p>Dutch family if you are reading this: Thank you.</p>
<figure>
<a href="moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu661c5e839e40484fa03f173660bdb4e2_2414526_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu661c5e839e40484fa03f173660bdb4e2_2414526_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu661c5e839e40484fa03f173660bdb4e2_2414526_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu661c5e839e40484fa03f173660bdb4e2_2414526_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/moroder_heineken_lowlands_2019_hu661c5e839e40484fa03f173660bdb4e2_2414526_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption> At this specific moment, the legend that is Giorgio Moroder was
taking us on a trip through his, and our, musical history. We were stationed, not
altogether statically, on one of the upper floors of the Terrazia across from
the Heineken, experiencing one of those exquisitely perfect summer festival
moments.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>P.S. The <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">Weekly Head Voices series was <em>born</em> in the afterglow of Lowlands
2009</a>.</p>
<h2 id="celebration">Celebration.</h2>
<p>Somewhere during the past three weeks I added another birthday to my scarily
growing collection.</p>
<p>When I woke up on the relevant weekend morning, I had made the deliberate
decision to fill the day with as many as possible of my favourite things.</p>
<p>So:</p>
<p>I started the day with a run.</p>
<p>You would probably not say it if you looked at my running frequency over the
last few weeks (&ldquo;winter weather&rdquo; is all I can say), but this is definitely one
of my favourite activities ever. (I just checked: It seems I have now racked up
just over 1000km on sandals, and about 200km on bare feet.)</p>
<p>After that, I cooked up some pretty respectable Indian cuisine for my <em>inner</em>
circle, that is: genetic progenitor, genetic co-offspring (sibling man, you
have to keep up!), genetic offspring units and life partners.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s something really special about having one&rsquo;s peeps at the kitchen table
with good wine while one, also armed with some of the aforementioned good wine,
does one&rsquo;s best not to embarrass the recipe one has meticulously selected for
the occasion.</p>
<p>(In this case the journey was great, and even the dhal-based destination was
nothing to sneeze at!)</p>
<p>Finally, I made a point of getting out at least one blog post. It turned out to
be <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/08/25/format-flowed-with-long-lines/">a fairly technical
job</a>, but it
checked the relevant box.</p>
<p>As I was working through the list, my real-time life satisfaction meter (what
do you mean you don&rsquo;t have one?) soon became stuck at the 12/10 mark, at which
point I just stopped looking and focused everything I have on the people. 🤗</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #152: A small but highly trained team of 11 year olds.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/09/03/weekly-head-voices-152-a-small-but-highly-trained-team-of-11-year-olds/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 21:07:10 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/09/03/weekly-head-voices-152-a-small-but-highly-trained-team-of-11-year-olds/</guid><description> GOU#2, age 8, made this for the blog, super special.
This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Monday August 6 to Sunday September 2.
Somewhere during this period, I experienced my 44th birthday.
More than once since then, my partner has had to endure my brand-new joke / half-truth that I’m now as clever as a team of four smart 11-year olds. (Hey, it took a team of four smart 11-year olds to come up with that joke!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/sylvia_henna.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/sylvia_henna-1024x719.jpg"
        
            alt="GOU#2, age 8, made this for the blog, super special."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>GOU#2, age 8, made this for the blog, super special.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Monday August 6 to Sunday September 2.</p>
<p>Somewhere during this period, I experienced my 44th birthday.</p>
<p>More than once since then, my partner has had to endure my brand-new joke / half-truth that I’m now as clever as a team of four smart 11-year olds. (Hey, it took a team of four smart 11-year olds to come up with that joke!)</p>
<p>On the big (for me) day, I cooked for a super tiny group of friends. I experienced the ritual of preparing dinner for friends to be an honest one, and filled with human warmth. 12/10 – Would do again.</p>
<p>The next morning, ever-so-slightly in recovery mode, I was surprised by my little brother and my little sister (in-law). MY FAMILY HAD CONSPIRED AGAINST ME WITH SUCH SUCCESS!</p>
<p>Somewhere during this period, I also had the fantastic privilege of going back to my other home (the one with the cheese, and the clogs, and the social democracy FTW) and spending time with my family there.</p>
<p>So much celebration. So much warmth.</p>
<p>(There is also some bitter-sweetness, but that’s the price one has to pay for having roots in different hemispheres.)</p>
<p>I would have liked to say more, but this is one of those WHAMPSAMP* situations.</p>
<p>(As part of a deal I made at AfrikaBurn with a brother, I went fully vegetarian from the Friday to the Monday. It was actually really good!)</p>
<p>(* WHAMPSAMP = What Happens At Mysterious Place Stays At Mysterious Place.)</p>
<h1 id="music-nerd-andor-plain-nerd-section">Music (nerd) and/or plain nerd section.</h1>
<p>Somewhere during that period, Evil Charl went ahead and implemented that <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/spotify2applemusic/gehbfaolompeeapflihekomijnhgccbk">Spotify2AppleMusic chrome plugin</a> that Responsible Charl mentioned in a <a href="/2018/08/08/weekly-head-voices-151-we-are-pleased-to-meet-you/#chrome-or-firefox-plugin-to-convert-spotify-playlists-to-apple-music-using-the-new-musickit-js-api">previous edition of the WHV</a> with the explicit purpose of getting it out of our system.</p>
<p>It’s out there now, and it’s free, so you might as well try it the next time that you need to convert any public (or private in your account) Spotify playlist to the corresponding Apple Music playlist.</p>
<p>I wrote this one in TypeScript where the type interfaces were a fantastic help in writing correct code for the parsing of the various APIs that this plugin has to inter-operate with.</p>
<h1 id="nerd-section-bitbar-with-lua-hammerspoon-nerd-motivations">Nerd section: BitBar with Lua, Hammerspoon, nerd motivations.</h1>
<p>Also somewhere during that period, but in a slightly more surprising twist, I <a href="https://github.com/matryer/bitbar-plugins/pull/1084">added lua support to the open-source macOS utility called bitbar</a>, purely because I wanted to write a network bandwidth plugin that consumed less memory and was faster than the built in shell + awk versions.</p>
<p>That means I’m now also an <a href="https://getbitbar.com/contributors/cpbotha">official bitbar plugin author</a>, which I find strangely satisfying.</p>
<p>Well, maybe it’s not so strange. I do have a thing with producing artifacts that other people (might) use in some way. There’s even more vagueness on this topic at the bottom of this post.</p>
<p>(BTW, the Python version of the same plugin consumed 8 times as much memory as the lua version, which itself consumed about 30% less memory than the shell+awk version.)</p>
<p>(BTW, if you’re on a Mac, and you know a little bit of lua, <a href="https://www.hammerspoon.org">Hammerspoon</a> is an amazing tool for automating your desktop via its lua bindings to the mac desktop API. In a few lines of code, I was able to throw out <a href="https://www.spectacleapp.com">Spectacle</a>, which itself is a great app, but Hammerspoon, the successor of Mjolnir, scores highly on the nerd street-cred scale and has MOAR FUNCTION.)</p>
<h1 id="au-revoir">Au revoir</h1>
<p>I am grateful that you are here reading this, thank you!</p>
<p>I have recently acquired a new side-project (Evil Charl: “HELL YEAH!” BRRRAAAAAAAAMMMM &lt;— crashes straight through office wall to the great outdoors on big motorbike. Responsible Charl: “sigh.”) which is currently sucking up a great deal of my creative output.</p>
<p>We all know what usually happens to side-projects. I guess the high probability of failure may even add to their attractiveness.</p>
<p>In either case, high or low probability outcome, I’ll eventually spill the beans over here. Suffice to say that I do seem to have a thing for <a href="/2018/05/09/weekly-head-voices-141-albert-was-burning-really-hard/">setting things up and then calling them universities</a>, and in this case it’s even allowing me to produce reasonably sized packets of usefulness that might just magically add up to a valuable whole.</p>
<p>I am ever-so-slightly excited.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Lowlands Tooth Fairy #37. [Weekly Head Voices #55]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/28/the-lowlands-tooth-fairy-37-weekly-head-voices-55/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2011 21:20:41 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/28/the-lowlands-tooth-fairy-37-weekly-head-voices-55/</guid><description> In this week’s Weekly Head Voices, looking back at weeks 33 and 34 of 2011, there are three important topics that I’d like to discuss. For your convenience, I’ve arranged them in order of increasing significance. This has the added advantage of guaranteeing that this post ends, at least technically speaking, with a sort of climax. Oh yes, the theme of today’s post is dry.
Photo of the Bravo tent during Lowlands 2011, taken by Andreas Terlaak for NRC Handelsblad.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this week’s Weekly Head Voices, looking back at weeks 33 and 34 of 2011, there are three important topics that I’d like to discuss. For your convenience, I’ve arranged them in order of increasing significance. This has the added advantage of guaranteeing that this post ends, at least technically speaking, with a sort of climax. Oh yes, the theme of today’s post is <em>dry</em>.</p>
<a href="http://www.nrc.nl/inbeeld/trefwoord/lowlands/">
<figure class="wp-caption alignnone">
<img src="http://www.nrc.nl/inbeeld/files/2011/08/Lowlands_2011_Sfeer_39_Andreas_Terlaak-980x735.jpg"/>
<figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Photo of the Bravo tent during Lowlands 2011, taken by Andreas Terlaak for NRC Handelsblad. I hope they don't mind me linking to their picture. You can see more of Terlaak's Lowlands 2011 work by clicking on the photo.</figcaption>
</figure>
</a>
<h3 id="one">One</h3>
<p>I turned 37 very recently. This is the last prime number I’ll have the privilege of gracing before shooting past the big four-oh. I remember when I turned 32. Amongst other defects which I believe I’ve gotten more or less under control, I was extremely <em>smug</em>, and I would probably have irritated the living daylights out of 37-year-old me. I’ve been very much desmugged in my search for harmony and balance in life, although I’ve been told that I tend to be self-congratulatory, an observation that I personally think might have been triggered by my extroverted optimism. Whatever the case may be, I’ll take 5 more years to de-self-congratulatorise myself as well. It’s really a small price to pay for harmony with the universe.</p>
<p>On my birthday, many wonderful people left sweet messages on my facebook wall, in my email inbox, in my SMS whatever and even to my face. It can’t be understated what a positive experience this was. Thank you wonderful people.</p>
<h3 id="two">Two</h3>
<p>I had the awesome privilege and unbridled pleasure (when last did you read about <em>unbridled pleasure</em> in a blog post?! hmm?) of spending 3 sunny days at <a href="http://lowlands.vpro.nl/2011/" title="vpro lowlands 2011 site">Lowlands 2011</a>, an alternative reality where it’s sunny (if you were in NL this “summer”, you would know that sunny weather is a purely theoretical concept) and you get to hang around on the grass drinking beer or in tents <em>experiencing</em> <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WWai4UZ0OqI" title="snippets from Amon Tobin's ISAM">Amon Tobin doing ISAM</a>, or <a data-rel="lightbox-video-1" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_y81nowQ_MU" title="shuffle a dream by little dragon">Little Dragon being absolutely gorgeous</a> on Sunday morning, or Trentemöller and his band being superbly Danish. Of course you get to do this with a group of Exceptionally Wonderful People (EWPs). There is one thing you should take into account before starting to hang out with EWPs: They attract even more EWPs, resulting in huge groups of like-minded EWPs that renders linking up with your favourite EWPs (a subset of the larger group) an interesting challenge, further complicated by the fact that 65000 people SMSing at the same time in the middle of nowhere tend to clog up the few available cellphone towers, which in turn delays any SMS by a random amount from a few seconds to a few hours.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I had an awesome time and am already very quietly counting down until August 2012. EWPs, get ready!</p>
<h3 id="three">Three</h3>
<p>Genetic Offspring #1 lost her first milk tooth and this is of course a major life event. So the Tooth Fairy, or the Tooth Mouse as we call it (GO#1 has ascertained that fairies don’t exist, but she has visually confirmed that mice in fact do, so she’s willing to play along for now), or actually just Yours Truly, had to sneak into her bedroom and exchange said tooth for a sizeable (compared to what my teeth went for back in the day) amount of cash. Remember that this is her major life event, but I did spend a few moments pondering the fact that <em>I’m now someone else’s Tooth Fairy</em>. That’s just huge man…</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>That’s (almost) all I have to say kids. This is my fourth blog post of
the weekend: I also wrote one on <a href="http://blog.timescapers.com/2011/08/27/django-nose-selenium-a-concise-tutorial/" title="timescapers blog post on django testing with selenium">Django testing with selenium</a>, one on
<a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/08/28/a-windows-console-that-does-not-suck/" title="vxlabs on a windows console that doesn't suck">getting a Windows console that doesn’t suck</a>, and another pre-dated
one <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/" title="samsung np300v3a post">on my newest toy</a>.</p>
<p>I really liked writing them all, but I enjoyed this one the most.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Happy returns! [Weekly Head Voices #29]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/05/happy-returns-weekly-head-voices-29/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2010 20:48:49 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/05/happy-returns-weekly-head-voices-29/</guid><description> Dearest readers,
I’m truly sorry that you’ve had to endure three full weeks without any Head Voices. I’ve been in full-on Crisis Mode(tm) for the past weeks, doing my best to complete a number of projects, most prominent of which has been the brand-spanking new TU Delft first year CS course TI 1100-a. During Crisis Mode, all but the most critical of tasks have to spend some time on the back-burner.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dearest readers,</p>
<p>I’m truly sorry that you’ve had to endure three full weeks without any Head Voices. I’ve been in full-on Crisis Mode(tm) for the past weeks, doing my best to complete a number of projects, most prominent of which has been the brand-spanking new TU Delft first year CS course TI 1100-a. During Crisis Mode, all but the most critical of tasks have to spend some time on the back-burner. Almost like the adrenaline-fueled mammalian fight-or-flight response, when even one’s digestion is temporarily halted in order to divert all energy to for example bounding over trees whilst evading some sharp-toothed predator, even my GTD processing more or less came to a stand-till. <a href="/2010/08/08/workin-9-to-5-weekly-head-voices-28/#comment-2385" title="TNR suggesting the Pomodoro technique in a comment to a previous post.">TNR’s pomodoro suggestion</a>, however, was a life-saver. There’s nothing like a succession of 25 minute periods of being completely in the zone for flattening mountains of work. If you’re not continuously zoning yet, I can’t more firmly recommend giving this a try.</p>
<p>In any case, here I am, a slightly debauched weekend drawing to a close (thank you L and friends!), joyfully writing a special anniversary Weekly Head Voices.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/lowlands_cois_15_1280.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/lowlands_cois_15_1280-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Photo taken of the magical entrance to Lowlands, taken by my mysterious and resourceful friend fpixel.wordpress.com"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Photo taken of the magical entrance to Lowlands, taken by my mysterious and resourceful friend fpixel.wordpress.com</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/TI1100A" title="TI 1100-a website">TI 1100-a</a> (which I plan to write a detailed blog post about; the short version: All TU Delft CS first years spend their whole first week doing a single project-oriented course, which I, with much help from my friends, completely redesigned during the past months) concluded with, as far as I could surmise, some success. Fifteen groups of enthusiastic students demonstrated fifteen working augmented reality music instruments in a room packed with 140+ people, and much fun was had by all. With this more or less concluded, I still have more than enough to do, but the decrease in shoulder-weight is considerable and very welcome.</p>
<p>Reaching slightly further back in time to a different slightly debauched weekend, I was one of the 55000 exceptionally privileged human beings spending three life- and humanity-affirming days in the third week of August: <a href="http://lowlands.nl/" title="Lowlands website">Lowlands</a> is not so much a music festival as a fantastic and sizeable post-human community that meets once a year to enjoy each other’s happy presence.  I had the further privilege of also being in the company of a slightly smaller group of exquisite friends. Hello there exquisite friends! Due to our still-strict policy of <em>What happens at Lowlands, stays at Lowlands</em>, I’m not able to give you much more information than the photo of the main festival entrance above. Please do note the huge “Welcome Home” sign at the centre, it’s quite telling.</p>
<p>Those of you who’ve been with this blog for slightly longer, might remember that <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/" title="First edition of the WHV, posted right after LL 2009.">the very first edition of the Weekly Head Voices</a> was posted directly after last year’s Lowlands. <strong>This means that the WHV has now lasted one whole year!</strong> Astute readers will note that the actual frequency of my posts might dictate a name-change to Bi-Weekly Head Voices, which is nice (it has “bi” in there!), but is still not going to happen.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be: Happy birthday Weekly Head Voices, I wish you very many happy returns!</p>
<p>On the topic of happy returns, and my hobby of somehow managing to string together disparate paragraphs in an almost convincing fashion, <a href="/2010/08/01/the-human-animal-post/" title="Link to my Human Animal post">the animal</a> that houses my consciousness also turned one year older in week 34, three days after Lowlands. I’m not mentioning this so that you can send me presents (although these are always welcome, especially if they’re gadget-related), but rather to dwell briefly on the unexpectedly fabulous day. In spite of the deadline-related stress dominating at that stage, being the happy target of a day-long deluge of such positive facebook messages, texts, email and telephone calls was just beautiful, thank you thank you thank you! I really do love being the gregarious human that I am, right in the middle of this information-age.</p>
<p>Alright boys and girls, it’s now time to get some rest, then to wake up bright and early, and then, then to continue on your life mission of <em>creating value</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>