<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Work on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/work/</link><description>Recent content in Work on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2022 14:05:14 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/work/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #240: I am just a copy of a copy of a copy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 21:06:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</guid><description>Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three weeks instead of one.
I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking
back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of
the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three
weeks instead of one.</p>
<p>I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about
alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more
resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough
time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</p>
<p>(Some more famous bloggers that I follow manage to put out a paragraph or two
every single day. It would be interesting to try an experiment like that.)</p>
<p>Anyways, switching out of meta mode back to the mishmash of on-topics for edition
240:</p>
<h2 id="blood-flowers">Blood flowers</h2>
<p>During a recent karma-restoring family beach walk, we came across the following
pretty striking flowers:</p>










<figure><a href="blood-flowers.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_238a35b31dd55230.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_e403e50b40bb34ef.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_435955d294620145.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_51541743b6371d19.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_e403e50b40bb34ef.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Blood flowers in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Blood flowers in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The <a href="http://pza.sanbi.org/haemanthus-coccineus">PlantZAfrica website tells us</a> that these are examples of <em>Haemanthus
coccineus</em>, also known as &ldquo;March flower&rdquo; (no idea why) or &ldquo;blood flower&rdquo;, the
latter which is more in line with the meaning of its Greek genus (haima =
blood, anthos = flower), and its Latin species.</p>
<p>We are not the first or only people to find it quite striking:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It was probably the first flower to be collected from Table Mountain and,
probably also the first illustration of a South African flower to appearin a
European publication. The illustration was by the Flemish botanis de L&rsquo;Obel
in 1605. &ndash; PlantZAfrica</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, as if the name &ldquo;Blood Flower&rdquo; is not metal enough, it turns out
<em>Haemanthus coccineus</em> lives fully underground in the form of a large bulb for
the dry summer months, only revealing its brilliant red flower when the rainy
season is about to start.</p>
<h2 id="fantastic-karma-and-how-to-destroy-it">Fantastic karma and how to destroy it</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s Friday evening. We&rsquo;ve just had a brilliant edition of our Friday evening
family braai tradition, and everyone starts retiring to their various
individual relaxation activities.</p>
<p>I decide that it&rsquo;s a great idea to forge ahead with the <a href="https://github.com/vega/react-vega/tree/master/packages/react-vega">react-vega</a> and <a href="https://redux-toolkit.js.org/rtk-query/overview">RTK
Query</a> visualization functionality I had ended my work week with.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d successfully worked with a previous version of the former, and my
confidence in RTKQ&rsquo;s quality was trending upwards due to recent experience in
one of our products.</p>
<p>I had already made a start with this new instance, and surely my first fully
backend-data-driven visualization was only an hour or two away, giving me a
final Friday evening boost.</p>
<p>Well friends, in hindsight I should have stopped right there and then.</p>
<p>Sure, it was the sort of gamble that had often paid off in the past &ndash; who does
not like to start their weekend with the dopamine rush that comes with the
solving of a little technical puzzle, especially one that results in pretty
pictures?! &ndash; but in this case it was doomed to failure.</p>
<p>The later it got, the less able I was to debug the issue, and the less
emotional control I was able to exert over my growing frustration.</p>
<p>(I am still less than happy with the new react-vega&rsquo;s limited documentation,
error handling and examples.)</p>
<p>I went to bed far later than normal, frustrated, and with no solution in sight.</p>
<p>All of this continued to affect my Saturday (grumpy with capital G&hellip; no wait,
all capitals&hellip;), until I finally made the conscious decision to disconnect
from the technical problem completely.</p>
<p>Anyways, I&rsquo;m writing this down as a reminder to me to be really, really careful
with the work-to-weekend transition.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-1-make-my-home-smart-but-do-it-really-slowly">Techno interlude #1: Make my home smart, but do it really slowly</h2>
<p>I finally got around to hooking up one (1) of the <a href="https://shelly.cloud/products/shelly-1-smart-home-automation-relay/">Shelly 1 smart relays</a> I
bought at the end of 2020.</p>
<p>My whole family is now able to open the main yard gate using&hellip; THEIR PHONES.</p>
<p>Noteworthy here is how easily the Shelly switches can be flashed, over the air
(OTA) no less, with the third party <a href="https://github.com/mongoose-os-apps/shelly-homekit">shelly-homekit firmware</a> to make them
natively Apple homekit compatible.</p>
<p>You can read about the how and the what in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/03/05/connecting-the-shelly-1-to-an-et-systems-gate-motor-for-apple-homekit-control/">this vxlabs post</a>.</p>
<p>Shortly after that post appeared, we held a <a href="https://fb.me/e/30MWR7Rq3">&ldquo;home automation&rdquo;-themed Helderberg
Software Developers and Entrepreneurs meetup</a>. Thanks to current interest in the
topic, and the three absolutely brilliant speakers who were willing to take us
along on their HA adventure, it was the biggest and most active we&rsquo;ve had in
years, by far!</p>
<p>In another probably surprising move, we are currently moving the meetup group
away from meetup.com and onto facebook as a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/helderberg.swdev.entrep.meetups/">group</a> (join if you&rsquo;re on fb!) from
where we can easily setup events.</p>
<p>Since 2019, meetup.com has been charging a pretty ridiculous $50 / 6-months fee
for a 100% free meetup with 0 commercial intent. In return for that, they
handle attendance (ish, we ofen had &gt;50% no-shows) and supply a bit of
discoverability.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, we now fortunately also have a snazzy website at
<a href="https://helderberg.dev/">https://helderberg.dev/</a> where you&rsquo;ll always be able to find the meetup, no
matter the events platform <em>du jour</em>.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-2-make-emacs-more-prettier">Techno interlude #2: Make Emacs More Prettier</h2>
<p>In spite of general business, I did have to make time for some <code>init.el</code>
wrangling, as is the privilege and sworn duty of every Emacs user.</p>
<p>This time, I refined my font and specifically <code>variable-pitch</code> setup.</p>
<p>I settled on the <a href="https://www.figma.com/blog/the-birth-of-inter/">Inter font</a> because I liked the look of <a href="https://obsidian.md/">obsidian.md</a>, where it&rsquo;s
the default. Then I discovered that it was designed (based on the Roboto font)
by Figma designer Rasmus Andersson as &ldquo;a font meant to make it easier to read
text on computer screens&rdquo; (hey, that&rsquo;s exactly what I need!), and is now also
the default on github, mozilla, and notion. Pretty good typographic company
right there.</p>
<p>The other small change I made which was much more satisfying than I expected,
was setting the default font size based on the estimated pixel density of the
current screen.</p>
<p>This means that my Emacs will render its default fonts at sizes that make sense
on whichever display I&rsquo;m using it.</p>
<p>Yes, I know that we should have been able to specify <a href="https://github.com/kickingvegas/12pt-should-be-the-same-everywhere/blob/master/absoluteMeasurementDPI.md">resolution invariant font
sizes by now</a>, but until that future arrives, my Emacs config will just have to
compensate.</p>
<p>The screenshot below shows an example of variable-pitch rendering on the left
(org-roam entry at the bottom, automatic topic backlinks at the top) and in the
centre (a slightly earlier draft of this post) and fixed-pitch on the right,
the relevant parts of my <code>init.el</code> showing the font and (<a href="https://github.com/humanoid-colors/emacs-humanoid-themes">humanoid</a>) theme setup.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_11d3fdd8a77e004c.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_9340b6edcd6a7e76.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_5a93f6bca3ed7d30.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_ce3b5cd81ec4bea7.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_9340b6edcd6a7e76.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Emacs screenshot. No, I don&rsquo;t like dark themes."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Emacs screenshot. No, <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">I don&rsquo;t like dark themes</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="permutation-city">Permutation City</h2>
<p>When I saw a recommendation for <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156784.Permutation_City">Permutation City, a 1994 sci-fi novel by the
Australian author Greg Egan</a>, I was hesitant.</p>
<p>Would a novel, written more than 25 years ago, about uploading digital copies
of humans to virtual reality (I wrote a bit about that in <a href="/2020/07/01/weekly-head-voices-199-a-bit-stubborn/#a-totally-unexpected-ramble-on-cycles-patterns-and-teleportation">WHV #199</a> back in
2020), still be up to date with the latest ideas on the topic, seeing that
several adjacent fields of research have been advancing at a break-neck pace in
recent decades?</p>
<p>Weeeeell&hellip;.</p>
<p>It turns out great sci-fi has no problem reaching ahead through a quarter
century of modern technological development and then blowing my mind several
times.</p>
<p>With Permutation City, Egan has written the book I would have wanted to write,
in my wildest fantasies of course, about humans, and copies of humans, and the
philosophically indistinguishable self-awareness and consciousness of the
copies, and of their copies, and so on, literally ad infinitum.</p>
<p>Fortunately this is my first Egan novel, and even more fortunately it turns out
that he has produced a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/32699.Greg_Egan">considerable collection of stories</a> which I now have the
privilege to proceed to assimilate!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #231: Two thousand four hundred fourty-four</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW
This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to Sunday August 29, 2021.
Orbital mechanics that are important to me Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="pano_from_watsonia.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_hu_bb9baf7faa47d7be.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_hu_486f45e6d2ddf616.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_hu_adf7ac3a79656963.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_hu_76653095a66b6ba0.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_hu_486f45e6d2ddf616.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &ldquo;run&rdquo; with bestie DW"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &ldquo;run&rdquo; with bestie DW</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to
Sunday August 29, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="orbital-mechanics-that-are-important-to-me">Orbital mechanics that are important to me</h2>
<p>Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.</p>
<p>Let me try again:</p>
<p>Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for
another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</p>
<p>As is our custom here, I get to increase the mathematical encoding (this is a
fantastically consistent and useful approach to the structured modelling of
reality) of my time as an alive unit by one.</p>
<p>When I was younger, it was possible to use this number to impress one&rsquo;s
friends. Sometimes, the number of an older sibling or even a parent could also
be used to increase social standing, if one&rsquo;s own number was still quite small.</p>
<p>Ironically, as the number gets bigger, we prefer not to talk or even think
about it too much.</p>
<p>Thanks to math, the number could in theory be transformed into &ldquo;number of
revolutions remaining&rdquo;, but fortunately our complex physiologies and
environments greatly complicate the estimation of the required term for that
transformation, in this case greatly comforting us with uncertainty.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS&hellip;</p>
<p>I had an amazing birthday.</p>
<p>From morning video chats with homies, to working lunches that turned into
superbly relaxed lunches with old friends, surprise visits by far-off friends
the day before, birthday mountain runs with a bestie, and so many (voice)
messages on various platforms from friends everywhere, my birthday was a
friendship-and-life-affirming business.</p>
<p>Friends, thank you for working together like that. You are all breath-taking!</p>
<p>P.S. Experiencing this acted as a beautiful reminder to send that message,
write that email or make that call whenever you can find an excuse!</p>
<h2 id="how-i-m-putting-down-my-work"><em>How</em> I&rsquo;m putting down my work</h2>
<p>In the previous edition of the WHV, I talked about <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">the important skill of being
able to put down one&rsquo;s work</a>.</p>
<p>Here I would just like to mention how I&rsquo;ve been trying to practise this in my
life, especially because it really seems to have helped me since we last spoke.</p>
<p>Ok, get ready!</p>
<p>You Won&rsquo;t Believe This One Trick&hellip;</p>
<p>At 17:00, 17:30 at the latest, I explicitly switch off any tools that I use for
work, and disconnect from all dayjob-related systems.</p>
<p>Work email closed, development enviroments exited, docker containers all stopped.</p>
<p>For good measure, I roll a tumbleweed or two across my office floor, blowing
air out through my pursed lips.</p>
<p>The thing is, my brain has the tendency to continue cogitating on the last
thing I kept it busy with.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I used to have the tendency to still try and solve that problem
before bed, only resulting in me later lying in said bed, unable to get my
brain to stop cogitating, leading to bad sleep, contributing to subpar
performance the next day.</p>
<p>I have to qualify here that putting down work tools does not exclude me from
picking up hobby programming projects later in the evening, after &ldquo;The Making
of The Dinner, With Wine&rdquo; and &ldquo;The Chilling With The Family&rdquo; stages.</p>
<p>Although programming plays a substantial part of dayjob, I have never stopped
enjoying and being relaxed by this activity in the recreational setting.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, making a point of putting down work on time, starting
the gradual wind-down, has drastically reduced the number and severity of
<em>Trying Unsuccessfully to Solve All Work Problems In The Dark, From One&rsquo;s Bed</em> for
me.</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/">Oliver Burkeman</a>, author of <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">the putting-down-your-work post</a>, also wrote a
book titled <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2021/aug/16/four-thousand-weeks-time-and-how-to-use-it-by-oliver-burkeman-review">Four Thousand Weeks: Time and How to Use It</a>, which my mom got me
for my birthday (THANKS MOM!).</p>
<p>As soon as I&rsquo;m done with <a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">Seligman&rsquo;s book flourish</a>, I&rsquo;ll start with this book,
which will hopefully filter through to this blog.</p>
<p>In the meantime, here&rsquo;s the blurb which is already food  for thought:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The average human lifespan is absurdly, insultingly brief.</p>
<p>If you live to be 80, you’ll have had about 4,000 weeks. But that’s no reason for despair.</p>
<p>Confronting our radical finitude  and how little control we really have  is the key to a fulfilling and meaningfully productive life.</p>
</blockquote>










<figure><a href="helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_hu_fc115b2d989aa611.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_hu_e72496ac6e41cb3e.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_hu_93f755774811e38.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_hu_3420bb97bcbcbfc0.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_hu_e72496ac6e41cb3e.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&rsquo;ve been treated with."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&rsquo;ve been treated with.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #230: Follow your blisters</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</guid><description> Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&amp;rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &amp;ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&amp;rdquo; (I didn&amp;rsquo;t and I don&amp;rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="van_breda_cottage_angles.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_b81e281e98679d6a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_1e9bab3660c89449.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_cecd63736e6ae3a2.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_f936d96a4cce0835.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_1e9bab3660c89449.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV covers the three weeks from Monday July 26 to Sunday August 15.</p>
<h2 id="why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">Why I don&rsquo;t like dark mode anymore</h2>
<p>As you might know, I spent most of my working (and sometimes hobby, we&rsquo;ll get
back to that further down) hours in front of this screen or some other screen.</p>
<p>Up to now, I was really convinced that I preferred dark mode everywhere, until
recently two events transpired:</p>
<p>I started noticing more eye-strain than usual, even on my 27&quot; screen, something
which had a perceptible effect on my productivity. This I resignedly ascribed
to my advancing age, although I did find the suddenness quite surprising,
especially since I recently had my glasses updated.</p>
<p>Then, after years with only the admittedly brilliant <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">zenburn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/fniessen/emacs-leuven-theme">Leuven (dark)</a>
Emacs themes checking all of the boxes for me, I finally ran into a really
interesting and usable theme called <a href="https://github.com/kunalb/poet">Poet</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s interesting, because it uses variable pitched fonts for everything but
code, tables and elements of the fixed width domain, where most Emacs fonts
stick to the traditional all-fixed-width approach.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="20210822-poet-theme-screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_61bc38e25939896c.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_741ea773817f7739.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_19248625c7c1a3e8.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_4cb0af8349c12ee4.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_741ea773817f7739.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can probably understand that for someone who uses Emacs almost primarily
for technical notes and other writing, this book-like appearance could work
really well.</p>
<p>The theme was even more interesting for me personally, as it suddenly became
clear as day that I experienced almost no eye-strain when using Emacs with this
lighter theme than when I used any of my other usually dark-themed tools!</p>
<p>It became obvious that poet-theme&rsquo;s lighter background was much easier on my
eyes than dark mode in vscode. (No, this specific advantage can&rsquo;t be ascribed
to Emacs itself I&rsquo;m afraid.)</p>
<p>Reading pages such as <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/digital-eye-strain/is-dark-mode-better-for-eyes/">this</a> explains that dark mode leads to pupils having to
dilate more to let in more light, which there is less of with dark themes.</p>
<p>This leads to, just like with cameras and any other optics with lenses and
apertures, a shortened depth of field, and hence more difficulty focusing on
the screen!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/dark-mode/">This article by the well-known Nielsen Norman Group</a> nicely summarises research
on this topic. In short:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In people with normal vision (or corrected-to-normal vision), visual
performance tends to be better with light mode, whereas some people with
cataract and related disorders may perform better with dark mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Up until recently, I did not experience a qualitative difference in vision
between dark and light, but I sit here relieved that my eye-strain issue has
been resolved by an Emacs theme!</p>
<h2 id="know-how-to-put-down-your-work">Know how to put down your work</h2>
<p>The following take from <a href="https://twitter.com/brandsrock/status/1426163442256330753">a recent tweet by mike joubert</a> struck me
(tweet-take-strike! words are funny&hellip;):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly valuable skill isn&rsquo;t the capacity to push yourself harder, but to
stop and recuperate despite the discomfort of knowing that work remains
unfinished, emails unanswered, other people&rsquo;s demands unfulfilled.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">article, titled <em>The three-or-four-hours rule for getting creative work
done</em></a>, is itself a good read about the observation that creative types (amongst
which I count engineers) have at their best three to four hours of focus time
per day &mdash; so it is crucially important that their days are structured such
that there is an <strong>uninterrupted</strong> block of three to four hours inside of which
that lovely focus has the possibility of appearing.</p>
<p>The tweet-extract focuses on the similarly important but more subtle art of
being able to put one&rsquo;s work down, completely, when that block of time is over,
even when it feels like the work is far from complete.</p>
<p>I especially like that it also explicitly mentions the illusions created by
one&rsquo;s perception of &ldquo;other people&rsquo;s demands&rdquo;, something that ironically becomes
even harder to walk away from when one is more tired at the end of the work
day.</p>
<p>For me, becoming better at putting work down has pleasant echoes of running
slower to run faster, of emptiness in art and more broadly, <a href="https://zenhabits.net/work-less/">choosing fewer f*cks
to give</a>.</p>
<h2 id="follow-your-blisters">Follow your blisters</h2>
<p>On the topic of choosing your ducks&hellip;</p>
<p>I initially did not like <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/what-you-should-follow-instead-of-your-passion">this HBR</a> post when it first crossed my stream, because
it smacks a bit too much of the current social media style of &ldquo;wisdom&rdquo;, namely
&ldquo;everything you need to know in 280 characters&rdquo;, or &ldquo;this 1 minute tiktok video
will change your life&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the title is pretty clickbaity: <em>What You Should
Follow Instead of Your Passion</em>.</p>
<p>However, the core message of the post, which I could not help reading, did
stick with me, and after a few days I realised that I would have to go find the
article again in order to talk about it here.</p>
<p>The core message is to replace <em>find your passion</em> with <strong><em>Find your blisters.</em></strong></p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s point is that folks often get the wrong idea with <em>passion</em> as
something that is simply always delightful, whilst the thing you should
actually be looking for, is that activity that you simply are unable to stop
doing, even when you try, and especially even when you don&rsquo;t directly derive
pleasure from it, for example because you feel that you&rsquo;re not that good at it.</p>
<p>They give the personal example of writing.</p>
<p>Although they&rsquo;ve been at it for years, it&rsquo;s still a difficult and laborious
process, and they are often not happy with the results.</p>
<p>However, they have been unable to stop from returning to writing projects again
and again over the years.</p>
<p>Ironically, even although they find that they are still bad at it, they have in
fact become really good, simply because they have been pushing through and
practising more than almost anyone else over the years.</p>
<p>I really like this down-to-earth view.</p>
<p>One can indeed source almost unlimited amounts of energy from one&rsquo;s &ldquo;blisters&rdquo;,
but true benefits will for a large part be brought about by a <a href="/tags/practice/">lifetime of often
challenging practice</a>.</p>










<figure><a href="flowers_everywhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_77f0491ce2bb652a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_c88a425b4a6e1547.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_26051671c6ea88b0.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_c1d1549ff9af473f.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_c88a425b4a6e1547.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Workin’ 9 to 5? [Weekly Head Voices #28]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/08/08/workin-9-to-5-weekly-head-voices-28/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2010 11:57:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/08/08/workin-9-to-5-weekly-head-voices-28/</guid><description>(This post touches on one noteworthy good news tidbit from my last week, then secretly waxes nostalgic over Dolly Parton, showcases some cheeky parkour and then, after complaining about my overloaded schedule, raises backyard sociological questions as to the most suitable work approach: Time-driven 9 to 5 or output-driven? Oh yes, its WHV Nerd Index is a reassuring 0/5, so it’s safe for everyone!)
I couldn’t come up with a catchy title involving Dolly, so you’re going to have to make do with what I have. When I say Dolly, I’m not referring to the cloned sheep, but to her Country singer namesake Dolly Parton. Google seems to think that Dolly Parton (3 million hits) is more famous than Dolly the cloned sheep (1.25 million hits), so now you know. In any case, Dolly (Parton, for those of you with really short attention spans) once starred in a movie called Nine to Five and, being a famous Country singer, also performed the theme song, called, in a completely unexpected turn of events, 9 to 5. And yes, I do remember seeing the movie more or less when it came out, and I vividly remember Dolly Parton: She was on our television a whole lot, plus that her unique appearance would make it hard not to. Dolly Parton with Lily Tomlin and Jane Fonda at the left and right respectively: The leading Nine to Five cast. Those were the days!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This post touches on one noteworthy good news tidbit from my last week, then secretly waxes nostalgic over Dolly Parton, showcases some cheeky parkour and then, after complaining about my overloaded schedule, raises backyard sociological questions as to the most suitable work approach: Time-driven 9 to 5 or output-driven? Oh yes, its WHV Nerd Index is a reassuring 0/5, so it’s safe for everyone!)</em></p>
<p>I couldn’t come up with a catchy title involving Dolly, so you’re going to have to make do with what I have.  When I say Dolly, I’m not referring to the cloned sheep, but to her Country singer namesake Dolly Parton.  Google seems to think that Dolly Parton (3 million hits) is more famous than Dolly the cloned sheep (1.25 million hits), so now you know. In any case, Dolly (Parton, for those of you with really short attention spans) once starred in a movie called <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0080319/" title="Link to IMDB page on Nine to Five">Nine to Five</a> and, being a famous Country singer, also performed the theme song, called, in a completely unexpected turn of events, <a href="http://www.dollyon-line.com/archives/lyrics/9to5.shtml" title="9 to 5 lyrics on Dolly's site.">9 to 5</a>. And yes, I do remember seeing the movie more or less when it came out, and I <em>vividly</em> remember Dolly Parton: She was on our television a whole lot, plus that her unique appearance would make it hard not to.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/nine-to-five.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/nine-to-five.jpg"
        
            alt="Dolly Parton with Lily Tomlin and Jane Fonda at the left and right respectively: The leading Nine to Five cast. Those were the days!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Dolly Parton with Lily Tomlin and Jane Fonda at the left and right respectively: The leading Nine to Five cast. Those were the days!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Perhaps as a kind of unicorn chaser, or, if you’re secretly a Parton fan, just as an entertaining interlude, I’d like to show you this wonderful YouTube clip of two British parkour gentlemen, who obviously have a great deal of pleasure in their chosen careers:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/voB6WiP83NU?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>On the good news front, our Articulated Planar Reformation (APR: remember it, use it, spread it) paper will be presented at IEEE Visualization 2010 in Salt Lake City, Utah!  The citation is as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>﻿P. Kok, M. Baiker, E.A. Hendriks, F.H. Post, J. Dijkstra, C.W. Löwik, B.P. Lelieveldt, and C.P. Botha, <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Kok2010" title="Link to APR paper">“Articulated Planar Reformation for Change Visualization in Small Animal Imaging,”</a> <em>IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</em>, 2010.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s called a citation, because you should cite it. Often. :)</p>
<p>On the being-busy front, I, Captain Obvious, have recently realised that the reason I’m so busy at the moment, probably has to do with the fact that I have perhaps a few too many projects on my list! Looming and very serious deadlines are August 16,  August 27, August 30, September 15, September 16 and October 2.  These include papers and research proposals as well as the development and running of completely new undergrad and postgrad courses. Continuously feeling like a mole that has been tasked with digging a multi-lane highway through a mountain-range, I have been spending some time (not much, don’t worry) thinking about my method of working.  Once again, the most significant optimisation I could employ was minimising interruptions (facebook, twitter, email, damn email!!) and maximising periods of concentrated work. One measure that really helps is using an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egg_timer" title="wikipedia on the egg timer">egg timer</a>, real or virtual. Whilst the egg timer is counting down, you’re not allowed to touch or think about anything else besides the activity you’ve set for those 30 to 45 minutes. Once the timer goes, you have to spend 5 to 10 minutes goofing off, preferably away from the computer. If you sometimes wake up in a daze and notice that you’ve been facebooking away through the pre-lunch half-hour (20 new friends! yay! who are these people?!), the egg timer is for you!</p>
<p>This leads nicely to our final bit of backyard sociology, an issue that recently came up in discussions with my SO, TNR and TPN (see <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">here</a> for abbreviations): <em>Which do you find the most suitable work approach, time-driven or output-driven?</em></p>
<p>In the <strong>time-driven</strong> approach, one goes to and leaves work at agreed-upon times, performing work up to some agreed-upon standard. However, when the day or the week ends, work really does too. One leaves the office, and, besides the normal mental after-effects, there is no expectation that one is going to spend time doing more work. In the <strong>output-driven</strong> approach, there is much less (or no) expectation as to the hours one will spend working.  In fact, in many cases, one is allowed to plan one’s work day as one pleases, even integrating brief stints at the beach if one’s schedule of meetings and other required physical presence so allows. However, one’s work output is measured, in terms of cases handled, papers written, students supervised, products delivered, and so forth. Even in cases where one has not taken any liberties, this often leads to work in the evenings and on the weekends.</p>
<p>Where I work, output-driven is the norm amongst the research staff members. It sounds like a really good deal, as one could in theory do all kinds of neat things in what is normally considered to be work-time.  In practice however, meetings, deadlines and achievement pressure all conspire to complicate capitalising on the perceived perks. In the end, days are full and evenings and weekends too. Mostly this is fine, as the type of work I do mostly overlaps with what I would consider my hobbies in any case and I can get all passionate about most of the projects I’m involved in. Also, the freedom can be exhilarating. Sometimes, however, I wonder what it would be like to leave the office on Friday and <em>completely switch off the work part of my brain</em>. Sometimes I wonder what it’s like to spend a whole weekend thinking exclusively thoughts that have to do with family, friends and sun. Perhaps it’s got nothing to do with my job, and everything with my brain.</p>
<p>What do you think, time-driven or output-driven? Start-up people, what do you think about being able to switch off? Time-driven fans, care to chime in? You can let it all hang out in the comments!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>