<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>altra on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/altra/</link><description>Recent content in altra on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 22:22:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/altra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #204: What is your purpose?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 22:22:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</guid><description> Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September 13, 2020.
Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.
Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.
Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices,
examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September
13, 2020.</p>
<p>Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more
subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being
outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.</p>








<figure><a href="guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with Microsoft Research&amp;rsquo;s Image Composite Editor, and the power of math."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/product/computational-photography-applications/image-composite-editor/">Microsoft Research&rsquo;s Image Composite Editor</a>, and the power of math.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="sleep-update">Sleep update</h2>
<p>With our teenager back in school, we have to get up at 5:45, mercifully only
for two days of the week with the school in COVID-19-mode.</p>
<p>On other days we get to sleep in until 6:45. LUXURY!</p>
<p>(The lock-down also saved us from a few months of 5:45 wake-ups 5 time per
week during the darkest part of the winter, so there&rsquo;s that.)</p>
<p>This, together with increased pressure at work, has again brought into sharp
focus my sleep hygiene.</p>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t been doing too badly during the past months, but the current period
seemed to require a tad more attention to good sleep.</p>
<p>After reading the disappointing news that the promised first-party (Apple, in
other words) sleep-tracking in the new WatchOS 6 release was not going to be
much more than tracking time in bed, I searched around for the best third-party
sleep tracking app.</p>
<p>Well folks, after a few weeks of testing, I think that <a href="http://autosleep.tantsissa.com/">AutoSleep</a> is it!</p>
<p>(Beware, there&rsquo;s a straight rip-off app in the Google Play store. It&rsquo;s not even
in the same reality as the real thing, although the scammers have stolen a
bunch of visual elements and even copy from the real autosleep website. Oh
Android&hellip;)</p>
<p>The app appears to be almost too full of complicated-looking visual gizmos, so
much so that initially I was not as positive about it. See below for an example
of my sleep history overview:</p>








<figure><a href="autosleep_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot_huce0efa54e288cea4a99599142a3b63a7_817330_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot.png"
            

         width="240px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>However, after using it for a while, and coming to grips with the various
pieces of feedback, this app has turned out to be a great tool in my quest for
sleep hygiene nirvana.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I did have to change my watch charging habits by charging my watch
in the evening hours, so that I can sleep with it on my wrist, and I also have
to remember to tap the &ldquo;lights out&rdquo; button when I attempt to start my sleep
(you don&rsquo;t have to do this, but it gives more accurate tracking that way).</p>
<p>Now I have measurements to show how important the wind-down routine is (if I
can fit in some book-reading in bed, I can fall asleep after that in almost no
time); how some nights when it feels like I&rsquo;m quite restless, I actually do get
quite an amount of sleep; and finally how a drink or two on a weekend night can
affect my average heart rate through the night (+5 beats, oof), and more.</p>
<h2 id="wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 and nativecomp Emacs workflow update</h2>
<p>The following is for my more nerdy readers.</p>
<p>After running into <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/WSL/issues/4619#issuecomment-678652118">this comment</a> on a github issue I am subscribed to, I learned
that you can use the versatile <a href="http://www.dest-unreach.org/socat/">socat</a> tool to forward connections from a unix
socket on WSL2, via the WSL bridge and a WSL1 instance, to a TCP port on
localhost.</p>
<p>The upshot of this is that I now have a robust X11 connection from WSL2 to X410
running on my Windows laptop.</p>
<p>This is possible without socat, but you either need to forward ports using SSH
(which I&rsquo;ve done), or punch holes in the firewall, and then, as if that&rsquo;s not
bad enough, deal with a connection that breaks every time the laptop goes into
suspend.</p>
<p>With the socat X11 connection in place, I decided that it was time to go
further around the WSL2 bend and replace my complicated rsync-based scripts for
copying source code from the Windows host to the WSL2-native filesystem with a
second instance of dropbox running directly on WSL2, with a severe selective
sync configuration.</p>
<p>By the way, after <a href="https://dropbox.tech/infrastructure/rewriting-the-heart-of-our-sync-engine">Dropbox rewrote their sync engine (in Rust)</a>, nothing else
even comes close in terms of performance.</p>
<p>Thanks to this perfect storm of socat-X11-boosted WSL2 and MULTI-dropbox, I
decided that it was finally time to commit to <a href="https://akrl.sdf.org/gccemacs.html">the new nativecomp Emacs &ldquo;capable
of compiling and running Emacs Lisp as native code&rdquo;</a>, so I busted out my
slightly modified version of <a href="https://masteringemacs.org/article/speed-up-emacs-libjansson-native-elisp-compilation">Mickey Petersen&rsquo;s</a> Dockerfile and compiled me one.</p>
<p>This very post is being written on native-compiled Emacs Lisp, running on WSL2,
displaying via socat to X410.</p>
<p><code>#feelsgoodman</code></p>
<p>(P.S. I&rsquo;ve been running like this for about three weeks, with nary an
issue. The future is now.)</p>
<h2 id="keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">Keyboard update: Unicorns-with-RGB</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/#my-attempt-at-dipping-my-toes-carefully-into-the-world-of-mechanical-keyboards">WHV #200 how I carefully started dipping my toes in the
clickity-clackety waters of mechanical keyboards</a> by acquiring a cheap keyboard
with hot-swappable <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile-clicky/outemu-blue/">Outemu blue switches</a>.</p>
<p>What I did not tell you then, was that shortly after acquiring that keyboard, I
had already ordered the <a href="https://youtu.be/e9gRESbY-e8">Womier K87 all-acrylic RGB-overload keyboard</a> from
Banggood.</p>
<p>My reason for ordering that specific board was not so much the lighting (WHICH
IS FREAKING SPECTACULAR BUT BACK THEN I DID NOT KNOW THIS), but rather because
it was the most affordable mechanical keyboard with universal(-ish)
hotswappable switches.</p>
<p>You see, the Outemu board can only take Outemu switches, while with a board
with universal sockets, you have access to a whole smorgas(key)bord of
different switches!</p>
<p>The Womier finally arrived after slightly more than a month, with <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile/gateron-brown/">Gateron brown
switches</a> installed as I had requested.</p>
<p>Probably due to both the brown switches (rated 45g actuation force but probably
less, tactile but not clicky) and due to the board&rsquo;s far more solid
composition, my typing comfort and speed on this thing are close to what I
usually have on my Microsoft Sculpt ergonomic.</p>
<p>Because of this, I don&rsquo;t swap back to the Sculpt nearly as often.</p>
<p>Together with the fact that the keyboard has an impressive and varied
collection of intricate animated lighting patterns thanks to the RGB LED behind
each and every single key, and a whole bunch of extra LEDs in the acrylic body,
this leads to a great deal of typing fun.</p>
<p><code>#feelsbrightman</code></p>
<h2 id="running-update">Running update</h2>
<p>Back in <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">WHV #177</a> I embraced the space and acquired my first pair of Altras, a
pair of road shoes named Escalante 1.0, for a good price, because the 1.5 had
already been released.</p>
<p>Recently I was again in the fortunate position to buy a pair of 1.5s for a good
price, as, you guessed it, the 2.0 had already been released.</p>
<p>The new babies look like this:</p>








<figure><a href="altra_escalante_1.5.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Running in them has been super enjoyable.</p>
<p>(The 1.0s are at about 700km, which is usually a good time to retire them from
running. Now they are just for cocktail parties and business meetings.)</p>
<p>On a more philosophical note, with the aforementioned improving weather, the
aforementioned increased pressure at work, and the non-aforementioned abundance
of mountains all around me, I have taken to randomly taking a few hours off
from aforementioned work to go run in the now aforementioned mountains.</p>
<p><code>#feelslifeaffirmingman</code></p>
<h2 id="what-is-your-purpose">What is your purpose?</h2>
<p>We have a great tradition here at the WHV of revising our official and utterly
complete life philosophy based on discussions with wise friends.</p>
<p>See for example <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">WHV #124</a> where I had to add a third rule to <em>WHV&rsquo;s Two Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em>.</p>
<p>Quite poetically, the additional rule was &ldquo;Evolve&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(FYI, the current official WHV approach to life, the universe and everyhing is
summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.)</p>
<p>During the beautifully-surrounded lunch discussion with longest-time friend
(LTF, henceforth), as depicted in the panoramic photo at the start of this
post, we also spent some time talking about life directions vs. goals.</p>
<p>As you know, I am <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">not a fan of life goals, instead opting for life directions</a>.</p>
<p>LTF agreed with some of my reasoning, but made the valid point that goals were
required to measure and maintain velocity along one&rsquo;s chosen directions, or
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">systems</a>.</p>
<p>In principle we agree on this point also, but I believe that the conversation
will have to continue, as we still need to define and then articulate a
closed-form solution to the directions vs goals issue, or rather a guideline
that can be used to determine the correct relative dosage.</p>
<p>Probably more important was LTF&rsquo;s contribution of the concept of &ldquo;purpose&rdquo;.</p>
<p>One could argue that life directions form one&rsquo;s purpose, but that would be
missing an opportunity I think.</p>
<p>As LTF later quipped:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Purpose = the reason you get up in the morning. Goals = help you go to sleep at
night.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At least in my case, I have a number of life directions, but I think a purpose
is a higher-level, mostly singular, desired outcome of your life&rsquo;s work.</p>
<p>Ideally, <em>life directions</em> should be set in order to orient one towards
fulfilling one&rsquo;s <em>purpose</em>, with continuously evolving <em>goals</em> punctuating the way
there.</p>
<p>What is <em>your</em> purpose?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #190: 3=4.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 15:38:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</guid><description> Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok, because that's how life is. Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!
This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to Sunday March 8, 2020.
(I had made a good start on the post on March 8, but then the work week and a bunch of homing missile deadlines hit.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was
still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok,
because that's how life is.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to
Sunday March 8, 2020.</p>
<p>(I had made a good start on the post on March 8, but then the work week and a
bunch of homing missile deadlines hit. As I write this bit, it is Saturday
March 14, 14:30 SAST.)</p>
<h2 id="gou-3-turns-4">GOU #3 turns 4!</h2>
<p>Our third Genetic Offspring Unit, creative named GOU #3, fairly recently
completed another year of life.</p>
<p>She has now collected the grand total of 4.</p>
<p>It was a pleasure celebrating her birthday with her as it felt like this was
the first time that she was intellectually fully present.</p>
<p>With apparent ease she even understood the sometimes tricky concept of having
one&rsquo;s party on a different day than one&rsquo;s birthday.</p>
<p>For future us, I would also like to note that her pronunciation and sentence
construction are growing more and more precise, sometimes even overly so, the
observation of which delights me.</p>
<p>GOU#3, if you read this years and years in the future: We can already see that
you are an amazing human being. We are deeply happy that you have come here to
join our clan.</p>
<h2 id="new-pair-of-altras-acquired">New pair of Altras acquired.</h2>
<p>In an unexpected but quite happy turn of events, it is starting to look like I
might have to take part in a trail run in July.</p>
<p>(Charl from the future: Only if my finicky ankles man up between now and then.)</p>
<p>Once I&rsquo;ve actually done it, and I&rsquo;m still able to tell the tale, I will surely
do so.</p>
<p>Because I am one of the World&rsquo;s Worst Trail Runners, I will definitely have to
step up my training between now and then.</p>
<p>As with many other endeavours in life, an important component of all of this is
acquiring suitable shoes.</p>
<p>Because <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">my giant-toe-box-zero-drop
Escalantes</a> have been treating
me very well, I had soon narrowed it down to any one of the Altra trail shoes:
Superiors (minimalist), Lone Peaks (jack-of-all-trades), Timp (sightly more
support) and Olympus (maximalist-ish).</p>
<p>After having read all of the internet regarding the different Altra trail
shoes, I reluctantly came to the conclusion that none of them really knocked it
out of the park.</p>
<p>Anyways, one Sunday I walked into our local sports super store (I&rsquo;m sorry my
fellow nerds), and it so happened that they had a pair of Lone Peak 4.5s in my
size: GINORMOUS CLOWN SHOE SIZE.</p>
<p>Trying them on, I tripped and fell right into the psychological black hole of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases">biases</a> and
<em>instantly</em> convinced myself that these were the shoes for me.</p>
<p>Fast forward a week of calling my behavioural insurer (starts with a Disco ends
with a Y) every single day, and they finally managed to figure out what was
wrong somewhere deep in their unfortunately quite sub-par IT systems, and
flipped the <a href="https://www.discovery.co.za/vitality/fitness-booster-shoe">Shoe Purchase Gamification
switch</a>.</p>
<p>In short, if you are able to activate this feature (you have to be super
patient and a bit stubborn), said insurer will subsidise the purchase of a pair
of running shoes based on how often you exercise every week.</p>
<p>This is one neat way of making your running addiction work for you, if you can
somehow absorb the possibly substantial startup cost, i.e. the hours you have
to spend on the phone with the friendly support agents.</p>
<p>Behold my beautiful new trail running shoes:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>State-of-the-art trail-running shoes for the World's Worst Trail
Runner.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="crabby-wallet">Crabby Wallet!</h2>
<p>After years of eyeing Fido U2F and FIDO2 hardware security keys on the
internet, I finally took the plunge and acquired <a href="https://www.yubico.com/product/security-key-nfc-by-yubico">a Yubico Security Key
NFC</a>.</p>
<p>Up to now I used mostly the LastPass Authenticator app and more recently Authy
to generate OTPs as second factor (2FA) for most of my important accounts.</p>
<p>(BTW, if you&rsquo;re not yet using 2FA for your important accounts, such as email,
now is the best time to upgrade. I would recommend getting <a href="https://authy.com/">the Authy
app</a> because it optionally supports multi-device
synchronization.)</p>
<p>The YubiCo hardware device is supposed to be more secure than authenticator
apps due to domain hashing, and it&rsquo;s pretty cool that you don&rsquo;t have to copy
across 6-digit codes, but what I didn&rsquo;t foresee as clearly was the following
simple difference:</p>
<p>I almost always have my phone with me. However, I don&rsquo;t always have my keyring
with me.</p>
<p>I set out to find a new wallet to replace my already pretty minimalist fake
leather credit card booklet. The new wallet had to be at least as minimalist,
but it had to have some sort of lanyard to which I could attach the security
key.</p>
<p>I was delighted to discover that (of course) there&rsquo;s a whole community of
minimalist wallet enthusiasts on the internet.</p>
<p>I was even more delighted when I discovered that the Crabby Wallet C3, a
second-generation product of a <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1369622196/the-crabby-wallet-a-wallet-that-is-not-for-everyon">super successful 2015
kickstarter</a>,
was available all the way down here!</p>
<p>Behold the minimalist wonder that is my new Crabby Wallet:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The Crabby Wallet C3. As you can see, it's only slightly larger than a credit
card. It's made of canvas which looks pretty durable. After a breaking-in
period, it easily holds up to 10 cards. Sometimes there's even cash stashed
under the rubber-band.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>(Charl from 6 days in the future writes: This looks like it&rsquo;s going to be a
keeper. It&rsquo;s more compact and more secure than my previous credit card booklet,
and it has become much more ergonomic after the initial break-in period.)</p>
<h2 id="the-end-of-this-post">The end of this post.</h2>
<p>Thank you for connecting with me here!</p>
<p>Remember, it&rsquo;s now Saturday March 14, 15:26 SAST, but this post will forever
act like it finds itself on Sunday March 8.</p>
<p>I hope that tomorrow I can write WHV #191, a less complicated post that will
come into being not too far away from the moment that is its observation point.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Do you feel like you have an observation point, a specific location that is
your momentary source of perception and thought?</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been getting back into the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up guide</a>, and
there are some truly delightful exercises of the all-encompassing
consciousness.</p>
<p>Remember: <em>There is no observation point!</em></p>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #177: Streakers.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 22:26:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</guid><description> A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly challenging post-Sunday-lunch run. This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to Sunday September 8, 2019.
On friendship, 25 years later. The birthday mentioned previously, along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends for more than 25 years now.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="lourensriver_at_vergelegen.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly
challenging post-Sunday-lunch run.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to
Sunday September 8, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="on-friendship-25-years-later">On friendship, 25 years later.</h2>
<p>The birthday <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/#celebration">mentioned
previously</a>,
along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two
small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends
for more than 25 years now.</p>
<p>In the bigger scheme of things, it&rsquo;s not <em>that</em> long, but what I would like to
mention here is how much such friendships can grow into the most honest of
human connections.</p>
<p>It is as if with the passing years, one is able to shed all of the unnecessary
baggage one tends to carry around as a beginner human.</p>
<p>What is left, is pure human warmth, unconditional support and, perhaps most
significantly, the effortless loss of self.</p>
<p><em>You</em> fade away, quite happily so, when one of your friends gets up in the
light to tell a story.</p>
<p>For a while at least, one&rsquo;s only representative in the conversation is one&rsquo;s
undivided recognition of and attention to the other.</p>
<p>This is certainly not reserved for 25+ year friendships, although this
pre-requisite seems to facilitate the process to the point of effortlessness.</p>
<h2 id="nested-headings-of-miscellany-nhom-nhom">Nested Headings of Miscellany (NHoM-NHoM).</h2>
<h3 id="org-pdf-tools-for-constructing-unifying-notes">org-pdf-tools for constructing unifying notes.</h3>
<p>Recently, I had to work through a stack of regulatory documents in PDF format.</p>
<p>The challenge was that the documents described different aspects of a single,
complicated procedure, but were severely lacking in overview-engendering
outlines or, even better, diagrams.</p>
<p>I did what I mostly do when faced with any research-related complexity: BUST
OUT SOME MORE OF THAT EMACS!</p>
<p>I found the Emacs package
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/">org-pdftools</a>, which I then
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/pull/4">PRd to work on my newer
Orgmode</a> (github makes
this sort of collaboration so easy!) and then integrated into my workflow.</p>
<p>org-pdftools enables one to link to specific annotated extracts, created
on-demand inside Emacs, from one&rsquo;s orgmode notes.</p>
<p>I used this to synthesise an overview document explaining the whole process,
linking to different parts of multiple PDFs explaining each aspect in more
detail.</p>
<p>Being able to jump effortlessly from a central overview document to specific
positions in reference PDFs is a huge boon to the research process.</p>
<h3 id="escalante">Escalante!</h3>
<p>One friend of work pointed me at an online source of affordable Altras.</p>
<p>I have secretly been pining for a pair of these shoes.</p>
<p>I was planning to use them for the longer runs when I can feel that my feet
need a little more support than my sandals are able to provide.</p>
<p>However, my feet have really gotten used to the wide open spaces of sandals, or
even better, of going barefoot.</p>
<p>Altras are zero-drop shoes, with <em>ginormous</em> toe boxes. Their motto is &ldquo;Embrace
the Space&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It seems like I have found some shoes with the right motto&hellip;</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://altrarunning.com/">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/altra-foot-space.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>Friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation had shoes that were semi-affordable, contrary to my
expectation.</p>
<p>When I pointed friend #2 from work at friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation, he pointed me
at an even <em>more</em> affordable source.</p>
<p>I <em>could</em> have continued with this iterative process, but I was unable to delay
this purchase any longer.</p>
<p>My new pair of Altra Escalante 1.0s arrived the next day.</p>
<p>(Yes, I know, 1.5 and 2.0 are available. However, <a href="https://runrepeat.com/altra-escalante">the stellar reviews of
1.0</a> have not changed, and did I say
&ldquo;affordable&rdquo;?!)</p>
<p>On Friday I broke them in, and on Sunday I made a slightly longer than normal
run (see in-progress photo above) to see how they did.</p>
<p>Anyways, in spite of the rest of me taking quite a beating on the second run, I
can happily report that the shoes did a marvellous job of balancing support
on the one hand and foot-freedom on the other.</p>
<h2 id="life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">Life optimisation tip #73: Streak more.</h2>
<p>As I was scrolling aimlessly through my facebook feed during my last session
before the Great Social Media Fast of September 2019 (see next section), I
quite ironically ran into a truly interesting post by a Swedish visualization
colleague (SVC).</p>
<p>In this post, he talked about his hobby and progress as a <em>run streaker</em>.</p>
<p>It turns out that there are runners with the <em>excellent</em> additional hobby of
<em>streaking</em>, which in <em>this</em> context refers to the act of running every single
day of their lives, and trying to do these daily runs for the longest
continuous streak possible.</p>
<p>The streakers know of each other, almost like Highlander, and are in a friendly
competition, very much unlike Highlander.</p>
<p>SVC now has a single uninterrupted streak, spanning multiple years, of daily
running behind him. He has friends in his city who have also been streaking for
multiple years now.</p>
<p>I find this fantastic, both specifically as a running and fitness feat, and
more generally as a brilliant human optimisation trick.</p>
<p>The longer your streak, the harder it&rsquo;s going to become to break that
streak. Add in the friendly competition element, and you have become an
accomplishment machine.</p>
<p>I see great potential here in the context of
<a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">compounding</a>
more consistently, and for longer.</p>
<p>What else could we streak folks?</p>
<h2 id="the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">The Great Social Media Fast of 2019.</h2>
<p>Twitter, Facebook, Reddit and friends&hellip; hot durnit.</p>
<p>Because I recently re-acquired the habit of checking reddit and twitter
multiple times during the day, I again examined the mechanisms driving this
undesirable behaviour.</p>
<p>The insidiousness, at least for me, lies in the fact that TwiFRaF (twitter,
facebook, reddit and friends) always has something looking like new information
on tap, where with tap, I mean firehose.</p>
<p>At any given moment during the day, when brain desires new input, or is just
tired and would like to take a break, TwiFRaF firehoses are ready to spew
something that appears to be new information but is only a very convincing
analogue.</p>
<p>Brain thinks it&rsquo;s getting what it wanted, plus a tiny and uninspired spurt of
discovery-dopamine here and there, which helps to keep up the illusion.</p>
<p>Any chance of real curiousity taking its natural course is cancelled.</p>
<p>Instead of pondering a question, and then going out on a slow and deliberate
search for information and later enlightenment, the firehose is opened, because
it&rsquo;s easier.</p>
<p>Furthermore, brain is unnecessarily exhausted trawling through a mix of mostly
generic rubbish with, granted, an interesting nugget every blue moon.</p>
<p>Hot durnit.</p>
<p>Fortunately, I like experiments, and Cold Turkey is my middle name!</p>
<p>So, on Saturday I decided to cut out TwiFRaF completely.</p>
<p>Initially I thought it would be an experiment until the end of September, but
now I&rsquo;m thinking that streaking might be an even better option.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;ll see.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>