<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>React on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/react/</link><description>Recent content in React on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:48 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/react/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 4 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-22 As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&amp;rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS! At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&amp;hellip; Short but really nice streamlit demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually played with it. Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3. In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola. Tuesday 2024-01-23 At the office nice and early (7:30). Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at react-flow and comfyui react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY! streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &amp;ldquo;things I learned&amp;rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document. Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&amp;rsquo;s a zero day vulnerability in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites. Wednesday 2024-01-24 8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW! Remember kids: Our spine&amp;rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally. This is also the reason why I&amp;rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair. Lovely working lunch with friend S at No Way José Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work: idea: make github so that people can pipx install marimo-turbo to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on. idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS &amp;hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844 (post is also embedded below) idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&amp;gt; nginx -&amp;gt; supervisord -&amp;gt; tornado systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation I would prefer to use supervisord for this This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick? ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &amp;ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&amp;rdquo; googling blog post: https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/ the kubernetes thing: https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&amp;rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via iframe.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-22">Monday 2024-01-22</h2>
<ul>
<li>As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &ldquo;When you&rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS!</li>
<li>At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&hellip;</li>
<li>Short but really nice <a href="https://streamlit.io/">streamlit</a> demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&rsquo;ve never actually played with it.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3.
<ul>
<li>In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-23">Tuesday 2024-01-23</h2>
<ul>
<li>At the office nice and early (7:30).</li>
<li>Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at <a href="https://reactflow.dev/">react-flow</a> and comfyui
<ul>
<li>react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see <a href="https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary">https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary</a>
<ul>
<li>it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster</li>
<li>marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &ldquo;things I learned&rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document.</li>
<li>Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&rsquo;s a <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/news/apple-issues-urgent-security-updates-to-fix-zero-day-flaw-update-your-iphone-and-mac-right-now">zero day vulnerability</a> in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-24">Wednesday 2024-01-24</h2>
<ul>
<li>8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot</li>
<li>dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work</li>
<li>right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW!
<ul>
<li>Remember kids: Our spine&rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally.</li>
<li>This is also the reason why I&rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lovely working lunch with friend S at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/NoWayJoseSomerset">No Way José</a></li>
<li>Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work:
<ul>
<li>idea: make github so that people can <code>pipx install marimo-turbo</code> to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on.</li>
<li>idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap
<ul>
<li>sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets</li>
<li>in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS
<ul>
<li>&hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844</a> (post is also embedded below)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&gt; nginx -&gt; supervisord -&gt; tornado
<ul>
<li>systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: <a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation">https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation</a></li>
<li>I would prefer to use supervisord for this</li>
<li>This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&rdquo; googling
<ul>
<li>blog post: <a href="https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/">https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/</a></li>
<li>the kubernetes thing: <a href="https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s">https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0" width="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><script src="https://emacs.ch/embed.js" async="async"></script>
<h3 id="til-mastodon-embeds-are-not-as-durable-as-twitter-embeds">TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds</h3>
<p>As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via <code>iframe</code>.</p>
<p>With twitter, you get more self-contained HTML which will render even when twitter or just the original tweet don&rsquo;t exist anymore.</p>
<p>This is probably just another reason to figure out how I can get more low-friction microblogging going on my own websites so that the embedding implementations of other microblogging sites become irrelevant.</p>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-25">Thursday 2024-01-25</h2>
<ul>
<li>Took a look at <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/connections/connect-networks/get-started/">cloudflare tunnels</a> to expose marimo and other dashboards to the internet
<ul>
<li>great that I can use my existing domains for this, and I can route between multiple domains to multiple locally running services</li>
<li>some more steps to setup, but it did not take more than about 5 minutes, and gives me even more options than tailscale funnels. OPTIONS MAN!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At work, quickly got react-flow&hellip; flowing. SHINY!</li>
<li>In the evening, found <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/">https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/</a> which is the new Shortcuts based way, based on the old AppleScript way, of getting a <code>message://</code> link onto the clipboard.
<ul>
<li>You <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#email-linking">might recall from this blog</a> that <code>message://</code> are the most durable and cross-platform way to link to emails from your notes (or anywhere else)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-26">Friday 2024-01-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up to cool, overcast weather, a big change from a series of 30℃ + days. Really had to resist going out for a run (normal run day + that amazing coolness), because of Wednesday&rsquo;s partially pulled back muscle not being 100% yet.</li>
<li>Worked on mystery visualization project (react-flow)</li>
<li>Lovely and energising lunch with previous colleague and friend. Happy that I reached out on Thursday although they have a packed schedule because only in country for limited time. I guess this is quite related to <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">calling up your friends</a>, with a ping of serendipity salt.</li>
<li>I was shocked by how well and fast <a href="https://ollama.ai/">ollama</a> worked on my MacBook. See embedded tweet below.</li>
<li>Almost at the end of the afternoon, friend S and I went to some more friends for the first Weiss-off, that is, a Weiss beer tasting contest. It was huge fun blind-tasting 10 different Weiss beers, ranking them, trying to identify them (so much harder than I thought!), and then having them revealed at the end.
<ul>
<li>Between the experts there (read: us), Stangen Weiss Bier came out on top, followed by Weisbier No5 and Jack Black Atlantic Weiss. The fourth place was shared by Erdinger and CBC Amber Weiss.</li>
<li>My favourite, Stellenbrau Jonkersweiss, is glaringly absent from the top. I&rsquo;ll live, probably consoled by just such a Jonkersweiss. Super happy that Amber Weiss and Atlantic are both present!</li>
<li>There was a trophy (for the taster who could blind-identify the most beers in the Weiss-off), which we have christened the <em>David Weisselhoff wisseltrofee</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">With <a href="https://twitter.com/MistralAI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@MistralAI</a>&#39;s Mistral 7B at Q4_0 on this MacBook M1 Pro 10C / 16C, <a href="https://twitter.com/ollama?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ollama</a> looks like it&#39;s easily 3 times faster than the new MLX 0.0.11 (with GGUF support).<br><br>It&#39;s subjectively (visually) faster, and the tokens/s measurements confirm this. <a href="https://t.co/9vyluimLKK">pic.twitter.com/9vyluimLKK</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1750824125419942036?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 26, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-27">Saturday 2024-01-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yesterday&rsquo;s Wonderful Weiss-off also had some, thankfully quite minor, effect the next morning, but I went out for a careful weekday distance run, which fortunately went without a hitch. Just very hot thanks.</li>
<li>Went to Buco and then to <a href="https://appletoolandgas.com/">Apple Tool and Gas</a> to find the rest of the screws I needed to repair the shower door. Friendly gentleman at Apple even sawed some of my screws to size! Shower door back in operation.</li>
<li>Updated my &ldquo;old&rdquo; M1 MBA to macOS 14.3 and then reset to transfer to GOU#1&rsquo;s iCloud. Say what you want about Apple, but that part of their stuff works <em>really</em> well.</li>
<li>Left for Betty&rsquo;s Bay at about 16:00 with GOUs #1 and #2. The rest of the family already there.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-28">Sunday 2024-01-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up in Betty&rsquo;s Bay after a longer than normal night of sleep, but Garmin body battery was still not completely happy.</li>
<li>In spite of having run yesterday and still feeling a bit tired (see body battery above), I had the best run of the month so far in Betty&rsquo;s. Go figure.</li>
<li>Spent some time with Canva &ndash; what a great resource for doing nice designs, even flow charts &ndash; but not sure where I could use this.</li>
<li>Background thought through the past weeks, and mentioned on Tuesday: I would really like to do (and promite) more TIL-style writing at work and at home. See <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/">Simon Willison&rsquo;s amazing TIL collection</a> for inspiration.</li>
<li>Ran into <a href="https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines">https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines</a> a Python library that can guarantee structured text generation from many LLMs, e.g. 100% valid JSON according to a specified schema. What makes it different from similar libraries? &ldquo;Unlike other libraries, regex-guided generation in Outlines is almost as fast as non-guided generation.&rdquo;</li>
<li>I already had <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/autogen">AutoGen</a> on my list for experimenting with multi-agent LLM applications, but now it has been joined by <a href="https://github.com/joaomdmoura/crewAI">crewAI</a> which I have also just ran into (thanks reddit!) and which seems to have significant support online.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #187: Checklists everywhere.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 19:15:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/</guid><description>Welcome back ANYONE WHO IS READING THIS!
Fiery sky in Betty's Bay. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about the situation in the Northern hemisphere, but down here in the South it seems as if just about everyone has disconnected for the Christmas period.
I decided that I would prefer at least trying to end the year with a few more-or-less on time WHVs, even if they have to slim down a bit to do so.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back ANYONE WHO IS READING THIS!</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu_6b234d3255d24c43.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu_542a2a33eb9bcf99.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu_e2eea2fe9d713e6e.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu_177f891ef0fdb5d5.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu_542a2a33eb9bcf99.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Fiery sky in Betty's Bay.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure about the situation in the Northern hemisphere, but down here in
the South it seems as if just about everyone has disconnected for the Christmas
period.</p>
<p>I decided that I would prefer at least trying to end the year with a few
more-or-less on time WHVs, even if they have to slim down a bit to do so.</p>
<p>So here we are: Just you and me. Maybe just me.</p>
<p>This WHV looks back on the week from Monday December 16 to Sunday December 22, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="the-last-work-week-of-2019-partially-in-bullets">The last work-week of 2019, (partially) in bullets.</h2>
<p>For me this was the last <em>real</em> work week.</p>
<p>I did spend most of it working from places other than the office, which was
nice.</p>
<p>Other than that, I would like to mention the following noteworthy learnings and
events:</p>
<ul>
<li>Schlepping along my Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic Desktop keyboard (current
favourite) and mouse, as well as my collapsible laptop stand (to bring the
laptop screen up to eye height) made a huge positive difference to my
ergonomics. 12/10 would do again.</li>
<li>We had a gratifying 4 day turn-around from the report of a pretty
obscure and initially irreproducible bug, through analysis and debugging, to
a new Windows driver release.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/projectstorm/react-diagrams">react-diagrams</a> is an
amazing TypeScript library for putting together a boxes and lines frontends
to manipulate graph-based dataflow backends. However, the TypeScript class
hierarchies and lack of documentation complicate customisation, if that&rsquo;s
your goal. I had to throw out that work and start over, building everything
on React (<a href="https://reactjs.org/docs/hooks-intro.html">hooks</a> all the way
baby!) and little bits of d3 for the spliny bits.</li>
<li>In the same vein, <a href="https://github.com/tgdwyer/WebCola">Cola.js / WebCola</a> is
an impressive layout approach for graphs. The force-directed layout in d3 is
great for interactive demos, but sometimes you want something that, you know,
lays out the graph. See this <a href="https://js.cytoscape.org/demos/2ebdc40f1c2540de6cf0/">cytoscape
demo</a> for even more
fun.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="on-checklists">On checklists.</h2>
<p>During this last week, as I was fighting to maintain the last islands of focus
being relentlessly eroded by the persistent seas of vacation-temptation, I was
helped a great deal by micro-checklists.</p>
<p>I briefly debated calling them multi-scalar checklists, but they are really
just normal checklists, except applied to any duration of work or focus time.</p>
<p>In other words, given an hour in the evening to spend on research, I would
start the hour by quickly jotting down (in Emacs Orgmode of course) a checklist
of the 4 to 5 things I would like to get done in that hour.</p>
<p>It was surprising to me much that 5 minute time investment would return in the
subsequent 55.</p>
<p>The lesson that I am taking from this, is that <a href="http://localhost:1313/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">my daily planning
checklist</a>
is not enough.</p>
<p>The daily landscape itself, my energy levels and my interest change far too
much and too quickly for a single daily checklist.</p>
<p>When you only get a few hours here and there to work, this problem is even more acute.</p>
<p>I am still figuring out how exactly to cultivate this new habit of making a new
checklist before every block of work, multiple times per day.</p>
<p>(What exactly is a block of work? Practically, how can I delineate this during
the day?)</p>
<h2 id="on-disconnecting-for-recuperation">On disconnecting for recuperation.</h2>
<p>During this time of the year I&rsquo;m usually spending a number of mental cycles
debating how exactly to disconnect from The Network.</p>
<p>(See <a href="/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/#you-are-turning-into-a-cyborg">You are turning into a
cyborg</a>
from a 2014 Weekly Head Voices, for example.)</p>
<p>Even longer ago than that, I used to keep my work and personal email separate.</p>
<p>During vacations, I would temporarily remove the work account from all of my
devices so that I could only see the mostly social-related personal emails.</p>
<p>These days, work and personal networks seem to have become even more
intertwined all by themselves, complicating measures like the above.</p>
<p>When I re-joined the Exciting World of Business and Great Success in 2013, I
merged all of my email back into a single account, for better knowledge
management and especially retrieval.</p>
<p>Another more important and more current example of this is WhatsApp, which more
or less dominates all instant messaging and a great deal of general
communication down here.</p>
<p>Many people I know use WhatsApp for work.</p>
<p>However, most of them, probably like most of you, use a single phone with a
single SIM.</p>
<p>This means that they will probably see work-related messages and activities
during their vacation, traditionally, but now perhaps increasingly
anachronistically, a period of disconnection.</p>
<p>(By the way, see <a href="/2011/02/05/postmodern-creativity-weekly-head-voices-37/">me in 2011 recommending WhatsApp over
SMS</a> when WhatsApp
was still quite small, and see <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">me in 2016 recommending Signal over
WhatsApp</a>. Signal
is still the best choice by far if you value your privacy and security.)</p>
<p>Personally, it feels like my current adventure in the Exciting World of
Business and Great Success requires me to be available, just in
case. Therefore, I am planning only a very few days of &ldquo;offline&rdquo;, which is more
of a mental state than a technological setting.</p>
<p>Other than that, my colleagues are all really great about staying off the
emails and the WhatsApps, partly because they <em>are</em> really great (see above)
and partly because they are applying similar methods.</p>
<p>The only question that remains is, how much disconnection, and at which
intensity, does the disconnecting human require for optimal functioning?</p>
<p>Friends, whatever your level of disconnect, I wish you maximum rest.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hu_fe6237de90ac474d.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hu_eff8659883b576ab.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hu_4d41224b7ca59266.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hu_9692582ef35776d8.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hu_eff8659883b576ab.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
</figcaption>
</figure>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #128: Water water everywhere, but not a drop to drink.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/21/weekly-head-voices-128-water-water-everywhere-but-not-a-drop-to-drink/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 15:39:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/21/weekly-head-voices-128-water-water-everywhere-but-not-a-drop-to-drink/</guid><description> Hey friends, welcome back!
We have to talk about the water situation, seeing that Cape Town is now in the international news as being on track to be the first major city EVAR to run out of water.
In short, if it doesn’t rain in substantial amounts during the coming three months (which history and projections say it won’t), the municipal water supply will be shut off on April 21, a date festively referred to as Day Zero.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/bbay-pano-20180121.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/bbay-pano-20180121-1024x326.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Hey friends, welcome back!</p>
<p>We have to talk about the water situation, seeing that Cape Town is now in the international news as <a href="http://time.com/5103259/cape-town-water-crisis/">being on track to be the first major city EVAR to run out of water</a>.</p>
<p>In short, if it doesn’t rain in substantial amounts during the coming three months (which history and projections say it won’t), <a href="http://untoldafrica.com/calling-all-capetonians-its-time-to-prepare-for-day-zero/">the municipal water supply will be shut off on April 21</a>, a date festively referred to as <em>Day Zero</em>.</p>
<p>This means when we try to open any tap, no water will come out. This situation might continue for quite a while, which is pretty intense.</p>
<p>On that day, we will be celebrating by dressing up as Kevin Costner and running around barefoot shouting “NOTHING’S FREE IN WATERWORLD!”. Those who are not big fans of Kevin are allowed to dress up as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imperator_Furiosa">Imperator Furiosa</a>.</p>
<p>At my house, we stopped watering our garden with municipal water months ago. We installed a grey water recovery system: Shower and bath water ends up in the only remaining green corner of the garden.</p>
<p>We also installed a rain water recovery system three months ago, which has fortunately enabled us to collect a few thousand litres of rain water via the rerouted gutters and pipework from the roof. This water we will probably use after Day Zero to be able to wash and to flush a toilet now and then.</p>
<p>(Flushing frequency has necessarily decreased significantly. Around these parts we now have the saying: “If it’s yellow, let it mellow. If it’s br***, flush it down.” Please excuse the mental graphics.)</p>
<p>We have been managing to keep our use of municipal water under the requested 87 litres per person per day. Starting on February 1, we will have to stay consistently under 50 litres per person per day, including drinking, cooking and washing. I guess 2 minute showers were wasting too much of my time in any case.</p>
<p>I have to do more research and corroboration (fingers are being pointed in all directions), but it seems the fundamental issue is not so much the current drought alone, but to a large extent mismanagement by <em>both</em> local and national government. It’s complicated, and politics is involved, so read at least <a href="https://theconversation.com/cape-towns-water-crisis-driven-by-politics-more-than-drought-88191">this</a> (otherwise good piece, but author is a DA / local government apologist), <a href="https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/article/2018-01-22-op-ed-cape-town-a-city-drowning-in-incompetence/">this</a> (DA / local government IS to blame) and <a href="https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/article/2018-01-22-analysis-a-drought-of-nature-compounded-by-a-drought-in-leadership/">this</a> (a longer, more balanced piece) to start with.</p>
<p>That being said, I <em>am</em> happy that a large part of the populace has become much more water efficient. If we get through this, in spite of “this” being called “the new normal”, I hope that we retain our mad Dune-grade water saving skills.</p>
<p>With that out of the way, it would be sort of anti-climactic for me to talk extensively about what-I-did-last-week, so I’m going to limit it to a REAL bullet list (ping me in the comments if something interests you):</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pypa/pipenv">pipenv</a> is the bee’s knees, I have switched my non-miniconda projects.</li>
<li>convincingly but fortunately only temporarily locked myself out of my one laptop due to TCG-Opal hardware encryption, UEFI32, UEFI64 and legacy boot incompatibilities. I’m getting old, I used to NOT lock me out of my laptop in my sleep.</li>
<li>A compulsive twitch made me fix years of old-style broken youtube shortcodes using the <a href="https://wordpress.org/plugins/search-regex/">wordpress regex plugin</a>. The regexp you are looking for is <code>/\[youtube\](.*)\[\/youtube\]/</code> which you can replace with <code>\1</code>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/why-people-dislike-really-smart-leaders/">People dislike really smart leaders</a>. See water crisis above for one possible reason why this is a bad thing.</li>
<li>In spite of having invested a significant amount of time in deciding on the <a href="https://github.com/OfficeDev/office-ui-fabric-react">Office UI Fabric React components</a> for my most major side-project (#38465 if you’ll recall), I switched to <a href="https://react.semantic-ui.com/introduction">Semantic UI React</a> (which was also in the running, together with <a href="http://blueprintjs.com/">Palantir’s blueprint</a>, <a href="http://grommet.io/">HP’s grommet</a>, <a href="https://ant.design/docs/react/introduce">Alibaba’s Ant Design of React</a> and more) at the last minute. I am happier now.</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it from me for now. Have fun this week kids, I hope to see you soon!</p>
<p> </p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>