<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>marcus aurelius on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/marcus-aurelius/</link><description>Recent content in marcus aurelius on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 09:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/marcus-aurelius/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #167: Yes, and...</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/</guid><description> (I initially posted this blog with an incorrect slug, so I had no choice but to re-publish with the correct slug and URL. It is possible that you receive the email notification twice. I am really sorry about this! P.S. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s a dirtly little secret of the blogging industry that slugs are involved.)
I have posted similar photos before, but this one is special, because it was a crystal clear and almost wind-free Friday afternoon, hosting an almost perfect barefoot run.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(I initially posted this blog with an incorrect slug, so I had no choice but
to re-publish with the correct slug and URL. It is possible that you receive
the email notification twice. I am really sorry about this! P.S. Yes, it&rsquo;s a
dirtly little secret of the blogging industry that slugs are involved.)</em></p>
<figure>
<a href="strand_crystal_clear.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='photo of strand beach at macassar rheinmetal fence' />



</a>
<figcaption>I have posted similar photos before, but this one is special,
because it was a crystal clear and almost wind-free Friday afternoon, hosting
an almost perfect barefoot run.  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Oh hi there friends, from this <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">brand new and quite shiny Hugo blogging
setup</a>!</p>
<p>When the novelty wears off, as it invariably does, I expect that I will be
<em>quite</em> content with this graduation to a more minimalist blogging experience:
It&rsquo;s just me, and you, and this old text editor.</p>
<p>I am looking forward.</p>
<p>At this very moment however, I am also looking back, at the week from Monday
March 25 to Sunday, March 31, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="fire-and-motion">Fire and Motion.</h2>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know how else to describe it, but the thought that came up most often
last week was: What a silly day.</p>
<p>It felt like I had to put in three times the energy to get out just a little
bit of focus. Every morning I returned to the grind, just to continue with
this Sisyphean struggle.</p>
<p>On Thursday, co-worker adt (not the security company) sent me <a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2002/01/06/fire-and-motion/">Joel Spolsky&rsquo;s
&ldquo;Fire and Motion&rdquo;
essay</a>. (I
previously thought that I had read all the best of Spolsky, but apparently
not!)</p>
<p>Spolsky starts with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes I just can’t get anything done.</p>
<p>Sure, I come into the office, putter around, check my email every ten seconds,
read the web, even do a few brainless tasks like paying the American Express
bill. But getting back into the flow of writing code just doesn’t happen.</p>
<p>These bouts of unproductiveness usually last for a day or two. But there have
been times in my career as a developer when I went for weeks at a time without
being able to get anything done. As they say, I’m not in flow. I’m not in the
zone. I’m not anywhere.</p>
<p>Everybody has mood swings; for some people they are mild, for others, they can
be more pronounced or even dysfunctional. And the unproductive periods do seem
to correlate somewhat with gloomier moods.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Suddenly I felt far less bad, and super grateful that Spolsky had the guts to
publish this admission.</p>
<p>If someone as amazing as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joel_Spolsky">Joel
Spolsky</a> can experience these
bouts of non-productivity, there is hope for me too.</p>
<p>What really struck a chord is what he writes about the unproductive periods
seeming to correlate somewhat with gloomier moods.</p>
<p>I did have a lot on my mind last week.</p>
<p>Local politics are heating up before the May elections, and so various people,
including acquaintances and friends, are fighting it out on social (and
sometimes mainstream) media.</p>
<p>These fights, apart from their intrinsic violence (ad hominem seems to be in
vogue), often involve race-directed utterances that can catch one quite badly,
making one literally question one&rsquo;s place in society.</p>
<p>Added to this are the regular reminders, including the previously mentioned
load-shedding and numerous corruption scandals, that the current ANC
government is an utterly failed mechanism.</p>
<p>Added to <em>that</em> is at least one other very much related bureaucracy-fueled
personal existential issue that was both burning up mental cycles <em>and</em> stealing
sleep cycles.</p>
<p>Taking stock like this, I can&rsquo;t say anymore that I&rsquo;m surprised that last week
was not my best focus-wise.</p>
<p>You should really go read Spolsky&rsquo;s story, but I&rsquo;ll paraphrase his advice
here.</p>
<p>Everyone has these difficult days, and that&rsquo;s ok.</p>
<p>The important thing is to keep on moving forward a little bit, every day.</p>
<h2 id="yes-and">Yes, and&hellip;</h2>
<p>The extra mental cycles were fortunately not all in vain.</p>
<p>Many of them were dedicated to the question of how exactly I should best act
and react in the current situation.</p>
<p>One of the conclusions I came to is that we have to make peace with the fact
that we&rsquo;re all stuck with each other: You, the person you disagree with most
vehemently, and everyone in between.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re probably not going to be able to change each other that much in the
short term, and especially not if the narrative remains this aggressive.</p>
<p>At best, people at the fringes of the various groupings might come to new
conclusions, and gravitate towards friendlier and more humanist pastures.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, attack / defend mode is the worst mode for causing
positive change.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s also extremely tiring.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know if this is better at the political level, but I do know what my
personal approach is going to be from here on out.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s always some similarity to be found between me and my &ldquo;enemy&rdquo;, for
varying degrees of &ldquo;enemy&rdquo;. (Remember, &ldquo;enemy&rdquo; is just an extreme point on the
friendship spectrum. :)</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re all human. We really do have similar needs. Safety of our families, time
with our friends, a place in the sun for all our fellow humans.</p>
<p>We might differ on how we get there, but it can make a huge difference to
start with all of the needs that we share.</p>
<p>I have resolved to start every every discussion and every related
thought-process with the things that we have in common.</p>
<p>By starting conversations like this, one builds on a platform of similarity,
instead of trying to break down whatever you see before the conversation has
even started.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, and&hellip;&rdquo; is a trick used in improv theater. When it&rsquo;s your turn to take
the dialogue, you start with &ldquo;Yes, and &hellip;&rdquo; and then build on the creativity
of the previous actor. The next actor in line also starts with &ldquo;Yes, and&hellip;&rdquo;,
only further enriching the world of imagination that the previous actors are
constructing on stage.</p>
<p>I think we should &ldquo;Yes, and&hellip;&rdquo; much more in real life.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll start.</p>
<h2 id="what-stands-in-the-way-becomes-the-way">What stands in the way becomes the way.</h2>
<p>The following was recently used <em>in anger</em> (not actual anger, just in actual
application) somewhere in my network:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Our actions may be impeded by [obstacles], but there can be no impeding our
intentions or our dispositions because we can accommodate and adapt. The mind
adapts and converts to its own purposes the obstacle to our acting.</p>
<p>The impediment to action advances action.</p>
<p>What stands in the way becomes the way.</p>
<p>&ndash; Marcus Aurelius</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This could be applied to the story in this post, but one could also go a
little more meta: Initial embarrassment at not even knowing about Marcus
Aurelius&rsquo;s Meditations softly transformed into a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Meditations-New-Translation-Modern-Library-ebook/dp/B000FC1JAI/ref=as_li_ss_tl?s=digital-text&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1452403537&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=meditations+marcus+aurelius&amp;linkCode=sl1&amp;tag=camdezcom-20&amp;linkId=5a0d37b29a42b5e13ed9bc805aff9456">humble button
click</a>, and hopefully soon into a studied book.</p>
<p>Friends, I hope you have a brilliant week. Please remember &ldquo;yes, and&hellip;&rdquo;!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>