<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>D3.js on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/d3.js/</link><description>Recent content in D3.js on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 22:40:37 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/d3.js/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 2 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/15/daily-head-voices-2024-01-08_14/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 22:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/15/daily-head-voices-2024-01-08_14/</guid><description>Inspired by the impressive power (and philosophy) of One Punch Man&amp;rsquo;s Consecutive Normal Punches, I present: A Series of Consecutive Normal Daily Head Voices!
Monday 2024-01-08 First day back at work 😱 &amp;hellip; but the most lovely lunch run (not literally) and chat with colleague E. Single cable life at work is there, but it&amp;rsquo;s complicated: Thunderbolt3 cable from macbook to Thinkpad dock, dock thunderbolt3 to displayport-mini (adapter), displayport-mini to displayport to monitor. Had blood drawn for my quarterly PSA test. (prostate-specific antigen; regular test to check that prostate cancer stays gone) Double Commander (currently at 1.1.8) on macOS is even better than I remember it, and is only a brew install --cask double-commander away. Tuesday 2024-01-09 marimo looks really good! From the github: a reactive notebook for Python. It allows you to rapidly experiment with data and models, code with confidence in your notebook&amp;rsquo;s correctness, and productionize notebooks as pipelines or interactive web apps. I still have to play with it, but it sounds like an Observable for Python. Wednesday 2024-01-10 Shorter weekday run because hip and because sun. Hip only started complaining by the end, a little later than my last short run. 🎉 Tried to find reclining high-back office chairs with footrest in South Africa, starting from: https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/ Spectacular failure! Google Bard, Bing Chat, Perplexity come up with plausible looking links that go to different sites, but nowhere any chairs to be found perplexity is probably the least bad because it more often admits to just not finding any links in SA See e.g. https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c and https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5 Because of work, started to spend some quality time with d3.js again. I hope to be doing some nice interactive visualization soon! Thursday 2024-01-11 PSA is 0.006! 🥳 if you&amp;rsquo;ve ever worked with d3.js, you will have used bl.ocks.org quite often. To my surprise, none of these links work anymore, and instead redirect you to the source gist, where they used to show you the live visualization. I could not find much official news about this sunsetting, but was consoled by the discovery of the open source bl.ocks.org clone at https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/ via https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513 Tune of the evening: RÜFÜS DU SOL - On My Knees (Adriatique Remix) Friday 2024-01-12 Short week-day run, no hip issues! Very nice focused day at home: First half wrapping up a code review. Second half diving back into d3.js. So much old memories I have to unearth. In between hacked in an idle mode for org-roam-similarity, in the process discovered that on this M1 Pro, CPU is much faster (2x) and uses much less RAM than the hardware accelerated PyTorch MPS version Lovely weekend-starter braai with family. Ran into the final sections (and private comments the source org file) of WHV #208 &amp;ndash; besides the nostalgic music bits, really enjoyed reading some of the older journals. Publish or not, strong motivation to keep on writing journals. (now-you is often a very different person than then-you. interesting to keep in touch!) Saturday 2024-01-13 one of the highlights of the day was phone-call by and substantial conversation with bestie PK rest of day quite laid-back with the whole family, which was great thinking a lot about stefanv&amp;rsquo;s week planner instead of day planner, and the implications of this seemingly reduced planning effort (my daily planning is mostly only theoretical) greater family braai (GFB) Sunday 2024-01-14 Overslept a bit, woke up at 9 AM. This has not happened in ages. Slightly longer weekend run at 10 with new running hat and SPF50 on me face and neck. Hip issue did not manifest, am touching wood! Because I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about more visual ways to plan my week, worked on org-roam-canvas, making it a whole lot faster.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Inspired by the impressive power (and philosophy) of One Punch Man&rsquo;s <em>Consecutive Normal Punches</em>, I present: A Series of Consecutive Normal Daily Head Voices!</p>
<h2 id="monday-2024-01-08">Monday 2024-01-08</h2>
<ul>
<li>First day back at work 😱</li>
<li>&hellip; but the most lovely lunch run (not literally) and chat with colleague E.</li>
<li>Single cable life at work is there, but it&rsquo;s complicated: Thunderbolt3 cable from macbook to Thinkpad dock, dock thunderbolt3 to displayport-mini (adapter), displayport-mini to displayport to monitor.</li>
<li>Had blood drawn for my quarterly PSA test. (prostate-specific antigen; regular test to check that prostate cancer stays gone)</li>
<li>Double Commander (currently at 1.1.8) on macOS is even better than I remember it, and is only a <code>brew install --cask double-commander</code> away.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-09">Tuesday 2024-01-09</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/marimo-team/marimo">marimo</a> looks really good! From the github: <em>a reactive notebook for Python. It allows you to rapidly experiment with data and models, code with confidence in your notebook&rsquo;s correctness, and productionize notebooks as pipelines or interactive web apps</em>. I still have to play with it, but it sounds like an <a href="https://observablehq.com/">Observable</a> for Python.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-10">Wednesday 2024-01-10</h2>
<ul>
<li>Shorter weekday run because hip and because sun. Hip only started complaining by the end, a little later than my last short run. 🎉</li>
<li>Tried to find reclining high-back office chairs with footrest in South Africa, starting from: <a href="https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/">https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/</a>
<ul>
<li>Spectacular failure! Google Bard, Bing Chat, Perplexity come up with plausible looking links that go to different sites, but nowhere any chairs to be found</li>
<li>perplexity is probably the least bad because it more often admits to just not finding any links in SA</li>
<li>See e.g. <a href="https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c">https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c</a> and <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5">https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Because of work, started to spend some quality time with <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a> again. I hope to be doing some nice interactive visualization soon!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-11">Thursday 2024-01-11</h2>
<ul>
<li>PSA is 0.006! 🥳</li>
<li>if you&rsquo;ve ever worked with d3.js, you will have used bl.ocks.org quite often. To my surprise, none of these links work anymore, and instead redirect you to the source gist, where they used to show you the live visualization. I could not find much official news about this sunsetting, but was consoled by the discovery of the open source bl.ocks.org clone at <a href="https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/">https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/</a> via <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513">https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513</a></li>
<li>Tune of the evening: <a href="https://youtu.be/IAmmkJZ55vM?si=WjEjD8MLge7sCo0E">RÜFÜS DU SOL - On My Knees (Adriatique Remix)</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-12">Friday 2024-01-12</h2>
<ul>
<li>Short week-day run, no hip issues!</li>
<li>Very nice focused day at home: First half wrapping up a code review. Second half diving back into d3.js. So much old memories I have to unearth.</li>
<li>In between hacked in an idle mode for <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity">org-roam-similarity</a>, in the process discovered that on this M1 Pro, CPU is much faster (2x) and uses much less RAM than the hardware accelerated PyTorch MPS version</li>
<li>Lovely weekend-starter braai with family.</li>
<li>Ran into the final sections (and private comments the source org file) of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/#thank-you-joris">WHV #208</a> &ndash; besides the nostalgic music bits, really enjoyed reading some of the older journals. Publish or not, strong motivation to keep on writing journals. (now-you is often a very different person than then-you. interesting to keep in touch!)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-13">Saturday 2024-01-13</h2>
<ul>
<li>one of the highlights of the day was phone-call by and substantial conversation with bestie PK</li>
<li>rest of day quite laid-back with the whole family, which was great</li>
<li>thinking a lot about stefanv&rsquo;s week planner instead of day planner, and the implications of this <em>seemingly</em> reduced planning effort (my daily planning is mostly only theoretical)</li>
<li>greater family braai (GFB)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-14">Sunday 2024-01-14</h2>
<ul>
<li>Overslept a bit, woke up at 9 AM. This has not happened in ages.</li>
<li>Slightly longer weekend run at 10 with new running hat and SPF50 on me face and neck. Hip issue did not manifest, am touching wood!</li>
<li>Because I&rsquo;ve been thinking about more visual ways to plan my week, worked on <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">org-roam-canvas</a>, making it a <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas/commit/a67ad1ee59c93a2998a0c2975ed7d567e7f02c8d">whole lot faster</a>.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #148: Data stylist.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 07:22:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/</guid><description> Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)
This post covers the week from Monday July 9 to Sunday July 15.
The business part of my week was unfairly dominated by far too much after-work obsessing over programming languages, with which I seem to have an unhealthy (or perhaps not) obsession.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/drakenstein_trail.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/drakenstein_trail-1024x241.jpg"
        
            alt="Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This post covers the week from Monday July 9 to Sunday July 15.</p>
<p>The business part of my week was unfairly dominated by far too much after-work obsessing over programming languages, with which I seem to have an unhealthy (or perhaps not) obsession.</p>
<p>I will externalise some of these thoughts further down in this post.</p>
<p>I’m starting with a weekend / running update, which should be reasonably safe for non-nerds to read. However, after that, the nerd dial will go up to 11 with stuff about tools and programming languages right up to the end of the post.</p>
<p>I would have wanted to use the adjective “face-melting”, but I’m not sure if any intensity of nerdery could ever reach that level.</p>
<p>We can dream.</p>
<h1 id="weekend-running-update">Weekend running update</h1>
<p>Most fortunately the weekend had other plans and supplied us with at least 2.5 parties, the first of which even culminated in a <em>ridiculously</em> fun trail run in the mountains on the winter morning after.</p>
<p>The winter morning sun was just perfect, the company was great, and I had forgotten all forms of performance tracking devices at home.</p>
<p>Readers with bionic eyes might notice the Lunas on my feet.</p>
<p>I have now ran just over 260km in them, but, in a surprise twist to the regular readers of this blog, my biological equipment has still not yet completely adjusted to the new style of locomotion.</p>
<p>The latest victim seems to be one of Tom, Dick and Harry, the tendons running under the medial <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malleolus">malleolus</a> of my left foot, also known as that big knob on your inside ankle. Tom (the primary suspect in this case according to Trail Friend #1 who is knowledgable with regard to these matters, being a running foot surgeon and all), Dick and Harry <a href="https://radiopaedia.org/articles/posterior-ankle-tendons-mnemonic">are also known as the *T*ibialis posterior, flexor *D*igitorum longus and the flexor *H*allucis longus</a>.</p>
<p>They currently have to work extra hard to stabilise my feet while running, because, you know, no shoes.</p>
<p>Because doing this thing was not hard enough already, and because the Lunas are perhaps still a bit too cushiony, and because my friend the Very Flat Cat forgot that I’m very suggestible after 11:00 in the morning when my prefrontal cortex takes the rest of the day off, I am now also the very shy owner of a pair of <a href="https://xeroshoes.com/shop/genesis/genesis-men/">Xero Genesis running sandals</a>:</p>
<p><img src="https://xeroshoes.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/Genesis_Limeade-3-4-770x500.jpg" alt="Image result for xero genesis"></p>
<p>The soles are only 5mm thick, and quite hard, being <a href="https://xeroshoes.com/warranty/">rated for a few thousand miles</a> and all. The upshot of this is that one’s feet have to work even harder than in the Lunas.</p>
<p>My first run in these was amazing: I could feel my feet reacting to every little pebble, and my running style having to adapt even more to the terrain.</p>
<p>However, there was a price to pay for all of that additional terrain feel (and the fact that I took a much longer maiden run than I should have): The next day, the tendons in my feet felt even more (ab)used than usual.</p>
<p>WITH GREAT POWER COMES GREAT RESPONSIBILITY, it seems.</p>
<p>Due to these shoes being so powerful, I have had to resign to introducing Xero running far more gradually than I had initially thought.</p>
<h1 id="vacation-based-thinking-driven-tool-sharpening-aka-the-wvv-2018-data-science-toolboxtm">Vacation-based-thinking-driven tool sharpening aka The WVV 2018 Data Science Toolbox(tm).</h1>
<p>During the <a href="/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/">previously blogged-about</a> Mpumalanga vacation, the lack of alarms, devices, and other work accoutrements, resulted in there being ample time for staring-into-space-grade thinking sessions.</p>
<p>During one of these thinking sessions, I realised that I had somehow neglected my data science toolbox for a while.</p>
<p>At some point a few years back, I was so into ipython notebooks (what has now become jupyter) that I used them as my main work lab notes modality.</p>
<p>However, in the meantime I had fallen slightly out of love with the computational notebook style of data programming, because I had begun to develop doubts about their role in the analysis pipeline.</p>
<p><strong>interlude 1:</strong> <em>jupyter notebooks are nice for initial data exploration, and they’re especially useful for remote computation with embedded graphics. However, that initial momentum of discovery risks devolving into an unwieldy monolith of code snippets, data transformations and experiments. There’s a fine line to be walked between flexible experimentation on the one hand, and version-controlled, time-stamped, permutational and scientific rigour on the other.</em></p>
<p><strong>interlude 2:</strong> <em>I have to apologise for using the term “data science” in a non-comedic context. In spite of the inherent humour, it has turned into a usable blanket term for computational data understanding.</em></p>
<p>Due to my growing doubts in the order of Jupyter, and due to being occupied with less traditionally data sciencey work projects, I had unfortunately let my data science toolbox gather perhaps a bit too much dust.</p>
<p>Slightly more worrying than falling out of love with the Jupyter Notebooks (I still like them, I’m just not that madly in love anymore), was the more specific issue that I’d even let the datavis parts get a bit dusty.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Although I should probably write a more complete post about this, here is the list of ingredients of the official <em><strong>2018 WHV Data Science Toolbox(tm)</strong></em>:</p>
<h2 id="programming-language-and-library-ecosystem-python">Programming language and library ecosystem: Python.</h2>
<p>This language, in spite of its shortcomings, <em>dominates</em> the data science / machine learning world thanks to its STELLAR ecosystem.</p>
<p>numpy, pandas, scipy, scikit-*, tensorflow, pytorch, keras, cython… this snowball has turned into a pretty sizeable planet.</p>
<p>For this reason, it would be hard to justify any other choice for data science.</p>
<p>However, since I’ve been seeing more of Lisp and the rest of the ever-expanding programming language landscape, I can see (Python’s shortcomings as a programming language) clearly now.</p>
<p>In terms of interactive programming, Python beats the majority of practical programming languages, with Common Lisp being one notable exception.</p>
<p>However, it’s not functional enough, which engenders unnecessarily imperative, side-effecting code.  More specifically, it’s not expression-oriented.</p>
<p>More about this slightly further down. Maybe.</p>
<h2 id="datavis-anything-as-long-as-its-vega-or-vega-lite">Datavis: Anything, as long as it’s Vega or Vega-Lite.</h2>
<p>I spent a few years of my life wrangling <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a>, down to INNARD-LEVEL.</p>
<p>Mike Bostock’s idea of <a href="https://bost.ocks.org/mike/join/">data-element-joins</a> is genius, and internalising it was intellectually satisfying.</p>
<p>I thought that these d3 skillz would serve me well for decades (that’s WEEKS in javascript-time), but it turns out that there’s a new, even smarter kid in town.</p>
<p>(if it’s any consolation, the new kid can be considered the grand-child of d3.js.)</p>
<p><a href="https://vega.github.io/">vega and vega-lite</a> are so-called visualization grammars, or visualization DSLs (domain specific languages).</p>
<p>The upshot is that one codes up a chart, or a whole set of linked charts and their interactive behaviour, using a language that was designed for this purpose.</p>
<p>This chart code can be easily shared, or converted into interactive visual representations that can be embedded in applications, online or in print quality documents.</p>
<p>Genius!</p>
<p>With <a href="https://altair-viz.github.io/">Altair</a>, you can even send your pandas dataframes to vega and vega-lite charts all from the comfort of your slightly defective Python armchair.</p>
<h2 id="development-environment-pycharm">Development Environment: PyCharm.</h2>
<p>You knew it was not going to be Jupyter Notebooks, but you probably expected it to be <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tag/emacs/">Emacs</a>.</p>
<p>Well it’s not. Surprise!</p>
<p>The remote interpreter support in PyCharm enables me to connect to a Python virtual environment anywhere on the planet, which I often do.</p>
<p>The JetBrains wizards have optimised the remote communication of code intelligence, so completion, documentation and general code understanding is almost indistinguishable from that on a completely local project.</p>
<p>Being able to step through a <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/12/08/variational-autoencoder-in-pytorch-commented-and-annotated/"><em>remote</em> PyTorch neural network training iteration with the PyCharm debugger</a> or any other remote Python algorithmics is insightful.</p>
<p>Two notable drawbacks are visualization and long-running jobs.</p>
<p>For the long-running jobs I do tend to use Jupyter Notebooks or when at all possible <a href="https://mosh.org/">mosh</a>, which is amazing. However, because the primary modality is not the notebook, my code is versioned and organised into separate libraries which I can call into from notebook or mosh.</p>
<p>For visualization, it’s either connecting to the altair chart server via SSH pipe, dumping the chart to the unison-synced project, and/or a Jupyter Notebook.</p>
<h2 id="the-rest">The rest.</h2>
<p>Of course you use Postgres on an SSD for your data, and of course you know enough SQL to make short work of most of the heavy-weight transformations often required at the start your data crunching pipeline.</p>
<p>For all of my lab notes, reports, books, papers and blog posts, I use <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tag/orgmode/">Emacs Org mode</a>.</p>
<p>LaTeX math with live preview, live code snippets, SVG graphics, bibtex references, export to anything. This is one of the best ways to document your science.</p>
<h1 id="programming-language-addiction-update">Programming language addiction update.</h1>
<p>I spend far too much obsessing over programming languages, old and new.</p>
<p>For the past two weeks, I wasted even more precious time than usual reading up about programming languages.</p>
<p>Because I would really like to spend more of my time on other, perhaps more valuable activities, I’ve been trying to better define what it is I’m actually looking for.</p>
<p>Of course there is no single best programming language, but a whole set of good languages that map in intricate ways to different problem domains.</p>
<p>In spite of this, I have been pining for a language with, in order of importance:</p>
<ol>
<li>A Functional Programming DNA, with which I’m referring to a) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expression-oriented_programming_language">expression-orientedness</a>, b) a preference for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pure_function">pure functions</a>, and at a higher level, c) the modelling of reality as more or less explicit dataflows.</li>
<li>Interactive programming, with Common Lisp being the textbook example of this.</li>
<li>Great tooling and IDEs, meaning first-class support by something from JetBrains, Microsoft or Emacs.</li>
<li>Great concurrency and parallelism stories.</li>
<li>A great library ecosystem.</li>
<li>Modest memory use.</li>
</ol>
<p>Having just explicitly written this down for the first time (!! – it was consuming so much glucose just being kept amorphously swirling around in my brain) I can now mentally map some of my most recent language dalliances to these points.</p>
<h2 id="go">go</h2>
<p>This language is far too simple for my taste, but probably really great for teams.</p>
<p>I did recently take a more serious look when <a href="https://tutorials.botsfloor.com/develop-your-own-telegram-bot-with-golang-and-tbot-de726883b83c">setting up a telegram bot using tbot</a> and being amazed at how simple it was building web services like these using goroutines and channels.</p>
<p>Go satisfies points 3 to 6 from the list above. Makes sense that I decided to file this experiment away under “check when you need to put a webservice together REALLY QUICKLY”.</p>
<h2 id="rust">rust</h2>
<p>When I saw up that rust, surprisingly, is an expression-oriented language, I flew through the O’Reilly Programming Rust book I had bought previously as part of a bundle.</p>
<p>Evaluating rust by the list above, we award it a fractional 1 because expression-oriented, 3 due to jetbrains plugin amongst others, 4(ish) – great memory safety, but compared to clojure, concurrency and parallelism stories still have much room to grow, a solid 5 thanks to cargo and a very strong 6.</p>
<p>I filed this one away under “re-evaluate whenever you reach for your trusty C++”. (also, <a href="https://github.com/actix/actix-web">actix-web</a> looks amazing for super high performance microservices.)</p>
<h2 id="f">f#</h2>
<p>You didn’t see this one coming, did you?</p>
<p>Very strong 1 to 5 and a solid 6.</p>
<p>WAT?!</p>
<p>I’m currently working my way through <a href="https://pragprog.com/book/swdddf/domain-modeling-made-functional">Domain Modeling Made Functional</a> by Scott Wlaschin, who is also the author of the brilliant <a href="https://fsharpforfunandprofit.com/">f# for fun and profit</a> website.</p>
<p>In addition to f# hitting all 6 of my 2018 PL-requirements above, I’m slowly starting to see the advantages of having a real type system under the hood.</p>
<p>f# is a member of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ML_(programming_language)">ML-family</a> of functional languages, which have their origin in Lisp (some very naughty person removed all of the lovely parentheses I’m afraid…).</p>
<p>I hope that at some point I’ll have the opportunity to use f# in anger, at which point I’ll be able to report more concretely as to its suitability.</p>
<h1 id="the-end">The End</h1>
<p>Let me know in the comments what you think about any of this, or anything else.</p>
<p>I hope to meet you again in a few days, here or elsewhere.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #102: High on life.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/20/weekly-head-voices-102-high-on-life/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 07:21:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/20/weekly-head-voices-102-high-on-life/</guid><description>The week of Monday January 11 to Sunday January 17, 2016 got off to a brilliant start with a business lunch at Bodega, a restaurant that finds itself on the Dornier Wine Estate. The view looked something like this:
… and the company was suitably awesome. (This is not the first time that Bodega makes its appearance on this blog, or in the blog-free suburbs of my social calendar. The company might be different every time, but so far its level of awesomeness has been quite consistent.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The week of Monday January 11 to Sunday January 17, 2016 got off to a brilliant start with a <em>business</em> lunch at <a href="http://www.dornier.co.za/restaurant">Bodega</a>, a restaurant that finds itself on the Dornier Wine Estate. The view looked something like this:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/view_from_bodega.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/view_from_bodega-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>… and the company was suitably awesome. (This is not the first time that Bodega makes its appearance on this blog, or in the blog-free suburbs of my social calendar. The company might be different every time, but so far its level of awesomeness has been <em>quite</em> consistent.)</p>
<p>The rest of the (work) week was consumed by extreme nerdery, which is of course the way I love it. Besides more GPU shader fine-tuning (at least once I exclaimed on the <a href="http://www.stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> HipChat, hopefully soon the Stone Three <a href="http://www.mattermost.org/">Mattermost</a>,  <em>WITNESS THE POWER OF MATH!</em>, before showing a rendering that was marginally better than the one where the POWER OF MATH had not yet been invoked a sufficient number of times), there was Javascript, <a href="http://d3js.org/">d3.js</a> (d3 is another fantastic example of what you can do with vectorised thinking and computation) and Python.</p>
<p>In break time I finally took a closer look at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C%2B%2B14">C++14</a> and beyond and came away super impressed. There’s a blog post in the pipeline on generic lambda expressions, because I think they’re brilliant. I don’t know why I love different programming languages so much, but I do.</p>
<p>On Saturday,  I got really high with one of my besties, a superb gentleman who also goes by the name of A Very Flat Cat. We reached this altered state by the old-fashioned but extremely reliable (and cheap!) method of physically increasing our altitude via ambulation up the west peak of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helderberg">Helderberg</a>. The walk (a few hours in 35 degrees Celsius…) was exhilarating, and the view from the top awe-inspiring. Check it (click for high-res):</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/20160116_100314-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/20160116_100314-PANO-1024x137.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I’ve often wondered about the effect of one’s surroundings on one’s mindfulness. This was one of those cases where mother nature, without asking for permission or anything like that, simply brute-forced the <em>being</em> switch with her astonishing beauty. Very grateful I was.</p>
<p>Have a great week friends, see you on the other side!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>