<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Jack Black on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/jack-black/</link><description>Recent content in Jack Black on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 12:48:57 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/jack-black/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #112: Emergency Smörgåsbord.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 12:48:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/</guid><description>(This blog post documents snippets of time taken from the period starting on Monday August 15 and ending on Tuesday November 8, 2016.)
My longing simply became too great.
For an epic few days in August, I found myself in The Netherlands (my other home) mixing business and pleasure like a boss. Thank you besties, my cup has not stopped running over. Photo by Bestie DJ Fiasco.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This blog post documents snippets of time taken from the period starting on Monday August 15 and ending on Tuesday November 8, 2016.)</em></p>
<p>My longing simply became too great.</p>
<p>For an epic few days in August, I found myself in The Netherlands (my other home) mixing business and pleasure like a boss. Thank you besties, my cup has not stopped running over.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/IMG-20160827-WA0010.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/IMG-20160827-WA0010-1024x576.jpg"
        
            alt="Photo by Bestie DJ Fiasco."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Photo by Bestie DJ Fiasco.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Shortly after returning from NL, my year counter ticked over one more time.</p>
<p>I have become indeed <em>quite</em> middle-aged.</p>
<p>On the flip side, I am content with where I find myself in space-time, both physically and meta-physically. Although I seem to think more slowly, I do seem to have become slightly better at retrospection, introspection and at <a href="/2016/05/22/weekly-head-voices-107-balance/">seeing the bigger picture</a>.</p>
<p>As an additional consolation, it seems that I am in the best physical condition I have been for years due to a recent(ish) and surprising discovery of a latent jogging addiction. I am terrible at the action itself, but I really enjoy being repeatedly terrible at it.</p>
<p>On the topic of consolation, I tasted (at least) three new local craft beers, the experience of which I would like to share with you.</p>
<div class="gallery galleryid-2538 gallery-columns-3 gallery-size-thumbnail" data-carousel-extra='{"blog_id":1,"permalink":"https:\/\/cpbotha.net\/2016\/11\/12\/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord\/"}' id="gallery-3">
<figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon portrait">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651.jpg" title=""><img alt="" aria-describedby="gallery-3-2541" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" data-attachment-id="2541" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"2.4","credit":"","camera":"LG-D855","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1476385610","copyright":"","focal_length":"3.97","iso":"350","shutter_speed":"0.071428571428571","title":"","orientation":"1"}' data-image-title="20161013_190651" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651-576x1024.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651-169x300.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651.jpg" data-orig-size="1280,2276" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/20161013_190651/" height="150" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651-150x150.jpg" width="150"/></a>
</div><figcaption class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-3-2541"> Striped Horse Pils. Deserving of the awards it won in 2015 and 2016! </figcaption></figure><figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon portrait">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835.jpg" title=""><img alt="" aria-describedby="gallery-3-2543" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" data-attachment-id="2543" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":"","orientation":"0"}' data-image-title="20161029_121835" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835-452x1024.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835-132x300.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835.jpg" data-orig-size="934,2115" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/20161029_121835/" height="150" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835-150x150.jpg" width="150"/></a>
</div><figcaption class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-3-2543"> Jack Black Atlantic Weiss: a 9.8 on the Celis White scale! </figcaption></figure><figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon landscape">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings.jpg" title=""><img alt="" aria-describedby="gallery-3-2545" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" data-attachment-id="2545" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":"","orientation":"0"}' data-image-title="mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings-1024x921.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings-300x270.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings.jpg" data-orig-size="2601,2340" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings/" height="150" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings-150x150.jpg" width="150"/></a>
</div><figcaption class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-3-2545"> Mountain Weiss is a lovely white beer that gives me very mixed feelings, because reasons. </figcaption></figure>
</div>
<p>The Striped Horse Pils won gold at the 2015 and <a href="http://brewmistress.co.za/winners-of-the-2016-south-african-national-beer-trophy/">2016 National Beer Trophy</a>. More importantly, it also won the WHV-two-voices-cheering-loudly award, because it’s a full-bodied hoppy beer.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.jackblackbeer.com/#atlantic-weiss">Jack Black Atlantic Weiss</a> gets a whopping 9.8 on <a href="/2016/08/15/weekly-head-voices-111-a-swift-hack/">my famous Celis White scale</a>. This is the lighter, fresher version of the Bone Crusher that we’ve all been waiting for. Now you just have to cross your fingers that more suppliers will get this. At this moment, it’s still quite tricky to track down.</p>
<p>On a subsequent failed mission to acquire more Atlantic Weiss, I ran into the Newlands Spring Brewing Company’s <em>Mountain Weiss</em>. As I was enjoying this light white beer (THE SUMMER IS COMING) something was tugging at the edge of my memory…</p>
<p>As I turned the bottle around, my worst suspicions were confirmed: Newlands Spring Brewing Company belongs to South African Breweries (SAB), the behemoth beer-brewing international mega-corp. They’ve been trying to get into the craft beer market, a sector traditionally belonging to often entrepreneurial and even family-run small enterprises, and this was their sneaky attempt.</p>
<p>In spite of its lovely taste, I do prefer spending my craft beer budget on mom-and-pop setups. Besides the truly tasty beer, I really like that craft beer has democratised a traditionally closed (by SAB!) area of commerce, and so would prefer putting my money there.</p>
<p>(That is not to say that I don’t buy SAB’s non-craft beers. A man gets thirsty!)</p>
<p>The following marvelous animation <a href="https://twitter.com/WorldAndScience/status/795747812424216576">popped up in my twitter timeline</a>:</p>
<div class="wp-video" style="width: 718px;">
<!--[if lt IE 9]><![endif]--><video class="wp-video-shortcode" controls="controls" height="522" id="video-2538-1" preload="metadata" width="718"><source src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/stable_milkyway_earth_rotation.mp4?_=1" type="video/mp4"/>
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/stable_milkyway_earth_rotation.mp4">https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/stable_milkyway_earth_rotation.mp4</a></video>
</div>
<p>Someone configured their camera stabilisation to lock on to the milky way in this National Geographic timelapse video. The result of this simple experiment is that you can clearly see the rotation of the Earth.</p>
<p>It’s really amazing what you can achieve by simply changing your perspective.</p>
<p>In Other Much More Important News, one of my last academic children <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/defended-phd-thesis-virtual-surgical-pelvis-anatomy-visualization-education-surgical-planning/">got doctorified on October 31</a>. I left academia for entirely non-children-related reasons (the children were the best part of academia!) <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/my-phd-supervisor-left-me/">shortly after she started with her doctorate</a>, hence the significance of this.</p>
<p>Henceforth, everyone has to add an extra DOCTOR to her already impressive title, namely <a href="https://twitter.com/eagereyes/status/793107701400162305">Evil Empress of the SciVis Galaxy</a>. Doctor Evil Empress of the SciVis Galaxy will continue her reign from her new (iron?) throne in the Visualization Group at the University of Bergen, Norway.</p>
<p>Don’t worry puny subjects, you are in good hands!</p>
<p>I read somewhere that good stories tend to make circles (could anyone help me out with a good reference?), so let me end this thing with a brilliantly coloured but slightly more lonesome sunset:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161102_192034.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161102_192034-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Have fun peeps, I hope to see you soon!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #105: There will be tears.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/15/weekly-head-voices-105/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 20:04:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/15/weekly-head-voices-105/</guid><description>Congratulations, you have successfully completed the week of Monday February 8 to Sunday February 14, 2016!
About 4 seconds after posting previous edition WHV #104 to Facebook with the “When you’re a vegan and haven’t told anyone in 10 minutes” meme image included, friend Ivo T. zinged me with this reply:
So much truth. I have been put back in my place. Sorry vegans. Sorry MBA students. Not sorry Ayn Randers.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Congratulations, you have successfully completed the week of Monday February 8 to Sunday February 14, 2016!</p>
<p>About 4 seconds after posting previous edition <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/08/weekly-head-voices-104-let-me-update-you/">WHV #104</a> to Facebook with the “When you’re a vegan and haven’t told anyone in 10 minutes” meme image included, friend Ivo T. zinged me with this reply:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/12651073_10153234132252035_804640390912092906_n.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/12651073_10153234132252035_804640390912092906_n.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>So much truth. I have been put back in my place. Sorry vegans. Sorry MBA students. Not sorry Ayn Randers.</p>
<p>This is currently my favourite lager ever (at least until next week):</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/jack_black_lager.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/jack_black_lager-576x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>It is indeed a craft beer. If we’ve ever chatted more than 10 minutes in the past (or in the future), you’ll know everything about my braai, and you probably also know that I find craft beer to be one of the greatest inventions ever, along with fire, and the internet.</p>
<p>Here’s a another beer which I recently had the pleasure of enjoying, at a secret networking meeting (yes, we have secret meetings where we in fact do manage a large number of aspects of your daily life, and where we also orchestrate it so you’ll never suspect that we are behind everything, subtly manipulating reality) where, when the beer arrived at the table, everyone who looked vaguely hipster-like claimed vocally not in fact to be even remotely hipster-like:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/tears_of_the_hipster.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/tears_of_the_hipster-576x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>META-HIPSTER CRAFT BEER! At first I was confused, but then I realised it was just another case of <strong>WHAT A TIME TO BE ALIVE!</strong></p>
<p>(By the way, I stripped the EXIF GPS data from the Jack Black photo, because privacy, but I left it hidden in the tears of the hipster. First one who tells me in the comments where the secret meeting was held gets a free craft beer!)</p>
<p><em>Nerd tip of the week</em>: It’s somehow not prominent enough on their site, but GitLab, the open source GitHub alternative, also <a href="https://about.gitlab.com/gitlab-com/">offer free hosting of an unlimited number of private repositories with an unlimited number of private collaborators</a>. In other words, if you’re on a budget, you can host your commercial and proprietary project git repositories (and bug tracking and wikis) there at <em>no cost</em>. This is cheaper than github ($7 for the smallest subscription for 5 private repos) and better than bitbucket (private repos for free, but if you have more than 5 team members you have to pay). I pay quite gladly for the online services I use, but in this particular case, such a level of free is hard not to like.</p>
<p><em>Nerd tip #2 of the week:</em> The <a href="http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/">Clang static C++ analyser</a> is brilliant. If you program in C++, and you need to up your game, integrating this into your workflow is a solid step in the right direction. I’ve been using this via the <a href="http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/scan-build.html">scan-build method</a>. Let me know in the comments if you’d like to know more about this!</p>
<p>After some <a href="http://www.pcservices.co.za/">professional</a> ethernet cabling down to the sort-of basement of our new house, I have checked off another item from my non-existent bucket list: <em>We now have a lab at our house.</em> So far there are computers, all kinds of DIY supplies and art stuff for the genetic offspring units, and all of this to <em>create</em>. I spent some of the best times of my life in labs of some sort of another. It’s really great bringing some of that back home to my clan.</p>
<p>Have a great week kids, see you on the other side!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #97: Beerbow.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/10/weekly-head-voices-97-beerbow/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 19:59:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/10/weekly-head-voices-97-beerbow/</guid><description>This, the ninety seventh edition of the WHV, looks back at the week of Monday August 3 to Sunday August 9, 2015.
John Scalzi (famous and successful SciFi author) describes how he works in this post on lifehacker. What I found really interesting was that when he’s working on a book or other project, he switches off the internet between 8 and noon. I just discovered that Four Tet’s mom is South African-born. This week my work time was divided between having to analyse someone else’s quite complex application and bits of their domain in order to implement new features on the one hand, and designing a new relational data representation for workflow provenance on the other. I perceived both of these activities as challenging, and hence (I think) my work week as very satisfying. After the whole day programming at work, I often relax at home in the evenings by programming some more. I’ve noticed that the after-dinner beer (or two) make architectural and design-level work more challenging. On the topic of programming for relaxation, this weekend I had the feeling that my longest-running side-project was finally getting off the ground, at least technically. When it grows up, it really wants to be a non-linear graphical personal knowledge management tool – the crazy and colourful glue linking together all of your digital stuff. On the topic of beer, I made you a photo of my weekend craft beer (the Skeleton Coast IPA by Jack Black) with a rainbow in the background. I call it a beerbow: Have a great week everyone!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the ninety seventh edition of the WHV, looks back at the week of Monday August 3 to Sunday August 9, 2015.</p>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<img alt="Brainbow_(Lichtman_2008).jpg" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/58/Brainbow_(Lichtman_2008).jpg"/>
</p>
</div>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Scalzi">John Scalzi</a> (famous and successful SciFi author) describes how he works in <a href="http://lifehacker.com/im-john-scalzi-and-this-is-how-i-work-1720935145">this post on lifehacker</a>. What I found really interesting was that when he’s working on a book or other project, he switches off the internet between 8 and noon.
  </li>
<li>
    I just discovered that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Tet">Four Tet’s</a> mom is South African-born.
  </li>
<li>
    This week my work time was divided between having to analyse someone else’s quite complex application and bits of their domain in order to implement new features on the one hand, and designing a new relational data representation for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provenance#Data_provenance">workflow provenance</a> on the other. I perceived both of these activities as challenging, and hence (I think) my work week as very satisfying.
  </li>
<li>
    After the whole day programming at work, I often relax at home in the evenings by programming some more. I’ve noticed that the after-dinner beer (or two) make architectural and design-level work more challenging.
  </li>
<li>
    On the topic of programming for relaxation, this weekend I had the feeling that my longest-running side-project was finally getting off the ground, at least technically. When it grows up, it really wants to be a non-linear graphical personal knowledge management tool – the crazy and colourful glue linking together all of your digital stuff.
  </li>
<li>
    On the topic of beer, I made you a photo of my weekend craft beer (the <a href="http://www.jackblackbeer.com/#skeleton-coast">Skeleton Coast IPA by Jack Black</a>) <i>with a rainbow in the background</i>. I call it a <b>beerbow</b>:
  </li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-skeleton_coast_ipa_rainbow.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-skeleton_coast_ipa_rainbow.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Have a great week everyone!</p>
<p>P.S. I could not help adding that <em>beerbow</em> was partly inspired by the <em>brainbow</em>, a technique for making individual neurons (brain cells!) fluoresce with different colours. This technique has played a major role in the study of neural connections in the brain (this study is also called <em>connectomics</em>). Read more about the technique in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brainbow">its wikipedia article</a>, and see the pretty examples I have now added to the top of this post!</p>
<p>P.P.S. I just saw that a book chapter called <em>Visualization in Connectomics</em> that we put <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1206.1428">on arxiv (FREE fulltext!!)</a> whilst waiting for the rest of the book to happen, did eventually get <a href="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-1-4471-6497-5_21">published by Springer</a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>A blacksmith and a lumberjack walk into a bar</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/18/a-blacksmith-and-a-lumberjack-walk-into-a-bar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 17:21:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/18/a-blacksmith-and-a-lumberjack-walk-into-a-bar/</guid><description>Jack Black brewery’s Lumberjack is an amber ale craft brewed in Cape Town. As bottle designs go, this one is pretty metal:
Amongst a number of impressive-sounding statements, the back of the bottle concludes with:
Lumberjack has a sturdy malt driven backbone packed with loads of roasted malt. Huge hop additions intensify the piney-citrus aromas of this full flavoured ale. A beer for the brave.
After reading that, who does not want to drink this beer for the brave?! Based on extensive testing, I can report that this is indeed a full-bodied beer that deserves and rewards your full attention.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Jack Black brewery’s Lumberjack is an amber ale craft brewed in Cape Town. As bottle designs go, this one is pretty <em>metal</em>:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/lumberjack_front.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/lumberjack_front-576x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Amongst a number of impressive-sounding statements, the back of  the bottle concludes with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Lumberjack has a sturdy malt driven backbone packed with loads of roasted malt. Huge hop additions intensify the piney-citrus aromas of this full flavoured ale. A beer for the brave.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>After reading that, who does <em>not</em> want to drink this <strong>beer for the brave</strong>?! Based on extensive testing, I can report that this is indeed a full-bodied beer that deserves and rewards your full attention.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://blacksmithskitchen.co.za/">Blacksmith’s Kitchen</a> is a vineyard restaurant in Paarl. It looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/blacksmiths_kitchen.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/blacksmiths_kitchen-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The views from the outside tables are quite beautiful:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/blacksmiths_kitchen_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/blacksmiths_kitchen_view-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Weather permitting (which is very often in Paarl), this kitchen is absolutely worth a visit.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>