<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>visualisation on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/visualisation/</link><description>Recent content in visualisation on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2011 21:29:09 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/visualisation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>You have beautiful ize. [Weekly Head Voices #62]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/19/you-have-beautiful-ize-weekly-head-voices-62/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2011 21:29:09 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/19/you-have-beautiful-ize-weekly-head-voices-62/</guid><description> I completely lack the genes that usually cause human males to have a thing for cars, but I do love Top Gear. This trailer for a fictional 60s detective show, made by Jeremy Clarkson, James May and Richard Hammond, encapsulates many of the reasons why:
Moustaches, guns, girls, cars and Hammond karate-chopping the porter at Playboy Club London for absolutely no reason whatsoever at 41 seconds can be nothing but 100% pure AWESOME.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I completely lack the genes that usually cause human males to have a thing for cars, but I do love Top Gear. This trailer for a fictional 60s detective show, made by Jeremy Clarkson, James May and Richard Hammond, encapsulates many of the reasons why:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qLp4FhDAfQk?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Moustaches, guns, girls, cars and Hammond karate-chopping the porter at Playboy Club London for absolutely no reason whatsoever at 41 seconds can be nothing but 100% pure AWESOME.</p>
<p>It’s crazily busy at the moment, for a large part due to the extra load of having to teach and revamp, AT THE SAME TIME, the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4086" title="TU Delt DataVis course">TU Delft’s postgraduate Data Visualization course</a>. I’ve chucked out the written exam and the structured lab work, and exchanged it for paper reading, class discussion and four independent projects, inspired by positive experience with my <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4307" title="TU Delft postgraduate MedVis course">Medical Visualization Ninja Training Course</a> (third year in the running, Ninjas all over the place!), the <a href="/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/" title="infovis in stellenbosch">postgraduate InfoVis course I gave at Stellenbosch</a> and of course the teaching materials of esteemed colleagues at UBC, Harvard, Berkeley and Stanford. With a bit of luck, we will soon deliver a whole class of new-style DataVis Ninjas.</p>
<p>At a recent conference, I ran into an erudite half-British colleague from the far North, who in a few minutes almost managed to turn my world into rubble. You see, I’ve always proudly promoted the use of the -ise forms of certain words, such as visualise, realise, colonise and so forth, these being examples of British English. (Obviously, I adapt when American English is required.)</p>
<p>It turns out that, as is the case with life in general, it’s unfortunately not as simple as that.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_and_British_English_spelling_differences#-ise.2C_-ize_.28-isation.2C_-ization.29" title="wikipedia article on britsh vs english spelling">It turns out</a> that many of the -ise words are originally from the Greek or the Latin with “-ize” endings, and therefore the Oxford spelling prefers their use, although it accepts the “-ise” forms as well. On the other hand, the Cambridge University Press, as well as the mainstream media and most of the public in Britain and the former colonies, has a strong preference for the “-ise” forms. Certain other words like for example advertise, advise and surprise always take the “-ise” form in British English.</p>
<p>So now I’m faced with this conundrum. It would otherwise not have been such an issue, but the words “visualise” and “visualisation” come up quite often during my work day. Sticking to “-ise” is easier and still correct when in British English mode, but “-ize” for those few words of Greek  and Latin origin could perhaps be considered more correct, and has the great advantage of allowing me to standardise on “visualize” as the canonical form of that important term. However, then I would run the risk of confusing the “-ize” and the true “-ise” words in Oxford English, potentially leading to painful embarrassment at the many cocktail parties that I frequent.</p>
<p>So you see, the Universe is just full of mysteries. Another mystery that has plagued humankind for decades, is what would happen if Stephen Hawking and Albert Einstein got involved in a rap battle. Well humankind, wonder no more:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zn7-fVtT16k?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Ok kids, thank you for tuning in again. Have a great week, I hope to see you again soon!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>EuroVis 2011</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/26/eurovis-2011/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2011 11:25:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/26/eurovis-2011/</guid><description> I’ve written before about EuroVis, the most important European scientific conference on visualisation. In 2009, it took place in Berlin, in 2010 it was in Bordeaux, and, an a surprise non-twist of alliteration, the 2011 edition was held in Bergen, Norway. With 216 attendees and a practically perfect organization, this year’s edition has been described as the biggest and the best EuroVis ever. In a bid to save some time (I still owe you a mega-edition of the Weekly (actually Monthly) Head Voices), I’m going to give my biased account in bullet-list form:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve written before about EuroVis, the most important European scientific conference on visualisation. In <a href="/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/" title="blog post on eurovis 2009">2009, it took place in Berlin</a>, in <a href="/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/" title="blog coverage of eurovis 2010">2010 it was in Bordeaux</a>, and, an a surprise non-twist of alliteration, the <strong>2011 edition was held in Bergen, Norway.</strong> With 216 attendees and a practically perfect organization, this year’s edition has been described as the biggest and the best EuroVis ever. In a bid to save some time (I still owe you a mega-edition of the Weekly (actually Monthly) Head Voices), I’m going to give my biased account in bullet-list form:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>On Tuesday evening, we were welcomed by the very charismatic vice mayor of Bergen in the Tårnsalen of the Lysverket building of the Bergen Art Museum. It seems the photo I took of the inside of the art deco tower, built in 1938, is quite a popular shot. The food was divine, thank you very much.

  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/tarnsalen.jpg">
      <img
          
              
              src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/tarnsalen-1024x612.jpg"
          
              alt="Art Deco tower from the inside in the Tårnsalen, Lysverket."/> </a><figcaption>
              <p>Art Deco tower from the inside in the Tårnsalen, Lysverket.</p>
          </figcaption>
  </figure>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The next morning, during the conference opening, the following Bergen (rainiest city in Europe) joke was told: <em>A visitor asks a local boy in exasperation “Does it rain like this all the time?” and the little boy answers “I don’t know, I’m only 12 years old!”</em>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/speakers.php#mcCloud" title="conference keynote page">conference keynote</a> was given by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_McCloud" title="Wikipedia page on Scott McCloud">Scott McCloud</a>, American cartoonist and comic theorist, on aspects of visual communication. This was most probably the best presentation I’ve ever had the privilege of experiencing. Besides brilliant oratorship, his slides are somehow more a visual stream of consciousness affair than discrete quanta of information. When I grow up, I’m going to present like that.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As per usual, I get to award the <strong>Weekly Head Voices Best Paper awards</strong>, and they go to the following papers:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.mevis-research.de/~crieder/pdf/EuroVis2011_paper175.pdf" title="fulltext of Rieder 2011 eurovis paper">A Shader Framework for Rapid Prototyping of GPU-Based Volume Rendering</a> by Christian Rieder, Stephan Palmer, Florian Link and Horst K. Hahn. Rieder and his colleagues have constructed a full GPU-based volume rendering pipeline in MeVisLab of which the various shader based components are modifiable at runtime. This means that you can prototype your GPU-based volume rendering ideas in no time flat!</li>
<li><a href="http://www.ii.uib.no/vis/publications/publication/2011/lampe11curveDensity" title="curve density estimates website">Curve Density Estimates</a> by Ove Daae Lampe and Helwig Hauser. Back to basics and really important work on the effective visualisation of complex curves at any resolution, with smooth scaling between levels.</li>
<li><a href="http://vgl.serc.iisc.ernet.in/pdf/pub/MultifieldComparisonMeasureEUROVIS2011.pdf" title="fulltext gradient-based comparison metric paper">A Gradient-Based Comparison Measure for Visual Analysis of Multifield Data</a> by Suthambhara Nagaraj, Vijay Natarajan and Ravi S. Nanjundiah. Another back-to-basics paper in which the authors show how to find the agreement between hundreds of scalar fields and visualise this agreement, thus enabling comparison.</li>
</ul>
<p>The slightly less prestigious EuroVis 2011 Best Paper awards went to:</p>
<ol>
<li>Uncertainty-Aware Exploration of Continuous Parameter Spaces Using Multivariate Prediction  by Wolfgang Berger, Harald Piringer, Peter Filzmoser, Eduard Gröller. I was unfortunately in the other session, but was told by numerous colleagues that this was indeed an award-winning presentation as well.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.sci.utah.edu/publications/anderson11/Anderson_eurovis2011.pdf" title="fulltext of Anderson's paper">A User Study of Visualization Effectiveness Using EEG and Cognitive Load</a> by Erik Anderson, Kristin Potter, Laura Matzen, Jason Shepherd, Gilbert Preston, Claudio Silva. This was presented in the Evaluation session which I had the privilege of chairing. It is indeed a very compelling idea to measure the effectiveness of a visualisation through cognitive load and this paper documents the first very important steps in this direction.</li>
<li>A Gradient-Based Comparison Measure for Visual Analysis of Multifield Data by Suthambhara Nagaraj, Vijay Natarajan and Ravi S. Nanjundiah. This was also amongst the more prestigious WHV best paper award winners, see above!</li>
</ol>
<p>The rest of the conference featured the following bullets:</p>
<ul>
<li>During the social event on Thursday evening, Frits Post (my boss), was elevated to the rank of Eurographics Honorary Fellow, recognizing his service to and standing in the visualisation community. Including this newest addition, there are only <a href="http://www.eg.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=90&amp;Itemid=52" title="list of EG honorary fellows">five (5!) EG Honorary Fellows</a> in the world today. I am very proud!</li>
<li>During the first session of the morning after the social event, I had the exquisite privilege of presenting the work of my Brazilian colleagues: <a href="http://www.lcad.icmc.usp.br/~nonato/pubs/plp.pdf" title="fulltext PLP paper">Piecewise Laplacian-based Projection for Interactive Data Exploration and Organization</a> by Fernando V. Paulovich, Danilo M. Eler, Jorge Poco, Charl P. Botha, Rosane Minghim, Luis G. Nonato. I really do like presenting at events like these, and it’s been a while. Do read and cite the paper, it documents a practical way of reducing any set of high-dimensional data points to the visual space, and enabling interaction with those points on the visual space!</li>
<li>The <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/speakers.php#groller" title="capstone page">capstone of the conference</a> was presented by the legendary Prof. E. Gröller, also known by the whole community as <em>Meister</em>. In typical style, the title of his talk was only announced during the talk itself. The title was <em>The Haunted Swamps of Heuristics</em>. In this philosophical and visionary contribution, it was argued that algorithms and parameters are too deeply intertwined to focus only on the former, but that it was more important to study, in detail, the exact behaviour of the latter. More broadly speaking, we need to accept the fact that there is a great deal of uncertainty also in the parameter spaces of our algorithms, but that this uncertainty can and should be dealt with correctly.</li>
</ul>
<p>That thought-provoking capstone and this blog post will share the same concluding quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Doubt is not a pleasant condition, but certainty is absurd. — Voltaire / Gröller</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I hope to see you in the comments below! You could also opt to click on my shiny new +1 button, or my slightly older but no less shiny retweet or facebook share buttons.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>An Inside Job. [Weekly Head Voices #33]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 14:10:36 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</guid><description> Hiatus: temporarily over.
My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to that, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hiatus: temporarily over.</p>
<p>My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to <em>that</em>, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am. :)</p>
<p>In this post, I’m going to touch upon the highlights of the past seven weeks (40 to 46) and I’m going to do so with bullets, seeing as I’m in a bullety-kind of mood.</p>
<ul>
<li>I spent a week in Stellenbosch teaching Information Visualisation! Read all about it in <a href="/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/" title="stbvis2010 blog post">this special blog post</a>.</li>
<li>The week after that my mom came to visit us. She really has the best genes.</li>
<li>I met my new work laptop: A Dell Latitude E6410 with Core i5 M540 2.53GHz CPU, 4G ram, 500G HDD, NVidia NVS 3100m GPU with 512 MB video mem. It’s a 14″ latop (15.4″ is a completely useless format, flame me in the comments), but due to the materials used quite heavy. I like it!</li>
<li>Another one of our STW NIG research proposals has been granted. I conceived and developed this one together with colleagues from the LUMC Departments of Anatomy, of Surgery and of Orthopaedics. The title is <em>High-definition Atlas-based surgical planning for Pelvic Surgery</em> and we get to combine high-resolution human histology, mega-volume rendering, , biomechanical modelling and surgical simulation. With this grant we can appoint two more Ph.D. students (one in my group, one at the LUMC) for four years to work on this!!</li>
<li>The week after that I went to Salt Lake City (Utah, US and A) to attend the conference previously known as <a href="http://vis.computer.org/VisWeek2010/" title="IEEE VisWeek 2010 website">IEEE Visualization</a>. It was AWESOME! (blog post half-written, will soon publish).</li>
<li>The week after that I had a really cool dream: I was playing high-speed catch with a bunch of people outside. The ball was randomly changing shape between rock, papers and scissors. If you wanted to catch it, you didn’t only have to be at the right place at the right time, but your hand also had to be in the right complementary configuration to catch the shape-shifting ball.</li>
<li>Now that we’re talking about dreams: <em>I finally saw <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1375666/" title="IMDB page for Inception">Inception</a> and was completely blown away.</em> It’s not about being complicated, it’s about being a well-told story and a fantastically filmed movie. What I positively adored, is the fact that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan" title="Wikipedia page about Christopher Nolan">Nolan</a> doesn’t require much: He only needs you to believe that dreams can be shared, without giving away too many of the details of the mechanism, and then builds a marvellous story on that canvas. My absolute favourite scene was the waking up on the plane, just before the landing, almost at the end of the film. I loved the way in which the characters looked at each other, and the possible interpretations of their expressions.</li>
<li>On the topic of the Underworld gig in the Heineken Music Hall: I hope I have my voice back before my morning lecture tomorrow morning. Thank you Fantastic Friends!</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it kids. If you’ve come this far, you’re now mostly up to date. Please leave me a comment, it’s good for my serotonin! I hope you have a great week. To get you off to a  good start, here’s a music video showing what an infectious idea could look like…</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<div class="embed-vimeo" style="text-align: center;">
<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="473" mozallowfullscreen="" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/15391189" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="840"></iframe>
</div>
</div>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Teaching InfoVis in Stellenbosch</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 11:42:36 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/</guid><description> In week 40 (that’s Monday October 4 to Friday October 8 for those of you not so much into week numbers) I had the privilege of giving a week-long Information Visualisation course to a group of post-graduate students (a mix of B.A. Honours in either Socio-informatics or in Decision-making and Values Studies) at the Centre for KDD of the University of Stellenbosch in the building previously-known-as “The BJ”.
With this post, I want to summarise, extremely compactly, my impressions:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In week 40 (that’s Monday October 4 to Friday October 8 for those of you not so much into week numbers) I had the privilege of giving a week-long Information Visualisation course to a group of post-graduate students (a mix of B.A. Honours in either Socio-informatics or in Decision-making and Values Studies) at the <a href="http://www.informatics.sun.ac.za/" title="Centre for KDD website">Centre for KDD</a> of the University of Stellenbosch in the building previously-known-as “The BJ”.</p>
<p>With this post, I want to summarise, extremely compactly, my impressions:</p>
<ul>
<li>In spite of the odd publication at an InfoVis venue, and in spite of putting significant effort into broadening my horizons also into InfoVis, I’m strictly speaking still a Scientific Visualisation (SciVis) guy. In this context, developing and giving an InfoVis course was a fantastically educational experience. I aspire to be equally fluent in SciVis and InfoVis when I grow up.</li>
<li>I designed a course based on a mix of lecturing, paper reading and discussion and hands-on exercises. I can now highly recommend this combination. Next time I will put more effort into involving everyone more actively in the discussion. What also seemed to work well was the course website that students could add their work to during class.</li>
<li>I sourced almost all of my material from generous InfoVis colleagues, primarily Dr. Tamara Munzner, but also Dr. John Stasko, Prof.dr. Jarke van Wijk and Dr. Maneesh Agrawala. Thank you!</li>
<li>Having spent 7 years at the Stellenbosch Engineering Faculty (1500 guys all wearing t-shirts in jeans; furthermore, social skills are frowned upon) and the past 10 years at the TU Delft, a kind of Ultra-Engineering-Faculty, spending the week at The BJ interacting with socially adept and skilled communicators was a truly interesting experience.</li>
<li>I was otherwise also impressed with the level of cooperation between the students and their willingness to work hard (and long).</li>
<li>Laptop-use during lectures in a relatively small class: It’s an interesting phenomenon, having to deal with your own little <a href="http://mariandoerk.de/visualbackchannel/" title="visual backchannel paper at infovis 2010">communication backchannel</a>. Banning laptop use is obviously not an option as there are too many possible advantages, but I’m not sure yet what a good solution would be towards making sure that the laptops are being used to augment learning.</li>
<li>Most students chose <a href="http://vis.stanford.edu/protovis/" title="ProtoVis website">ProtoVis</a> (from <a href="http://stbvis2010.medvis.org/syllabus/p-infovis-design" title="list of software toolkits stbvis2010 students could use">a list of 8 possibilities</a>, and they were free to use anything else too) to implement their final mini-projects with. This was probably due to their previous web-programming experience, and also that ProtoVis requires more or less zero setup.</li>
</ul>
<p>Conclusion: Much learned, hopefully the students did too. :) All in all a positive and energising experience!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>VCBM 2010 [Weekly Head Voices #26]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/07/08/vcbm-2010-weekly-head-voices-26/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 09:58:51 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/07/08/vcbm-2010-weekly-head-voices-26/</guid><description> (This post is a slightly longer than average report detailing our trip to the EG VCBM 2010 conference. It’s of course super-entertaining, but if you still do wish to skim through it, I’ve bolded the per-paragraph themes. If you’re not sure what these danged conferences are about, see my recent EuroVis 2010 post for a general introduction.)
Last week, I accompanied Peter Schaafsma (he of the orbital fat mobility paper), Bastijn Vissers and André van Dixhoorn (they of the resting state fMRI brain connectivity paper) to Leipzig, where they had been selected to present their work at the second Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine (VCBM).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This post is a slightly longer than average report detailing our trip to the EG VCBM 2010 conference. It’s of course super-entertaining, but if you still do wish to skim through it, I’ve bolded the per-paragraph themes. If you’re not sure what these danged conferences are about, see my <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/" title="my EuroVis 2010, with general introduction to scientific conferences">recent EuroVis 2010 post</a></em> <em>for a general introduction.)</em></p>
<p>Last week, I accompanied Peter Schaafsma (he of the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Schaafsma2010" title="orbital fat mobility paper">orbital fat mobility paper</a>), <a href="http://www.bastijn.nl/" title="Bastijn Visser's website">Bastijn Vissers</a> and André van Dixhoorn (they of the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Dixhoorn2010" title="rs-fMRI connectivity paper">resting state fMRI brain connectivity paper</a>) to Leipzig, where they had been selected to present their work at the <a href="http://vcbm.org/2010/" title="VCBM 2010 website">second Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine (VCBM)</a>.








<figure><a href="http://vcbm.org/2010/">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/newlogo-270x150.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty VCBM logo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty VCBM logo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Things got off to a great start when, as we were travelling there by speeding bullet (okay, it was just a brand-new rental Opel, but the Autobahn turns any car into a Speeding Bullet!), we managed to <strong>strike, at high speed, a high-quality German plastic bucket that had suddenly appeared right in the middle of the road</strong>. After a few more kilometres of noticing that our speeding bullet was not able to pass the very slowly accelerating bullet stage and was making strange disconcerting noises to boot (excuse the automotive pun), we stopped to investigate, noticing to our shock that the bucket, having been very badly burnt, <a href="http://www.moviedeaths.com/austin_powers:_international_man_of_mystery/mustafa/" title="Mustafa?">Mustafa-style</a>, was still lodged under the car.</p>
<p>After carefully dislodging the remaining half of the bucket, we were even more shocked to notice that the car was dripping concerning amounts of liquid more or less from the spot where the bucket had been stuck. Further on-site and online investigation by the crew brought to light the following observations: 1) The liquid was not hot, and so probably did not come from the engine. 2) The liquid was tasteless (don’t ask). 3) The air-conditioner had been running all the time, and certainly would have to get rid of water condensate from the cooled air. This latter observation was to us not immediately obvious, but now is, and hopefully to you as well: <strong>Automobile air-conditioners often get rid of condensed water through outlets under the car.</strong> Phew.</p>
<p>Our speeding bullet tore through the remaining 200 kilometres in record time, where <a href="http://simvis.at/" title="Link to SimVis, Helmut's company.">my man Helmut from Vienna</a> <em>and</em> these <strong>wonderful brain-boosters</strong> were waiting for us on the <a href="http://maps.google.nl/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=Nikolaikirchhof,+Leipzig,+Deutschland&amp;sll=51.34071,12.378302&amp;sspn=0.000678,0.001742&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=Nikolaikirchhof,+04109+Leipzig,+Germany%E2%89%AA=51.340525,12.378309&amp;spn=0.001356,0.003484&amp;t=h&amp;z=19" title="Google Maps link to Nikolaikirchhof">Nikolaikirchhof</a>:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/leipzig_4x1l.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/leipzig_4x1l.jpg"
        
            alt="Leipzig&#39;s famous 1 litre brain boosters. Image deliberately deFaced. The arms in the photo might or might not belong to anyone that you know."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Leipzig's famous 1 litre brain boosters. Image deliberately deFaced. The arms in the photo might or might not belong to anyone that you know.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  The conference kicked off the next morning bright and early with a <strong>brilliant keynote by </strong><strong><a href="http://webstaff.itn.liu.se/~andyn/ITN/Home.html" title="website prof. Anders Ynnerman">Prof. Anders Ynnerman</a></strong>.  This was related to the great talk he gave in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/06/28/sometimes-being-in-academia-rules-weekly-head-voices-25/" title="blog post including Prof. Ynnerman's talk in Delft">Delft the week before</a>, but even better, as, amongst other things, he had had the Virtual Autopsy multi-touch table shipped all the way to Leipzig to be able to demo live during his presentation. He even managed to undo the evil our projector in Delft had wrought on his laptop’s colour profiles and finally showed his visualisations in their full glory on the projector in the <a href="http://www.mediencampus-villa-ida.de/" title="link to Mediencampus Villa Ida website">Mediencampus Villa Ida</a>.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  The <strong>second keynote, given by <a href="http://rsl.stanford.edu/bammer/" title="homepage Dr Roland Bammer">Dr Roland Bammer</a></strong><strong>, focused on their work on eliminating motion artefacts in brain MRI</strong>, both by image post-processing but also, and this is the really cool bit, by mounting a special marker on the forehead of the subject that allows real-time 3D motion tracking and linked real-time low-level correction of the MRI acquisition process. They are currently working hard on getting their tech into users’ hands. Help them by bugging your local Radiology Department about this! :)
</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/virtual_autopsy_at_vcbm2010.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/virtual_autopsy_at_vcbm2010.jpg"
        
            alt="The multi-touch virtual autopsy table was available throughout the conference to try out. Two observations: 1. Sometimes the glass surface of the multitouch.fi table is harder to work with than the MS Surface&#39;s matt finish. 2. It&#39;s hard to use the table in environments with too much lighting."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The multi-touch virtual autopsy table was available throughout the conference to try out. Two observations: 1. Sometimes the glass surface of the multitouch.fi table is harder to work with than the MS Surface's matt finish. 2. It's hard to use the table in environments with too much lighting.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
 
<p>The rest of the scientific program was perfectly varied, consisting of paper presentations, an invited talks session and a posters session, including a plenary fast-forward where each poster author was given three minutes to promote their work.  What really shone throughout the two days, was the <strong>superb organisation in Leipzig</strong>: Thanks to <a href="http://www.cbs.mpg.de/staff/wiebel-11088" title="website Dr Alex Wiebel">Dr Alex Wiebel</a> and colleagues, the conference was a text-book example of conference organisation, with each event occurring at exactly the right time, not a moment too soon or a moment too late.  The <a href="http://www.mediencampus-villa-ida.de/" title="Mediencampus Villa Ida website">Mediencampus Ida Villa</a> was the ideal location for the conference, not in the least due to its air-conditioned auditorium shielding us from the more than 30 degrees Celsius outside temperatures. Another important manifestation of the superb organisation were the magical coffee breaks, always taking place exactly when <em>you</em> needed them, with copious amounts of cookies to boot!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  Erik Pernod and Herve Delingette won the <strong>VCBM 2010 Best Paper award</strong> with their paper titled <em>Interactive real time simulation of cardiac radio-frequency ablation</em>, really great work combining elements of simulation, visualisation and a clear clinical application.  The best paper committee had a relatively easy choice, as the reviews (3 to 4 per submission) were also unanimous about this paper’s ranking. As an added bonus, the work is available within the open-source <a href="http://www.sofa-framework.org/" title="SOFA framework website">SOFA framework</a>.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  My personal and completely biased <strong>Head Voices VCBM 2010 Best Talk Award</strong> however, goes to the invited talk by <a href="http://www.icg.tu-graz.ac.at/Members/streit" title="website Marc Streit">Marc Streit</a> and <a href="http://www.icg.tugraz.at/Members/alex" title="website Alexander Lex">Alexander Lex</a> on <em>Caleydo: Visual Analysis of Biomolecular Data</em>. The presentation was an extremely entertaining show by two skilled speakers, striking just the right balance between focus and variety as they demonstrated several aspects of their Caleydo visual analysis software.  At several points, for example the explicit visual linking of different heterogeneous data sources (paper <a href="http://www.caleydo.org/publication/2010_GI_VisualLinksAcrossApplications.pdf" title="caleydo: linking different applications paper">here</a>, youtube video <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4uXvxAeb5xA" title="Caleydo: Linking different applications video.">here</a>, see <a href="http://www.caleydo.org/publications.html" title="All Caleydo publications">here</a> for other publications.), I had the typical reaction to good scientific contributions: Now why didn’t I think of that?!
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  Three to four of the VCBM 2010 papers (this includes the best paper of course) will soon be selected to submit an extended version to the <strong>forthcoming special issue in the Computers and Graphics journal on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine</strong>.  Very importantly: <em>Everyone is welcome to submit an aptly themed paper to this special issue!</em> See the <a href="http://vcbm.org/2010/cagissue/" title="C&amp;G special issue on VCBM call for papers">C&amp;G special issue on VCBM call for papers</a> for more information.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  On a more personal note: This was the second VCBM workshop, with the first having been held in Delft in 2008, organised by yours truly. It was really great in Leipzig experiencing the growing community around this event and especially connecting with some of my favourite people. I’m greatly looking forward to future VCBM workshops, which makes it doubly cool that  VCBM 2012 will be hosted by Prof. Anders Ynnerman in Linköping (Sweden) and that after that, it will become a yearly phenomenon.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  Will you join us?
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Sometimes, being in academia rules. [Weekly Head Voices #25]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/28/sometimes-being-in-academia-rules-weekly-head-voices-25/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2010 20:41:50 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/28/sometimes-being-in-academia-rules-weekly-head-voices-25/</guid><description> Kids! It’s now truly summer over here, which means as much as possible time outside, which means less time available for writing blog posts. However, weeks 24 and 25 of 2010 contained such newsworthy items, that I’m simply forced to trade some sun-light for a bit of TFT exposure. In this post, we talk flowers, PhD defences, scientific talks, funny Js and finally stick figures, so please stick around! I took this photo of the Oude Kerk in Delft as we were taking a walk with one of our esteemed guests.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Kids!  It’s now truly summer over here, which means as much as possible time outside, which means less time available for writing blog posts. However, weeks 24 and 25 of 2010 contained such newsworthy items, that I’m simply forced to trade some sun-light for a bit of TFT exposure. In this post, we talk flowers, PhD defences, scientific talks, funny Js and finally stick figures, so please stick around!








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/delft_oude_kerk_1280x960.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/delft_oude_kerk_1280x960-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="I took this photo of the Oude Kerk in Delft as we were taking a walk with one of our esteemed guests. So it&#39;s really relevant to this post, ok?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>I took this photo of the Oude Kerk in Delft as we were taking a walk with one of our esteemed guests. So it's really relevant to this post, ok?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Last week we had our department’s yearly BBQ at the Blue Lagoon at Scheveningen.  In a not altogether surprising turn of events, I’ve been working at the TU for 10 years, and I now have the bunch of orange flowers to show for it! Time is really fun when you’re having flies.</p>
<p>Five of my MedVis (that’s <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4307" title="MedVis IN4307 website">IN4307</a>; if you’re at the TU, make sure you take this life-changing course! :P ) students presented their final project work. Between the visualisations of coronary stents from optical coherence tomography data, the 3D lung volume reduction surgery (LVRS) planning tool and the real-time X-Ray simulator, I was hugely and pleasantly impressed.  Expect to see a large part of this functionality in a future release of <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Projects/DeVIDE" title="compulsory link to DeVIDE">DeVIDE</a>. This was energy-producing event #1 of the past two weeks. Energy-producing event #2 was a M.Sc. defence that I opposed just this past Friday, where the candidate presented and defended, in a highly-entertaining and convincing fashion, his thesis on investigating 3D synthetic aperture radar construction on multi-core architectures.</p>
<p>Energy-producing event #3 was when the now freshly minted <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/~eric/" title="Eric Griffith's homepage">Dr Eric Griffith</a> defended his PhD thesis on <em><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Griffith2010" title="Link to Eric's PhD page">Visualizing Cumulus Clouds in Virtual Reality</a></em> in stellar fashion.  Dr Griffith did a superb job of maintaining an eloquent discussion with all 7 of his opponents. The offence of <a href="http://www.cs.rug.nl/~roe/" title="homepage Prof. Jos Roerdink">Prof Jos Roerdink</a> (Visualisation, Groningen) also deserves mention: The multi-level questions and typically professorial delivery were most entertaining.</p>
<p>The final energy-producing event that I’m going to mention has been named #4 for mysterious reasons, and, for other reasons that will soon become clear, was for me the most significant. <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/~jorik/" title="Jorik's homepage">Jorik Blaas</a>, close collaborator and friend for the past seven (7!) years, defended his PhD on the <em><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Blaas2010" title="Link to Jorik's PhD page">Visual Analysis of Multi-Field Data</a></em>, on Thursday June 24. To take part in the offence, we were extremely honoured to welcome three <em>luminaries</em> of my research field (that’s Visualisation, for those of you who’ve just joined!): <a href="http://www.win.tue.nl/~vanwijk/" title="homepage Prof. Jack van Wijk">Prof.dr. Jack van Wijk</a>, <a href="http://www.itn.liu.se/~andyn/" title="homepage Prof.dr. Anders Ynnerman">Prof.dr. Anders Ynnerman</a> and the Viennese-Bergenesque <a href="http://www.ii.uib.no/vis/team/hauser/" title="homepage Prof.dr. Helwig Hauser">Prof.dr. Helwig Hauser</a>. Having all three of them in Delft was just <strong>WOW</strong>, you just have to trust me on this. In any case, for the first time at the TU, I was also allowed to take my place in the PhD committee. :)</p>
<p>Of course, Dr Blaas sailed through the defence, his usual understated yet verbally effective hyper-intelligent self. Invited lectures by our guests, much late night discussion on the nature of (visualisation) science and of life in general and finally a PhD party that stress-tested all glandular resilience helped to turn this into one seriously wonderful and life-affirming week. I am thankful to all involved.</p>
<p>In completely unrelated news:</p>
<ul>
<li>Have you ever wondered what that funnily isolated ‘J’ character is doing at the end of sentences in emails?  Well, <a href="http://chris.pirillo.com/j-smiley-outlook-email-problem-and-fix/" title="funny J in emails">wonder no more</a>! (5-second-version: it’s supposed to be a smiley, but Outlook on the sending side substitutes it with a character from the Wingdings font that is rendered at the receiving side, if that font is not available, as a ‘J’)</li>
<li>My 4-year old daughter recently made a drawing with two stick figures standing next to each other. Not significant as such, but the one stick figure was wearing a bow tie, while the other stick figure had a thought bubble above its head with a bow tie in it.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thank you for joining me again for this edition of the Weekly Head Voices, and please feel free to kick-off completely unrelated discussions in the comments.  Next week (actually this week, I’m late), four of us will be going to Leipzig for the bi-annual Eurographics workshop on <a href="http://vcbm.org/2010" title="EG VCBM 2010 website">Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine (VCBM)</a>, which I’ll probably be reporting on in a future blog post (and hopefully on twitter with hashtag <a href="http://twitter.com/search?q=%23vcbm2010" title="link to twitter hashtag #vcbm2010">#vcbm2010</a>). Stay tuned for much fun and excitement!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>EuroVis 2010 [Weekly Head Voices #24]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2010 10:13:19 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/</guid><description> Welcome all to the latest edition of the Weekly Head Voices! In a bid to get more numbers into my titles (oh who am I kidding, I’m clearly trying to slightly injure or preferably frighten two birds with a single stone, splitting infinitives as I go along), this WHV is dedicated to the EuroVis 2010 conference, which on its part is the reason I spent most of last week in Bordeaux.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome all to the latest edition of the Weekly Head Voices!  In a bid to get more numbers into my titles (oh who am I kidding, I’m clearly trying to slightly injure or preferably frighten two birds with a single stone, splitting infinitives as I go along), this WHV is dedicated to the EuroVis 2010 conference, which on its part is the reason I spent most of last week in Bordeaux.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/chateau_faugeres-1024.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/chateau_faugeres-1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Château Faugères, youngest of the chateaux. Photo by Peter Krekel."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Château Faugères, youngest of the chateaux. Photo by Peter Krekel.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>EuroVis is definitely the most important European scientific conference on Visualisation. For detailed and complete coverage, see <a href="http://www.cse.msstate.edu/~tjk/" title="T.J. Jankun-Kelly's website">T.J. Jankun-Kelly’s</a> (he was also the uncontested tweetmaster of the conference) detailed blog posts on the <a href="http://www.vizworld.com/2010/06/eurovis2010-day-1-wrapup/" title="tj's blog post on eurovis 2010 day 1">first</a>, <a href="http://www.vizworld.com/2010/06/eurovis2010-day-2-wrapup/" title="TJ's blog post on eurovis 2010 day 2">second</a> and <a href="http://www.vizworld.com/2010/06/eurovis2010-day-3-wrapup/" title="tj's blog post on day 3 of eurovis 2010">third</a> days of the conference. The post you are reading now is my very own extremely biased and mostly incomplete view of the conference and of conferences in general, which can sometimes be interesting.  Or just very misleading.</p>
<p>Let’s start with the basics: A scientific conference is where a bunch of mostly scientists get together somewhere in the world, ostensibly to present recent results of their research to each other. Work certainly gets presented, and in some cases it’s a treat seeing a gifted orator giving a superb presentation.</p>
<p>However, in my mind the primary reason to go to a conference is not to discuss work that was submitted half a year ago, but to meet with colleagues and <em>friends</em> and to discuss important things, such as life, science in general and the research that has not yet been published or even started up yet. It is a hugely important element of the social goo that keeps a research field coherent and cooperative.</p>
<p>There are numerous overlapping interest and social groups that continuously split off to discuss something or just socialise, and then merge back into the larger group. The various attendees each has their own character and associated mode of operation: Some flit around, speaking to all and sundry, some stick to and act as the backbone of the subgroup that they belong to, some walk around and think, sometimes being approach by yet another type of agent. It’s interesting to watch from the corner of one’s eye whilst one is also <em>enjoying</em> taking part in this system. Sometimes the backyard anthropologist in me wonders how exactly the nature of this social fabric affects the performance of science. I imagine that it would be cool to put together a taxonomy of social conference types and even map their behaviour during a single conference such as this.</p>
<p>In any case, at EuroVis there were, the same as <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/" title="link to eurovis 2009 post">last year in Berlin</a>, 190 attendees.  Three days of presentations, with a poster session and a visit to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint-%C3%89milion" title="wikipedia page on Saint-Emilion">Saint-Émilion</a> thrown in for good measure.</p>
<p>With regard to the presentations, I seemed to notice an ever-so-slight upwards trend in the number of papers accompanied by open source software implementations (both <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Krekel2010a" title="Link to MotionVA paper">MotionVA</a> and <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Busking2010" title="Link to SSX paper">ShapeSpaceExplorer</a> by respectively our very own Peter Krekel and Stef Busking are open source, but there were more examples). This is really a great development, as it is an important component of the whole open science idea. With the implementations available, colleagues can reproduce one’s results and thus have a greater chance of being able to improve on them. Also, new implementations can be directly compared to existing ones, something which is currently incredibly hard.</p>
<p>Two of my favourite presentations were the following:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Visual Support for Interactive Post-Interventional Assessment of Radiofrequency Ablation Therapy</em> by Christian Rieder, Andreas Weihusen, Christian Schumann, Stephan Zidowitz, Heinz-Otto Peitgen: I really like this genre of solutions, where complex 3D problems are reduced to normalised 2D representations. A previous example is the <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/" title="my eurovis 2009 blog post">work of Neugebauer et al. at EuroVis 2009</a>. In this case, the authors presented “tumor maps”, a 2D map-style representation of the tumor and its surroundings which greatly facilitates the post-therapy tumor assessment. The fulltext paper will hopefully be linked on <a href="http://www.mevis-research.de/~crieder/" title="Christian Rieder's website">Christian’s website</a> soon.</li>
<li><em><a href="http://www.cs.sfu.ca/~torsten/Publications/Papers/ev10-3.pdf" title="Link to fulltext PDF">Estimation and Modeling of Actual Numerical Errors in Volume Rendering</a></em> by Joel Kronander, Jonas Unger, Anders Ynnerman, Torsten Möller: Although this is not my personal favourite type of research, I think the work (and work like it) is tremendously important. The authors meticulously measure the impact of different precision and sampling strategies on the volume rendering pipeline, and, as if that wasn’t enough, derive a mathematical model with which the role of these variables can be predicted in unseen volume rendering problems. In my view, this is a great example of research towards deriving elements of that elusive visualisation <em>theory</em>. Just to help ram the point home, the presentation was <em>extremely</em> well executed.</li>
</ul>
<p>On a slightly higher level, what I’ve also started noticing is the different <em>styles</em> of visualisation.  Many research groups have a distinct style of visually representing their data: One can easily recognise a <a href="http://www.cg.tuwien.ac.at/research/vis/" title="Link to TU Wien vis group">Viennese design</a>, and sometimes even notice how elements thereof have been subtly adapted by a faction of ex-Viennese scientists in Bergen.  The <a href="http://www.ii.uib.no/vis/" title="link to Bergen vis group">Bergenesque style</a> is still quite young, but will probably soon spread to different groups.  Of course not all groups are that easy: Our own style is heterogeneous, although I’m glad to see at least the blue-to-yellow more-or-less perceptually linear colour-scale starting to permeate our work. It would still be interesting to start a kind of genealogical tree showing the various styles and also how they spread along with the persons practising them.</p>
<p>On the topic of Saint-Émilion: 1000 vineyards covering 95% of the available land, oldest of the vineyards 2000 years old, number of beautiful old Chateaux (castles man, castles!) each having on average 6 hectares of land. 5 different classes of wine produceds, ranging from 5 euros per bottle (hello there!) up to 7000 euros per bottle. It’s a beautiful piece of country.  In fact, it reminded me very strongly of the Western Cape in South Africa,where I grew up.</p>
<p>My group ended up visiting <a href="http://www.chateau-faugeres.com/" title="website chateau">Château Faugères</a>, by far the youngest of the chateaux, but awesomely cool nonetheless, as it was designed by a Swiss-Italian architect by the awesomely cool name of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mario_Botta" title="Mario Botta's wikipedia page">Mario Botta</a>. We got to taste one (1) wine. This was slightly less reminiscent of the vineyards of the Western Cape in South Africa, where one can taste wines until one starts developing very entertaining coordination problems. Fortunately, this very small oversight was more than compensated for by the subsequent visit to the town of Saint-Émilion, its monolithic church and the catacombs, all narrated by an extremely gifted and humorous guide, and finally by the marvelous concluding dinner, done as only the French can.</p>
<p>So kids, that it was it for this week’s lecture on Further Mystifying Scientific Conferences!  I have to go, as I have to start thinking about the next Weekly Head Voices.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #18: Refactor my dogfood.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/21/weekly-head-voices-18-refactor-my-dogfood/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2010 16:25:11 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/21/weekly-head-voices-18-refactor-my-dogfood/</guid><description> Welcome all, to this, the 18th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I discuss a number of issues that mostly have nothing specific to do with the 11th week of 2010, but which might or might not have crossed my mind during that time! Issues include good news on the EuroVis 2010 front, a new edition of the Head Voices Review featuring my completely unexpected stay in a 7 Tesla MRI scanner (as a test subject, of course) and finally some nerdy backyard philosophy dealing with the well-known itch to Rewrite Everything From Scratch, Because What’s There Now Sucks.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome all, to this, the 18th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I discuss a number of issues that mostly have nothing specific to do with the 11th week of 2010, but which might or might not have crossed my mind during that time! Issues include good news on the EuroVis 2010 front, a new edition of the Head Voices Review featuring my completely unexpected stay in a 7 Tesla MRI scanner (as a test subject, of course)  and finally some nerdy backyard philosophy dealing with the well-known itch to Rewrite Everything From Scratch, Because What’s There Now Sucks.</p>
<p>First, because I have no other visual element for this week’s post, and  because I am, as you might have noticed, a method blogger, I present you with probably the best <a href="http://chatroulette.com/" title="chatroulette website">chatroulette.com</a> improv I’ve ever seen so far. For those of you who have been completely asleep the past few weeks, chatroulette is a new site that’s been taking the interwebs by storm. The site pairs up random strangers for webcam chats. One is allowed to move to the next random stranger with the click of a buttom (resulting in the new English verb <a href="http://www.kk.org/thetechnium/archives/2010/02/nexted.php" title="Kevin Kelly's blog post on nexting">“to next”</a> someone..). Random hilarity (and often perversity) ensues! Here’s that mostly SFW and brilliant piano improv:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JTwJetox_tU?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p><em>(The original video had to be pulled, after 4 million views, due to some YouTube issues. Merton, pianist, has posted this new version. Thanks to</em> <a href="http://fpixel.wordpress.com/" title="Link to Francois' photography site"><em>Francois</em></a> <em>for the heads-up!)</em></p>
<p>Back to business, we have just heard the great news that our two <a href="http://eurovis2010.labri.fr/" title="eurovis 2010 website">EuroVis 2010</a> submissions have been finally accepted for publication.  The articles are:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>S. Busking, C.P. Botha, and F.H. Post, <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Busking2010" title="Link to Stef's EuroVis 2010 paper page (fulltext available)">“Dynamic Multi-View Exploration of Shape Spaces,”</a> <em>Computer Graphics Forum</em>, 2010.</li>
<li>P.R. Krekel, E.R. Valstar, J. de Groot, F.H. Post, R.G. Nelissen, and C.P. Botha, <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Krekel2010a" title="Link to Krekel EuroVis 2010 Visual Analysis of Human Motion paper">“Visual Analysis of Multi-Joint Kinematic Data,”</a> <em>Computer Graphics Forum</em>, 2010.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Fantastic work you first authors you! Remember people: YOU HAVE TO CITE THESE SOON, AND YOU HAVE TO CITE THEM OFTEN! This also means that a number of us will be going to Bordeaux in June (I can imagine worse places to go to in June) to mingle with other scientists and to drink really good red wine.</p>
<p>That good news brings us to the influential WHV feature, the <strong>Head Voices Review</strong>! (My TPN is still working on the new jingle.  Hopefully it’ll be on time for our joint Vodka review feature.) In this edition, I’ll be reviewing the Philips 7 Tesla MRI scanner and the JBL Duet-200 computer speakers.</p>
<p>On Friday, I unexpectedly had the pleasure of trying out a state-of-the-art 7 Tesla Philips MRI scanner, as a test subject. I can report that the bore, although small, is quite comfortable. However, test subjects with claustrophobic tendencies should probably look elsewhere.  Scanning can be quite noisy, especially when a diffusion weighted imaging protocol is applied that involves scanning in 162 different gradient directions (to study the structural connectivity in my brain). However, the music that gets piped in between scanning sessions more than makes up. After scanning, it was scientifically confirmed that there is indeed a brain housed in my skull, an observation that pleasantly surprised me. Soon I hope to be able to post visualisations, made by one of our MedVis ninjas, of the structural connections in my brain.</p>
<p>All in all, if you have a few million euros lying around, this piece of kit is highly recommended.  To summarise:</p>
<ul>
<li>Philips 7T MRI: AWESOME.</li>
</ul>
<p>In a <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/03/09/weekly-head-voices-16-go-go-gadget/" title="previous review of the Logitechh S3-30 speakes">previous review</a>, I was quite negative about the Logitech S3-30 speakers, for a large part due to the absolute mess of cables that it comes with. This past week I took delivery of the new <a href="http://www.amazon.com/JBL-DUET-200BLKV-Performance-Loudspeaker-Multimedia/dp/B0017XO2R6" title="JBL DUET-200 on amazon">JBL Duet-200</a> speakers I ordered, for the grand amount of 30 eurobucks, to replace it. The JBL is a single unit containing two speakers, something which might be seen as a drawback, but which I consider an advantage. In spite of its compact appearance, it packs quite a base and more than sufficient volume.  In addition, there are exactly two (2) cables: One for the power supply, and one for the audio. I can only hope that Logitech contracts JBL on their next PC speaker product design. My only (minor) gripe is that the JBL-supplied audio cable is only about 40cm long. All in all:</p>
<ul>
<li>JBL Duet-200 at € 30 price-point: AWESOME.</li>
</ul>
<p>MRI scanners and PC speakers: No product too big, no product too small for the Head Voices Review!</p>
<p>Finally, it’s time for some backyard philosophy.  This week, it’s a brief point of really nerdy philosophy, although I think the principles apply to some non-nerdy activities as well. Software developers, as well as many other engineering types, often reach a point during working on a project, when they have a hard-to-control urge to trash the whole thing and start from scratch.  There is usually a very strong belief that the project / software / product can be designed much better by starting from scratch.</p>
<p>It turns out that this is an insidious and mostly incorrect belief, for a large part due to all the knowledge present in the existing “ugly” product that will get thrown out. Engineers easily underestimate the importance of this knowledge. It turns out, much as we don’t like to hear this, that <strong>refactoring</strong> is, nine times out of ten, a far better answer than rewriting from scratch. Experienced developers know this, and are <em>mostly</em> able to suppress the rewrite from scratch itch.</p>
<p>Joel Spolsky wrote a <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000069.html" title="Joel Spolsky on why you shouldn't rewrite software">really good essay</a> on this phenomenon. Go read it!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #14: My Week Was A Wormhole.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/21/weekly-head-voices-14-my-week-was-a-wormhole/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2010 18:25:33 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/21/weekly-head-voices-14-my-week-was-a-wormhole/</guid><description> In this week’s post, documenting the 7th week of 2010, I wonder about perceived business, mention two of our most recent open source releases and give to you, my readers, two screencasts about the DRE, in addition probably highly effective in the treatment of insomnia. Screenshot of the FoBVis system. This is just one of our many attempts to take over the world, subtly.
Just before bedtime on Monday, I had still managed to make a note in my special top-secret Weekly Head Voices journal.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this week’s post, documenting the 7th week of 2010, I wonder about perceived business, mention two of our most recent open source releases and give to you, my readers, two screencasts about the DRE, in addition probably highly effective in the treatment of insomnia.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/fobvis1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/fobvis1.jpg"
        
            alt="Screenshot of the FoBVis system. This is just one of our many attempts to take over the world, subtly."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Screenshot of the FoBVis system. This is just one of our many attempts to take over the world, subtly.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Just before bedtime on Monday, I had still managed to make a note in my special top-secret Weekly Head Voices journal.  I usually do this every day to make sure I don’t forget anything by the weekend, when I usually have some time to write these posts.  Thursday night’s entry simply says “WTF, where did my week go?!” — There had been no other entries since Monday. I’m still not quite sure why it felt that way, as my breakdown of activities is similar to that of the previous week: 2 hours of lecture preparation, 3 hours of lecturing, 15 hours of scheduled meetings and 20 tasks completed (one more than last week!!) across 10 projects. Perhaps those four extra hours of meetings don’t scale linearly in the amount of business they cause, due to the number of extra context switches that they bring. I have to add that a number of truly exciting projects are brewing, but I can’t say more about them until I can say more about them, if you know what I mean.</p>
<p>We (The Group, of course) recently released two new open source software projects:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://fobvis.googlecode.com/" title="FoBVis project site">FoBVis</a> is a tool for the real-time acquisition and visualisation of human motion: Currently it supports the Flock-of-Birds electromagnetic acquisition system, we are currently working to integrate Optotrak optical tracking system. We should also shortly have a version of the <a href="http://code.google.com/p/devide/wiki/HelpDRE" title="You can use the DRE to run stuff, including the FoBVis.">DRE</a> that can run the FoBVis on YOUR computer as well.</li>
<li><a href="http://histovis.googlecode.com/" title="HistoVis project site">HistoVis</a> is a client-server system for the visualisation of large collections of (registered) histological sections.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s all very exciting that more products of our research are entering the big bad outside world!  The FoBVis is already being actively used by the LUMC Laboratory for Motion Analysis (we hope that more labs will start using this soon), and HistoVis will soon go live from the <a href="http://visible-orbit.nl/" title="Visible Orbit website">visible-orbit.nl server</a>. Of course these have both been released under the new BSD license, as the GPL sucks.</p>
<p>Screencasts: Video Performance Art of the Nerdily Inclined. That’s where one makes a recording of one’s computer screen whilst demonstrating some or other procedure, optionally narrated by oneself, and then proceeds to upload said recording (called a screencast) to YouTube or similar. See <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/05/10/recording-screencasts-on-windows-with-free-software/" title="Instructions on creating screencasts in Windows.">a previous post of mine</a> for one possible (and free) way of doing this on Windows. This weekend I produced and uploaded two such pieces, both demonstrating aspects of the DeVIDE Runtime Environment, or <a href="http://code.google.com/p/devide/wiki/HelpDRE" title="DRE help page">DRE</a>, that paradoxically do NOT involve DeVIDE itself. Especially the second is really soothing, one could even say mildly sleep-inducing.  I just say: <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xEbYw73y3pM" title="First sleep-inducing DRE screencast.">(1) Try</a> <a data-rel="lightbox-video-1" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7FwPw9qlsms" title="Second sleep-inducing DRE screencast.">(2) it</a>.</p>
<p>To conclude, I give you a track from the new Massive Attack album Heligoland, called Paradise Circus. It should make your brain sit and scratch its chin stubble, not unlike the usual dose of backyard philosophy:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jEgX64n3T7g?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #12: Ceci n’est pas une bibliothèque.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/09/weekly-head-voices-12-ceci-nest-pas-une-bibliotheque/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2010 22:04:48 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/09/weekly-head-voices-12-ceci-nest-pas-une-bibliotheque/</guid><description> Welcome to the latest edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I briefly touch upon the, to my mind, mention-worthy events that took place within my field of observation during week 5 of the year 2010, and with which I too finally have an excuse to (ab)use the famous words of Magritte for my dubious ends. :)
WE INTERRUPT THIS PROGRAMME FOR THE FOLLOWING IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT:
I’m officially not supposed to talk about this until the next edition of the Weekly Head Voices, but it’s too big and too cool to keep quiet about until then.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the latest edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I <em>briefly</em> touch upon the, to my mind, mention-worthy events that took place within my field of observation during week 5 of the year 2010, and with which I too finally have an excuse to (ab)use the famous words of Magritte for my dubious ends. :)</p>
<p>WE INTERRUPT THIS PROGRAMME FOR THE FOLLOWING IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT:</p>
<p>I’m officially not supposed to talk about this until the next edition of the Weekly Head Voices, but it’s too big and too cool to keep quiet about until then.  Google has just released Buzz, their location-based status / media updating system, and it’s fantastically cool.  I’ve just posted my first Buzz via Google Maps 4.0 on my E71 (I think I’m the third buzz in Delft EVAR).  Don’t know what Buzz is? Check this YouTube clip:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yi50KlsCBio?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>YOU WILL NOW BE RETURNED TO YOUR NORMAL PROGRAMMING.</p>
<p>The reason for the title of this post is my Saturday visit to <a href="http://dok.info/" title="DOK website">DOK</a>, Delft’s unique library concept. It’s not really a library, but more of a fantastic place of gathering that coincidentally contains thousands of books, CDs, DVDs and, err, a coffee shop! They even have a number of <a href="http://www.sonicchair.de/" title="Sonic Chair website">sonic chairs</a> that one can make use of to listen to music via the mounted Macs. This Saturday, live music by one of the artists who exhibited at the DOK.  I made you a short snippet:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/R251vTFuM0s?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>As even this short edition should end on a philosophical note, I’d like to conclude with an interesting discussion I had on whether the type of research we do in (medical) visualisation can be considered to be science. Very strictly speaking, the scientific method consists of observation, hypothesis forming and finally experimentation to prove or disprove the hypothesis. A large body of visualisation work is concerned with <em>making stuff that solves hard problems</em>, i.e. formulative research as opposed to the more traditional evaluative research. Although the question of whether <em>making stuff that solves hard problems</em> constitutes science is a complex discussion that deserves a whole year of blog posts, I am going to conclude with one possible and simple take on situation:</p>
<p>By taking this constructive approach we are, besides actually solving problems (a neat by-product, no?), discovering <em>how</em> to create effective visual representations of complex phenomena hidden in even more complex data. By doing this, we are in fact observing the supremely complex system consisting of the whole pipeline from data acquisition to insight, all the while experimenting with parameters (in the widest possible sense of the world) and thus confirming or disproving hypotheses concerning the nature of the pipeline and its various components. Together, these hypotheses make up the model that governs the effective extraction of insight from data via the human visual system.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>