<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>experiment alcohol zero on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/experiment-alcohol-zero/</link><description>Recent content in experiment alcohol zero on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 19:21:25 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/experiment-alcohol-zero/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #116: Nothing much to see here, please move on.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/02/12/weekly-head-voices-116-nothing-much-to-see-here-please-move-on/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 19:21:25 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/02/12/weekly-head-voices-116-nothing-much-to-see-here-please-move-on/</guid><description> This WHV is all about the weeks from Monday January 30 to Sunday February 12, 2017. I’ve mostly been in heads-down mode on two projects, so this post will be shorter than is usually the case.
I had my very first beer after the 30-day long Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) on Friday, February 3. It was a good one:
EAZ has taught me that it would not be the worst idea to limit alcohol consumption slightly more.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This WHV is all about the weeks from Monday January 30 to Sunday February 12, 2017. I’ve mostly been in heads-down mode on two projects, so this post will be shorter than is usually the case.</p>
<p>I had my very first beer after the 30-day long Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) on Friday, February 3. It was a good one:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/cbc_ambe_weiss_number1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/cbc_ambe_weiss_number1-768x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>EAZ has taught me that it would not be the worst idea to limit alcohol consumption slightly more.</p>
<p>As with many other enjoyable things, there is a price to be paid for this enjoyment. If paying that price interferes with the other enjoyable habits in your collection, it makes sense to evaluate and adjust the balance.</p>
<p>That reminds me of one of my favourite electronic music productions of all time: Balance 014 by Joris Voorn. He <a href="https://www.residentadvisor.net/reviews/5988">blew everyone’s minds</a> when he decided to paint these fantastic soundscapes by mixing together more than 100 tracks, often 5 or 6 at a time.</p>
<iframe allow="autoplay" frameborder="no" height="300" scrolling="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/28875905&amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;show_teaser=true&amp;visual=true" width="100%"></iframe><div style="font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;"><a href="https://soundcloud.com/ukacsukumokacsi" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;" target="_blank" title="Ukacsuku Mokacsi">Ukacsuku Mokacsi</a> · <a href="https://soundcloud.com/ukacsukumokacsi/joris-voorn-balance-014" style="color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;" target="_blank" title="Joris Voorn - Balance 014, Mizuiro Mix CD1">Joris Voorn - Balance 014, Mizuiro Mix CD1</a></div>
<p>Right at this point, just after that not-quite non sequitur, I wrote a far too long section on the relative performance of Android and iPhone, with a big “nerd content ahead” warning on it. Fortunately for you, I came to my senses before publishing and copied it out into its own little blog post: <a href="/2017/02/12/android-vs-iphone-performance-a-quick-note/"><em>Android vs iPhone performance: A quick note</em></a>.</p>
<p>Last weekend I dusted off my trusty old <a href="https://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/mu4e.html">mu4e</a>, an unbelievably attractive email client, again. This means I’m reading your mail and sending you beautifully UNformatted plain text emails right from my Emacs. As an additional bonus, I put all of the boring details about my configuration into a completely separate blog post, which you don’t have to read, titled: <em><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/02/07/mu4e-0-9-18-e-mailing-with-emacs-now-even-better/">mu4e 0.9.18: E-Mailing with Emacs now even better</a></em>.</p>
<p>What I will mention here and not in the other post, is that the current situation is subtly different from my previous adventure with mu4e: Where I previously synchronised all 60 thousand emails to process locally with mu4e, I am now following a more mellowed approach where I’m only synchronising the current year (and perhaps the previous year, still considering) of email. I use the fastmail web-app for searching through longer term storage.</p>
<p>I’m happy to report that so far it’s working out even better than the previous time. I really enjoy converting HTML emails (that’s what everyone sends, thanks GMail!) to well-behaved plain text when I reply.</p>
<p>Finally, after the Nth time that someone shared a clearly bogus science news post on Facebook, instantly bringing my blood to the boil, I decided to write a handy guide titled: <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2017/02/10/critical-thinking-101-three-super-easy-steps-to-spot-poppycock-on-the-internet/">Critical Thinking 101: Three super easy steps to spot poppycock on the internet</a>.</p>
<p>This guide is 100% free, and really easy to send to your friends when you think this is necessary. Please let me know if you have any suggestions for improvement.</p>
<p>Ok kids, that’s it from me for now. I wish you a great week ahead. In the words of Yo-Play: <em>Come on Mitch, don’t give up. Please try again.</em></p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ax0MGlIVjiY?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;start=63&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #115: So much Dutch.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/02/03/weekly-head-voices-115/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 07:07:05 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/02/03/weekly-head-voices-115/</guid><description> Monday January 16 to Sunday January 29 of the year 2017 yielded the following possibly mention-worthy tidbits:
On Saturday, January 21, we had the privilege of seeing Herman van Veen perform live at the Oude Libertas Theatre. The previous time was a magical night many years ago in the Royal Theatre Carré in Amsterdam.
Herman van Veen is a living, extremely active and up to date legend. To most Dutch people you’ll ever meet he is a formidable part of their rich cultural landscape.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Monday January 16 to Sunday January 29 of the year 2017 yielded the following possibly mention-worthy tidbits:</p>
<p>On Saturday, January 21, we had the privilege of seeing Herman van Veen perform live at the Oude Libertas Theatre. The previous time was a magical night many years ago in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carr%C3%A9_Theatre">Royal Theatre Carré in Amsterdam</a>.</p>
<p>Herman van Veen is a living, extremely active and up to date <em>legend</em>. To most Dutch people you’ll ever meet he is a formidable part of their rich cultural landscape.</p>
<p>That evening, we heard so much Dutch spoken in the audience around us, it was easy to imagine that we had been teleported to a strange midsummer night’s performance, all the way back in The Netherlands.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, at 72 this artist and superb human being seems to have energy and magic flowing from every limb.</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/IMG_20170121_2151270.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/IMG_20170121_2151270-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<h1 id="things-which-running-nerds-might-find-interesting">Things which running nerds might find interesting</h1>
<h2 id="the-dutch-watch">The Dutch Watch</h2>
<p>I had to start facing facts.</p>
<p>The <a href="/tag/samsung-gear-fit-2/">Samsung Gear Fit 2</a> and I were not going to make a success of our relationship. The GF2 (haha) is great if you’re looking for a hybrid smart-fitness-watch. However, I was using it primarily for running, and then one tends to run (I’m on a roll here) into its limitations.</p>
<p>My inner engineer, the same guy who has a thing for hiking shoes, as they are the couture epitome of function over form, made the call and selected the <a href="https://www.wareable.com/gps-running-watch/tomtom-spark-3-review">TomTom Runner 3 Cardio+Music</a> watch (the Runner 3 and the Spark 3 are identical except for styling) to replace my GF2.</p>
<p>Hidden in the name, there’s a <em>subtle</em> hint as to the focus of this wearable.</p>
<p>It has a less pretty monochrome display that manages to be highly visible even in direct sunlight. It does not have a touch screen, instead opting for a less pretty directional control beneath the screen that always manages to select the correct menu option. The menu options remind me of the first TomTom car navigation we bought years ago: Not pretty, but with exactly the right functions, in this case for runs and hikes.</p>
<p>Most importantly, the watch has an explicit function for syncing so-called QuickGPSFix data, so that when you want to start running, it is able to acquire a GPS lock almost immediately. Importantly, the device keeps you informed of its progress via the ugly user interface.</p>
<p>Also, I am now able to pre-load GPX routes. Below you can see me navigating my local mountain like a pro with a sense of direction, when in reality I am an amateur with pathological absence of sense of direction:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/IMG_20170128_1626242.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/IMG_20170128_1626242-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="That’s me in the corner, losing my Re-Samsung."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>That’s me in the corner, losing my Re-Samsung.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Anyways, after being initially quite happy with the GF2, I am now more careful with my first judgement of the Runner 3. What I can say is that the first 40km with it on my arm has been a delight of function-over-form.</p>
<p>P.S. Well done Dutchies. The optical heart rate sensor in the previous Spark was based on technology by South African company LifeQ. I have not been able to find a good reference for the situation in the Spark 3 / Runner 3.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-alcohol-zero-early-results-not-what-i-was-hoping">Experiment Alcohol Zero early results: Not what  I was hoping</h2>
<p>The completely subjective Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) I announced in <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">my 2016 to 2017 transition post</a> has almost run (err… too soon?) to completion.</p>
<p>November of 2016 was my best running month of that year: I clocked in at 80km.</p>
<p>EAZ started on January 4 and will conclude probably on Friday February 3.</p>
<p>Although I was a much more boring person in January of 2017, I did manage to run 110 km. The runs were all longer and substantially faster than my best runs of 2016.</p>
<p>Subjectively, there was just always energy (and the will) available to go running, and subjectively there was more energy available during the runs. This is probably for a large part due to the vicious upward spiral of better glucose processing, better sleep, hence better exercise, rinse, repeat.</p>
<p>I am planning to use some of this extra energy to sweep these results right under the proverbial carpet in order to try and limit the suffering that it might lead to.</p>
<p>(Seriously speaking, I will have to apply these findings to my pre-EAZ habits in a <em>reasonable</em> fashion. :)</p>
<h1 id="things-which-linux-nerds-might-find-interesting">Things which Linux nerds might find interesting</h1>
<p>My whole web-empire, including this blog, my <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">serious nerd business blog</a>, and a number of websites I host for friends and family, has been migrated by the wonderful webfaction support to a new much faster shared server in London.</p>
<p>The new server sports 32 Intel Xeon cores, is SSD based and has a newer Linux distribution, so I was able to move over all of my wordpress instances to PHP 7.</p>
<p>Upshot: This blog might feel microscopically quicker! (I am a bit worried with my empire now being stuck in the heart of Article 50. I worry slightly more about a great deal of my data that lives on servers in the USA however. Probably more about that in a future post.)</p>
<p>On the topic of going around the bend, I now have emacs running on my phone, and I’m able to access all of my orgmode notes from there. It looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Screenshot_20170116-151204.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Screenshot_20170116-151204-576x1024.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>One might now ask a pertinent question like: “So Charl, how often do you make use of this wonderful functionality?”</p>
<p>To which I would currently have to answer: “Including showing the screenshot on my blog? Once.”</p>
<p>I’m convinced that it’s going to come in handy at some point.</p>
<h1 id="things-which-backyard-philosophy-nerds-might-find-interesting">Things which backyard philosophy nerds might find interesting</h1>
<p>With what’s happening in the US at the moment, which is actually just one nasty infestation of the political climate around the globe, I really appreciate coming across more positive messages with advice on how we can move forward as a human race in spite of the efforts of the (libertarian) right.</p>
<p>The World Economic Forum’s <a href="http://wef.ch/igd17">Inclusive Growth and Development Report 2017</a> is one such message. As summarised in <a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2017/01/these-are-the-most-inclusive-advanced-economies-in-the-world">this WEF blog post</a>, it tries to answer the question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>How can we increase not just GDP but the extent to which this top-line performance of a country cascades down to benefit society as a whole?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In other words, they present approaches for making our economies more inclusive, thus helping to mitigate the huge gap between rich and poor.</p>
<p>According to the report, the answer entails that national and international economic policies should focus primarily on people and living standards. In order to do this, each country will have to work on a different mix of education, infrastructure, ethics, investment, entrepreneurship and social protection.</p>
<p>The countries that are currently doing the best in terms of having inclusive economies, and are generally shining examples of socialism working extremely well thank you very much, are Norway, Luxembourg, Switzerland, Iceland, Denmark, Sweden, Netherlands, Australia, New Zealand and Austria. See <a href="https://www.weforum.org/agenda/2017/01/these-are-the-most-inclusive-advanced-economies-in-the-world">the blog post</a> for the specific different factors helping each of these countries to perform so well on the Inclusive Development Index (IDI).</p>
<p>Although the countries in the top 10 list all still have room for improvement, it’s great to see that it is actually quite a great idea to combine socialism (which is actually just another word for being further along the human development dimension) with economic survival and even success in today’s world.</p>
<p>(I am still hopeful that one day Gene Roddenberry’s dream of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_Federation_of_Planets">United Federation of Planets</a> will be realised.</p>
<p>LLAP!)</p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2016 to 2017 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 11:05:01 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/</guid><description> Following the rich tradition over here of year transition posts, having just rounded off a brilliant outdoorsy take-your-mind-off-of-everything vacation with friends, and also inspired by wogan.blog’s nicely personal 2016 review post, I decided that a farewell-2016 how-you-doin’-2017 post was in order.
By the way, by rich tradition I mean that I wrote the grand total of one (1) similarly titled post previously, as the year ticked from 2009 to 2010, and at least one other, disguised as a weekly head voices, as we entered 2012.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Following the rich tradition over here of year transition posts, having just rounded off a brilliant outdoorsy take-your-mind-off-of-everything vacation with friends, and also inspired by <a href="https://wogan.blog/2017/01/01/2016-in-review/">wogan.blog’s nicely personal 2016 review post</a>, I decided that a farewell-2016 how-you-doin’-2017 post was in order.</p>
<p>By the way, by <em>rich tradition</em> I mean that I wrote the grand total of one (1) similarly titled post previously, <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">as the year ticked from 2009 to 2010</a>, and at least one other, disguised as a weekly head voices, <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">as we entered 2012</a>. <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">That last one</a> is worth another read, early 2012 cpbotha had some really good tips. There might be more such posts, <a href="/about/history/">this blog has been around for more than 15 years</a> and much of what I’ve written is not available from my short-term memory, which is nice.</p>
<p><em><strong>Warning:</strong> This post is long (1800 words+), rambly and sometimes even a bit mushy. I hope you enjoy it!</em></p>
<h1 id="2016-the-review">2016: The Review</h1>
<h2 id="the-bad-with-a-hopefully-slightlypositive-outlook-at-the-end">The bad, with a hopefully slightly positive outlook at the end</h2>
<p>Let’s get the bad stuff out of the way as soon as we can…</p>
<p>For me the biggest disappointments of 2016 were the double-whammy of the Brexit followed by the Trumpocalypse.</p>
<p>I really did not expect either of these events to go the way they did.</p>
<p>This is probably because I was, ever the optimist, over-estimating the level of human development of British and US voters.</p>
<p>The exclusionist, nationalist, xenophobic and in many cases even white supremacist thinking associated with Trump’s support in the US and the Leave vote in the UK are truly abhorrent.</p>
<p>I understand that there were many other factors at play. However, these voters were either throwing out the baby with the bath water, or, much much  worse, agreeing with the abhorrent sentiments mentioned above. Especially this second possibility depressed me greatly after the US election.</p>
<p>After such setbacks, one needs to look for solutions.</p>
<p>After Brexit, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/06/brexit-vote-statistics-united-kingdom-european-union/488780/">analysis showed that education level was the strongest indicator of a vote for leave or remain</a>. Higher education was strongly associated with remain, whilst the opposite was the case for leave.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Screen-Shot-2017-01-05-at-12.28.37-PM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Screen-Shot-2017-01-05-at-12.28.37-PM-709x1024.png"
        
            alt="Leave / remain voter analysis by The Atlantic. Click to go to article &#43; interactive version of this graphic."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Leave / remain voter analysis by The Atlantic. Click to go to article + interactive version of this graphic.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>For Trump voters, you probably guessed it, it was more or less the same idea. <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/education-not-income-predicted-who-would-vote-for-trump/">Less educated citizens voted for Trump, more educated citizens for Clinton</a>.</p>
<p>This is yet another strong indication that we should really be pouring every resource we have into the education of our people. (yes, correlation and causation, I know. hence the terms “strong indication”. discuss in the comments if you like.)</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrence_M._Krauss">Lawrence M. Krauss</a>, superstar theoretical physicist and author of the book A Universe from Nothing, <a href="https://twitter.com/LKrauss1/status/814947974203641857">recently tweeted</a> this <a href="http://www.quotationspage.com/quote/26977.html">1920 quote by H.G. Wells</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Human history has become, more and more, a race between education and catastrophe.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The way things are going now, that thought, and movements like #feesmustfall, are more important than ever. There can be absolutely no excuse for neglecting the highest quality and <strong>accessible</strong> education (basic up to tertiary) of future generations of humans whom we expect to further our civilization.</p>
<h2 id="therunning-and-the-mindful">The running and the mindful</h2>
<p>In 2016, I ran 440km.</p>
<p>There are a great deal of people who have run much more than that, but those are <em>my</em> 440 kilometers and somehow they brought me a great deal of deep satisfaction.</p>
<p>During the year, my per-run distance and speed have gradually increased.</p>
<p>Besides fitness gradually increasing, I discovered experimentally that shorter, quicker steps get me further and a higher pace. It took a biomechanical friend to explain to me that this was about muscles operating within the more efficient middle of their full extension/contraction ranges. I could probably just have read this somewhere, but doing it the hard way and then having a friend explain it on top of Table Mountain definitely added something to the experience.</p>
<p>For the last 200 kilometres or so, I have listened to the exact same album: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skin_(Flume_album)">Skin by Flume</a>. Every single run, I start that exact same album with the exact same sequence of tracks. As I learned from <a href="https://www.swimgeek.com/blog/2016/11/16/quick-update-445/">the SwimGeek’s blog</a>, <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/2113776/question-everything-tim-ferriss-fitness"><em>finding your soundtrack and putting it on repeat</em> whilst exercising is apparently a thing</a>.</p>
<p>With the surroundings over here being what they are, it does not take much to slip into a state of mindfulness.</p>
<p>No doing, no planning; just absorbing all of the surroundings, physical and mental, the music, and feeling how the meat-based machine that houses me propels us forward.</p>
<p>On the topic of mindfulness, for the last few months I added a repeat event to my todoist, helping me to spend five minutes every morning before work doing the breathing exercise. More recently I do this without any voice track, but previously Prof. Mark Williams at one point would say (original quote is due to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon_Kabat-Zinn">Jon Kabat-Zinn, PhD</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Each breath a new beginning; each out-breath a letting go.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There’s a whole lot in there. I have spent quite some time with it and I am far from done.</p>
<h3 id="the-blog">The blog</h3>
<p>The first rule of blogging: You don’t blog about blogging.</p>
<p>However, I hope you don’t mind me breaking that rule to mention that in 2016, this blog was viewed 133 thousand times. I already get happy when one other person reads a post. You can imagine how happy it makes me to know that there are even slightly more people who have come here to consume some of the words I have written, and even some who have taken the time to leave behind comments!</p>
<p>The lion’s share of those views were due to focused posts that got picked up by some of the more popular nerd sites. I have to admit that I derived the most enjoyment from the more personal posts that were only read by friends.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, this has to be my most satisfying hobby. Thank you for the crucial role that you who read play in it!</p>
<h3 id="the-new-life">The new life</h3>
<p>In early(ish) 2016, our third daughter, affectionately known as Genetic Offspring Unit #3 (GOU#3 for short) around these parts, <a href="/2016/05/05/weekly-head-voices-106-ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/">was born</a>.</p>
<p>This wonderful little cellular mega-cluster is currently making noises that have the primary purpose of being immensely cute, but are also slowly starting to make sense. Her ambulation capabilities have increased immensely, and she is on the verge of standing up by herself and so we will probably have to re-arrange our interior. Again.</p>
<p>Long ago, <a href="/2011/08/28/the-lowlands-tooth-fairy-37-weekly-head-voices-55/">I wrote here about my unexpected new role as someone else’s Tooth Fairy</a>. In the meantime, working as a part-time tooth fairy and a full-time papa to three little humans has turned out to be a more fulfilling career than I ever could have imagined.</p>
<h1 id="2017-not-much-planned-yet-you">2017: Not much planned yet, you?</h1>
<p>I prefer making resolutions in secret, then carrying them out or not, and only then reporting on them. However, that would mean that I would have to wrap up this post right now, and for that I’m not quite ready yet.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-alcohol-zero">Experiment Alcohol Zero</h2>
<p>One resolution that I am already executing on, is performing an interesting little experiment. After reading about <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/the-running-blog/2014/apr/23/how-does-alcohol-affect-athletic-performance">the effects of alcohol on one’s (running) performance and general energy levels</a>, I have decided to go for 30 days without a drop of alcohol to try and get a subjective idea of its potential impact.</p>
<p>Those of you who have spent more than 8 seconds in my or my blog’s vicinity know that I absolutely adore craft <a href="/tag/beer/">beer</a> (this includes local, but also special beers of the Belgian type) and local wines, both of which are regularly consumed by me and “business partners” during “business lunches” in the not-unattractive local surroundings.</p>
<p>This decision was not taken lightly.</p>
<p>It is mid-morning of day 2 of Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) as I write this. With the air full of smoke due to <a href="/2017/01/04/massive-fires-around-here-thanks-to-firefighters-my-neighbourhood-escaped/">local vegetation fires</a>, I have not been able to go running yet, but I am imagining that my energy lasted later last night, and I got up easier this morning. I have 29 more days to investigate.</p>
<h2 id="reminders-for-a-hopefully-better-life">Reminders for a hopefully better life</h2>
<p>Every day, I remind myself <a href="/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/">to be the kindest I can possibly be to everyone I come into contact with</a>. We have infinite amounts of kindness to spread.</p>
<p>I also remind myself to <a href="/2014/11/03/weekly-head-voices-84-on-being-grateful/">be grateful</a>. It takes continuous practice to identify the many things one can be grateful for every day, but it is definitely worth it.</p>
<p>I often remind GOU#1 (#2 and #3 are not old enough yet for this lesson) that, besides the guidelines above, we have to keep on working on two more related characteristics: being useful, and being likable.</p>
<p>Being useful means continuously developing and refining skills that enable one to contribute value to one’s surroundings. Being likable means understanding and appreciating how we humans stick together. Kindness, see above, is an important component of this.</p>
<p>In 2017, I would like to write more (on this blog probably), and read more.</p>
<h1 id="rapidly-morphing-goalpostsjumping-randomly-through-even-more-randomly-pulsating-hyperspace-with-a-slightly-positive-outlook-at-the-end">Rapidly morphing goalposts jumping randomly through even more randomly pulsating hyperspace, with a slightly positive outlook at the end</h1>
<p>Yes folks, this is going to be my parting thought.</p>
<p>When I was much younger, I used to believe that one’s life could be “cracked”. That is, if you searched, and you worked really hard at understanding yourself, your people and your surroundings, you could come up with some kind of answer with which you would be able to attain contentment.</p>
<p>In the meantime I’ve come to the realisation that that Much Younger Me, although quite dashing, was of course utterly wrong.</p>
<p>Life is utterly dynamic. You Now are a different person from You Last Year. The same goes for people around you, and the same goes for everything around you.</p>
<p>The goal posts are not just moving all the time, they are an illusion flashing in and out of an hallucinogenic and especially dynamic perception.</p>
<p>One trick to help one deal with this, is to stop thinking about goals in the first place, and instead <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">consider the directions of your movement</a>.</p>
<p>Also keep in mind that <a href="/2016/02/02/weekly-head-voices-103-chips/">there are no answers, only choices</a>. You work to make the best ones you can with the means at your disposal at that moment.</p>
<p>Importantly, in this restless environment, some peace can be found by realising that a large part of the restlessness originates from within you. Fortunately, you have slightly more say in you than you have in your surroundings.</p>
<p>What one can do then, is nicely summarised by Prof. Mark Williams in the audio accompanying <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mindfulness-Eight-Week-Finding-Peace-Frantic/dp/1609618955">his mindfulness book</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The deep stillness we seek does not arise because the world is still or the mind is quiet. Stillness is nourished when we allow things to be just as they are for now, in this moment, moment by moment and breath by breath.</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="the-end-for-now">The End (for now)</h1>
<p>Alright friends, that was it from me, for now. I hope that you have the best 2017 possible. I hope especially that your kindness and that of those around you flows deeply and freely.</p>
<p>As a parting gift, here is the high-resolution panoroma I made from the top of Table Mountain, after hiking up Platteklip Gorge with friends:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama-1024x325.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net. Click for high-res."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net. Click for high-res.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>