<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>stilbaai on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/stilbaai/</link><description>Recent content in stilbaai on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 22:24:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/stilbaai/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #234: Huis op die duin</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 22:24:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/</guid><description> Hello and welcome back my friends!
It&amp;rsquo;s 17:50 on Sunday, October 10, 2021 as I write this.
We have just returned from the most amazing spring break in one of our favourite spots. I&amp;rsquo;m relaxing on the sofa, with GOU #3 to my right doing what little digital natives do.
Figure 1: Beach run on Lappiesbaai at low tide is as great as it looks.
I&amp;rsquo;m not sure when exactly this post will be done, but whatever the case may be, it samples, extremely sparsely as always, the period of time from Monday September 27 to Sunday October 10, 2021.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello and welcome back my friends!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s 17:50 on Sunday, October 10, 2021 as I write this.</p>
<p>We have just returned from the most amazing spring break in one of our
favourite spots. I&rsquo;m relaxing on the sofa, with GOU #3 to my right doing what
little digital natives do.</p>








<figure><a href="lappiesbaai-run.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Beach run on Lappiesbaai at low tide is as great as it looks."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Beach run on Lappiesbaai at low tide is as great as it looks.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure when exactly this post will be done, but whatever the case may be,
it samples, extremely sparsely as always, the period of time from Monday
September 27 to Sunday October 10, 2021.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m wrapping this up on Thursday evening, four pretty full days
later. Phoowee!)</p>
<h2 id="strange-days">Strange days</h2>
<p>In the previous edition of the WHV, <a href="/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">I mentioned that I had found a solution for
making my Org mode notes database accessible from my phone</a>.</p>
<p>Well, it&rsquo;s a rather unconventional trick involving CMake, pandoc and Microsoft
Word that you can read about in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">this probably nerdy vxlabs post</a>.</p>
<p>(Back in 2018, I <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">did something similar by exporting my Org mode database to
Apple Notes</a>, which worked well when most of my devices were of Apple
manufacture. Fortunately the Org mode part of the equation, the most important bit,
remains the same.)</p>
<p>Continuing on from the <a href="/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/#this-blog-hopefully-immortalised-on-github">blog mirroring work mentioned in WHV #232</a>, I configured
the necessary github workflows to auto-publish this site to a github.io site.</p>
<p>In other words, if I were to disappear for whatever reason, this blog should
remain available via <a href="https://cpbotha.github.io/">https://cpbotha.github.io/</a> for quite a while longer after
my hosting and domain registration eventually expire.</p>
<h2 id="spring-break">Spring break</h2>
<p>As part of the week-long Sprink break, we spent an absolutely fabulous long
weekend in Stilbaai, more specifically in the Bosbokduin private game reserve,
in a <a href="http://huisopdieduin.co.za/">house with the most amazing views over the ocean</a>.</p>
<p>Although we were there for only a few days, it feels like we were somehow able
to compress the experiences of a substantially longer period into the time at
our disposal.</p>
<p>I am grateful for all of the runs and walks on beautiful trails on various bits
of the coast, notably the trail passing right in front of the house connecting
Stilbaai and Jongensfontein, paddling on the river, lounging on the beach, and
just lots of family time in that beautiful house.</p>
<p>(When I look back at my notes from the return on Sunday, it&rsquo;s quite clear that
we were still on a sort of perfect vacation high.)</p>
<p>What was interesting to me this time, was that almost immediately after the
initial <a href="/tags/disconnecting/">disconnect</a> which thankfully happened quite soon, my brain started
producing strange (as in, far removed from work, and in some cases just plain
unconventional) but quite plausible new (engineering) ideas.</p>
<p>In other words, this is the nerd version of experiencing creativity.</p>
<p>This made me reconsider the effect of spending a fair bit of energy on work
every day.</p>
<p>Of course the picture is almost always complicated, but my work currently
requires a great deal of <em>focused</em> creativity, that is, thought and effort that
goes in one primary direction.</p>
<p>This is great in terms of getting those big things done, and also of
compounding (personal) improvement in that same direction, but the trade-off is
that the energy spent is now spent, and can&rsquo;t go into the exhilarating feeling
of ideas shooting off in different and often new directions.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #219: Stilbaai Easter weekend 12/10</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 19:01:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/</guid><description> This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Monday March 29 to Sunday April 4, 2021.
However, its raison d&amp;rsquo;être is to act as a reminder of the epic weekend in Stilbaai that we have just returned from, and also to practise the borderline (un)justified use of a posh French expression or two.
Figure 1: If morning starts like this, day could turn out OK.
You might remember me mentioning this place for the first time almost exactly a year ago in WHV #191, when we went there for the first time and had to cut our visit short due to the first COVID lockdown.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Monday March 29
to Sunday April 4, 2021.</p>
<p>However, its <em>raison d&rsquo;être</em> is to act as a reminder of the epic weekend in
Stilbaai that we have just returned from, and also to practise the borderline
(un)justified use of a posh French expression or two.</p>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_morning_run.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: If morning starts like this, day could turn out OK."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: If morning starts like this, day could turn out OK.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You might remember me mentioning this place for the first time almost exactly a
year ago in <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">WHV #191</a>, when we went there for the first time and had to cut our
visit short due to the first COVID lockdown.</p>
<p>A few months later, in <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/">WHV #208</a> to be exact, we had the good fortune to return
there, and for me to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/disconnecting/">get disconnected</a> unexpectedly quickly.</p>
<p>This time, exactly 11 WHVs later, we executed a text-book
maximise-your-Easter-weekend <em>manoeuvre</em> as we (the whole clan) left town after
school on Thursday.</p>
<p>Although the roads were quite busy, we did not get caught in any jams, and were
rewarded after a few hours (including a pretty busy stop at Heidelberg (ZA,
haha, I don&rsquo;t drive <em>that</em> fast) for coffee) by finding ourselves safe and sound
somewhere in Stilbaai on the Thursday evening, ready for a LONG weekend of fun
and games.</p>
<p>Oh, and this time <a href="/tags/disconnecting/">the disconnect</a> took place almost immediately upon arrival!</p>
<p>The weekend was pretty much perfect, with all of the stars aligning: The
weather (for a large part thanks to our sun, WHICH IS ONE OF THE STARS ALIGNING
TUN TUN TUUUUUN. Stilbaai is balmy this time of the year!), beautiful
surroundings and, most importantly, all of my clan peeps committed to having
fun.</p>
<p>The specific experiences I will want to remember include but are not limited
to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Morning runs, large parts on the tranquil beach, with its
perfect-for-barefoot-running sand, once also accompanied by GOU#1, who found
it exhilarating in spite of not <em>wanting</em> to run on the beach, because
teenager.</li>
<li>Long days on the beach by the river mouth, with all of my peeps, some of the
time spent trying not to fall from an inflatable <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standup%5Fpaddleboarding">SUP</a>. The general mood on the
beach is truly Laid Back.</li>
<li>Evening walks with the whole clan on that same tranquil, golden beach.</li>
<li>A visit to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stilbaai%5FTidal%5FFish%5FTraps">the ancient intertidal stonewall fish traps in Stilbaai</a>. See below
for a photographic impression.</li>
<li>As it behooves the people from this part of the world, daily fire and braai,
with craft beer and wine. (Also my music playlists, which I&rsquo;m mentioning
here, not because they&rsquo;re loved (they&rsquo;re not), but because they transported
me back into yet older but equally fond memories of more experiences with
friends.)</li>
</ul>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: One of the Stilbaai Tidal Fish Traps. Fish swim into trap when high tide. Fish now trapped, ready for&amp;hellip; next stage."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: One of the Stilbaai Tidal Fish Traps. Fish swim into trap when high tide. Fish now trapped, ready for&hellip; next stage.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>On the return journey, a little bit of our luck ran out as we got caught in the
post-long-weekend jam.</p>
<p>You see, it seems that the whole of Cape Town decided to return home from
various spots on the warmer coast in such a way so as to meet in exactly the
same spot (on the pass between the Hermanus turn-off and Houwhoek) at exactly
the same time (around about lunch).</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure how they coordinated this so perfectly (WhatsApp? maybe Discord?),
but we were definitely part of the project.</p>
<p>Thousands of cars, bumper to bumper, fortunately moving, albeit slowly. We were
going to make it, it would just take a bit longer.</p>
<p>I told my kids &ldquo;This is like life. Sometimes you go really slow, but the trick
is to just keep on going, one foot in front of the other. You&rsquo;ll be surprised
how far you can get.&rdquo;</p>
<p>They were probably not listening. Maybe they&rsquo;ll read it here one day.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the weekend had been so sublime that even the Great
Easter Jam of &lsquo;21 came, and then simply unraveled, just like any other thought
always does during meditation practice.</p>
<p>With that observation similarly unraveling, we have almost reached the end of
the 219th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, with only one more thing to say:</p>
<p><em>À bientôt les amis!</em></p>
<p>(hehe)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #208: Stilbaai</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 10:59:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</guid><description> Welcome back folks!
Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.
It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.
Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.
Running and reading I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, GOU #1 (14) completed her first (virtual) 10km race.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks!</p>
<p>Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.</p>
<p>It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period
Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="skulpiesbaai_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="running-and-reading">Running and reading</h2>
<p>I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> (14) completed her
first (virtual) 10km race.</p>
<p>Her journey started when a friend from school invited her to join the race, at
which point GOU #1 suddenly became much more enthusiastic about running
regularly with her old dad. (that&rsquo;s me)</p>
<p>There is something pretty primal about running with your offspring, an
observation that I might have mentioned before on these pages.</p>
<p>Anyways, after her race she was visibly happy, and also relieved that, in her
words, &ldquo;she didn&rsquo;t die&rdquo;.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m perhaps even more happy about than the preparatory runs together, and
her completing the race, is that since the race we&rsquo;ve been out together for a
run or three.</p>
<p>(Running and reading are two of the most important low-level habits I would
like to try and get my offspring hooked on.)</p>
<h2 id="ieee-vis2020">IEEE VIS2020</h2>
<p>At the start of October, I had a great experience <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#vcbm-2020-virtually">virtually attending the VCBM
2020 conference</a>.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough grade A1 10/10 conferencing for one year, my other
favourite conference, IEEE VIS (for visualization) was also fully virtual this
year in the week of October 26, so again I dove into YouTube streams and
well-organised discord rooms, and again this experience was highly edifying and
enjoyable.</p>
<p>Somehow, it was even <em>more</em> fun than my already optimistic expectations to run
into friends at the conference.</p>
<p>I would like to transfer this one piece of sage advice given by the amazing
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%5Fvan%5FWijk">Prof. Jarke van Wijk</a> during the panel on &ldquo;Why should I stay in academia&rdquo; when
the discussion treated the issue of dealing with rejection, something that is
unfortunately a regular part of most academic careers.</p>
<p>At this point, he was referring specifically to accepted papers and proposals,
but the advice should really be applied to any victory, large or small, in all
walks of life:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Celebrate your victories.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="cycles">Cycles</h2>
<p>You will of course remember that we were fortunate enough to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">spend our last few
days of freedom in Stilbaai,</a> as autumn was arriving, and more acutely right
before the first lockdown started on March 26,</p>
<p>It was really great going back to the exact same house (thanks kind host!),
after months of various levels of lockdown, this time just as spring was really
getting off the ground.</p>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_0181.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I did take work with me for the long weekend, but this time, and quite
unexpectedly, the important <a href="/tags/disconnecting">disconnect</a> happened quite quickly without too much
conscious effort from my side.</p>
<p>If I had to put my finger on it, I would say that getting everyone to go
outside as often as possible on little adventures of various sizes was the
catalyst.</p>
<h2 id="back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">Back to reality: An 18-minute plan for managing your day</h2>
<p>I could not imagine a more sudden transition from the long weekend zen above
than this jump to Peter Bregman&rsquo;s 18 minute plan for planning your work day.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Sometimes, fortunately mostly later in the afternoon, I wonder why my systems
have failed in helping me to keep my eye on that ball for longer. (See <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">my
slippery eel</a> for more struggles.)</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s when I procrastinate quasi-productively by searching online for any new
self-optimisation tricks that I might have missed, and which might constitute
that Last Piece of The Puzzle that will fix this once and for all.</p>
<p>This time, to my great surprise, I did actually run into something 1. that was
written aaaaaall the way back in 2009 and 2. that contained something new that
I had not run into before, namely the &ldquo;refocus&rdquo; reminder.</p>
<p>The refocus reminder is literally an alarm that goes off every hour on the
hour, at which point you explicitly take a step back for a whole minute to
review the past hour, and, if required (most probably the case the later it is
in the day), to re-commit to the following hour.</p>
<p>This reminded me specifically about mindfulness&rsquo;s <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#therunning-and-the-mindful">&ldquo;Each breath a new beginning;
each out-breath a letting go&rdquo;</a>, and more generally about <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">life as eternal
practice</a>.</p>
<p>You can use any sort of timer to do this, but this seemed like a great feature
for the little Lazar Focus app, so I implemented it along with a nice
mindfulness bell sound to add some gravitas to the moment.</p>
<p>If you like, you can read the short summary I wrote about the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/10/24/peter-bregmans-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day-and-the-surprising-power-of-refocus-reminders/">18-minute plan
and refocus reminders over on the LazarFocused blog</a>. There are some other more
widely known but great tips for running your work days more efficiently.</p>
<h2 id="kind-regards">Kind regards</h2>
<p>Folks, thank you very much for joining me here.</p>
<p>The comments section below is ready for your thoughts, if you would like to
externalise them.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #192: COVID-19 part 2.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 11:09:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/</guid><description> A scene from Stilbaai, my number one favourite new vacation destination, taken on the morning after the lockdown had been announced. We were extremely fortunate to spend our last day of freedom in a place like this. Greetings, fellow humans!
It&amp;rsquo;s 16:15 (UTC+2) on Sunday afternoon as I sit here writing this.
The post seems to be mostly planned out, with fragments of text strewn around the editor window right below this sentence.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/stilbaai_preekstoel_hu6ea1a8fe0f433c89b3ea1d175aa8c0a6_1088132_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
A scene from Stilbaai, my number one favourite new vacation destination, taken
on the morning after the lockdown had been announced. We were extremely
fortunate to spend our last day of freedom in a place like this.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Greetings, fellow humans!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s 16:15 (UTC+2) on Sunday afternoon as I sit here writing this.</p>
<p>The post seems to be mostly planned out, with fragments of text strewn around
the editor window right below this sentence.</p>
<p>With sheer luck, I&rsquo;ve managed to find music that interacts well with my current
mood trajectory (finding <em>the right music</em> seems like a truly hard problem),
and at this moment I&rsquo;m still hopeful that I might also have found <a href="/tags/pomodoro/">one whole
pomodoro</a> to work with here.</p>
<p>We are living through some of the most surrealistic times I have ever
experienced.</p>
<p>For friends, for other curious observers and for posterity I think it&rsquo;s now an
even better idea than usual to write down at least some of my observations.</p>
<p>On that note, the older I get, the more clearly I see how the idea of a unified
&ldquo;I&rdquo; going through life is nothing more than an illusion, albeit seemingly
well-made.</p>
<p>In 2014 I <a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">wrote about us being patterns continuously shifting in the sands of
the universe</a>.</p>
<p>Back then, at least if I can go by my writing, it was a dawning
realisation. Now it has become Captain Obvious territory.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS</p>
<p>In this post, I look back at the period of time from Wednesday March 25 to
Sunday April 11.</p>
<h2 id="lockdown-extension">Lockdown extension.</h2>
<p>The South African national lockdown started at midnhight on Thursday, March 26
and would continue for three weeks until April 16.</p>
<p>Of course this virus wasn&rsquo;t magically going to give up and go home after
exactly three weeks.</p>
<p>Just like everyone else, we were only buying time, and I&rsquo;m super happy that we
started when we did.</p>
<p>We know <em>much</em> more now than we knew then. In three weeks more, we&rsquo;ll know even
more.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I&rsquo;ve never before seen the whole of South Africa work
together this well.</p>
<p>There is certaintly some dissent, but by and large the measures seem to be
working, and the curve looks like it is flattening for us.</p>
<p>(There will <em>of course</em> be those, as there always are, who will claim that it
was all much ado about nothing&hellip;)</p>
<p>Although we sort of saw it coming, it was still quite something hearing on
Friday evening, April 10, that the national lockdown would be extended to April
30.</p>
<h2 id="masks4all">#Masks4All</h2>
<p>On March 30, I &ldquo;joined&rdquo; the twitter #masks4all campaign by doing my little bit
to try and convince people everywhere that if <strong>all</strong> of us started wearing
home-made (the good stuff is for the healthcare workers yo!) masks as a rule,
it would contribute substantially to preventing the virus from spreading.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">South Africans, how do
we get our leaders and their advisors to look into <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Masks4All?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Masks4All</a>
as a way to end this lockdown *safely* and get the economy back into action
again? See e.g. <a href="https://t.co/iCMNAwAJhr">https://t.co/iCMNAwAJhr</a>
for a summary. <a
href="https://twitter.com/DrZweliMkhize?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@DrZweliMkhize</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/PresidencyZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@PresidencyZA</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/nicd_sa?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@nicd_sa</a></p>&mdash;
Charl Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a
href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1244511197921185792?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March
30, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>I find this extra important, because it could play a really important role,
together with physical distancing, hand-washing and more, in how we end the
lockdown safely and get our already-less-than-robust economy back up and
running.</p>
<p>At the start it felt like no-one was listening, and I was getting anxious.</p>
<p>SOMEONE WAS WRONG ON THE INTERNET, AND THIS TIME IT WAS SERIOUS!</p>
<p>It really did not help that the <a href="https://www.westerncape.gov.za/gc-news/147/54065">official line of the Western Cape Health
Department on March 29 was warning <em>against</em> masks and
gloves</a>. (I&rsquo;ve archived the
statement in case anyone loses it.)</p>
<p>The point that many people were utterly missing at that point but that is
hopefully now embarrassingly obvious, is that the mask is not there to protect
the wearer, it&rsquo;s there to help protect <em>everyone else</em> from being infected by the
wearer.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a week or so (an eternity in COVID-19 time) to April 10, and South
Africa&rsquo;s very own and very respected health minister Dr Zweli Mkhize started
tweeting the new official line that the department of health now also
recommends that everyone wears cloth masks:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Cloth face mask
recommendations: <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MasksCOVID19?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#MasksCOVID19</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ClothFaceMask?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ClothFaceMask</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/COVID_19_ZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@COVID_19_ZA</a>
<a href="https://twitter.com/HealthZA?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@HealthZA</a> <a
href="https://t.co/ptNsa4oUFl">pic.twitter.com/ptNsa4oUFl</a></p>&mdash; Dr
Zweli Mkhize (@DrZweliMkhize) <a
href="https://twitter.com/DrZweliMkhize/status/1248613456934129667?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April
10, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>See the great <a href="https://masks4all.co/">#masks4all.co</a> for more information.</p>
<p>My (microscopic little) work here is done.</p>
<h2 id="work-exercise-and-the-future-in-captivity">Work, exercise and the future, in captivity.</h2>
<h3 id="remote-work">Remote work.</h3>
<p>In <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#outlook">the previous
WHV</a>, I might have
mentioned remote work once or twice.</p>
<p>Well, since then it feels like I&rsquo;ve spent at least three and a half years
working remotely, hard.</p>
<p>I underestimated the amount of automatic, implicit, in-person communication
that happens when you&rsquo;re at the office.</p>
<p>All of that currently has to happen via various video meetings, instant
messenging, emails, and then many more instant messages during the rest of the
day.</p>
<p>In its new form, all of this communication takes quite an amount of time and
energy. It feels like I can only bunker down late morning to start on the
actual work.</p>
<p>(Microsoft Teams is our tool for all of this. Whilst it&rsquo;s not perfect, it has
been serving us quite well.)</p>
<p>In spite of the feeling that communication is taking up significantly more time
and energy, my perception is that, over-all, we engineers get a lot more done
in this new configuration.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I am hopeful that continued practice will reduce the perceived
additional communication effort.</p>
<h3 id="exercise">Exercise.</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s not allowed to leave the house even for exercise, and so my running has
taken quite a hit.</p>
<p>I have had to resort to running circles around the house for half an hour at a
time, which, in spite of me usually really enjoying the monotony of
road-running, is quite a challenge.</p>
<p>On the other hand, there are people who are stuck in apartments and <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/mar/21/man-runs-marathon-on-7-metre-balcony-during-french-lockdown">then run
42km on the
balcony</a>,
and there&rsquo;s even the South African <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/southafrica/comments/fzvtak/south_african_runner_from_george_runs_100_miles/">Eddie Mouton who ran 160km in his
yard</a>.</p>
<p>The elliptical trainer which we bought on July 31 of 2007 (it&rsquo;s the FINNLO
crosstrainer 3252), and for the almost 13 years since then has been nothing
more than an overpriced clothing and towel hanger, has seen more actual
exercise use in the past weeks than during its whole lifetime up to now.</p>
<p>One great upshot of all of this is that we more often train together, or at
least close enough for a high-five now and then.</p>
<h3 id="the-future">The future.</h3>
<p>As I alluded to in the previous <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#outlook">WHV
#191</a>, and
especially as the lockdown has now been extended, giving us even more time to
practise and build habits, I would really like to know how much of what we
learn and experience now is going to stick in the post-covid-19-era?</p>
<p>Noticing how we have to pay much more attention to how exactly we communicate,
realising how much work can actually be fit into a day without too many
interruptions, and seeing how quickly nature uses this time to recover from our
normally incessant onslaught, all lead me to think that we should not stop
analysing and discussing the changes that COVID-19 has brought.</p>
<p>Do you think we&rsquo;ll just flip back to the old normal as soon as we (hopefully)
get through this, or do you think we can look forward to a slightly upgraded
humanity?</p>
<h2 id="thats-all-folks">That&rsquo;s all folks!</h2>
<p>Because this post had already grown substantially larger than I had intended, I
just removed two whole subsections, the beefiest one about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niklas_Luhmann">Niklas
Luhmann</a> and <a href="https://writingcooperative.com/zettelkasten-how-one-german-scholar-was-so-freakishly-productive-997e4e0ca125">his amazing
Zettelkästen / external
brain</a>.</p>
<p>Do not fear, they&rsquo;ll probably make an appearance in a subsequent WHV, or
perhaps even separate posts.</p>
<p>As some of you might have read previously on this blog, the struggle in my head
between these longer form mish-mash-life-snapshot WHV posts on the one hand and
more topic-focused shorter posts on the other has been going on for years, and
will hopefully continue for years more.</p>
<p>(I say hopefully, because that means I might still be posting as well.)</p>
<p>This specific thought is still developing, but I might be starting an
experiment where I do try to write some shorter, more focused posts.</p>
<p>I will keep you up to date!</p>
<p>Ok reader, whoever and wherever you are, I wish you the very best that humanity
has to offer!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>