<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Lex Fridman on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/lex-fridman/</link><description>Recent content in Lex Fridman on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 22:05:52 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/lex-fridman/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #239: Embarrassing finitude</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 22:05:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</guid><description>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.
Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay.
House gets more energy reserves In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three
weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.</p>










<figure><a href="bettys-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_74eb8d485118227a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_82bbe2abd04f454.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_d618afba10beff8e.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_ad4c99d4cb012cd8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_82bbe2abd04f454.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&rsquo;s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Fiery sunset in Betty&rsquo;s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="house-gets-more-energy-reserves">House gets more energy reserves</h2>
<p>In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium
ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of
the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</p>
<p>The complete stack looks as follows, with the new UP5000 on top, and the two
&ldquo;old&rdquo; US3000 units (3.5kWh each) under it:</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_c456be51232ea52.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_907b8abe3409612e.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_cf07fa7f64eb5e01.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_22ea2d044cfbe8ef.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_907b8abe3409612e.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A cluster of lithium ion house batteries." width="400px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A cluster of lithium ion house batteries.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I can already see the positive effect of this on the daily line chart of solar
energy stored: Where previously there were gaps, because the battery was full,
the hot water geysers were either already hot or had not come on yet (in our
house, these act as water batteries on fixed charge times) and we were not
drawing much load, the gaps are smoothed out and the area under the curve is
consistently higher.</p>
<h2 id="dot-dot-dot-while-human-has-to-make-peace-with-limited-energy-reserves">&hellip; while human has to make peace with limited energy reserves</h2>
<p>As a human, you have to deal with a limited amount of energy every day, as if
the fact that your total time on earth was embarrassingly finite was not
challenging enough.</p>
<p>In other words, during one&rsquo;s waking hours, of which one gets a limited number,
one can&rsquo;t rely on operating at the highest energy output all of the time.</p>
<p>As far as I can surmise, one can increase one&rsquo;s daily energy through the
consistent and continuous application of positive lifestyle choices.</p>
<p>This can be hard work, and due to the infernal complexity of organics (have you
looked at a <a href="http://biochemical-pathways.com/">map of metabolic pathways recently</a>? &ndash; you should really go take a
look, it&rsquo;s complicated but also really interesting) and the effects of aging
maybe even an intractable problem, and as if that&rsquo;s not enough, the right
lifestyle can be extremely boring (to those around you).</p>
<p>My mornings usually start pretty nicely, but by the middle of the afternoon my
brain starts disassembling itself anywhere from just after lunch to later in
the afternoon.</p>
<p>What I have recently started noticing, is that when I enjoy one of those highly
productive days with focus straying sharp until late in the afternoon, I pretty
much have to tone it down a bit the next day.</p>
<p>I can still do good work, but I do need to approach the day in a slightly more
relaxed fashion in order to make it through the whole thing in one piece, and
to increase the chances of having a highly productive day after the toned down
one.</p>
<h2 id="the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">The rickety raft of life directions and priorities</h2>
<p>Staying on the theme of limited energy, but taking many steps back from the
cyclical alternate day grinding effect, I&rsquo;ve had to make peace with another
phenomenon:</p>
<p>Again thanks to embarrassingly limited energy, one can only focus on a subset
of one&rsquo;s life directions and priorities at any one time.</p>
<p>For example, when your children are younger, it&rsquo;s normal to dedicate a
substantial chunk of your time to them.</p>
<p>Between that and the necessary parts of work, not much time is left for one&rsquo;s
own hobbies, like Trying To Be a Better Human, or for other worthy goals, like
writing that novel(la) (short story, err or maybe just a nice haiku).</p>
<p>Conversely, when you&rsquo;re training for an important cycle race (not me, a
friend), some of those other dimensions by definition spend time on the
dimensional back burner.</p>
<p>So while you probably have a longer list of priorities which are all very
important to you, you have no choice but to make peace with the fact that at
any one point in time, you can only deal with a fairly narrow subset.</p>
<p>To me it looks the most important to make peace with this fact, and to treat it
as a deliberate and honest choice.</p>
<p>Oh and don&rsquo;t flip flop too much. (that&rsquo;s meant for me)</p>
<h2 id="young-human-wise-beyond-her-years">Young human wise beyond her years</h2>
<p><a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU#1</a> and I were chatting in the car, on way back from one of her social
commitments.</p>
<p>We talked about sleep. (Had she gotten enough?)</p>
<p>She mentioned people that get by on six hours per night and seem to get more
done&hellip;</p>
<p>As I was preparing to attempt commenting Socratically about this, she
pre-empted me by volunteering that when she sleeps well, and for much longer
than six hours, she experiences that she is better with other humans, and that
she feels emotions more intensely.</p>
<p>Goodness!</p>
<h2 id="two-pages-per-week">Two pages per week</h2>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. on the topic of GOU #1 and how best to spend my puny energy:</p>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/#gou-1-reveals-her-plans-and-makes-us-think--more">WHV #194</a> when GOU #1 revealed her cunning plan for
completing a PhD, part of which was writing only 136 words a day for a year,
leaving the two sandwich years for respectively planning and proofreading,
leading to a perfect thesis.</p>
<p>In the recent <a href="https://lexfridman.com/tim-urban/">Lex Fridman podcast #264 with Tim Urban</a>, he of <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/">Wait but why</a> fame,
they start <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Jd7fJgFkPU&amp;t=7166s">talking in-depth about procrastination at the 2 hour mark</a>. (relax,
you can listen to it later. <strong>&lt;ba dum tiss!&gt;</strong>)</p>
<p>(Urban considers himself a procrastinator, but he is a deep thinker, and so this
is a pretty interesting bit of conversation.)</p>
<p>He starts off with the example of a writer who is able to commit to producing
only two pages <em>per week</em>, and by consistently hitting this pretty modest
sounding goal, is able to prepare a book per year.</p>
<p>Glossing over the fact that 200 pages is perhaps not a very <em>impressive</em> book, at
least in terms of girth, publishing one every two years would be frankly
amazing.</p>
<p>He then talks about this idea of being able to attain something substantial and
worthwile by consistently chipping away.</p>
<p>He is clearly searching for the right word,
<a href="https://youtu.be/0Jd7fJgFkPU?t=7203">but then comes up with <em>compiling</em></a>.</p>
<p>I would really like to think that he was in fact searching for our old friend
<a href="/tags/compounding"><em>compounding</em></a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #237: Don't step over the thing</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 22:29:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/</guid><description>Well hello there and welcome to the first Weekly Head Voices of the year 2022!
Figure 1: So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay.
Where we usually pretend that a WHV covers a certain period of time since the previous one, this one will simply engage in some excessive but pretty skillful hand-waving and say that if you read it and the 2021 to 2022 year transition post, you should be more or less up to date with the state of this nation up to Sunday, January 30, 2022.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well hello there and welcome to the first Weekly Head Voices of the year 2022!</p>










<figure><a href="stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu_9866263410c58c6b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu_9f59b96960f2cf8f.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu_ce1bc52f149811aa.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu_e4ea40aad9c981ff.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu_9f59b96960f2cf8f.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&rsquo;s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&rsquo;s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Where we usually pretend that a WHV covers a certain period of time since the
previous one, this one will simply engage in some excessive but pretty skillful
hand-waving and say that if you read it and the <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/">2021 to 2022 year transition
post</a>, you should be more or less up to date with the state of this nation up to
Sunday, January 30, 2022.</p>
<h2 id="eaz-and-sleep">EAZ and sleep</h2>
<p><a href="/tags/eaz/">EAZ (Experiment Alcohol Zero - no alcohol for at least a month but usually
more)</a> is still going strong, and it&rsquo;s getting harder for me to ignore the fact
that it&rsquo;s (again) having a drastic impact on my sleep quality.</p>
<p>Where I normally am quite chuffed to wake up feeling that I&rsquo;ve had a solid
night of sleep, these days it feels like I&rsquo;m almost guaranteed a great night of
shut-eye as long as I can get to bed on time.</p>
<h2 id="gou-updates">GOU updates</h2>
<p>In other much more important news, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> has left the nest.</p>
<p>Ok fortunately only sort of&hellip; She now spends her weeks in the school&rsquo;s
dormitory.</p>
<p>They are extremely well looked-after, and she gets to participate even more
fully in school activities where previously this was a bit constrained by the 1
to 1.5 hour travel time (school bus in traffic) involved.</p>
<p>We do miss her quite a lot in the weeks.</p>
<p>In her absence, GOU #2 (2IC, IOW) has quickly taken on a new role, which is
interesting to see.</p>
<p>GOU #3 has just started with Grade R (first year of &ldquo;big school&rdquo;), and it looks
like she&rsquo;s taken to it like a fish to water.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a lot more fun now with both #2 and #3 in the car in the mornings,
although we could probably do without all the karma loss I suffer in traffic
every morning. The 4km from my house to school can easily take up to 25
minutes, during which I&rsquo;m obviously surrounded by people who clearly can&rsquo;t
drive.</p>
<h2 id="the-apple-doesn-t-fall-far-from-the-tree">The apple doesn&rsquo;t fall far from the tree</h2>
<p>At the start of 2019 I decided for some or other reason that I really wanted to
know how my branch of the Botha family connected to the rest of the tree.</p>
<p>Botha is a pretty common surname down here.</p>
<p>Many Botha&rsquo;s probably know that we are the descendants of <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Both-15">Friedrich Both</a>, a
soldier who came to the Cape from Wagenheim (from the Thuringen region of
Germany) in 1678 to assist the Dutch colonists.</p>
<p>OR ARE WE?</p>
<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23948326/">A 2013 study by Greeff and Erasmus, titled <em>Appel Botha: The abc of a three
hundred year old divorce case</em></a>, showed that Theunis Botha, the first of four
sons of Friedrich Both and his Dutch wife, Maria Kickers (divorced from Jan
Cornelisz because they could not have children), was in fact the extra-marital
product of Maria&rsquo;s relationship with Ferdinandus Appel!</p>
<p>DUN DUN DUUUUUUUN!</p>
<p>According to the study, Theunis Appel is responsible for roughly half (38000) of all
of the Botha&rsquo;s (78000) living in 2013.</p>
<p>Returning to my branch all the way down here: My uncle E was so kind to send me
notes he made of the gravestones on one of the farms my ancestors lived on,
including full names and dates of birth and death of a number of said
ancestors. As you might realise, full names and birth / death dates are genealogy gold.</p>
<p>My aunt M&rsquo;s many stories helped to fill in any further gaps, especially by
confirming identities through matching full names with nick names.</p>
<p>Although initially I was unable to make the connection to the greater Botha
tree using this information, the <a href="https://www.myheritage.com/">MyHeritage</a> databases, and various bits of
information I could get from older clan members, I recently picked up my notes
again (after a two year hiatus!) and was suddenly able to make a single
high-impact connection (my great-great-grandfather) that I previously missed.</p>
<p>Long story short, the moment I did this all of the fragments came together, and
I&rsquo;m now able to say with reasonable confidence that <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Appel-29">Ferdinandus Appel</a> and <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Kickers-1">Maria
Kickers</a> are my great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-grandparents.</p>
<p>DUN DUN DUUUUUUUUUN!</p>
<h2 id="i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">I don&rsquo;t want to step over the thing</h2>
<p>At the end of their <a href="https://lexfridman.com/sam-harris/">3 hour long podcast interview from May</a>, Lex Fridman asks
Sam Harris one of his standard questions (you can listen to the bit in question
<a href="https://youtu.be/4dC_nRYIDZU?t=11241">precisely here</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is the meaning of life?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In almost typical Sam Harris fashion, he replies that it&rsquo;s the wrong question.</p>
<p>Less cryptically, Sam explains that if you&rsquo;re searching for that mythical
<em>meaning of life</em> that&rsquo;s going to make everything better, you might be doing it
wrong.</p>
<p>In his words (which I have transcribed and cleaned up a little bit especially
for you):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You don&rsquo;t have to live with the illusion anymore that you need a good enough
reason and that things are going to get better when you do get those reasons.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a mirage-like quality to every future attainment and every future
breakthrough and every future peak experience that eventually you get the
lesson that you never quite arrive.</p>
<p><strong>You don&rsquo;t arrive until you cease to step over the present moment in search of
the next thing.</strong></p>
<p><strong>We&rsquo;re constantly stepping over the thing that we think we&rsquo;re seeking in the
act of seeking it.</strong> [ed: my emphasis. I loved this bit]</p>
<p>&hellip;</p>
<p>You can&rsquo;t actually become happy. You can only be happy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>His words hit home for me.</p>
<p>Dear readers, I truly wish you an abundance of recognizing the thing, and of
<em>being</em> happy.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #203: Spiritual</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 10:06:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</guid><description> Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&amp;rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&amp;rsquo;s magic.
Dear friends,
It brings me joy to meet you here again.
Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10 to Sunday September 6, 2020.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="jonkershoek_magic_20200901.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu_28595f28cd694315.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu_5fc03e24e413cf6a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu_5321de94fb7dcccf.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu_4685e595358ca61c.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu_5fc03e24e413cf6a.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&rsquo;s magic."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&rsquo;s magic.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>It brings me joy to meet you here again.</p>
<p>Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will
attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10
to Sunday September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>If I were in your shoes, I would hop skip and jump selectively over the
hopefully not too unhelpfully titled headings.</p>
<p>In order to reduce this wall of text somewhat, I have pre-emptively moved a
sub-section or two to the next edition of the WHV.</p>
<p><em>Dear Charl of the Future,</em></p>
<p><em>You have no choice. (also no free will haha) I am writing this for you, so you
better read every last bit.</em></p>
<p><em>I am watching you.</em> 👀</p>
<h2 id="i-m-sorry-but-it-really-is-just-quite-complicated">I&rsquo;m sorry, but it really is just quite complicated</h2>
<p>I would like to kick this off with the following cartoon by Wiley Miller, which
entered my information field of view via dr topol&rsquo;s tweet stream. (don&rsquo;t worry,
this came in via my rss reader. i have not returned to twitter.)</p>










<figure><a href="science_vs_everything_else.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu_ea956afa5c76d839.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu_447c9ceb699dd34c.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu_75ab4297e7442f6.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu_3bf24d9f94823e4f.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu_447c9ceb699dd34c.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It is ironic that the people who get it, already got it, but that the people who
really should get it, won&rsquo;t get it.</p>
<p>As is the case with many of these efforts, i guess that the best we can hope
for is that some of those on the borders between the aforementioned two groups
might be gently encouraged to gravitate towards the light.</p>
<h3 id="the-giant-band-aid-phenomenon">the giant band-aid phenomenon</h3>
<p>Related to the cartoon above, it is quite interesting to me how often
well-meaning people desire to come up with a giant band-aid for any current
problem.</p>
<p>Climate change? Inequality? Surely if we just find a band-aid big
enough we can make the problem go away!</p>
<p>There really is no band-aid.</p>
<h2 id="on-the-minimum-unit-of-focus">On the minimum unit of focus</h2>
<p>Somewhere in week 34 i was struggling to wrap up a piece of programming work
that i had been struggling with for a few days, in-between meetings and a whole
smorgasbord of other modern interruptions.</p>
<p>Finally i decided to bust out the little focus tool that i shall not name here,
because that&rsquo;s not the point.</p>
<p>The point is rather that i created an interruption-free block of time and then
wrapped up the stupid programming problem decisively, there and then.</p>
<p>Relieved that it was finally done, I did feel stupid that it had taken me that
long to just shut off those damn interruptions.</p>
<p>The experience did remind me of the following cartoon by <a href="https://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/">the slightly
disgruntled scientist</a>. It describes <strong>extremely</strong> well how a single little
interruption can derail a whole constellation of mental models in an instant.</p>
<p>Click or tap to zoom in, or skip past if you know this:</p>










<figure><a href="ProgrammerInterrupted.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted_hu_34eca978376a1d8a.png 480w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted.png"
            

         width="30%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>I have found that the absolute minimum block of distraction-free time i need to
do reliably something worthwhile is about an hour.</p>
<p>A large part of my job is indeed handling the information that arrives via all
of the those pesky interruptions, but sometimes i wonder if there&rsquo;s not a
better way to reconcile these two facets.</p>
<p>Very much related to this phenomenon, is falling into the morning distraction
trap, something which is probably familiar to a number of you. (future charl,
you don&rsquo;t count.)</p>
<p>It goes like this: i arrive at work (or these days, i walk a few metres on from
the kitchen into the guest bedroom / home office), and then i start the day
with meetings, microsoft teams chats, and emails.</p>
<p>If I&rsquo;m not careful, I get stuck in this reactive mode, forgetting until far too
late in the day to eject from the reactive-jet for some of them juicy focus
hours.</p>
<p>#feelsbadman</p>
<p>Just this past week, I decided on Thursday and Friday to start work directly on
my main project, ignoring emails and chats and any other distractions until the
first stand-up meeting at 9:00.</p>
<p>Just priming my mind like this for slightly more than an hour was enough to
give the whole day a flavour of focus and intentionality.</p>
<p>It feels like I forget this lesson every other day.</p>
<p>How do you manage this?</p>
<h2 id="on-the-opposite-of-focus">On the opposite of focus</h2>
<p>Sort of inspired by <a href="https://youtu.be/0m3hGZvD-0s">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s deliberate scheduling of a shallow work
session</a> after the day&rsquo;s deep work, I was pleasantly surprised during a past few
evening sessions where I combined an entertaining DJ Set on the second screen
with some actual programming work on the main.</p>
<p>Somehow the fully intentional addition of distracting entertainment, and
importantly the <em>acceptance</em> that the work would necessarily be approached with
a leisurely attitude, I got a surprising amount of extra work done, and
experienced the whole session as relaxing.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to file this under &ldquo;101 stupid but effective tricks to fool your mind
into being more useful&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Let me know if you try this, or if you knew this all along and <em>that&rsquo;s</em> how you
manage everything so well!</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://lexfridman.com/podcast/">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s podcasts</a> are edifying and humanity-affirming. Try them if
you haven&rsquo;t yet.</p>
<h2 id="on-divide-and-conquer-for-the-email">On divide and conquer for the email</h2>
<p>Spontaneously in the night somewhere during the past weeks, I had the idea that
it was time to split my <a href="https://www.stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> work email account from the rest of my
email empire (which is partially also work, because vxlabs, but not my main
job).</p>
<p>I did this because the account I use to manage everything, the <a href="/tags/fastmail/">fastmail one</a>,
was becoming far too chaotic.</p>
<p>(Back in the TU Delft days, an adventure that ended now almost 7 years ago, I
also used to sport an e-mail split.)</p>
<p>My perception now is that I&rsquo;m working against the idea of the whole being
greater than the sum of the parts, i.e. the whole chaos is perhaps worse than
the two smaller chaos explosions by themselves.</p>
<p>(That&rsquo;s a pretty convoluted way to think about &ldquo;divide and conquer&rdquo;, isn&rsquo;t it?)</p>
<p>Also, the dream of being able to search through all of my email and actually
finding stuff is not being realised.</p>
<p>Email searching these days is usually a last resort, because I have a pretty
good <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">personal knowledge management system</a>. It could also be that fastmail
search is not as clever as gmail search.</p>
<p>In the weeks since I did this split (my notes tell me this happened on Friday,
August 21, 2020 at around 8:30 in the morning), I have noticed that my Stone
Three email is now under control, while my personal email is slightly out of
control, which is an improvement.</p>
<p>I have noticed that I do in fact apply a whole different mode of cognition and
context to the handling of work email than I do to personal/work-ish email.</p>
<p>A further advantage is that I can now focus on mastering the way of life that
is called Outlook. The first artifact I have to show for this is a pretty
complicated blog post in the drafts folder that shows how you can link to
arbitrary outlook items (in the latest outlook) from anywhere, in my case of
course Emacs.</p>
<h2 id="life-progress-update">Life progress update</h2>
<p>During the past several weeks, I passed a birthday.</p>
<p>As one bestie remarked, I am now just past the halfway mark, at least by one
pretty optimistic estimate of the total duration of me.</p>
<p>Anyways, moving on&hellip;</p>
<p>I took the largest part of the day off to go run the in the mountains here in my
backyard.</p>
<p>The route that I took for the first time, and which caused a considerable
amount of enjoyment, could be described by Watsonia, Baboon traverse, Leopard
Loop, Caracal, Protea, Sugarbird.</p>
<p>Making time for outdoorsy activities on your birthday: Two WHV thumbs up, would
do again.</p>
<p>Thanks to the <a href="http://www.workoutdoors.net/">WorkOutDoors Apple Watch app</a>, which I bought two years ago but
have never used, I did not get lost like I usually do when attempting trail
runs.</p>
<p>The app displays brilliant vector maps on your watch, optionally overlaid with
GPX routes supplied by generous friends.</p>
<p>After the birthday run, I use it again on more trails (see photo at start of
post) to run almost like someone who actually possesses a sense of
direction.</p>
<p>Technological augmentation FTW!</p>
<h2 id="here-s-to-a-more-regular-return">Here&rsquo;s to a more regular return</h2>
<p>Thank you for working through this mishmash with me!</p>
<p>We are now caught up until Sunday, September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>At this stage, I would have preferred to post more coherent little posts more
often, but I seem to find myself in a loop of slightly too much busyness (and
other issues), which ironically is contributing to my need to write more, but
which is taking up so much time and so many mental cycles that blog-writing
opportunities are hard to create and make use of.</p>
<p>Anyways&hellip; at least the overfull post-pipeline fence has now been cleared.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you equanimity, kindness and health.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next connection.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #202: I don't even have to miss Dr Topol!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 22:16:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/</guid><description>Welcome everyone to this, the two hundred and second edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 27 to Sunday August 9 of the year of our simulation-running overlords 2020.
Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome everyone to this, the two hundred and second edition of the Weekly Head
Voices, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 27 to Sunday August 9 of
the year of our simulation-running overlords 2020.</p>










<figure><a href="closeup_prot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_d89573766f676725.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_993a91b5290b8eed.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_464ae933d5fcdd43.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_3e99996eb6e88668.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu_993a91b5290b8eed.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="shape-up-stop-running-in-circles-and-ship-work-that-matters">Shape Up: Stop Running in Circles and Ship Work that Matters</h2>
<p>After it having spent a few quality months in my to-do list, I finally got
around to reading <a href="https://basecamp.com/shapeup">the Shape Up book by Ryan Singer</a>.</p>
<p>(You can too, by clicking on that link, it&rsquo;s free!)</p>
<p>This book documents the development methodology that the folks over at
37signals, also the original makers of <a href="https://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a>, <a href="https://basecamp.com/">Basecamp</a>, and most
recently the new email re-imagining <a href="https://hey.com/">HEY</a>, have evolved over the years.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not currently using any of those artifacts, but RoR has made (and is
probably still making) a significant impact on the technology landscape, and
the other products are truly impressive in their own right.</p>
<p>My point is, the 37signals company ships high-impact products like it&rsquo;s
nobody&rsquo;s business, so one should probably pay attention if they are willing to
explain to the rest of us how they are able to perform this feat so
consistently.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re involved in software development, or are interested, then this
compact book is worth your time.</p>
<p>However, until you can get around to it, I present to you the book&rsquo;s own
bullet-list summary (you&rsquo;ll find it in the conclusions chapter), where I&rsquo;ve
embellished each bullet with my from-memory explanation.</p>
<dl>
<dt>Shaped versus unshaped work</dt>
<dd>In Shape Up, each project is a user-visible
feature that can be done in 6 weeks or less. Senior devs in the company
<em>shape</em> the work, which means that they derisk and write down enough to
delineate the work, to specify the parameters, but not so much that it has
been pinned down. The team that gets the project assigned is given free reign
as to <em>how</em> exactly they fill in the space delineated by the shaping.</dd>
<dt>Setting appetites instead of estimates</dt>
<dd>Instead of specifying a feature,
and then estimating how much time it will take (feature first, number
second), Shape Up suggests rather determining at management level how much
appetite / motivation there is for a feature, up to a maximum of 6 weeks,
knowing that the feature will be <em>hammered</em> down to fit into the appetite for
it (number first, feature second).</dd>
<dt>Designing at the right level of abstraction</dt>
<dd>As mentioned above, the
shaping process has to reach the Goldilocks level somewhere between abstract
and concrete. Enough detail so there are no surprises that could risk the
success of the project, but little enough so that the team has the freedom to
construct a solution independently and in a more data-driven fashion.</dd>
<dt>Concepting with breadboards and fat marker sketches</dt>
<dd>These are practical
tricks to keep the detail level under control. For example, during shaping, a
<strong>fat marker</strong> is used to draw UI ideas to prevent the shapers from inking in
too much detail.</dd>
<dt>Making bets with a capped downside (the circuit breaker) and honoring uninterrupted time</dt>
<dd>This
is pretty hardcore. If a project runs over its time (e.g. 6 weeks), it is
cancelled, that is, moth-balled. End of story. As a corollary, teams are not
to be interrupted during their project cycle.</dd>
<dt>Choosing the right cycle length (six weeks)</dt>
<dd>Six weeks is the maximum time
a team will get to finish a feature. This seems to be the sweet spot for
features that are significant enough to be interesting, but don&rsquo;t get too big
to manage.</dd>
<dt>A cool-down period between cycles</dt>
<dd>After every six week cycle, all teams
get two weeks of cool-down time. This is to be used for fixing bugs, writing
tests, doing spikes, and just generally recovering from the feature
development cycle.</dd>
<dt>Breaking projects apart into scopes</dt>
<dd>As a team works on a certain feature,
the sub-tasks that they formulate as they work, can be naturally grouped into
thematic scopes. It&rsquo;s important that these emergent groupings are closely
monitored and updated. They are useful for understanding the feature, and for
reporting on progress.</dd>
<dt>Downhill versus uphill work and communicating about unknowns</dt>
<dd>The team
gives <em>asynchronous</em> feedback on project progress by plotting each scope on a
<a href="https://basecamp.com/features/hill-charts">hill chart</a>. To me this is yet another interesting and useful concept from the
book. If a scope is somewhere on the uphill part, there are still unknowns
that have to be investigated. Once the team thinks there are no more
unknowns, a scope can be moved past the top and somewhere onto the downhill
section.</dd>
<dt>Scope hammering to separate must-haves from nice-to-haves</dt>
<dd>In this case,
scope is used in the more traditional software development sense, and scope
hammering refers to the action of whittling down features until a project
fits into the time allotted to it.</dd>
</dl>
<p>At work, we are currently experimenting with elements of this methodology for a
new product we&rsquo;re working on. I&rsquo;m curious to see how much of this will work in
our setup. It sure looks good on paper!</p>
<p>(The book impressed me further with its chapter containing practical advice on
how to implement various levels of Shape Up in organizations of various types
and sizes. Super pragmatic!)</p>
<h2 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion Effect</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently reading the organizational psychologist Adam Grant&rsquo;s book <a href="https://www.adamgrant.net/give-and-take">Give
and Take</a>.</p>
<p>In this book he describes the classic study led by Harvard psychologist Robert
Rosenthal, where he told the teachers of 18 different classrooms that 20
percent of their children had scored high on a Harvard aptitude test, when in
fact they had been randomly chosen.</p>
<p>In spite of being <em>randomly chosen</em>, those children showed consistently higher
performance than their peers, even when they were measured years later.</p>
<p>From Grant&rsquo;s book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Harvard test was discerning: when the students took the cognitive ability
test a year later, the bloomers [the randomly selected kids, ed.] improved more
than the rest of the students. The bloomers gained an average of twelve IQ
points, compared with average gains of only eight points for their
classmates. The bloomers outgained their peers by roughly fifteen IQ points in
first grade and ten IQ points in second grade. Two years later, the bloomers
were still outgaining their classmates. The intelligence test was successful in
identifying high-potential students: the bloomers got smarter &ndash; and at a faster
rate than their classmates</p>
</blockquote>
<p>and then a paragraph or two later:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Teachers&rsquo; beliefs created self-fulfilling prophecies. When teachers believed
their students were bloomers, they set high expectations for their success. As
a result, the teachers engaged in more supportive behaviors that boosted the
students&rsquo; confidence and enhanced their learning and development. Teachers
communicated more warmly to the bloomers, gave them more challenging
assignments, called on them more often, and provided them with more
feedback. Many experiments have replicated these effects, showing that teacher
expectations are especially important for improving the grades and intelligence
test scores of low-achieving students and members of stigmatized minority
groups.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just to reiterate: These kids were randomly selected, but just because their
teachers <em>thought</em> that they had scored higher on an aptitude test and hence
treated them differently, they started and then kept out-performing their peers
for years.</p>
<p>Grant writes that similar experiments have been successfully performed in different
learning contexts, and the results were always the same.</p>
<p>This really blows my mind folks. I hope I can keep this knowledge close.</p>
<h2 id="yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">Yet another social media fast because you have to keep on doing them</h2>
<p><a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">The Great Social Media Fast of 2019</a> really was great when it started, but it
unfortunately fizzled out a few months later, probably when the end-of-the-year
vacation started.</p>
<p>When COVID-19 hit, I had such a need for up-to-the-minute news that my phone
soon had twitter almost permanently on position #1 of the app suggestions you
get when you swipe down.</p>
<p>Fast-forward another few months, and I was again stuck in TwiFRaF-Yo like it
was nobody&rsquo;s business.</p>
<p>Anyways, this weekend I had some serious discussions with myself, during which
I <em>again</em> had to convince myself that the select few jewels of Twitter (Dr
Topol, I salute you) and the rest of TwiFRaF-Yo did not even come close to
justifying the amount of mental cycles I was spending.</p>
<p>Fortunately I won that debate, and so now I&rsquo;m again officially on a social
media fast, during which I have resolved to read more books, blogs and other
long-form content, and to write more notes and blogs.</p>
<p>My brain already feels substantially more roomy and relaxed than it did a mere
day ago.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I didn&rsquo;t mention one of my favourite College Humor skits
in this context:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315"
src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/md4kM9AKjHs" frameborder="0"
allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
allowfullscreen></iframe>
<h3 id="a-not-quite-satisfactory-solution-for-not-having-to-miss-dr-topol">A not quite satisfactory solution for not having to miss Dr Topol</h3>
<p>Dr Topol did briefly complicate my temporary exit.</p>
<p>How was I going to keep up to date with his twitter stream without using the
twitter app and getting sucked in?</p>
<p>Unfortunately, my inoreader &ldquo;supporter&rdquo; subscription does not include its
social media subscription function that does exactly what I need, and the
upgrade is $50 per year instead of my current $20.</p>
<p>While I think about this, I&rsquo;ve activated <a href="https://ifttt.com/applets/xcHFiVvR-get-an-email-when-there-s-a-new-tweet-from-a-specific-username">the IFTTT twitter to email thingy</a>.</p>
<p>This sends me an email for <em>each</em> tweet, which constitutes a whole new problem
in itself.</p>
<h3 id="inoreader-satisfaction-with-a-side-of-retail-therapy">Inoreader satisfaction with a side of retail therapy</h3>
<p><em>&hellip; 8 hours pass after this post was published &hellip;</em></p>
<p>Narrator: <em>It became a whole new problem in itself.</em></p>
<p>Dr Topol can&rsquo;t stop tweeting admittedly truly interesting health- and
covid-related research, but the format of one email per tweet is indeed not
going to cut it.</p>
<p>I have deactivated that IFTTT thingy, and upgraded my inoreader subscription to
pro.</p>
<p>This is where I read all my blog subscriptions when I make time for that, so
having Dr Topol&rsquo;s feed there as well makes a great deal more sense.</p>
<h2 id="an-ai-to-fall-in-love--with">An AI to fall in love (with)</h2>
<p><a href="https://lexfridman.com/">Lex Fridman</a> is another of the internet&rsquo;s jewels, who is fortunately accessible
via long-form podcast.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://lexfridman.com/matt-botvinick/">episode #106</a>, he talks with <a href="https://hai.stanford.edu/people/matthew-botvinick">Prof. Matt Botvinick</a>, a brilliant
neuro-scientist who also employs AI in his research, and clearly likes to think
deeply about deep questions.</p>
<p>One of the things I (and apparently many of his interviewees) love about Dr
Fridman, is the left-field questions he often poses.</p>
<p>He does this with Botvinick:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But let me ask the over-romanticized question: Do you think we&rsquo;ll ever engineer
an AGI system that we humans would be able to love and that would love us back?
So have that level and depth of connection?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Goodness, so many layers.</p>
<p>What do you think?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>