<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>spring on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/spring/</link><description>Recent content in spring on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/spring/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #230: Follow your blisters</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="van_breda_cottage_angles.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&amp;rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &amp;ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&amp;rdquo; (I didn&amp;rsquo;t and I don&amp;rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV covers the three weeks from Monday July 26 to Sunday August 15.</p>
<h2 id="why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">Why I don&rsquo;t like dark mode anymore</h2>
<p>As you might know, I spent most of my working (and sometimes hobby, we&rsquo;ll get
back to that further down) hours in front of this screen or some other screen.</p>
<p>Up to now, I was really convinced that I preferred dark mode everywhere, until
recently two events transpired:</p>
<p>I started noticing more eye-strain than usual, even on my 27&quot; screen, something
which had a perceptible effect on my productivity. This I resignedly ascribed
to my advancing age, although I did find the suddenness quite surprising,
especially since I recently had my glasses updated.</p>
<p>Then, after years with only the admittedly brilliant <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">zenburn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/fniessen/emacs-leuven-theme">Leuven (dark)</a>
Emacs themes checking all of the boxes for me, I finally ran into a really
interesting and usable theme called <a href="https://github.com/kunalb/poet">Poet</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s interesting, because it uses variable pitched fonts for everything but
code, tables and elements of the fixed width domain, where most Emacs fonts
stick to the traditional all-fixed-width approach.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="20210822-poet-theme-screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can probably understand that for someone who uses Emacs almost primarily
for technical notes and other writing, this book-like appearance could work
really well.</p>
<p>The theme was even more interesting for me personally, as it suddenly became
clear as day that I experienced almost no eye-strain when using Emacs with this
lighter theme than when I used any of my other usually dark-themed tools!</p>
<p>It became obvious that poet-theme&rsquo;s lighter background was much easier on my
eyes than dark mode in vscode. (No, this specific advantage can&rsquo;t be ascribed
to Emacs itself I&rsquo;m afraid.)</p>
<p>Reading pages such as <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/digital-eye-strain/is-dark-mode-better-for-eyes/">this</a> explains that dark mode leads to pupils having to
dilate more to let in more light, which there is less of with dark themes.</p>
<p>This leads to, just like with cameras and any other optics with lenses and
apertures, a shortened depth of field, and hence more difficulty focusing on
the screen!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/dark-mode/">This article by the well-known Nielsen Norman Group</a> nicely summarises research
on this topic. In short:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In people with normal vision (or corrected-to-normal vision), visual
performance tends to be better with light mode, whereas some people with
cataract and related disorders may perform better with dark mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Up until recently, I did not experience a qualitative difference in vision
between dark and light, but I sit here relieved that my eye-strain issue has
been resolved by an Emacs theme!</p>
<h2 id="know-how-to-put-down-your-work">Know how to put down your work</h2>
<p>The following take from <a href="https://twitter.com/brandsrock/status/1426163442256330753">a recent tweet by mike joubert</a> struck me
(tweet-take-strike! words are funny&hellip;):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly valuable skill isn&rsquo;t the capacity to push yourself harder, but to
stop and recuperate despite the discomfort of knowing that work remains
unfinished, emails unanswered, other people&rsquo;s demands unfulfilled.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">article, titled <em>The three-or-four-hours rule for getting creative work
done</em></a>, is itself a good read about the observation that creative types (amongst
which I count engineers) have at their best three to four hours of focus time
per day &mdash; so it is crucially important that their days are structured such
that there is an <strong>uninterrupted</strong> block of three to four hours inside of which
that lovely focus has the possibility of appearing.</p>
<p>The tweet-extract focuses on the similarly important but more subtle art of
being able to put one&rsquo;s work down, completely, when that block of time is over,
even when it feels like the work is far from complete.</p>
<p>I especially like that it also explicitly mentions the illusions created by
one&rsquo;s perception of &ldquo;other people&rsquo;s demands&rdquo;, something that ironically becomes
even harder to walk away from when one is more tired at the end of the work
day.</p>
<p>For me, becoming better at putting work down has pleasant echoes of running
slower to run faster, of emptiness in art and more broadly, <a href="https://zenhabits.net/work-less/">choosing fewer f*cks
to give</a>.</p>
<h2 id="follow-your-blisters">Follow your blisters</h2>
<p>On the topic of choosing your ducks&hellip;</p>
<p>I initially did not like <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/what-you-should-follow-instead-of-your-passion">this HBR</a> post when it first crossed my stream, because
it smacks a bit too much of the current social media style of &ldquo;wisdom&rdquo;, namely
&ldquo;everything you need to know in 280 characters&rdquo;, or &ldquo;this 1 minute tiktok video
will change your life&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the title is pretty clickbaity: <em>What You Should
Follow Instead of Your Passion</em>.</p>
<p>However, the core message of the post, which I could not help reading, did
stick with me, and after a few days I realised that I would have to go find the
article again in order to talk about it here.</p>
<p>The core message is to replace <em>find your passion</em> with <strong><em>Find your blisters.</em></strong></p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s point is that folks often get the wrong idea with <em>passion</em> as
something that is simply always delightful, whilst the thing you should
actually be looking for, is that activity that you simply are unable to stop
doing, even when you try, and especially even when you don&rsquo;t directly derive
pleasure from it, for example because you feel that you&rsquo;re not that good at it.</p>
<p>They give the personal example of writing.</p>
<p>Although they&rsquo;ve been at it for years, it&rsquo;s still a difficult and laborious
process, and they are often not happy with the results.</p>
<p>However, they have been unable to stop from returning to writing projects again
and again over the years.</p>
<p>Ironically, even although they find that they are still bad at it, they have in
fact become really good, simply because they have been pushing through and
practising more than almost anyone else over the years.</p>
<p>I really like this down-to-earth view.</p>
<p>One can indeed source almost unlimited amounts of energy from one&rsquo;s &ldquo;blisters&rdquo;,
but true benefits will for a large part be brought about by a <a href="/tags/practice/">lifetime of often
challenging practice</a>.</p>








<figure><a href="flowers_everywhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &amp;ldquo;blommetjieskyk&amp;rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Spring has arrived in suburbia! [Weekly Head Voices #40]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/03/06/spring-has-arrived-in-suburbia-weekly-head-voices-40/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2011 22:07:43 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/03/06/spring-has-arrived-in-suburbia-weekly-head-voices-40/</guid><description> Allow me to start with two bits of good news:
You have arrived at the 40th edition of the Weekly Head Voices! This blog will soon buy a black leather jacket, start riding around on a motorcycle that is far too big for it and see its therapist concerning its little “Is this all there is?” existential crisis. Spring has arrived in suburbia! Today was glorious, with zillions of little kids running around outside in the sun, and parents chatting contentedly about the barbecue potential of the coming season.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Allow me to start with two bits of good news:</p>
<ol>
<li>You have arrived at the 40th edition of the Weekly Head Voices! This blog will soon buy a black leather jacket, start riding around on a motorcycle that is far too big for it and see its therapist concerning its little “Is this all there is?” existential crisis.</li>
<li>Spring has arrived in suburbia! Today was glorious, with zillions of little kids running around outside in the sun, and parents chatting contentedly about the barbecue potential of the coming season. See this camera-phone impression:

  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/km_spring.jpg">
      <img
          
              
              src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/km_spring-1024x612.jpg"
          
              alt="Scenes of spring, straight from the hood."/> </a><figcaption>
              <p>Scenes of spring, straight from the hood.</p>
          </figcaption>
  </figure>
</li>
</ol>
<p>It’s been a really busy week, so let’s get started. In a surprising and innovative move, I’ll be using headings instead of bullets to indicate each new item in this week’s Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<h3 id="internet-video-conferencing">Internet Video Conferencing</h3>
<p>I had to organize a mini <strong>internet-video-conference</strong>, i.e. more than two people at different locations chatting with voice and video over internet. Skype you say? No sir, Skype wants more money for this functionality. I’m already paying them for Skype Access and for the odd VOIP call to a PSTN line, but I find this extra surprise inexcusable. Therefore, without any further ado, I bring you this week’s WHV Review:</p>
<ul>
<li>Skype for video conferencing: SUCKS.</li>
<li><a href="http://me.tokbox.com/" title="tokbox website">TokBox</a> for video conferencing: RULES! I was able to set this up in 2 minutes, and it required no software besides flash-enabled browsers at all nodes. All conference participants get a link and can join immediately, without logging in. Unfortunately, TokBox is stopping their service in April, as they’ve changed their business model and are  selling their tech (OpenTok) to OEMs. After April, I will probably look at PalTalk for my free video-conferencing needs.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="powerline-networking">Powerline networking</h3>
<p>Because one of my favourite WAB (Work Avoidance Behaviour) routines is to further optimise my home network (1 cable modem, 3 router / access points, 2 servers, 3 laptops, 1 media centre and 1 networked game console), I bought PowerlineAV adapters to bridge one of the wireless sections (pulling cables between the floors involved is a schlep). Hey, that brings us to this week’s second WHV Review:</p>
<ul>
<li>Powerline / HomePlug powerline network adapters: SUCKS! Read all about it in this <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/03/02/dont-buy-homeplug-adapters/" title="vxlabs blog post on why you shouldn't buy powerline adapters">detailed blog post</a> on my nerd blog.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="hacking">Hacking</h3>
<p><em>(NERD ALERT! NERD ALERT! skip this paragraph if you’re not an uber nerd.)</em> I’m old school, so when I say hacking, I mostly mean doing hardcore programming. I fixed a nasty and long-standing bug in the GSVideo video acquisition stack for processing and wrote about in <a href="/2011/03/04/i-crushed-the-gsvideo-problematic-frame-error/" title="link to my gsvideo fix">another nerdy blog post</a>, and then I updated my <a href="/2010/06/05/processing-nyartoolkit-multiple-marker-tracking/" title="multiple-marker nyar4psg page">multiple-marker modification</a> to NyARToolkit for processing to support the P3D renderer. Huh?! You should’ve skipped this paragraph!</p>
<h3 id="fetishes">Fetishes</h3>
<p>As is undoubtedly the case with all of you, I possess quite a number of fetishes, two of which I’m going to share with you today. Don’t worry, they’re relatively safe.</p>
<p>I used to be one of those die-hard <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norton_Commander" title="wikipedia page on Norton Commander">Norton Commander</a> users in the DOS days. Norton Commander was what is called an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orthodox_file_manager#Orthodox_file_managers" title="wikipedia on orthodox file managers">Orthodox File Manager</a>, or OFM. My OFM-fetish has been dormant for years, but has come back with a vengeance due to my rather late discovery of <a href="http://www.farmanager.com/" title="Far Manager website">Far Manager</a>. What a crazy and wonderful piece of software! (To you Loonix-fetishists: MC doesn’t even come close. Unfortunately, Far is Windows only.) Check out the special effects:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/far2_screenie.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/far2_screenie.jpg"
        
            alt="Far Manager version 2. This thing has more hot-keys than you have keys on your keyboard. It can do ANYTHING."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Far Manager version 2. This thing has more hot-keys than you have keys on your keyboard. It can do ANYTHING.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>My long-time <em>musical fetish</em>, the brilliant <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trent_Reznor" title="wikipedia on trent reznor">Trent Reznor</a> (Nine Inch Nails ring a bell?) <a href="http://newsroom.mtv.com/2011/02/28/trent-reznor-oscar-the-social-network/" title="Trent Reznor won an Oscar for the Social Network soundtrack">won an Oscar</a> for his work, together with Attacus Ross, on the Social Network soundtrack. By the way, the movie also pleasantly surprised me, and would have done so even without Reznor’s brilliant work.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>My brain has served up very little backyard philosophy this week, probably because I’ve been too busy acting like a little code-monkey, so I’ll limit my philosophising to the following:</p>
<ol>
<li><em>Thou shalt not link facebook and twitter status updates.</em> These are two different forms of media, and you’re possibly alienating (that’s a big word for “ticking off”) your most loyal followers, i.e. the fantastic people following you on both networks, with duplicate status messages. See it as a challenge to drive each of your social networks in a way which most suits its nature, or see it as double the opportunity to express yourself!</li>
<li>I’ve quoted this once before on this blog, but there are new readers, and it’s good to be reminded every so often: <em>Be kind, for everyone you meet is fighting a hard battle. — Plato.</em></li>
</ol>
<p>That’s it for this week kids. Have a beautiful and springy week!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>