<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>gou on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou/</link><description>Recent content in gou on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #225: Just a perfect weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</guid><description> Dear reader,
Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.
Keyboard update: K1 You&amp;rsquo;ll remember from WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the Womier K87 with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown switches.
That keyboard is so much fun to type on.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear reader,</p>
<p>Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th
installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="la_autumn_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="keyboard-update-k1">Keyboard update: K1</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll remember from <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the
Womier K87</a> with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown
switches.</p>
<p>That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt
Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the case that fingers also like the exercise, just like their
human owners.</p>
<p>I was not planning to buy any keyboards again soon, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was quite curious whether low profile key switches (that is, slightly less
finger travel) would be a good compromise between the fun of the Womier and the
efficiency of the Sculpt.</li>
<li>The K1 was on my list of candidates of keyboards with low-profile mechanical
switches.</li>
<li>I find it difficult to resist a good deal.</li>
</ul>
<p>You see, a friendly little bird (who also hangs out on the keyboards channel of
the zatech slack) told me about the extra-special Takealot birthday special
discount on <a href="https://www.imore.com/keychron-k1-v4-review">the Keychron K1 V4 87-key keyboard</a>.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a credit card transaction, a week of waiting for delivery and
another week of getting accustomed to the new board, and here we are, with at
least me typing these words on the new K1.</p>
<p>It took a while to get used to the keycaps, which can be a slippery sometimes
(or rather, my finger tip traction is variable), but my typing speed and
accuracy on this thing are in the neighbourhood of where they should be.</p>
<p>The thing is a great deal more <em>stylish</em> than my Womier; the Womier is that
guilty pleasure 80s disco that you really love, the K1 could work in a serious
coffee shop.</p>
<p>Also, having a keyboard which can switch this easily between wired operation
(the default for my desktop) and three different bluetooth connections is
pretty convenient. On trips where I usually only take the MacBook, I could
consider taking the K1 along when I have to do A Great Deal of Serious Typing.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I can&rsquo;t yet say if the low profile switches are indeed
the compromise that I wondered about. My subjective impression now is indeed
that my fingers don&rsquo;t get so physically tired as sometimes happens with the
Womier, but I&rsquo;ll have to switch between them a few times to get a better idea.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am certainly enjoying the experience of typing on
this thing, and I am certainly wondering about the interesting role that
different types of mechanical keyboards have begun to play in my computing
life.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-about-a-new-book-notes-post-about-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Lessons about a new book notes post about Seven and a Half Lessons about the Brain</h2>
<p>After two months of early(ish) morning typing on various keyboards, I finally
managed to wrap up <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">my book notes about Seven and a Half Lessons about the
Brain</a>, a fantastic book by neuro-scientist and psychologist Lisa Feldman
Barrett.</p>
<p>I had plans, in retrospect clearly too ambitious, to have at least two (2) book
notes posts out in Q1 of this year (after it took me months to complete <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my book
notes on Creativity, Inc.</a> by the end of last year).</p>
<p>That goal was necessarily postponed to Q2, and as we can all see now, there is
not enough time for a second post like this.</p>
<p>Either I have to change the format of the book notes to something more compact,
like a bunch of bullet lists, or I should make peace with the fact that I write
these like I write them, a little prose with quotes interspersed that can
generally be read like a mini story itself, and with the fact that they&rsquo;re
going to take as much time as they do.</p>
<p>Sometimes I have mixed feelings about the practice itself.</p>
<p>It takes fragments of hobby time spread out over weeks, fragments of time that
I could probably use for more reading, other interesting tidbits and, uhm,
extra work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it feels like a sort of a mini-rebellion doing exactly this,
assembling so many little pieces into something slightly more coherent and
significant, something that stands apart from work.</p>
<p>It seems I do know what to do.</p>
<p>Thanks for the chat!</p>
<h2 id="perfect-weekends-and-the-necessary-reminders-that-precede-them">Perfect weekends and the necessary reminders that precede them</h2>
<p>The weekend of June 4, 2021, was unexpectedly perfect, and I would like to make
note of that here for future me.</p>
<p>This is the recipe that we followed, utterly by happy accident:</p>
<ul>
<li>1x reminder during the week to really focus on the now.</li>
<li>1x absolutely perfect autumn weather package: balmy 20ish degrees Celsius,
lots of sun, very little wind.</li>
<li>3x braais, one per day, with various subsets of family.</li>
<li>2x runs: one a long weekend morning run, and the other an unplanned one
with GOU#1.</li>
<li>1x polishing and publishing of the blog post mentioned above.</li>
<li>1x unexpected Sunday evening star watching with GOU#2.</li>
</ul>
<p>One would think that daily practice would help, but it turns out that sometimes
a serendipitous reminder by a friend can help to switch one&rsquo;s brain into
exactly the right gear, right before the weekend.</p>
<p>During our Friday evening start-the-weekend ritual (it&rsquo;s a braai. surprise!), I
had my first quite visceral &ldquo;THIS, this is it, this is everything&rdquo;
experience. (so lovely)</p>
<p>From then on, brain remained in the right mode right through most of the
weekend.</p>
<p>If you ever run into me before the weekend (it&rsquo;s always before the weekend!), I
would be grateful if you could remind me that it is in fact now.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you much nowness.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #223: The potjie never left</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 22:34:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/</guid><description> Welcome friends to the two hundred and twenty third edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the period of time from Monday May 3 to Sunday May 16, 2021.
(Hah, by writing out the words like that, I&amp;rsquo;ll get paid even more for this article!)
Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome friends to the two hundred and twenty third edition of the Weekly Head
Voices, covering the period of time from Monday May 3 to Sunday May 16, 2021.</p>
<p>(Hah, by writing out the words like that, I&rsquo;ll get paid even more for this
article!)</p>








<figure><a href="verg_just_before_endurance_broke.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu2af5629a3a1a06676bdc87f622145d11_479381_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="vxlabs-software-development-handbook-v1-is-out">vxlabs software development handbook v1 is out</h2>
<p>Well, it&rsquo;s not really a book, more of a blog post really, but it is chock full
of practical guidelines for developers.</p>
<p>It is also 100% free and open source, and can be accessed <a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/">over at the vxlabs</a>.</p>
<p>None of this will be surprising for any of you experienced developers, but it&rsquo;s
super handy having a single place that you can point folks at when you have
some specific advice in mind.</p>
<p>My personal favourite and most important guideline is <a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/#comment-your-code">&ldquo;Comment your code&rdquo;</a>. It
seems that this advice really can&rsquo;t be repeated often enough.</p>
<p>The first commit (i.e. words written) happened on December 14 of 2020, and
version 1 published on 2021-05-03. Most of this had to happen in between other
activities, but that&rsquo;s ok. This is one of the <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#interstitial-projects">interstitial projects</a> I implied
in January.</p>
<h2 id="world-in-my-eyes">World in my eyes</h2>
<p>The photo at the start of this post was taken at the entrance of Vergelegen, at
about 7km into an absolute epic Saturday late afternoon run.</p>
<p>It was epic, because the autumn weather was absolutely perfect, my running
mechanism was smooth and efficient, and there was great music piping into my
brain via the recently acquired JBL Endurance Run bluetooth earphones.</p>
<p>I mention the earphones specifically, because for the first time I had found
something that fit perfectly and even advertised being &ldquo;sweatproof&rdquo; on the box,
a characteristic that is quite important when you produce as much sweat as I
do. (TMI, but please bear with me here)</p>
<p>I was so satisfied after five or six runs that I had taken a few photos earlier
that day, as I was planning a short blog post extolling the virtues of said
gadget.</p>
<p>Probably about 60 seconds after I took the photo, running back out to the road,
thinking to myself how great these earphones were working and how far I was
still going to run and how amazing everything is, the right earphone starts
going &ldquo;GGGGGGGHHHHHRRRRRRRRGGGGGWWWWWGGGGHHHHHH&rdquo; (you have to read that with an
authentic, hard Dutch guttural) and it simply does not stop.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have you tried switching them off and on again?&rdquo; you might say.</p>
<p>Well, the sound just kept on going, switched on, or off.</p>
<p>No amount of power cycling, shaking, re-pairing or swearing made any
difference.</p>
<p>Right earphone just kept on going &ldquo;GGGGGGGHHHRRRRRGGGGHHHHH&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I finally bundled up the JBL TripSpoiler BT into my hand, and ran home, like a
person who runs without music.</p>
<p>P.S. The section title is a Depeche Mode song (one of my teenage favourites) in
which the highest mountain is contrasted with the deepest sea, albeit in a
utterly different context.</p>
<p>P.P.S. As I write this, takealot is sending me a replacement set. I&rsquo;m hoping
the new unit is an anti-lemon.</p>
<h2 id="pretty-hip-birthday-party">Pretty hip birthday party</h2>
<p>GOU #2 held her 11th party here at our facility.</p>
<p>The plans started out as a VR party (or at least that&rsquo;s what I thought), but
great forces out of my control determined that There Would Also Need to Be
Karaoke.</p>
<p>This is one time where the more technically inclined dads can shine!</p>
<p>I purchased exactly one cheap but great value Karaoke microphone (the Samson
SCR10S Karaoke Dynamic Microphone with Switch, if you must know), and then
mixed everything together using an old Windows laptop, our old burglary-proof
(when flat screens were still thick) TV with HDMI input, and a bunch of cables.</p>
<p>Friends arrived, and an extremely fun-looking and partially sugar-fuelled
teenage chaos ensued.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the VR setup ended up getting a significant chunk of the
attention. Even amongst these ultra-connected digital natives, the tech is
still new enough to garner a substantial amount of the unobtainium aka
attention.</p>
<p>(Although I never ever sing, not even in the shower, that karaoke setup has a
surprisingly strong magnetic force, if you catch my drift. GOU #2 was quite
relieved when none of her parents decided to make a guest appearance at the
main event. In my case, it&rsquo;s really for the better.)</p>
<h2 id="boomer-party">Boomer party</h2>
<p>A few days later, after we had sufficiently recovered from the teenage party,
it was time to invite long time friends of ours over for an old people party.</p>
<p>As is our wont down here, when the friends are this dear, we take time to make
a potjie.</p>
<p>The autumn weather contributed fabulously, and so we enjoyed scenes like this:</p>








<figure><a href="chicken-curry-potjie-2021.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu4ef2407d2d9072b862053f2bb470f814_1889922_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: From this photo, it&amp;rsquo;s also quite clear that I have become much taller."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: From this photo, it&rsquo;s also quite clear that I have become much taller.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Readers of this blog might recognise the visual composition above, perhaps from
<a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/">a post back in January of 2016</a>, when I initiated the pot with coincidentally
the same recipe.</p>
<p>The potjie scene seems to repeat itself (these are not the only two examples),
acting as a sort of reliable cast iron backdrop (with enamel coating!) for our
family and friendship rituals.</p>
<p>On this day, the ritual was indeed sublime.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #216: Sup?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</guid><description> Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.
Figure 1: Sup?
The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard with Lots of Focus.
I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily application of the One Main Thing idea, but experience has taught me that it&amp;rsquo;s probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&amp;rsquo;ll be solidly back in the arms of my old friend the really slippery eel.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks
from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="sup_bettys.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sup?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Sup?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard
with Lots of Focus.</p>
<p>I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily
application of <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">the One Main Thing idea</a>, but experience has taught me that it&rsquo;s
probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure
factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&rsquo;ll be solidly
back in the arms of my old friend the <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">really slippery eel</a>.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I have been making good use of the (temporarily?)
increased capacity.</p>
<h2 id="fresh-from-the-oven-vxlabs-software-development-handbook">Fresh from the oven: vxlabs software development handbook</h2>
<p><a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/">The vxlabs software development handbook</a>, at the time of this writing about 65%
complete (that&rsquo;s a random number that my brain gives me every time I publish a
new version), is now available over on my nerdy blog.</p>
<p>If you are working with a smaller development team, or you&rsquo;re starting with a
new dev team, the handbook is not the worst place to look for development
process tips. Furthermore, it&rsquo;s available under the Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License, so you can copy and paste and rebrand to
your heart&rsquo;s content as long as you give due credit somewhere to the original
author (me and vxlabs).</p>
<p>In the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll be trying to complete more sections to get closer to
that mythical 100% completion grade.</p>
<h2 id="two-miscellaneous-tips-for-nerds">Two miscellaneous tips for nerds</h2>
<h3 id="printfriendly-on-your-phone">PrintFriendly on your phone</h3>
<p>You might remember from my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#web-pages-and-articles">2019 note-taking strategy post</a> that I convert all
interesting web pages I come across to PDF and dump them in my dropbox.</p>
<p>This has turned out to be the best way to store web-pages for later searching,
reference and winning of arguments.</p>
<p>However, the mobile part of that strategy was traditionally weak, as is also
discussed in that post.</p>
<p>The problem was that Safari on iPhone has a great reading mode that strips ads
and other unnecessary bits, but when you print from reading mode, the PDF is
formatted for mobile, and, more importantly, there&rsquo;s no way to get the source
URL embedded in the PDF.</p>
<p>Anyways, after years of using the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/">PrintFriendly</a> browser extension on the
desktop (as is also explained in the note-taknig post), I finally got around to
installing their mobile bookmarklet on the iPhone. (this should work on any
mobile browser)</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/extensions/iOS">instructions are a bit finicky</a>, but one ends up with a bookmark that you
can activate on any page to have the printfriendly service pre-process that
page for reading, from which you can tap on the print icon to get a mostly
perfect PDF that is also stamped with the source URL!</p>
<h3 id="fish-shell">Fish shell</h3>
<p>After years of resisting all the zsh blog posts and especially the pretty
oh-my-zsh powerline prompts and sticking to my stock standard bash because
get-off-my-lawn, I finally broke down and installed&hellip;</p>
<p><a href="https://fishshell.com/">fish!</a></p>
<p>fish shell is a &ldquo;smart and user-friendly command line shell for Linux, macOS,
and the rest of the family&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I like it because one of its goals is to be more useful with hardly any extra
configuration, but you can also install <a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/oh-my-fish">oh-my-fish</a> with my new favourite theme
<a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/theme-bobthefish">bobthefish</a>.</p>
<p>I <em>was</em> planning to convince you of my choice with a number of technical
reasons, but it is now clear to me that technical arguments are irrelevant when
you can rock a theme called &ldquo;bobthefish&rdquo;.</p>
<p>P.S. Let me know in the comments if you would still prefer to talk about
technical reasons.</p>
<h2 id="a-brief-pause">A brief pause</h2>
<p>Since we <a href="/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/#gou-1-s-growing-running-habit">last spoke about GOU#1&rsquo;s running habit</a>, it gives me great pleasure to
report that she has, quite routinely if I may add, done another two or three
10k runs, one of them even up to eleven by accident.</p>
<p>Folks I wish you all the best. I look forward to our next connection!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #215: Gateway to an unknown universe (aka Taalmonument)</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 09:48:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/</guid><description><![CDATA[ How do you do, fellow humans? (Sub-vocalise in Steve Buscemi voice for maximum effect.)
This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the week from Monday January 25 to Sunday January 31 of the year 2021.
 Figure 1: Weekend scene from the Afrikaans Language Monument (or &ldquo;Taalmonument&rdquo;, when you speak the lingo). Initially I thought about &lsquo;shopping out the photo-shooting couple, but I&rsquo;ve grown to like them now.
  My notes for the period don&rsquo;t have much that is WHV-worthy, except for the following two humble offerings:]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>How do you do, fellow humans? (Sub-vocalise in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve%5FBuscemi">Steve Buscemi</a> voice for maximum
effect.)</p>
<p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the week from Monday January 25
to Sunday January 31 of the year 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="taalmonument_front.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Weekend scene from the Afrikaans Language Monument (or &amp;ldquo;Taalmonument&amp;rdquo;, when you speak the lingo). Initially I thought about &amp;lsquo;shopping out the photo-shooting couple, but I&amp;rsquo;ve grown to like them now."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Weekend scene from the Afrikaans Language Monument (or &ldquo;Taalmonument&rdquo;, when you speak the lingo). Initially I thought about &lsquo;shopping out the photo-shooting couple, but I&rsquo;ve grown to like them now.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>My notes for the period don&rsquo;t have much that is WHV-worthy, except for the
following two humble offerings:</p>
<h2 id="gou-1-s-growing-running-habit">GOU #1&rsquo;s growing running habit</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned <a href="/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/#mafish">MAF (maximum aerobic function) before on this blog</a>, when I was
trying to nurse back to health an ankle I had injured.</p>
<p>More recently, <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/PhilMaffetone/">Peter Attia hosted Phil Maffetone, the inventor of the MAF idea,
on his podcast</a>. Relative to the normal Attia standards of multi-hour blog
posts, this one was quite compact, and definitely worth a listen if you&rsquo;re into
running.</p>
<p>Just to recap: Maffetone recommends running at a heart rate of 180 minus your
age (a rule of thumb, of course), in order to exercise at one&rsquo;s maximum aerobic
function (MAF).</p>
<p>This is usually lower than 80% of one&rsquo;s maximum, so think long and slow.</p>
<p>The goal of this is to increase the use of stored fat as the primary source of
fuel, the idea being that one would be able to go much further with reduced
effort.</p>
<p>Anyways, this running without too much effort simply sounded too good to GOU
#1, and so she asked me if we could try another 10k like this. (We usually do 5
to 6 together.)</p>
<p>As you might know, <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#the-absolute-basics">my rule for running</a> is that if there&rsquo;s a question about
whether to go run the answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;.</p>
<p>So an Saturday I started with my own 11k so that I would not mind slowing down
for the GOU-leg (I do realise that me slowing down for her is temporary&hellip;),
and then we set out for the MAF(ish) 10km.</p>
<p>She found it super tricky to maintain the lower-than-normal heart rate, which
is to be expected, and for the last few kilometres had no choice but to let it
increase quite a bit, but&hellip; she did a really comfortable 10km!</p>
<p>Since then she has asked if I&rsquo;m up for another one, which is of course the best
possible sign that this habit is being imprinted quite nicely.</p>
<p>(I was pretty tired after the whole episode, but don&rsquo;t tell anyone.)</p>
<h2 id="we-visited-a-gateway-to-another-dimension-and-didn-t-even-get-a-t-shirt">We visited a gateway to another dimension and didn&rsquo;t even get a t-shirt</h2>
<p>On Sunday we planned to take the family up Bretagne Rock (see <a href="/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/#getting-high">this 2017
vacation WHV for a photo</a>), but were met by closed gates, thanks to surprising
lockdown regulations.</p>
<p>Well, the journey there was picturesque (Paarl valley is beautiful, also from
up there), and we suddenly had the opportunity to visit another old favourite
instead: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afrikaans%5FLanguage%5FMonument">The Afrikaans Language Monument</a>!</p>
<p>If you grew up in Paarl like I did, and especially if your school was located
as close to the monument as mine was, you would have spent many hours of your
young life, both during terribly official ceremonies and outings, at this
impressive artifact.</p>
<p>I always did think it was a pretty science fiction design, especially taking
into account it was erected in 1975.</p>
<p>Well, to my pleasant surprise, it turns out that my Taalmonument featured in
season 12 of Dr Who, and <a href="https://screenrant.com/doctor-who-timeless-child-identity-time-lord-origin-explained/">specifically as the monument marking the location of a
gateway to &ldquo;another unknown dimension or universe&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>In an even more pleasant turn of events, the monument and the gateway played a
pivotal role in the fairly specific origins of The Doctor, the protagonist of
the series.</p>
<p>When the gateway is active, the Taalmonument apparently looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="taalmonument_from_below_gateway.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_from_below_gateway_hu88e74d0b4c5604d2173bc986e54e3230_23704_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_from_below_gateway.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Taalmonument in gateway to another universe mode. Image courtesy of screenrant post linked above."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Taalmonument in gateway to another universe mode. Image courtesy of screenrant post linked above.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a tweet about the relevant episode, with some more photos:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">The Gate where Tecteun found the Timeless Child is actually the Afrikaans Language Monument overlooking Paarl, in Western Cape Province, South Africa. The real setting is every bit as dramatic as any movie could envisage 😍 <a href="https://t.co/4IDJZc6C7O">pic.twitter.com/4IDJZc6C7O</a></p>&mdash; The Timeless Doctors (@Ten_Doctors) <a href="https://twitter.com/Ten_Doctors/status/1297283229712560136?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 22, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>Note: I grew up knowing what a Dalek was, but I&rsquo;ve never, as far as I can
remember, followed a Dr Who series. I might have seen snippets of old episodes
in the 80s.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s another view of the monument which you may not (yet) have seen in any
science fiction productions. I think its time will come.</p>








<figure><a href="taalmonument_spheres.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: 1975 had some serious sci-fi architecture mojo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 3: 1975 had some serious sci-fi architecture mojo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>With that my friends, and my wish that you are really able to shine this week,
I declare this post concluded.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2020 to 2021 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 15:19:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Welcome to the year 2021 friends.
Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.
You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to the &ldquo;transition&rdquo; tag page.
If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition.
This transition tradition started at the end of 2009, which coincidentally is also the year that the Weekly Head Voices was born.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2021 friends.</p>
<p>Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.</p>
<p>You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to <a href="/tags/transition/">the &ldquo;transition&rdquo;
tag page</a>.</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/">last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition</a>.</p>
<p>This transition tradition <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">started at the end of 2009</a>, which coincidentally is
also the year that <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">the Weekly Head Voices was born</a>.</p>
<p>The goal of the transition post is to do a really spotty year review, and then
to gaze unsuccessfully into the future.</p>








<figure><a href="leopards_kloof.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&amp;rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>More seriously, the ever-evolving network of posts on this website (there are
now literally hundreds of them), along with the ever-evolving but also fading
network of neurons in my head (probably at least a few hundred of them too!),
benefit from an occasional higher-level connecting of some of the dots.</p>
<p>In the introduction of the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/">2018 to 2019 transition post</a>, I ramble on slightly
more about the multiscalar nature of my subjective experience, and how that is
reflected in my notes database, of which this blog is one aspect.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s get on with it!</p>
<h2 id="noteworthy-snippets-through-the-lens-of-this-blog">Noteworthy snippets through the lens of this blog</h2>
<h3 id="covid-19">COVID-19</h3>
<p>One of the biggest issues for most people last year and still at this moment is
COVID-19.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested, you could take a look at the Weekly Head Voices posts
that had something to say about <a href="/tags/covid19/">COVID-19</a>, but you don&rsquo;t really have to.</p>
<p>Fortunately, world-wide vaccination has commenced. However, we have to keep our
fingers crossed that:</p>
<ol>
<li>The world succeeds in getting the vaccine to a sufficient number of humans
on time.</li>
<li>A vaccine-resistant strain does not happen. It could, because math, and
because evolution (selection pressure due to the vaccine, doh),</li>
</ol>
<p>Whether the above outcomes realise or not, I do also hope that we retain as
many as possible of the lessons we have been learning thanks to the pandemic.</p>
<ul>
<li>Mask-wearing and generally improved hygeine with the major goal of protecting
our fellow humans are great habits.</li>
<li>We have made great strides towards the future of work, where many workers (by
far not all, but it&rsquo;s a good meaningful chunk) are able to commute less,
pollute less, better organize the interaction of their work and family lives
and, importantly, their work is measured by its value and not by the number
of hours it takes place in.</li>
<li>We humans are in this (today pandemic, tomorrow something else!) together.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="lazar-focus-the-side-project-that-got-released">Lazar Focus: The side-project that got released</h3>
<p>Around these parts we have a rich tradition of starting but then never
finishing side-projects, and the concomitant giant side-project graveyard to
show for it.</p>
<p>This year, I did manage to ship the little distraction blocker tool I wrote,
called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a>. The <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">first WHV mentioning was #196</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the fact that this little tool has ended up helping me to rescue
many aspirant unproductive days, it has sold more than 10 copies, which was my
life goal for this project.</p>
<h3 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion effect</h3>
<p>From Adam Grant&rsquo;s book Give and Take, I learned about the <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#the-pygmalion-effect">Pygmalion effect</a>,
where a teacher&rsquo;s <em>belief</em> in the intrinsic capabilities of a student, whether
those were justified or not at the time, had a significant and enduring
positive, one could say potentially life-changing, effect on that student&rsquo;s
performance.</p>
<p>Besides the bit about the Pygmalion effect, <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/">that post (WHV #201)</a> contains a
micro-summary of the Shape Up book by Basecamp, which is also worth a look.</p>
<h3 id="take-the-day-off-to-go-run-in-the-mountain">Take the day off to go run in the mountain</h3>
<p>During the year, for example in <a href="/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/#life-progress-update">WHV #203</a> when I took my birthday off to go
running in the mountains, I learned that taking days off on the birthdays of you
and your loved ones to go do stuff outdoors is a Great Idea(tm).</p>
<p>(I also learned that sometimes you don&rsquo;t even need an excuse. Just take the day
off and go run in the mountains.)</p>
<h3 id="use-it-or-lose-it">Use it or lose it</h3>
<p>The human system is amazingly adaptable.</p>
<p>The price that we pay for that flexibility is that each and every one of our
learned capabilities requires continuous practice in order to be maintained.</p>
<p>In short humans, <a href="/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/#use-it-or-lose-it">use it, or lose it</a>.</p>
<h3 id="fool-your-mind">Fool your mind</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m making peace with the fact that I apparently need to apply, continuously,
various silly tricks to keep <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">the slippery eel that is my mind</a> on the
straight-and-narrow.</p>
<p>As a shining example, <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">the refocus reminder</a>, a bell that reminds you at hourly
intervals to focus, indeed sounds a bit silly but adds a great deal of value.</p>
<p>My favourite example from last year however is creating yet more (but smaller!)
habits to kickstart my bigger habits, in this case a <a href="/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/#wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">3-item morning checklist
to kickstart the more daunting full day checklist</a>.</p>
<p>The morning bootstrap checklist is, at the risk of sounding like a startup-bro:</p>
<ol>
<li>meditation,</li>
<li>deep reading and</li>
<li>planning.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="blogging-stats">Blogging stats</h2>
<p>Since February 17 of 2020 when I <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">migrated everything to a small Hetzner VPS</a>,
the server log files tell me that cpbotha.net saw just over 157000 unique
visitors, which is 492 per day on average.</p>
<p>I wrote 30 posts on cpbotha.net during 2020, of which 25 were editions of the
Weekly Head Voices.</p>
<p>Thanks to the shiny new archive page I put together today, you can now finally
<a href="/archive/#2020">see all of 2020&rsquo;s posts in one place</a>, or of any other year, should you be more
into the older stuff.</p>
<p>In addition to the cpbotha.net posts, I also published 11 posts over on
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the regular WHV posts, I&rsquo;m happy to have published what will
hopefully be only the first in a whole collection of book notes posts, namely
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Creativity, Inc.&rdquo; by Ed Catmull with Amy Wallace</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s chunky at just over 7000 words, but it will give you a pretty good idea of
the contents of the much more substantial book it is based on!</p>
<h3 id="details-for-nerds">Details for nerds</h3>
<p>This is the invocation I used to generate reports from the nginx log files
using the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess</a> tool:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">zcat -f -- /var/log/nginx/cpbotha.net.access.log.*.gz |<span style="color:#2aa198">\
</span><span style="color:#2aa198"></span>    goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</code></pre></div><h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>In 2020 I seem to have run just 100 metres shy of 1100km. (Typical&hellip;)</p>
<p>More would have been good, but I&rsquo;m happy with this.</p>
<p>Exercise did take a bit of a hit due to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/#exercise">lockdown</a>, although I could definitely
have squeezed more in.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the aggregated amount of enjoyment and satisfaction
was astronomical.</p>
<p>A personal highlight was <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#random-notes-on-the-kogelberg-trail-adventure">running the 24km(ish) Kogelberg trail with a tiny
crew that included two of my Dutch family members</a>.</p>
<p>(These blog retrospectives are strange, because they are also life
retrospectives, but they shouldn&rsquo;t get too personal. I would be remiss however
if I did not mention that having these specific Dutch peeps here in 2020 was
magical. I am going to miss them terribly.)</p>
<p>Also thanks to said peeps, I did more trail running this year than ever before.</p>
<p>It turns out that I am surrounded by beautiful trails. WHO KNEW?!</p>
<p>The other highlight I want to mention was <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations">GOU#1</a> running her first race, the
distributed <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#running-and-reading">CTM 10km in Jonkershoek</a>. Here&rsquo;s to many more GOU kilometres!</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>Thanks to some strict words by friend PK during the year, I got solidly back on
the daily meditation train, which ended up being the start of a streak of
(workday) morning meditation longer than anything I&rsquo;ve been able to maintain up
to now.</p>
<p>(The bootstrap checklist in <a href="#fool-your-mind">Fool Your Mind</a> above might also have contributed to
this.)</p>
<p>The Waking Up course by Sam Harris has been amazing for more than two years
now, and even more so when trying to build and keep up a daily meditation
habit.</p>
<p>What I especially like about Waking Up is its focus on the explicit practice of
the experience of consciousness and the role (or non-role) of the self within
that. (for a tiny example, see <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#find-a-place-in-the-universe-that-is-your-consciousness">WHV #207</a>)</p>
<p>Practising this daily has been an experience that I can only recommend in the
strongest terms.</p>
<p>(Please let me know if you&rsquo;d like to try a month for free. As a subscriber, I
get to give these out to as many peeps as I want to.)</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV approach to life, the universe and everything (also known as &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo;,
but you have to over-emphasize the terribly soft &ldquo;W&rdquo;) has been evolving for a
few years now, but it was most recently summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.</p>
<p>At the basis of this approach we find the two formidable pillars of</p>
<ol>
<li><em>love</em> and</li>
<li><em>science</em>,</li>
</ol>
<p>and in that order. On top of these pillars rest <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">The WHV&rsquo;s Two no Three Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</a>.</p>
<p>The two no three rules are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be useful.</li>
<li>Be likable.</li>
<li>Evolve.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the previous transition post, I talked about <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">six personal daily life
directions</a>, the continuous reformulation of which I had integrated into my
morning routine.</p>
<p>It was a good start, but the life directions were a bit too specific, and six
separate things is too many to keep at the core of your thoughts.</p>
<p>Motivated by this, and also by <a href="https://lexfridman.com/chris-lattner-2/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Chris Lattner</a>
wherein Lattner, an amazing engineer, but more importantly such a kind human
being, underlined the importance to him of always continuing to grow and learn,
I mashed together everything I had to come up with two clusters of daily life
directions:</p>
<ol>
<li>Grow, learn, build, enjoy. (motion)</li>
<li>Be useful. Be likeable. Be kind. (self-checks)</li>
</ol>
<p>In the stupid-dimensional universe that is my mind, I know that these
directions are obviously in the spirit of WALUE, but I can&rsquo;t yet articulate
clearly how they relate to the pillars and the rules of WALUE.</p>
<p>Maybe they&rsquo;re just a neat little pile on top, or a little bit to the side,
leaning against the WALUE building?</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, they have been part of my daily checklist for a few
months now, and they seem to work in the sense of being practical, checkable
and tiny enough to keep in mind always.</p>
<h2 id="plans--for-tomorrow-at-least">Plans (for tomorrow, at least)</h2>
<p>This bit is quite scary.</p>
<p>I hardly know what&rsquo;s going to happen tomorrow, and here I wanted to talk about
plans for the whole year!</p>
<p>So, to be clear, what I&rsquo;ve listed below is limited to the concrete items that I
can see before me right now.</p>
<h3 id="the-absolute-basics">The absolute basics</h3>
<ul>
<li>Attempt to apply <a href="#life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</a> all of the time.</li>
<li>Practise mindfulness every day.</li>
<li>If I&rsquo;m wondering whether I should go run, the answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="comms-upgrade">Comms upgrade</h3>
<p>I would like to level up my communication game.</p>
<p>Work from home is here to stay, and that&rsquo;s a good thing, but it has muffled my
face-to-face communication modality, something that has had a profound impact
on my full communication suite.</p>
<p>Most of the clever folks now agree that <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">the correct answer is asynchronous
communication</a>. Future-facing companies like Basecamp and <a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/">Doist have been
preaching this long before COVID-19</a>.</p>
<p>To be more specific, I need to figure out first how to do asynchronous
communication in my daily work, and then to become really good at it.</p>
<h3 id="write-more-about-good-books">Write more about good books</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to publish more focused book notes like the recently appeared
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Creativity, Inc. post</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s great reading these books, but I&rsquo;ve noticed that if I&rsquo;m planning to
publish book notes, I read more intently, I take better notes, and the extra
processing stage before starting to put together a blog post really helps me to
integrate the knowledge contained in the book.</p>
<p>Every good book one is able to integrate is in fact a cheap, but possibly
game-changing firmware upgrade&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2021-for-you">Wishes for 2021, for you</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this. I am grateful that you&rsquo;re here.</p>
<p>I wish you and everyone you hold dear the best 2021 possible.</p>
<p>Quite concretely, we can all help to make this happen by being as kind as we
possibly can to as many fellow humans as we possibly can.</p>
<p>In the words of a fellow traveller: SMÉAGOL OUT!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #208: Stilbaai</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 10:59:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</guid><description> Welcome back folks!
Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.
It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.
Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.
Running and reading I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, GOU #1 (14) completed her first (virtual) 10km race.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks!</p>
<p>Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.</p>
<p>It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period
Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="skulpiesbaai_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="running-and-reading">Running and reading</h2>
<p>I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> (14) completed her
first (virtual) 10km race.</p>
<p>Her journey started when a friend from school invited her to join the race, at
which point GOU #1 suddenly became much more enthusiastic about running
regularly with her old dad. (that&rsquo;s me)</p>
<p>There is something pretty primal about running with your offspring, an
observation that I might have mentioned before on these pages.</p>
<p>Anyways, after her race she was visibly happy, and also relieved that, in her
words, &ldquo;she didn&rsquo;t die&rdquo;.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m perhaps even more happy about than the preparatory runs together, and
her completing the race, is that since the race we&rsquo;ve been out together for a
run or three.</p>
<p>(Running and reading are two of the most important low-level habits I would
like to try and get my offspring hooked on.)</p>
<h2 id="ieee-vis2020">IEEE VIS2020</h2>
<p>At the start of October, I had a great experience <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#vcbm-2020-virtually">virtually attending the VCBM
2020 conference</a>.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough grade A1 10/10 conferencing for one year, my other
favourite conference, IEEE VIS (for visualization) was also fully virtual this
year in the week of October 26, so again I dove into YouTube streams and
well-organised discord rooms, and again this experience was highly edifying and
enjoyable.</p>
<p>Somehow, it was even <em>more</em> fun than my already optimistic expectations to run
into friends at the conference.</p>
<p>I would like to transfer this one piece of sage advice given by the amazing
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%5Fvan%5FWijk">Prof. Jarke van Wijk</a> during the panel on &ldquo;Why should I stay in academia&rdquo; when
the discussion treated the issue of dealing with rejection, something that is
unfortunately a regular part of most academic careers.</p>
<p>At this point, he was referring specifically to accepted papers and proposals,
but the advice should really be applied to any victory, large or small, in all
walks of life:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Celebrate your victories.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="cycles">Cycles</h2>
<p>You will of course remember that we were fortunate enough to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">spend our last few
days of freedom in Stilbaai,</a> as autumn was arriving, and more acutely right
before the first lockdown started on March 26,</p>
<p>It was really great going back to the exact same house (thanks kind host!),
after months of various levels of lockdown, this time just as spring was really
getting off the ground.</p>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_0181.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I did take work with me for the long weekend, but this time, and quite
unexpectedly, the important <a href="/tags/disconnecting">disconnect</a> happened quite quickly without too much
conscious effort from my side.</p>
<p>If I had to put my finger on it, I would say that getting everyone to go
outside as often as possible on little adventures of various sizes was the
catalyst.</p>
<h2 id="back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">Back to reality: An 18-minute plan for managing your day</h2>
<p>I could not imagine a more sudden transition from the long weekend zen above
than this jump to Peter Bregman&rsquo;s 18 minute plan for planning your work day.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Sometimes, fortunately mostly later in the afternoon, I wonder why my systems
have failed in helping me to keep my eye on that ball for longer. (See <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">my
slippery eel</a> for more struggles.)</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s when I procrastinate quasi-productively by searching online for any new
self-optimisation tricks that I might have missed, and which might constitute
that Last Piece of The Puzzle that will fix this once and for all.</p>
<p>This time, to my great surprise, I did actually run into something 1. that was
written aaaaaall the way back in 2009 and 2. that contained something new that
I had not run into before, namely the &ldquo;refocus&rdquo; reminder.</p>
<p>The refocus reminder is literally an alarm that goes off every hour on the
hour, at which point you explicitly take a step back for a whole minute to
review the past hour, and, if required (most probably the case the later it is
in the day), to re-commit to the following hour.</p>
<p>This reminded me specifically about mindfulness&rsquo;s <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#therunning-and-the-mindful">&ldquo;Each breath a new beginning;
each out-breath a letting go&rdquo;</a>, and more generally about <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">life as eternal
practice</a>.</p>
<p>You can use any sort of timer to do this, but this seemed like a great feature
for the little Lazar Focus app, so I implemented it along with a nice
mindfulness bell sound to add some gravitas to the moment.</p>
<p>If you like, you can read the short summary I wrote about the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/10/24/peter-bregmans-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day-and-the-surprising-power-of-refocus-reminders/">18-minute plan
and refocus reminders over on the LazarFocused blog</a>. There are some other more
widely known but great tips for running your work days more efficiently.</p>
<h2 id="kind-regards">Kind regards</h2>
<p>Folks, thank you very much for joining me here.</p>
<p>The comments section below is ready for your thoughts, if you would like to
externalise them.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #196: Get focused</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 22:27:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</guid><description> Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&amp;rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&amp;rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&amp;rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.
Well hello there folks, please make yourself at home!
This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday May 18 to Sunday May 31 of the extremely strange year of 2020.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="sylvia_draws_family_20200531.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&amp;rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&amp;rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&amp;rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there folks, please make yourself at home!</p>
<p>This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday May 18 to Sunday May 31 of the
extremely strange year of 2020.</p>
<p>That effort of looking back has resulted in the following three items.</p>
<h2 id="when-building-automatic-analysis-pipelines-get-your-batch-accuracy-testing-up-as-soon-as-you-can">When building automatic analysis pipelines, get your batch accuracy testing up as soon as you can</h2>
<p>A substantial part of my work hours these past two weeks went into working on a
automatic medical image analysis pipeline, with machine learning
inside™. (I mean &ldquo;AI&rdquo;, of course. And drones.)</p>
<p>I really do love this stuff, but sometimes it ends up coming down to putting
your head down and keeping it down, in order to grind out every percent or two
in improved accuracy.</p>
<p>The tip I wanted to offer here is the following: Even when you think your
pipeline is way too far from &ldquo;done&rdquo;™, get your batch accuracy testing up
and running.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a double whammy:</p>
<ol>
<li>You and your team get early and regular feedback on how your performance is
going.</li>
<li>You are forced to have the whole concept working from end-to-end. It can be
surprising how many little issues you still need to solve, and running into
them sooner rather than later is only good.</li>
</ol>
<p>By the way, the practical machine learning icon <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew%5FNg">Professor Andrew Ng&rsquo;s</a> free book
<a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/machine-learning-yearning/">Machine Learning Yearning</a> is filled to the brim with practical tips for
implementing ML in practice.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">Lazar Focus: The super tiny Windows app and website distraction blocker that you&rsquo;ve always wanted</h2>
<p>Back at the <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">start of 2018 I wrote the following about the macOS app and website
distraction blocker called Focus</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>After years of resisting these types of software tools due to my belief that I
should simply apply more grit and will power to squeeze out more focus hours,
I finally broke down and purchased the macOS app called Focus. You click its
pretty icon, and then your computer goes into focus mode: The Mail application
and a bunch of other non-focus-related apps all get killed, and a bunch of
websites (reddit, youtube, work chat, etc) are blocked for a user-configurable
block of time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even if you skipped that extract, please read the following one about the
<em>idea</em> behind such a focus app:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It usually takes a single moment of weakness for a distraction to terminate a
valuable block of focus. It takes a single moment of strength for this tool to
start a valuable block of focus.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Anyways, I was really missing this functionality on Windows, and so I busted
out my trusty <a href="https://www.lazarus-ide.org/">Lazarus IDE</a> (who <em>didn&rsquo;t</em> make apps back in the day with the old
win32 Delphi?!) and figured out the various required Windows APIs to create
this brand new super tiny but super effective app and website blocker:</p>








<figure><a href="lazar_focused_screenshot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As shown in the screenshot, it&rsquo;s sitting at 5 MB of memory use. In the age of
Electron apps, that&rsquo;s really small.</p>
<p>When you activate focus mode, it&rsquo;ll prevent your browser (Chrome, Brave,
Firefox or Edge) from viewing any distracting website (you get to configure the
list) by redirecting to a local web page with an inspiring quote, e.g.:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Concentration can be cultivated. One can learn to exercise willpower,
discipline one&rsquo;s body and train one&rsquo;s mind. &ndash; Anil Ambani</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It will also terminate any distracting apps, and helpfully prevent you from
starting them up during your focus session.</p>
<p>The convenient progress bar shows how far you are on your way to a 25 minute
pomodoro, but that is purely for motivation, and not enforced.</p>
<p>The total focus blocks and hours at the top should also help to keep us
motivated and&hellip; <strong>LAZAR FOCUSED!</strong></p>
<p>So, because there are probably (hopefully?) at least two other people who&rsquo;ll
find this as useful as I do, and because shipping and selling software that you
made yourself is awesome especially when it&rsquo;s a hobby project, I have decided
to try and sell Lazar Focus using something like <a href="https://gumroad.com/">gumroad</a>.</p>
<p>Hopefully soon with a hobby hour or three I can finish the installer and the
website, and then make the beta available at a reduced rate.</p>
<p>Because I prefer it for apps like this when I am the buyer, I have decided to
make it available as a one-time purchase, no eval but money-back, with
time-limited upgrades (probably a year?), but with your last licensed version
obviously remaining fully functional until the end of The Windows API.</p>
<h2 id="art-fun-with-portrait-ai">Art fun with Portrait AI</h2>
<p>Ever since I spent a bit of time better curating my twitter subscriptions,
getting rid of the vitriol and adding much more STEM (shout out to <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Eric Topol</a>
&ndash; you could install twitter <em>just</em> for him and you would be great), they often
bring me shiny treasures.</p>
<p>Recently, it was <a href="https://portraitai.com/">portraitai.com</a> which brought a great deal of mirth to my home
as we made authentic looking portraits of each other. (We&rsquo;re just a bunch of
silly primates with amazing gadgets.)</p>
<p>It didn&rsquo;t seem to work all that well on me however, until I started pulling
funny faces:</p>








<figure><a href="charl_portraitai.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>With that, dear friends, I bid you kindness, happiness and health.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #194: 136 words a day</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 23:19:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/</guid><description> Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&amp;rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&amp;rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies.
This post quite compactly gazes back at the week from Monday May 4 to Sunday May 10.
It starts with a short summary of my work week, followed by a story which you will hopefully enjoy.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="afrikaburn2017-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&amp;rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&amp;rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This post quite compactly gazes back at the week from Monday May 4 to Sunday
May 10.</p>
<p>It starts with a short summary of my work week, followed by a story which you
will hopefully enjoy.</p>
<h2 id="how-was-your-week-honey">How was your week honey?</h2>
<p>I hacked on and fixed iPad microphone support in our direct-to-patient
TeleMedicine app.</p>
<p>If you are a programmer, or you have programmers in your life, you&rsquo;ll hopefully
understand the absolute catnip of technical rabbit holes that suck you in for
hours on end, only to eject you on a beautiful but extremely short-lived
dopamine deluge of discovery.</p>
<p>We integrated <a href="https://casual-effects.com/markdeep/">markdeep</a> into the performance tracking component of one of our
medical image processing pipelines.</p>
<p>Having a format, namely .md.html, which is this easy to generate
programmatically from some computational pipeline, yet results in such
attractive output documents is a great boon.</p>
<h2 id="gou-1-reveals-her-plans-and-makes-us-think--more">GOU #1 reveals her plans and makes us think (more)</h2>
<p><a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> turned another year older.</p>
<p>At the dinner table on the big day, we were having a conversation about further
education in general and about postgraduate studies and PhDs in particular.</p>
<p>(She is now in high school, so these conversations are happening more often.)</p>
<p>I said that she will have to get a PhD in Physics or Math, but that I would
probably be able to make peace with a PhD in Engineering also.</p>
<p>She asked us how the PhD works, and so we explained the background as well as
we could.</p>
<p>We spent quite some time on the observation that the most important part of a
successful PhD is just never giving up.</p>
<p>Although never giving up is a chronic aspect, many PhD-veterans will tell you
that this adventure often includes a fairly acute existential crisis, mostly at
about the halfway mark.</p>
<p>This is when the candidate asks pertinent questions like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Why, oh why did I ever think this was a good idea?</li>
<li>Is this work really worth <em>anything</em>?</li>
<li>Does anyone really care about this?</li>
<li>I wonder what the non-academic job market is like at this moment?!</li>
</ul>
<p>Fortunately in many cases, the candidate gets through this process and emerges
from the other side of the ordeal ever so slightly stronger and wiser.</p>
<p>(For those of you who have been paying attention, this crisis is like the super
deluxe version of the <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">5-stage Creative Process</a>.)</p>
<p>I digress&hellip;</p>
<p>Talking more about the mechanics, GOU #1 asked how long a PhD thesis usually
is.</p>
<p>Off the top of my head I said: &ldquo;Around 50 thousand words, but there is of
course huge variation&rdquo;.</p>
<p>At that point she got out her phone (well, it&rsquo;s actually never not out) and
made a quick calculation, after which she quipped: &ldquo;Well, that&rsquo;s
straight-forward then. I&rsquo;ll spend one year planning, then I&rsquo;ll spend the year
after that writing only 136 words per day, and the year after that revising
everything to make it perfect.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was a simply lovely and humorous conversation to have at that moment, but
what a great point she made: If you can manage to write 136 words per day for a
year, you&rsquo;ll have 50000 words.</p>
<h3 id="the-slightly-modified-136-word-plan">The slightly modified 136 word plan</h3>
<p>136 words is really not that much if you look at it in isolation. The text
above, from right after &ldquo;I digress&hellip;&rdquo; until right before the heading above, is
exactly 136 words (if Emacs can be trusted).</p>
<p>To me the <a href="/tags/compounding/">compounding</a> nature of this act of writing such a paltry number of
words every day, but simply keeping at it for months and years, is quite
amazing.</p>
<p>So, thanks to my daughter&rsquo;s inspiration, I added a daily item to <a href="/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/">my habit
tracker</a> that says <em>Write 100 words towards publication</em>.</p>
<p>I hope she won&rsquo;t mind that I changed the limit to 100, simply because I would
like to increase my chances of being consistent and maintaining those <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">streaks</a>.</p>
<p>I have added the explicit qualifier that the 100 words I write should be
towards publication: This means that my intention should be for them to end up
either in a blog post, or perhaps a future book project, or any other form of
publication that is intended for public consumption.</p>
<p>Wish me luck folks! Even better, why not join me on this journey?!</p>
<h2 id="friendly-wishes">Friendly wishes</h2>
<p>Thank you friends for meeting me here.</p>
<p>I wish you all health and kindness and contentment.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #193: COVID-19 part 3.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 15:33:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</guid><description> Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.
The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12 to Sunday May 2.
This post has a strong nerd flavour. If that is not your inclination, please use the table of contents (to your right) to navigate to the bits that you do find interesting.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!--
2020-05-02 21:38 Boiler Room Solomun 2015 playing on the second screen while
I'm typing this.  I was hoping to understand why this has 43M views, and my
favourite boiler room of all time, Maceo Plex in Berlin in 2015, has "only"
11M.

Let me know in the comments if you read this. :)
-->
<p>The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12
to Sunday May 2.</p>
<p>This post has a strong nerd flavour. If that is not your inclination, please
use the table of contents (to your right) to navigate to the bits that you do
find interesting.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re in a rush, and can only select one section, I would recommend <a href="#the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">the
one on Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Have fun!</p>
<h2 id="covid-19-status-update">COVID-19 status update</h2>
<p>On Friday, May 1, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/lockdown-level-4-what-is-now-allowed-2020-4">the South African lockdown was slightly lifted from level 5
to level
4</a>.</p>
<p>This means that a part of the workforce will start returning to work, and that
citizens are allowed slightly more freedom of movement.</p>
<p>If safety had been the only requirement, we should probably have had to
continue with level 5 for a while longer, but that darned economy unfortunately
also has to be kept afloat.</p>
<p>In spite of this, I was super pleased to read the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Masks are obligatory.</strong> Everyone has to wear cloth face masks outside their
homes. If you don&rsquo;t yet have a cloth mask, you can wear a scarf or a t-shirt
wrapped around your mouth and nose, says Dlamini-Zuma.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This might end up being the thing that gets us through this in something that
resembles one piece.</p>
<p>The second announcement I was super happy with, was that we would be allowed
outside for exercise between 6 and 9 in the mornings.</p>
<p>So on Saturday morning I went out for my first post-level-5 run, ON THE
OUTSIDE. (It does feel strange going out on the street for the first time in
five weeks.)</p>
<p>The majority of people I saw actually had some form of face mask going on.</p>
<p>I had expected otherwise, because doing cardiorespiratory exercise with a mask
on is not easy, and people can be stubborn.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/advanced/a20842404/product-review-buff-headwear/">Buffs</a>
are these fantastically useful &ldquo;seamless tubular garments made from
high-performance microfibre&rdquo; that many runners swear by.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out you can <em>also</em> use them as as-running-proof-as-possible face
masks:</p>








<figure><a href="cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask_hu815c169f7dc006fef835eddef66e09fe_118854_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg"
            

         width="240"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>Pro-tip: If there&rsquo;s a runner in your life, and you&rsquo;re on the lookout for a
gift, just get them a buff. You can <em>never</em> have too many buffs.</p>
<h2 id="gou-2-is-10">GOU #2 is 10</h2>
<p>My most favourite middle child in the whole world recently hit the double
digits, and she was suitably chuffed with this.</p>
<p>It must be strange experiencing your 10th birthday under these truly surreal
conditions.</p>
<p>On the other hand, when you&rsquo;re 10, you probably don&rsquo;t dwell on thoughts like
that for too long.</p>
<h2 id="miscellaneous-catch-up">Miscellaneous catch-up</h2>
<p>In the past weeks, I wrote a number of other blog posts, started a new blog,
and discovered an obscure but fantastic new blogging tool.</p>
<p>Oh, and my expensive ergonomic keyboard broke.</p>
<h3 id="fantastic-blogging-tools-and-where-to-find-them">Fantastic blogging tools and where to find them</h3>
<p>It all started when I finally got around to exploring
<a href="https://ox-hugo.scripter.co/">ox-hugo</a>, the Emacs package for writing Hugo
posts using Org mode.</p>
<p>You might not recall this, but the mere <em>existence</em> of <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/#build-and-upload-the-new-static-hotness">ox-hugo was the reason
I chose
Hugo</a>
when it was time to leave Wordpress behind.</p>
<!--
Hey there friends reading these hidden messages!

There are multiple explicit and implicit streams of connection running through
these channels and it's lovely.

Anyways, it is now 22:44 and I finished the Solomun boiler room set.

There are indeed so many stories happening in those frames, many of which will
only become apparent after more viewings.

I'm now back to the Maceo Plex set, with a smile of recognition on my face.
-->
<p>Well, it turns out that, <em>if</em> you&rsquo;re an Emacs Org mode user, ox-hugo is pretty
close to blogging nirvana.</p>
<p>In the past few days, I&rsquo;ve used it to turn arbitrary Org mode entries from my
month journal into blog posts, to send the exact same Org mode file to two
different blogs with different sets of title and metadata, and to assert
Neo-in-the-matrix-style control over what goes where and how.</p>
<p>If I have to put my finger on the core of ox-hugo&rsquo;s extreme utility, I would
say that <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi">Kaushal Modi</a>, the brains behind
ox-hugo, has managed to create a perfect coupling between Org mode on the one
hand and Hugo on the other, a coupling that maximally leverages the strengths
of each.</p>
<p>(I will probably be writing more about this, but &hellip; elsewhere. <em>[queue
suspenseful music here]</em>)</p>
<h3 id="other-mostly-very-nerdy-blog-posts">Other mostly very nerdy blog posts</h3>
<p>As part of the ox-hugo investigation, I had to figure out how to <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/04/26/cite-consistently-between-org-ref-and-ox-hugo/">cite
consistently between straight Org mode and
ox-hugo</a>
for automatic bibtex-backed bibliographies.</p>
<p>Inspired by friend <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2020/04/28/voice-capture-org-tasks-on-android/">Stéfan&rsquo;s post on voice capturing and automatically
transcribing notes to Org
mode</a>,
I figured out how to <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/2020/04/30/voice-capture-org-mode-notes-and-more-using-siri-shortcuts-on-ios/">do the same on iOS and wrote it all
up</a>.</p>
<p>If you clicked on that second link, you will have discovered my brand new blog,
the hopefully catchily titled <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">Org Mode
Exocortex</a>. I will be posting <em>ultra</em>-nerdy Emacs
Org mode content over there.</p>
<p>(Friend Stéfan is the very first guest blogger, with a re-post of his Android
speech recognition post linked above. BTW, that was my first guest blogging
experience ever. Life for the Z-list blogger does not move fast.)</p>
<p>Finally, also thanks to ox-hugo&rsquo;s motivation, I figured (haha, now I see what I
did there) out how to make and publish a new <a href="/2020/05/02/drop-in-replacement-for-hugo-figure-shortcode-with-responsive-img-srcset/"><code>figure</code> shortcode for Hugo that
automatically resizes images and gets your browser to download only the best
one</a>!</p>
<h3 id="microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-desktop-at-4-years-rip">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic Desktop at 4 years: RIP</h3>
<p>After all of that good news, I do have to report the following not-so-great news:</p>
<p>After just under four years of approximately one half of my typing, the
<a href="/2016/05/22/weekly-head-voices-107-balance/">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboard I welcomed into my home at the start of
May of 2016</a>, has developed a key
failure.</p>
<p>More specifically, the physical &ldquo;G&rdquo;, which is my &ldquo;I&rdquo; (thanks
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dvorak_keyboard_layout">Dvorak</a>), fails about
30% of the time, with that duty cycle slowly growing.</p>
<p>(You may bring your jokes about why specifically the &ldquo;I&rdquo; is failing first to
the comment section below!)</p>
<p>I opened up the keyboard following <a href="http://emmanuelcontreras.com/how-to/how-to-disassemble-microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-keyboard-and-make-it-wired/">the instructions and photos of Emmanuel
Contreras</a>.</p>
<p>(What I can add to Contreras&rsquo;s information, is that the palm rest is held fast
by no less than 12 little screws, some odd-sized. Pro-tip: When you remove all
of these, put them down in the same pattern as the holes, so that you can get
them back in later.)</p>
<p>However, one unfortunately ends up at the metal backing which is attached to
the top-plate with about 30 or more plastic pop-rivet like mechanisms.</p>
<p>Information online also seems to indicate that once a single key goes, you have
to replace the whole board.</p>
<p>Some more searching brought me to <a href="https://youtu.be/x09inK8-G1Y">this obscure but helpful YouTube
review</a> where Kevin explains that although
everyone at his company loved the keyboard, they had simply accepted it as part
of their business expense to replace them every 6 months to a year.</p>
<p>If you search through <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Microsoft-Ergonomic-Keyboard-Business-5KV-00001/product-reviews/B00CYX26BC/ref=cm_cr_arp_d_viewopt_kywd?pageNumber=1&amp;filterByKeyword=durability">the Amazon reviews for
&ldquo;durability&rdquo;</a>,
it really starts to look like a case of a fantastic keyboard marred by issues
with its durability.</p>
<p>However, if you need a relatively affordable &ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; keyboard, where with
&ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; I mean shaped in such a way that your wrists get to stay more or
less straight while typing, with really great feel and low-impact typing, the
Sculpt comes out on top.</p>
<p>Although it goes against my grain, I should probably be happy with the above
average 4 years that this one managed, and start finding a local source for its
inevitable replacement.</p>
<p>Nerds in the audience: I am very curious to hear about your keyboard
preferences in the comments. Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="two-lessons-learnt-from-how-to-take-smart-notes">Two lessons learnt from How to Take Smart Notes</h2>
<p>On March 31 I quickly read through <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/34507927-how-to-take-smart-notes">Sönke Ahrens&rsquo;s book, How to Take Smart
Notes</a>.</p>
<p>(The full title is actually &ldquo;How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to
Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking &ndash; for Students, Academics and Nonfiction
Book Writers&rdquo;)</p>
<h3 id="the-most-portable-cross-platform-ebook-format-with-self-contained-annotations-is">The most portable cross-platform ebook format with self-contained annotations is&hellip;</h3>
<p>I bought the Kindle book on Amazon, because that&rsquo;s how I&rsquo;ve been doing it for
years.</p>
<p>However, although I prefer reading novels on my Kindle e-Ink device, for
reference works it&rsquo;s a deal breaker that my highlights and notes are not in a
standards compliant format that integrates nicely with <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing personal
knowledge management system</a>.</p>
<p>My goal was to find an alternative format for these books with the following features:</p>
<ul>
<li>Before you answer PDF, which I use extensively for academic papers, typeset
books, and many other things: The alternative format should be fully
reflowable, like the source Kindle book.</li>
<li>Readable and annotations editable on all my non-Kindle devices (Windows,
Linux, macOS, iOS).</li>
<li>Most importantly: Flexible annotations, including at least highlighting and
positional notes, that are stored within the file itself, so they can never
be lost.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t expect this to be too much of a challenge.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<p>After a number of hours spent spelunking down a number of different
rabbit-holes, with epub3 being the greatest disappointment (the spec has all
the features, but the implementations largely lack good annotation support), I
ended up in a place where you probably would not expect to find me&hellip;</p>
<p>Dear readers, the best format that satisfies all requirements above
is&hellip; <code>&lt;FRITS_DRUMROLL /&gt;</code> &hellip; <strong>Microsoft DOCX</strong>!</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been DeDRM&rsquo;ing (google it) the Kindle reference books I
purchase in order to be able to read and annotate them across all my platforms.</p>
<p>For this, the iPad is pretty great.</p>
<p>Once read, the DOCX files, including all of the annotations I made, are stored
in the correct place in my synchronised file hierarchy, and are fully
searchable and accessible with standard tools.</p>
<h3 id="the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">The amazing Niklas Luhmann and his Zettelkasten</h3>
<p>The book itself, <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em>, spends well-deserved time on the
phenomenon that was the prodigiously productive German sociologist Professor
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niklas_Luhmann">Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Over his career, Prof. Luhmann wrote more than 70 books and published almost
400 research articles.</p>
<p>He made a massive impact on the world of sociology and systems theory.</p>
<p>When asked in <a href="https://www.uni-bielefeld.de/soz/luhmann-archiv/pdf/jschmidt_zettelkasten-als-uberraschungsgenerator.pdf">a 1997
interview</a>
how he managed to this productive, he answered:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Ich denke ja nicht alles allein, sondern das
geschieht weitgehend im Zettelkasten. [&hellip;]
Meine Produktivität ist im wesentlichen aus dem
Zettelkasten-System zu erklären. [&hellip;]
Der Zettelkasten kostet mich mehr Zeit als das
Bücherschreiben</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Translated this is probably something like (German readers, help me out here
please):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think everything by myself, but that largely happens in the slip box. [&hellip;]
My productivity is essentially due to that slipbox system. [..]
The slipbox costs me more time than that writing books</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <em>zettelkasten</em> he referred to were quite simply a set of wooden slipboxes,
in which he could store pieces of paper (the &ldquo;slips&rdquo;), each of which had a
single idea written on it.</p>
<p>It looked more or less exactly like this:</p>








<figure><a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu61195ac08eb6003207b1b95bfe6dfa0b_91461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu61195ac08eb6003207b1b95bfe6dfa0b_91461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu61195ac08eb6003207b1b95bfe6dfa0b_91461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Photo of Luhmann&amp;rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Photo of Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Over the course of his career, he managed to write about 90000 (yes, ninety
thousand) of these notes, all of which you can now <a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">browse online at the Niklas
Luhmann-Archiv</a>.</p>
<p>Importantly, he had come up with an ingenious numbering system for linking each
new note to its chain of predecessors, and also to other related chains
anywhere in the zettelkasten.</p>
<p>When it was time to write a book or a paper, he would dive into his this
collection, and then take a stroll through his amazing web of interlinked
thoughts, some of them having matured for years.</p>
<p>Putting together the publication became an exercise in harvesting index cards
from his slipboxes, instead of a positively intimidating mountain of writing,
thinking and rewriting.</p>
<p>This is such a boss-level example of the principle of
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/compounding/">compounding</a>, and one which is
definitely worth trying to follow.</p>
<p>Since reading Ahrens&rsquo;s book, I have started extending <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing note-taking
universe</a> to be more Zettelkasten-like,
when appropriate.</p>
<p>Org mode is a great basis for this, and packages like
<a href="https://github.com/jethrokuan/org-roam">org-roam</a> help us to get closer to our
90-thousand-notes-dreams.</p>
<p>On a higher level, I have been thinking and writing a great deal about how to
merge effectively the Zettelkasten one-idea-per-note approach into the full
spectrum of writing complexity that Org mode supports.</p>
<p>It is important to be mindful of the <em>mode</em> of documentation that you need to
apply at any give point.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about the Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten, <a href="https://writingcooperative.com/zettelkasten-how-one-german-scholar-was-so-freakishly-productive-997e4e0ca125">this Writing
Cooperative article in
English</a>
and <a href="https://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Missing-Link-Luhmanns-Denkmaschine-endlich-im-Netz-4364512.html">this Heise article in
German</a>
are a great start.</p>
<p>This might not be the last time that you&rsquo;ll hear me talking about Luhmann and
his Zettelkasten.</p>
<h2 id="uitzwaaien">Uitzwaaien</h2>
<p>Thank you friends for reading this and connecting with me here!</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #190: 3=4.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 15:38:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</guid><description> Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok, because that's how life is. Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!
This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to Sunday March 8, 2020.
(I had made a good start on the post on March 8, but then the work week and a bunch of homing missile deadlines hit.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was
still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok,
because that's how life is.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to
Sunday March 8, 2020.</p>
<p>(I had made a good start on the post on March 8, but then the work week and a
bunch of homing missile deadlines hit. As I write this bit, it is Saturday
March 14, 14:30 SAST.)</p>
<h2 id="gou-3-turns-4">GOU #3 turns 4!</h2>
<p>Our third Genetic Offspring Unit, creative named GOU #3, fairly recently
completed another year of life.</p>
<p>She has now collected the grand total of 4.</p>
<p>It was a pleasure celebrating her birthday with her as it felt like this was
the first time that she was intellectually fully present.</p>
<p>With apparent ease she even understood the sometimes tricky concept of having
one&rsquo;s party on a different day than one&rsquo;s birthday.</p>
<p>For future us, I would also like to note that her pronunciation and sentence
construction are growing more and more precise, sometimes even overly so, the
observation of which delights me.</p>
<p>GOU#3, if you read this years and years in the future: We can already see that
you are an amazing human being. We are deeply happy that you have come here to
join our clan.</p>
<h2 id="new-pair-of-altras-acquired">New pair of Altras acquired.</h2>
<p>In an unexpected but quite happy turn of events, it is starting to look like I
might have to take part in a trail run in July.</p>
<p>(Charl from the future: Only if my finicky ankles man up between now and then.)</p>
<p>Once I&rsquo;ve actually done it, and I&rsquo;m still able to tell the tale, I will surely
do so.</p>
<p>Because I am one of the World&rsquo;s Worst Trail Runners, I will definitely have to
step up my training between now and then.</p>
<p>As with many other endeavours in life, an important component of all of this is
acquiring suitable shoes.</p>
<p>Because <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">my giant-toe-box-zero-drop
Escalantes</a> have been treating
me very well, I had soon narrowed it down to any one of the Altra trail shoes:
Superiors (minimalist), Lone Peaks (jack-of-all-trades), Timp (sightly more
support) and Olympus (maximalist-ish).</p>
<p>After having read all of the internet regarding the different Altra trail
shoes, I reluctantly came to the conclusion that none of them really knocked it
out of the park.</p>
<p>Anyways, one Sunday I walked into our local sports super store (I&rsquo;m sorry my
fellow nerds), and it so happened that they had a pair of Lone Peak 4.5s in my
size: GINORMOUS CLOWN SHOE SIZE.</p>
<p>Trying them on, I tripped and fell right into the psychological black hole of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases">biases</a> and
<em>instantly</em> convinced myself that these were the shoes for me.</p>
<p>Fast forward a week of calling my behavioural insurer (starts with a Disco ends
with a Y) every single day, and they finally managed to figure out what was
wrong somewhere deep in their unfortunately quite sub-par IT systems, and
flipped the <a href="https://www.discovery.co.za/vitality/fitness-booster-shoe">Shoe Purchase Gamification
switch</a>.</p>
<p>In short, if you are able to activate this feature (you have to be super
patient and a bit stubborn), said insurer will subsidise the purchase of a pair
of running shoes based on how often you exercise every week.</p>
<p>This is one neat way of making your running addiction work for you, if you can
somehow absorb the possibly substantial startup cost, i.e. the hours you have
to spend on the phone with the friendly support agents.</p>
<p>Behold my beautiful new trail running shoes:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>State-of-the-art trail-running shoes for the World's Worst Trail
Runner.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="crabby-wallet">Crabby Wallet!</h2>
<p>After years of eyeing Fido U2F and FIDO2 hardware security keys on the
internet, I finally took the plunge and acquired <a href="https://www.yubico.com/product/security-key-nfc-by-yubico">a Yubico Security Key
NFC</a>.</p>
<p>Up to now I used mostly the LastPass Authenticator app and more recently Authy
to generate OTPs as second factor (2FA) for most of my important accounts.</p>
<p>(BTW, if you&rsquo;re not yet using 2FA for your important accounts, such as email,
now is the best time to upgrade. I would recommend getting <a href="https://authy.com/">the Authy
app</a> because it optionally supports multi-device
synchronization.)</p>
<p>The YubiCo hardware device is supposed to be more secure than authenticator
apps due to domain hashing, and it&rsquo;s pretty cool that you don&rsquo;t have to copy
across 6-digit codes, but what I didn&rsquo;t foresee as clearly was the following
simple difference:</p>
<p>I almost always have my phone with me. However, I don&rsquo;t always have my keyring
with me.</p>
<p>I set out to find a new wallet to replace my already pretty minimalist fake
leather credit card booklet. The new wallet had to be at least as minimalist,
but it had to have some sort of lanyard to which I could attach the security
key.</p>
<p>I was delighted to discover that (of course) there&rsquo;s a whole community of
minimalist wallet enthusiasts on the internet.</p>
<p>I was even more delighted when I discovered that the Crabby Wallet C3, a
second-generation product of a <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1369622196/the-crabby-wallet-a-wallet-that-is-not-for-everyon">super successful 2015
kickstarter</a>,
was available all the way down here!</p>
<p>Behold the minimalist wonder that is my new Crabby Wallet:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The Crabby Wallet C3. As you can see, it's only slightly larger than a credit
card. It's made of canvas which looks pretty durable. After a breaking-in
period, it easily holds up to 10 cards. Sometimes there's even cash stashed
under the rubber-band.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>(Charl from 6 days in the future writes: This looks like it&rsquo;s going to be a
keeper. It&rsquo;s more compact and more secure than my previous credit card booklet,
and it has become much more ergonomic after the initial break-in period.)</p>
<h2 id="the-end-of-this-post">The end of this post.</h2>
<p>Thank you for connecting with me here!</p>
<p>Remember, it&rsquo;s now Saturday March 14, 15:26 SAST, but this post will forever
act like it finds itself on Sunday March 8.</p>
<p>I hope that tomorrow I can write WHV #191, a less complicated post that will
come into being not too far away from the moment that is its observation point.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Do you feel like you have an observation point, a specific location that is
your momentary source of perception and thought?</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been getting back into the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up guide</a>, and
there are some truly delightful exercises of the all-encompassing
consciousness.</p>
<p>Remember: <em>There is no observation point!</em></p>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>