<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>neil degrasse tyson on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/neil-degrasse-tyson/</link><description>Recent content in neil degrasse tyson on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 22:35:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/neil-degrasse-tyson/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #185: Starship GOU #1.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 22:35:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</guid><description> Welcome back friends!
It&amp;rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.
Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file two weeks ago, but then I didn&amp;rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).
In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more
precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.</p>
<p>Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file
two weeks ago, but then I didn&rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then
everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).</p>
<p>In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time
right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look
back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view from a Friday afternoon arrival run along the Langebaan Lagoon in the West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="lecturing-old-school">Lecturing, old school.</h2>
<p>On Thursday, November 21, I gave a two hour lecture titled &ldquo;IoMT in Healthcare
Innovation&rdquo; at the <a href="https://www.usb.ac.za/">University of Stellenbosch Business
School</a>.</p>
<p>IoMT expands to the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/bernardmarr/2018/01/25/why-the-internet-of-medical-things-iomt-will-start-to-transform-healthcare-in-2018/#46f18c694a3c">&ldquo;Internet of Medical
Things&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>My knowledge of IoT is spotty, and before giving this lecture I didn&rsquo;t even
know that the term &ldquo;IoMT&rdquo; existed.</p>
<p>Fortunately, it turns out that a lot of what we&rsquo;re currently doing at Stone
Three Healthcare (connecting patients with specialist care through
diagnostic-grade streaming of auscultation (and soon other modalities) device
data) can in fact be classified as IoMT.</p>
<p>Phew.</p>
<p>I would like to make the following observations based on this experience:</p>
<ol>
<li>I still really love getting up in front of a group of people to present
something. There are so many things that could go wrong, but when they go
right, the experience is great.</li>
<li>A two hour lecture is quite long, for both the students, even when they&rsquo;re
as advanced as this, <em>and</em> for the lecturer, especially when he is as out of
practice as this.
<ul>
<li>If there&rsquo;s a next time, I will either insert my own 15 minute break, or I
will get the class to break out into some sort of topic-strengthening
activity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I had somehow forgotten how much time lecture preparation could take up,
even when you just had to present your own day-to-day reality.
<ul>
<li>BIG UP TO THE LECTURERS IN THE WHV AUDIENCE!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="productivity-system-tuneup">Productivity system tuneup.</h2>
<p>Last Sunday morning, as the family took a last swim at Kraalbaai before we had
to return home, I tried to apply some serious thinking (well, I did this by
stringing together a series of normal thinking moments) to the problem of
increasing my efficiency and focus at work.</p>
<p>At that moment, the scenery outside looked like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view of the Preekstoel from Kraalbaai beach, West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Regular readers will know that coming up with new ways to increase and maintain
focus is a life-long endeavour, which my subconscious self enjoys inventing
interesting new ways to subvert.</p>
<p>Conscious me has made peace with the fact that it has no choice but to keep on
working at its end of the bargain, until the very end.</p>
<p>With the opposing forces involved, my focus seems to oscillate with varying
frequencies between terrible and not too bad.</p>
<p>Anyways, having had a few days of fresh air and majestic scenery to jog the
neural circuitry, I applied myself, again, to the problem at hand.</p>
<p>I thought that sketching could help, so I was scribbling using a rather
impressive electronic pencil-analogue on a glass screen.</p>
<p>After several focused minutes (SEVERAL MINUTES, I TELL YOU!), I had a mindmap
with &ldquo;increase efficiency&rdquo; in a little oval at the center, arrows pointing
outwards into three terribly familiar habits, each in a rectangle <em>this</em> time,
and finally more connecting lines to lists of pretty plausible sounding reasons
for the three well-known habits.</p>
<p>The three rectangles were:</p>
<ol>
<li>Morning planning.</li>
<li>Inbox 0.</li>
<li>Pomodoro always.</li>
</ol>
<p>Over the years, these three items have made pretty regular appearances, in
various different forms, on this blog.</p>
<p>(I laughed when I just looked up <a href="/2010/09/20/an-indecent-proposal-weekly-head-voices-31/">this old 2010
post</a> and found a
pretty effective focus technique in the comments.)</p>
<p>Anyways, although the little thinking and drawing session documented here
seemingly did not result in any new revelations, the act of going through the
whole thought process, and documenting the results (again), seemed to have
contributed to a pretty great week in terms of focus.</p>
<p>I wrote down a little mantra for myself (definitely not fit for publication),
weaving together the three points above and the reasoning behind them, almost
like the affirmation in Wreckit Ralph&rsquo;s bad guy support group:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m bad, and that&rsquo;s good. I will never be good, and that&rsquo;s not bad. There&rsquo;s
no one I&rsquo;d rather be than me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have <em>chosen</em>
to take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having <em>decided</em>
to <em>commit</em>, i.e. active.</p>
<p>My humble focus mantra is following in this tradition.</p>
<p>(I really hope that my subversive sub-conscious is not paying attention right
now&hellip;)</p>
<h2 id="starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">Starship GOU #1, taxiing on the runway.</h2>
<p>Wednesday, December 4, was officially <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU
#1&rsquo;s</a> last day of primary school.</p>
<p>Although she seemed to navigate this emotional event with her customary
even-keeled demeanour, some of the moments were really just too big to let go by
without a good cry or two.</p>
<p>I was also happy to observe the level of retrospection and sunny candour she
applied to her informal post hoc analyses of above-mentioned crying moments.</p>
<p>I really hope that she strengthens and maintains this important human ability.</p>
<p>From our perspective as parents, it feels like the stakes are being raised
quite significantly.</p>
<p>The thing is, our oldest is now quite obviously becoming an adult.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like that scene at the end of the brilliant 2015 movie <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2096673/">Inside
Out</a>, where the protagonist&rsquo;s brain
console is suddenly upgraded to one with at least 9000 new knobs and dials.</p>
<p>Up to now, we (the parents) were GOU #1&rsquo;s only control system.</p>
<p>Now it is becoming quite clear that she is increasingly forming her own
opinions, and making her own decisions.</p>
<p>In most cases, the physical constraints of a 13 year old living in her parent&rsquo;s
house still afford us some level of control.</p>
<p>However, relying on that would be missing the point entirely.</p>
<p>You see, we find ourselves in the moment of truth, when the past 13 years of
mostly gentle programming has to start executing all by itself.</p>
<p>Our little GOU #1, our first co-created human intelligence, is preparing to go
out into the world.</p>
<p>She has not taken off yet, so we do our best to apply the final touches to her
already promising software.</p>
<p>We exhort her regularly: <em>Be useful. Use your (rational) brain. Be kind. Find
the kindness in others.</em></p>
<p>In the darkness, when we are at our weakest, stripped down to our core, we do
what all parents do:</p>
<p>We worry, and we hope with a passion, the intensity of which it is difficult to
describe, that our offspring units do manage to <a href="/2012/03/04/rhythm-of-the-night-weekly-head-voices-66/#life-philosophy-that-works">generate their own motivation,
to manufacture meaning, and to create
love</a>.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
This could be a runway, but it is the entrance to Vergelegen Wine Estate. At
this point, I was in fact running on this way.
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Rhythm of the Night. [Weekly Head Voices #66]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/03/04/rhythm-of-the-night-weekly-head-voices-66/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 12:49:36 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/03/04/rhythm-of-the-night-weekly-head-voices-66/</guid><description> (This post has an extremely high slightly-insane-rambling index (SIRI). You have been warned.)
The rhythm of life I love Unkle. Here’s the introduction to their song Back and Forth:
The only life you can get is one made up of ups and downs. The trick is in learning how to deal with the downs, increasing the number and duration of the ups, and enjoying every last drop out of them. This realisation was brought to the surface by a car advert in which the narrator claimed that time in the car equalled “quality time”.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This post has an extremely high slightly-insane-rambling index (SIRI). You have been warned.)</em></p>
<h1 id="the-rhythm-of-life">The rhythm of life</h1>
<p>I love Unkle. Here’s the introduction to their song Back and Forth:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TDVYJQPwHw0?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>The only life you can get is one made up of ups and downs. The trick is in learning how to deal with the downs, increasing the number and duration of the ups, and enjoying every last drop out of them. This realisation was brought to the surface by a car advert in which the narrator claimed that time in the car equalled “quality time”. I don’t like cars, but I love quality time. It usually comes in little bits and, as <a href="/2011/04/07/happinessexception-weekly-head-voices-44/" title="HappinessException blogpost">I’ve reported before on this very blog</a>, happiness and other important things also come in little bits, interspersed by other often less interesting bits. Although one has a limited extent of control over some parameters of this rhythm of ups and downs, of excitement and boredom, it can never be smoothed out. As is often the case, the best course of action is the zen one: Step outside and try to absorb completely the multi-factorial whole.</p>
<p><em>Intermezzo – this post’s title was inspired by this Italian masterpiece:</em></p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u3ltZmI5LQw?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<h1 id="selling-ones-soul-to-the-virtual">Selling one’s soul to the Virtual</h1>
<p>A week ago, I started going through my bookshelf trying to find books that could potentially be given away or sold, freeing up some space for I’m not sure exactly what. Here’s a photo of some of them:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/somebooks.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/somebooks.jpg"
        
            alt="Books traded for space."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Books traded for space.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Each of these gave me pleasure at some point in my life, taking me on journeys to faraway corners of my imagination. Each of these contributed in some way to the ball of thoughts that is me. Years ago, I would not have considered giving even a single book away. Now I do, because I convince myself that everything is available digitally. I do read on my Kindle, where everything is far more convenient and takes up zero real-world space. I can never lose anything again. If I want anything, I can either find it in my archives or acquire it anew.</p>
<p>Could this line of reasoning, this position, be something that’s really quite insidious? Besides containing information on their pages, the books are tangible and visible reminders of the knowledge that they represent. By getting rid of them, could it be that I’m exchanging parts of my soul for an empty, virtual promise, for oblivion? Maybe the books should remain there, on my bookshelf, as constant physical reminders of the knowledge that they brought me — of all the knowledge that I should continually cultivate and upgrade.</p>
<p>Maybe the time has finally come for the 21st century reboot of Microsoft BOB. :) Then a failed (and the brunt of many jokes) experiment, perhaps now the seeds of a solution to the problem of trading the physical for the virtual. Imagine a private room where you can walk between your virtual bookshelves, a virtual haven to keep your slow, real humanity intact.</p>
<h1 id="life-philosophy-that-works">Life philosophy that works</h1>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil_deGrasse_Tyson" title="wikipedia page Neil deGrasse Tyson">Neil deGrasse Tyson</a> is a prominent American astrophysicist and science communicator. Recently he took part in a <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/qccer/i_am_neil_degrasse_tyson_ask_me_anything/" title="Neil deGrasse Tyson reddit IAmA">IAmA session</a> on reddit, where he answered the questions of random reddit users. To the question “What can you tell a young man looking for motivation in life itself?” his answer was the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The problem, often not discovered until late in life, is that when you look for things in life like love, meaning, motivation, it implies they are sitting behind a tree or under a rock. The most successful people in life recognize, that in life they create their own love, they manufacture their own meaning, they generate their own motivation.</p>
<p>For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This will definitely find its place in the Unified Dogma of Me (UDM). For now, I’m doing my best to fuse it permanently with my atoms.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>