<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Docker on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/docker/</link><description>Recent content in Docker on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/docker/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #260: I'm not your guy, buddy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</guid><description>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.
The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. GOU #3 (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining. It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250322_palmiet_hike.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_94326a752c7d0837.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_3039937a478d9ff0.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_95661b4813429562.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&rsquo;s Bay. <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #3</a> (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining.  It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</p>
<p>A week or two later, GOU #3 recovered by being an absolute trooper through the whole of the slightly more substantial and absolutely brilliant 6.5km family hike all around the little <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/rreQJ7uyT1SFSKfJ7">Sea Farm private reserve&rsquo;s peninsula</a>. I tell myself, and others, that this is partially due to involving her in the progress of the event, by showing her at regular intervals on Google Maps exactly where we found ourselves, and how we were making progress around the peninsula.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, we will both have better answers to the question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why am I in such a rush to get through life when I want so much to enjoy it?</p>
<p>&ndash; Jan Chozen Bays</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(With that in mind, you might also find <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237</a> interesting!)</p>
<h2 id="the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-migrates-again">The whole cpbotha.net-hive migrates again</h2>
<p>Slightly more than five years after <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">the previous migration of the whole so-called cpbotha.net-hive from WebFaction (RIP) to Hetzner</a>, I got an offer I could not refuse, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/mackuba.eu/post/3ll7dgrep7c25">on Bluesky (!)</a>, for a <a href="https://www.netcup.com/en/server/vps/vps-1000-g11-12m-iv">netcup VPS</a> with double the number of vCPUs, double the RAM and 5x the storage, all for about 25% cheaper every month.</p>
<p>On the weekend of March 28 I managed to port the six websites in question across (3 easy static ones, including this blog, and 3 slightly more tricky wordpress ones).</p>
<p>I am most grateful that as part of this porting effort I have now finally been able to dockerize the binaries I built years ago of the super obscure <a href="https://github.com/ma-tech/WlzIIPSrv">WlzIIPSrv fork of the C++ IIP image slice server</a> and will in future be able to migrate much more easily if I ever need to do so again. WlzIIPSrv is the software that serves the pannable and zoomable histology slices when you browse a <a href="https://visible-orbit.org/slices/dk2904l-registered/">visible-orbit.org (wordpress site also hosted on this new server) stack like this one</a>.</p>
<p>Although this migration is a significant and positive technical event for me, most of you will probably not even notice that this site responds a tad (or three) more snappily than it used to.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am celebrating that this is officially the first blog post coming to you from this shiny new server!</p>
<h2 id="productivity-devolution">Productivity (d)evolution</h2>
<h3 id="just-get-it-done-with-kanban">Just get it done with Kanban</h3>
<p>Someone once called using Trello for task management &ldquo;the time management connoisseur equivalent of lying in the gutter with a cheap bottle of wine in a brown paper bag&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(So, by the way, that someone was me! See <a href="/2014/11/27/weekly-head-voices-86-beardy/#note-taking-and-todo-system-chaos-nerd-warning">the previous admission on this blog, in WHV #86 from 2014</a>, original source of my statement is <a href="https://noeskasmit.com/comparison-of-task-managers-rtm-astrid-wunderlist-todoist/#comment-71">this comment on Noeska&rsquo;s blog</a>.)</p>
<p>I mention this now, because my current system, the one which has to act as replacement for <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my almighty Emacs Org-mode</a>, is a monthly Kanban board with columns for &ldquo;todo&rdquo;, &ldquo;today / next&rdquo;, &ldquo;doing&rdquo; and &ldquo;done&rdquo;, and task cards that I can move, quite satisfyingly, from column to column, which is essentially a less full-featured but fully local version of my old Trello-based system.</p>
<p>While the 2014-org-mode-me mind really cannot comprehend this, the current system, based on the plugins <a href="https://github.com/mgmeyers/obsidian-kanban">obsidian-kanban</a> and <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/tasks/Introduction">obsidian-tasks</a>, is working just fine for the moment.</p>
<h3 id="pomodori-made-from-100-xbar">pomodori made from 100% xbar</h3>
<p>You might recall from the previous WHV that I was still <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#productivity-hack-of-the-year">using Emacs as an over-powered pomodoro timer</a>.</p>
<p>Well, even that started itching a bit too much, and now I&rsquo;ve just re-implemented the whole thing, along with the productivity boosting auto-DnD setting, by <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/xbar-pomodoro-timer-with-DnD-for-macOS">modifying an existing self-contained macOS xbar script</a> which you can use if you too wish to work harder.</p>
<h3 id="loggin-time">Loggin&rsquo; time</h3>
<p>Together with the pomodoro timing, I was also using org-mode to maintain detailed time logs for work, using the built-in org-clock functionality.</p>
<p>Because of above-mentioned itch, I now have a semi-usable replacement which I put together as an <a href="https://blacksmithgu.github.io/obsidian-dataview/api/code-reference/#dvviewpath-input">Obsidian Dataview custom view</a>, in other words, a bunch of javascript that piggy-backs on the dataview parser and groups bullet items with start and end timestamps under their parent tasks and container headings, as projects, in order to spit out daily and monthly timelog breakdowns.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve only been testing this since the start of April. Although it&rsquo;s giving me all of the data that I need, the UX is just barely over the threshold of usable-by-me.</p>
<p>Perhaps in the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll find some time to write more about this tool to hear what others think.</p>
<h2 id="the-bozo-explosion">The Bozo explosion</h2>
<p>My great friend Dave told me about this phenomenon, of which I then had to go find the source.</p>
<p>It turns out the originator is none other than Steve Jobs, with the idea being injected into the internet hive-mind by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_Kawasaki">Guy Kawasaki</a>, a Guy who worked for Jobs at Apple (I see what I&rsquo;m doing here) from 1983 until about 1986.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a short but great post by Guy Kawasaki titled <a href="https://guykawasaki.com/what-i-learned-from-steve-jobs/">What I Learned From Steve Jobs</a> which is definitely worth a few minutes of your time.</p>
<p>Here I want to focus on point 9, namely &ldquo;A players hire A+ players&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve personally seen this a number of times with the smartest and best leaders I&rsquo;ve ever had the privilege of interacting with. They, the A players, actively seek and appoint colleagues who are smarter or better than they are, the A+ players. They absolutely revel in the opportunity of being challenged by the best people they can find. This turns into a positive feedback loop, with more and more similarly capable people seeking out their peers.</p>
<p>The opposite of this happens when you start with B players. B players easily feel threatened by more capable folks, and so they tend to recruit C players so that they can maintain the pecking order. Those C players will accordingly recruit D players and so on. This process of course leads to what Jobs coined as &ldquo;the Bozo explosion&rdquo;, which sounds frighteningly similar to what is currently happening in some parts of the world today.</p>
<p>Next time when you&rsquo;re evaluating a new opportunity, do make some time to ensure that the folks involved have the A player mentality.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>For future me, here&rsquo;s a list of other notable events from the period under review:</p>
<ul>
<li>Two 50th celebrations.</li>
<li>Various very special eating and drinking occasions with treasured friends, some from afar, and family.</li>
<li>Three family hikes.</li>
<li>1 Sting concert (with my life partner) which exceeded all my expectations.</li>
<li>My first running race (Spookhill challenge).</li>
<li>Visits with Parisian friends and family to the breathtaking <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeitz_Museum_of_Contemporary_Art_Africa">Zeitz Museum of Contemporary Art Africa (MOCAA)</a> and the Two Oceans aquarium.</li>
<li>Far too many marshmallow eggs.</li>
</ul>
<p>&hellip; and with that, I would like to leave you with this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The trick is to learn how to want the things you already have.</p>
<p>&ndash; William B. Irvine</p>
</blockquote>








    


<figure><a href="zeitz_mocaa_ocular.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7e8591922bb9e2d9.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_426183b3ab1ebea9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7a603b5cd15f6d27.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp"
            

        
            alt="Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!-- "not your guy, buddy" from the South Park episode "Canada on strike" https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1211261/characters/nm0005295/ --> ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #245: This too shall pass</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 20:18:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/</guid><description>WELL HELLO EVERYONE and welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices, edition #245 to be specific, looking back at the period of time from Monday July 25 to Sunday Aug 7, 2022.
Figure 1: Scene from a walk after a delicious family Sunday lunch.
In the spirit of full disclosure, I do seem to be going through a patch of mostly pretty &amp;ldquo;meh&amp;rdquo; WHV attempts.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>WELL HELLO EVERYONE and welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices, edition #245 to
be specific, looking back at the period of time from Monday July 25 to Sunday
Aug 7, 2022.</p>










<figure><a href="vergelegen-peekaboo.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_6485fe595a71baa1.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_1b86f2c5acf415fc.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_f00fcd5217c38b3e.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_a041747863e6b183.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_1b86f2c5acf415fc.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a walk after a delicious family Sunday lunch."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Scene from a walk after a delicious family Sunday lunch.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In the spirit of full disclosure, I do seem to be going through a patch of
mostly pretty &ldquo;meh&rdquo; WHV attempts.</p>
<p>However, as they say, a badly written but <em>published</em> blog post is miles better
than an unpublished blog post of <em>any</em> quality.</p>
<p>Also, one day when I finally reach <a href="/2017/06/11/weekly-head-voices-122/">the A-list</a> you&rsquo;ll be able to say that you
were already reading my stuff before it was cool.</p>
<p>More seriously though, the whole of <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">life is continuous practice</a>, which can
include long stretches of rolling hills of meh.</p>
<p>(see also <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">WHV #144&rsquo;s section on Mastery</a>)</p>
<h2 id="nerdy-bits">Nerdy bits</h2>
<h3 id="postel-s-law-and-iso-8601-date-and-time-formatting">Postel&rsquo;s law and ISO 8601 date and time formatting</h3>
<p>This movie is based on a true story that happened at work.</p>
<p>I published a short org-roam note to my nerd blog. You can read it here:
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/08/05/conservative-rendering-and-liberal-parsing-of-iso-8601-timestamps-in-python/">Conservative rendering and liberal parsing of ISO 8601 timestamps in Python</a></p>
<h3 id="replacing-ddw-with-rd-on-windows-for--wsl--devcontainers">Replacing DDW with RD on Windows for (WSL) devcontainers</h3>
<p>I have replaced Docker Desktop for Windows with <a href="https://rancherdesktop.io/">Rancher Desktop</a>, with the
dockerd runtime, on two of my Windows development machines.</p>
<p>Although you have to create some WSL symlinks manually, configure RD&rsquo;s
<code>docker-credential-wincred.exe</code> (if you&rsquo;re using private container registries)
and manually install zsh completions, the end-result is a great and
fully-functional replacement for my use-case of <a href="https://containers.dev/">devcontainers</a> everywhere.</p>
<p>Please let me know if you need more detail about the RD config.</p>
<p>P.S. It might come as a shock to some readers, not to mention me of 10 years
ago, that I have not only one, but two Windows workstations. My excuse is:
&ldquo;adaptation&rdquo;.</p>
<p>P.P.S. There will soon be three of them.</p>
<h3 id="notes-on-locally-upgrading-the-firmware-of-the-gw5048d-es-inverter">Notes on locally upgrading the firmware of the GW5048D-ES inverter</h3>
<p>There is a Goodwe GW5048D-ES 4.6 kVA inverter at the heart of the solar system powering my house.</p>
<p>I love it, because it&rsquo;s reliable, and just does the work 99.7% of the time.</p>
<p>However, because that 0.3% manifested recently (settings were partially
scrambled, resulting in a few minutes of darkness during a load shedding
session; could have been the Home Assistant Goodwe integration; more acutely,
its wifi access point, needed for configuration, recently disappeared) and the
OTA firmware I requested via Goodwe support failed, probably due to firmware
being a bit old already, I had to attempt a local firmware upgrade, with a USB
cable, like <a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">I last did three years ago</a> (rocky road then).</p>
<p>Well, although my inverter is now sporting firmware version 2424G, the upgrade
definitety went on roads of the more rocky variety.</p>
<p>Here are some tips to help you if you&rsquo;re in the same boat:</p>
<ul>
<li>Follow the instructions to the letter:
<ul>
<li>Remove all power sources except for a single DC source. I disconnected grid
and solar panels, keeping only the batteries connected which were close to
full.</li>
<li>Remove the wifi module: 4 screws, and then carefully remove the plastic
connector.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Get a straight USB-A male to USB-A male cable. None of my USB-C to USB-A
cables, or my various Frankensteined extensions, could connect (as reported
by EzFlash.</li>
</ul>
<p>In my case, the EzFlash upgrade worked (two bin files), but then right after
that the DataSend failed.</p>
<p>I retried DataSend multiple times, but finally lost connection to the
inverter&rsquo;s USB port.</p>
<p>After I put everything back together (having resolved to contact support to
help troubleshoot), the inverter&rsquo;s access point magically appeared, at which
point I could connect to see that everything was functioning, and inverter
reported firmware version as 2424G.</p>
<p>I did contact Goodwe to ask about the implications of DataSend
failing. Although I&rsquo;m happy with their service, I would have appreciated a bit
more detail.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve summarised our email thread below:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I asked: &ldquo;When I did the upgrade, the DataSend file did not go through at
all. Could you help me understand how the upgrade is OK if I only did the
EzFlash stage, and NOT the DataSend phase?&rdquo;</p>
<p>They answered: &ldquo;Do note that the datasend file is only for use when updating
the Armware. When updating firmware its only the EZflash and master bin file
that is use.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Then I asked: &ldquo;What is the Armware for then? Why is it not necessary to upgrade
it, although the upgrade manual gives instructions to upgrade it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Upon which they replied: &ldquo;You ARM is already updated that is why i advised not
to worry about it. There isn&rsquo;t anything technical that i can share on this. The
arm as we know normally works with communication with the batteries.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="school-s-anti-wikipedia-stance-leads-to-lessons-and-pi-hole">School&rsquo;s anti-wikipedia stance leads to lessons and Pi-hole</h2>
<p>Last week, GOU #2 tried to print a pretty nasty, infinite-scroll, ad-infested
site with stolen wikipedia content because her school has a far too simplistic
and strict rule <em>against</em> using wikipedia for school work.</p>
<p>I then proceeded to:</p>
<ol>
<li>have a long talk with her about computers not doing what you intend, but
rather exactly what you tell them to,</li>
<li>Do some research and realise to my shock that this anti-wikipedia stance
seems to be a world-wide teacher thing;</li>
<li>Write a long but friendly email to the teacher explaining that it&rsquo;s a lot
more nuanced, and could I please help them to understand the nuances so that
our kids get better at filtering information rather than just blindly
avoiding wikipedia and</li>
<li>At long last get around to installing <a href="https://pi-hole.net/">Pi-hole</a> on this old linux laptop (via
docker-compose) and sending all DNS requests its way (via my main router&rsquo;s
DHCP service), all-in-all quite a painless process!</li>
</ol>
<p>What this means is that all devices in my household (and there&rsquo;s quite a number
of them) get all of their ads blocked automatically.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_9f33616edd076712.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_2fe147269d2279a1.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_76a38c9e9321d821.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_1b46d164299f7434.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_2fe147269d2279a1.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: The Pi-hole dashboard a few moments ago. The percentage of blocked queries remains around 10%." width="480"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>The Pi-hole dashboard a few moments ago. The percentage of blocked queries remains around 10%.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I should have done this much earlier. There&rsquo;s really no chance I can install
ublock origin or equivalent on each of the growing cloud of devices and
accounts at home. Pi-hole makes 10x more sense.</p>
<h2 id="this-too-shall-pass">This too shall pass</h2>
<p>On Saturday July 30, the date of the final interschools clash between Paarl
Boys&rsquo; High School (my alma mater) and its arch-opponent Paarl Gimnasium, I had
the privilege of attending the 30th (!!) anniversary of my matriculation year,
along with about 50 class mates.</p>
<p>As a bit of context, back then I operated probably at the lowest end of the
popularity scale, mostly because of my personality. Not that it&rsquo;s that
important anymore, but I think that I would probably have irritated myself (in
both ways) to quite an extent.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, I had even <em>less</em> ball sense then than I do now.</p>
<p>In spite of all that, the reunion was a sublime and deeply enjoyable affair.</p>
<p>It was so great connecting again with the human journeyers I had in many cases
last seen right before we would all set off on the start of adulthood.</p>
<p>Back then, we were all bright-eyed, hot-headed, full of plans and with heads
full of luscious hair.</p>
<p>Now there was substantially less hair, many hard lessons learned, but wisdom,
and sometimes peace, in the eyes.</p>
<p>To me it really felt as if everyone there had this collective, positive
realisation of:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You know what?</p>
<p>Everything&rsquo;s OK.</p>
<p>We know better what&rsquo;s truly important, and it&rsquo;s not what we believed back then.</p>
<p>All of this? Let us enjoy it without complication.</p>
<p>Like everything before it, this too shall pass.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps I am over-projecting.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the enjoyment was as real as could be.</p>
<p>Thank you Boys High&rsquo; Class of &lsquo;92!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #93: A thank you note.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/06/28/weekly-head-voices-93-a-thank-you-note/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2015 11:31:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/06/28/weekly-head-voices-93-a-thank-you-note/</guid><description> The week of Monday June 21 to Sunday June 28 as seen through bullets:
On Monday I received a super sweet email from an ex-student of one of my DataVis courses at the TU Delft. My course got a “one of the best” rating, but more importantly, the gentleman in question explained that it had inspired him to make a career in DataVis (and judging by his work record up to now, he’s doing a really good job of it!). It’s hard to explain how much good such a thank you mail does to my heart. This reminded me accutely of the concluding life advice the American author David Sedaris gave to the guests attending his edition of the Dutch College Tour. The advice was: Write thank you notes.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/wpid-pompen_en_pimpen1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/wpid-pompen_en_pimpen1.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The week of Monday June 21 to Sunday June 28 as seen through bullets:</p>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
    On Monday I received a super sweet email from an ex-student of one of my DataVis courses at the TU Delft. My course got a “one of the best” rating, but more importantly, the gentleman in question explained that it had inspired him to make a career in DataVis (and judging by his work record up to now, he’s doing a really good job of it!). It’s hard to explain how much good such a thank you mail does to my heart.
  </li>
<li>
    This reminded me accutely of the concluding life advice the American author <a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Sedaris">David Sedaris</a> gave to the guests attending his edition of the Dutch <a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/College_Tour">College Tour</a>. The advice was:
  </li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>Write thank you notes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He made it patently clear that “thanks in advance” was absolutely not good enough, but that a dedicated thank you email or letter after the fact was an art that he recommended we all practise. I shall try harder to remember to do this more often!</p>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
    I wrote a really nerdy bullet in this post about trying out docker. <i>Then</i> I wrote this bullet to warn you about the nerdiness of the subsequent one.
  </li>
<li>
    I finally got to try out <a href="https://www.docker.com/">docker</a>. It gave me great pleasure to do this in exactly the way that would probably cause any docker expert to pass out due to the sheer magnitude of rules and guidelines I alternatively <a href="http://blog.docker.com/2014/06/why-you-dont-need-to-run-sshd-in-docker/">broke and bent</a>. I’m only using docker as a convenient way to bring up development-only light(er)-weight isolated virtual environments on my macbook using boot2docker. On Linux I would probably just use <a href="https://linuxcontainers.org/lxd/introduction/">LXD/LXC</a>, but there’s no boot2lxd (yet?) and I like to have my development tools consistent everywhere. I can report that even when you’re doing it wrong, docker works pretty well. The upshot is that I now have a docker image, based on <a href="https://registry.hub.docker.com/_/ubuntu-upstart/">ubuntu-upstart</a>, with postgres, solr, redis and a whole bunch of Python to start containers from and work on one of our products that requires that stack. I use IntelliJ’s remote interpreter support for the IDE parts of this solution.
  </li>
<li>
    This week, I <i>really</i> missed my AfrikaBurn family. I guess we should start thinking seriously about our next appearance in Tankwa Town. This has also made me think a little more about <i>nostalgia</i>, and especially the fact that it’s directed at a point in space-time. We <i>can</i> travel through relevant space more or less at will. However, through time we can only move in one direction, and as if that wasn’t bad enough, we have to move at the same speed as everyone else. If we wish to reach back through space-time to that exact point of nostalgic origin, our only choice is to learn how to warp reality by sculpting with perception.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>Have a great week, and remember to write that thank you note! Thank <em>you</em> very much for reading <em>this</em>!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>