<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Windows 7 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/windows-7/</link><description>Recent content in Windows 7 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2009 20:35:02 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/windows-7/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #9: Windows 7 Geek-o-Rama.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2009 20:35:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/</guid><description>I’ve unfortunately not been involved in any quantum entanglement accidents recently — teaching duties are mostly to be blamed for my two-week silence. Besides spending at least a whole work-day every week on our Data Visualisation practical, I’ve been lecturing and also been preparing a new lecture block on information visualisation with a dash of visual data analysis. Due to my not secretly being an infovis expert, this latter activity has taken up quite a chunk of my time and effort. On the other hand, the exercise has forced me to acquire a significant amount of new infovis brain juice which I’ll probably soon be applying to impressive effect.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve unfortunately not been involved in any quantum entanglement accidents recently — teaching duties are mostly to be blamed for my two-week silence.  Besides spending at least a whole work-day every week on our <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4086p" title="datavis practical website">Data Visualisation practical</a>, I’ve been lecturing and also been preparing a new lecture block on information visualisation with a dash of visual data analysis.  Due to my not secretly being an infovis expert, this latter activity has taken up quite a chunk of my time and effort.  On the other hand, the exercise has forced me to acquire a significant amount of new infovis brain juice which I’ll probably soon be applying to <em>impressive</em> effect.</p>
<p>In any case.</p>
<p>On the geek front, I have to say that I’m <strong>really liking Windows 7</strong>.  Partly eye-candy, partly the SuperBar, partly the revamped file manager: I’m a happy camper both on the NetBook (just installed 4GB of SDHC especially for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ReadyBoost" title="wikipedia page on readyboost">ReadyBoost</a>) and on the quad core workstation.  Feel free to discuss this in the comments, even, or especially, my black turtleneck-wearing friends! :)  Unrelated to the big 7, it turns out that if you use large removable (USB) drives between computers with different operating systems, NTFS is your best bet.  Even more unrelated, I’ve also discovered that one can implement complete independent Windows applications using <a href="http://www.autohotkey.com/" title="AutoHotkey website">AutoHotkey</a>.  Before I knew what I was doing, I had re-implemented most of my <a href="http://cpbotha.net/software/envedit/" title="envedit website">envedit</a> application in AutoHotKey, with GUI and all (you can find my efforts in <a href="http://code.google.com/p/envedit/source/browse/trunk/ahk/envedit.ahk" title="source of envedit.ahk">SVN</a>, AHK’s a strange little language).  The resultant stand-alone app is 400k, which compares favourably to the 4MB envedit installation.  To conclude this week’s edition of I Really Like Geeking Out, I broke down and bought 20G of extra Google storage for slightly less than EUR 5 per year.  I’m not using it (yet), but I somehow get a kick from seeing this at the bottom of my GMail interface (click the image for a slightly larger version):</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png" title=""><img alt="gmail_storage_screenie" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-701" data-attachment-id="701" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":""}' data-image-title="gmail_storage_screenie" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie-300x88.png" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png" data-orig-size="533,158" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/gmail_storage_screenie/" height="88" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie-300x88.png" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie-300x88.png 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/gmail_storage_screenie.png 533w" title="gmail_storage_screenie" width="300"/></a>
</p>
<p>With regard to research, things have been going just swimmingly.  There are a number of really cool articles being lovingly incubated as we speak.  Some mathematical visualization and some time-varying VDA will go to Eurovis, whilst one other submission is already being carefully groomed for the Vis deadline in March next year.</p>
<p>In other news that absolutely made my day on Monday, November 9, 2009: After being in the oven for almost two years, our pathological shoulder segmentation article should soon appear at a news-stand near you:</p>
<div>
<blockquote>
<p>
      Peter R Krekel, Edward R Valstar, Frits H Post, Piet M Rozing, and Charl P Botha. 2009. <em><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Krekel2010" title="Link to paper website.">Combined Surface and Volume Processing for Fused Joint Segmentation</a>.</em> The International Journal for Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery.
    </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
<strong>Mr Cricket, that was just marvelous!</strong>
</p>
<p>
    Finally, I’m ecstatic to report that due to an unfair dose of serendipity, not in the least brought about by the involvement of <a href="http://gpsgek.nl/" title="website of said extremely resourceful individual">one extremely resourceful individual</a>, <strong>Longitudinal Medical Visualisation</strong> (google should take you to the right place) looks like it might be getting off the ground in a Really Big Way soon.  Stay tuned kids, stay tuned.
  </p>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #8: Uninterruptible Fun Supply</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/07/weekly-head-voices-8-uninterruptible-fun-supply/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2009 22:29:38 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/11/07/weekly-head-voices-8-uninterruptible-fun-supply/</guid><description>Dear readers,
Due to a small accident with a friend’s quantum entanglement device, I briefly got stuck in a high pressure reality vortex. The headaches have subsided, but I do still seem to be suffering from slight time compression artifacts. In any case, that’s why there’s only this one edition of the Weekly Head Voices to cover weeks 43 to 45. As is always the case, please make use of the bolded phrases to guide you through this post. In other words, the fat words tell you what you you might find interesting so that you can skip the rest.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear readers,</p>
<p>Due to a small accident with a friend’s quantum entanglement device, I briefly got stuck in a high pressure reality vortex. The headaches have subsided, but I do still seem to be suffering from slight time compression artifacts. In any case, that’s why there’s only this one edition of the Weekly Head Voices to cover weeks 43 to 45. As is always the case, please make use of the <strong>bolded phrases to guide you through this post</strong>. In other words, the fat words tell you what you you might find interesting so that you can skip the rest.</p>
<p>Week 43 was for a large part about re-learning a lesson that I’ve learned and forgotten more times than I care to count, but it was mostly about joining <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/" title="The same people are mentioned in a previous post...">Superbly Cool Extraordinarily Lovely People</a> (hi there y’all!) and going here:</p>
<p><span style="background-color: #ffffff;"><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9sOxfcWlGr0">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9sOxfcWlGr0</a> HEAD ASPLODE!</span></p>
<p>Now how about that lesson? Let’s go:</p>
<p><strong>On the Importance of Not Getting Interrupted.</strong></p>
<p>During these past weeks I’ve been hard at work completing a mini-thesis (some call it a teaching portfolio) documenting my teaching activities, meaning that I had to spend a significant amount of Contiguous Time(tm) producing a significant body of text. In order to supplement the scarce supply of said Contiguous Time, I spent two mornings working at home. Furthermore, I for some or other vague reason decided not to check email before I started early in the morning and of course also not to keep my e-mail client running whilst working.</p>
<p>My word, what a difference!</p>
<p>Who woulda thunk it, it turns out that that habitual and reflexive email checking really breaks one’s speed and, in my case, causes unnecessary stress as each time the inbox piles up with even more remotely injected work. Bottom line: I’m going back (for the umpteenth time) to 3 fixed email checks and inbox emptying sessions per day: one before the early morning daily review, one just after lunch when my brain is too busy coping with digestion anyway and one in the late afternoon.</p>
<p><strong>Operating Systems all-you-can-eat Buffet</strong></p>
<p>During wind-down time in these past three weeks, I installed and tried out the following operating systems:</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="background-color: #ffffff;">Moblin 2.1 preview on my netbook: Oh my it boots really fast and is very pretty. It would take some getting used to, my experience was too much mobile internet device and too little computer.</span></li>
<li><span style="background-color: #ffffff;">OSX 10.5.7 on my <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/07/15/pleasure-apparatus-2008/" title="my q9450 blog post">Q9450 quad-core</a>: First: No, I have no idea how that got there! Second: Meh. Looks nice, not my thing though. Third: Eventually I’m going to port DeVIDE to OSX, when either wxCocoa or pySide is ready. I’m only doing this for my goateed, turtle-necked and beret-wearing apologist friends and definitely not for the OS or the company behind it.</span></li>
<li><span style="background-color: #ffffff;">Ubuntu 9.10 Netbook Remix on my, err, netbook: My jotted down thoughts at the time: Very slick, clutter interface (including maximus) is great for netbooks. It seems the ath9k wlan adapter still has minor problems connecting / staying connected at full speed.</span></li>
<li><span style="background-color: #ffffff;">Windows 7 on my netbook: Yes, the TU does in fact give us all licenses for this type of stuff, it’s a cool perk. Wow, it went on there quite easily, I simply ran “setup.exe” from the unpacked ISO and installed it to an extra 70G partition. After installing the usual suspects (truecrypt, 7zip, avira, vim, asus stuff [Super Hybrid Engine, Hotkey, Asus Update, Touchpad driver], fastcopy, chrome), I was up and running. Looooong battery life seems to be intact.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The End, My Friend</strong></p>
<p><span style="background-color: #ffffff;">In week 44 a number of us went to defend the whole <strong>TU Delft Computer Science research programme</strong> at an <strong>international research evaluation</strong>. Besides leading to my <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/10/31/two-powerpoint-2007-tricks-that-could-save-your-life/" title="powerpoint 2007 two tricks post">recent PowerPoint post</a>, this occasion surprisingly turned out to be great fun (probably thanks to the 5-star evaluation committee and their interviewing style) and we seem to have done quite well in the evaluation.</span></p>
<p>Preparing for the evaluation and finishing my teaching portfolio took up much of my time, so much so that I have not been giving the people around me all the time and attention that they deserve. People around me, I am acutely aware of this and I will make it up to you!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>