<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>music on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/music/</link><description>Recent content in music on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2019 08:33:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/music/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #174: Row row row your boat.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2019 08:33:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/</guid><description> The view through one of the old windows of Cucina di Giovanni in Paarl on a brilliant winter afternoon. The symbolism of this will hopefully shine through soon. Hello friends.
Although these Weekly Head Voices look back at the week from Monday July 15 to Sunday July 21, it is already Wednesday, July 24, as I write this.
As is usually the case this time of the year, I access the below visualization perhaps a tad too often:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="view_from_giovannis_paarl.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu975d1d0487715ee55833a14d8065559b_3125111_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
The view through one of the old windows of Cucina di Giovanni in Paarl on a brilliant winter afternoon. The symbolism of this will hopefully shine through soon.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Hello friends.</p>
<p>Although these Weekly Head Voices look back at the week from Monday July 15 to
Sunday July 21, it is already Wednesday, July 24, as I write this.</p>
<p>As is usually the case this time of the year, I access the below visualization
perhaps a tad too often:</p>
<a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-africa/cape-town?month=7&year=2019">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu7b457eb91d598aa5b697ea92f5e0f54b_43837_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu7b457eb91d598aa5b697ea92f5e0f54b_43837_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu7b457eb91d598aa5b697ea92f5e0f54b_43837_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu7b457eb91d598aa5b697ea92f5e0f54b_43837_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
  

   />



</a>
<p>Although it&rsquo;s grey and cold and rainy down here at the moment, I console myself
with the fact that the days are slowly but surely getting longer again, minute
by minute.</p>
<p>Starting from the depths of the Winter Solstice on June 21, when there were 9
hours and 53 minutes of daylight, today that had already stretched to a period
of 10 hours and 16 minutes.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re slowly making our way to 14 hours and 25 minutes of daylight on December
22, the Summer Solstice.</p>
<p>Although I do try to savour every moment, I can&rsquo;t help but look forward to the
warmth.</p>
<p>Anyways, the rest of this post exploded into a solid dollop of backyard
philosophy, which I hope you enjoy.</p>
<h2 id="bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Bullet List of Miscellany (BLoM).</h2>
<p>Before we dig in to the promised solid dollop, let&rsquo;s warm up with a BLoM.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Last week I
reported</a>
that we had half-bricked the solar inverter with a firmware upgrade. Shortly
after that, with some help from local support, we reflashed everything from
scratch (note: Although the manual says NOT to use EzFlash for GW5048-ES
inverters shipped after March, you in fact have to use EzFlash in this case)
and, lo and behold, the inverter was resurrected!
<ul>
<li>With BMS (battery management system) communication online, the system works
like a charm. Record solar consumption so far is 24.1 kWh, which is great for
winter!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>My favourite (and only) TPN (Tall Philosophical Neighbour) alerted me to the
fact that images were positively ginormous in the email version of this
blog. I&rsquo;ve fine-tuned the Hugo image-resizing shortcode to do a better job.</li>
<li>After a discussion with a friend from work about kindness, I came across this
post I wrote five (5) years ago: <a href="/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/">Weekly Head Voices #81 - Middle-aged
zen</a>. For me it was worth
reading again. (Also, the person who wrote that seems to be more advanced
than I currently am. Life is circles.)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="life-is-but-a-dream">Life is but a dream.</h2>
<p>I would like to take you on a little trip.</p>
<p>Please imagine an extremely dark room.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;re stuck in this room.</p>
<p>Fortunately there are two really small holes in the thick black walls through
which light shines in. If you get up and peak out through the holes, you can
make out what&rsquo;s going on outside of the room.</p>
<p>There are two more holes through which you can hear sounds from the outside
world, if you put your ears up to them.</p>
<p>Every day, someone shoves food in through yet another small hole.</p>
<p>At least you won&rsquo;t go hungry.</p>
<p>However, if you have to be honest, this room, your jail, is still really
dark and really lonely.</p>
<p>After some time, you discover, behind a really heavy floor tile, a number of
levers.</p>
<p>Using these levers, you are able to make the room rock to and fro.</p>
<p>After some months of practice, you learn how to rock the room more
consistently, and move it in a certain direction.</p>
<p>When you do this, the rays of light coming in through the two pinprick holes
change in interesting ways.</p>
<p>Very slowly, over a period of years, you start figuring out that the rays of
light coming in through the two holes, and the sounds coming in through the
other holes, are often caused by other prisoners, all trapped in cells similar
to yours.</p>
<p>You start making <em>contact</em>.</p>
<h3 id="real-time-reality-synthesis">Real-time reality synthesis.</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to tell this story without giving it away of course.</p>
<p>Your brain is in fact trapped in a bony cage.</p>
<p>It has two slimy nerve bundles slithering out through two holes in your
skull. The ends of those nerve bundles are sensitive to photons falling on them
(light), and send electrical signals back along their bodies when this happens.</p>
<p>Your brain has more slimy nerve bundles connected to your ears.</p>
<p>Sound waves hitting your eardrums via a chain of contact end up as vibrations
in the fluid inside your cochleae, where another set of nerve endings are
stimulated and send more electrical signals back along their bodies.</p>
<p>Your whole body is criss-crossed by more of these bundles of super long
neurons.</p>
<p>Trapped in its terribly dark bony cage, your brain is a slimy mass that absorbs
all of the electrical signals coming back from your eyes, your ears, and the
rest of your nervous system.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s really not that much coming in folks.</p>
<p>However, somehow, somewhere inside of that slimy mass, &ldquo;you&rdquo; experience all of
this as a multi-coloured, high definition, surround-sound, smell-&lsquo;o-vision,
multi-million dollar 3D Hollywood movie.</p>
<p>When I look at the imbalance between the real-time sensory data coming in on
the one hand, and the incredible richness of the experience on the other, and
bolstered slightly by what I know about the human sensory system, I come to the
conclusion that the multi-million dollar experience is a result of an almost
perpetual hallucination.</p>
<p>In other words, the reality that we experience while awake is <em>seeded</em> by our
senses, but a large part of its verdant richness is synthesised, in real-time,
by our amazing brains.</p>
<p>Thinking about it this way, it is not so surprising that we are apparently able
to synthesise whole realities while we dream, including people, environments,
conversations, relationships and experiences, all in apparent real-time.</p>
<h3 id="ps-its-the-music">P.S. It&rsquo;s the music.</h3>
<p>This whole story came up in a conversation I recently had with my partner.</p>
<p>I was trying to explain that I easily get lost in thought with the right
music.</p>
<p>Heck, when I go running (for realz), I sometimes get utterly lost in my
imagination, and it&rsquo;s quite a visual, even multi-sensory affair.</p>
<p>During that conversation, I had the insight that when this happens (i.e. I get
lost in thought), it&rsquo;s only some of the lower bandwidth sensory feeds that are
suppressed and/or slightly disrupted, for example by the right music, enabling
the super deluxe reality synthesis equipment in my brain to do what it normally
does, only slightly less constrained by outside stimuli.</p>
<p>Taking this one step further, although one might be permanently hallucinating,
one does have some control over the balance between incoming feeds and internal
simulation.</p>
<p>In <a href="/2018/02/04/weekly-head-voices-130-2-direct-experience-dopamine/#your-brain-at-work-part-2-dopamine-and-more-mindfulness">direct experience
mode</a>,
one shifts more bandwidth to the incoming feeds.</p>
<p>(Internal simulation still has to fill in the multitude of blanks.)</p>
<p>Then, when one&rsquo;s imagination takes flight, incoming feeds are turned down
somewhat, enabling internal simulation to take over.</p>
<h2 id="row-row-row-your-boat">Row, row, row your boat.</h2>
<p>I wish you an amazing week, and I look forward to when we meet again.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>OK Go’s new video for “The One Moment” is a stunning example of high-speed video.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/24/ok-gos-new-video-for-the-one-moment-is-a-stunning-example-of-high-speed-video/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2016 07:13:38 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/24/ok-gos-new-video-for-the-one-moment-is-a-stunning-example-of-high-speed-video/</guid><description> The whole music video was shot with high-speed video in one single, glorious 4.2 second take, and then played back at “normal” speed to result in this mind-blowing end-product:
(BTW, since when are facebook videos a thing? Fortunately, WordPress immediately understood the facebook video link I pasted and correctly embedded it.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The whole music video was shot with high-speed video in one single, glorious 4.2 second take, and then played back at “normal” speed to result in this mind-blowing end-product:</p>
<div class="fb-video" data-allowfullscreen="true" data-href="https://www.facebook.com/okgo/videos/10153836041340683/">
</div>
<p>(BTW, since when are facebook videos a thing? Fortunately, WordPress immediately understood the facebook video link I pasted and correctly embedded it.)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #108: Gaga.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/06/24/weekly-head-voices-108-gaga/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 21:55:42 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/06/24/weekly-head-voices-108-gaga/</guid><description> I was reminded that future me really enjoys having written these things. (Present me knows about extrapolation.)
Actually present me also enjoys this, but creating sufficient amounts of time to do so is often challenging. I have most recently convinced myself that I should see this as practice so that I will later be able to write really entertaining posts in minimal time. Until then my two readers, I hope to compensate with edification.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I was reminded that future me really enjoys having written these things. (Present me knows about extrapolation.)</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/IMG-20160526-WA0000.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/06/IMG-20160526-WA0000.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Actually present me also enjoys this, but creating sufficient amounts of time to do so is often challenging. I have most recently convinced myself that I should see this as practice so that I will later be able to write really entertaining posts in minimal time. Until then my two readers, I hope to compensate with edification.</p>
<p>Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, the rapidly glowing cellular mega-city that first made contact with extra-wombular (I made that up) light slightly more than three months ago, suddenly started babbling a few weeks ago. To be honest, I thought that she was going to be really quiet to compensate for the immense amount of continuous talking in my house. It turns out that her reaction has instead been one of taking this bull by the horns. SHE WILL BE HEARD. (GOU#1 and #2 are able to produce speech with an intensity that is to be heard to be believed. I have no idea where they got that from.)</p>
<p>Speaking of babbling, I sometimes make videos of me trying to explain nerdy programming-related tricks, and then I upload them to YouTube. My most recent creation is about using the conan.io C++ package manager to get a small SFML-based GLSL example going (that’s GPU programming). It has a soundless explosion at the end!</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RFjvz_Ppbv8?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>I came across a really interesting bit of research performed at the Vienna University of Economics and Business (WU) on how really small, seemingly inconsequential rewards, can actually ignite people’s intrinsic motivation. This is interesting exactly because it has long been thought that extrinsic rewards diminish intrinsic motivation, a phenomenon called the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overjustification_effect">overjustification effect</a>.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://hbr.org/2016/06/even-tiny-rewards-can-motivate-people-to-go-the-extra-mile">the recent study by researchers at the WU</a>, students were encouraged to do extra homework assignments. However, this was done by allocating an amount of extra credit which was perceived by the students as being trivial (this was measured in a separate study). Lo and behold, this perceived trivial extra credit still jump-started that group’s extra assignment submissions, and the students in that group then showed evidence of autonomously (intrinsically) motivated behaviour.</p>
<p>The researchers hypothesise that this could be due to the fact that the students being jump-started could not internally explain their behaviour on the basis of the negligible reward, and hence automatically came up with more intrinsically-oriented motivations, such as personal importance, interest or enjoyment).</p>
<p>South Africa is a really strange and wonderful place. I don’t write about it that much, because in that respect it is my <em>place</em> to be quiet here in the background. However, sometimes someone else writes something that, if you’re interested in the perspective of South Africans who’ve lived abroad for a significant amount of time, and have then returned, somewhat the wiser, because the country in their blood called them back, you really should read. Disco Pants, or rather her blog, helped me a whole lot when we had to decide whether we would be coming back or not. She has a new post out titled <a href="https://discopantsblog.com/2016/06/06/on-surviving-the-madness-of-south-africa/">“On Surviving the Madness of South Africa”, and it’s a beaut</a>.</p>
<p>On the topic of beauty, <a href="http://www.flumemusic.com/">Flume</a> has new album out. It’s called <em>Skin</em>, and it gets the highly coveted but completely unknown Weekly Head Voices Album of Right Now award! Here’s the first track to whet your appetite (or not):</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7HKVvcNOQb0?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Have a fun week listeners!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #103: Chips!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/02/weekly-head-voices-103-chips/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 18:02:59 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/02/weekly-head-voices-103-chips/</guid><description> I thought that I had nothing for the two weeks from Monday January 18 to Sunday January 31, 2016, but my notes begged to differ. They suggested the following items for your reading, listening and viewing pleasure:
Party trick If you&amp;rsquo;re like me, you stop two to three chips short of finishing the packet so that you can explain to your conscience that you didn&amp;rsquo;t finish the whole thing. However, once or twice in my life, I&amp;rsquo;ve been faced with the terrifying conundrum of a partially finished packet of chips, but no way to seal the packet for later utilisation.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I thought that I had <em>nothing</em> for the two weeks from Monday January 18 to Sunday January 31, 2016, but my notes begged to differ. They suggested the following items for your reading, listening and viewing pleasure:</p>
<h2 id="party-trick">Party trick</h2>
<p>If you&rsquo;re like me, you stop two to three chips short of finishing the packet so that you can explain to your conscience that you didn&rsquo;t finish the <em>whole</em> thing. However, once or twice in my life, I&rsquo;ve been faced with the terrifying conundrum of a partially finished packet of chips, but no way to seal the packet for later utilisation. Readers, agonise no more! Learn from this animated demonstration:</p>
<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" data-id="ZZwR7cQ" lang="en"><a href="//imgur.com/ZZwR7cQ">How to seal a bag of chips without a clip</a></blockquote><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js"></script>
<h2 id="music">Music</h2>
<p>A musically inclined colleague recently suggested I try out <a href="http://pitchfork.com/reviews/albums/20458-in-colour/">In Colour</a>, the 2015 studio album by <a href="http://www.jamiexx.com/#order">Jamie XX</a>. After multiple listens, I can only highly recommend that you too try this out on your favourite music source. I&rsquo;m currently on Apple Music, because it is currently the best way for me and my whole family to get access to all the music we can eat. What a time to be alive! Below is one of my favourite tracks from the album:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cumIVrQN5QM?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<h2 id="irrelevant-miscellany-for-my-ocd">Irrelevant miscellany, for my OCD</h2>
<p>At Stone Three, as I have previously hinted, we have now switched to a self-hosted <a href="http://www.mattermost.org/">Mattermost</a>. So far, this is going swimmingly, with some of the resident experts also getting the github integration going (when someone pushes to any of the linked github repos, we get a nicely formatted message on the relevant channels). If you&rsquo;re curious about how exactly this compares to HipChat, Slack or Campfire (remember that?), let me know in the comments.</p>
<p>For the Saff Efricans reading this: <a href="http://www.afrihost.com/landing/mobile/">When Afrihost announced that they were going to play MVNO (mobile virtual network operator)</a>, I jumped on them. <strong>Much</strong> more data, somewhat more airtime and contract-free for not very many peanuts sounded like a great deal to me. Let me know in the comments if you need more info.</p>
<h2 id="backyard-linguistics">Backyard linguistics</h2>
<p>Millenials, or Generation Y, are humans that were born anywhere from the early 80s to the early 2000s. As a backyard anthropologist, one of my favourite articles about millenials is <a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/2013/09/why-generation-y-yuppies-are-unhappy.html">“Why Generation Y Yuppies Are Unhappy” by Tim Urban</a> on the Wait but Why blog. However, I found this recent article by Jeff Guo titled <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2016/01/13/the-totes-amazesh-way-millennials-are-changing-the-english-language/">“The totes amazesh way millennials are changing the English language”</a> at the Washington Post even more fascinating.</p>
<p>It turns out that millenials have introduced new forms like <em>totes delish</em> (most delicious), <em>abbreviash</em> (abbreviation), <em>appreesh</em> (appreciate) and many more brilliant inventions into the English language. It&rsquo;s fantastic seeing a language evolve like this, especially now that the internet and the hyper-connected humans on it are acting as such a powerful catalyst, and simultaneously as an instrument of observation, or should I say <em>observash</em>?</p>
<h2 id="inspiring-quotes-that-you-can-repost-if-you-want">Inspiring quotes that you can repost if you want</h2>
<p>This is from <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0307479/?ref_=fn_al_tt_1">Soderbergh&rsquo;s Solaris</a>, which I thought was brilliant (I did read <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solaris_(novel)">Lem&rsquo;s book</a> when I was much younger, could be that that did the trick). The quote was brought to my attention by <a href="https://twitter.com/ckritzinger">@ckritzinger</a> on the twitters as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There are no answers. Only choices.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let&rsquo;s broaden the quote slightly. Remember, this is the dialogue between one of the last living characters on a space station, and a flesh-and-bones version of one of the other crew members that was resurrected (you know, from being completely dead) by the utterly strange planetary intelligence that is Solaris (you can also read <a href="http://www.rifters.com/crawl/?p=5566">this fine analysis</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you keep thinking there’s a solution, you’ll die here. There are no answers. Only choices.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That sounds like an even more apt bit of advice for most of us here on Earth, except that it&rsquo;s only going to make the difference between dying, or dying with the disappointing belief that there must have been a <em>solution</em> or final <em>answer</em> somewhere that you were just unable to find.</p>
<p>There is no <em>why</em>.</p>
<p>There is only <em>how</em>, and that&rsquo;s awesome!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>(more) music for programming</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/19/more-music-for-programming/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 12:38:44 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/19/more-music-for-programming/</guid><description> Currently listening to Chris Sneddon’s mix on musicForProgramming();
For this last hour it has been exactly the right levels of everything to drown out distractions from my surroundings whilst not acting as a distraction in itself.
(Yes, I’m doing small status updates here now. It’s an experiment.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Currently listening to <a href="http://datashat.net/music_for_programming_32-chris_seddon.mp3">Chris Sneddon’s mix</a> on <a href="http://musicforprogramming.net/">musicForProgramming();</a></p>
<p>For this last hour it has been exactly the right levels of everything to drown out distractions from my surroundings whilst not acting as a distraction in itself.</p>
<p>(Yes, I’m doing small status updates here now. It’s an experiment.)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Soulwax</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2008/01/08/soulwax/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2008 08:36:02 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2008/01/08/soulwax/</guid><description> Last year I acquired this:
So I could go here:
… with some exceptionally cool individuals.
Thanks to one of these individuals who has developed the amazing ability to stop time in his close proximity and, as if that wasn’t enough, to possess a pair of the coolest spectacles this side of the equator, you should be able to find me on the photo to his left.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Last year I acquired this:</p>
<p><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/cpbotha/Misc/photo#5153018499801037154"></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center">
<a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/cpbotha/Misc/photo#5153018499801037154"><img src="http://lh6.google.com/cpbotha/R4MzBhGoOWI/AAAAAAAAChU/V8ZENTEt1Vg/s400/soulwax_20080104_ticket.jpg"/></a>
</p>
<p>So I could go here:</p>
<p><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/cpbotha/Misc/photo#5153018495506069842"></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center">
<a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/cpbotha/Misc/photo#5153018495506069842"><img src="http://lh5.google.com/cpbotha/R4MzBRGoOVI/AAAAAAAAChM/FOuIgji3NCg/s400/soulwax_20080104_crowdshoot_miletic.jpg"/></a>
</p>
<p>… with some <em>exceptionally</em> cool individuals.</p>
<p>Thanks to one of these individuals who has developed the amazing ability to stop time in his close proximity and, as if that wasn’t enough, to possess a pair of the coolest spectacles this side of the equator, you should be able to find me on the photo to his left.</p>
<p>Take a whiff of <a href="http://www.soulwax.com/" title="Soulwax / 2 Many DJs website (loud and proud)">Soulwax / 2 Many DJs</a> live by clicking <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://youtube.com/watch?v=_Urig4OpnhY" title="Soulwax Rocket Ride live Youtube video">here</a> (the ROCKET RIDING fun starts at 2:05), <a data-rel="lightbox-video-1" href="http://youtube.com/watch?v=w-PqYy45g8k" title="Soulwax live in Paradiso (youtube, part1)">here</a> or <a data-rel="lightbox-video-2" href="http://youtube.com/watch?v=nEK_h9T6DW8" title="Soulwax live in Paradiso (youtube, part2)">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>