<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>nim-lang on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/nim-lang/</link><description>Recent content in nim-lang on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 15:04:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/nim-lang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #211: Table Mountain Run(ish)</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 15:04:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/</guid><description> Welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices friends!
These ones, the two hundred and eleventh (haha, remember at school you always wondered if anyone would ever really need to be able to write out numbers&amp;hellip; IT WAS ALL FOR ME) edition, will hopefully be talking more or less coherently about events that took place during the two weeks from Monday November 23 to Sunday December 6 of the year 2020.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices friends!</p>
<p>These ones, the two hundred and eleventh (haha, remember at school you always
wondered if anyone would ever really need to be able to write out numbers&hellip; IT
WAS ALL FOR ME) edition, will hopefully be talking more or less coherently
about events that took place during the two weeks from Monday November 23 to
Sunday December 6 of the year 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="table-mountain-20201204-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Not the worst spot to eat one&amp;rsquo;s peanut butter sandwiches"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Not the worst spot to eat one&rsquo;s peanut butter sandwiches</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">Wetware checklist to bootstrap your software checklist</h2>
<p>My <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">daily review</a> routine has been taking quite a beating.</p>
<p>The busier it gets, the more easily I somehow skip my whole daily review in the
morning thinking that I can better invest that time into just jumping on the
most urgent things first.</p>
<p>This is of course one of the stupidest things I can do at that point.</p>
<p>It doesn&rsquo;t help that the daily review contains quite a number of points I have
to take care of every morning.</p>
<p>So, what does one do to help sticking to your morning daily review habit?</p>
<p>Logically, one creates yet another, but this time smaller and hopefully more
robust, habit that triggers the larger habit!</p>
<p>(In the end, it&rsquo;s turtles all the way down in any case.)</p>
<p>The one redeeming factor in my morning routine has been the increasing
regularity of meditation exercise. (Thanks PK for putting me back on that
horse, or should I say <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/#shorter-focus-blocks-work-better">elephant</a>, and thanks to Sam Harris and his Waking Up
app.)</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;ve now added to my system is a smaller checklist with three items on it:</p>
<ol>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> meditation</li>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> deep reading</li>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> planning: review + task setting</li>
</ol>
<p>The difference is that this checkpoint now lives in my brain, and is much
harder to side-step. Also, because of the firmly embedded meditation kernel,
there&rsquo;s a bit of momentum to help me move on to items 2 and 3.</p>
<p>I sneaked in item 2, because reading is basically cheap but really powerful
cybernetic upgrades for normal humans, and I found that it nicely completes
this 30 minutes (or so) of quiet time in the morning before I start with work.</p>
<p>So far, this small addition to my firmware has made quite a positive impact,
although I have to admit that AoC (see further down) is temporarily interfering
with items 2 and/or 3.</p>
<p>Oh well, one just has to keep on keeping on.</p>
<h2 id="someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet-part-972387">Someone is wrong on the internet, part 972387</h2>
<p>Some of you (does 2 out of my total of 5 readers qualify as &ldquo;some of you&rdquo;,
relatively speaking?) will remember that I sometimes have a fraught
relationship with people being wrong on the internet, or you could just look up
<a href="/2014/07/01/weekly-head-voices-76-someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet/">WHV #76 to read about a previous episode</a>.</p>
<p>Most recently, I was again trying spectacularly unsuccessfully to avoid
twitter, when I ran into a thread where people were arguing about wearing
facemasks or not in these times.</p>
<p>My plan was to pull myself away from my phone, then throw the phone into the
fire, and then start the BBQ, but unfortunately one of the persons who was
arguing on the wrong side carries the same name as I do.</p>
<p>Although I am the <strong>one true Charl Botha</strong>, as is confirmed by the world&rsquo;s
premier reference on everything Charl Botha, namely the website <a href="https://charlbotha.com/">charlbotha.com</a>,
I was still worried that someone somewhere might confuse me with the third-rate
Charl Botha who was putting his lack of humanity on display.</p>
<p>My initial reaction was to go in there with all of my verbal guns blazing in
order to correct the poor sod, and to ensure that people would see there were
more Charls, some of which were not <em>as</em> bad, but fortunately some of the
psychology I have been absorbing from the literature kicked in on time and I
managed to limit my reply tweet to the fact that 1) I was in fact the real
Charl Botha (the one with a brain), and 2) that I thought one should wear a
mask because it&rsquo;s kind to other humans.</p>
<p>This made me think about the observation that mask deniers would always believe
that there were holes in the science of mask-wearing, when the most important
consideration comes down to the fact that even if mask-wearing helped your
fellow humans possibly only a little bit, it&rsquo;s already the kind thing to do.</p>
<p>After that, I made the following tweet to summarise my thinking on this topic:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Folks, remember that
of the 14 mask types tested in <a
href="https://t.co/BrQ6cpCnkk">https://t.co/BrQ6cpCnkk</a> (sensitive to
droplet size all the way down to 0.5um), 13 of them reduced droplet
transmission relative to no mask. SO: Be kind. Wear a multi-layer mask, reduce
droplets, help your fellow humans. <a
href="https://t.co/COyrdksV9K">pic.twitter.com/COyrdksV9K</a></p>&mdash; Charl
Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a
href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1332014932481732608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November
26, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>What I learned from this would-be altercation, is that it&rsquo;s better for me to
focus my someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet rage into something that&rsquo;s more
constructive:</p>
<p>Strip the issue down as far as you can. Inject information. Combine that with
the desire that many humans share for a society where we can all just get
along.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s probably still not going to work, but just maybe, it&rsquo;ll cause less trouble
and result in a little bit more goodwill, and who knows where that may lead?</p>
<p>P.S. On the topic of mask-wearing: Even if there were no COVID-19, don&rsquo;t you
think we&rsquo;d all be a little better of if the wearing of good masks became the
norm?</p>
<p>There are indications that <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/flu-season-never-came-to-the-southern-hemisphere1/">mask-wearing and physical distancing basically
stopped flu season in the Southern Hemisphere</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Never in my 40-year career have we ever seen rates &hellip; so low</p>
<p>&ndash; Greg Poland, influenza expert at the Mayo Clinic</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="advent-of-code-2020">Advent of Code 2020</h2>
<p>Thanks to this tweet by <a href="https://twitter.com/RameezKhanSA">@RameezKhanSA</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My pledge this year is
to do the <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/AdventOfCode?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#AdventOfCode</a>
in <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Clojure?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Clojure</a>. Looking
forward to it. Already started doing some of last years challenges. Want to
keep it simple. No Leiningen just a plain deps.edn.</p>&mdash; Rameez
(@RameezKhanSA) <a
href="https://twitter.com/RameezKhanSA/status/1332692669190074370?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November
28, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; I am taking part, for the first time, in <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">the Advent of Code</a>!</p>
<p>Nerds from the world over get a new two-part programming puzzle every day at 5
AM UTC, from December 1 to December 25, for a total of 50 puzzles.</p>
<p>The idea is that said nerds use any programming language, or combination of
programming languages, to solve the puzzles and enter the answers on the AoC
website.</p>
<p>The quickest nerds, the ones who manage to solve these puzzles in an amazing
minute or three, earn a highly-coveted place on the <a href="https://adventofcode.com/2020/leaderboard">leaderboard</a>.</p>
<p>Just like Rameez, I wanted to use the AoC to get to know a programming language
better, although in my case that language is Nim.</p>
<p>So far, this has been a great deal of fun!</p>
<p>To my non-programmer friends: Solving puzzles is like concentrated cat nip to
programmers. In the case of AoC, you get unadulterated puzzle solving, and none
of the other complications of writing production software.</p>
<p>Besides the fun, Nim <em>really</em> shines at this. As I mentioned in <a href="/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/#save-image-from-clipboard">the previous
WHV</a>, Nim somehow manages to combine the expressivity and development velocity
of Python, with a great dollop of Python&rsquo;s famed batteries-included, with close
to the metal performance.</p>
<p>(My brain is currently spending background cycles figuring out if I could
somehow use this in a product.)</p>
<p>I am sort of expecting to drop out eventually, because, based on past years,
it&rsquo;s going to take up an increasing amount of time.</p>
<p>However, although I&rsquo;m already happy with what I have (day 6&rsquo;s puzzles completed
on Sunday December 6, ostensibly the end of this WHV&rsquo;s window of reality), I
would be really chuffed reaching the double digits!</p>
<p><em>Narrator: He ended up reaching the double digits.</em></p>
<h2 id="table-mountain-run--ish--2020">Table Mountain Run(ish) 2020</h2>
<p>We thought we were going to do a trail run up Skeleton Gorge.</p>
<p>Well, if one is us, one does not simply run up Skeleton Gorge. Instead, one
huffs and one puffs, for about a kilometre of ascent. It is a substantial
amount of huffing and puffing.</p>
<p>We did get to run on top of the mountain, from the beach at the top of Skeleton
Gorge (yes, there&rsquo;s a beach), to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maclear%27s%5FBeacon">Maclear&rsquo;s Beacon</a>, which I&rsquo;ve now learned was
used in the calculation of the curvature of he Earth, to the old cable station,
past the reservoirs to end up walking really slowly back down Nursery Gorge.</p>
<p>It was an interesting observation that although I found parts of the route hard
and sometimes maybe even a little unpleasant (coming down Nursery Gorge&hellip;)
whilst in the thick of things, the whole memory of the experience started
transmogrifying into <em>wonderful</em> verging on <em>magical</em> extremely soon after we
had reached the finish.</p>
<p>12/10 would do again, but next time a more gradual descent please!</p>
<h2 id="hi-mom">Hi mom</h2>
<p>My mom has now seen three quarters of a century.</p>
<p>I am happy to report that she is as fit as a fiddle. Genetics and some really
great habits are a really solid combination.</p>
<p>Importantly, we are truly fortunate to count her as an integral part of our
household.</p>
<p>(Them is some big words for: We have so much fun together! Our GOUs, who are
also her GOUs, will probably never forget these stories with their Oma.)</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s to the next quarter century!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve convinced her of the great business opportunity of publishing a book at
100 with tips and tricks for other (aspirant) centenarians, so she really needs
to remain as sharp and as fit as she is today!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #210: MiniBurn 2020</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 09:50:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/</guid><description> Welcome back to the WHV blogging clubhouse, gang!
Somewhat inspired by Descartes, I can say with a fair amount of confidence that you are now reading these words, and for that I am grateful.
This post covers the weeks from Monday, November 9 to Sunday, November 22 of the year 2020.
papercite_static: put some bibtex into your Hugo After languishing for almost a year on my todo list, I finally got around to cleaning up and making available my Python script for embedding your BiBTeX bibliographies in your markdown files.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="dirt_road_to_stanford.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Welcome back to the WHV blogging clubhouse, gang!</p>
<p>Somewhat inspired by Descartes, I can say with a fair amount of confidence that
you are now reading these words, and for that I am grateful.</p>
<p>This post covers the weeks from Monday, November 9 to Sunday, November 22 of
the year 2020.</p>
<h2 id="papercite-static-put-some-bibtex-into-your-hugo">papercite_static: put some bibtex into your Hugo</h2>
<p>After languishing for almost a year on my todo list, I finally got around to
cleaning up and making available my Python script for embedding your BiBTeX
bibliographies in your markdown files.</p>
<p>The script is called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/papercite%5Fstatic">papercite_static</a>, because it was inspired by <a href="https://wordpress.org/plugins/papercite/">the papercite
Wordpress plugin</a> that I previously used, but it was built for use in static
websites.</p>
<p>Catchy right?</p>
<p>This is pretty useful when you are academically inclined, or just really like
managing BiBTeX files.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re one of those people, you can go check it out at <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/papercite%5Fstatic">the papercite_static
github page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="save-image-from-clipboard">save_image_from_clipboard</h2>
<p>From the Department of Catchy Names, the same one that brought you the script
above, comes <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/save%5Fimage%5Ffrom%5Fclipboard">save_image_from_clipboard</a>!</p>
<p>I wrote this to scratch my own extremely niche itch (scranitch-ware!), but it
could be useful in other slightly less niche contexts.</p>
<p>My Emacs is configured with the org-download package so that I can use any
system tool to screenshot an arbitrary region of my screen to the clipboard,
and then tell Emacs to attach whatever is in the clipboard to the current
Orgmode heading.</p>
<p>This is something I use really often during daily note-taking and task
management.</p>
<p>The org-download package expects a PNG image to be available on the
clipboard. When this is not the case, because the screenshotting or other image
copying workflow instead copied a JPG or a BMP (long story, starts with a W,
ends with SL&hellip;), I get a blank attachment which makes me sad, and costs me
more time.</p>
<p>On macOS, I used <a href="https://github.com/jcsalterego/pngpaste">pngpaste</a> for this, a tool that ensures that whatever image
format is in the clipboard gets converted to PNG.</p>
<p>Well, <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/save%5Fimage%5Ffrom%5Fclipboard">save_image_from_clipboard</a> does exactly this, and a little more by simply
converting whatever&rsquo;s on the clipboard to the format that you specify.</p>
<p>This has already saved me countless SECONDS of time, and a substantial amount
of frustration.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;ve again been spending more hobby time with <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a>, which would have
resulted in a much smaller and faster binary in this case, but the Python
version wrote itself fairly quickly, with both of my hands behind my back.</p>
<p>P.P.S. nim is <em>so</em> hard to resist, in spite of what <a href="/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/#nimfatuation-is-now-over">I wrote about nimfatuation
being over, back in WHV #169</a>. It combines much of the expressiveness and some
of the batteries-included of Python, paired with the generation of tiny
self-contained binaries.</p>
<h2 id="my-emacs-is-now-all-in-on-ivy">My Emacs is now all-in on Ivy</h2>
<p>As you will <em>most probably</em> remember from <a href="/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/#you-can-easily-dired-jump-to-the-currently-ivy-readd-file-in-emacs">WHV #171</a>, my Emacs configuration used
a mishmash of <a href="https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm">Helm</a> and <a href="https://github.com/abo-abo/swiper">Ivy</a>.</p>
<p>Helm and Ivy are two great, but different, examples of Emacs completion /
selection frameworks, something that is really important to any disciple of
this amazing religion.</p>
<p>In something that is probably some sort of reflection of my character, I was
happily using both of them simultaneously for quite a while.</p>
<p>However, waking up one morning with the realisation that this was yet another
small context switch that was costing me time and focus, in one of my highest
ROI tool workflows to boot, I decided that it was time to excise Helm from my
configuration.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a few hours of Lisp-driven terraforming, and I was all-in on my
Ivy.</p>
<p>During this terraforming I ran into some undesired behaviour in ivy-rich, which
resulted first in me writing <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/11/15/fix-ivy-rich-switch-buffer-directories-display-in-emacs/">a blog post documenting the work-around</a>, then
noticing that ivy-rich&rsquo;s astute author had subsequently integrated part of my
fix, and finally authoring a <a href="https://github.com/Yevgnen/ivy-rich/pull/92">github pull request (PR)</a>, merged shortly after to
fix the remaining issues.</p>
<p>P.S. I sometimes wonder whether people outside of the open source world
understand how much github contributed to the software world by streamlining
the process whereby random developers are able to contribute lines of source
code into open source projects like this.</p>
<p>WELL DO YA?!</p>
<h2 id="mynoise-dot-net-is-an-amazing-soundscape-generator">mynoise.net is an amazing soundscape generator</h2>
<p>In the past few weeks, Lazar Focus has rescued my days so often.</p>
<p>What usually happens is that I get distracted&hellip; no wait, I fall down a
rabbit-hole&hellip; no wait, I actually get violently pulled into a rabbit
<strong>singularity</strong> from whence no productivity can escape.</p>
<p>The best I can do at that point, is to pour all will power into my puny arm and
click on that FOCUS button in Lazar Focus, at which point it instantly kills
everything that&rsquo;s sapping my attention, and then I again have a chance to save
the day.</p>
<p>Thanks to a recommendation by Noeska which ended up languishing in my
sub-conscious but then fortunately managed to bubble to the top, I found myself
on a wonderful site called <a href="https://mynoise.net/">myNoise</a>.</p>
<p>This is the creation of <a href="https://stephanepigeon.com/">Dr. Ir. Stéphane Pigeon</a>, a research engineer &amp; sound
designer from Belgium, who has combined noise generation as well as a library
of the highest quality recording of samples from the world over with a system
for composing these into the most amazing sound-scapes.</p>
<p>Why is this interesting, you might ask?</p>
<p>Well, in one&rsquo;s quest to block distractions of all kinds, finding the perfect
aural stimulus that is pleasant, but does not soak up attention itself, and is
also able to mask both external and internal (tinnitus, e.g.) sounds, myNoise
is exactly what the doctor ordered!</p>
<p>To give you a taste of Dr Pigeon&rsquo;s attention to detail, see for example the
<a href="https://mynoise.net/NoiseMachines/singingBowlsDroneGenerator.php">singing bowls generator</a>, and then the <a href="https://mynoise.net/NoiseMachines/enliaVocalSoundscape.php">Free-falling with vocalist Enlia
soundscape</a>.</p>
<p>Notice that in both cases you are able to customise different elements of each
soundscape with the sliders, or even press <code>A</code> to have them animate randomly
over time, morphing the landscape as you work.</p>
<p>What I only recently learned, is that Dr Pigeon designed the soundscapes to
work also simultaneously. In other words, keep the two soundscapes above open
in two browser tabs, and note how wonderfully they mesh.</p>
<p>It really feels like my brain is starting to associate high attention mode with
the mynoise soundscapes.</p>
<p>Between that and LF, we might be going places!</p>
<p>P.S. Narrator: <em>Yes, he did make a small donation to mynoise, and based on the
value he has derived since, will probably make another.</em></p>
<h2 id="what-does-it-mean-for-humanity-when-the-ai-can-derive-your-talking-face-from-your-voice-alone">What does it mean for humanity when the AI can derive your talking face from your voice alone?</h2>
<p>You might have read about <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/5/21502003/nvidia-ai-videoconferencing-maxine-platform-face-gaze-alignment-gans-compression-resolution">NVIDIA&rsquo;s new AI-based video conferencing bag of
tricks, called Maxine</a>.</p>
<p>An interesting part of this is that they use a technique, similar to deepfakes,
to send only the pose of your face over the internet, and then reconstruct a
high quality version of it on the other side.</p>
<p>From the article:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Instead of streaming the entire screen of pixels, the AI software analyzes the
key facial points of each person on a call and then intelligently re-animates
the face in the video on the other side,&rdquo; said the company in a blog
post. &ldquo;This makes it possible to stream video with far less data flowing back
and forth across the internet.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This made me think:</p>
<p>Soon the AI will be good enough that it can reconstruct your face from just the
audio, or maybe even text that you type.</p>
<p>This idea started as a half-serious joke, but it does raise really interesting
questions around the implications of this technology. (BTW, it is technically
entirely possible.)</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re having a conversation with someone, and both of your faces are
indistinguishable <em>simulations</em> of the real thing, and hence help the quality
of the conversation, what does that mean for the conversation that&rsquo;s happening?</p>
<p>In other words, imagine for a second that you&rsquo;re having an intense (emotional)
conversation with someone, but the faces that both of you are seeing, are 100%
synthesised.</p>
<p>They reflect almost exactly how your faces would have looked had you had a
video link, but they are estimated by the AI.</p>
<p>Did you really have that intense conversation?</p>
<h2 id="miniburn-2020">MiniBurn 2020</h2>
<p>As you might remember from <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#sht-gets-real-in-mzansi">WHV #191</a>, AfrikaBurn 2020 was one of the first group
events down here that was cancelled by the pandemic.</p>
<p>Months after that, and with stats looking almost reasonable, the local subset
of our camp (THE BURNIVERSITY) decided to celebrate life together, as
responsibly as possible (which mostly comes down to: stay outside, keep your
distance), by gathering at some secret but beautiful location for the weekend.</p>
<p>(You might have deduced by now that this is one of those Burny situations where
I have no choice but to keep things as vague as they are. I still wanted to
write <strong>something</strong> as a beacon for future me. Future me, when you read this:
Read our private notes man. I left you something there.)</p>
<p>We sort of modeled the weekend like a whole Burn: Friday is arrival, setup, and
first small celebrations. Saturday represents the body of the week: Running,
workshops, celebration. Sunday is, just like it is for the full Burn, the
slightly depressing but already nostalgic clean-up, pack-up and leave the
desert stage. It&rsquo;s surprising how well this whole sequencing worked.</p>
<p>Thanks to the awe-inspiring talents of specific camp members, the cuisine was
divine and the music beautiful. Combined with the personalities and shared
memories of our small ensemble, the resultant experience was nothing short of
magic.</p>
<p>P.S. Ironically, <a href="/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/#thank-you-joris">GU43 <strong>is</strong> turning into the 2020 soundtrack that I wanted</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #169: A cunning plan.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 22:12:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/</guid><description> Beautiful evening skies above my house. I just went through my notes.
As far as I can see now, the week from Monday April 8 to Sunday April 14 2019, although otherwise quite solid in terms of productivity and of The Important Stuff(tm), did not fare too well on the blog-worthiness scale.
About the exact implications of this discrepancy, I am also not entirely sure.
Nonetheless, my mission at this moment is to try and give you something entertaining and/or educational, and for this I have a cunning plan&amp;hellip;</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="pretty_clouds_above_home.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/pretty_clouds_above_home_hu4312bfdcd43b2079e55aafe4c2ba7609_2403668_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/pretty_clouds_above_home_hu4312bfdcd43b2079e55aafe4c2ba7609_2403668_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/pretty_clouds_above_home_hu4312bfdcd43b2079e55aafe4c2ba7609_2403668_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/pretty_clouds_above_home_hu4312bfdcd43b2079e55aafe4c2ba7609_2403668_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/pretty_clouds_above_home_hu4312bfdcd43b2079e55aafe4c2ba7609_2403668_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='pretty evening clouds above my home' />



</a>
<figcaption>
Beautiful evening skies above my house.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I just went through my notes.</p>
<p>As far as I can see now, the week from Monday April 8 to Sunday April 14 2019,
although otherwise quite solid in terms of productivity and of The Important
Stuff(tm), did not fare too well on the blog-worthiness scale.</p>
<p>About the exact implications of this discrepancy, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/If_a_tree_falls_in_a_forest">I am also not entirely
sure</a>.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, my mission at this moment is to try and give you something
entertaining and/or educational, and for this <a href="http://blackadderquotes.com/i-have-a-cunning-plan">I have a cunning
plan&hellip;</a></p>
<h2 id="nimfatuation-is-now-over">nimfatuation is now OVER.</h2>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-common-lisp" data-lang="common-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; consider reading this section if this line of code is clear to you</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#859900">if</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">not</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">are-nerd</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">you</span>)) (<span style="color:#268bd2">skip-this-section</span>))
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Last week, <a href="/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/#nim-surprise">I had happily started diving into the nim language and its
ecosystem</a>.</p>
<p>I was quite happy to hear that in addition to the enjoyment it had given me,
the spark had jumped over to at least one other peep (O HAI THERE S!) via
these writings.</p>
<p>However, after getting deeper into <a href="https://github.com/dom96/jester/issues/194">jester&rsquo;s multi-threading
intricacies</a> and discovering that
I could not get run-time confirmation that my requests were being handled by
separate threads, I returned to my initial target language for this experiment of
rewriting, namely f#!</p>
<p>nim is really a great little experiment: It consists of higher level
abstractions that compile down to C, and it&rsquo;s quite amazing to see what this
enables one to do.</p>
<p>However, I require something richer and more functional for my language
learning slot.</p>
<p>As I have written previously, <a href="/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/#f">f# hits all six of my 2018
PL-requirements</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualities of the language itself, <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-net-core-3-preview-3/">dotnet core 3, currently
at preview
3</a>, is
showing great progress, also in terms of memory efficiency and raw
performance.</p>
<p>I spent some time during the past week to re-re-implement my
nim-re-implementation of parts of isso, again purely for learning purposes.</p>
<p>(As an aside, it&rsquo;s interesting how close such a real-world example enables one
to get to using a tool or language <em>in anger</em>.)</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a fragment from my learning experiment, because if you&rsquo;re like me
you&rsquo;ll want to see what f# looks like:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-fsharp" data-lang="fsharp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#859900">let</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">getCommentsHandler</span> : <span style="color:#268bd2">HttpHandler</span> =
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#859900">fun</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">next</span> : <span style="color:#268bd2">HttpFunc</span>) (<span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span> : <span style="color:#268bd2">HttpContext</span>) -&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        <span style="color:#268bd2">task</span> {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>            <span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">// going from normal str -&gt; Result to str -&gt; Task&lt;Result&gt;,
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic"></span>            <span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">// so unfortunately no railway OP here.
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic"></span>            <span style="color:#859900">match</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span>.<span style="color:#268bd2">GetQueryStringValue</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;uri&#34;</span> <span style="color:#859900">with</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>            | <span style="color:#268bd2">Error</span> _ -&gt; <span style="color:#859900">return</span>! <span style="color:#268bd2">setStatusCode</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">404</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">next</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>            | <span style="color:#268bd2">Ok</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">uri</span> -&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>                <span style="color:#859900">match</span>! <span style="color:#268bd2">getThreadForUriAsync</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">uri</span> <span style="color:#859900">with</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>                | <span style="color:#268bd2">Ok</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">thread</span> -&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>                    <span style="color:#859900">match</span>! <span style="color:#268bd2">getCommentsForThreadId</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">thread</span>.<span style="color:#268bd2">id</span> <span style="color:#859900">with</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>                    | <span style="color:#268bd2">Ok</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">comments</span> -&gt; <span style="color:#859900">return</span>! <span style="color:#268bd2">json</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">comments</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">next</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>                    | <span style="color:#268bd2">Error</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">msg</span> -&gt; <span style="color:#859900">return</span>! (<span style="color:#268bd2">setStatusCode</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">404</span> &gt;=&gt; <span style="color:#268bd2">text</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">msg</span>) <span style="color:#268bd2">next</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>                | <span style="color:#268bd2">Error</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">msg</span> -&gt; <span style="color:#859900">return</span>! (<span style="color:#268bd2">setStatusCode</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">404</span> &gt;=&gt; <span style="color:#268bd2">text</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">msg</span>) <span style="color:#268bd2">next</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        }
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This is a <a href="https://github.com/giraffe-fsharp/Giraffe">Giraffe</a> handler that
handles a request with a <code>uri</code> query parameter. First it looks up the comment
thread in the isso database. If it finds a thread, it looks up the comments
and returns the whole list as JSON.</p>
<p>As you can see, there is error handling at every level.</p>
<p>F# code is expressive, but it is also fully typed. In this case it is
executed asynchronously (that&rsquo;s what the <code>task {}</code> and the <code>!</code>s are for), with
the asynchronous tasks distributed over threads.</p>
<p>In other words, we have a compiled functional language with Python-level
expressivity with really strong (and easy!) concurrency support.</p>
<p>If there had been no need for asynchrony, the code above could have been
rewritten following the <a href="https://swlaschin.gitbooks.io/fsharpforfunandprofit/content/posts/recipe-part2.html">railway-oriented
programming</a>
idea (from memory, not tested, as one does!):</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-fsharp" data-lang="fsharp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">// create chain of input -&gt; Result calls using the railway operator
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">// an Error anywhere will exit from the chain and can be handled by caller
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic"></span><span style="color:#859900">let</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">getCommentsForRequest</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span>: <span style="color:#268bd2">HttpContext</span>) =
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span>.<span style="color:#268bd2">GetQueryStringValue</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;uri&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    &gt;&gt;= <span style="color:#268bd2">getThreadIdForUri</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    &gt;&gt;= <span style="color:#268bd2">getCommentsForThreadId</span>    
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#859900">fun</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">next</span> : <span style="color:#268bd2">HttpFunc</span>) (<span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span> : <span style="color:#268bd2">HttpContext</span>) -&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#859900">match</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">getCommentsForRequest</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span> <span style="color:#859900">with</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    | <span style="color:#268bd2">Ok</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">comments</span> -&gt; <span style="color:#859900">return</span>! <span style="color:#268bd2">json</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">comments</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">next</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    | <span style="color:#268bd2">Error</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">msg</span> -&gt; <span style="color:#859900">return</span>! (<span style="color:#268bd2">setStatusCode</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">404</span> &gt;=&gt; <span style="color:#268bd2">text</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">msg</span>) <span style="color:#268bd2">next</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">ctx</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>During this exercise, I found F# Interactive (the built-in repl) super useful
to select and execute blocks of code from my source, Lisp-style, in order to
get my database support up and running.</p>
<p>In terms of the learning journey, I have not even left my own village
yet. However, F# seems to be triggering all of the right receptors.</p>
<h2 id="someone-is-right-on-the-internet">Someone is right on the internet.</h2>
<p><em>My</em> week might not have been the most blog-worthy, but, my goodness, the
Wonderful World of Science has not been sitting still!</p>
<p>You see, in desperation I went rummaging through the recent additions to
<a href="/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">JBOP</a>,
aka my growing collection of Really Interesting PDFs, and I hand-picked a few
tidbits worthy of casually mentioning during the undoubtedly erudite
discussion at your next cocktail party!</p>
<h3 id="each-millilitre-of-vosub2sub-max-reduces-your-risk-of-dying-by-28">Each millilitre of VO<sub>2</sub> max reduces your risk of dying by 2.8%.</h3>
<p>If we&rsquo;ve run (I see what I did there) into each other more than once, <a href="/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/#grab-bag-of-thought-and-or-debate-provoking-pieces">I&rsquo;ve
probably
mentioned</a>
last year&rsquo;s publication of the Cleveland treadmill study where they put 122000
people on a treadmill (the study took 20 years) to show that being unfit on a
treadmill is at least as risky (in terms of you dying) as being a smoker.</p>
<p>Well, last week the result of an even larger Swedish study, with 316137
participants, <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2019-04/esoc-mmt040819.php">were reported at EuroPrevent
2019</a>.</p>
<p>With each additional millilitre of oxygen per kilogram of body mass per minute
(<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VO2_max">VO<sub>2</sub> max, a cardiorespiratory fitness
measure</a>), the risk of all-cause
mortality fell by 2.8%, and the risk of cardiovascular events fell by 3.2%.</p>
<p>According to at least <a href="https://www.topendsports.com/testing/norms/vo2max.htm">one
source</a>, the range
between poor and excellent VO<sub>2</sub> max in most age segments for men and
women is 20 millilitres or more.</p>
<p>At 2.8% per millilitre, that certainly makes one think!</p>
<h3 id="hpv-vaccine-linked-to-dramatic-drop-in-cervical-disease">HPV vaccine linked to dramatic drop in cervical disease.</h3>
<p>Almost exactly 10 years ago, I wrote <a href="/2009/05/21/you-must-vaccinate/">a post on this blog titled &ldquo;You must
vaccinate&rdquo;</a> because friends and acquaintances
were asking questions which I found surprising on the one hand and quite
alarming on the other.</p>
<p>At that point I thought that even the slowest among us would have caught up to
the fact that there are an extremely large number of good reasons to
vaccinate, and almost none not to.</p>
<p>It seems that I over-estimated the capabilities and size of the slow group&hellip;</p>
<p>It is now 10 years later, and the anti-vaxxers have managed to <a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/29-11-2018-measles-cases-spike-globally-due-to-gaps-in-vaccination-coverage">bring measles
(and some friends) back from
extinction</a>.</p>
<p>Fortunately, there is also much to celebrate on the vaccination front.</p>
<p>Scotland started with their <a href="https://www.womenshealth.gov/a-z-topics/human-papillomavirus">human
papillomavirus</a>
vaccination programme 10 years ago, administering the vaccine to girls when
they are at around 12 years of age.</p>
<p>Researchers now say that since then the HPV vaccine has <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-scotland-47803975">&ldquo;nearly wiped out
cases of cervical pre-cancer in young
women&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s also heartening is that unvaccinated women also showed a reduction in
disease, implying that the immunisation programme is protecting even more
humans from the disease due to the herd effect.</p>
<p>(GOU#1 had her HPV shot at school last year. There were parents who
complained. I don&rsquo;t know if there were any refusers.)</p>
<p>I am still hopeful that one day all of these victories will contribute to the
attrition of the irresponsibly dangerous anti-vaxx movement.</p>
<h3 id="how-the-matrix-built-a-bullet-proof-legacy">How The Matrix Built A Bullet-Proof Legacy.</h3>
<p>Surprise! This one is not from science, but it was such an amazing read that I
have to share.</p>
<p>If, like me, you saw The Matrix more times than you can count, you will also
enjoy this write-up of how the whole project came together:</p>
<p>Extract from the book <em>How 1999 blew up the Big Screen</em> by Brian Raftery: <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/the-matrix-legacy-book-excerpt/">HOW
THE MATRIX BUILT A BULLET-PROOF
LEGACY</a></p>
<h2 id="you-never-write">You never write.</h2>
<p>At Tuesday&rsquo;s edition of the Helderberg Software Developers and Entrepreneurs
meetup, organised by <a href="https://wogan.blog/">Wogan May</a> (pssst, he has a
personal blog with mostly weekly updates!) and myself, <a href="http://johan.beyers.co.za/">Johan
Beyers</a> talked about the personal resolution of
doing a given amount of (personal) writing every day.</p>
<p>I try to do it once weekly with the WHV, and I mostly manage to make a few
bullet points detailing my exploits every day, but the idea of additionally
writing a few more prose-like paragraphs of thoughts every day really
resonates with me.</p>
<p>Derek Sivers (he was a famous startup-person even before the whole startup
boom, thanks <a href="https://twitter.com/gerwindehaan">Gerwin de Haan</a> for that book
so many years ago!) <a href="https://sivers.org/dj">makes a good case for writing a few diary-like sentences
every evening</a>.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s even more intriguing, is his suggestion to maintain separate &ldquo;Thoughts
On&rdquo; journals for various topics that you think about often. In my case, these
could be for example &ldquo;Thoughts on Programming Languages&rdquo;, or &ldquo;Thoughts on
mindfulness for children&rdquo;, or &ldquo;Thoughts on the WHV rules for a contented
life&rdquo;, and so on.</p>
<p>I think it would be a cunning plan to give both of these additional writing
practices a good go.</p>
<p>Let me know in the comments what you think!</p>
<figure>
<a href="strand_running_clouds_on_mountains.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/strand_running_clouds_on_mountains_hu38426c04232e1444bb0c0608208a1e21_2519865_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/strand_running_clouds_on_mountains_hu38426c04232e1444bb0c0608208a1e21_2519865_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/strand_running_clouds_on_mountains_hu38426c04232e1444bb0c0608208a1e21_2519865_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/strand_running_clouds_on_mountains_hu38426c04232e1444bb0c0608208a1e21_2519865_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/strand_running_clouds_on_mountains_hu38426c04232e1444bb0c0608208a1e21_2519865_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



</a>
<figcaption> 
You've seen photos like these before, but on this very day, I really liked how the clouds
were creating patterns of light and dark created on the mountains in the distance.
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #168: Postcards from the edge.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:43:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek, Stellenbosch. My friend showed me a photo and said &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s a picture of me when I was younger&rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger. &ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)
In this edition of the WHV, I cast my now older eyes back on the week starting on Monday, April 1 and ending on Sunday, April 7, 2019.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="postcard_cafe_view.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



</a>
<figcaption> 
Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes
you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek,
Stellenbosch.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<blockquote>
<p>My friend showed me a photo and said &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s a picture of me when I was
younger&rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger.
&ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this edition of the WHV, I cast my now older eyes back on the week starting
on Monday, April 1 and ending on Sunday, April 7, 2019.</p>
<p>I have to apologise for the extremely high nerd content. There will be wine at
the end to make up for it!</p>
<h2 id="working-late-like-its-1998">Working late like it&rsquo;s 1998.</h2>
<p>At the start of the week, I had resolved to get more sleep.</p>
<p>It seems that when I have a good night&rsquo;s sleep, really working that
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glymphatic_system">glymphatic system</a> (I&rsquo;m
currently fascinated by the glymphatic system, I hope you like it too),
amongst other nightly repair activities, there is a greater probability that I
am able to hold my focus the next day.</p>
<p>This was going swimmingly.</p>
<p>At least that was the case until Wednesday, when I decided that the time had
come to port <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs</a>, the far more nerdy sister of this
blog, from <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">wordpress to hugo as
well</a>.</p>
<p>One thing led to another, and by 1:00AM (on a school night no less!) I was
busy wrapping up the isso commenting system configuration.</p>
<p>(We&rsquo;re able to use free and ad-free disqus over here because this is a
personal blog. vxlabs on the other hand is strictly speaking a commercial
site, even although it&rsquo;s filled with non-commercial blog posts.)</p>
<p>One of the many funny things about being a nerd, is that it&rsquo;s almost
impossible to go to bed before a technical thing like this has been
convincingly put to bed.</p>
<p>Fortunately this late night indiscretion yielded a working self-hosted
commenting system, and, far more importantly, a <a href="/2019/04/06/isso-on-webfaction/">rather attractively styled
post, thanks to the Hugo-port, detailing the whole
installation</a>.</p>
<p>In entirely predictable fashion, the next day was not the best focus-wise.</p>
<p>P.S. 1998 - first postgrad year in the DSP lab. All-nighters all the way down&hellip;</p>
<figure>
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu9ee58e4bdba0ae214d7d56f78a627136_96292_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu9ee58e4bdba0ae214d7d56f78a627136_96292_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu9ee58e4bdba0ae214d7d56f78a627136_96292_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



<figcaption>DSP lab, somewhen between 97 - 99.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="nim-surprise">nim-surprise.</h2>
<p>I chose Isso because it&rsquo;s Python.</p>
<p>DayJob(tm) is all about Python, so this was a great choice in terms of time
savings.</p>
<p>With all of the time I had saved, I decided that I would experiment with
re-implementing parts of Isso in <a href="https://fsharp.org/">f#</a>, my current hobby
functional language.</p>
<p>Setting aside the irony here, I learned after some time that getting f#, the
impressive looking <a href="https://fsprojects.github.io/SQLProvider/">SQLProvider</a> and
sqlite (isso&rsquo;s database) all working together on Linux was <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/fsharp/comments/8ufvzz/how_can_i_add_sqlprovider_to_my_existing_project/e1idy1o/">&ldquo;probably the
single most complicated thing that you can do with a F# project, when it comes
to
tooling&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>In this case, I was thankfully able to switch gears and did a brief review of
possible candidates for a functional(ish), memory efficient, fast(ish)
compilation languages that could be used to implement an Isso web-service
replacement.</p>
<p>Somehow I ended up with <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a>.</p>
<p>This has been on my radar for a while now, but there were always shinier
things to try.</p>
<p>I think what might have put me off was the similarity to Python.</p>
<p>So, with the rest of the time I had saved choosing Isso, I got up to
speed(ish) with nim by starting to implement a replacement for parts of the
isso commenting system.</p>
<p>I was quite positively surprised by the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Compilation speed: The nim compiler transforms my webservice code into C and
then compiles that in about 1.2 seconds.</li>
<li>Performance and memory size of resultant binary: This is not a fair
comparison to Python, but the multi-threaded nim service consumes a few
megabytes in total.</li>
<li>Availability of packages especially for building a web service like this:
Using the nimble package manager, I could install
<a href="https://github.com/dom96/jester">jester</a> and had my first running
web-service in a few minutes.</li>
<li>Built-in sqlite support.</li>
<li>Real macros: I used the list comprehension one in the <code>sugar</code> module.</li>
</ul>
<p>This was really just an exercise (for now), but I have a new tool for whenever
I need to write a fast and compact compiled web-service again!</p>
<p>P.S. Learning new programming languages is one of my favourite things.</p>
<p>P.P.S. Thanks to the internet and open source, and especially tools like
github, we are currently going through a sort of programming language Cambrian
explosion. See this <a href="http://fll.presidentbeef.com/">Fledgling Languages List</a>
for example. Pony!</p>
<h2 id="decompression">Decompression.</h2>
<p>On Sunday, we made the drive out to Jonkershoek in Stellenbosch.</p>
<p>Even although it&rsquo;s only 40 minutes away, I haven&rsquo;t been there in far too
long. It&rsquo;s a truly beautiful corner of the planet.</p>
<p>At the Postcard Café, after some internal deliberation, I made the decision
that the moment was special enough to interrupt LAZ
(lifestyle-alcohol-zero(tm)) with an all the more special glass of the
<a href="https://winemag.co.za/stark-conde-the-field-blend-2014/">Stark-Condé Field Blend white
wine</a>.</p>
<p>This is a hyper-local blend of Chenin Blanc, Rousanne, Verdelho and Viognier,
all four varietals which grow on the mountain-side right across from the
Café&rsquo;s veranda.</p>
<p>It really was divine.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>