<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Physics on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/physics/</link><description>Recent content in Physics on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2022 18:34:28 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/physics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #248: Oh snap</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 17:11:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/</guid><description>Welcome back everyone to this completely normal and of course utterly on-time edition of the WHV which spans (checks notes&amp;hellip;) the one (1) week from Monday October 31 to Sunday November 6, 2022.
Figure 1: Watsonia posing in front of mountain. Photo by partner.
(Yes, I am a little bit excited that for once this post is technically on time enough to cover only that one week. Of course what&amp;rsquo;s in the post does not necessarily have to do anything with the events that transpired in that week, but we won&amp;rsquo;t let that keep us from this little punctuality celebration.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone to this completely normal and <em>of course</em> utterly on-time
edition of the WHV which spans (checks notes&hellip;) the one (1) week from Monday
October 31 to Sunday November 6, 2022.</p>










<figure><a href="watsonia.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/watsonia_hu_debc42276bb7bad6.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/watsonia_hu_489cb78722af20c0.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/watsonia_hu_98048fffdfaecbb4.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/watsonia_hu_6905e08d387e7840.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/watsonia_hu_489cb78722af20c0.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Watsonia posing in front of mountain. Photo by partner."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Watsonia posing in front of mountain. Photo by partner.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>(Yes, I am a little bit excited that for once this post is technically on time
enough to cover only that one week. Of course what&rsquo;s in the post does not
necessarily have to do anything with the events that transpired in that week,
but we won&rsquo;t let that keep us from this little punctuality celebration.)</p>
<p>On to the post: We have keyboards, file synchronization approaches and some
surprising mathematical terminology!</p>
<h2 id="keyboard-never-endgame">Keyboard never-endgame</h2>
<p>It has been &hellip;9 (nine)&hellip; months since I last talked about <a href="/tags/keyboards/">keyboards on this
blog</a>.</p>
<p>At that point, <a href="/2022/02/09/weekly-head-voices-238-live-deep-and-suck-out-all-the-marrow-of-life/#womier-k87-keyboard-customization-unlocked">I had just replaced the tactile brown switches in my Womier with
linear reds</a>, and discovered to my surprise that I do in fact prefer linears.</p>
<p>Since then, I have again replaced the switches on that board, but this time
with Kailh Speed Silvers.</p>
<p>My plan was to get as close as possible to the effortlessly smooth feel of my
Varmilo VA87m (with Cherry MX Speed Silvers) at work.</p>
<p>While that board was certainly inching closer, it was still missing a little
something&hellip;</p>
<p>&hellip; perhaps, perhaps it was just missing a completely new little new keyboard!</p>
<p>When respected YouTube reviewers call a keyboard with factory-lubed switches,
luxury double-shot PBT OSA-profile keycaps and this particular sound the <a href="https://youtu.be/HVphB6RYBaY">&ldquo;The
Keychron V1 <strong>Bargain</strong>&rdquo;</a>, and other reviewers remark that the only issue with this
board is that you&rsquo;ll be hard-pressed to find one in stock due to its level of
bang-for-buck, you could probably predict that I would find it quite hard to
resist.</p>
<p>I had to pull some (Aramex) strings to get the keyboard delivered here, but
wow, it was so worth it!</p>
<p>Although I was hoping for something close to my Varmilo in terms of feel, this
V1 with its red switches is at least the Varmilo&rsquo;s equal, if not a little more.</p>
<h2 id="hell-freezes-over--again">Hell freezes over (again)</h2>
<p>Readers of this blog know that I&rsquo;ve been <a href="/tags/dropbox/">using (and paying for) Dropbox</a> for
quite a number of years.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;ve been together for long enough that we even got to do a <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">break-up-make-up
cycle back in 2013</a>, and in 2019 I tried and <a href="/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/#my-big-and-stupid-misstep-into-google-drive">failed spectacularly to migrate to
a cheaper competitor whose name starts with a G</a>.</p>
<p>One would have thought that I learned my lesson in 2019 (that post even
explicitly lists the lessons learned&hellip;), but apparently not.</p>
<p>After I recently discovered how to get the fantastic <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/10/22/unison-file-synchronization-directly-via-the-wsl-bridge/">unison bi-directional
syncing tool to sync between WSL and the Windows host</a>, I decided that it was
again time to attempt <em>something</em> stupid, this time migrating my whole digital
life to OneDrive, the cloud file synchronization tool made by Microsoft, our
erstwhile sworn enemy who later turned out to be pretty cool after all.</p>
<p>My main reason this time was again cost, and reducing the number of
subscriptions and cloud systems we use. (we already have OneDrive as part of
the incredibly reasonably priced Microsoft 365 family)</p>
<p>About two weeks ago I managed to copy all of my files (more than 500 thousand
files totalling over 200GB) from Dropbox to OneDrive over a few days, using the
amazing rclone tool, via my Hetzner VPS in Germany.</p>
<p>After some initial hiccups as the various OneDrive clients had to catch up to
the deluge of new files that were coming in, this setup has been working pretty
well!</p>
<p>On each of my Windows development machines (2 active, 1 semi-active) I have
unison running in watch mode under tmux syncing only the subset of the folders
that I need to be on WSL2, namely source code and my pkb4000 notes
database. (the same notes database containing the month file that houses this
blog post draft &ndash; every time I hit <code>C-x C-s</code>, the Emacs hotkey for save, this
file is synced from WSL to the host drive by Unison, and then from there to the
OneDrive cloud)</p>
<p>I also have the OneDrive client on my M1 MBA where it uses more ram than
Dropbox, but where its RAM for some reason gets compressed much more readily
than the Dropbox client.</p>
<p>While the syncing is not as fast as dropbox (in terms of picking up changes and
zapping them to the cloud and to other machines), it&rsquo;s entirely
serviceable. unison is blindingly fast for its part of the job.</p>
<p>As an added bonus, this enabled me to exclude <code>node_modules</code> FOREVER in the
default unison profile that I use.</p>
<p>Note that you can configure OneDrive to exclude files BY WILDCARD (see <a href="https://superuser.com/a/1662761/130835">this
superuser.com answer</a>), something that even the great Dropbox has no way of
doing.</p>
<h3 id="yes-you-can-keep-your-checked-out-source-code-in-dropbox-or-onedrive">Yes, you CAN keep your checked-out source code in Dropbox or OneDrive!</h3>
<p>Finally, hereby I also officially announce that: Why yes, I do keep <em>all</em> of my
checked out source code projects in OneDrive. Previously, I did the same for
years and years in Dropbox.</p>
<p>I have very good reasons for doing this.</p>
<p>My tweet below and the blog post that I link explain some of these reasons:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Every time someone asks about storing git repos in <a href="https://twitter.com/Dropbox?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@Dropbox</a> / <a href="https://twitter.com/onedrive?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@onedrive</a> someone asks &quot;why?! because git already does that!&quot; - well no, it doesn&#39;t instantaneously sync all your work so that you can change workstations on a whim! <a href="https://twitter.com/Lexisomes?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@Lexisomes</a> explains: <a href="https://t.co/UCiNcAGCal">https://t.co/UCiNcAGCal</a></p>&mdash; charlbotha dot com dot net dot org (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1582682819037626368?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">October 19, 2022</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; and here I recently came out about this issue on reddit:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I have been hosting all of my source code in dropbox AND pushing to various git
repos for years and years now, with nary a hitch. For the past few weeks, I
have been trying OneDrive, and so far it&rsquo;s been going well.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been trying to explain to people over the years that there are good
reasons for doing so, in my case primarily the fact that I work on the same
projects on various machines and laptops, and I prefer NOT abusing git commits
for manual syncing</p>
<p>Furthermore, I&rsquo;m often working on a number of repos, and having to commit all
of them just to switch ot my laptop does not make any sense.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The next time someone claims that this is what git is for, please send them to
me, because it&rsquo;s not.</p>
<h2 id="from-the-departments-of-physics-and-breakfast">From the Departments of Physics and Breakfast</h2>
<p>I recently learned about the official names of the third to sixth derivates of
position, from <a href="https://twitter.com/JimPfaendtner/status/1588987738426314752">Twitter of all places</a>.</p>
<p>(Over the years, I&rsquo;ve actually learned quite a lot from there, but who knows
how we&rsquo;ll look back at it in a few years time.)</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth,_fifth,_and_sixth_derivatives_of_position">Wikipedia confirms</a> that indeed after the pretty unsurprisingly named first and
second derivatives, namely <em>velocity</em> and <em>acceleration</em>, things started getting just a
little bit weird, but understandable, with <em>jerk</em> for the third, and <em>snap</em> or <em>jounce</em> for the
fourth, but then the clown gloves came off with <strong><em>snap</em></strong>, <strong><em>crackle</em></strong> and <strong><em>pop</em></strong> for the
fourth to the sixth derivatives!</p>
<p>Isn&rsquo;t that just marvelous?!</p>
<p>I really wanted to reproduce the list here using the built-in \(\KaTeX\) support
in this blog, and so I fell down a small rabbit-hole because \(\KaTeX\), while
amazing and fast, does not have <code>eqnarray</code>, and its <code>aligned</code> environment needs
some help with vertical spacing (<code>\\[1.5ex]</code> at the end of every line to give it
a bit of an extra nudge).</p>
<p>Secondly, I had to update my modification of the <a href="https://github.com/carsonip/hugo-theme-minos">hugo-minos theme</a> so that it
uses the latest version of \(\KaTeX\), and so that I could add that very <code>aligned</code>
environment to its default list of <a href="https://katex.org/docs/autorender.html#api">delimiters via the optional <code>options</code>
argument to <code>renderMathInElement()</code></a>.</p>
<p>Finally, while Org-mode and the brilliant ox-hugo usually automatically pass
<a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/LaTeX-fragments.html">\(\LaTeX\) fragments</a> through to Hugo, in this case I had to wrap it in an <code>HTML</code>
export block and manually specify the correct number (four) of slashes, as it was
automatically transforming <code>\\[1.5ex]</code> into <code>\\\[1.5ex]</code> (note the three slashes
instead of four, whilst without the <code>[...]</code> it correctly generates four).</p>
<p>Anyways, after all that, you get these nicely rendered equations:</p>
<p>\begin{aligned}
\bm{r} &amp;= \operatorname{position}\\[1.5ex]
\frac{d\bm{r}}{dt} &amp;= \operatorname{velocity}\\[1.5ex]
\frac{d^2\bm{r}}{dt^2} &amp;= \operatorname{acceleration}\\[1.5ex]
\frac{d^3\bm{r}}{dt^3} &amp;= \operatorname{jerk}\\[1.5ex]
\frac{d^4\bm{r}}{dt^4} &amp;= \operatorname{snap}\\[1.5ex]
\frac{d^5\bm{r}}{dt^5} &amp;= \operatorname{crackle}\\[1.5ex]
\frac{d^6\bm{r}}{dt^6} &amp;= \operatorname{pop}
\end{aligned}</p>
<p>Wow, blogging with Org-mode and Hugo sure is easy! :)</p>
<p>P.S. You might remember that it was also a <a href="https://blogs.scientificamerican.com/news-blog/how-a-fake-word-from-the-simpsons-e/">Physics paper that helped
main-streaming the word <em>embiggen</em></a> from The Simpsons right into our
dictionaries.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #183: Wave functions wearing lycra.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2019 17:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/</guid><description>This, the 183d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the week from Monday November 4 to Sunday November 10, 2019.
In this post we have a BLoM, a story about the conflict between a man and a toy and finally some great quantum mechanics visualizations for your meat-based neural network.
On the way home from a compact but enjoyable Sunday party with built-in family gathering at Skilpadvlei near Stellenbosch. BLoM (Bullet List of Miscellany). Thanks to the gentle urging of my friend the Vogon Poet, I finally got around to fixing my custom Hugo shortcode for image inclusion so that it would use full path names. This will hopefully result in RSS feeds and the subscription email correctly displaying images. I forgot to mention in the previous WHV that I wrote a post explaining how you can use Emacs and Orgmode to form and maintain good habits. This has really been working quite well for me. It is hard to explain how happy I am that the comments on this blog are now also self-hosted using the open-source software isso. Of all of the advantages, I think I appreciate the lower barrier to entry the most. With full markdown support, you should be able to post whole blog posts down below in the comment section! (HINT HINT) I should really look where I&amp;rsquo;m walking. Picture this:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 183d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the week from
Monday November 4 to Sunday November 10, 2019.</p>
<p>In this post we have a BLoM, a story about the conflict between a man and a toy
and finally some great quantum mechanics visualizations for your meat-based
neural network.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu_de5155d5e2ecc729.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu_8d8fa95909e712e.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu_674e1ad7a2c14f7c.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu_1aca6a21b9ccaf33.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu_8d8fa95909e712e.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
On the way home from a compact but enjoyable Sunday party with
built-in family gathering at Skilpadvlei near Stellenbosch. 
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="blom-bullet-list-of-miscellany">BLoM (Bullet List of Miscellany).</h2>
<ul>
<li>Thanks to the gentle urging of my friend <a href="https://twitter.com/vogonpoet">the Vogon
Poet</a>, I finally got around to fixing my
custom Hugo shortcode for image inclusion so that it would use full path
names. This will hopefully result in RSS feeds and the subscription email
correctly displaying images.</li>
<li>I forgot to mention in the previous WHV that I wrote a post explaining how
you can <a href="/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/">use Emacs and Orgmode to form and maintain good
habits</a>. This has
really been working quite well for me.</li>
<li>It is hard to explain how happy I am that the comments on this blog are now
also <a href="/2019/11/10/we-now-have-self-hosted-isso-comments/">self-hosted using the open-source software
isso</a>. Of all of the
advantages, I think I appreciate the lower barrier to entry the most. With
full markdown support, you should be able to post whole blog posts down below
in the comment section! (HINT HINT)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="i-should-really-look-where-im-walking">I should really look where I&rsquo;m walking.</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>On Wednesday evening, as I was walking onto the carpet in our room, feet nicely
marinated and super soft thanks to the shower I had just taken, senses and
planning wetware focused on three different non-floor points in the room (I was
carrying two items that needed to be deposited in two different locations, and
I spotted genetic relation units on the bed), I managed to step right onto the
single pink plastic toy my youngest GOU had left on the floor.</p>
<p>Naturally I did this with the softest part of my soft foot.</p>
<p>The plastic shattered, and somehow my reflexive foot action only served to
result in a partial retract followed by an apparently inevitable rejoining of
the vertical foot-toy-mashup, which on its part served to bring more bits of
shattered plastic into membrane piercing force levels of contact with the soft
underside of my foot.</p>
<p>Are you still picturing?</p>
<p>Relatively-speaking large floor, unoccupied with one small exception.</p>
<p>Single highly shatter-friendly toy, made of <em>pink</em> plastic.</p>
<p>Man manages to angle foot <em>just so</em>, applies copious force, and impales said
foot on lone toy, not once, but multiple times.</p>
<p>Anyways people, measuring by the amount of blood and other KPIs, I can in all
honesty say that this is somewhat worse than stepping on a lego.</p>
<p>Three days later, we extracted what was hopefully the last bit of plastic from
the underside of my foot.</p>
<p>On the bright side, the tweezer from <a href="/2018/02/11/weekly-head-voices-131-function-over-form/#what-a-tool">my Gerber every day carry (EDC)
micro-tool</a>
has now shown itself excellent for the purpose of light home surgery.</p>
<p>Also on the bright side, this will hopefully serve as powerful reminder that I
should really focus better on where I put my feet down at home, at least until
the volume of toys starts to diminish in a few years time.</p>
<p>(On Sunday, I couldn&rsquo;t not, so I did squeeze in a short and careful run. I was
quite happy that everything did still seem to work, albeit with some extra
feeling.)</p>
<h2 id="gravitational-waves-on-the-high-seas-of-curved-spacetime">Gravitational waves on the high seas of curved spacetime.</h2>
<p>My favourite video showing the idea of how gravity warps (curves; bends)
spacetime is the one below.</p>
<p>For those of you who prefer not viewing YouTube videos, let me do another
&ldquo;picture this&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Sooooo&hellip; PICTURE THIS:</p>
<ul>
<li>The gentleman explaining the idea has a sheet of lycra stretched taut over a
circular frame. He makes a funny joke about it being an old swimming costume.</li>
<li>Placing heavy bearings on the sheet stretches the lycra down into a
funnel-shape, as you would expect. (that reminds me of this tangential thing
I wanted to tell you at some other point: it turns out your neural network
had to learn explicitly that model of material stretching as you were growing
up)</li>
<li>Throwing more bearings onto the lycra, one can see how the curved surface
causes them to orbit around the larger bearings!</li>
</ul>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/MTY1Kje0yLg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>Well, isn&rsquo;t that just a fabulous image to have in your mind&rsquo;s eye right now?!</p>
<p>This is exactly how you can visualize the warping of the gravity field in which
you and I and all of our friends and the Earth and all the planets and
everything in the whole universe are snugly embedded!</p>
<p>This more than explains the old <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Action_at_a_distance">&ldquo;action at a
distance&rdquo;</a> mystery.</p>
<p>In other words, how is it possible that the Sun is able to exert a force on the
planet-formerly-knows-as-Pluto?</p>
<p>Well, as you can visualize now, the Sun, being the baddest mofo in this valley,
warps the gravitational field (enveloping us all) the most, and this is what
keeps Pluto in orbit.</p>
<p>Anyways, as beautiful as this is, it is probably old news to many of you.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go on to my NEW story!</p>
<p>During a recent <a href="https://lexfridman.com/sean-carroll/">Lex Fridman podcast</a>
with the CalTech theoretical physicist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sean_M._Carroll">Sean
Carroll</a>, Carroll non-chalantly
mentioned that general relativity was simply the extension to the idea of
warped spacetime of a change at one point of the gravitational field not being
able to propagate faster than the speed of light to another point!</p>
<p>BRAIN ASPLODE.</p>
<p>I had never thought of it this way before.</p>
<p>When an object accelerates, it emanates a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravitational_wave">gravitational
wave</a> which travels through
the gravitational field at the speed of light. (Yes, these <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_observation_of_gravitational_waves">gravitational waves
have been
measured</a>.)</p>
<p>Going back to our lycra visualization, it made intuitive sense to me that a
change in the warping of the lycra, for example due to the heaviest bearing
being moved by a giant hand, would have to travel at finite speed through the
lycra material for the new warped configuration to have reached all of its
corners!</p>
<p>At that point in the podcast, as if my brain was not reeling sufficiently from
these brilliant new mental images of gravitational waves rippling through
curved spacetime, just like the patterns formed by small rocks skipping over
water, Carroll started explaining how we are all just quantum wave functions
continuously getting entangled with each other the whole time.</p>
<p>I think I have just convinced myself <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Something-Deeply-Hidden-Emergence-Spacetime-ebook/dp/B07LCP3YRY/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=1573570733&amp;sr=8-1">what I will have to
read</a>
right after I finish with <em>Why we sleep</em>&hellip;</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #98: Lemons.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/16/weekly-head-voices-98-lemons/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 20:08:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/16/weekly-head-voices-98-lemons/</guid><description>This, the ninety eighth edition of the WHV, looks back at the week of Monday August 10 to Sunday August 16, 2015.
Today we took a brief walk up into the mountain, as one does around these parts. This is what False Bay looks like from the Helderberg Nature Reserve:
When life hands you lemons, build a battery Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #1 had to do a show and tell at school, so I helped her to construct a battery from 4 lemons. Besides that because of this I got to refresh my own knowledge (can you remember exactly why a battery such as this works?!) we got to chat about molecules, atoms, protons, neutrons, electrons, atomic numbers and the periodic table.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the ninety eighth edition of the WHV, looks back at the week of Monday
August 10 to Sunday August 16, 2015.</p>
<p>Today we took a brief walk up into the mountain, as one does around these
parts. This is what <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_Bay">False Bay</a> looks like from the Helderberg Nature
Reserve:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-false_bay_from_helderberg_nature_reserve.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-false_bay_from_helderberg_nature_reserve.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="when-life-hands-you-lemons-build-a-battery">When life hands you lemons, build a battery</h2>
<p>Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #1 had to do a show and tell at school, so I
helped her to construct a battery from 4 lemons. Besides that because of this I
got to refresh my own knowledge (can <i>you</i> remember exactly why a battery
such as this works?!) we got to chat about molecules, atoms, protons, neutrons,
electrons, atomic numbers and the periodic table.</p>
<p>The next day she quite coolly took the whole kit to school, proceeded to
connect up the disassembled kit before the class, and got the little LED to
switch on, all the while explaining in high-level 9-year-old-ish how it worked.</p>
<p>In case you’re wondering, the experiment looked like this:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-lemon_battery.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-lemon_battery.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>With zinc-covered screws and heavy duty stripped copper wire, we got about 0.9V per lemon. There was enough current to light up a small 3V LED.</p>
<p>(Will GOU#1 one day become an engineer? Stay tuned to this blog for the next 10 years to find out!)</p>
<h2 id="taking-a-break-from-facebook">Taking a break from Facebook</h2>
<p>One of my more interesting Facebook friends announced that she was taking a break from Facebook, because “this stuff is toxic and no good”.</p>
<p>This made me evaluate what I thought of FB at the moment.</p>
<p><i>Toxic</i> is a strong word, but after thinking about this for a while, I have to admit that a large part of the time I spend on the site is probably not that good for my karma. The problem is that there are a whole bunch of friends I really would like to stay in contact with, but for the most part they are quite silent. The people that do pipe up the most on FB are people with some or other silly and/or misguided agenda.</p>
<p>Although <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2014/07/01/weekly-head-voices-76-someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet/">I have learnt to stop correcting the infinite number of people who are wrong on the internet</a>, I’m still reading their contributions, getting slightly worked up, formulating a response, and then resisting posting it, all of this a number of times per day.</p>
<p>To the question whether seeing the one or two positive and life-affirming posts is justified by a seemingly much larger number of the opposite, my response has also become to take a break from Facebook and to see for myself.</p>
<p>I’m not going to cancel my account, so I will receive notifications for example when people message me, but I’m just going to stop checking the site completely. I am also giving myself permission to post new WHV editions there now and then: It’s sometimes the best way to reach some of those silent but desirable FB friends I mentioned, because not all of them are subscribed to this blog. THAT’S A SUBTLE HINT SILENT BUT DESIRABLE FRIENDS.</p>
<p>(BTW, I’m almost 3 days in now, so far no problems. I’ll report back in future WHVs.)</p>
<h2 id="the-mind-is-a-terrible-thing-to-taste">The mind is a terrible thing to taste</h2>
<p>This week I learned about <a href="http://www.nih.gov/researchmatters/october2013/10282013clear.htm">fascinating sleeping brain research</a> (that summary is from the NIH, also see <a href="http://news.sciencemag.org/brain-behavior/2013/10/sleep-ultimate-brainwasher">this one by Science Magazine</a>) that was published in 2013.</p>
<p>In short, when mice sleep, the area between their brain cells is temporarily increased by 60% (!!), and the cerebro-spinal fluid between the cells flows much more rapidly than when they’re awake. This rapid flow literally flushes out of the brain the toxins that build up during the waking hours. HOW COOL IS THAT?!</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-sciencemag_brainwash.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-sciencemag_brainwash.jpg"
        
            alt="Toxins flushed out via bright blue channels between brain cells. Image from Science Mag summary linked above."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Toxins flushed out via bright blue channels between brain cells. Image from Science Mag summary linked above.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Going down one detail level, the researchers showed that the glial cells (the non-neuronal cells in the brain) control the flow of cerebro-spinal fluid through channels in their cell membranes. By using different coloured dyes, they showed that there was significantly more flow during sleeping than when awake, clearing out toxins twice as quickly.</p>
<p>This research took place in mice, but the researchers hypothesise that this same mechanism operates in humans, and <a href="https://www.urmc.rochester.edu/labs/nedergaard-lab/projects/glymphatic_system">are working on verifying that this is the case</a>.</p>
<p>Original article full text: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3880190/"><i>Sleep Drives Metabolite Clearance from the Adult Brain</i></a>, Xie et al., 2013, Science.</p>
<h2 id="this-is-the-end-my-friends">This is the end my friends</h2>
<p>Have a great week kids, and do remember to get your sleep!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>