<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>nerd on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/categories/nerd/</link><description>Recent content in nerd on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 21:49:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/categories/nerd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>New Emacs-capable hardware: M1 MacBook Air</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 21:49:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</guid><description><![CDATA[ You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I usually write a little something about it.
These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&rsquo;ve back-tagged most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient &ldquo;new computer&rdquo; tag list!
Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of the new Apple M1 chip and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I
usually write a little something about it.</p>
<p>These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&rsquo;ve back-tagged
most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient <a href="/tags/new-computer/">&ldquo;new computer&rdquo; tag
list</a>!</p>
<h2 id="fast-cheap-and-energy-efficient-choose-three">Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three</h2>
<p>This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of
the new <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple%5FM1">Apple M1 chip</a> and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great
performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.</p>








<figure><a href="m1-macbook-air-about.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_huf0cf78004650233083ccbdd28c330650_588664_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_huf0cf78004650233083ccbdd28c330650_588664_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_huf0cf78004650233083ccbdd28c330650_588664_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_huf0cf78004650233083ccbdd28c330650_588664_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;m still <em>quite</em> happy with the <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1 Extreme Gen1</a> as my main
workstation, but although classed as thin-and-light it <em>is</em> still a
workstation.</p>
<p>Specifically, due to the fact that it takes at least a minute or two to resume
from sleep, and the fact that its performance on battery is substantially
slower than on AC, it&rsquo;s not the sort of machine that you can flip open to work
on when inspiration strikes.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, it&rsquo;s a really effective lap warmer, and so gets
uncomfortable <em>quite</em> quickly.</p>
<p>In sharp contrast, the performance of this MacBook Air is the same, namely
&ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;, whether it&rsquo;s on AC or on battery, the laptop resumes from
standby faster that I&rsquo;m able to open the lid, and it hardly ever gets warm.</p>
<p>In short, I can bust this out of my bag and be typing on my lap in under 3
seconds, and this is something that has already started paying off in terms of
my writing.</p>
<h2 id="this-might-be-the-best-emacs-host-i-ve-ever-used">This might be the best Emacs-host I&rsquo;ve ever used</h2>
<p>This very post is currently being typed on <code>GNU Emacs 27.1.91 (build 1, arm-apple-darwin20.3.0, Carbon Version 164 AppKit 2022.3) of 2021-03-15</code> on the
device in question.</p>
<p>Have I mentioned &ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;?</p>
<p>By the way, if you build Emacs like this on the M1:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell">brew tap railwaycat/emacsmacport
brew install --formula emacs-mac --HEAD
</code></pre></div><p>&hellip; you should be good to go.</p>
<h3 id="update-on-2021-04-15">Update on 2021-04-15</h3>
<p>A few days ago, I started seeing the following error during homebrew Emacs update:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">./temacs --batch  -l loadup --temacs=pbootstrap
make[1]: *** [bootstrap-emacs.pdmp] Killed: 9
make: *** [src] Error 2
</code></pre></div><p>This looks similar to <a href="https://github.com/d12frosted/homebrew-emacs-plus/issues/292">this github issue on emacs-plus</a>, which was fixed on emacs
master.</p>
<p>It was easiest for me to switch to emacs-plus, which went like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell">brew uninstall emacs-mac
brew tap d12frosted/emacs-plus
brew install emacs-plus@28 --with-no-titlebar
</code></pre></div><h2 id="quo-vadis-one-device-to-rule-them-all">Quo vadis, one device to rule them all?</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s a pity that the ThinkPad, although powerful enough to satisfy <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#the-story-behind-this-story-one-context-to-rule-them-all">my single
computing device / single context requirement</a>, and with <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 becoming
increasingly useful</a> and hence addressing the dual-boot issue, does not satisfy
the <em>instantly available</em> requirement.</p>
<p>Fortunately the two devices cater for complementary contexts.</p>
<p>The Air is for instant-on writing, communication, admin and maybe a tiny bit of
development, whilst the ThinkPad is for all of the heavy lifting, but who knows
how these lines are going to be blurred in the coming months?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>meepx1e: I haz new laptop!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 14:02:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/</guid><description> WARNING: EXTREME PC hardware-related nerdiness ahead. Read at your own risk.
Just the new laptop, skulking in the bush. It is tradition around these parts that the welcoming of new computer machines is celebrated by, amongst many other rituals, a sometimes incomprehensible amount of customisation-related labour and a mention (or two) in these pages.
Some examples from the past include:
Hacking Radeon suspend / resume support into the Linux kernel and the X-Server in 2002, so that my cheap clone laptop could too.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>WARNING: <strong>EXTREME</strong> PC hardware-related nerdiness ahead. Read at your own risk.</em></p>
<figure>
<a href="x1_skulking_in_bush.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hucc4f1dd7c04ce38f9433032922073901_1607520_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hucc4f1dd7c04ce38f9433032922073901_1607520_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hucc4f1dd7c04ce38f9433032922073901_1607520_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hucc4f1dd7c04ce38f9433032922073901_1607520_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hucc4f1dd7c04ce38f9433032922073901_1607520_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>Just the new laptop, skulking in the bush.
</figure>
<p>It is tradition around these parts that the welcoming of new computer machines
is celebrated by, amongst many other rituals, a sometimes incomprehensible
amount of customisation-related labour and a mention (or two) in these pages.</p>
<p>Some examples from the past include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2002/07/26/whoohooo-xfree86-dri-hacked-to-suspendresume/">Hacking Radeon suspend / resume support into the Linux kernel and the
X-Server in 2002</a>,
so that my cheap clone laptop could too.</li>
<li><a href="/2004/05/26/laptop-no-2/">Acquiring my first name-brand laptop (HP NC6000) in
2004</a>, with a whole gigabyte of RAM.</li>
<li><a href="/2006/07/22/new-new-laptop-laptop/">My first dual-core laptop in 2006</a>.</li>
<li><a href="/2007/04/10/a-critical-look-at-ubuntu-feisty-beta-on-an-hp-nc8430-laptop/">Reviewing Ubuntu Feisty on above-mentioned
laptop</a>
led to, as far as I can remember, my first really popular post, with about
50k visitors in a few days.</li>
<li>Relatively low-key announcements during my macOS phase, starting with the <a href="/2015/06/14/weekly-head-voices-91-theyre-back/">2015
MacBook Pro</a> and then later
the <a href="/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/">2017 MacBook Pro</a> on my birthday in
2017.</li>
</ul>
<p>Well folks, this post exists because on Tuesday, April 17, 2019 I became the
new owner of a Lenovo ThinkPad X1 Extreme.</p>
<p>This new device, just like all the previous ones, took up a considerable amount
of mental cycles before, during and after its acquisition.</p>
<p>This does make sense: It&rsquo;s the technical artefact I use for a large part of the
day to interface with and shape the universe around me. This shaping is how I
try to create value, so the main physical tool I used for this should be as
sharp as possible.</p>
<h1 id="so-tell-me-why-did-your-somewhat-stylish-macbook-phase-have-to-come-to-an-end">So, tell me, why did your somewhat stylish MacBook phase have to come to an end?</h1>
<p>It seems like <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/#new-laptop">just the other day when my mysterous employer bought me that
shiny 2017 top-of-the-line(ish) MacBook
Pro</a>.</p>
<p>They grow up so fast!</p>
<p>&hellip; at which point they summarily have to be replaced by a slightly different
and hopefully more effective new thing.</p>
<p>The virtual machines I have to use for some of my projects caused the <a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/SP756?locale=en_US">16GB
2.9GHz 2017 MacBook Pro</a> to
grind to a halt once too often.</p>
<p>I evaluated upgrading to the <a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/SP776?locale=en_US">2018 model with 32GB RAM and the 8th generation
i7</a>, but the disappointing
keyboards on the current MacBook Pro range made it even trickier than usual to
justify the substantial price of the upgrade.</p>
<p>The MacBooks are stellar machines, but only if you can look past the keyboard.</p>
<p>To add to that, after five years of macOS, it was time to check that I was
still able to work just as efficiently with The Other desktop operating
systems.</p>
<h1 id="why-did-you-decide-to-get-the-thinkpad-x1-extreme">Why did you decide to get the ThinkPad X1 Extreme?</h1>
<p>When you go searching for laptop workstations that are in the same class as the
15&quot; MacBook Pros, one of the main candidates is the <a href="https://www.lenovo.com/za/en/laptops/thinkpad/x-series/ThinkPad-X1-Extreme/p/22TP2TXX1E1">ThinkPad X1
Extreme</a>,
which, to my delight, was straight-forward to obtain from my favourite local
supplier!</p>
<figure>
<a href="x1e_180.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hua94385e7b7a7f2b00c868afbf8f5c2ba_1021475_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hua94385e7b7a7f2b00c868afbf8f5c2ba_1021475_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hua94385e7b7a7f2b00c868afbf8f5c2ba_1021475_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hua94385e7b7a7f2b00c868afbf8f5c2ba_1021475_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hua94385e7b7a7f2b00c868afbf8f5c2ba_1021475_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>Can your workstation do this? (The keyboard is definitely an
improvement. I'm reserving judgement until a few months in. I'm still getting
used to that red mouse nub. In theory, this should be ideal for mostly keyboard
use with Emacs for example.) </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>(Interestingly, the price down here in ZAR is better than the dollar price on
Amazon directly converted to ZAR. This is usually the other way round.)</p>
<p>I made a deliberate choice for the version with the FullHD screen, and <em>not</em>
the 4k multi-touch panel.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WHAT? ARE WE BACK IN THE 1990s?!!&rdquo; you might ask, tapping away on your
high-resolution touch device with its beautiful screen and superb battery life.</p>
<p>During the 1.5+ years of using the 15&quot; MacBook Pro, with one of the most
beautiful screens in the business, I very rarely used that screen. Furthermore,
when mobile, the significantly longer battery life of the FHD version, along
with the slightly reduced weight, are more important.</p>
<p>Along with the 6-core 8750H i7 CPU, 16GB of RAM and 512GB of SSD ThinkPad, I
ordered an additional 1TB Samsung EVO Plus 970 NVMe SSD and an additional 16GB
RAM module.</p>
<p>One simply unscrews the bottom panel to reveal two accessible DIMM slots, and
two accessible M.2 SSD slots. I added the extra drive and extra RAM, put the
panel back, and booted up to a pretty sweet upgrade.</p>
<p>(Both drives are in the gigabytes per second read and write class. The built-in
WDC PC SN720 SDAQNTW-512G-1001 is only slightly slower than the Samsung 970.)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s good to know that I will be able to upgrade the RAM to 64GB, and the
storage to multiple terabytes of SSD, should that become necessary, or should I
be able to fabricate some or other good reason for this in the future.</p>
<h2 id="pro-tip-beware-duplicate-volume-ids-when-you-clone-a-drive">Pro-tip: Beware duplicate volume IDs when you clone a drive.</h2>
<p>I used the free <a href="https://www.samsung.com/semiconductor/minisite/ssd/download/tools/">Samsung Drive Migration Software for Consumer SSD
tool</a> to
image the factory-install of Windows to the new 1TB Samsung SSD.</p>
<p>After this, I simply changed the boot order in the BIOS (which also swaps C:
and D:, oh Windows!, and Bob was my uncle.</p>
<p>OR WAS HE?!</p>
<p>Only later when diagnosing why the Windows indexer was not picking up any new
files from my drive, did I figure out that the duplicate volume IDs on the
drives was confusing it.</p>
<p>Even later, after I had almost forgotten about the volume IDs, I had huge fun
fighting with the Windows boot loader simply giving up after an Ubuntu install.</p>
<p>You won&rsquo;t guess what the issue was, or will you?</p>
<h1 id="what-are-your-first-impressions">What are your first impressions?</h1>
<p>Although it feels lighter than the MBP, the laptop is thicker and slightly
bigger than the MBP. Due to the shape of the chassis, and especially the
ventilation rib on the bottom, it feels good in the hand.</p>
<p>The fans do come on quite easily in Windows, which can be disturbing. There are
fortunately a number of configuration options to ameliorate this issue.</p>
<p>The Linux support for this laptop is quite good. After a few hours of Manjaro
(I&rsquo;ve always wanted to see what an Arch-derivative was like), I installed
Ubuntu 19.04.</p>
<p>With minimal tuning, I can get the idle power consumption (with Emacs running
of course) down to about 7W.</p>
<p>This would in theory give me 10 hours of staring at Emacs, which is epic.</p>
<p>(Shortly after getting the laptop, I had to invest a not inconsiderable number
of hours into fine-tuning my Emacs configuration for Windows. Although Emacs on
Linux is still the ultimate experience, Emacs on Windows comes close
enough. For now.)</p>
<p>Probably due to the reduced weight and due to the laptop being able to keep
itself cool much more easily, the laptop fares significantly better than the
15&quot; MacBook Pro in the official Working in Bed and also Flipping Out Your
Laptop To Do Something Real Quick tests.</p>
<p>Other than that, features like the way the BIOS unlocks both hardware-encrypted
SSDs at boot using my fingerprint, are really quite neat.</p>
<h1 id="do-you-have-anything-else-to-say">Do you have anything else to say?</h1>
<p>No.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>(more) music for programming</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/19/more-music-for-programming/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 12:38:44 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/19/more-music-for-programming/</guid><description> Currently listening to Chris Sneddon’s mix on musicForProgramming();
For this last hour it has been exactly the right levels of everything to drown out distractions from my surroundings whilst not acting as a distraction in itself.
(Yes, I’m doing small status updates here now. It’s an experiment.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Currently listening to <a href="http://datashat.net/music_for_programming_32-chris_seddon.mp3">Chris Sneddon’s mix</a> on <a href="http://musicforprogramming.net/">musicForProgramming();</a></p>
<p>For this last hour it has been exactly the right levels of everything to drown out distractions from my surroundings whilst not acting as a distraction in itself.</p>
<p>(Yes, I’m doing small status updates here now. It’s an experiment.)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>meepz97: I haz a new computar machine!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2015 07:36:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/</guid><description> WARNING: EXTREME PC hardware-related nerdiness ahead. Read at your own risk.
My most awesome employer to date (that’s the vxlabs of course!) decided to treat me with a brand new workstation. On Tuesday, February 10 of the year 2015 the new desktop PC arrived. (Around these parts, we have a long tradition of writing about new computer acquisitions, see for example 2002, 2004, 2006, 2008, 2009, 2010, 2011 or 2013.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>WARNING: <strong>EXTREME</strong> PC hardware-related nerdiness ahead. Read at your own risk.</em></p>
<p>My most awesome employer to date (that’s <a href="http://www.vxlabs.com/">the vxlabs</a> of course!) decided to treat me with a brand new workstation. On Tuesday, February 10 of the year 2015 the new desktop PC arrived. (Around these parts, we have a long tradition of writing about new computer acquisitions, see for example <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2002/07/17/toe-matj-toe-sei-not-enaf-taim/">2002</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2004/05/26/laptop-no-2/">2004</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2006/07/22/new-new-laptop-laptop/">2006</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/07/15/pleasure-apparatus-2008/">2008</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/">2009</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/">2010</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/">2011</a> or <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2013/03/24/acer-v3-571g-fullhd-ips-superb-priceperformance-linux-development-laptop/">2013</a>.)</p>
<p>Because this event has sparked quite some interest amongst the various groups reading this blog, management has decided to present workstation-related information in a Q and A format.</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/wpid-meepz97_exposed.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/wpid-meepz97_exposed.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="say-what-a-desktop-pc-and-not-a-laptop">Say what?! A desktop PC and not a laptop??!</h2>
<p>Yes people, it’s an actual desktop PC, not a laptop. They’re big boxy things that eat laptops for breakfast and they really appeal to old-school nerds like me. Plus, when I go to work at the coffee shop around the corner with a ginormous black midtower PC under my arm instead of some far-too-easy-to-carry mac laptop, the other hipsters have no choice but to concede that <i>I</i> am their new king.</p>
<p>(Beautiful and thin laptops have become completely mainstream. Even that erstwhile PC-toting bro with his suit supply suit and his excel spreadsheets and his outlook email now has one. Hehe.)</p>
<h2 id="what-exactly-do-you-have-in-that-big-black-box">What exactly do you have in that big black box?</h2>
<p>I’m so happy you asked. Sensitive readers might want to look away, because this is going to get fairly graphical. I hand-picked all components from the limited set available to us this far south on the African continent. This is what I came up with:</p>
<ul>
<li>One hundred and twenty rainbows.</li>
<li>Fifty growth-hormone boosted angry unicorns, with twenty spares.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.technologyx.com/featured/gigabyte-ga-z97-d3h-motherboard-review/">Gigabyte Z97-D3H motherboard</a> (Intel LAN, Realtek ALC1150 audio)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.guru3d.com/articles-pages/core-i7-4790-processor-review,1.html">Intel Core i7 4790</a></li>
<li>16 JIJABYTES of Corsair DDR3 RAM</li>
<li><a href="http://www.guru3d.com/articles-pages/gigabyte-geforce-gtx-750-ti-windforce-review,1.html">Gigabyte GeForce GTX750Ti Windforce</a> graphics</li>
<li><a href="http://www.techradar.com/reviews/pc-mac/pc-components/storage/disk-drives-hdd-ssd/samsung-850-pro-512gb-1255900/review">Samsung 850 PRO 512GB SSD</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.guru3d.com/articles-pages/cooler-master-cm-690-iii-review,1.html">Cooler Master 690 iii chassis</a> with 550W Cooler Master Vanguard power supply</li>
<li>More rainbows.</li>
</ul>
<p>As nerdiness-fuelled retail fixes go, this rated 23 on a scale of 1 to 10, with 10 being multiple head asplosions. Even now, multiple days later, when I look sideways at the beautiful black box, my knees turn into jelly and I blush a little bit.</p>
<h2 id="what-operating-system-have-you-installed-on-this-machine">What operating system have you installed on this machine?</h2>
<p>Emacs and Linux, software of the gods.</p>
<p>(By the way, if you run into kernel GPFs in <code>__slab_alloc</code> with this hardware, remember to add <code>intremap=no_x2apic_optout</code> to the kernel boot parameters. It seems the BIOS is being naughty and reporting that it does not have x2apic when it in fact does.)</p>
<h2 id="how-fast-is-the-samsung-850-pro-ssd">How fast is the Samsung 850 PRO SSD?</h2>
<p>This SSD is STUPID FAST, there is just no other way to describe it.</p>
<p>Anandtech <a href="http://www.anandtech.com/show/8216/samsung-ssd-850-pro-128gb-256gb-1tb-review-enter-the-3d-era/13">has this to say about the drive</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To be honest, there is not a single thing missing in the 850 Pro because
regardless of the angle you look at the drive from, it will still top the
charts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(My employer is still smarting a little bit from the cost angle however. I’ll work extra hard to compensate.)</p>
<h2 id="are-you-disappointed-that-having-to-encrypt-the-ssd-will-slow-it-down">Are you disappointed that having to encrypt the SSD will slow it down?</h2>
<p>Fortunately, this drive also has hardware-based full disc encryption built right in. A further major improvement over my previously favourite drives which also have hardware support for encryption, the Intel 520 SSDs, is that the Samsung 850 PRO supports the TCG Opal 2.0 standard for the configuration and unlocking of the drive encryption.</p>
<p>In short, all data that touches the drive is transparently encrypted, at over 500 megabytes / second (!!). When the PC boots up, it asks me for my decryption password. If I get it right, the drive unlocks itself; if I don’t it does not. If anyone (I’m not paranoid, they really ARE out to get me!) gets access to my PC by whichever means, they will most probably not be able see one bit of my or my client’s data.</p>
<p>If you’re interested, you can find much more detail about how this works, and I how I configured it using open source tools, in <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2015/02/11/use-the-hardware-based-full-disk-encryption-your-tcg-opal-ssd-with-msed/">this other post I wrote over at vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<h2 id="are-you-happy-now">Are you happy now?</h2>
<p>Yes.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Dear USA, my data has left your building.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2013 18:02:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/</guid><description> NSA, GCHQ, Prism, FISA, Project Bullrun, Sigint.
After Edward Snowden, former CIA and NSA employee, started revealing how massively, intensely and easily we are all being spied upon by the intelligence agencies of various governments, the terms above have suddenly been spending a great deal more time in the media. Image by BLOGGING via TYPEWRITER
It turns out that government agencies are allowed to extract, at a whim, your and my data from service providers, such as Google, Microsoft and Yahoo.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>NSA, GCHQ, Prism, FISA, Project Bullrun, Sigint.</p>
<p>After <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden" title="Edward Snowden wikipedia page">Edward Snowden</a>, former CIA and NSA employee, started revealing how massively, intensely and <em>easily</em> we are all being spied upon by the intelligence agencies of various governments, the terms above have suddenly been spending a great deal more time in the media.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/tumblr_mp3xgwYLsi1qz82gvo1_1280.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/tumblr_mp3xgwYLsi1qz82gvo1_1280.jpg"
        
            alt="Image by BLOGGING via TYPEWRITER"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Image by BLOGGING via TYPEWRITER</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>It turns out that government agencies are allowed to extract, at a whim, your and my data from service providers, such as Google, Microsoft and Yahoo. There is no real legal process (unless you can call a secret judge in a secret court giving a secret order a real legal process), <em>especially</em> if you’re not a US citizen, and the providers that have been forced to give up your data in this way are not allowed to notify you about your digital self being violated. So even if they <em>say</em> that you shouldn’t worry, <em>you can never be entirely sure</em>.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it has also been revealed that the NSA has for years being acquiring encryption keys via legal (secretly forcing companies to give them the keys) and extra-legal (simply hacking into company servers) means. Even worse, they have for years been deliberately introducing security weaknesses into software products and encryption software in order to be able to crack open your data even more easily.</p>
<p>You can read more about this state of affairs in <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/the-nsa-files" title="The Guardian NSA files">The Guardian’s NSA files</a>. The Guardian has been doing a sterling job of analysing and bringing to light the depths to which our governments have sunk. There’s a whole lot of information, and most of it is quite upsetting.</p>
<p>For me the final straw was when secure email service <a href="http://lavabit.com/" title="lavabit website with close-down message">lavabit</a> voluntarily shut itself down, when faced with the prospect of being forced to leak user information to the US government without being allowed to tell anyone. The message on the site is quite chilling, and concludes with the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This experience has taught me one very important lesson: without congressional action or a strong judicial precedent, I would <em>strongly</em> recommend against anyone trusting their private data to a company with physical ties to the United States.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At this point, I was a super happy and pretty heavy user of a number of US-based services, including GMail (all my email, about 40000 conversations consisting of 60000 mails, that’s excluding my work email which I also hosted on GMail), Google+ Photos (all my photos, about 21000 of ’em), Google Drive, Dropbox (50G of data spread out over 120000 files). <em>In all cases, I still consider these to be best of class services.</em> In putting my money where my mouth is, I was paying both Google and Dropbox for extra storage.</p>
<p>I also had no problem with Google filtering through my email to show me targeted advertising. This is the deal I had with them. I also had no problem with the possibility of someone getting my data after due legal process. However, the idea that some NSA or other government agency flunky could quite easily stick their grubby paws into my data, and that I would never know about this, was too much.</p>
<p>There’s probably nothing much of interest in my data. However, it has become a matter of principle; Privacy is a basic human right. <a href="http://www.wired.com/politics/security/commentary/securitymatters/2006/05/70886" title="value of privacy by Bruce Schneier">Here’s an old essay by Bruce Schneier</a> if you need to read more about why privacy is so important.</p>
<p>In short: <strong>It was time to extricate all of my lovely data from probably well-meaning US companies, thanks to the ridiculously powerful and secretive NSA, and thanks to all of its shadowy counterparts around the world.</strong></p>
<p>Here’s how I did it:</p>
<ul>
<li>Considered building another low-cost Linux server, or even a Raspberry Pi. Decided against this due to time required for configuration and acquired a Synology DS213j NAS, which is at this moment standing on the desk about 1 metre to my left. My recommendation: Just get this, you won’t be sorry.</li>
<li>Downloaded 60000 emails to Synology using Thunderbird mail client. Deleted everything from GMail. Google engineers assure me that after a few months, data will <em>really</em> be gone.</li>
<li>My webhoster (<a href="https://www.webfaction.com/">WebFaction</a>) receives mail for all my domains. My Synology retrieves mail every 5 minutes via POP (you can set this up via Roundcube on the Synology) and deletes it from WebFaction.</li>
<li>Outgoing mail is relayed by the Synology via the WebFaction SMTP server. I don’t have to worry too much about blacklisting and whatnot, my hoster does this.</li>
<li>I’m back to interacting with my mail using Thunderbird and IMAP SSL. The loss of GMail conversation view was initially really REALLY painful. People have forgotten the ancient art of quoting. However, I’ve configured Thunderbird to archive all mail to year-stamped archive folders, and to put my sent mail there. Poor-man’s Conversation View! (the <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-us/thunderbird/addon/gmail-conversation-view/">conversations plugin</a> is wonky. it’s shocking how much the availability of GMail, which works really well, has stunted the development of alternative email clients) Importantly, I am now able to use <a href="http://www.openpgp.org/">OpenPGP</a> again for the strong encryption and cryptographic signing of my emails.</li>
<li>On my Android telephone (whoops…) I am using <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.kaitenmail&amp;hl=en" title="Kaiten email on the Google Play store">the Kaiten IMAP client</a>.</li>
<li>All the data I had in Dropbox is now being synced between the Synology, two laptops and a workstation using <a href="http://labs.bittorrent.com/experiments/sync.html" title="bittorrent sync">BitTorrent Sync</a>. This peer-to-peer syncing system is still a little rough around the edges, but falls squarely in the category of “Best Things Since Sliced Bread”, and it’s <em>FAST</em>. CloudStation, Synology’s dropbox-inspired solution, was just far too slow on my Synology model.</li>
<li>My photos (21000 of them) have been downloaded from Google+ Photos (thank you <a href="https://www.google.com/takeout/" title="Google Takeout">Google Takeout</a>) and are now being served from the Synology using PhotoStation.</li>
<li>My music (5400+ tracks) is downloading from Google Music as we speak, and will be served from the Synology using AudioStation.</li>
<li>I make incremental backups of everything to an encrypted external USB drive, using <a href="http://www.dirvish.org/" title="dirvish website">dirvish</a>. I will probably add an extra external drive to the mix and try to keep that off site.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s been an interesting process moving my stuff out, and getting used to these alternative systems is sometimes slightly uncomfortable, but I am quite happy with the end result. I hope that more people will take this step, and I really hope that more and easier-to-use alternatives for secure email (such as <a href="http://www.mailpile.is/" title="mailpile website">mailpile</a>) and for ubiquitous private data will become available.</p>
<h1 id="addendum-2013-09-16">Addendum 2013-09-16</h1>
<p>My <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=6392322">submission of this post</a> spent some time on the Hacker News front page, and from there was <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/technology/comments/1mhpqj/dear_usa_my_data_has_left_your_building/">picked up by reddit</a> as well. This brought many comments, a number of which were positive and thoughtful, and a number of which that were far less so. It’s amazing how anonymity and comment sections can bring out the worst in people. (if you have to know, the Hacker News community is generally MILES more polite than reddit)</p>
<p>In any case, I wanted to clarify an issue or two: After moving my data away from GMail and Dropbox, I am not under any impression that my data is now secure. I can still be hacked. My hardware and software could be full of backdoors. My email will still be read as it jumps from server to server, probably ending up in someone else’s GMail. :) However, if more people were to move their data out to their own premises, it becomes more complicated and costly for government agencies to monitor us all. At the moment, the NSA cuts deals with a few large email and other cloud service providers, and with that they’re able to monitor large swathes of users. However, if more of those users were to move away, many more deals have to be cut and servers hacked, costing more time and more money. Add to that increased used of OpenPGP (which I do use, and mention in my post), and it becomes even more difficult. I know that I’m just a drop in a bucket, but hey, at least I am a drop in a bucket!</p>
<p>My goal with posting this was to show that it’s relatively easy to move much of your data away. I have the feeling that many of the most impolite anonymous commenters still store their data with cloud providers, and would really prefer to believe that there are no worthwhile alternatives, hence all the ad hominem attacks.</p>
<p>Fortunately, each polite and humane comment makes up for a whole pile of bad ones. :)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Nerd-alert: Ubuntu Linux 12.04 on my NVIDIA Optimus Samsung NP300V3A laptop</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/05/02/nerd-alert-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-my-nvidia-optimus-samsung-np300v3a-laptop/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 08:01:14 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/05/02/nerd-alert-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-my-nvidia-optimus-samsung-np300v3a-laptop/</guid><description> When I acquired my pre-ultrabook-era but still pretty Samsung NP300V3A laptop some nine months ago, I lamented that I’d probably never be able to put Linux on there due to the NVIDIA Optimus graphics switching thingamagoo.
Well, yesterday I ate my hat.
If you have nerdy tendencies, head on over to VXLabs, my nerd blog, to read all about it.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>When I acquired my pre-ultrabook-era but still pretty <a href="/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/" title="samsung np300v3a welcome post">Samsung NP300V3A laptop some nine months ago</a>, I lamented that I’d probably never be able to put Linux on there due to the NVIDIA Optimus graphics switching thingamagoo.</p>
<p>Well, yesterday I ate my hat.</p>
<p>If you have nerdy tendencies, head on over to VXLabs, my nerd blog, to <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2012/05/01/review-of-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-the-samsung-np300v3a-core-i5-nvidia-optimus-laptop/" title="ubuntu 12.04 on Samsung NP300V3A post on VXLabs">read all about it</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>You have beautiful ize. [Weekly Head Voices #62]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/19/you-have-beautiful-ize-weekly-head-voices-62/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2011 21:29:09 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/11/19/you-have-beautiful-ize-weekly-head-voices-62/</guid><description> I completely lack the genes that usually cause human males to have a thing for cars, but I do love Top Gear. This trailer for a fictional 60s detective show, made by Jeremy Clarkson, James May and Richard Hammond, encapsulates many of the reasons why:
Moustaches, guns, girls, cars and Hammond karate-chopping the porter at Playboy Club London for absolutely no reason whatsoever at 41 seconds can be nothing but 100% pure AWESOME.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I completely lack the genes that usually cause human males to have a thing for cars, but I do love Top Gear. This trailer for a fictional 60s detective show, made by Jeremy Clarkson, James May and Richard Hammond, encapsulates many of the reasons why:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qLp4FhDAfQk?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Moustaches, guns, girls, cars and Hammond karate-chopping the porter at Playboy Club London for absolutely no reason whatsoever at 41 seconds can be nothing but 100% pure AWESOME.</p>
<p>It’s crazily busy at the moment, for a large part due to the extra load of having to teach and revamp, AT THE SAME TIME, the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4086" title="TU Delt DataVis course">TU Delft’s postgraduate Data Visualization course</a>. I’ve chucked out the written exam and the structured lab work, and exchanged it for paper reading, class discussion and four independent projects, inspired by positive experience with my <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4307" title="TU Delft postgraduate MedVis course">Medical Visualization Ninja Training Course</a> (third year in the running, Ninjas all over the place!), the <a href="/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/" title="infovis in stellenbosch">postgraduate InfoVis course I gave at Stellenbosch</a> and of course the teaching materials of esteemed colleagues at UBC, Harvard, Berkeley and Stanford. With a bit of luck, we will soon deliver a whole class of new-style DataVis Ninjas.</p>
<p>At a recent conference, I ran into an erudite half-British colleague from the far North, who in a few minutes almost managed to turn my world into rubble. You see, I’ve always proudly promoted the use of the -ise forms of certain words, such as visualise, realise, colonise and so forth, these being examples of British English. (Obviously, I adapt when American English is required.)</p>
<p>It turns out that, as is the case with life in general, it’s unfortunately not as simple as that.</p>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_and_British_English_spelling_differences#-ise.2C_-ize_.28-isation.2C_-ization.29" title="wikipedia article on britsh vs english spelling">It turns out</a> that many of the -ise words are originally from the Greek or the Latin with “-ize” endings, and therefore the Oxford spelling prefers their use, although it accepts the “-ise” forms as well. On the other hand, the Cambridge University Press, as well as the mainstream media and most of the public in Britain and the former colonies, has a strong preference for the “-ise” forms. Certain other words like for example advertise, advise and surprise always take the “-ise” form in British English.</p>
<p>So now I’m faced with this conundrum. It would otherwise not have been such an issue, but the words “visualise” and “visualisation” come up quite often during my work day. Sticking to “-ise” is easier and still correct when in British English mode, but “-ize” for those few words of Greek  and Latin origin could perhaps be considered more correct, and has the great advantage of allowing me to standardise on “visualize” as the canonical form of that important term. However, then I would run the risk of confusing the “-ize” and the true “-ise” words in Oxford English, potentially leading to painful embarrassment at the many cocktail parties that I frequent.</p>
<p>So you see, the Universe is just full of mysteries. Another mystery that has plagued humankind for decades, is what would happen if Stephen Hawking and Albert Einstein got involved in a rap battle. Well humankind, wonder no more:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/zn7-fVtT16k?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Ok kids, thank you for tuning in again. Have a great week, I hope to see you again soon!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>New Samsung NP300V3A laptop is welcomed into the family!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2011 11:03:53 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/</guid><description> It’s traditional around these parts that I write a post whenever I get to welcome a new computer into the family. In July of 2002 it was Dr. Evil, more a brick than a laptop, in May of 2004 it was my beloved 14″ HP NC6000 laptop, in July of 2006 I met my 15.4″ HP NC8430 (employer-supplied, thank you employer!), which in turn led to this Ubuntu-critical blog post of mine that attracted 50000 (yes, fifty thousand) readers over 2 days, in July of 2008 I splurged on a lovely quad core desktop machine, in September of 2009 I acquired an Asus 1005HA-H netbook, and in November of 2010 my employer got me a super-strong Dell Latitude E6410 laptop.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>It’s traditional around these parts that I write a post whenever I get to welcome a new computer into the family. In <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2002/07/17/toe-matj-toe-sei-not-enaf-taim/" title="dr evil laptop">July of 2002 it was Dr. Evil</a>, more a brick than a laptop, in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2004/05/26/laptop-no-2/" title="NC6000 post">May of 2004 it was my beloved 14″ HP NC6000 laptop</a>, in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2006/07/22/new-new-laptop-laptop/" title="nc8430 post">July of 2006 I met my 15.4″ HP NC8430</a> (employer-supplied, thank you employer!), which in turn led to <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2007/04/10/a-critical-look-at-ubuntu-feisty-beta-on-an-hp-nc8430-laptop/" title="15 seconds of blog fame">this Ubuntu-critical blog post of mine</a> that attracted 50000 (yes, fifty thousand) readers over 2 days, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/07/15/pleasure-apparatus-2008/" title="bees blog post">in July of 2008 I splurged on a lovely quad core desktop machine</a>, in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/" title="asus 1005HA-H netbook">September of 2009 I acquired an Asus 1005HA-H netbook</a>, and in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/" title="dell e6410 post">November of 2010 my employer got me a super-strong Dell Latitude E6410 laptop</a>.</p>
<p>Today I welcomed the latest and probably prettiest laptop so far into the family:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/samsung_np300v3a.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/samsung_np300v3a.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty Samsung NP300V3A-S01NL laptop!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty Samsung NP300V3A-S01NL laptop!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Behold the <a href="http://tweakers.net/pricewatch/286118/samsung-np300v3a-s01nl.html" title="tweakers pricewatch page for the Samsung NP300V3A-S01NL">Samsung NP300V3A-S01NL (Series 3)</a>. It has an absolutely gorgeous-to-type-on chiclet keyboard, a 13.3″ matte (!) display, NVIDIA GT520m graphics with Optimus, second-gen Core i5 2410m, 4G RAM and 500G disc, all for a terribly reasonable price, which is important, as this one is not employer-bought. A man needs a laptop like this for his top-secret personal biznizz, yes?</p>
<p>It’s running Windows Home Premium, so I have to use Truecrypt instead of EFS for encrypting my biznizz, which is stored mostly in my Dropbox pro account. The battery life is quite impressive probably due in part to Optimus switching. The drawback of this is that I probably won’t be putting Linux on here anytime soon. These days you can use both the graphics adapters in Linux, but both of them stay active all the time, so it kills the battery really quickly.</p>
<p>We learn at least two more things from this post:</p>
<ol>
<li>I do seem to exhibit a certain obsessive compulsive behaviour when it comes to keeping track of the arrival dates of the various computers in my life.</li>
<li>When spring comes around, hide my credit card.</li>
</ol>
<p><em>Update on May 2, 2012:</em> I have just eaten my hat. Ubuntu Linux 12.04 with Bumblebee runs just wonderfully on this laptop. Read all about it in <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2012/05/01/review-of-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-the-samsung-np300v3a-core-i5-nvidia-optimus-laptop/" title="vxlabs blog post reviewing ubuntu 12.04 on the samsung np300v3a">my VXLabs blog post</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Schloss Dagstuhl: Computer Scientist Heaven</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/19/schloss-dagstuhl-computer-scientist-heaven/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2011 19:56:43 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/19/schloss-dagstuhl-computer-scientist-heaven/</guid><description> Somewhere in a remote but picturesque location in southern Germany, there’s a special castle called Schloss Dagstuhl. Every week, the castle fills up with a smallish group of Exceptionally Privileged Computer Scientists, who can only go there Because They Have Been Invited. Every week hosts a different field; In my case this was the Scientific Visualization seminar, one of the oldest participating groups. Everything has been setup just so to guarantee a perfect computer sciencey week for all guests.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Somewhere in a remote but picturesque location in southern Germany, there’s a special castle called Schloss Dagstuhl. Every week, the castle fills up with a smallish group of Exceptionally Privileged Computer Scientists, who can only go there Because They Have Been Invited. Every week hosts a different field; In my case this was the Scientific Visualization seminar, one of the oldest participating groups. Everything has been setup <em>just so</em> to guarantee a perfect computer sciencey week for all guests. Because I’ve already been boring too many people with this story in person, I thought it prudent to write it up. Let’s hope it’s not a first (and second!) rule of Fight Club situation, in which case posting frequency over here might drop <em>quite</em> drastically.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Dagstuhl_DSC02285.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Dagstuhl_DSC02285-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Schloss Dagstuhl, picture courtesy of Wikipedia."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Schloss Dagstuhl, picture courtesy of Wikipedia.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>To begin with, the meals are exquisite, three times a day, every day. As we all know, the path to a computer scientist’s heart is through buying them new gadgets, but feeding them well is a great backup plan. Another very nice touch is the fact that seating is deliberately randomised, meaning that your introvert self is forced to sit at the table with a different group of guests during each lunch and dinner, in turn meaning that even if you try otherwise, you will probably get to have a good conversation with every one of the fifty attendees.</p>
<p>In the case of our seminar, the working day consists of presentations in blocks of three or four, followed by a longer block of discussion on all the preceding presentations, panel style. Attendees were all asked not just to give a standard scientific presentation, but to discuss open problems and future challenges in their respective sub-fields. I (and many others, judging by the aggregated post-meeting feedback) really enjoyed this format. The presentations made one think, and the discussion blocks were long enough to really get into the details. You can check out abstracts and slides on <a href="http://www.dagstuhl.de/mat/index.en.phtml?11231" title="site with Dagstuhl SciVis 2011 materials">the seminar website</a>.</p>
<p>After a full day of quite intensive discussion, there were breakout sessions during which four subgroups started working on the various chapters of a new Springer book that should appear sometime early in next year. The book will deal with multi-field, uncertainty, biomedical and scalable visualization, and it has the makings of being a keeper.</p>
<p>The other extremely important magic bit about this castle is the abundance of real coffee machines (ones that grind coffee beans for every cup), snack corners and, uhm, beer fridges. You can’t really go anywhere, as you’re in the middle of nowhere, so after dinner the conversations tend to continue till late in the night, conversant stamina enhanced by said coffee and beer facilities. Evil science plans were made, good old-fashioned deep conversations were had and the early next morning consequences were flatly ignored. I haven’t laughed quite so much in a long time, but <em>that</em> part of the programme prefers, and has the right, to remain completely silent.</p>
<p>If you ever get <em>the</em> invitation, don’t hesitate for a second to accept: You shall return an exhausted but terribly happy computer nerd.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>I crushed the GSVideo problematic frame error!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/03/04/i-crushed-the-gsvideo-problematic-frame-error/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 20:44:27 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/03/04/i-crushed-the-gsvideo-problematic-frame-error/</guid><description> Nerd warning: This post really belongs on my nerd blog VXLabs.com, but as this blog has a rich tradition of popular [processing posts][2], I’m posting it here.
[][3]
[GSVideo][4] is a brilliant library that you can use in [processing][5] to capture live video, on Windows, Linux and OSX, and it’s a huge improvement over the built-in capturing support. Unfortunately, a number of us (including some of the 123 students we got to build augmented reality music instruments this September) have been running into a problematic frame error crash that meant captures didn’t last for very long before unceremoniously crashing the application.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Nerd warning: This post really belongs on my nerd blog <a href="http://vxlabs.com/" title="VXLabs.com, my favourite nerd blog!">VXLabs.com</a>, but as this blog has a rich tradition of popular [processing posts][2], I’m posting it here.</em></p>
<p>[<img alt="Debugging" height="180" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2676/4047355843_0fd2fa0036_m.jpg" width="240"/>][3]</p>
<p>[GSVideo][4] is a brilliant library that you can use in [processing][5] to capture live video, on Windows, Linux and OSX, and it’s a huge improvement over the built-in capturing support. Unfortunately, a number of us (including some of the 123 students we got to build augmented reality music instruments this September) have been running into a problematic frame error crash that meant captures didn’t last for very long before unceremoniously crashing the application. Error info and stack trace look something like the following (edited for brevity):</p>
<pre class="brush: plain; title: ; notranslate" title=""># A fatal error has been detected by the Java Runtime Environment:
#
#  EXCEPTION_ACCESS_VIOLATION (0xc0000005) at pc=0x7c342eee, pid=1564, tid=2052
#
# JRE version: 6.0_20-b02
# Java VM: Java HotSpot(TM) Client VM (16.3-b01 mixed mode windows-x86 )
# Problematic frame:
# C  [msvcr71.dll+0x2eee]
#
---------------  T H R E A D  ---------------

Current thread (0x18db7000):  JavaThread "Animation Thread" [_thread_in_native, id=2052, stack(0x1bfd0000,0x1c020000)]

Stack: [0x1bfd0000,0x1c020000],  sp=0x1c01f8a0,  free space=13e1c01f384k
Native frames: (J=compiled Java code, j=interpreted, Vv=VM code, C=native code)
C  [msvcr71.dll+0x2eee]
C  [java.dll+0x728d]
J  java.nio.Bits.copyToByteArray(JLjava/lang/Object;JJ)V
j  java.nio.DirectIntBufferU.get([III)Ljava/nio/IntBuffer;+126
j  java.nio.IntBuffer.get([I)Ljava/nio/IntBuffer;+5
j  codeanticode.gsvideo.GSCapture.read()V+24
j  CathetAR.draw()V+22
</pre>
<p>Read more about it on this [forum thread][6].</p>
<p>In any case, today I spent some hours I don’t really have and finally managed to crush it. Turns out, and some of you will probably not be surprised, that it was a threading problem. The capture event handler invokeEvent() and the read() call were being interleaved, and the buffer they were using is also not thread-safe. Doh. Some synchronization here and there, and an extra capture buffer, now I can’t get it to crash anymore.</p>
<p>Get the [patch here][7], and a [patched GSVideo.jar][8] here. Both of these are for the GSVideo 20110203 test version. If you can’t patch and build it yourself, just copy my GSVideo.jar over the GSVideo.jar in your unpacked GSVideo 20110203 plugin directory (sub-directory library). <strong>Update: See below, GSVideo 0.8 has been released and now contains my patch. Rather get the 0.8 download!</strong></p>
<p>Leave me a comment if this helps!</p>
<h3 id="update-on-2011-03-06">Update on 2011-03-06</h3>
<p>Andres Colubri, author of GSVideo, has refined and [integrated][9] my patch. The next GSVideo release (0.8 and newer) should have this fix.</p>
<h3 id="update-on-2011-03-15">Update on 2011-03-15</h3>
<p>Andres has just released GSVideo 0.8, which integrates my fix and many other improvements. Go read his [0.8 release post][10]!</p>
<p>[2]: /tag/processing/ &ldquo;All posts on this site tagged with &ldquo;processing&rdquo;.&rdquo;
[3]: <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/28208534@N07/4047355843/">http://www.flickr.com/photos/28208534@N07/4047355843/</a> &ldquo;Debugging by mikemol, on Flickr&rdquo;
[4]: <a href="http://gsvideo.sourceforge.net/">http://gsvideo.sourceforge.net/</a> &ldquo;GSVideo website&rdquo;
[5]: <a href="http://processing.org/">http://processing.org/</a> &ldquo;processing website&rdquo;
[6]: <a href="http://forum.processing.org/topic/gsvideo-0-6-crash-problem">http://forum.processing.org/topic/gsvideo-0-6-crash-problem</a> &ldquo;forum thread 1 concerning the problematic frame crash&rdquo;
[7]: <a href="http://cpbotha.net/files/gsvideo-20110203-patch-20110304/gsvideo-20110203-problematic-frame-fix-cpbotha.diff">http://cpbotha.net/files/gsvideo-20110203-patch-20110304/gsvideo-20110203-problematic-frame-fix-cpbotha.diff</a> &ldquo;gsvideo problematic frame fix&rdquo;
[8]: <a href="http://cpbotha.net/files/gsvideo-20110203-patch-20110304/GSVideo.jar">http://cpbotha.net/files/gsvideo-20110203-patch-20110304/GSVideo.jar</a> &ldquo;patched and built GSVideo.jar&rdquo;
[9]: <a href="http://gsvideo.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/gsvideo/trunk/src/codeanticode/gsvideo/GSCapture.java?r1=152&amp;r2=151&amp;pathrev=152">http://gsvideo.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/gsvideo/trunk/src/codeanticode/gsvideo/GSCapture.java?r1=152&amp;r2=151&amp;pathrev=152</a> &ldquo;gsvideo changeset integrating crash fix&rdquo;
[10]: <a href="http://codeanticode.wordpress.com/2011/03/15/gsvideo-0-8/">http://codeanticode.wordpress.com/2011/03/15/gsvideo-0-8/</a> &ldquo;gsvideo 0.8 release post&rdquo;</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>