<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>signal on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/signal/</link><description>Recent content in signal on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 13:44:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/signal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #217: Continuum of Consciousness</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 13:44:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Hey, welcome to the Monthly Weekly Head Voices!
This one covers the extensive period from Monday Feb 15 to Sunday March 21, 2021.
  Since we last connected here, much has transpired, a strangely selected subset of which is mentioned below:
New computer An M1 MacBook Air became part of my computing zoo. See the new computer post if you&rsquo;re into that sort of thing. Short version if you&rsquo;re not: It&rsquo;s the best Emacs-capable device I&rsquo;ve ever used.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hey, welcome to the Monthly Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This one covers the extensive period from Monday Feb 15 to Sunday March
21, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys_bay_somewhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu6ac4ad035e7b6786a81fd6c9089d46d3_1759942_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu6ac4ad035e7b6786a81fd6c9089d46d3_1759942_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu6ac4ad035e7b6786a81fd6c9089d46d3_1759942_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu6ac4ad035e7b6786a81fd6c9089d46d3_1759942_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu6ac4ad035e7b6786a81fd6c9089d46d3_1759942_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Since we last connected here, much has transpired, a strangely selected subset
of which is mentioned below:</p>
<h2 id="new-computer">New computer</h2>
<p>An M1 MacBook Air became part of my computing zoo. See <a href="/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/">the new computer post</a> if
you&rsquo;re into that sort of thing. Short version if you&rsquo;re not: It&rsquo;s the best
Emacs-capable device I&rsquo;ve ever used.</p>
<h2 id="pgp-i-m-not-dead-yet">PGP: I&rsquo;m not dead yet!</h2>
<p>In a pleasantly surprising turn of events, I found myself counter-signing PGP
encryption keys with different sets of friends.</p>
<p>In spite of my <a href="/2016/12/11/pgp-never-gonna-give-you-up/">PGP never gonna give you up post</a> of 2016, the thought that
old-fashioned PGP might soon disappear even from my archaic view, to be
replaced by more user-friendly and modern solutions such as <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">Signal</a>, has been on
my mind more often recently.</p>
<p>This would not be the worst turn of events. The more people are using secure
and private communication, the better.</p>
<p>However, it <strong>was</strong> fun doing our modest part to bolster the tiny and dwindling
group of humans who know how to use PGP and think that they still should.</p>
<p>All of that being said, we did also make use of the opportunity to perform
defensible <a href="https://support.signal.org/hc/en-us/articles/360007060632-What-is-a-safety-number-and-why-do-I-see-that-it-changed-">Signal safety number verification</a>.</p>
<h2 id="stone-three-healthcare-has-joined-back-up-with-the-rest-of-voltron">Stone Three Healthcare has joined back up with the rest of Voltron</h2>
<p>Back in July of 2019, I <a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">announced that Stone Three Healthcare had been
officially spun out from Stone Three Venture Technology</a>.</p>
<p>More recently, our corporate mothership embarked on a newly engineered (and
funded) scaling-up journey, bringing with it a host of opportunities for
positive impact on the world.</p>
<p>In the Healthcare company we had to make a choice between sticking it out as a
smaller startup on the one hand, or re-integrating into a newly-designed merged
organization and making use of the extended new capabilities to further our
vision.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m really trying to keep it real here, but the line between that and
corp-speak is like mono-filament!)</p>
<p>So, since this past week or so, I&rsquo;m working together with the new merged
entity.</p>
<p>My mandate is now broader in two ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll be focusing on technological solutions for precision Health <strong>and</strong>
Safety, where it was previously healthcare only.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ll be assisting all parts of the company by optimizing technological
processes of all sorts.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is all very exciting to me, and they&rsquo;re even letting me keep some of the
science in my new official title!</p>
<h2 id="the-strange-continuum-of-consciousness">The strange continuum of consciousness</h2>
<p>This is a tricky one to mention, because it probably needs much more space than
I have here, and much more skill than I have to explain.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to try in any case, because just maybe it sparks something for
someone.</p>
<p>A large part of the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up meditation</a> daily practice is exploring the exact
nature of one&rsquo;s experienced consciousness.</p>
<p>Specifically, there is the realisation that the whole of your consciousness,
including your thoughts, your interactions with real, live people, and
everything else, takes place in <strong>your</strong> mind.</p>
<p>Furthermore, <em>internal</em> sensations, like an itch, or pain, or a tingling on
your skin, and <em>external</em> sensations, like hearing or sight, although they seem
to be localised <em>inside</em> and <em>outside</em>, take place in the exact same
consciousness.</p>
<p>Everything that you experience, whether &ldquo;real&rdquo;, like looking at the sea, or
imaginary, like thinking about (and hence &ldquo;seeing&rdquo;) something that you need to
take care of tomorrow, or something that you experienced yesterday, are all
simulations that are running as part of your consciousness.</p>
<p>There is a continuum from internal to external, and a continuum from direct
sensory experience to remembered or predicted experience, along with all of its
thoughts and emotions.</p>
<p>These are all the same sort of signals coursing through the same neural
pathways.</p>
<p>Another core idea here is that although your brain is housed in your skull,
your feeling that your consciousness is somehow also localised behind your eyes
is not entirely apt.</p>
<p>Your consciousness is the <em>whole</em> space, with all of your observed reality in
it, <em>including</em> the illusion (or rather simulation) of your localisation.</p>
<p>You (the observer) are not at a single point, but rather everywhere where
consciousness is.</p>
<p>Everything that you perceive to happen, by definition &ldquo;happens&rdquo; in the space
that you call consciousness.</p>
<p>These are tricky lessons to learn, and it seems that at least in my case we are
destined to spend only fleeting moments together, but they have profound and
positive implications for how we go through life.</p>








<figure><a href="machineray2-668-16.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/machineray2-668-16_hu0bfd1bd6c135d93dbf77acde1766c220_1028475_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/machineray2-668-16.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: I used the neural network-based artwork generator, called MachineRay 2, by artist Robert A. Gonsalves to generate this piece. Read more in his blog post."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: I used the neural network-based artwork generator, called MachineRay 2, by artist Robert A. Gonsalves to generate this piece. Read more in <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/creating-abstract-art-with-stylegan2-ada-ea3676396ffb">his blog post</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #214: One Main Thing</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/</guid><description> WELCOME BACK EVERYONE TO THIS WARM AND WELCOMING CIRCLE OF WEEKLY HEAD VOICES!
Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded.
You are reading the 214th edition of the WHV, the first of 2021 (hurrah), and spottily covering the intersections of my consciousness with the period of time from Monday, January 11 to Sunday, January 24 of the year 2021.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>WELCOME BACK EVERYONE TO THIS WARM AND WELCOMING CIRCLE OF WEEKLY HEAD VOICES!</p>








<figure><a href="hermanus_coastal_walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You are reading the 214th edition of the WHV, the first of 2021 (hurrah), and
spottily covering the intersections of my consciousness with the period of time
from Monday, January 11 to Sunday, January 24 of the year 2021.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not entirely happy with the water-tightness of this coverage, but <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/">the
2020-2021 year transition post</a>, which I hope you&rsquo;ve read or at least heard
about, is probably worth this bit of start-point haziness.</p>
<h2 id="first-rule-of-blogging-we-don-t-blog-about-blogging">First rule of blogging: We don&rsquo;t blog about blogging</h2>
<p>As you know, <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">I <strong>really</strong> love Hugo</a>, the software tool with which I can write
these posts in Emacs (text editor, you heathens) and then convert them to the
fast static pages that you are now reading.</p>
<p>The one thing I <em>was</em> a bit disappointed with, was the lack of some form of
built-in yearly post archives.</p>
<p>Well, while writing the year transition post, this disappointment spiked into
action, and so I applied just enough internet and elbow grease to scratch my
yearly archive itch on this blog.</p>
<p><a href="/2021/01/10/super-simple-yearly-post-archives-hugo/">This post shows you how to do it</a>, and <a href="/archive/">here you can see the result, yearly
archives for all of the posts on this blog</a>!</p>
<p>As a first step on <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#comms-upgrade">my path to become better at asynchronous communication</a>, I
wrote <a href="/2021/01/16/intro-asynchronous-communication/">an introductory blog post on the topic</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not as happy with it as I would have liked to be, but it&rsquo;s the line in the
sand that I really wanted to draw.</p>
<p>More importantly, I&rsquo;ve been able to get a few people to read it.</p>
<h2 id="signal-i-told-you-so">Signal: I told you so</h2>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2021/01/whatsapp-users-must-share-their-data-with-facebook-or-stop-using-the-app/">WhatsApp recently making clear that they will be sharing increasing
amounts of the massive amounts of your data at their disposal with all other
companies in the Facebook family</a>, many folks have been looking for
alternatives.</p>
<p>Even more fortunately, many of those folks have been choosing the most
pragmatically private alternative, namely Signal.</p>
<p>You might recall that <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">I started recommending that we use Signal back in January
of 2016</a>, which is infinity years ago in internet time.</p>
<p>Telegram does indeed count as an alternative to WhatsApp, but its chats are by
default not end-to-end encrypted, and it&rsquo;s still backed by a for-profit
company. There&rsquo;s nothing wrong with this, but if your concern is privacy now
and in the future, Signal is by far the better choice.</p>
<p>Anyways, I am happy to see more of my contacts appear in the Signal list.</p>
<h2 id="one-main-thing">One Main Thing</h2>
<p>In 2011, <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#pro-tip-2">I wrote about starting the day by writing down concretely the tasks
one would like to complete by the end of the day</a>.</p>
<p>A few years later, <a href="/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/#thinking-of-future-you">I picked up a tip from a podcast with Sam Harris and Derren
Brown that one should explicitly ask the question which tasks would satisfy you
the most at the end of the day</a>.</p>
<p>(Interestingly, in the 2018 post above I misquoted my 2011 post as suggesting
that one writes down &ldquo;the two to three really important tasks for the
day&rdquo;. That &ldquo;two to three&rdquo; came from some other memory which I can&rsquo;t track down
right now.)</p>
<p>Last year <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#its-what-future-you-would-want-quote-edition">I ran into Lubbock&rsquo;s far more eloquent formulation</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If we are ever in doubt about what to do, it is a good rule to ask ourselves
what we shall wish on the morrow that we had done. &ndash; John Lubbock</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the comments to that post, friend AJ added the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Another iteration of what to do next that I recently heard was Gary Kellers
version: The One Thing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have not yet gotten around to reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%5FOne%5FThing%5F(book)">The One Thing</a>, but I think AJ&rsquo;s comment
did plant a seed&hellip;</p>
<p>Fast forward a few months, and I have started to realise that my most
productive and satisfying days often coincide with the days when I have the
guts in the morning to commit to one main thing for the day.</p>
<p>Conversely, when I don&rsquo;t select and commit to One Main Thing, but due to
deadlines and other expectations put more than two or more bigger items on my
list, that day has a high probability of leaving me quite frazzled by its end.</p>
<p>One Main Thing days are scary, because I feel like there is always a long list
of things I&rsquo;m not going to get to, and people I&rsquo;m going to have to disappoint.</p>
<p>However, selecting that One Main Thing wisely, explicitly committing to it, and
then knocking it off after a few hours of focus is undeniably satisfying, and
will probably help a bunch of people.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it turns out that even with this commitment, one does still manage
to get some of the little things done in the scraps of left-over time.</p>
<p>You know, just after lunch, just before dinner and so on.</p>
<p>Pay some bills, answer a few emails, and then dive back into your One Main
Thing.</p>
<h3 id="interstitial-projects">Interstitial projects</h3>
<p>In addition to this, it turns out some of my projects can be specifically
treated as <em>interstitial</em>.</p>
<p>This is the label I&rsquo;ve chosen for those projects that 1. are supported by
low-friction tools that are instantly available and 2. benefit from slivers of
thought.</p>
<p>For example, I&rsquo;m working on a few blog posts dealing with issues I come across
during my work.</p>
<p>During the day, I see something that warrants a section in one of the blog
posts&hellip;</p>
<p>Switch to Emacs, hotkey search the relevant notes file, hotkey search the
relevant section in that file, type the sentence or two in your head, switch
back to work.</p>
<p>That took all of a minute or two, but now there are two new sentences, and we
all know what sentences do, right? They <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a> into blog posts!</p>
<h2 id="do-you-want-to-produce-or-consume">Do you want to produce or consume?</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m technically not allowed to write about something that appeared after the
published timespan of a WHV, but I would be remiss if I did not mention the
nudge that got WHV #214 off the ground.</p>
<p>That nudge is <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/recommendations/">this post by Noeska</a>, and specifically these words:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Do I want to produce or consume?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You should really go read the post for context, but if you need to hear that
sentence, you&rsquo;ll probably understand exactly what it means.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #187: Checklists everywhere.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 19:15:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/</guid><description> Welcome back ANYONE WHO IS READING THIS!
Fiery sky in Betty's Bay. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about the situation in the Northern hemisphere, but down here in the South it seems as if just about everyone has disconnected for the Christmas period.
I decided that I would prefer at least trying to end the year with a few more-or-less on time WHVs, even if they have to slim down a bit to do so.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back ANYONE WHO IS READING THIS!</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Fiery sky in Betty's Bay.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure about the situation in the Northern hemisphere, but down here in
the South it seems as if just about everyone has disconnected for the Christmas
period.</p>
<p>I decided that I would prefer at least trying to end the year with a few
more-or-less on time WHVs, even if they have to slim down a bit to do so.</p>
<p>So here we are: Just you and me. Maybe just me.</p>
<p>This WHV looks back on the week from Monday December 16 to Sunday December 22, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="the-last-work-week-of-2019-partially-in-bullets">The last work-week of 2019, (partially) in bullets.</h2>
<p>For me this was the last <em>real</em> work week.</p>
<p>I did spend most of it working from places other than the office, which was
nice.</p>
<p>Other than that, I would like to mention the following noteworthy learnings and
events:</p>
<ul>
<li>Schlepping along my Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic Desktop keyboard (current
favourite) and mouse, as well as my collapsible laptop stand (to bring the
laptop screen up to eye height) made a huge positive difference to my
ergonomics. 12/10 would do again.</li>
<li>We had a gratifying 4 day turn-around from the report of a pretty
obscure and initially irreproducible bug, through analysis and debugging, to
a new Windows driver release.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/projectstorm/react-diagrams">react-diagrams</a> is an
amazing TypeScript library for putting together a boxes and lines frontends
to manipulate graph-based dataflow backends. However, the TypeScript class
hierarchies and lack of documentation complicate customisation, if that&rsquo;s
your goal. I had to throw out that work and start over, building everything
on React (<a href="https://reactjs.org/docs/hooks-intro.html">hooks</a> all the way
baby!) and little bits of d3 for the spliny bits.</li>
<li>In the same vein, <a href="https://github.com/tgdwyer/WebCola">Cola.js / WebCola</a> is
an impressive layout approach for graphs. The force-directed layout in d3 is
great for interactive demos, but sometimes you want something that, you know,
lays out the graph. See this <a href="https://js.cytoscape.org/demos/2ebdc40f1c2540de6cf0/">cytoscape
demo</a> for even more
fun.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="on-checklists">On checklists.</h2>
<p>During this last week, as I was fighting to maintain the last islands of focus
being relentlessly eroded by the persistent seas of vacation-temptation, I was
helped a great deal by micro-checklists.</p>
<p>I briefly debated calling them multi-scalar checklists, but they are really
just normal checklists, except applied to any duration of work or focus time.</p>
<p>In other words, given an hour in the evening to spend on research, I would
start the hour by quickly jotting down (in Emacs Orgmode of course) a checklist
of the 4 to 5 things I would like to get done in that hour.</p>
<p>It was surprising to me much that 5 minute time investment would return in the
subsequent 55.</p>
<p>The lesson that I am taking from this, is that <a href="http://localhost:1313/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">my daily planning
checklist</a>
is not enough.</p>
<p>The daily landscape itself, my energy levels and my interest change far too
much and too quickly for a single daily checklist.</p>
<p>When you only get a few hours here and there to work, this problem is even more acute.</p>
<p>I am still figuring out how exactly to cultivate this new habit of making a new
checklist before every block of work, multiple times per day.</p>
<p>(What exactly is a block of work? Practically, how can I delineate this during
the day?)</p>
<h2 id="on-disconnecting-for-recuperation">On disconnecting for recuperation.</h2>
<p>During this time of the year I&rsquo;m usually spending a number of mental cycles
debating how exactly to disconnect from The Network.</p>
<p>(See <a href="/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/#you-are-turning-into-a-cyborg">You are turning into a
cyborg</a>
from a 2014 Weekly Head Voices, for example.)</p>
<p>Even longer ago than that, I used to keep my work and personal email separate.</p>
<p>During vacations, I would temporarily remove the work account from all of my
devices so that I could only see the mostly social-related personal emails.</p>
<p>These days, work and personal networks seem to have become even more
intertwined all by themselves, complicating measures like the above.</p>
<p>When I re-joined the Exciting World of Business and Great Success in 2013, I
merged all of my email back into a single account, for better knowledge
management and especially retrieval.</p>
<p>Another more important and more current example of this is WhatsApp, which more
or less dominates all instant messaging and a great deal of general
communication down here.</p>
<p>Many people I know use WhatsApp for work.</p>
<p>However, most of them, probably like most of you, use a single phone with a
single SIM.</p>
<p>This means that they will probably see work-related messages and activities
during their vacation, traditionally, but now perhaps increasingly
anachronistically, a period of disconnection.</p>
<p>(By the way, see <a href="/2011/02/05/postmodern-creativity-weekly-head-voices-37/">me in 2011 recommending WhatsApp over
SMS</a> when WhatsApp
was still quite small, and see <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">me in 2016 recommending Signal over
WhatsApp</a>. Signal
is still the best choice by far if you value your privacy and security.)</p>
<p>Personally, it feels like my current adventure in the Exciting World of
Business and Great Success requires me to be available, just in
case. Therefore, I am planning only a very few days of &ldquo;offline&rdquo;, which is more
of a mental state than a technological setting.</p>
<p>Other than that, my colleagues are all really great about staying off the
emails and the WhatsApps, partly because they <em>are</em> really great (see above)
and partly because they are applying similar methods.</p>
<p>The only question that remains is, how much disconnection, and at which
intensity, does the disconnecting human require for optimal functioning?</p>
<p>Friends, whatever your level of disconnect, I wish you maximum rest.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #162: Converse with a stranger today.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/02/14/weekly-head-voices-162-converse-with-a-stranger-today/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 11:25:16 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/02/14/weekly-head-voices-162-converse-with-a-stranger-today/</guid><description> This edition of the WHV looks back at the week from Monday February 4 to Sunday February 10, 2019.
It feels like this post took even longer than usual to get “done”. I think it might have to do with me breaking it up into several early morning writing sessions, which resulted in two partially formed blog posts compressing themselves quite inelegantly into this edition.
I will try to do better next time.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/crab_on_strand_beach.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/crab_on_strand_beach-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the week from Monday February 4 to Sunday February 10, 2019.</p>
<p>It feels like this post took even longer than usual to get “done”. I think it might have to do with me breaking it up into several early morning writing sessions, which resulted in two partially formed blog posts compressing themselves quite inelegantly into this edition.</p>
<p>I will try to do better next time.</p>
<p>Anyways, the rest consists of a nerd part (which you could skip if you’re not interested in nerds or their things, but then you would miss the part where I explain why you should be using Signal instead of WhatsApp), followed by a story about conversations with strangers.</p>
<h2 id="the-nerd-part">The Nerd Part</h2>
<h3 id="a-reminder-to-mix-up-your-messaging-life-with-some-privacy">A reminder to mix up your messaging life with some privacy</h3>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/Signal_Blue_Icon.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/Signal_Blue_Icon.png"
         width="50%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>By the end of 2017, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/01/31/whatsapp-hits-1-5-billion-monthly-users-19b-not-so-bad/">WhatsApp had 1.5 billion monthly active users</a>.</p>
<p>That’s a pretty serious chunk of the world population.</p>
<p>Down here in South Africa, WhatsApp dominates the mobile messaging space.</p>
<p>There’s nothing else that even comes close.</p>
<p>In order to communicate with the largest subset of friends and contacts, I need WhatsApp. In order to participate in school and neighbourhood groups, or to coordinate with service providers (pretty darned useful that), I have no choice but to use WhatsApp.</p>
<p>Unless some enormous calamity strikes, I don’t think that this is not going to change any time soon.</p>
<p>In January of this year, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/25/technology/facebook-instagram-whatsapp-messenger.html">The New York Times reported</a> that Facebook was planning to merge the underlying technical infrastructure of WhatsApp, Instagram and Facebook Messenger.</p>
<p>Although this will result in users being able to cross-message between WhatsApp, Insta (I’m not a user, I just heard hipster kids calling it this) and Facebook Messenger, which is great, it will also enable the Facebook mothership to monitor very closely who connects with whom across all three networks.</p>
<p>Think about this: Facebook will be able to analyse, across all three of these giant networks, who interacts with whom and when, and sometimes in which way, and will be able to build an even more detailed and powerful social network than they have already done.</p>
<p>If we do nothing, everyone else will just keep on keeping everyone else on WhatsApp. This circular logic is extremely hard to beat.</p>
<p>If we’re even slightly concerned (ok, new we’re down to about 12 people, 5 of which read this blog), what can we do about this?</p>
<p>Install <a href="https://signal.org/">Signal</a> on your phone, and use that whenever you can. (<a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">I started nagging about this</a> in early 2016.)</p>
<p>Signal is one of the most secure and private messaging apps available. Importantly, there’s no company behind it that wants to mine your data for whatever reason.</p>
<p>Sure, you can keep on arguing that no-one else is on Signal. However, I’m here, and you can message me.</p>
<p>Once you install it in addition to the incumbents, <em>you</em> then have a great opportunity of becoming the token Signal user in your social sub-network who by the sheer power of nag-itude gets one or two of your friends to join this small but valuable network.</p>
<p>Whatever we can do to redirect a fraction of the world’s messaging traffic away from the Facebook behemoth is a worthwhile endeavour.</p>
<h3 id="visual-studio-code-is-evolving-at-a-terrific-pace">Visual Studio Code is evolving at a terrific pace</h3>
<p>Looking at the <a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/updates/v1_31">changelog for the January release of Visual Studio Code</a>, and the <a href="https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/pythonengineering/2019/01/29/python-in-visual-studio-code-january-2019-release/">changelog for the January release of the Python extension</a>, I was astonished by the development velocity on display.</p>
<p>I am the guy who got <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/11/19/configuring-emacs-lsp-mode-and-microsofts-visual-studio-code-python-language-server/">Microsoft’s Python Language Server working with the existing LSP support in Emacs</a>, and then very fortunately <a href="https://github.com/andrew-christianson/lsp-python-ms/issues/9">two different open source projects ran with it</a>. However, it seems like there are whole armies of programmers working on Visual Studio Code and its Python extension, which sometimes makes this feel like a micro-example of (a slightly wonky) cathedral and the bazaar.</p>
<p>In any case, where I used to fall back to Emacs for smaller Python projects where it wasn’t worth it firing up the <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/">PyCharm machinery</a>, I now often reach for Visual Studio Code, which in a growing number of cases is even able to go toe-to-toe with PyCharm.</p>
<h3 id="pro-tip-use-zlua-to-change-directories-really-quickly">Pro-tip: Use z.lua to change directories Really Quickly</h3>
<p>For years now I’ve been using either <a href="https://github.com/clvv/fasd">fasd</a> or more recently <a href="https://github.com/wting/autojump">autojump</a> (because it installs on macOS with a one-liner more or less) to jump really quickly between recently visited directories in the shell.</p>
<p>However, in a stunning case of there-really-is-always-room-for-one-more-solution-to-the-same-problem, I ran into <a href="https://github.com/skywind3000/z.lua">z.lua</a>, a command-line directory jumper programmed in Lua (<a href="/tag/lua/">which I’ve always had a thing for</a>), which is also many times faster than fasd or autojump.</p>
<p>Now, I simply do <code>z blog</code> to jump to the most frecent (frequent and recent you plebs) directory containing the word “blog”, or <code>zf tele</code> to show me a selectable list of the directories I’ve frecently visited containing the sub-word “tele”.</p>
<p>(Here’s a bonus pro-tip for macOS users: If you don’t mind scripting in Lua, <a href="http://www.hammerspoon.org">hammerspoon</a> is an amazing desktop open source automation tool. It is the spiritual successor to Mjolnir (hence its name), which you can use to script any number of shortcut-associated desktop tricks. I for example have code to resize any window to a relative portion of the current desktop, and to stick that window neatly into a specific quadrant or half of the desktop. This meant I could remove <a href="https://www.spectacleapp.com/">Spectacle</a> from my machine.)</p>
<h2 id="conversations-with-strangers">Conversations with Strangers</h2>
<p>Thanks to lady luck, or perhaps thanks to serendipity engineering (hat tip to traveller tzhau), I have had the pleasure of some utterly unexpected but pretty epic conversations, with strangers, over the years.</p>
<p>(The secret is that you have to plug in to the conversation apparatus of a stranger. Just remember to configure the communication protocol to hallucin-8. No I don’t mean that you should go on a trip together. This just refers to the ancient mechanism of being able to experience vividly another’s reality via your real-time multi-sensory imagination, synchronised via the primitive but reliable speech signal.)</p>
<p>For example, <a href="/2014/11/03/weekly-head-voices-84-on-being-grateful/#lesson-2-on-being-grateful">back in WHV #84</a> I wrote about the fellow eternal foreigner I met at a weekend party (weekend parties are the best), who taught me the trick of applying gratefulness generously and continously.</p>
<p>One of the more epic conversations I never wrote about, is the two fellow travellers I met on the Final Flight back to South Africa <a href="/2013/12/14/on-leaving-the-netherlands/">after our brilliant Dutch adventure</a>.</p>
<p>These were some of the darkest times of my recent life.</p>
<p>I had just watched for three days as our home was being hollowed out by the movers, until it was just an empty shell.</p>
<p>During that time, I slept in that empty shell, with the ever-increasing echoes of even the smallest sounds doing quite effectively the exact opposite of buoying my mood.</p>
<p>Spending some of these final few days with some of my best friends was truly bitter sweet.</p>
<p>By the time I entered the plane back to Cape Town, I was lower than I had been in a very long time.</p>
<p>My cunning plan at that point was to have a truly depressing flight, but fate had conspired to put me in row 44, where I found myself next to CL and CS.</p>
<p>I can’t remember exactly how the process started, but before I knew it we were embroiled in a solid 11+ hours of <em>continuous</em> and <em>life-affirming</em> conversation.</p>
<p>Besides the differences between us that made the cross-exploration that much more interesting, meeting someone on a plane usually has no to very few implications for later, so one is somehow even more free to open up and connect. In that sense, this is reminiscent of the conversations I’ve gotten involved in at AB.</p>
<p>(In this case, that assumption was proven wrong by pretty serious post-flight collaborations. If you’re reading this CS, thank you for that also!)</p>
<p>At a more recent weekend party (<a href="/2014/11/03/weekly-head-voices-84-on-being-grateful/#lesson-1-weekend-parties-are-the-best-parties">remember they are the best</a>) I again found myself involved in a pretty intense conversation with a stranger.</p>
<p>Again, this stranger had wisdom to share, a tidbit of which I would like to reproduce here.</p>
<p>He referred to this guideline as not negotiating with the self.</p>
<p>If you’re like me, you are now making your “Huh?” face.</p>
<p>His example was about going to the gym, or rather, future him coming up with all kinds of excuses for not going. His rule was that in these cases future him had to go and, without any exception (there’s the non-negotation clause), complete the exercise bike session. Only then, if future him at that point still <em>really</em> did not want to go, was there the possibility of calling it quits.</p>
<p>This feels similar to what I’m trying to do with my checklists.</p>
<p>When I’m thinking about ways to live better, I am by definition in my <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/">rider-on-elephant</a> state. It makes a whole lot of sense to use this time to lay <em>reverse-traps</em> for future me in my tired elephant-running-loose state.</p>
<p>The underlying idea is for Super-You to design systems, e.g. checklists, non-negotiable and easy-to-follow rules, and fully formed habits, that help Normal-Low-Energy-You to keep on functioning as well as possible.</p>
<h2 id="a-message-from-our-sponsor-socrates">A message from our sponsor Socrates</h2>
<p>For edition #6431 of Really Abrupt and Sometimes Jarring WHV endings(tm) I shall end with a quote. I recently ran into this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_unexamined_life_is_not_worth_living">famous dictum by Socrates</a> which I definitely resonate with:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>
    ὁ … ἀνεξέταστος βίος οὐ βιωτὸς ἀνθρώπῳ
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>also known as:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>
    The unexamined life is not worth living
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>Have a brilliant week kids!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #100: Happy 2016!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/03/weekly-head-voices-100-happy-2016/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 09:20:26 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/03/weekly-head-voices-100-happy-2016/</guid><description> Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res.
I wish you a truly happy 2016, filled with learning and helping other people! Neil deGrasse Tyson, exemplary human, said it best:
For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And along the way, lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/table_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/table_mountain_view.jpg"
        
            alt="Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I wish you a truly happy 2016, filled with learning and helping other people! Neil deGrasse Tyson, exemplary human, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/qccer/i_am_neil_degrasse_tyson_ask_me_anything/c3wgffy">said it best</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And along the way, lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Time is fun when you&rsquo;re having flies! I can&rsquo;t believe that four months have flown by since <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/23/weekly-head-voices-99-no-lands/">the previous WHV</a>. Since then, quite a bunch has happened. Some highlights for me:</p>
<ul>
<li>I spent a week in The Netherlands, my other home, taking part in a second hackathon with the Evalueserve peeps (the previous one was in Gurgaon in India). This was again loads of fun, and we managed to build a significant new shippable feature (measurable value!) almost from scratch.</li>
<li>In October, I went back to The Netherlands (it&rsquo;s my other home, remember) for 2.5 days to take part in the Doctorification of <a href="http://francoismalan.com/">a friend</a>. Besides the doctorification process (I&rsquo;ve been out of academia for a while, so my terminology might not be 100%) which went swimmingly, I had so many high-intensity interactions with some of my favourite people that I literally almost missed my flight back. Just picture me waking up in Delft at 8:30 with a flight leaving from Amsterdam at 10:00…</li>
<li>For a work project,  I started programming in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swift_(programming_language)">Apple&rsquo;s Swift</a>. As compiled high-performance languages go, this one has a number of modern language features which make it a truly interesting addition to one&rsquo;s programming toolbox.</li>
<li>Further on the nerd-front, I&rsquo;m trying to get more of us to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">use Signal instead of WhatsApp</a> whenever possible.</li>
<li>We spent so many weekends and the Christmas vacation doing fun outdoorsy stuff (living at the southern tip of Africa has serious perks), not least of which was a trip up Table Mountain for the first time in 15 years. See the photo up top for an impression.</li>
</ul>
<p>I have some fun changes in mind for this blog in 2016, but you&rsquo;re going to have to stick around to find out what they are, so… see you later peeps!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>When we can, let’s use Signal instead of WhatsApp.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 09:38:11 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/</guid><description> (Post updated on January 8, 2021. See section at the end.)
Signal, the open source messaging and voice calling app that does end-to-end encryption. The whole world is using WhatsApp to message each other. I often do too, because I want to inter-operate with the rest of the world.
However, WhatsApp belongs to Facebook.
Although Facebook has promised otherwise (fast-forward a few years: Yes, they did break that promise. See updates at the end of this post.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(Post updated on January 8, 2021. See section at the end.)</em></p>
<figure>
<img alt="Screenshot of Signal." src="https://whispersystems.org/blog/images/signal-new.jpg"/>
<figcaption>Signal, the open source messaging and voice calling app that does end-to-end encryption.</figcaption></figure> 
<p>The whole world is using WhatsApp to message each other. I often do too,
because I want to inter-operate with the rest of the world.</p>
<p>However, WhatsApp belongs to Facebook.</p>
<p>Although Facebook <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2014/02/24/zuckerberg-facebook-whatsapp_n_4848205.html">has promised otherwise</a> (fast-forward a few years: Yes,
they did break that promise. See updates at the end of this post.), the
temptation to link all of your WhatsApp messages with Facebook logins (a
straight-forward process, as they have the mobile phone numbers of a great
number of their users) must be <strong>quite</strong> tempting to the people at
Facebook. Imagine how well they would then be able to target their advertising,
based on their access to both your Facebook profile and your private WhatsApp
messages!</p>
<p>Fortunately, we now have an open source app, called <a href="https://signal.org/">Signal</a> (available on
<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.thoughtcrime.securesms&amp;hl=en">Android</a>, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/za/app/signal-private-messenger/id874139669?mt=8">IOS</a> and the desktop), which performs end-to-end encryption
on all messages and voice calls that go through it. This means that absolutely
no-one is able to read your messages or eavesdrop on your voice calls, except
the intended recipients.</p>
<p>My request is that you get your contacts to install and <a href="https://theintercept.com/2015/03/02/signal-iphones-encrypted-messaging-app-now-supports-text/">start using Signal</a>
instead of WhatsApp wherever possible. At the very least some of our messages
will not be accessible to various large corporations and any other prying
eyes. If the security argument is not enough for you, there is one more
extremely important topic: Signal handles animated gifs better than WhatsApp,
at least on Android. (Telegram supports them on both Android on IOS, but it is
by default less secure than Signal). See here the results of my experiments:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p dir="ltr" lang="en">Animated GIF support (most important feature in any messaging app): WhatsApp fail, Viber fail, Telegram pass, Signal pass on Android.</p>— Charl Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/682942239463587841?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 1, 2016</a></blockquote> <script async="" charset="utf-8" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js"></script>
<h1 id="updates">Updates</h1>
<h2 id="january-8-2021">January 8, 2021</h2>
<p>By now, if you use WhatsApp, the app will have forced you to accept the new
privacy and data sharing agreement.</p>
<p>As is explained in this <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2021/01/whatsapp-users-must-share-their-data-with-facebook-or-stop-using-the-app/">post on
arstechnica</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Under the new terms, Facebook reserves the right to share collected data with its family of companies.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In other words, even more of the personal data of 2 billion or so WhatsApp
users will be integrated with everything Facebook knows about them and about
you, including all of your connections to each other on all of the facebook
platforms, including facebook itself, instagram and whatsapp.</p>
<p>Like many of you, to interoperate with the world I do need to keep WhatsApp,
but I would greatly prefer chatting with you on Signal.</p>
<h2 id="august-25-2016">August 25, 2016</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.theverge.com/2016/8/25/12638698/whatsapp-to-start-sharing-user-data-with-facebook">The Verge reported that WhatsApp will now officially begin sharing data with
Facebook</a>. They will indeed link up telephone numbers and social networks,
meaning that both parties will get a tremendous boost in what they know about
you. I don&rsquo;t want to say I told you so, but I told you so. ;)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>