<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>creativity on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/creativity/</link><description>Recent content in creativity on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 22:24:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/creativity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #234: Huis op die duin</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 22:24:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/</guid><description> Hello and welcome back my friends!
It&amp;rsquo;s 17:50 on Sunday, October 10, 2021 as I write this.
We have just returned from the most amazing spring break in one of our favourite spots. I&amp;rsquo;m relaxing on the sofa, with GOU #3 to my right doing what little digital natives do.
Figure 1: Beach run on Lappiesbaai at low tide is as great as it looks.
I&amp;rsquo;m not sure when exactly this post will be done, but whatever the case may be, it samples, extremely sparsely as always, the period of time from Monday September 27 to Sunday October 10, 2021.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello and welcome back my friends!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s 17:50 on Sunday, October 10, 2021 as I write this.</p>
<p>We have just returned from the most amazing spring break in one of our
favourite spots. I&rsquo;m relaxing on the sofa, with GOU #3 to my right doing what
little digital natives do.</p>








<figure><a href="lappiesbaai-run.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/14/weekly-head-voices-234-huis-op-die-duin/lappiesbaai-run_hu6208b1a4610f5432d2e0695ddd4543b5_2242752_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Beach run on Lappiesbaai at low tide is as great as it looks."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Beach run on Lappiesbaai at low tide is as great as it looks.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure when exactly this post will be done, but whatever the case may be,
it samples, extremely sparsely as always, the period of time from Monday
September 27 to Sunday October 10, 2021.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m wrapping this up on Thursday evening, four pretty full days
later. Phoowee!)</p>
<h2 id="strange-days">Strange days</h2>
<p>In the previous edition of the WHV, <a href="/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">I mentioned that I had found a solution for
making my Org mode notes database accessible from my phone</a>.</p>
<p>Well, it&rsquo;s a rather unconventional trick involving CMake, pandoc and Microsoft
Word that you can read about in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">this probably nerdy vxlabs post</a>.</p>
<p>(Back in 2018, I <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">did something similar by exporting my Org mode database to
Apple Notes</a>, which worked well when most of my devices were of Apple
manufacture. Fortunately the Org mode part of the equation, the most important bit,
remains the same.)</p>
<p>Continuing on from the <a href="/2021/09/13/weekly-head-voices-232-side-project-smorgasbord/#this-blog-hopefully-immortalised-on-github">blog mirroring work mentioned in WHV #232</a>, I configured
the necessary github workflows to auto-publish this site to a github.io site.</p>
<p>In other words, if I were to disappear for whatever reason, this blog should
remain available via <a href="https://cpbotha.github.io/">https://cpbotha.github.io/</a> for quite a while longer after
my hosting and domain registration eventually expire.</p>
<h2 id="spring-break">Spring break</h2>
<p>As part of the week-long Sprink break, we spent an absolutely fabulous long
weekend in Stilbaai, more specifically in the Bosbokduin private game reserve,
in a <a href="http://huisopdieduin.co.za/">house with the most amazing views over the ocean</a>.</p>
<p>Although we were there for only a few days, it feels like we were somehow able
to compress the experiences of a substantially longer period into the time at
our disposal.</p>
<p>I am grateful for all of the runs and walks on beautiful trails on various bits
of the coast, notably the trail passing right in front of the house connecting
Stilbaai and Jongensfontein, paddling on the river, lounging on the beach, and
just lots of family time in that beautiful house.</p>
<p>(When I look back at my notes from the return on Sunday, it&rsquo;s quite clear that
we were still on a sort of perfect vacation high.)</p>
<p>What was interesting to me this time, was that almost immediately after the
initial <a href="/tags/disconnecting/">disconnect</a> which thankfully happened quite soon, my brain started
producing strange (as in, far removed from work, and in some cases just plain
unconventional) but quite plausible new (engineering) ideas.</p>
<p>In other words, this is the nerd version of experiencing creativity.</p>
<p>This made me reconsider the effect of spending a fair bit of energy on work
every day.</p>
<p>Of course the picture is almost always complicated, but my work currently
requires a great deal of <em>focused</em> creativity, that is, thought and effort that
goes in one primary direction.</p>
<p>This is great in terms of getting those big things done, and also of
compounding (personal) improvement in that same direction, but the trade-off is
that the energy spent is now spent, and can&rsquo;t go into the exhilarating feeling
of ideas shooting off in different and often new directions.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #69: No sugar added.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/04/29/weekly-head-voices-69-no-sugar-added/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 21:03:29 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/04/29/weekly-head-voices-69-no-sugar-added/</guid><description> This time, the head voices are echoing the span of time ending strictly on Sunday, April 27 at 23:59.
I have to break my rule and reach through past the start of that week however. On Wednesday April 16 I had quite a heavy sugar crash. After about 12 cups of coffee, each with a spoon of sugar (as per usual), some chocolates from the Stone Three sweetie jar during lunch ,and two giant coconut crunches at about TU Delft sugar fix time (yes children, I do my best to commemorate the sugar fix, even at 11000 km distance from you), my energy levels dropped through the floor and no amount of coffee could get them close to normal again.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This time, the head voices are echoing the span of time ending strictly on Sunday, April 27 at 23:59.</p>
<p>I have to break my rule and reach through past the start of that week however. On Wednesday April 16 I had quite a heavy sugar crash. After about 12 cups of coffee, each with a spoon of sugar (as per usual), some chocolates from the Stone Three sweetie jar during lunch ,and two giant coconut crunches at about TU Delft sugar fix time (yes children, I do my best to commemorate the sugar fix, even at 11000 km distance from you), my energy levels dropped through the floor and no amount of coffee could get them close to normal again.</p>
<p>That’s when I decided to stop taking sugar.</p>
<p>On Thursday April 17 I went cold turkey. I’m not taking any table sugar at all, no cookies or sweets (ARGH), and I’m even steering clear of breakfast cereals. Pretty boring, I know. After more than a week of completely unscientific N=1 case “study” experience, I can report that:</p>
<ul>
<li>It took some getting used to my coffee without any sugar.</li>
<li>NO MORE  COOKIES. ARGH ARGH ARGH. COME CLOSER SO I CAN BITE YOU.</li>
<li>My perceived energy levels seem significantly more stable, and I remain all energetic until late at night. Sometimes I don’t sleep, because I run around in the neighbourhood making growling noises. Sometimes I wake up, miles away from home, with all kinds of gunk under my finger nails. Oh well.</li>
</ul>
<p>On the topic of quitting, let’s talk about all of those lists we love so much. You should really go read Noeska’s presentation on Productivity, Project Management and Other Important Stuff in her <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/weekly-status-update-3/" title="Noeska's Weekly Status Update #3">latest status update blog post</a>. Besides all of the Getting Things Done and Pull Yourself Together tools and systems she presents, I was happy to see her talk about the dangers of productivity tools on slide 23, and especially the “doing the right things vs doing things right” dilemma.</p>
<p>You see, I’ve been thinking much about this lately. Usually when I’m doing the most valuable and important things (designing and building new products, learning new programming languages, coming up with brand new ideas for artefacts to build) my email inbox starts overflowing and my todo system (currently <a href="http://todoist.com/" title="todoist website">todoist</a>, which I do like) stagnates (my todoist karma is currently ZERO. I’m at KARMA ZERO damnit!!). Conversely, when I’m almost at inbox zero and my todoist is under control, it feels great, but I’m tired because I’ve spent all of that time taking care of a bunch of emails and mostly urgent but almost no important tasks.</p>
<p>Some people I’ve chatted with are hardcore enough to make the classification between important and urgent in their lists. However, when I see that list of tasks, my OCDs take over and I go into 100% reactive mode. NO ROOM FOR CREATIVITY.</p>
<p>I’m still thinking about how to solve this problem. I do think that the lists and the systems are really important, because some things do really need doing at certain points in time. For now, I’m still picking the three (or two, or one) most important things to do per day (see Noeska’s presentation, also <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/" title="old blog post: write down most important things to do each day">see pro tip #2 in this 2011 post of mine</a>). Also, what does work remarkably well for me, is maintaining a daily “done” or “I did it” list. <a href="http://jamesaltucher.quora.com/The-I-Did-List-%E2%80%93-I-Did-It" title="Altucher: I did it list.">Go read this</a>, you can thank me later.</p>
<p>After all of that, the weekend took us to Vaalvlei, a picturesque wine farm just outside of Stanford:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/vaalvlei.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/vaalvlei-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Vaalvlei wine farm, just outside of Stanford."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Vaalvlei wine farm, just outside of Stanford.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Here we were treated to a super-exclusive wine tasting of the Vaalvlei Sauvignon Blanc, 2012 Shiraz Reserve, 2011 Shiraz, Shiraz port, and the top TOP secret Shiraz cognac right from the cask (don’t tell anyone, ok?):








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/vaalvlei_tasting.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/vaalvlei_tasting-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Vaalvlei wine and cognac tasting"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Vaalvlei wine and cognac tasting</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I can report that these hand-crafted wines and the cognac were all beautiful, but I trust that my friend <a href="http://dewijnrecensent.nl/" title="De Wijnrecensent">De Wijnrecensent</a> (aka <em>the Tall Philisophical Neighbour!</em> all secrets are revealed on this blog.) will have more to say about this in a few months time.</p>
<p>Enjoy the rest of the week kids!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>What is love? [Weekly Head Voices #64 no #65]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/02/14/what-is-love-weekly-head-voices-64/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2012 22:05:43 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/02/14/what-is-love-weekly-head-voices-64/</guid><description> I’ve been dealing with a spot of blog writer’s block, hence the lateness of this post. I’d forgotten that these monthly instalments were initially intended to be extended status updates, with a spot of backyard philosophy every so often. Trying to come up with worthwhile backyard philosophy every week is just plain hard. This week I’m going for half a status update along with a list of possibly interesting sciencey tidbits.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/dont_herd_me.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/dont_herd_me-1024x681.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I’ve been dealing with a spot of blog writer’s block, hence the lateness of this post. I’d forgotten that these monthly instalments were initially intended to be extended status updates, with a spot of backyard philosophy every so often. Trying to come up with worthwhile backyard philosophy every week is just plain hard. This week I’m going for half a status update along with a list of possibly interesting sciencey tidbits.</p>
<ul>
<li>I’ve managed to <a href="http://devidenews.wordpress.com/2012/02/11/devide-12-2-7-sees-the-light-of-day/" title="devide 12.2.7 release post">release a stable version of DeVIDE</a>, my Frankenstein-Borg software system for visualization and image processing, only about 2.5 years after the previous stable release. Go get yours <a href="http://code.google.com/p/devide/wiki/Downloads?tm=2" title="devide downloads">fresh from the oven</a>, it’s completely open source!</li>
<li>It <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/" title="right after first MedVis course">seems like yesterday</a> when I got to design and teach the first MedVis Ninja course at the TU Delft. The fourth generation of students have just started with the course (partly the reason for pushing out a new DeVIDE release). The previous generations are kicking ass as we speak, and I’m proud of ’em all.</li>
<li>I had the privilege of giving another invited talk, in Dutch, at the yearly conference of the Dutch Anatomical Society. In my talk, titled <em>Data Visualization: Driving the human visual system for fun and profit</em>, I introduced data and medical visualization, and then discussed three illustrative examples in more depth: high quality volume rendering (work by Thomas Kroes), diffusion tensor imaging (work by Jorik Blaas) and fMRI connectivity visualization (work by André van Dixhoorn).</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it for the status update. The sciencey bits I thought were worth mentioning are:</p>
<ul>
<li>There’s been some press lately about the letter to the Wall Street Journal, signed by 16 scientists, in which they try to make the case that climate change is really not such an issue. Climate change denialists everywhere rejoiced, I cringed. I really don’t like denialism. Fortunately, it turns out that I’m not the only one, and that there’s a story behind the story: The WSJ editorial board is severely biased against climate science.  Another letter, signed by 255 real scientists (all members of the US National Academy of Science), dealing with the realities of climate change, was flat-out rejected by the WSJ. It’s a shame that the first factually dubious letter got so much of the press. Read more about the whole debacle in <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/petergleick/2012/01/27/remarkable-editorial-bias-on-climate-science-at-the-wall-street-journal/" title="forbes article concerning WSJ climate bias">this Forbes article</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://pss.sagepub.com/content/23/2/187" title="Lower Cognitive Ability Predicts Greater Prejudice ">A recent Psychological Science article</a> contains the results of a study  on more than 15000 UK inhabitants, as well as on a group in the US, that shows that lower cognitive ability predicts greater prejudice, manifesting in for example right-wing ideologies or homophobia. Ha ha.</li>
<li>In another not-so-surprising turn of events, it turns out that alcohol does indeed make you more creative.  <a href="http://francoismalan.com/">FrancoisMalan.com</a> sent me, albeit indirectly, this <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1053810012000037" title="Uncorking the muse: Alcohol intoxication facilitates creative problem solving">Consciousness and Cognition article</a>, titled <em>Uncorking the muse: Alcohol intoxication facilitates creative problem solving</em>. Note the creative title, draw your own conclusions about the state of intoxication required for authoring a successful scientific article. Ahem.</li>
</ul>
<p>Good science should be reproducible. Judging by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blood_alcohol_content">the blood alcohol content and weight tables</a> on Wikipedia, I should be more creative between 3 and 4 beers, a result I will certainly try to confirm during my next WHV writing session. It is left as an exercise to the reader to calculate my body weight based on this information.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>