<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>GOUs on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gous/</link><description>Recent content in GOUs on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 16:19:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gous/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #178: Parallel world.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/24/weekly-head-voices-178-parallel-world/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 16:19:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/24/weekly-head-voices-178-parallel-world/</guid><description> GOU#2, age 9, painted this unicorn for all of us. Sometimes you need more unicorn in your life, especially when you&amp;rsquo;ve reviewed photos for the past two weeks and came up with nothing and you start doubting everything. Now I believe!
This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday September 9 to Sunday September 22, 2019.
Miscellaneous bits. I was finally able to finish and publish a fairly extensive blog post documenting my current personal knowledge management strategy.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="gou2_unicorn_painting.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/24/weekly-head-voices-178-parallel-world/gou2_unicorn_painting_hua4ba3f5686f8e3ba54fd403c9e2eef8e_1755636_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/24/weekly-head-voices-178-parallel-world/gou2_unicorn_painting_hua4ba3f5686f8e3ba54fd403c9e2eef8e_1755636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/24/weekly-head-voices-178-parallel-world/gou2_unicorn_painting_hua4ba3f5686f8e3ba54fd403c9e2eef8e_1755636_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/24/weekly-head-voices-178-parallel-world/gou2_unicorn_painting_hua4ba3f5686f8e3ba54fd403c9e2eef8e_1755636_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/24/weekly-head-voices-178-parallel-world/gou2_unicorn_painting_hua4ba3f5686f8e3ba54fd403c9e2eef8e_1755636_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
<p>GOU#2, age 9, painted this unicorn for all of us. Sometimes you need more
unicorn in your life, especially when you&rsquo;ve reviewed photos for the past two
weeks and came up with nothing and you start doubting everything. Now I
believe!</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday September 9 to
Sunday September 22, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="miscellaneous-bits">Miscellaneous bits.</h2>
<p>I was finally able to finish and publish a fairly extensive blog post
documenting <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my current personal knowledge management
strategy</a>.</p>
<p>The purpose of that write-up is both for my own future reference, as I&rsquo;ve put
far more effort into it than into my internal recursive note-taking about my
note-taking strategy, and to be able to point people at it.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s nothing quite like being asked a question, and then being able to point
the questioner at the relevant post on one&rsquo;s blog.</p>
<p>There was a <a href="https://www.wired.co.uk/article/future-of-food-innovation-technology">great overview article in Wired about the work done in Wageningen
towards feeding the growing population of planet
earth</a>.</p>
<p>Having enjoyed one (1) fried
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mealworm">mealworm</a>-filled bread roll a few
years back, I for one am looking forward to our environmentally friendly
alternative meat sources of the future.</p>
<p>Quite compelling in this regard is the massive difference in energy efficiency
between the production of a kilogram of beef on the one hand, and a kilogram of
tasty cricket meat on the other.</p>
<p>This is my favourite quote from the Wired article:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Cold insect blood translates to a high food conversion rate: per kilogram of
meat produced, a cricket needs roughly 1.7 kg of feed, a cow 7-10. Insects
also emit less greenhouse gases than conventional livestock; among insect
species, only cockroaches, termites and scarab beetles produce any methane at
all.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="cadence-180-redux">Cadence 180 REDUX!</h2>
<p>Another friend from work, who runs better and faster than I do (they all do),
was explaining the other day that one had to make better use of one&rsquo;s <em>glutes</em>,
or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gluteal_muscles">gluteal muscles</a>, while
running.</p>
<p>This is not the first time that a superior running friend from work gave this
advice, and so I tried my best during the subsequent few runs to activate my
glutes.</p>
<p>Some of you know that I am not the most coordinated of humans, and so you might
be able to imagine what it looks like when I attempt both to run without
falling, and at the same time to <em>activate</em> those glutes more than they are
already activated.</p>
<p>Not elegant.</p>
<p>I soon decided that this experiment, besides looking really funny, was probably
going to lead to a pathologically bad gait that would end up to be super hard
to unlearn.</p>
<p>The internet fortunately had an answer(ish): <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3387288/">A 2012 study in the Gait Posture
journal, titled <em>Changes in Muscle Activation Patterns when Running Step Rate
is Increased</em></a>, showed
that the glutes, and a number of other muscles of the lower extremities, show
higher activation at a step rate higher than the runner&rsquo;s usual preference.</p>
<p>To me, this sounds exactly like my old friend called &ldquo;hey let&rsquo;s run at the
fairly uncomfortable feeling 180 steps per minute&rdquo;! He&rsquo;s <a href="/2018/06/18/weekly-head-voices-146-you-too-can-learn-kung-fu/#barefoot-style-running-update">been here
before</a>,
but that was in the context of reddit&rsquo;s barefoot running advice.</p>
<p>The study mentioned above, although focused on muscle activation, did echo some
of the well-known advice that this higher cadence would decrease joint stress
and would help to improve running form by ensuring that runners would land on
their feet right below their centres of mass.</p>
<p>Anyways, I&rsquo;m back to 180 cadence, as is also recommended by the box that my
<a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#escalante">new Altras</a> came in.</p>
<p>When I remember to eat a banana or two and to drink enough water before I go
out, focusing on the 180 step rate leads to a more tiring but somehow much more
satisfying run.</p>
<p>It seems that since my previous 180 period some time back, I had settled on a
slightly more comfortable lope, most probably in order to keep my <a href="/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/#maf-ish">heart rate
at 80% of my maximum or
lower</a></p>
<p>Currently, a step rate of 180 mostly means that I am unable to keep my heart
rate at 80% or lower. I am curious, and a little bit nervous, to find out if I
am able to bring my 180 cadence heart rate down by a percentage point or two.</p>
<h2 id="whats-your-yo-yo">What&rsquo;s your yo-yo?</h2>
<p>Because GOU#2 had just acquired a new yo-yo, we were watching youtube videos of
yo-yo champions performing their art.</p>
<p>One yo-yo, two yo-yos, yo-yos flying everywhere, sometimes even off their
strings to be deftly caught behind the back again, and so on.</p>
<p>It was a seriously impressive business.</p>
<p>I thought to myself: This is what happens when you dedicate thousands of hours
to one specific skill.</p>
<p>In the case of yo-yo&rsquo;ing, the skill is brilliantly displayable &ndash; I gawk, and I
have to watch that my jaw does not actually drop to the nearest horizontal
surface as it would really like to.</p>
<p>Thinking a bit more, I wondered whether I had any skill which came even close
to the levels of mastery being displayed here.</p>
<p>The skill I&rsquo;ve poured the most time into would have be the extremely exciting
and spectacular activity of&hellip; <em>computer programming</em>.</p>
<p>Yes folks, even when I&rsquo;m not working (computer programming, FOR MONEY), I will
sometimes sit down with a new or old programming language and code something up
for fun.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing this for the largest part of my life, which is getting longer
by the minute!</p>
<p>And so I have to come to the conclusion that <em>programming</em> is the closest I
currently have to a yo-yo.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s <em>your</em> yo-yo?</p>
<p>P.S. Thinking about it some more, Emacs is almost like some sort of yo-yo,
isn&rsquo;t it?</p>
<h2 id="extrawelt-abc">Extrawelt ABC.</h2>
<p>Some of you might have realised that the section above, ostensibly about
yo-yos, is actually a thinly disguised page in my fairly recently started
<a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding"><em>Always Be
Compounding</em></a>
theme.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;re so clever!</p>
<p>However, that is of course not all that I have to say for ABC today.</p>
<p>For the past week I had <a href="https://youtu.be/r98noHkkkBo">the brilliant September 4, 2019 Boiler Room
performance of Extrawelt</a> on repeat.</p>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/r98noHkkkBo?t=3674">At the very end</a>, the master of
ceremonies had the following to say, with a doubly convincing German accent:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>extrawelt! you know how it is if you believe in something, if you have the
right talent and if you keep going for a long long time you end up like these
guys: titans in the business, extrawelt!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Friends, I wish you the clarity of mind to know your yo-yos, and the tenacity
to keep practising for a long long time.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #170: Yeet.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2019 22:02:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/</guid><description> Hello there friends!
This edition of the WHV, number 170, is how I choose look back at the three weeks from Monday April 15 to Sunday May 5, 2019.
This period was host to whooshing-by-deadline-induced stress, one amazing and thought-provoking wedding, the birthdays of two of my GOUs, and, a bit strangely part of this list, the acquisition of a new computing device.
At least we were able to pause everything for a sublime afternoon at a favourite vineyard close to my backyard:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello there friends!</p>
<p>This edition of the WHV, number 170, is how I choose look back at the three
weeks from Monday April 15 to Sunday May 5, 2019.</p>
<p>This period was host to whooshing-by-deadline-induced stress, one amazing and
thought-provoking wedding, the birthdays of two of my GOUs, and, a bit
strangely part of this list, the acquisition of a new computing device.</p>
<p>At least we were able to pause everything for a sublime afternoon at a
favourite vineyard close to my backyard:</p>
<figure>
<a href="lourensford_cellar_skies.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
I ended the three week WHV-hiatus in this place, together with my
fam jam<sup>*</sup>. It was lit.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h1 id="a-brief-but-educational-interlude-how-to-speak-gen-z">A brief but educational interlude: HOW TO SPEAK GEN Z.</h1>
<p>I too did not know what &ldquo;fam jam&rdquo; meant until I viewed the educational video
below.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YtrxVWf91Jo" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>I feel like I understand my budding teenager (GOU#1) a little better now.</p>
<p>On a related note: GOU#1 and I went to watch End Game together, on her 13th
birthday.</p>
<p>This is the first time I&rsquo;ve been in a cinema since forever, as I usually find
it hard to justify the time expense.</p>
<p>In this case however, the film, but far more importantly my company and the
special occasion, made it doubly worth it.</p>
<p>P.S. Dumbledore doesn&rsquo;t make it. 😢</p>
<p>P.P.S. That emoji comes straight from my Emacs! (It comes as a bit of a
surprise to me that I am quite excited by how our systems of written
communication are evolving.)</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. If you too want your Emacs to do this, add the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; 💪💪💪</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#cb4b16">use-package</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">emojify</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cb4b16">:ensure</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">t</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cb4b16">:config</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  (<span style="color:#268bd2">emojify-set-emoji-styles</span> &#39;(<span style="color:#268bd2">unicode</span>))
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  (<span style="color:#268bd2">global-emojify-mode</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  (<span style="color:#268bd2">global-set-key</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">kbd</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;C-x 8 e&#34;</span>) <span style="color:#2aa198">&#39;emojify-insert-emoji</span>))
</span></span></code></pre></div><h1 id="the-other-blog-posts-i-did-get-around-to-writing">The other blog posts I did get around to writing.</h1>
<p>Perhaps unbeknownst to you, I was not completely quiet on the blogging front.</p>
<p>I produced the following four posts, the latter three of which will have to
live on the nerdy sister blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">meepx1e: I haz new laptop!</a> - The traditional
welcome-new-computer-to-my-household post on this blog.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/16/dotnet-fsi-in-vscode/">Using the new dotnet fsi from .NET Core 3 Preview 3 in Visual Studio
Code</a> - A modest trick
for an improved F# repl.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/19/django-typescript-docker-compose-windows/">PyCharm and Docker Compose for Django and TypeScript development on Windows
10</a> -
You can run your Linux inside of Microsoft-supported Docker containers on
your Windows laptop. How times have changed&hellip;</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/20/link-thunderbird-emails-from-emacs-orgmode/">Link directly to emails from Emacs Orgmode using Thunderbird and
Thunderlink</a> -
This is a core part of my task management workflows. On macOS it worked more
or less out of the box, on Windows and Linux you have to get your hands
dirty.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="the-easiest-but-most-high-impact-measure-you-can-take-to-not-die-too-soon-go-to-bed-on-time">The easiest but most high impact measure you can take to not die too soon: Go to bed on time.</h1>
<p><a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">I&rsquo;ve mentioned Matthew Walker, the increasingly world-renowned Professor of
Sleep Science, on this blog
before</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently working through a three-part podcast between <a href="https://peterattiamd.com">Dr Peter Attia
MD</a>, life optimisation expert with the
hyper-analytical accent(tm), and Prof. Walker, and it is absolutely
<em>fascinating</em>.</p>
<p>Several times now, points discussed by the two gentleman have made me go
&ldquo;OH. MY. GOODNESS.&rdquo; in the car between home, the daily school-run and work.</p>
<p>The long and the short of it is that although we so easily trade away sleep for
an extra hour of work, or even worse to assuage pangs of guilt at not working
enough during the day, that sleep is one of the most crucial components of
one&rsquo;s health.</p>
<p>Looking at it from a different angle, and one which Walker is not scared to
take, probably because it is so critical, lack of sleep has terrifyingly
deleterious effects on human health.</p>
<p>Anyways, if you&rsquo;re looking for a thought-provoking conversation, you could
easily do worse than this.</p>
<ul>
<li>Part 1: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker1/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker1/</a></li>
<li>Part 2: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker2/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker2/</a></li>
<li>Part 3: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker3/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker3/</a></li>
</ul>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have the opportunity to listen to the podcast, perhaps because you
need to catch up on your sleep, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/sep/24/why-lack-of-sleep-health-worst-enemy-matthew-walker-why-we-sleep">this 2017 article in The
Guardian</a>
is a great summary.</p>
<h1 id="the-edge-of-humanity">The Edge of Humanity.</h1>
<p>(Not interested in hearing about sleep? How about existential risks that
threaten the continued existence of our species? Here at the WHV we like to
keep the issues light and light-hearted!)</p>
<p><em>Homo Deus</em> by Yuval Harari is one of those books I really think <em>everyone</em>
should read. This is such a fantastic and broad treatise on where we came from,
and where we might be going.</p>
<p>I am happy that we have the privilege of Harari as the superbly articulate
thinker that he is.</p>
<p>This discussion between Yuval Harari and Sam Harris, available as <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/138-edge-humanity/">podcast #138
on Sam Harris&rsquo;s website</a>, is
both valuable and highly entertaining.</p>
<p>Besides the moment at about 32 minutes in when Harari made the case that all of
the large scale media manipulation and user data mining demonstrate that the
human mind is now indeed hackable (!!), I wanted to mention the
thought-provoking topic of how comically out of their depth our political
leaders are.</p>
<p>They don&rsquo;t seem to be able to do much more than <em>react</em> to short-term fears and
impulses (which they also play to), and as if that was not bad enough, they do
so with an horizon of not much more than about four years.</p>
<p>How many of our leaders would be able to field convincingly the question of
what their plans were, what their <em>vision</em> is for humanity, for the coming 40
years?</p>
<p>What <em>is</em> our 40 year grand plan for energy, for the environment, for poverty,
and for preventing another world war?</p>
<p>Please give your answers in the comments.</p>
<h1 id="a-strange-thing-happened-this-weekend">A strange thing happened this weekend.</h1>
<p>During my time at the TU Delft, I made and maintained a software tool called
DeVIDE, or the <em>Delft Visualisation and Image Processing Development
Environment</em>, or <em>Not Responding</em> as it was called by <em>some</em> of its users.</p>
<p>Development started in 2002, the first open source release was in 2007 and the
last release was in 2012.</p>
<p>(You can still download working binaries of the 2012 release from the
<a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/devide/wiki/Downloads">downloads page</a>. It was
pretty strong on loading chaotic collections of DICOM images, and it was pretty
strong on enabling users to talk to almost any part of it in Python, at
runtime. Frits Post and I published a <a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Hybrid-Scheduling-in-the-DeVIDE-Dataflow-Botha-Post/a96cc2530609d46d9a39f5884d8a9f8192991114">paper in 2008 which nicely summarised
the interesting parts of the
software</a>.)</p>
<p>When <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">I left the TU and
academia</a>, my work
positively careened off in a different direction and it became more or less
impossible for me to justify continuing to maintain DeVIDE.</p>
<p>Fast forward a few years, and due to Project Z I&rsquo;m again all up in the
<a href="https://www.dicomlibrary.com/dicom/">DICOMs</a>.</p>
<p>More acutely however, I feel the need for creatively implemented projective
geometry.</p>
<p>Well, my weekend brain got behind the steering wheel, and before I knew it I
was staring at the DeVIDE UI, all prettied up with Python 3 and VTK 8.2:</p>
<figure>
<a href="devide2019-screenshot-20190505.png">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hude98aed5ec064e93d609fc8a6d5e9b53_378650_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hude98aed5ec064e93d609fc8a6d5e9b53_378650_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hude98aed5ec064e93d609fc8a6d5e9b53_378650_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hude98aed5ec064e93d609fc8a6d5e9b53_378650_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>At this moment it&rsquo;s only a limping shadow of its previous self, but it still
managed to bring back so many warm memories.</p>
<p>With a few hours more of work, it could start becoming useful again.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not entirely sure where weekend-brain wanted to go with this. We&rsquo;ll have to
wait until he gets back to see.</p>
<h1 id="heading">🙏🙏🙏</h1>
<p>Friends, thank you for connecting with me here in these words and symbols.</p>
<p>I am already looking forward to the next time that we meet!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>