<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Our Man in Vienna on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/our-man-in-vienna/</link><description>Recent content in Our Man in Vienna on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 20:42:48 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/our-man-in-vienna/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Taxing but fun. [Weekly Head Voices #43]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/03/28/taxing-but-fun-weekly-head-voices-43/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2011 20:42:48 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/03/28/taxing-but-fun-weekly-head-voices-43/</guid><description>With every edition I claim that I have no time to post, but this time, I have even less time than usual. However, here I am to bring you a super-duper compact time-saving edition of the Weekly Head Voices, filled with the highlights of week 12 of 2011. I’ll start this edition with some church: Pretty spring photo of the back of the New Church in Delft, taken whilst I was waiting for my guest (Our Man in Vienna, temporarily in Delft!) to exit his hotel.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>With every edition I claim that I have no time to post, but this time, I have even less time than usual. However, here I am to bring you a super-duper compact time-saving edition of the Weekly Head Voices, filled with the highlights of week 12 of 2011. I’ll start this edition with some church:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/nieuwe_kerk_van_achter.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/nieuwe_kerk_van_achter.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty spring photo of the back of the New Church in Delft, taken whilst I was waiting for my guest (Our Man in Vienna, temporarily in Delft!) to exit his hotel."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty spring photo of the back of the New Church in Delft, taken whilst I was waiting for my guest (Our Man in Vienna, temporarily in Delft!) to exit his hotel.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<ul>
<li>I’ve tried to give you a more snappy blog loading experience by installing the <a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/wp-super-cache/" title="wp super cache page">WP Super Cache</a> (with a 24 hour site preload), <a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/db-cache-reloaded-fix/" title="db cache reloaded fix page">DB Cache Reloaded Fix</a> and <a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/use-google-libraries/" title="use google libraries plugin">Use Google Libraries</a> plugins. In many cases, you’ll get served a static HTML page, which is much faster than the on-demand SQL-spewing PHP-generated complexity WordPress usually does. In the great big quagmire that is WordPress caching plugins, this combination seems to be working best in my case. Measuring with <a href="http://tools.pingdom.com/" title="tools.pingdom.com site speed measurement">tools.pingdom.org</a> (awesome resource!), most of the pages on this site should now fully render in around 2 seconds.</li>
<li>The <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page, so you can figure out who's who">TNR</a> and I souped up the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/" title="work website: TU Delft Graphics group">work website</a>, it’s looking really spiffy now, with embedded RSS feeds and all!</li>
<li>I’ve finally installed <a href="http://latedroid.com/juicedefender" title="JuiceDefender website">JuiceDefender</a> on my <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/01/22/htc-desire-z-an-in-depth-and-nerdy-review/" title="review of my telephone">laptop with built-in telephone</a> (my HTC Desire Z smartphone, in other words), the battery almost lasts the whole day now! If you have an Android telephone and your not happy with your battery life (err, is that even a question?), get this app. Now.</li>
<li>I opposed an M.Sc. defence on Tuesday on the ultrasound measurement of tendon displacement <em>in vivo</em> and subsequent derivation of moment arms. Great fun diving into new work like that! The student did a great job.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.simvis.at/" title="our man in vienna's headquarters">Our Man in Vienna</a> came to visit us in Delft. Huge fun was had by me and Our Man in Vienna (I hope), and serious work was done. It’s a great combination, we will attempt to apply it more often.</li>
<li>On Friday evening I slipped and did our <a href="http://belastingdienst.nl/" title="belastingdienst site">yearly tax return</a> by accident. BAM!</li>
</ul>
<p>This is the end my friend. Here’s some more church (a different one, at least), taken after a scrumptious dinner in the city:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/oude_kerk_snachts.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/oude_kerk_snachts-613x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="The Old Church in Delft, with pretty lighting. This is not a simulation."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Old Church in Delft, with pretty lighting. This is not a simulation.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Have a great week everyone! Over here, we’ll be chasing deadlines, and many of ’em. WATCH OUT YOU DEADLINES!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>