<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>engineering on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/engineering/</link><description>Recent content in engineering on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 11:51:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #198: A short update for future me</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 11:51:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/</guid><description> Figure 1: Evening walk with the fam-jam up a familiar mountain route after a failed attempt at finding the start of a far more spectacular but unfamiliar route.
I was planning to skip a week, because a whole blog post about the work that has been filling my days is really no fun at all.
However, after a good night&amp;rsquo;s sleep, my mind changed itself, as it is wont to do, and in the morning gave the advice that future me would in fact be quite interested to look back into these times.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="sunset_walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Evening walk with the fam-jam up a familiar mountain route after a failed attempt at finding the start of a far more spectacular but unfamiliar route."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Evening walk with the fam-jam up a familiar mountain route after a failed attempt at finding the start of a far more spectacular but unfamiliar route.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I was planning to skip a week, because a whole blog post about the work that
has been filling my days is really no fun at all.</p>
<p>However, after a good night&rsquo;s sleep, my mind changed itself, as it is wont to
do, and in the morning gave the advice that future me would in fact be quite
interested to look back into these times.</p>
<p>So here we are, in the probably shorter-than-average 198th edition of the
Weekly Head Voices, ostensibly covering the week from Monday June 8 to Sunday
June 14. 2020.</p>
<h2 id="how-will-2020-go-down-in-history">How will 2020 go down in history?</h2>
<p>I wonder if in the future we will have some interesting name for 2020, or for
the era that 2020 ushered in?</p>
<p>The following tweet by Peter Kolchinsky, virologist and biotech investor,
struck a chord with me:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I think 2020 will be
remembered as the year politics tried to bend science &amp; nature yet they
just wouldn’t bend. Whether it’s how the virus spreads or which vaccines and
drugs work, the truth is waiting to be discovered with proper scientific
method, not punditry.</p>&mdash; Peter Kolchinsky
(@PeterKolchinsky) <a href="https://twitter.com/PeterKolchinsky/status/1272337332402884608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">June
15, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>I really hope that he&rsquo;s right.</p>
<p>In this, COVID-19 is a lot like science, except that it&rsquo;s a whole lot less
forgiving:</p>








<figure>
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/science_and_your_beliefs.jpg"
            

        /> 
</figure>

<p>I am scientifically extremely curious to see how all of this plays out, as the
heads of denialists (of any kind) are known to consist of some of the densest
materials in the universe.</p>
<p>Let us wait and see!</p>
<h3 id="aside-longevity-of-twitter-citations-in-this-blog">Aside: Longevity of Twitter citations in this blog</h3>
<p>Just to allay your fears, fictitious reader, and mine, I have just
double-checked: If twitter were ever to disappear completely from the internet,
the text of the above tweet is embedded in this blog and will remain readable.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know what the chances of twitter disappearing are, but one has to
remember that it&rsquo;s only been around since 2006, although it feels like it&rsquo;s
been part of the universe forever.</p>
<p>For those of you who find such things interesting, my late joining in 2009 is
of course <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">documented in a post on this blog</a>.</p>
<h3 id="how-we-are-personally-doing">How we are personally doing</h3>
<p>It was the main motivation for deciding to write this post, but I&rsquo;m hiding this
short piece away here in a subsection.</p>
<p>With us as a family it&rsquo;s going as well as it possibly could, under the
circumstances.</p>
<p>We have each other, and we appreciate each other. We have made our home as
comfortable as possible, because we are serious about physical distancing as
much as possible.</p>
<p>We are super grateful for what we have, and we are acutely aware of the fact
that most people don&rsquo;t have it this good.</p>
<p>GOU#1 sometimes struggles a bit with the fact that some of her friends are out
socializing, when we, the science-based parents, are sticking more closely to
the guidelines.</p>
<p>South Africa is currently at 73533 confirmed cases with 1568 deaths (2.1% <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/covid-mortality-risk">CFR,
or Case Fatality Rate</a>).</p>
<p>The whole province of the Western Cape (where we live) is responsible for a
disproportionately large part of those figures: 42892 cases and 1111 deaths.</p>
<p>In addition, we are fortunate enough to have grandma living with us, so we are
playing it as safe as we can. (Grandma is one of the healthiest, fittest 74
year olds that you could ever run into.)</p>
<p>Dear GOU#1 in the future: You were already so graceful and understanding
in 2020. Hopefully when future you reads this, you&rsquo;ll be reminded that we
mostly have good reasons for what we do.</p>
<h2 id="on-engineers-being-right-and-being-nice">On engineers, being right and being nice</h2>
<p>If you have an engineer in your life, this should ring bells, quite loudly:</p>








<figure>
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/arguing_with_an_engineer_hu88272c4f7339ec6f85b7ef50bd009825_28467_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/arguing_with_an_engineer.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Arguing with an Engineer is a lot like wrestling in the mud with a pig, after a couple of hours you realize the pig likes it."/> 
</figure>

<p>Yes, we love arguing.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the goal is usually not to win, but to reach the best answer.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;ve had a good argument with your team about some issue, and the winning
configuration was implemented, that engineering decision has a pretty good
motivation behind it.</p>
<p>More importantly, it usually has the buy-in of the team.</p>
<p>All of that being said, during the recent months a mis-remembered yet more
appropriate version of a quote has been slowly but surely integrating with the
latest version of my wetware.</p>
<p>(That&rsquo;s nerd-speak for: &ldquo;I&rsquo;m really trying to apply this life guideline more
consistently my fellow humans&rdquo;.)</p>
<p>The original quote is the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>They may forget what you said — but they will never forget how you made them
feel. &ndash; Carl W. Buehner</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(It has often been mis-attributed, most notably to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maya%5FAngelou">Maya Angelou</a>, but <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2014/04/06/they-feel/">Quote
Investigator</a> says it&rsquo;s most probably due to Buehner.)</p>
<p>My mis-remembered version is as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>People will quickly forget whether you were <em>right</em> or <em>wrong</em>, but they will
never forget how you made them feel.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m just going to leave that there.</p>
<h2 id="post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">Post Scriptum: The WHV approach to life, the universe and everything</h2>
<p>It <em>just</em> occurred to me that the core philosophy I teach my GOUs rests on
two main pillars: Love and Science.</p>
<p>That ordering is deliberate, as love sometimes has to override science, just
like being kind sometimes has to override being right.</p>
<p>As a reminder, <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/"><em>The WHV&rsquo;s Two no Three Rules for Achieving Great Success in
Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em></a> rests on top of those
pillars. The rules are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be useful.</li>
<li>Be likable.</li>
<li>Evolve.</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Dear Academia, I hope we can still be friends.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 14:06:05 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/</guid><description><![CDATA[ After many great years in academia, I finally decided in October of last year to resign from my position as tenured assistant professor. As of February of this year, I proudly walk the earth as an independent engineer.
It has taken me two years of thinking to reach this decision.
I started re-evaluating my life in academia two years ago after a review-for-promotion (See the &ldquo;oral defence&rdquo; bullet. :)) process that resulted in a &ldquo;not quite yet&rdquo; judgement.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>After many great years in academia, I finally decided in October of last year
to resign from my position as tenured assistant professor. As of February of
this year, I proudly walk the earth as an independent engineer.</p>
<p>It has taken me two years of thinking to reach this decision.</p>
<p>I started re-evaluating my life in academia two years ago after
a <a href="/2010/09/20/an-indecent-proposal-weekly-head-voices-31/">review-for-promotion (See the &ldquo;oral defence&rdquo;
bullet. :))</a> process
that resulted in a &ldquo;not quite yet&rdquo; judgement. It took this long to make my
decision, because it was actually going quite well. I had
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenure_(academic)">tenure</a>, the holy grail (well,
the first of a number of them) for many academics. I had built up and was
heading the TU Delft Medical Visualization research group. I was fortunate to
attract the best postgraduate students and Ph.D. candidates. My research
proposals were successful, so I had money to explore exciting new research
avenues. My h-index was (slowly) going in the right direction. Even my teaching
was more than occasionally positively received. :)</p>
<p>However, after all this thinking I was finally able to admit to myself that I
am a much better engineer than an academic. All of these years, I had been
applying my engineering talent to the design problem that is academia. This was
successful to a certain extent, but I would never be able to compete with a
Real Academic(tm).</p>
<p><em>More importantly, life is short. It makes sense, and is much more enjoyable,
to spend the largest possible part of it running at full efficiency.</em></p>
<p>Quickly after this realisation, came the next one: I had sub-consciously been
working on a fairly respectable engineering-oriented CV and a great network. I
now had the freedom to work for &hellip; <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">me</a>. I could get back
to designing and building advanced technical artefacts that people actually
use, and I could do so completely on my own terms.</p>
<p>It was definitely not easy to leave academia. The hardest part is leaving
behind the relationships I was privileged to have with my colleagues (friends),
in Delft and the rest of the world. Of course we will still have contact, but
it will never be the same as the 15:30 sugar fix, the caffeine-driven and
super-esoteric debates in the kitchen, the ultra-weird lunch discussions, or
the awesome conversations and beer-drinking at scientific (haha) conferences.</p>
<p>That being said, the wave of creative energy I have been riding on for the past
month, even after correcting for novelty, is a good sign that my choice was a
suitable one. I am happy and relieved to call myself an engineer again.</p>
<p>So Academia, it&rsquo;s really not you, it&rsquo;s me. :)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>