<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>kogelberg on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/kogelberg/</link><description>Recent content in kogelberg on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 15:58:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/kogelberg/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #207: Kogelberg</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 15:58:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/</guid><description> The 207th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, which in theory should cover the week from Monday October 5 to Sunday October 11, 2020, is in fact only here to remind future me of that time when I took the Thursday October 8 off from work to go run the Kogelberg Trail with friends PK, TvD and EW.
(Ok, well maybe there is also a backyard philosophy thing hidden at the end of the post&amp;hellip;)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The 207th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, which in theory should cover the
week from Monday October 5 to Sunday October 11, 2020, is in fact only here to
remind future me of that time when I took the Thursday October 8 off from work
to go run the <a href="https://www.hikingsouthafrica.co.za/kogelberg-trail/">Kogelberg Trail</a> with friends PK, TvD and EW.</p>
<p>(Ok, well maybe there is also a backyard philosophy thing hidden at the end
of the post&hellip;)</p>








<figure><a href="kogelberg_5005.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hucd0249f279acfa062b67703f6a8b0a88_1726187_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: About halfway through the first climb"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: About halfway through the first climb</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="random-notes-on-the-kogelberg-trail-adventure">Random notes on the Kogelberg Trail adventure</h2>
<ul>
<li>Taking the day off to go run in the mountains: These two separately pleasant
actions are even greater when applied together.</li>
<li>Based on the predictions a week or so before the time, we were going to run
in a bit of rain. As the date came closer, the predicted start time of the
rain kept on creeping later and later. The day itself was mostly gorgeous
sunshine with very little wind.</li>
<li>According to the Cape Nature peeps at the starting point, we were the first
people to run the route since before the lockdown when they, err, locked down
the nature reserve. This was noticeable by the overgrown vegetation we had to
fight through for a kilometre or two, just after the first climb. Other than
that, it felt pretty special!</li>
<li>I like running with a GPX of the route on my Apple Watch (<a href="http://www.workoutdoors.net/">WorkOutDoors</a> is
amazing for following a route with maps while you&rsquo;re running, especially if
you&rsquo;re directionless like me), but I could not find one available online
before the time.
<ul>
<li>So I started a Strava Pro trial so I could use their amazing <a href="https://www.strava.com/heatmap">global heatmap</a>
to draw the crowd-sourced GPX in about 6 clicks. I&rsquo;m probably going to keep
the Strava Pro: Being able to make routes like this of any place that you
might find yourself in is amazing.</li>
<li>You can download a GPX of the route we actually ran, as logged by my
iPhone, by clicking on the following link: <a href="./kogelberg_trail_cpbotha_20201008.zip">Kogelberg Trail GPX</a>. The whole
thing is just under 24km.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Below is a video impression somewhere just past halfway. Don&rsquo;t miss the waterfall!</p>
<video controls>
<source src="kogelberg_trail_impression_20201008.mp4" type="video/mp4">
Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
<h2 id="find-a-place-in-the-universe-that-is-your-consciousness">Find a place in the universe that is your consciousness</h2>
<p>On the morning of October 7, about halfway through a 10 minute mindfulness
practice with <a href="https://wakingup.com/">the Waking Up app</a>, Sam Harris says something like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Take a negative emotion, and examine it. Remember, you can find a place in
consciousness that is not implicated, to stand on and be able to do this.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>His words really struck home at that moment.</p>
<p>By the end of the session, analysing a particular negative thought, I
experienced quite viscerally (haha, sorry) the phenomenon of relatively easily
finding a non-implicated mental space to stand, from where I could take apart
that negative emotion piece by piece, without being drawn into it at all.</p>
<p>Now it feels like all of those practice sessions exploring the <em>experience</em> of
consciousness, as the whole of the reality simulation being run over the
trillions of neural connections in the human brain, were not in vain.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>