<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>posterior tibial tendon on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/posterior-tibial-tendon/</link><description>Recent content in posterior tibial tendon on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 15:39:34 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/posterior-tibial-tendon/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2018 to 2019 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 15:39:34 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</guid><description> The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.
Welcome to this, the most recent (as of this writing) instance of the venerable WHV year transition post tradition!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house-1024x646.jpg"
        
            alt="The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to this, the most recent (as of this writing) instance of the venerable WHV year transition post tradition!</p>
<p>You can find previous editions here:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 to 2018</a> – short post, can be summarised as: “Sorry I stopped blogging for a while, I did run a bit, I’m going to blog more.”</li>
<li><a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">2016 to 2017</a> – substantial post (1800 words) with: “education will improve stupid politics; running, blogging, meditation; we made a new baby!!; kindness and gratefulness; life changes the whole time, deal with it.”</li>
<li><a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">2011 to 2012</a> – transition post disguised as WHV with: “stop doing life goals, disconnect more, list of miscellaneous life tips, because in 2011 I am not-even-40-yet Mr Wisdom”.</li>
<li><a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">2009 to 2010</a> – super short but sweet, I am clearly still new at this.</li>
</ul>
<p>Putting that list together just reminded me of an interesting observation: The more I try to take notes and document everything I see, the more I notice the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiscale_modeling">multiscalar</a> nature of my subjective experience being exposed.</p>
<p>I make detailed daily notes, all of them grouped in monthly text files.</p>
<p>At a slightly higher scale, the frequency of these WHV blog posts is somewhere between a post per week down to a post every three weeks.</p>
<p>When I write each blog post, I look back through the previous weeks, at a daily scale, and perform an extremely lossy summarisation.</p>
<p>When I write the year transitions, I perform an extremely lossy summarisation of the weekly-scale WHV posts.</p>
<p>The list above links together the various yearly transition posts, thus creating a lovely ball of multi-scalar confusion, which should not be confused with a lemur ball, shown below:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball-1024x682.jpg"
        
            alt="At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>WARNING: This post has grown into a long ramble over the past few days. I hope that you enjoy reading the ramble as much as I did thinking of you while writing it.</p>
<h2 id="focus-quantity-and-quality">Focus: Quantity and Quality.</h2>
<p>This post has been taking a while.</p>
<p>I am now back here at the start, after having been almost at the end, because I did not want you to have the idea that my 2018 did not have aspects I am not that happy with, or that I don’t use multiple negations in confusing ways often enough.</p>
<p><em>(As an aside, a friend and I have been exchanging photos of the less glamorous but entirely normal aspects of our vacations via WhatsApp: Plastic on the beach, the washing line, filthy toilets, truly terrible interior decor, and so on. What started as a joke has turned into an unintended but interesting psychological experiment in</em> <strong><em>reverse image crafting</em></strong><em>, strongly underlining the effect that this sort of communication can have.)</em></p>
<p>Back to my main story: During retrospection, I have the tendency to focus (sorry, couldn’t resist) on the good parts, because this is what I remember the best.</p>
<p>However, for the purpose of this post, I did want to spend some words on one of the (multiple!) issues that I struggled with in 2018.</p>
<p>Either I am getting worse at focusing, or I am getting better at noticing when I lose focus, or a combination of both.</p>
<p>At the very least <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">five of the posts I wrote in 2018 dealt in some way with</a> <em><a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">focus</a></em>.</p>
<p>The mentioned posts specifically and my thinking generally take the form of some analysis but mostly tools and tricks to try and improve the frequency, intensity and length of periods of focus.</p>
<p>(What you don’t read in the posts because of above-mentioned memory bias, is that there is usually a significant amount of inwardly-directed regret and disappointment involved.)</p>
<p>Even more subtle is the problem of selecting That One Most Suitable Thing to focus on. What’s going to have the most impact? What do I have capacity for at the moment? Can I trust my own subjective assessment of my current capacity, or is Lazy-Me being sneaky?</p>
<p>By the time I have made a decision, it’s probably wrong. <em>Sometimes</em> it’s a good decision, but by then the little block of time I had has flown away or has been blown to smithereens by the latest interruption, and so the quality of the decision is moot.</p>
<p>I would have expected that at this advanced age focus would come naturally and easily, and that I would know exactly what to do. However, I have had to accept that <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#slippery-slippery-focus">focus will probably remain this slippery</a> and require constant attention (haha I see what I did there) until the very end.</p>
<p>Besides eating well, sleeping well, exercising regularly and taking time to meditate (just in case!), our old friend <a href="https://cpbotha.net/?s=pomodoro">the pomodoro technique</a> is still the best tool in the box.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging.</h2>
<p>During 2018, 36 blog posts were published here, most of which were Weekly Head Voices. Those of you who have a math degree or two will not need much time to calculate that the “W” in “WHV” is at the moment mostly a little inside joke.</p>
<p>However, I did publish 14 more posts than I did in 2017, so there is hope for this year!</p>
<p>The wordpress.com statistics plugin reports just over 19000 visitors (unique IP numbers) who were responsible for just over 26000 page views for the whole year.</p>
<p>Because many people use some form of ad and/or tracking blocking these days, their visits won’t be counted, as the wordpress.com statistics relies on a tiny image which is hosted by wordpress.com, access to which is (rightfully) blocked by many blocker plugins.</p>
<p>In order to get a better idea of how many ad-blocker people read my stuff, I installed the <a href="https://wp-statistics.com/">wp-statistics</a> plugin, which locally tallies up all visits and hence is not blocked by blockers, at the start of March. For the period from March 2018 until the end of the year, it is reporting just over 74000 visitors and somewhere north of 390000 page hits.</p>
<p>Although to me this seems on the high side, I do think we can safely say that there were somewhere between 19000 and 74000 unique hosts, which to me is a very pleasant surprise.</p>
<p>However, I am by far the happiest due to all of the interactions I had with friends, mostly old and some new, on this blog. Most recently, the comments section of <a href="/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/">WHV #156</a> blew up in such a brilliant way!</p>
<p>More generally speaking, even when there are no comments, I know that throughout the year I am connecting with various subsets of my peeps through the posts on this blog. This acts as tremendous motivation to keep on writing. If even a single friend reads, it has been more than worth it.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, there is now a</em> <a href="https://t.me/headvoices"><em>telegram group, quite surprisingly called “headvoices”</em></a><em>, that you can join to receive a summary whenever a new post is published, and for general chitchat. Although so far only two of my most avant-garde friends have joined, this new form of blog-related communication excites me!)</em></p>
<h3 id="looking-forward">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>Surprisingly, I again will aim to write one WHV post per week.</p>
<p>I will probably fail again, but I believe that this is one of those cases of “aim for the stars, reach the moon”.</p>
<p>As mentioned above, writing these letters and writing them regularly is really important to me.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, I should probably have declared <strong>email bankruptcy</strong> years ago. I am</em> <strong><em>just</em></strong> <em>managing to keep head above water, but writing letters to friends like we used to do in the old days is becoming increasingly difficult. What is your feeling currently re email and how it has changed over the past few years?)</em></p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>Strava says I ran 1286km in 2018.</p>
<p>Seeing that I had set myself a private goal of 1000km for 2018 (2016 was 440km and <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 was 880km</a>), I am quite happy with this.</p>
<p>(As an aside, I spent 119 hours running, spread out over a total of 149 runs, which means 2.86 runs every week of the year.)</p>
<p>I did 770 of those 1286 kilometres in sandals, and a further 35km on barefoot.</p>
<p>More importantly, I had to learn the humbling lesson that no amount of stubborn, brute-force exercise could work around the fact I am flat footed (arch-challenged?), resulting in easily overworked posterior tibial tendons.</p>
<p>As I pushed my weekly distance up, my feet complained more loudly, until I was forced to go back to normal-person-running-shoes.</p>
<p>After a few weeks eating humble pie in running shoes, things are going much better, and I recently did my first short and careful run in sandals.</p>
<p>(Similar to the observation confirmed by <a href="https://veronikach.com/progress-reports/my-goals-for-2018-final-progress-report/">the pattern recognition heroine veronikach in her end-of-2018 post</a>, I too ran slower this year in order to run better. I did this for the largest part due to my temporarily busted ankles, but also because more experienced athletes at work recommended heart rate training. For the past few hundreds of kilometres, I have regulated my running speed to try and keep my heart rate within the 75% to 85% of maximum range, mostly ending up closer to 85% than 80%. This has increased the occurrence of those addictive perfect runs, and it has helped to keep my ankles out of trouble.)</p>
<h3 id="looking-forward-1">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>In 2019, I would be happy to <em>maintain</em> my 2018 monthly running quota, to remain injury-free, and to maximise my running zen.</p>
<p>(“Running slow” explained above can contribute substantially to the latter two goals.)</p>
<p>I do have an additional concrete (but very humble) running-related resolution for 2019, but I have decided to keep that quiet until it’s in the pocket. :)</p>
<h2 id="other-plans-for-2019">Other plans for 2019.</h2>
<h3 id="experiment-alcohol-zero">Experiment Alcohol Zero #2.</h3>
<p>Yesterday, which at the time of writing is January 4, 2019, was the first day of EAZ #2.</p>
<p>It has been two years since <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#experiment-alcohol-zero">the previous EAZ in 2016</a>. The previous experiment coincided with a significant jump in my running performance, the effects of which did not fade away after the end of the experiment.</p>
<p>This time around, the plan is to run EAZ for at least as long as in 2016, but hopefully a few days or weeks longer.</p>
<p>(I should probably call this EA&lt;0.5, as that is what my current favourite “alcohol-free” beer, Devil’s Peak Zero to Hero, claims.)</p>
<h3 id="ship-more-side-projects">Ship more side-projects.</h3>
<p>Most nerds I know have <em>side-projects</em>.</p>
<p>These are the technical artifacts, systems and machines one builds, because one can’t stop building stuff, even after work ends.</p>
<p>Like most nerds, I have a number of these that started with high momentum (new programming language, new tools, new problem, EXCITING! … 3 hours later … NOVELTY COMPLETELY WORN OFF doh.) and are now lying around gathering dust.</p>
<p>Inspired by a colleague who managed to ship <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/656740/Cosmonator/">a brilliant shooter game side-project on Steam</a> last year, I made myself the promise to ship more side-projects.</p>
<p>After that, I managed to ship two side-projects, one small and the other quite tiny.</p>
<p>This was a satisfying experience that I would like to continue in 2019.</p>
<p>(P.S. the problem with shipping side-projects, is that you now have more things that you actually have to look after. Next year I’ll think up a resolution for unmaintained shipped side-projects.)</p>
<h3 id="mindful-more">Mindful more.</h3>
<p>This is a simple one.</p>
<p>I used to spend a few minutes every second morning before work doing simple mindfulness breathing and focus exercises.</p>
<p>It was worth the modest time investment many times over, in terms of focus, and especially in terms of seeing life in perspective.</p>
<p>In the second half of 2018 I let this habit slip for some or other reason. I think it’s because I convinced myself that running time could also count as meditation time.</p>
<p>In 2019, I’m going to #bringbackthemeditation.</p>
<h3 id="learn-more">Learn more.</h3>
<p>During 2018, I started taking a more structured approach to the books I wanted to read, and the courses I wanted to follow, by tracking these in my <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">sneaky longer term goals which form part of my daily planning routine</a>.</p>
<p>More structure meant more books read to completion, and more courses followed, resulting in an Ever So Slightly Improved Me.</p>
<p>I am planning to continue and extend this practice in 2019.</p>
<h3 id="evolve-the-system">Evolve The System.</h3>
<p>The System.</p>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
<p>One step, and then another, and then another, until the lights finally go out.</p>
<h3 id="try-to-grow-a-tree">Try to grow a tree.</h3>
<p>I grew up with a fuerte avocado tree that gave us hundreds of the divine fruit every season.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 40 odd years, and my mom (HI MOM!) gave us a beautiful baby fuerte avocado tree for Christmas!







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree-805x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>We are currently trying to nurture it through its first few weeks of life in our garden.</p>
<p>With the summer sun, and the new environment, it’s a bit touch and go at the moment, but we’re really rooting for that baby tree! (bad pun quota exhausted now?!)</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This is it my friends.</p>
<p>You have made it to the end, an endeavour for which I am truly grateful.</p>
<p>I wish you a 2019 filled with growth, health and happiness.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #158: Charlie and the Chocolate Factory.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/11/22/weekly-head-voices-158-charlie-and-the-chocolate-factory/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2018 20:20:39 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/11/22/weekly-head-voices-158-charlie-and-the-chocolate-factory/</guid><description> (Note that there’s now a Telegram group that you can join to be kept up to date with these posts. I’m never going to make the A-List, but at least I haz the gimmicks!)
This edition of the weekly (haha) head voices attempts to reflect on the period of time from Monday November 5 to Sunday November 18, 2018.
The following action scene happened exactly halfway through: Pre-requisite running photo, this one taken in Paarl.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(Note that there’s now a <a href="https://t.me/headvoices">Telegram group</a> that you can join to be kept up to date with these posts. I’m never going to make the A-List, but at least I haz the gimmicks!)</em></p>
<p>This edition of the weekly (haha) head voices attempts to reflect on the period of time from Monday November 5 to Sunday November 18, 2018.</p>
<p>The following action scene happened exactly halfway through:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/paarl-running-20181111.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/paarl-running-20181111-1024x642.jpg"
        
            alt="Pre-requisite running photo, this one taken in Paarl. It was already quite hot. Getting really hot really early in the morning is Paarl’s thing."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pre-requisite running photo, this one taken in Paarl. It was already quite hot. Getting really hot really early in the morning is Paarl’s thing.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<h1 id="running-aka-irony-update">Running aka Irony update</h1>
<p>Seeing that you’ve made me talk about running again, have a look at this photo of one Luna Mono 2.0 after about 700 km of (mostly road) running in about seven months, and one brand new Luna Mono 2.0:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/old-vs-new-lunas.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/old-vs-new-lunas-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>At around about the same time as the new shoes arrived, shortly after South African customs charged me a painful amount before letting the new babies through, both my ankles, from around the posterior tibial tendon area, let me know in no uncertain terms that they were now <em>demanding</em> a break.</p>
<p>After repeated explanations by my life partner (she counts being a rheumatologist amongst her many talents), and by a foot surgeon friend, that my flat feet mean that my posterior tibial tendons have to work even harder than they would usually have done had I been anatomically speaking more normal, I had to start facing the music:</p>
<p><em>I was going to have to wear normal person running shoes again.</em></p>
<p>(If I have to be honest I would have to say that the music was in fact more about having to take a running break. I had sneakily been pushing up my weekly distance, trying to run through ankle discomfort, and this was probably the true core of the problem.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I am choosing to interpret matters a bit differently. Running breaks are really hard yo.)</p>
<p>I’ve now done two runs in my pre-Mono Kinvara 8s, and it does indeed feel (of course it does) like my ankles might slowly be recovering. I am hopeful that the trend continues, and that I can eventually rotate in my Lunas again.</p>
<h1 id="nerd-toys-update-rtx-2070-in-da-house">Nerd toys update: RTX 2070 in da house.</h1>
<p>After weeks of deliberating, I broke down and bought an <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/geforce/graphics-cards/rtx-2070/">NVIDIA RTX 2070</a> for deep learning.</p>
<p>This in turn led to a flurry of experimentation and to be quite honest a slight case of deep learning binging.</p>
<p>At least I have the following new blog posts to show for it:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/11/04/pytorch-1-0-preview-nov-4-2018-packages-with-full-cuda-10-support-for-your-ubuntu-18-04-x86_64-systems/">PyTorch 1.0 preview (Nov 10, 2018) packages with full CUDA 10 support for your Ubuntu 18.04 x86_64 systems</a> – In order to use the shiny new TensorCores on the RTX for more efficient deep learning, you need a CUDA 10 build of PyTorch. YOUR WISH IS MY COMMAND.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/11/19/configuring-emacs-lsp-mode-and-microsofts-visual-studio-code-python-language-server/">Configuring Emacs, lsp-mode and Microsoft’s Visual Studio Code Python language server</a> – When you prefer using Emacs inside of a tmux in a mosh or ssh session to your Linux desktop with the RTX 2070 to develop PyTorch and fastai scripts (no Jupyter in sight, what a relief!), you need the best code-intelligence you can get. Visual Studio Code’s Python Language Server McGuyvered right into Emacs will do nicely thanks!</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/11/21/a-simple-ansible-script-to-convert-a-clean-ubuntu-18-04-to-a-cuda-10-pytorch-1-0rc-fastai-miniconda3-deep-learning-machine/">A Simple Ansible script to convert a clean Ubuntu 18.04 to a CUDA 10, PyTorch 1.0rc, fastai, miniconda3 deep learning machine</a> – When you need MOAR firepower to train your networks with larger batch sizes, or just to see how much memory your network would have taken in fp32 mode instead of mixed-precision, this ansible script will reproducibly convert a clean Ubuntu 18.04 GPU instance, such as that supplied by PaperSpace or Google Compute Engine, into a CUDA 10, PyTorch, fastai, miniconda3 deep learning playground, all in about 10 minutes.</li>
</ul>
<p>(I know that some of these occurred outside of the two week timespan covered by this post.)</p>
<h2 id="on-the-memory-saving-of-mixed-precision-training">On the memory saving of mixed-precision training.</h2>
<p>In my tests with ResNet50, a serious convolutional neural network for image classification, the exact same network with the exact same training settings required 14159 MiB in fp32 mode but only 7641 MiB in mixed precision mode.</p>
<p>This means that in some cases, this new RTX 2070 can go toe-to-toe with many far more expensive cards.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I informally measured a training speed boost of about 20% with the smaller ResNet34.</p>
<p>It’s no wonder that the <a href="http://timdettmers.com/2018/11/05/which-gpu-for-deep-learning/">RTX 2070 gets the Tim Dettmers stamp of approval for the most cost-effective training</a>.</p>
<h1 id="your-message-to-take-home">Your message, to take home.</h1>
<p>I came across this backyard philosophy jewel <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/todayilearned/comments/9ozu4e/til_in_test_screenings_willy_wonka_had_a_scene/">on reddit the other day</a> and loved it. It’s about the 1971 movie W_illy Wonka &amp; the Chocolate Factory_, a stellar adaptation of Roald Dahl’s book <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_and_the_Chocolate_Factory">Charlie and the Chocolate Factory</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>… in test screenings, Willy Wonka had a scene with a hiker seeking a guru, asking him the meaning of life. The guru requests a Wonka Bar. Finding no golden ticket, he says, “Life is a disappointment.” The director loved it, but few laughed. A psychologist told him that the message was too real.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just remember the <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#the-buddhist-twist">Buddhist Twist</a> my friends:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>… and finally passing through the gate of wishlessness (apranihita) – realizing that nirvana is the state of not even wishing for nirvana.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #156: Karma Chameleon.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 20:56:19 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/</guid><description> Scene from a recent lunch with a very flat cat. Whilst appreciating these moments with direct experience mode set to 11, one does have to realise that it’s all much more complicated than it looks.
Welcome to this, the 156th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, voices who are planning to sing about the two weeks from Monday October 8 to Sunday October 21.
Summer has arrived, and it’s really very hot down here.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/cavalli_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/cavalli_view-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Scene from a recent lunch with a very flat cat. Whilst appreciating these moments with direct experience mode set to 11, one does have to realise that it’s all much more complicated than it looks."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Scene from a recent lunch with a very flat cat. Whilst appreciating these moments with direct experience mode set to 11, one does have to realise that it’s all much more complicated than it looks.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to this, the 156th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, voices who are planning to sing about the two weeks from Monday October 8 to Sunday October 21.</p>
<p>Summer has arrived, and it’s really very hot down here.</p>
<p>As I’m writing this at 21:41, I am doing my best to limit my motion to the absolute minimum in a bid to keep my temperature within healthy limits.</p>
<p>You have to imagine me sitting utterly still, almost like a chameleon on a twig, with only my fingers making small darting movements over the keyboard.</p>
<p>Time is fun when you’re having flies.</p>
<h1 id="karma-running">Karma Running.</h1>
<p>This morning, after losing all my karma in traffic (there was an accident on one of the main roads in my town, resulting in the normally already impressive level of stupidity of the driving mob, which I am part of, reaching hitherto unseen levels; WHEN IS THE AI GOING TO TAKE OVER PLEASE?!), I started my long road to forgiveness, and zen, by taking a barefoot run on the beach near my place of work.</p>
<p>It looked like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/strand_run.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/strand_run-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Goldilocks sand: Not too hard, not too soft, just right."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Goldilocks sand: Not too hard, not too soft, just right.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I wish I could better communicate how it felt.</p>
<p>Imagine the 30 Celsius morning sun on your back, a slight breeze from the sea and your bare feet rhythmically brushing the wet sand as you glide softly along the coast.</p>
<p>Simply keep on doing this until your body creates the stillness that your mind needs.</p>
<p>This is my new favourite run.</p>
<h1 id="mafish">MAF(ish).</h1>
<p>A friend from work told me about this idea of exercising at 80% of your maximum heart rate.</p>
<p>The idea behind this is to <a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/beginner/a20812270/should-i-do-heart-rate-training/">train your aerobic system without injuring anything, and also to be able to do so with much more volume</a> (read: more kilometres).</p>
<p>Four weeks ago I tried to squeeze in too much running in the half hour I had at my disposal. Due to me being doubly stupid, I also did this in my Xero Tolerance 5mm sole sandals, and so I was rewarded with a brand new kind of pain in my posterior tibial tendon.</p>
<p>This is the same tendon <a href="/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/#weekend-running-update">previously mentioned on this blog</a>, also in the context of running injuries.</p>
<p>However, this time I must have injured the tendon more effectively than the previous time (practice makes perfect!), because the pain seemed to be a more permanent new inhabitant of my foot.</p>
<p>Long story short, the suggestion of lower heart rate training came at the perfect time, with my ankle serving as a continuous and visceral (literally) reminder to keep an eye on my heart rate.</p>
<p>This has been going swimmingly.</p>
<p>I am slowly increasing my distance, but, more importantly, runs are again characterised by a whole lot of grinning.</p>
<p>It has not escaped me that a man running on sandals (or barefoot) with a probably fairly unpredictable-looking grin on his big hairy face could give fellow humans pause for thought.</p>
<h1 id="grab-bag-of-thought--andor-debate-provoking-pieces">Grab bag of thought- and/or debate-provoking pieces.</h1>
<h2 id="not-exercising-worse-for-your-health-than-smoking-diabetes-and-heart-disease-study-reveals3"><a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2018/10/19/health/study-not-exercising-worse-than-smoking/index.html">Not exercising worse for your health than smoking, diabetes and heart disease, study reveals</a></h2>
<p>Over a period of more than 20 years, 122000 people were put on a treadmill at Cleveland clinic. It turns out that exercise plays a crucial role in not dying.</p>
<p>Core quote: “Being unfit on a treadmill or in an exercise stress test has a worse prognosis, as far as death, than being hypertensive, being diabetic or being a current smoker”.</p>
<h2 id="avoiding-meat-and-dairy-is-single-biggest-way-to-reduce-your-impact-on-earth4"><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2018/may/31/avoiding-meat-and-dairy-is-single-biggest-way-to-reduce-your-impact-on-earth">Avoiding meat and dairy is ‘single biggest way’ to reduce your impact on Earth</a></h2>
<p>I’m really sorry about this one, fellow meat lovers.</p>
<p>This also looks like a pretty solid study. Core quote: “The new research shows that without meat and dairy consumption, global farmland use could be reduced by more than 75% – an area equivalent to the US, China, European Union and Australia combined – and still feed the world.”</p>
<p>(I have slowly started to work on the vegetarian recipe section of my notes.)</p>
<h2 id="worlds-largest-sleep-study-shows-too-much-shut-eye-can-be-bad-for-your-brain5"><a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2018-10/uowo-wls100918.php">World’s largest sleep study shows too much shut-eye can be bad for your brain</a></h2>
<p>It is <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">well known</a> that we here at The Voices are huge fans of sleep.</p>
<p>However, now it turns out that lots of sleep is not going to cut it. You have to sleep just the right amount: Not too much and not too little.</p>
<p>You probably knew this, but this large study confirms it: Between 7 and 8 hours of sleep, no more and no less, is best for optimal mental performance.</p>
<p>Hard hitting quote: “One startling revelation was that most participants who slept four hours or less performed as if they were almost nine years older.”</p>
<h1 id="the-end">The End</h1>
<p>Thank you for connecting with me by reading this post. I am already looking forward to our next encounter, whichever form that may take!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #148: Data stylist.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 07:22:30 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/</guid><description> Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)
This post covers the week from Monday July 9 to Sunday July 15.
The business part of my week was unfairly dominated by far too much after-work obsessing over programming languages, with which I seem to have an unhealthy (or perhaps not) obsession.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/drakenstein_trail.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/drakenstein_trail-1024x241.jpg"
        
            alt="Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This post covers the week from Monday July 9 to Sunday July 15.</p>
<p>The business part of my week was unfairly dominated by far too much after-work obsessing over programming languages, with which I seem to have an unhealthy (or perhaps not) obsession.</p>
<p>I will externalise some of these thoughts further down in this post.</p>
<p>I’m starting with a weekend / running update, which should be reasonably safe for non-nerds to read. However, after that, the nerd dial will go up to 11 with stuff about tools and programming languages right up to the end of the post.</p>
<p>I would have wanted to use the adjective “face-melting”, but I’m not sure if any intensity of nerdery could ever reach that level.</p>
<p>We can dream.</p>
<h1 id="weekend-running-update">Weekend running update</h1>
<p>Most fortunately the weekend had other plans and supplied us with at least 2.5 parties, the first of which even culminated in a <em>ridiculously</em> fun trail run in the mountains on the winter morning after.</p>
<p>The winter morning sun was just perfect, the company was great, and I had forgotten all forms of performance tracking devices at home.</p>
<p>Readers with bionic eyes might notice the Lunas on my feet.</p>
<p>I have now ran just over 260km in them, but, in a surprise twist to the regular readers of this blog, my biological equipment has still not yet completely adjusted to the new style of locomotion.</p>
<p>The latest victim seems to be one of Tom, Dick and Harry, the tendons running under the medial <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malleolus">malleolus</a> of my left foot, also known as that big knob on your inside ankle. Tom (the primary suspect in this case according to Trail Friend #1 who is knowledgable with regard to these matters, being a running foot surgeon and all), Dick and Harry <a href="https://radiopaedia.org/articles/posterior-ankle-tendons-mnemonic">are also known as the *T*ibialis posterior, flexor *D*igitorum longus and the flexor *H*allucis longus</a>.</p>
<p>They currently have to work extra hard to stabilise my feet while running, because, you know, no shoes.</p>
<p>Because doing this thing was not hard enough already, and because the Lunas are perhaps still a bit too cushiony, and because my friend the Very Flat Cat forgot that I’m very suggestible after 11:00 in the morning when my prefrontal cortex takes the rest of the day off, I am now also the very shy owner of a pair of <a href="https://xeroshoes.com/shop/genesis/genesis-men/">Xero Genesis running sandals</a>:</p>
<p><img src="https://xeroshoes.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/Genesis_Limeade-3-4-770x500.jpg" alt="Image result for xero genesis"></p>
<p>The soles are only 5mm thick, and quite hard, being <a href="https://xeroshoes.com/warranty/">rated for a few thousand miles</a> and all. The upshot of this is that one’s feet have to work even harder than in the Lunas.</p>
<p>My first run in these was amazing: I could feel my feet reacting to every little pebble, and my running style having to adapt even more to the terrain.</p>
<p>However, there was a price to pay for all of that additional terrain feel (and the fact that I took a much longer maiden run than I should have): The next day, the tendons in my feet felt even more (ab)used than usual.</p>
<p>WITH GREAT POWER COMES GREAT RESPONSIBILITY, it seems.</p>
<p>Due to these shoes being so powerful, I have had to resign to introducing Xero running far more gradually than I had initially thought.</p>
<h1 id="vacation-based-thinking-driven-tool-sharpening-aka-the-wvv-2018-data-science-toolboxtm">Vacation-based-thinking-driven tool sharpening aka The WVV 2018 Data Science Toolbox(tm).</h1>
<p>During the <a href="/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/">previously blogged-about</a> Mpumalanga vacation, the lack of alarms, devices, and other work accoutrements, resulted in there being ample time for staring-into-space-grade thinking sessions.</p>
<p>During one of these thinking sessions, I realised that I had somehow neglected my data science toolbox for a while.</p>
<p>At some point a few years back, I was so into ipython notebooks (what has now become jupyter) that I used them as my main work lab notes modality.</p>
<p>However, in the meantime I had fallen slightly out of love with the computational notebook style of data programming, because I had begun to develop doubts about their role in the analysis pipeline.</p>
<p><strong>interlude 1:</strong> <em>jupyter notebooks are nice for initial data exploration, and they’re especially useful for remote computation with embedded graphics. However, that initial momentum of discovery risks devolving into an unwieldy monolith of code snippets, data transformations and experiments. There’s a fine line to be walked between flexible experimentation on the one hand, and version-controlled, time-stamped, permutational and scientific rigour on the other.</em></p>
<p><strong>interlude 2:</strong> <em>I have to apologise for using the term “data science” in a non-comedic context. In spite of the inherent humour, it has turned into a usable blanket term for computational data understanding.</em></p>
<p>Due to my growing doubts in the order of Jupyter, and due to being occupied with less traditionally data sciencey work projects, I had unfortunately let my data science toolbox gather perhaps a bit too much dust.</p>
<p>Slightly more worrying than falling out of love with the Jupyter Notebooks (I still like them, I’m just not that madly in love anymore), was the more specific issue that I’d even let the datavis parts get a bit dusty.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Although I should probably write a more complete post about this, here is the list of ingredients of the official <em><strong>2018 WHV Data Science Toolbox(tm)</strong></em>:</p>
<h2 id="programming-language-and-library-ecosystem-python">Programming language and library ecosystem: Python.</h2>
<p>This language, in spite of its shortcomings, <em>dominates</em> the data science / machine learning world thanks to its STELLAR ecosystem.</p>
<p>numpy, pandas, scipy, scikit-*, tensorflow, pytorch, keras, cython… this snowball has turned into a pretty sizeable planet.</p>
<p>For this reason, it would be hard to justify any other choice for data science.</p>
<p>However, since I’ve been seeing more of Lisp and the rest of the ever-expanding programming language landscape, I can see (Python’s shortcomings as a programming language) clearly now.</p>
<p>In terms of interactive programming, Python beats the majority of practical programming languages, with Common Lisp being one notable exception.</p>
<p>However, it’s not functional enough, which engenders unnecessarily imperative, side-effecting code.  More specifically, it’s not expression-oriented.</p>
<p>More about this slightly further down. Maybe.</p>
<h2 id="datavis-anything-as-long-as-its-vega-or-vega-lite">Datavis: Anything, as long as it’s Vega or Vega-Lite.</h2>
<p>I spent a few years of my life wrangling <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a>, down to INNARD-LEVEL.</p>
<p>Mike Bostock’s idea of <a href="https://bost.ocks.org/mike/join/">data-element-joins</a> is genius, and internalising it was intellectually satisfying.</p>
<p>I thought that these d3 skillz would serve me well for decades (that’s WEEKS in javascript-time), but it turns out that there’s a new, even smarter kid in town.</p>
<p>(if it’s any consolation, the new kid can be considered the grand-child of d3.js.)</p>
<p><a href="https://vega.github.io/">vega and vega-lite</a> are so-called visualization grammars, or visualization DSLs (domain specific languages).</p>
<p>The upshot is that one codes up a chart, or a whole set of linked charts and their interactive behaviour, using a language that was designed for this purpose.</p>
<p>This chart code can be easily shared, or converted into interactive visual representations that can be embedded in applications, online or in print quality documents.</p>
<p>Genius!</p>
<p>With <a href="https://altair-viz.github.io/">Altair</a>, you can even send your pandas dataframes to vega and vega-lite charts all from the comfort of your slightly defective Python armchair.</p>
<h2 id="development-environment-pycharm">Development Environment: PyCharm.</h2>
<p>You knew it was not going to be Jupyter Notebooks, but you probably expected it to be <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tag/emacs/">Emacs</a>.</p>
<p>Well it’s not. Surprise!</p>
<p>The remote interpreter support in PyCharm enables me to connect to a Python virtual environment anywhere on the planet, which I often do.</p>
<p>The JetBrains wizards have optimised the remote communication of code intelligence, so completion, documentation and general code understanding is almost indistinguishable from that on a completely local project.</p>
<p>Being able to step through a <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/12/08/variational-autoencoder-in-pytorch-commented-and-annotated/"><em>remote</em> PyTorch neural network training iteration with the PyCharm debugger</a> or any other remote Python algorithmics is insightful.</p>
<p>Two notable drawbacks are visualization and long-running jobs.</p>
<p>For the long-running jobs I do tend to use Jupyter Notebooks or when at all possible <a href="https://mosh.org/">mosh</a>, which is amazing. However, because the primary modality is not the notebook, my code is versioned and organised into separate libraries which I can call into from notebook or mosh.</p>
<p>For visualization, it’s either connecting to the altair chart server via SSH pipe, dumping the chart to the unison-synced project, and/or a Jupyter Notebook.</p>
<h2 id="the-rest">The rest.</h2>
<p>Of course you use Postgres on an SSD for your data, and of course you know enough SQL to make short work of most of the heavy-weight transformations often required at the start your data crunching pipeline.</p>
<p>For all of my lab notes, reports, books, papers and blog posts, I use <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tag/orgmode/">Emacs Org mode</a>.</p>
<p>LaTeX math with live preview, live code snippets, SVG graphics, bibtex references, export to anything. This is one of the best ways to document your science.</p>
<h1 id="programming-language-addiction-update">Programming language addiction update.</h1>
<p>I spend far too much obsessing over programming languages, old and new.</p>
<p>For the past two weeks, I wasted even more precious time than usual reading up about programming languages.</p>
<p>Because I would really like to spend more of my time on other, perhaps more valuable activities, I’ve been trying to better define what it is I’m actually looking for.</p>
<p>Of course there is no single best programming language, but a whole set of good languages that map in intricate ways to different problem domains.</p>
<p>In spite of this, I have been pining for a language with, in order of importance:</p>
<ol>
<li>A Functional Programming DNA, with which I’m referring to a) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expression-oriented_programming_language">expression-orientedness</a>, b) a preference for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pure_function">pure functions</a>, and at a higher level, c) the modelling of reality as more or less explicit dataflows.</li>
<li>Interactive programming, with Common Lisp being the textbook example of this.</li>
<li>Great tooling and IDEs, meaning first-class support by something from JetBrains, Microsoft or Emacs.</li>
<li>Great concurrency and parallelism stories.</li>
<li>A great library ecosystem.</li>
<li>Modest memory use.</li>
</ol>
<p>Having just explicitly written this down for the first time (!! – it was consuming so much glucose just being kept amorphously swirling around in my brain) I can now mentally map some of my most recent language dalliances to these points.</p>
<h2 id="go">go</h2>
<p>This language is far too simple for my taste, but probably really great for teams.</p>
<p>I did recently take a more serious look when <a href="https://tutorials.botsfloor.com/develop-your-own-telegram-bot-with-golang-and-tbot-de726883b83c">setting up a telegram bot using tbot</a> and being amazed at how simple it was building web services like these using goroutines and channels.</p>
<p>Go satisfies points 3 to 6 from the list above. Makes sense that I decided to file this experiment away under “check when you need to put a webservice together REALLY QUICKLY”.</p>
<h2 id="rust">rust</h2>
<p>When I saw up that rust, surprisingly, is an expression-oriented language, I flew through the O’Reilly Programming Rust book I had bought previously as part of a bundle.</p>
<p>Evaluating rust by the list above, we award it a fractional 1 because expression-oriented, 3 due to jetbrains plugin amongst others, 4(ish) – great memory safety, but compared to clojure, concurrency and parallelism stories still have much room to grow, a solid 5 thanks to cargo and a very strong 6.</p>
<p>I filed this one away under “re-evaluate whenever you reach for your trusty C++”. (also, <a href="https://github.com/actix/actix-web">actix-web</a> looks amazing for super high performance microservices.)</p>
<h2 id="f">f#</h2>
<p>You didn’t see this one coming, did you?</p>
<p>Very strong 1 to 5 and a solid 6.</p>
<p>WAT?!</p>
<p>I’m currently working my way through <a href="https://pragprog.com/book/swdddf/domain-modeling-made-functional">Domain Modeling Made Functional</a> by Scott Wlaschin, who is also the author of the brilliant <a href="https://fsharpforfunandprofit.com/">f# for fun and profit</a> website.</p>
<p>In addition to f# hitting all 6 of my 2018 PL-requirements above, I’m slowly starting to see the advantages of having a real type system under the hood.</p>
<p>f# is a member of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ML_(programming_language)">ML-family</a> of functional languages, which have their origin in Lisp (some very naughty person removed all of the lovely parentheses I’m afraid…).</p>
<p>I hope that at some point I’ll have the opportunity to use f# in anger, at which point I’ll be able to report more concretely as to its suitability.</p>
<h1 id="the-end">The End</h1>
<p>Let me know in the comments what you think about any of this, or anything else.</p>
<p>I hope to meet you again in a few days, here or elsewhere.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>