<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>linkedin on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/linkedin/</link><description>Recent content in linkedin on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2011 21:41:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/linkedin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Astropsychonaut. [Weekly Head Voices #63]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/12/03/astropsychonaut-weekly-head-voices-63/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2011 21:41:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/12/03/astropsychonaut-weekly-head-voices-63/</guid><description> I recently came across this hauntingly beatiful time-lapse view of Earth made from the ISS (the International Space Station! Yes, we have one!):
Watching this, my nostalgia flared up. You see, I’ve been addicted to science fiction ever since I can remember. It started with Buck Rogers, and the original Star Trek, and only got much worse when I discovered Arthur C. Clarke, Ray Bradbury, Isaac Asimov and Douglas Hill.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I recently came across this hauntingly beatiful time-lapse view of Earth made from the ISS (the International Space Station! Yes, we have one!):</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<div class="embed-vimeo" style="text-align: center;">
<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="473" mozallowfullscreen="" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/32001208" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="840"></iframe>
</div>
</div>
<p>Watching this, my nostalgia flared up. You see, I’ve been addicted to science fiction ever since I can remember. It started with Buck Rogers, and the original Star Trek, and only got much worse when I discovered Arthur C. Clarke, Ray Bradbury, Isaac Asimov and Douglas Hill. I find Kubrick’s 2001 and even the sequel movie 2010 beautiful.</p>
<p>For the longest time, I wanted to be an astronaut. I think I still do.</p>
<p>I believe I might have thought that my career plans would be seen as childish when I wrote this short piece for school detailing my life plans when I was 7 or 8 (late eighties, not saying anymore):








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/cpbotha_life_plans.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/cpbotha_life_plans.jpg"
        
            alt="My life plans as a 7 or 8 year old. My brother found this somewhere and put it on facebook. I wonder what it would be like to go back in time and explain that concept to myself."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>My life plans as a 7 or 8 year old. My brother found this somewhere and put it on facebook. I wonder what it would be like to go back in time and explain that concept to myself.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>For those of you without the required Afrikaans background, here is a short translation, as true as possible to the original:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When I gow up, I’d like to work with computers, because then I’ll become really smart and I’ll know more about the outdoors and nature. As I grow older, I’ll become a professor, because perhaps I’ll find a cure for leprosy and after that I’m going to study to be a millionaire, because then I’ll go abroad or around the world.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Not a bad plan for a 7 or 8 year old, if you don’t mind me saying so myself. This note has in fact reminded me that there’s still more than enough decisions to be made and work to do, so I’ll have to postpone becoming an astronaut for a little while longer. At least by the end I’m going to end up a rich traveller, which is probably not a bad deal.</p>
<p>In other news this week:</p>
<ul>
<li>It seems like just the other day that I made my <a href="/2011/05/22/just-one-thing-weekly-head-voices-49/" title="400th connection on LinkedIn connection post">400th connection on LinkedIn</a>. I’m happy to report that I broke the 500 barrier two weeks ago, and now I have that fancy looking “500+” next to my name. I finetuned my headline to celebrate the occasion, after which I promptly got approached by a head hunter.</li>
<li>Jonathan Dyer is the guru of facial hair. Check out <a href="http://www.dyers.org/blog/beards/beard-types/" title="dyers' beard types">all the beard types and accompanying facial expressions</a> that he has mastered. Yes, that’s a hint of jealousy that you detect in my writing.</li>
<li>More reasons to love the coffee: Giving rats the equivalent of what a human gets after two cups of coffee, the caffeine caused nerve cells in a certain region of the hippocampus to show a significantly bigger burst of activity. These strengthened synapses might have a role in learning and memory. Read <a href="http://boingboing.net/2011/11/21/caffeines-boosts-signals-in-th.html" title="coffee good for hippocampus activity (boingbonig)">this summary on boingboing</a> and <a href="http://www.nature.com/neuro/journal/vaop/ncurrent/abs/nn.2962.html" title="nature neuroscience article on effect of coffee on activty in CA2 of hippocampus">the article on Nature Neuroscience</a>.</li>
<li>In an exceptionally disappointing move, <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/southafrica/8907057/South-Africa-passes-secrecy-bill.html" title="south african secrecy bill in the telegraph">South African parliament has passed a new secrecy bill</a> that gives members of government the power to declare information a state secret, thus deterring honest-keeping journalists and other whistle-blowers with a 25 year jail sentence. Desmond Tutu sums it up nicely when he says that this makes the State answerable only to the State.</li>
</ul>
<div>
<p>
<span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 23px;">If this new bill manages to make it through the constitutional court as well, the country is going to take a giant step backwards. At least we’ll have <a href="http://drinkfacedrink.com/">facedrink</a> to cheer us up again!<a data-rel="lightbox-image-1" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/facedrink1.jpg" title=""><img alt="" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-1579" data-attachment-id="1579" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":""}' data-image-title="facedrink1" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/facedrink1.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/facedrink1-114x300.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/facedrink1.jpg" data-orig-size="152,400" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2011/12/03/astropsychonaut-weekly-head-voices-63/facedrink1/" height="300" sizes="(max-width: 114px) 85vw, 114px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/facedrink1-114x300.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/facedrink1-114x300.jpg 114w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/facedrink1.jpg 152w" title="facedrink1" width="114"/></a></span>
</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Just One Thing. [weekly head voices #49]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/05/22/just-one-thing-weekly-head-voices-49/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2011 12:31:51 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/05/22/just-one-thing-weekly-head-voices-49/</guid><description> (post summary: linkedin news, the week in bullets, backyard philosophy!)
Dearest readers,
Yesterday I made my 400th LinkedIn connection. Yes, I know there are people with zillions of LinkedIn connections, but mine are special. I’ve actually had contact, outside of LinkedIn, with each and everyone of them. In most cases the contact has been in person, in some cases even involving beer, and in the others the contact has been sufficiently significant, by my metrics of course, to warrant a real connection.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(post summary: linkedin news, the week in bullets, backyard philosophy!)</em></p>
<p>Dearest readers,</p>
<p>Yesterday I made my 400th LinkedIn connection. Yes, I know there are people with zillions of LinkedIn connections, but mine are <strong>special</strong>. I’ve actually had contact, outside of LinkedIn, with each and everyone of them. In most cases the contact has been in person, in some cases even involving beer, and in the others the contact has been sufficiently significant, by my metrics of course, to warrant a real connection. Whatever the case may be (how many times have I used the word “case” so far?), reaching this milestone has made really happy, and this again warrants a great big thank you to each of you little coloured dots! The visualisation below shows my complete network, where I’ve labeled each cluster with the place or institute it’s most associated with:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/cpbotha_linkedin_network_20110522.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/cpbotha_linkedin_network_20110522-1024x682.jpg"
        
            alt="My LinkedIn network, visualised today. If you&#39;re not in there yet, connect with me man!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>My LinkedIn network, visualised today. If you're not in there yet, connect with me man!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>You can also try out <a href="http://inmaps.linkedinlabs.com/share/Charl_Botha/30297409392129298845937723535068877713" title="my linkedin map">an interactive version of this map</a>, or <a href="http://inmaps.linkedinlabs.com/" title="make yer own linkedin map">make your own</a>.</p>
<h3 id="the-week-in-bullets">The week in bullets</h3>
<ul>
<li>On Monday I had the privilege of attending the <a href="http://www.yesdelft.nl/OverYESDelft/NetworkEvent2011.aspx" title="yes!delft network event 2011 website">Yes!Delft Network Event 2011</a>, secretly also the opening of their beautiful new building. Yes!Delft is an incubation centre where startups, once approved by the board, can find affordable office space and a number of other facilities, including for example advice and financing, that startups require. The show was really impressive, with multiple giant projection surfaces and super lighting, a number of VIPs (Maxime Verhagen amongst others) and a 3 or 4 of the involved starters doing their elevator pitches. It was great to see that through Yes!Delft, my little city is turning into such a startup innovation hub.</li>
<li>On Tuesday I attended a day-long course on drafting an ERC Starting Grant proposal. For those of you not in the know, this is a super-prestigious research grant of up to 1.5 million euros that can be requested from the EU. Logically the rejection rate is also sufficiently high, so wish me lots of luck. Better yet, explain to any family or network members that you might have in Brussels that they should give me the money and get it over with.</li>
<li>The rest of the week was spent in meetings. I’ve come to the conclusion that the number of contiguous meetings in my programme is just about the strongest determinant for me getting unhealthily bad-tempered. By the end of Thursday I was ready to start breaking things, by Friday I was in my denial stage. A meeting now and then is fine, especially the inspiring ones during which you come up with some awesome new idea, but having them all back-to-back is just dangerous.</li>
<li>Almost as if karma felt that it should compensate in some way for inflicting meeting hell on me, the weather on Saturday was absolutely perfect, and perfect weather means BBQing! The BBQ was even more perfect, filled with scorched meat, beer, wine, good friends and great conversation. Fortunately nobody was raptured.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="backyard-philosopy">Backyard philosopy</h3>
<p>There are two issues I’d like to discuss with you.</p>
<p>The first is the following realisation I had this past week, a slightly different incarnation of another recurring thought: At any one time, you can do exactly one (1) thing only. This has at least two implications:</p>
<ol>
<li>Don’t panic. Life is just a long sequence of these single things strung together. Just keep on doing them.</li>
<li>At any time, do make sure that you pick the best possible thing to do at that moment.</li>
</ol>
<p>The second issue is not really an issue, but an inspiring quote I came across recently <a href="http://jacecooke.tumblr.com/post/4583849705/if-our-young-men-miscarry-in-their-first" title="tumbl source of emerson quote">on the interwebs</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If our young men miscarry in their first enterprises, they lose all heart. If the young merchant fails, men say he is ruined. If the finest genius studies at one of our colleges, and is not installed in an office within one year afterwards in the cities or suburbs of Boston or New York, it seems to his friends and to himself that he is right in being disheartened, and in complaining the rest of his life. A sturdy lad from New Hampshire or Vermont, who in turn tries all the professions, who teams it, farms it, peddles, keeps a school, preaches, edits a newspaper, goes to Congress, buys a township, and so forth, in successive years, and always, like a cat, falls on his feet, is worth a hundred of these city dolls. He walks abreast with his days, and feels no shame in not ‘studying a profession,’ for he does not postpone his life, but lives already. He has not one chance, but a hundred chances.</p>
<p>— Ralph Waldo Emerson, <em>Self-Reliance</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>There you have it kids: Work hard, try new stuff, remember to fall on your feet, and live now.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>