<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>pocket on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/pocket/</link><description>Recent content in pocket on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 15:01:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/pocket/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #165: Get in my Pocket.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 15:01:20 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/</guid><description> This short WHV looks back at the week from Monday March 4 to Sunday March 10.
In the week after that, I had actually decided not to publish this one, instead folding whatever I wanted to say into the next edition.
However, fear of yet another much-too-long WHV, along with my current preference for a short warming-up of the writing pipes, have led me to change my mind, and so here we are!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This short WHV looks back at the week from Monday March 4 to Sunday March 10.</p>
<p>In the week after that, I had actually decided not to publish this one,
instead folding whatever I wanted to say into the next edition.</p>
<p>However, fear of yet another much-too-long WHV, along with my current
preference for a short warming-up of the writing pipes, have led me to change
my mind, and so here we are!</p>
<p>This post consists of a really short life part, followed by a longer nerdy
pro-tip for the storage and retrieval of your web references.</p>
<h2 id="gou3-turns-3">GOU#3 turns 3.</h2>
<p>It seems like <a href="/2016/05/05/weekly-head-voices-106-ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/">just the other day when Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3 joined
us</a> here in the warm and fuzzy Humanist Kingdom of WHV.</p>
<p>Well, the &ldquo;beautiful pink little not-yet-walking but rapidly expanding
cellular mega-city&rdquo; never stopped expanding, and is currently surprising us
every day with the new ways in which her neural network processes and
transforms the reality she finds herself in.</p>
<h2 id="replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">Replacing Pocket with Just a Bunch Of PDFs (JBOP).</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been a happy user of Pocket Premium since October 23, 2016, when they
cleverly offered me a locked discount on the annual plan.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m a sucker for a deal, and I needed something with which to store archive
versions of interesting blog posts and other web resources.</p>
<p>It served me well, as I frequently access and share especially
research-related articles and blurbs, such as <a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2016/11/161122193100.htm">this one</a> discussing the
observation that aspartame (a sugar substitute found in popular fizzy drinks)
interferes with some of your enzymes, possibly resulting in more weight gain
that straight sugar!</p>
<p>(For Real Academic Articles, i.e. RAA-RAA, I am still a huge fan
of <a href="https://www.zotero.org">Zotero</a>. If Zotero had better mobile access, I would have used it for
these straight web references also.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, recently the new beta pocket interface was failing me horribly as I
was trying to find the exact article mentioned up above.</p>
<p>Typing &ldquo;glu&rdquo; or &ldquo;glucose&rdquo; was unsuccessful in finding another article
&ldquo;Artificial sweeteners induce glucose intolerance by altering the gut
microbiota&rdquo;, even although I could see that exact article in the overview
screen. To add insult to injury, searching for &ldquo;aspartame&rdquo; also did not find
that entry, although I had explicitly tagged it with &ldquo;aspartame&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It could very well be that this is just a (serious) glitch in the beta system,
but it was a frustrating reminder that for something as important (to me) as
my collection of references (aka “argument-winning potion”), I was
at the mercy of someone else, with almost no other recourse.</p>
<p>This frustrating led me to find an alternative solution, which became&hellip; a big
ol&rsquo; bunch of PDFs! (call this JBOP, inspired by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Non-RAID_drive_architectures">JBOD</a>)</p>
<p>In order to do this, we need a method of turning web-pages into readable PDFs,
and some system for the storage and retrieval of said PDFs.</p>
<h3 id="use-a-browser-with-ad-blocking-and-reader-mode">Use a browser with ad-blocking and Reader Mode</h3>
<p>The general idea is to use a browser with ad-blocking and some sort of reader
mode, and then to print to PDF.</p>
<p>On desktop, I am using <a href="https://brave.com">Brave Browser</a> because of the great
built-in ad-blocking, and because I strongly support the idea of
micro-payments to long-form content producers instead of content-destroying
ads in my face.</p>
<p>Because its built in reader mode, called <a href="https://brave.com/speed-reader/">Speed Reader</a>, has not
shipped yet, I&rsquo;m currently using the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/print-friendly-pdf/ohlencieiipommannpdfcmfdpjjmeolj">Print Friendly &amp; PDF extension</a>.</p>
<p>Safari on macOS and Firefox have built-in reader modes / views. I can
recommend the <a href="https://adguard.com/en/adguard-browser-extension/safari/overview.html">AdGuard ad-blocking extension</a> for Safari.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, Safari on iOS 12 does not currently add the source URL to its
virtually printed PDFs, so I&rsquo;m using Brave there also, although on iOS I
generally prefer Safari, also with AdGuard.</p>
<p>To print to PDF on iOS, simply print (swipe up, tap share, tap print), then do
the zoom-in gesture to turn the print into a PDF, then share again to save out
the PDF.</p>
<h3 id="store-and-name-your-pdfs-so-you-can-search-them-from-everywhere">Store and name your PDFs so you can search them from everywhere</h3>
<p>I store all of these PDFs in year-named sub-directories of a directory
called <code>refs</code> in my Dropbox.</p>
<p>Each PDF is named &ldquo;publication-date - publisher / author - title / stub&rdquo;, so
the full path is e.g. <code>~/Dropbox/refs/2019/2019-03-09 - CBC Radio - Your brain may need sleep to repair DNA 'potholes'</code>.</p>
<p>On macOS, all of these PDFs are indexed by Spotlight, so I can find the ones I
want quite quickly. Your operating system of choice should have something
similar.</p>
<p>If you are a Dropbox Pro subscriber, the mobile app provides full-text
searching to mobile spotlight also, so you can find any article lightning fast
on your phone.</p>
<p>Google Drive will do this for cheaper, but <a href="/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/#my-big-and-stupid-misstep-into-google-drive">Google Drive might also end up
eating your files</a>. ;)</p>
<h3 id="profit">Profit!</h3>
<p>Now all of your web references are in PDF format, arguably the
typeset-document equivalent of plaintext in terms of accessibility and future
proofing.</p>
<p>As you change around your syncing and storage systems in the coming years,
your faithful directory of PDFs will follow you wherever you go.</p>
<p>As an added bonus, these PDFs can be annotated with your notes and text
highlights.</p>
<h2 id="this-ending-is-only-a-pause">This ending is only a pause.</h2>
<p>Thank you for sticking around for the warming up of the pipes.</p>
<p>I hope that they will not have cooled down too much before I find another bit
of time to start on WHV #166.</p>
<p>There will be pretty pictures!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>