<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>vitality on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/vitality/</link><description>Recent content in vitality on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 15:38:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/vitality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #190: 3=4.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 15:38:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/</guid><description> Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok, because that's how life is. Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!
This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to Sunday March 8, 2020.
(I had made a good start on the post on March 8, but then the work week and a bunch of homing missile deadlines hit.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/bettys_bay_harold_porter_path_hue70afc84053a91b8d588a12a7827b7a5_2855192_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Taking the new shoes for their first run in Betty's Bay. The zig-zag path was
still mostly closed off, so I had to run in circles, which is probably ok,
because that's how life is.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Welcome back friends to the Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This is the 190th edition, covering the two weeks from monday February 24 to
Sunday March 8, 2020.</p>
<p>(I had made a good start on the post on March 8, but then the work week and a
bunch of homing missile deadlines hit. As I write this bit, it is Saturday
March 14, 14:30 SAST.)</p>
<h2 id="gou-3-turns-4">GOU #3 turns 4!</h2>
<p>Our third Genetic Offspring Unit, creative named GOU #3, fairly recently
completed another year of life.</p>
<p>She has now collected the grand total of 4.</p>
<p>It was a pleasure celebrating her birthday with her as it felt like this was
the first time that she was intellectually fully present.</p>
<p>With apparent ease she even understood the sometimes tricky concept of having
one&rsquo;s party on a different day than one&rsquo;s birthday.</p>
<p>For future us, I would also like to note that her pronunciation and sentence
construction are growing more and more precise, sometimes even overly so, the
observation of which delights me.</p>
<p>GOU#3, if you read this years and years in the future: We can already see that
you are an amazing human being. We are deeply happy that you have come here to
join our clan.</p>
<h2 id="new-pair-of-altras-acquired">New pair of Altras acquired.</h2>
<p>In an unexpected but quite happy turn of events, it is starting to look like I
might have to take part in a trail run in July.</p>
<p>(Charl from the future: Only if my finicky ankles man up between now and then.)</p>
<p>Once I&rsquo;ve actually done it, and I&rsquo;m still able to tell the tale, I will surely
do so.</p>
<p>Because I am one of the World&rsquo;s Worst Trail Runners, I will definitely have to
step up my training between now and then.</p>
<p>As with many other endeavours in life, an important component of all of this is
acquiring suitable shoes.</p>
<p>Because <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">my giant-toe-box-zero-drop
Escalantes</a> have been treating
me very well, I had soon narrowed it down to any one of the Altra trail shoes:
Superiors (minimalist), Lone Peaks (jack-of-all-trades), Timp (sightly more
support) and Olympus (maximalist-ish).</p>
<p>After having read all of the internet regarding the different Altra trail
shoes, I reluctantly came to the conclusion that none of them really knocked it
out of the park.</p>
<p>Anyways, one Sunday I walked into our local sports super store (I&rsquo;m sorry my
fellow nerds), and it so happened that they had a pair of Lone Peak 4.5s in my
size: GINORMOUS CLOWN SHOE SIZE.</p>
<p>Trying them on, I tripped and fell right into the psychological black hole of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cognitive_biases">biases</a> and
<em>instantly</em> convinced myself that these were the shoes for me.</p>
<p>Fast forward a week of calling my behavioural insurer (starts with a Disco ends
with a Y) every single day, and they finally managed to figure out what was
wrong somewhere deep in their unfortunately quite sub-par IT systems, and
flipped the <a href="https://www.discovery.co.za/vitality/fitness-booster-shoe">Shoe Purchase Gamification
switch</a>.</p>
<p>In short, if you are able to activate this feature (you have to be super
patient and a bit stubborn), said insurer will subsidise the purchase of a pair
of running shoes based on how often you exercise every week.</p>
<p>This is one neat way of making your running addiction work for you, if you can
somehow absorb the possibly substantial startup cost, i.e. the hours you have
to spend on the phone with the friendly support agents.</p>
<p>Behold my beautiful new trail running shoes:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/altra_lonepeak_4.5_hucec0c9a6b58409819fadf530fa62e125_2510569_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>State-of-the-art trail-running shoes for the World's Worst Trail
Runner.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="crabby-wallet">Crabby Wallet!</h2>
<p>After years of eyeing Fido U2F and FIDO2 hardware security keys on the
internet, I finally took the plunge and acquired <a href="https://www.yubico.com/product/security-key-nfc-by-yubico">a Yubico Security Key
NFC</a>.</p>
<p>Up to now I used mostly the LastPass Authenticator app and more recently Authy
to generate OTPs as second factor (2FA) for most of my important accounts.</p>
<p>(BTW, if you&rsquo;re not yet using 2FA for your important accounts, such as email,
now is the best time to upgrade. I would recommend getting <a href="https://authy.com/">the Authy
app</a> because it optionally supports multi-device
synchronization.)</p>
<p>The YubiCo hardware device is supposed to be more secure than authenticator
apps due to domain hashing, and it&rsquo;s pretty cool that you don&rsquo;t have to copy
across 6-digit codes, but what I didn&rsquo;t foresee as clearly was the following
simple difference:</p>
<p>I almost always have my phone with me. However, I don&rsquo;t always have my keyring
with me.</p>
<p>I set out to find a new wallet to replace my already pretty minimalist fake
leather credit card booklet. The new wallet had to be at least as minimalist,
but it had to have some sort of lanyard to which I could attach the security
key.</p>
<p>I was delighted to discover that (of course) there&rsquo;s a whole community of
minimalist wallet enthusiasts on the internet.</p>
<p>I was even more delighted when I discovered that the Crabby Wallet C3, a
second-generation product of a <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1369622196/the-crabby-wallet-a-wallet-that-is-not-for-everyon">super successful 2015
kickstarter</a>,
was available all the way down here!</p>
<p>Behold the minimalist wonder that is my new Crabby Wallet:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/crabby_wallet_c3_canvas_hu1f536da3a64b778d7ea385a166b464bb_1978542_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The Crabby Wallet C3. As you can see, it's only slightly larger than a credit
card. It's made of canvas which looks pretty durable. After a breaking-in
period, it easily holds up to 10 cards. Sometimes there's even cash stashed
under the rubber-band.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>(Charl from 6 days in the future writes: This looks like it&rsquo;s going to be a
keeper. It&rsquo;s more compact and more secure than my previous credit card booklet,
and it has become much more ergonomic after the initial break-in period.)</p>
<h2 id="the-end-of-this-post">The end of this post.</h2>
<p>Thank you for connecting with me here!</p>
<p>Remember, it&rsquo;s now Saturday March 14, 15:26 SAST, but this post will forever
act like it finds itself on Sunday March 8.</p>
<p>I hope that tomorrow I can write WHV #191, a less complicated post that will
come into being not too far away from the moment that is its observation point.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Do you feel like you have an observation point, a specific location that is
your momentary source of perception and thought?</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been getting back into the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up guide</a>, and
there are some truly delightful exercises of the all-encompassing
consciousness.</p>
<p>Remember: <em>There is no observation point!</em></p>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/03/14/weekly-head-voices-190-3-turns-4/there_is_no_spoon_hu9c44b29177c2149c9fd0b66f883cb90d_110739_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #149: I forgot to proof-read this.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/24/weekly-head-voices-149/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 20:49:20 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/24/weekly-head-voices-149/</guid><description> Part of the Sunday morning trail. Although I really enjoy these, I’m at my happiest running down antelope on the savannah. Antelope strictly-speaking not required, but those wide open plains on the other hand…
This, the one hundred and forty ninth edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covers the week from Monday July 16 to Sunday July 22 of the year 2018.
This week, we have apple watch running adventures, deep learning in production (finally), yet another focus tip and finally a youtube poetry reading.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_0420-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_0420-PANO-1024x318.jpg"
        
            alt="Part of the Sunday morning trail. Although I really enjoy these, I’m at my happiest running down antelope on the savannah.  Antelope strictly-speaking not required, but those wide open plains on the other hand…"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Part of the Sunday morning trail. Although I really enjoy these, I’m at my happiest running down antelope on the savannah.  Antelope strictly-speaking not required, but those wide open plains on the other hand…</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This, the one hundred and forty ninth edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covers the week from Monday July 16 to Sunday July 22 of the year 2018.</p>
<p>This week, we have apple watch running adventures, deep learning in production (finally), yet another focus tip and finally a youtube poetry reading.</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h1 id="the-apple-watch-vitality-and-you">The Apple Watch, Vitality and You</h1>
<p>On Monday, I became the owner of a brand new Apple Watch 3, FOR FREE(ish).</p>
<p>I feel that two points are worth mentioning:</p>
<ol>
<li>Having one’s work macbook unlock <em>automatically</em> as one prepares to put one’s hands on the keyboard, with a sweet little unlock sound emitting from one’s watch, is much more fun than I had expected.
<ul>
<li>Said watch has a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_S3">dual-core processor with 768MB of RAM and 16GB of flash, and a GPU</a>. That’s just crazy.
<ul>
<li>In 2003, <a href="/2003/10/05/first-thoughts-on-the-tungsten-e/">I had similar thoughts about the processing power of my Tungsten E PDA</a>, and all the way back in <a href="/2016/12/06/weekly-head-voices-113-science-and-creation/#devil-on-my-arm">2016 I was already laughing at 2003 me</a>. I should know better by now.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>One was looking forward to using third party running apps on the watch, such as iSmoothRun which does real-time reporting of cadence, which can be shown together with a number of other stats on a number of configurable screens a la Garmin . One has had to cancel these plans, because Vitality, the shadowy organisation responsible for the FOR FREE(ish) nature of the watch, only recognises runs submitted by the built-in Workouts app.
<ul>
<li>The September watchOS update will include runtime (haha) cadence, which is great. However, some technical system for the support of third party apps would have been even better. I’ll live.</li>
<li>Runs logged with the built-in Workouts app can be easily and automatically submitted to other platforms, such as Strava, where many of my running peeps hang out, and even to one’s own Dropbox in FIT format, with <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/za/app/healthfit/id1202650514?mt=8">the HealthFit iOS app</a>, a very reasonable once-off purchase.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="deeplearning-insidetm">DeepLearning Inside(tm)</h1>
<p>On Friday, we shipped a new version of the most important work project I am currently involved in.</p>
<p>Again I feel that two points are worth mentioning:</p>
<ol>
<li>We now also have deep learning, albeit a humble example, out in actual production. I was starting to feel a little left out. Anonymous shout-out (because top secret) to the team members who made this happen!</li>
<li>They say one should never deploy or ship on Friday. Because I come from the I-won’t-do-what-you-tell-me generation, I cut the final release on Friday evening <em>after</em> the traditional weekend-starter braai.
<ul>
<li>To be honest, this was only <em>necessary</em> because I had promised our client that we would release, and it was only <em>possible</em> because we have a fairly good test-suite, with end-to-end being most crucial in this specific scenario, and a checklist-style release procedure.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="sobsodsit-cipwob-fba">SoBSoDSiT-CIPWOB-FBA</h1>
<p>As part of my chaotic but ever-evolving constellation of systems for maintaining work focus, I have renamed the <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/#shorter-focus-blocks-work-better">shorter focus blocks approach</a> to the <em>short-but-specially-defined-so-that-completion-is-possible-within-one-block focus blocks approach</em> (SBSDSTCIPWOB-FBA).</p>
<p>This adds the incentive of a small but probable shot of dopamine at the end of the focus block, and sometimes even leads to its unwitting extension by the woefully undersized (not to mention super lazy) rider sometimes sitting atop my mental elephant.</p>
<p>It sometimes feels like I’m slowly reinventing GTD.</p>
<p>(This blog post is an emotional roller coaster ride for me. This is the first time I’m feeling something.)</p>
<p><a href="/2007/10/07/my-palmos-based-gtd-setup/">I used to be a fan of GTD</a> when I still believed that my function in life was to answer emails really quickly, and master multi-tasking.</p>
<p>Since then however, I’ve slowly had to come to the realisation that, at least in my case, the amount of email processed is more or less exactly inversely correlated to the actual value that I produce.</p>
<h1 id="the-impotence-of-proof-reading">The impotence of proof-reading</h1>
<p>The following poetry reading made various subsets of my neurons fire in extremely pleasant ways.</p>
<p>I hope that you experience similar effects. See you next time!</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OonDPGwAyfQ?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>