<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>industry on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/industry/</link><description>Recent content in industry on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 14:06:05 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/industry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Dear Academia, I hope we can still be friends.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 14:06:05 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/</guid><description><![CDATA[ After many great years in academia, I finally decided in October of last year to resign from my position as tenured assistant professor. As of February of this year, I proudly walk the earth as an independent engineer.
It has taken me two years of thinking to reach this decision.
I started re-evaluating my life in academia two years ago after a review-for-promotion (See the &ldquo;oral defence&rdquo; bullet. :)) process that resulted in a &ldquo;not quite yet&rdquo; judgement.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>After many great years in academia, I finally decided in October of last year
to resign from my position as tenured assistant professor. As of February of
this year, I proudly walk the earth as an independent engineer.</p>
<p>It has taken me two years of thinking to reach this decision.</p>
<p>I started re-evaluating my life in academia two years ago after
a <a href="/2010/09/20/an-indecent-proposal-weekly-head-voices-31/">review-for-promotion (See the &ldquo;oral defence&rdquo;
bullet. :))</a> process
that resulted in a &ldquo;not quite yet&rdquo; judgement. It took this long to make my
decision, because it was actually going quite well. I had
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenure_(academic)">tenure</a>, the holy grail (well,
the first of a number of them) for many academics. I had built up and was
heading the TU Delft Medical Visualization research group. I was fortunate to
attract the best postgraduate students and Ph.D. candidates. My research
proposals were successful, so I had money to explore exciting new research
avenues. My h-index was (slowly) going in the right direction. Even my teaching
was more than occasionally positively received. :)</p>
<p>However, after all this thinking I was finally able to admit to myself that I
am a much better engineer than an academic. All of these years, I had been
applying my engineering talent to the design problem that is academia. This was
successful to a certain extent, but I would never be able to compete with a
Real Academic(tm).</p>
<p><em>More importantly, life is short. It makes sense, and is much more enjoyable,
to spend the largest possible part of it running at full efficiency.</em></p>
<p>Quickly after this realisation, came the next one: I had sub-consciously been
working on a fairly respectable engineering-oriented CV and a great network. I
now had the freedom to work for &hellip; <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">me</a>. I could get back
to designing and building advanced technical artefacts that people actually
use, and I could do so completely on my own terms.</p>
<p>It was definitely not easy to leave academia. The hardest part is leaving
behind the relationships I was privileged to have with my colleagues (friends),
in Delft and the rest of the world. Of course we will still have contact, but
it will never be the same as the 15:30 sugar fix, the caffeine-driven and
super-esoteric debates in the kitchen, the ultra-weird lunch discussions, or
the awesome conversations and beer-drinking at scientific (haha) conferences.</p>
<p>That being said, the wave of creative energy I have been riding on for the past
month, even after correcting for novelty, is a good sign that my choice was a
suitable one. I am happy and relieved to call myself an engineer again.</p>
<p>So Academia, it&rsquo;s really not you, it&rsquo;s me. :)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>