<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>autumn on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/autumn/</link><description>Recent content in autumn on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/autumn/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #225: Just a perfect weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</guid><description> Dear reader,
Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.
Keyboard update: K1 You&amp;rsquo;ll remember from WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the Womier K87 with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown switches.
That keyboard is so much fun to type on.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear reader,</p>
<p>Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th
installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="la_autumn_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="keyboard-update-k1">Keyboard update: K1</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll remember from <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the
Womier K87</a> with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown
switches.</p>
<p>That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt
Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the case that fingers also like the exercise, just like their
human owners.</p>
<p>I was not planning to buy any keyboards again soon, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was quite curious whether low profile key switches (that is, slightly less
finger travel) would be a good compromise between the fun of the Womier and the
efficiency of the Sculpt.</li>
<li>The K1 was on my list of candidates of keyboards with low-profile mechanical
switches.</li>
<li>I find it difficult to resist a good deal.</li>
</ul>
<p>You see, a friendly little bird (who also hangs out on the keyboards channel of
the zatech slack) told me about the extra-special Takealot birthday special
discount on <a href="https://www.imore.com/keychron-k1-v4-review">the Keychron K1 V4 87-key keyboard</a>.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a credit card transaction, a week of waiting for delivery and
another week of getting accustomed to the new board, and here we are, with at
least me typing these words on the new K1.</p>
<p>It took a while to get used to the keycaps, which can be a slippery sometimes
(or rather, my finger tip traction is variable), but my typing speed and
accuracy on this thing are in the neighbourhood of where they should be.</p>
<p>The thing is a great deal more <em>stylish</em> than my Womier; the Womier is that
guilty pleasure 80s disco that you really love, the K1 could work in a serious
coffee shop.</p>
<p>Also, having a keyboard which can switch this easily between wired operation
(the default for my desktop) and three different bluetooth connections is
pretty convenient. On trips where I usually only take the MacBook, I could
consider taking the K1 along when I have to do A Great Deal of Serious Typing.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I can&rsquo;t yet say if the low profile switches are indeed
the compromise that I wondered about. My subjective impression now is indeed
that my fingers don&rsquo;t get so physically tired as sometimes happens with the
Womier, but I&rsquo;ll have to switch between them a few times to get a better idea.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am certainly enjoying the experience of typing on
this thing, and I am certainly wondering about the interesting role that
different types of mechanical keyboards have begun to play in my computing
life.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-about-a-new-book-notes-post-about-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Lessons about a new book notes post about Seven and a Half Lessons about the Brain</h2>
<p>After two months of early(ish) morning typing on various keyboards, I finally
managed to wrap up <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">my book notes about Seven and a Half Lessons about the
Brain</a>, a fantastic book by neuro-scientist and psychologist Lisa Feldman
Barrett.</p>
<p>I had plans, in retrospect clearly too ambitious, to have at least two (2) book
notes posts out in Q1 of this year (after it took me months to complete <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my book
notes on Creativity, Inc.</a> by the end of last year).</p>
<p>That goal was necessarily postponed to Q2, and as we can all see now, there is
not enough time for a second post like this.</p>
<p>Either I have to change the format of the book notes to something more compact,
like a bunch of bullet lists, or I should make peace with the fact that I write
these like I write them, a little prose with quotes interspersed that can
generally be read like a mini story itself, and with the fact that they&rsquo;re
going to take as much time as they do.</p>
<p>Sometimes I have mixed feelings about the practice itself.</p>
<p>It takes fragments of hobby time spread out over weeks, fragments of time that
I could probably use for more reading, other interesting tidbits and, uhm,
extra work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it feels like a sort of a mini-rebellion doing exactly this,
assembling so many little pieces into something slightly more coherent and
significant, something that stands apart from work.</p>
<p>It seems I do know what to do.</p>
<p>Thanks for the chat!</p>
<h2 id="perfect-weekends-and-the-necessary-reminders-that-precede-them">Perfect weekends and the necessary reminders that precede them</h2>
<p>The weekend of June 4, 2021, was unexpectedly perfect, and I would like to make
note of that here for future me.</p>
<p>This is the recipe that we followed, utterly by happy accident:</p>
<ul>
<li>1x reminder during the week to really focus on the now.</li>
<li>1x absolutely perfect autumn weather package: balmy 20ish degrees Celsius,
lots of sun, very little wind.</li>
<li>3x braais, one per day, with various subsets of family.</li>
<li>2x runs: one a long weekend morning run, and the other an unplanned one
with GOU#1.</li>
<li>1x polishing and publishing of the blog post mentioned above.</li>
<li>1x unexpected Sunday evening star watching with GOU#2.</li>
</ul>
<p>One would think that daily practice would help, but it turns out that sometimes
a serendipitous reminder by a friend can help to switch one&rsquo;s brain into
exactly the right gear, right before the weekend.</p>
<p>During our Friday evening start-the-weekend ritual (it&rsquo;s a braai. surprise!), I
had my first quite visceral &ldquo;THIS, this is it, this is everything&rdquo;
experience. (so lovely)</p>
<p>From then on, brain remained in the right mode right through most of the
weekend.</p>
<p>If you ever run into me before the weekend (it&rsquo;s always before the weekend!), I
would be grateful if you could remind me that it is in fact now.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you much nowness.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #224: Zen machine</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 08:30:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/</guid><description> Dear friends,
You are reading the 224th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the week from Monday May 17 to Sunday May 23 of the year 2021.
Figure 1: Scene from a truly fabulous autumn Sunday lunch with the family. As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, Autumn weekends down here can be rough.
Fasted runs are not as scary as I thought At the time of drawing my anti-breakfast line in the sand in WHV #221, I did still make the exception of eating a banana or three before a morning run, with the reasoning that I would burn through much of the resultant glucose during the run, and that runs without all those sweet sweet carbs were probably quite difficult.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>You are reading the 224th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the week
from Monday May 17 to Sunday May 23 of the year 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="vergelegen_camphors_20210523.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu3b8384198c8dc993c78bb4d47145c527_2740074_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu3b8384198c8dc993c78bb4d47145c527_2740074_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu3b8384198c8dc993c78bb4d47145c527_2740074_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu3b8384198c8dc993c78bb4d47145c527_2740074_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu3b8384198c8dc993c78bb4d47145c527_2740074_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a truly fabulous autumn Sunday lunch with the family. As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, Autumn weekends down here can be rough."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from a truly fabulous autumn Sunday lunch with the family. As I&rsquo;ve mentioned before, Autumn weekends down here can be rough.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="fasted-runs-are-not-as-scary-as-i-thought">Fasted runs are not as scary as I thought</h2>
<p>At the time of drawing my <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#skip-you-some-breakfast-for-great-good">anti-breakfast line in the sand in WHV #221</a>, I did
still make the exception of eating a banana or three before a morning run, with
the reasoning that I would burn through much of the resultant glucose during
the run, and that runs without all those sweet sweet carbs were probably
quite difficult.</p>
<p>However, shortly after publishing that post, I decided that I would like to put
even more money where my mouth is, and started doing morning runs in the fasted
state.</p>
<p>I am happy to report that not only are fasted runs not scary at all, they are
actually quite enjoyable.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s no recently ingested food jostling around in your insides, which means
one less distraction from focusing on the running.</p>
<p>Perhaps most importantly, perceived energy did not seem to be a problem at all,
at least for the runs of up to an hour and a half that I have tried, some of
them over lunch time.</p>
<p>(It&rsquo;s possible that glycogen stores from the previous day were still
sufficient. I&rsquo;m hoping that at least some of those highly energy-dense fat
cells were involved. <a href="https://www.dietdoctor.com/fasting-and-exercise">This blog post about fasting and exercise</a> is a good read
and clearly explains the relevant concepts.)</p>
<p>I do need to caveat all of this with the remark that all of these runs have
been in the relative cool of autumn. I don&rsquo;t know (yet) how a longer, much more
sweaty run will go in the fasted state.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for the next few months to find out!</p>
<p>NB: Please see <a href="./#isso-2776">Pieter&rsquo;s comments below</a>. The text above is me talking about how
I experience my training (non-race) runs in the fasted state. If you decide to
exert yourself in the fasted state, please be careful, read what you can, and
measure carefully how your body responds to smaller doses initially.</p>
<h2 id="yarn-pnp-will-rescue-you-from-node-modules-hell">Yarn PnP will rescue you from <code>node_modules</code> hell</h2>
<p><em>NERD WARNING: <code>if not(nerd) skip_section();</code></em></p>
<p>The other day as I opened a laptop after having worked on the new zen machine
(see below) setting up some of our frontend development environments, its tiny
little metal frame almost creaked as dropbox started syncing, on all cores, the
many thousands of files from one of the cursed <code>node_modules</code> directories that
I had forgotten to exclude from syncing on the new machine.</p>
<p>My thoughts at that moment: &ldquo;YARGH! THAT DOES IT! we&rsquo;re going to try that shiny
new thing that we have been avoiding because the current solution was OK until
it absolutely wasn&rsquo;t.&rdquo;</p>
<p>That new thing is <a href="https://yarnpkg.com/features/pnp">Yarn 2&rsquo;s PnP</a>.</p>
<p>(That page describes the various other issues with <code>node_modules</code>, besides your
laptop creaking.)</p>
<p>Instead of downloading a thousand dependencies and then unpacking those
thousand dependencies to easily one hundred thousand tiny little files, right
in your source directory (and that&rsquo;s <code>node_modules</code> folks!), PnP creates a
single <code>.pnp.js</code> file along with a local cache of the one thousand packages
which it keeps neatly zipped up.</p>
<p>In terms of numbers of tiny files, this is an improvement of one to two orders
of magnitude, which is significant. With <code>enableGlobalCache</code>, you can even move
these out of your source dir, keeping just the <code>.pnp.js</code>.</p>
<p>In addition to this, because of this new structure, the PnP can be much more
strict in resolving dependencies, resulting in builds that are <strong>actually</strong>
reproducible.</p>
<p>I followed <a href="https://yarnpkg.com/getting-started/migration">the step-by-step instructions for migrating the project in question
to Yarn PnP</a>, and before you could say dependency-resolution 58 times, the
project in question was cured of the hundred thousand file problem, and IDEs
like Visual Studio Code or any of the JetBrains family were perfectly capable
of navigating through the new dependency structure, right down to lines of code
inside the package zips.</p>
<p>Based on this experience, and the momentum and support that PnP has, my advice
is to convert at your soonest convenience.</p>
<p>The feeling of relief and increased build speed are worth it!</p>
<h2 id="new-machine-zen">New machine zen</h2>
<p>The tradition around here is to write something about any new computers in the
family.</p>
<p>However, as this new one was not entirely planned, I almost wanted to keep it a
secret.</p>
<p>Weird instinct that.</p>
<p>As a compromise, I&rsquo;ll hide it in this section down here.</p>
<p>So, as I said, I was not yet planning to get a new workstation to complement
the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/">the new M1-powered mobile device</a>, because <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">the ThinkPad</a> is still a very
capable machine.</p>
<p>However, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen%5F3">the new AMD Zen3 architecture</a> was proving far too hard for me to
resist, and so I started <em>fantasy</em> shopping for my next Zen3-powered workstation.</p>
<p>This continued for quite a while in the evenings, with me swapping in and out
different components in my local retailer&rsquo;s online shop, reading reviews, and
generally enjoying the process of putting together my <em>imaginary</em> workstation,
with real parts, from a real store, and with the fairly specific rule (for some
or other reason) that I could only use parts that were in stock at the retailer
in question&hellip;</p>
<p>What could possibly go wrong, right?!</p>
<p>Well, what could go wrong, is that I&rsquo;m typing these words on a new Zen3
workstation with 12 cores (24 threads, I think you can guess the chip now?), a
really fast PCIe 4.0 SSD (around 7Gbytes/s read and write) and the &ldquo;old&rdquo;
RTX2070 GPU salvaged from the upgraded <a href="/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/">meepz97, the desktop that joined this
club back in 2015</a>.</p>
<p>(Back then the Samsung 850 Pro was indeed &ldquo;STUPID FAST&rdquo; at about 500MB/s. The
new drive, Sabrent&rsquo;s Rocket 4 Plus, is 7 times that speed, and 4 times as
large.)</p>
<p>Just a few years back, this sort of raw computing power could only be found in
well-guarded and relatively secret government facilities.</p>
<p>Now all of that is standing on my desk, running Emacs, a 40 year old text
editor.</p>
<p>Although getting my old friend Emacs running smoothly on <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/wslg">the bleeding edge WSLg</a>
has been causing a great deal of teeth gnashing, and although clearly many
other things have changed since then, I would like to conclude this post in the
same way as <a href="/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/#are-you-happy-now">the one for meepz97</a>:</p>
<h2 id="are-you-happy-now">Are you happy now?</h2>
<p>Yes.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Surviving Autumn in the Cape: Lourensford Harvest Market</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/10/surviving-autumn-in-the-cape-lourensford-harvest-market/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 13:40:23 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/10/surviving-autumn-in-the-cape-lourensford-harvest-market/</guid><description> Six jumping castles for the little ones, beautiful food and Lourensford wine for the adults. Lourensford Harvest Market is on every Sunday at Lourensford Wine Estate.
We might just make it through this autumn in one piece!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/wpid-20150510_142845-e1431279158724.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/wpid-20150510_142845-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Six jumping castles for the little ones, beautiful food and Lourensford wine for the adults. Lourensford Harvest Market is on every Sunday at Lourensford Wine Estate.</p>
<p>We might just make it through this autumn in one piece!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #68: Harsh Autumn Weekends.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/04/21/weekly-head-voices-68-harsh-autumn-weekends/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2014 20:32:59 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/04/21/weekly-head-voices-68-harsh-autumn-weekends/</guid><description> Noeska’s new weekly status update blog posts inspired me to get mine back on the road again. To be more precise, the observation that I really enjoyed being updated in this fashion with a far-away friend’s exploits hints at the possibility that, somewhere out there, there might be someone who finds it similarly enjoyable to read mine! (Long ago I learnt the trick from Swimgeek, who is still going strong with his weekly updates.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><a href="http://noeskasmit.com/weekly-status-update-1/" title="Noeska's weekly status updates">Noeska’s new weekly status update blog posts</a> inspired me to get mine back on the road again. To be more precise, the observation that I really enjoyed being updated in this fashion with a far-away friend’s exploits hints at the possibility that, somewhere out there, there might be someone who finds it similarly enjoyable to read mine! (Long ago I learnt the trick from <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/" title="Swimgeek's blog">Swimgeek</a>, who is still going strong with his weekly updates.)</p>
<p>You know the rules: We write short summaries of our week’s activities, often in the form of bullet lists. I’m going to break both rules this time by rambling on about the past three weeks, and by showing you a bunch of photos I took on the weekends.</p>
<p>I’d like to show you how the autumn weekends here in SA can be quite harsh, but first I need to geek out for a bit (do not fear non-nerds, there are pictures after this brief interlude!):</p>
<ul>
<li>I’m back with Emacs. &lt;3 &lt;3 &lt;3 On my continuous search for the ultimate information organizing system I have now arrived editing the Markdown files contained in a git-backed <a href="https://github.com/gollum/gollum" title="Gollum github page">Gollum wiki</a> with my Emacs 24.3. I even wrote a (nerdy) <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2014/04/08/syntax-highlighting-markdown-fenced-code-blocks-in-emacs/" title="vxlabs blog post on emacs fenced code block highlighting">blog post explaining how you to can configure your Emacs to do language-specific fenced code-block syntax highlighting</a>. Somehow Emacs and I are just getting along much better than we did before my Vim period (dark dark days). I think it’s because I’ve decided to embrace the Lisp, which brings me to:</li>
<li>In my copious amounts of free time, I was searching for a functional language to learn. The <a href="http://www.erlang.org/doc/getting_started/users_guide.html" title="Erlang tutorial">Erlang tutorial</a> was enjoyable, but I was not too crazy about what I read about the details of deploying Erlang systems. I bought <a href="http://learnyouahaskell.com/" title="Learn you a Haskell, man!">Learn you a Haskell for Great Good</a> and started reading it, but somehow Haskell didn’t tickle me enough. Then, probably infected by having to look at Emacs Lisp again, I picked up the <a href="http://www.clojurebook.com/" title="Clojure Programming">Clojure Programming book</a>. Now that pushed all of the right buttons! I haven’t this much fun with a new language since I picked up Python, and my mind has been expanded at a few points as well (what do you mean the code that I write <strong>IS</strong> the AST?! (Picture my Neo face saying: “Whoa.”)). <a href="http://clojure.org/" title="clojure website">Clojure</a> is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisp_(programming_language)">Lisp</a> dialect that does a pretty good job of walking the line between beauty and pragmatism. Built on the JVM (and having full interop with the rest of Java) it also has STM (software transactional memory), agents, and async channels all built-in. As if that wasn’t enough, I get to use Emacs with the CIDER package to play with it. (<code>M-x cider-jack-in</code> starts up the Clojure REPL and then… JACKS ME IN.)</li>
</ul>
<p>Err, I might have exhausted my nerd quota for the week. Let’s do the rest of the Weekly Head Voices in pictures!</p>
<p>Three weekends ago I went to visit the Spice Route farm in the Paarl with family and friends. Besides the coffee roastery, the chocolatier, the winery and the two restaurants, this farm also houses the Cape Brewing Company, a magical place that produces delicious craft beers, which you can taste, and take home with you. The view is not too shabby either:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/spice_route_panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/spice_route_panorama-1024x318.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from the Spice Route farm is Not Too Shabby(tm)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from the Spice Route farm is Not Too Shabby(tm)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>On the topic of delicious craft beers, THIS, my dear readers, is The Darling Bone Crusher, another super tasty white beer constructed with much love in the town called Darling:







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/darling_bone_crusher.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/darling_bone_crusher-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The Darling Bone Crusher white craft beer"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Darling Bone Crusher white craft beer</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>… and this is the sun setting on some Milk and Honey, crafted in Knysna (this one is quite good, but their other ale called the Old Wobbly is even nicer):








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/sunset_and_milk_and_honey.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/sunset_and_milk_and_honey-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Craft beer from the land of milk and honey"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Craft beer from the land of milk and honey</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Lest you think all we do is drink craft beers around here, here’s a photo of the vicious river delta I had to cross during my afternoon fitness activity (this was before we started drinking craft beers again):








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/jogging_delta.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/jogging_delta-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Vicious river delta"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Vicious river delta</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>… and here’s a pretty <del>butterfly</del> moth (thanks <a href="http://mentat.za.net/">Stéfan</a>) I just had to take a photo of:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/pretty_butterfly.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/pretty_butterfly-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty butterfly in Betty’s Bay"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty butterfly in Betty’s Bay</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>On the way back home after another harsh weekend, we were stuck in some sort of traffic jam. After a few minutes inching ahead, we ran into the culprits causing our delay:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/baboons_on_cars.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/baboons_on_cars-1024x504.jpg"
        
            alt="Baboons on cars!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Baboons on cars!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>(Yes, those are baboons sitting on people’s cars. “Oh, were you planning to drive that sir? You’re going to have to wait until the baboon decides it’s time to go home.”)</p>
<p>The road we were on (the R44 between Gordon’s Bay and Betty’s Bay) is one of the prettiest I know. On another of these autumn weekends, it looked like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/r44_to_bettys.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/r44_to_bettys-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="R44 between Gordon’s Bay and Betty’s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>R44 between Gordon’s Bay and Betty’s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The End.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>