<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Well-Being on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/well-being/</link><description>Recent content in Well-Being on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 19:47:51 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/well-being/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #242: Multiplicity of me</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 20:51:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</guid><description>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.
If you like backyard philosophy, you&amp;rsquo;re in the right place.
Even if you only like bullet lists, you&amp;rsquo;re going to be ok.
Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from
Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.</p>
<p>If you like backyard philosophy, you&rsquo;re in the right place.</p>
<p>Even if you only like bullet lists, you&rsquo;re going to be ok.</p>










<figure><a href="afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_41bd9f5429550d06.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_cd29c721e76c2270.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_968c3008cb01b577.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_454f8c3e3a4ec58f.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_cd29c721e76c2270.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo by friend WvdL.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="learning-at-the-burning">Learning at the Burning</h2>
<p>There&rsquo;s an unwritten rule that you should not make any life decisions for at
least three weeks after the (Afrika)Burn.</p>
<p>Apparently people have, inspired by the sometimes weird experiences of the
event, made some major but unfortunately quite regrettable decisions in its
afterglow.</p>
<p>Anyways, I did not come back with anything like that.</p>
<p>Without sounding (too much) like Zaphod eating the fairy cake powering the
Total Perspective Vortex and walking away pretty much unscathed, through the
week&rsquo;s ups (mostly) and downs I learned a bunch, and I did come back with some
internal changes, but they were at their most extreme a strong reminder (kick
in the butt might even be appropriate) of a partially buried perspective or
two.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it is now exactly three weeks after the thing, and although that
dusty afterglow has definitely waned, it feels like I&rsquo;ve just merged back into
reality without any major incidents, just a slight tweak (or gentle kick in the
butt) here and there, for the better.</p>
<p>(Because inquiring minds might want to know, yes, we again brought the
BURNIVERSITY. We&rsquo;re probably one of the smallest theme camps, but we were
intense, and it feels like our interactions were too.)</p>
<p>Anyways, here are some completely random words, some of them loosely based (or
not at all, or something in between) on a recent conversation with friend PK,
and some of them from friend DW:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA</a> is a good framework for your well-being, and that of your loved ones:
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion</li>
<li>Engagement</li>
<li>Relationships</li>
<li>Meaning</li>
<li>Accomplishment</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>That thing you&rsquo;re stressing about is most probably not worth such a high
personal cost, and health-risk.</li>
<li>Just do the work.</li>
<li><a href="https://typesense.org/blog/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-just-showing-up-everyday/">Just showing up every day is a super power</a>. Pick your thing(s), show up to
them every single day, profit.</li>
<li>Chopping onions is the physical manifestation of your love for the people for
whom you are cooking. Give it (chopping onions, making food, loving) your
<em>whole</em> attention, and see what happens. Thank you DW, for this wisdom, and
for the food.
<ul>
<li>(Dear reader, between you and me, man that guy was burning so bright&hellip;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Practice will boost your powers of attention. This will deeply improve you,
and how you interact with others.</li>
<li>Kindness is still the most important super power.</li>
<li>Check up on yourself every day, about all of these completely random words.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="multiplicity-of-you">Multiplicity of you</h2>
<p><a href="/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/#homo-deus">In 2018, I talked about <em>Homo Deus</em></a>, a book by Yuval Harari in which he
discusses several thought-provoking ideas, one of which I highlighted then and
would like to discuss again now:</p>
<p>Your experience of being a single identity, a single <em>I</em>, is most probably an
illusion, as your brain most probably houses more &ldquo;me&quot;s than you would think.</p>
<p>Research by the Nobel prize-winner Daniel Kahneman and his various
collaborators showed that we house at the very least two major selves, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow#Two_selves">namely
the remembering / narrating self and the experiencing self</a>.</p>
<p>The experiencing self is the one who actually does the living and the
<em>experiencing</em> of each moment, while the narrating self is the one who
continuously stitches together your whole story, often bending the truth to fit
its (your) opinions of yourself and those around you.</p>
<p>The narrating self is the one who dominates, for better or for worse.</p>
<p>Kahnemann himself pointed out the irony of this the best:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Odd as it may seem, I am my remembering self, and the experiencing self, who
does my living, is like a stranger to me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(You might have heard of <a href="https://positivepsychology.com/what-is-peak-end-theory/">Peak-End Theory</a>, or the phenomenon that humans tend to
judge an experience based largley on the single peak moment, and on how they
felt at the end. You can thank your remembering self for this, and you can
imagine how this could really complicate your decision making.)</p>
<p>Harari discusses Kahneman&rsquo;s selves, but continues into more research with
people who for various reasons have separated brain hemispheres.</p>
<p>When you show one brain hemisphere one version of reality, and the other
another, it is as if there are multiple narrating selves in the same person who
come up with stories that they are convinced are the truth, although in this
case these stories conflict diametrically with other thanks to the design of
the experiment.</p>
<p>From this and other data, Harari concludes that humans generally house multiple
identities.</p>
<p>What I want to to get at, is that it helps to remember (always) that &ldquo;you&rdquo; are
in fact a collection of sometimes competing &ldquo;you&quot;s.</p>
<p>As if that were not challenging enough, your narrating self takes
responsibility for all of these feelings, and tries to weave it all into a
consistent story, although that is often extremely difficult or even
impossible.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.samharris.org/blog/the-illusion-of-the-self2">an 2012 interview with Sam Harris</a>, Bruce Hood had the following to say about
this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>By rejecting the notion of a core self and considering how we are a multitude
of competing urges and impulses, I think it is easier to understand why we
suddenly go off the rails. It explains why we act, often unconsciously, in a
way that is inconsistent with our self image &ndash; or the image of our self as we
believe others see us.</p>
<p>That said, the self illusion is probably an inescapable experience we need for
interacting with others and the world, and indeed we cannot readily abandon or
ignore its influence, but we should be skeptical that each of us is the
coherent, integrated entity we assume we are.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because this thought has become much more prominent for me in quite a positive
way, I would like to take it even further, by reminding you to practise
reminding yourself of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Although your perception is generally tied to your narrating self (the one
that&rsquo;s going to remember this blog post), the complete &ldquo;you&rdquo; in fact
constitutes the whole playing field, the consciousness and its physical
medium, in which <em>all</em> of these selves live and move around. In the words of
Harris, &ldquo;you can drop back into that&rdquo; and just <em>be</em> the consciousness, <em>be</em> that
which contains it all.</li>
<li>While your own selves truly live in this conciousness, high definition
versions of your surroundings and everyone you interact with are also
running in this same (your) neural network.
<ul>
<li>This means that you have a surprising amount of control of how you
experience life.</li>
<li>When you hear a dog barking, this is really nothing more than clusters of
neurons firing in your brain, but you visualize the dog <em>over there</em>. When
you feel the wind blowing over your skin, there&rsquo;s just another set of
neurons firing not far away from the barking dog. It&rsquo;s all inside your
head, and the borders between &ldquo;inside&rdquo; and &ldquo;outside&rdquo; are far more blurry
than you might think.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>All of your selves are <em>you</em>. Treat them like you would a group of your closest
friends. You can hold them up to the group&rsquo;s standards, but you have to
forgive, and you have to be kind.</li>
</ul>
<p>Folks, I wish you all (and all the yous), and all of your people, peace and
love.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #229: Staycation PERMA-Station</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 21:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/</guid><description> Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&amp;rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="bettys_jocks.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_cd0e487bf3a491b3.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_fe1fd4e1918cf601.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_da4cbb1337c453aa.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_a75b8a71c1ebf5a5.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_fe1fd4e1918cf601.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the week from Monday July 19 to Sunday
July 25, 2021, a week of untold wonders and intense enjoyment, a week deserving
of the hallowed title of&hellip; <em>STAYCATION!</em></p>
<p>Jokes aside, it was a perfectly enjoyable week of time off, most of it spent at
home or close to it.</p>
<p>We spent time together, took care of hobby- and side-projects, and even had
time to daydream and come up with some wacky ideas which should probably never
see the light of day, but which one day just might.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-1-dot-3-released">Lazar Focus 1.3 released</h2>
<p>On the evening of Tuesday, July 20, after a flurry of programming and testing,
<a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2021/07/21/lazar-focus-1.3.0-released-real-time-focus-feedback/">Lazar Focus 1.3 was released</a>.</p>
<p>Noteworthy is its new ability to measure and give real-time feedback on your
current focus, as an easy to interpret percentage.</p>
<p>The more you resist distractions, the higher the focus percentage.</p>
<p>When developing this feature, I ended up selecting a 5 minute rolling window,
after I was initially planning a pomodoro length. Five minutes seem to be a
sort of sweet spot in terms of seeing one&rsquo;s distractions affect one&rsquo;s score,
but not having it immediately distroyed, so that there&rsquo;s still time to recover.</p>
<p>I wanted to mention here the interesting disconnect between the programming I
do for this completely disconnected hobby project in a language (Pascal-ish)
that I don&rsquo;t particularly prefer but don&rsquo;t mind on the one hand, and my day
job, for which I sometimes still get to program, on the other.</p>
<h2 id="perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA: The five building blocks of well-being</h2>
<p>So yeah, there&rsquo;s a pretty interesting disconnect&hellip;</p>
<p>Writing code for LF, in this case perhaps perhaps noteworthy the real-time
focus tracking data-structure, namely a run-length encoded series of (no)focus
time durations that automatically get truncated, lengthened and pruned as time
progresses, was 100% fun and relaxation.</p>
<p>This is not the most tricky thing to implement, but the process of first
cooking it up in my brain, and then later sitting down to implement it, and
seeing it work, was just challenging enough to result in several periods of
complete immersion in, or engagement with, the task.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Flourish-Visionary-Understanding-Happiness-Well-being/dp/1439190763/ref=sr%5F1%5F6?dchild=1&amp;qid=1627409990&amp;refinements=p%5F27%3AMartin+Seligman&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-6">Martin Seligman&rsquo;s book titled <em>Flourish</em></a>, which I&rsquo;m slowly working through
at the moment (he is a great and impactful psychologist, but perhaps not the
world&rsquo;s greatest story teller, sorry Prof Seligman), he explains that human
<a href="https://ppc.sas.upenn.edu/learn-more/perma-theory-well-being-and-perma-workshops">well-being, or flourishing, consists of five building blocks, namely</a>:</p>
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion: gratitude, savouring the present, hope and optimism,</li>
<li>Engagement: Lose oneself in a challenging (err) task,</li>
<li>Relationships: Love and be loved by friends and family,</li>
<li>Meaning: belonging to and serving some cause greater than oneself and</li>
<li>Accomplishment: Pursuing achievement and mastery for its own sake.</li>
</ol>
<p>My little LF programming exercise was <em>exactly</em> right for triggering a bit of
item number 2, namely engagement.</p>
<p>I am happy that I could slip a little PERMA in here on the back of Lazar Focus,
a little tool that is also proving useful in ways that I did not expect. ;)
Although the book is not the easiest going, it makes some valuable points if
you too are a fan of well-being.</p>
<h2 id="pfizer-jab-1-in-da-pocket">Pfizer jab #1 IN DA POCKET</h2>
<p>I really loves me some cutting edge science.</p>
<p>I know that the mRNA vaccines have been in development for decades now, but
they still represent such an amazing technological flex.</p>
<p>How fantastic is it that some of our cleverest humans have designed and tested
<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/different-vaccines/mrna.html">this vaccine that consists of usually unstable mRNA</a>, to be injected into human
cells where our the cellular machinery in our bodies will dutifully follow the
mRNA instructions to frikking synthesise and display a piece of spike protein
that looks enough like the COVID-19 spike protein so that our immune system
will notice and immediately start creating antibodies, all without us actually
getting infected.</p>
<p>As if that&rsquo;s not enough, the introduced mRNA is broken down ASAP after
synthesis.</p>
<p>HOT DAMN we live in the future and it&rsquo;s pretty awesome up here!</p>
<p>I AM EXCITE</p>
<p>I am also really happy with the super efficient walk-in vaccination procedure at the Town Hall here in Somerset West.</p>
<p>I would have been in and out in 30 minutes with Pfizer jab #1 had I not run
into and started chatting with friends in the side-effect waiting area.</p>
<p>Kudos to the Western Cape for running this like the Star Trek medical bay.</p>
<p>Still friends, how strange are the days that we find ourselves in?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>