<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Keystroke Megaphone on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/keystroke-megaphone/</link><description>Recent content in Keystroke Megaphone on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 14:04:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/keystroke-megaphone/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Can machine learning or algorithms be used in an electoral process?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/24/can-machine-learning-or-algorithms-be-used-in-an-electoral-process/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 14:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/24/can-machine-learning-or-algorithms-be-used-in-an-electoral-process/</guid><description>Guided by the &amp;ldquo;keystroke megaphone&amp;rdquo; principle, I decided to post this email reply I just sent.
An anonymous reader emailed me the following question:
Is it possible to use machine learning or algorithms in a campaign or in an electoral process?
I wrote the following reply:
I don&amp;rsquo;t have any personal experience with this, but I do know that all kinds of algorithms have been and are still used to influence elections, in the US and in the UK, and probably in other countries.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Guided by the <a href="/2014/06/10/weekly-head-voices-73-keystroke-megaphone/#conserving-keystrokes">&ldquo;keystroke megaphone&rdquo;
principle</a>,
I decided to post this email reply I just sent.</p>
<p>An anonymous reader emailed me the following question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Is it possible to use machine learning or algorithms in a campaign or in an
electoral process?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I wrote the following reply:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have any personal experience with this, but I do know that all kinds of
algorithms have been and are still used to influence elections, in the US and
in the UK, and probably in other countries.</p>
<p>If you search online for &ldquo;Cambridge Analytica&rdquo;, you&rsquo;ll find some of the quite
immoral ways in which they used facebook and other social network data to
influence public opinion.</p>
<p>(The Guardian has a great collection called <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/news/series/cambridge-analytica-files">The Cambridge Analytica
Files</a>.)</p>
<p>In short: With enough data and some clever &ldquo;big data&rdquo; analytics, it is possible
to determine with quite some precision which groups to target with personalised
advertising campaigns, in order to get whole cities or important states to vote
for your candidate.</p>
<p>Usually this form of analytics is coupled with social media bots, that is to
say, a large number of &ldquo;fake&rdquo; social media accounts that say some or other
thing.</p>
<p>These efforts can be further boosted with purpose-created websites on
legitimate-sounding domains.</p>
<p>The websites and fake accounts strengthen their combined message by citing each
other.</p>
<p>One could go further and even apply psychology to craft these messages very
carefully, so that they have an even higher success rate.</p>
<p>Folks forward these messages in their various forms via communication networks
such as whatsapp (<a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/2/12/21134652/whatsapp-2-billion-monthly-active-users-encryption-facebook">2 billion users this
month</a>)
and facebook. The poisoned messages are further strengthened because new
victims receive them from trusted sources, their social connections.</p>
<p>In an even shorter form: <em>The human mind and its social context have been hacked
and are being actively exploited.</em></p>
<p>Kind regards,
Charl</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Have I mentioned that I sometimes think about doing a startup that employs all
of the above techniques and more <em>For Good™</em>, where with <em>For Good™</em>
I mean for all ideas that align with <em>my</em> perfect worldview?</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2017/03/25/fake-news-is-just-the-beginning/">Fake news is just the beginning,
2017.</a> is
quite relevant.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>