<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Hetzner on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/hetzner/</link><description>Recent content in Hetzner on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/hetzner/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #260: I'm not your guy, buddy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</guid><description>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.
The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. GOU #3 (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining. It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250322_palmiet_hike.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_94326a752c7d0837.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_3039937a478d9ff0.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_95661b4813429562.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&rsquo;s Bay. <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #3</a> (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining.  It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</p>
<p>A week or two later, GOU #3 recovered by being an absolute trooper through the whole of the slightly more substantial and absolutely brilliant 6.5km family hike all around the little <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/rreQJ7uyT1SFSKfJ7">Sea Farm private reserve&rsquo;s peninsula</a>. I tell myself, and others, that this is partially due to involving her in the progress of the event, by showing her at regular intervals on Google Maps exactly where we found ourselves, and how we were making progress around the peninsula.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, we will both have better answers to the question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why am I in such a rush to get through life when I want so much to enjoy it?</p>
<p>&ndash; Jan Chozen Bays</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(With that in mind, you might also find <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237</a> interesting!)</p>
<h2 id="the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-migrates-again">The whole cpbotha.net-hive migrates again</h2>
<p>Slightly more than five years after <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">the previous migration of the whole so-called cpbotha.net-hive from WebFaction (RIP) to Hetzner</a>, I got an offer I could not refuse, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/mackuba.eu/post/3ll7dgrep7c25">on Bluesky (!)</a>, for a <a href="https://www.netcup.com/en/server/vps/vps-1000-g11-12m-iv">netcup VPS</a> with double the number of vCPUs, double the RAM and 5x the storage, all for about 25% cheaper every month.</p>
<p>On the weekend of March 28 I managed to port the six websites in question across (3 easy static ones, including this blog, and 3 slightly more tricky wordpress ones).</p>
<p>I am most grateful that as part of this porting effort I have now finally been able to dockerize the binaries I built years ago of the super obscure <a href="https://github.com/ma-tech/WlzIIPSrv">WlzIIPSrv fork of the C++ IIP image slice server</a> and will in future be able to migrate much more easily if I ever need to do so again. WlzIIPSrv is the software that serves the pannable and zoomable histology slices when you browse a <a href="https://visible-orbit.org/slices/dk2904l-registered/">visible-orbit.org (wordpress site also hosted on this new server) stack like this one</a>.</p>
<p>Although this migration is a significant and positive technical event for me, most of you will probably not even notice that this site responds a tad (or three) more snappily than it used to.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am celebrating that this is officially the first blog post coming to you from this shiny new server!</p>
<h2 id="productivity-devolution">Productivity (d)evolution</h2>
<h3 id="just-get-it-done-with-kanban">Just get it done with Kanban</h3>
<p>Someone once called using Trello for task management &ldquo;the time management connoisseur equivalent of lying in the gutter with a cheap bottle of wine in a brown paper bag&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(So, by the way, that someone was me! See <a href="/2014/11/27/weekly-head-voices-86-beardy/#note-taking-and-todo-system-chaos-nerd-warning">the previous admission on this blog, in WHV #86 from 2014</a>, original source of my statement is <a href="https://noeskasmit.com/comparison-of-task-managers-rtm-astrid-wunderlist-todoist/#comment-71">this comment on Noeska&rsquo;s blog</a>.)</p>
<p>I mention this now, because my current system, the one which has to act as replacement for <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my almighty Emacs Org-mode</a>, is a monthly Kanban board with columns for &ldquo;todo&rdquo;, &ldquo;today / next&rdquo;, &ldquo;doing&rdquo; and &ldquo;done&rdquo;, and task cards that I can move, quite satisfyingly, from column to column, which is essentially a less full-featured but fully local version of my old Trello-based system.</p>
<p>While the 2014-org-mode-me mind really cannot comprehend this, the current system, based on the plugins <a href="https://github.com/mgmeyers/obsidian-kanban">obsidian-kanban</a> and <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/tasks/Introduction">obsidian-tasks</a>, is working just fine for the moment.</p>
<h3 id="pomodori-made-from-100-xbar">pomodori made from 100% xbar</h3>
<p>You might recall from the previous WHV that I was still <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#productivity-hack-of-the-year">using Emacs as an over-powered pomodoro timer</a>.</p>
<p>Well, even that started itching a bit too much, and now I&rsquo;ve just re-implemented the whole thing, along with the productivity boosting auto-DnD setting, by <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/xbar-pomodoro-timer-with-DnD-for-macOS">modifying an existing self-contained macOS xbar script</a> which you can use if you too wish to work harder.</p>
<h3 id="loggin-time">Loggin&rsquo; time</h3>
<p>Together with the pomodoro timing, I was also using org-mode to maintain detailed time logs for work, using the built-in org-clock functionality.</p>
<p>Because of above-mentioned itch, I now have a semi-usable replacement which I put together as an <a href="https://blacksmithgu.github.io/obsidian-dataview/api/code-reference/#dvviewpath-input">Obsidian Dataview custom view</a>, in other words, a bunch of javascript that piggy-backs on the dataview parser and groups bullet items with start and end timestamps under their parent tasks and container headings, as projects, in order to spit out daily and monthly timelog breakdowns.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve only been testing this since the start of April. Although it&rsquo;s giving me all of the data that I need, the UX is just barely over the threshold of usable-by-me.</p>
<p>Perhaps in the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll find some time to write more about this tool to hear what others think.</p>
<h2 id="the-bozo-explosion">The Bozo explosion</h2>
<p>My great friend Dave told me about this phenomenon, of which I then had to go find the source.</p>
<p>It turns out the originator is none other than Steve Jobs, with the idea being injected into the internet hive-mind by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_Kawasaki">Guy Kawasaki</a>, a Guy who worked for Jobs at Apple (I see what I&rsquo;m doing here) from 1983 until about 1986.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a short but great post by Guy Kawasaki titled <a href="https://guykawasaki.com/what-i-learned-from-steve-jobs/">What I Learned From Steve Jobs</a> which is definitely worth a few minutes of your time.</p>
<p>Here I want to focus on point 9, namely &ldquo;A players hire A+ players&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve personally seen this a number of times with the smartest and best leaders I&rsquo;ve ever had the privilege of interacting with. They, the A players, actively seek and appoint colleagues who are smarter or better than they are, the A+ players. They absolutely revel in the opportunity of being challenged by the best people they can find. This turns into a positive feedback loop, with more and more similarly capable people seeking out their peers.</p>
<p>The opposite of this happens when you start with B players. B players easily feel threatened by more capable folks, and so they tend to recruit C players so that they can maintain the pecking order. Those C players will accordingly recruit D players and so on. This process of course leads to what Jobs coined as &ldquo;the Bozo explosion&rdquo;, which sounds frighteningly similar to what is currently happening in some parts of the world today.</p>
<p>Next time when you&rsquo;re evaluating a new opportunity, do make some time to ensure that the folks involved have the A player mentality.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>For future me, here&rsquo;s a list of other notable events from the period under review:</p>
<ul>
<li>Two 50th celebrations.</li>
<li>Various very special eating and drinking occasions with treasured friends, some from afar, and family.</li>
<li>Three family hikes.</li>
<li>1 Sting concert (with my life partner) which exceeded all my expectations.</li>
<li>My first running race (Spookhill challenge).</li>
<li>Visits with Parisian friends and family to the breathtaking <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeitz_Museum_of_Contemporary_Art_Africa">Zeitz Museum of Contemporary Art Africa (MOCAA)</a> and the Two Oceans aquarium.</li>
<li>Far too many marshmallow eggs.</li>
</ul>
<p>&hellip; and with that, I would like to leave you with this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The trick is to learn how to want the things you already have.</p>
<p>&ndash; William B. Irvine</p>
</blockquote>








    


<figure><a href="zeitz_mocaa_ocular.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7e8591922bb9e2d9.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_426183b3ab1ebea9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7a603b5cd15f6d27.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp"
            

        
            alt="Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!-- "not your guy, buddy" from the South Park episode "Canada on strike" https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1211261/characters/nm0005295/ --> ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Sunday 2024-01-07</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:48:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</guid><description> Last day of my vacation. 🥹 Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder than rest in the &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; periods instead. The assault bike saddles are garbarge. Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me. Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me. &amp;hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so. After getting wlziipsrv built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&amp;hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (bug in macOS 17.2) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS! Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 and GOU#2 ❤️</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Last day of my vacation. 🥹</li>
<li>Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes
<ul>
<li>Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder  than rest in the &ldquo;rest&rdquo; periods instead.
<ul>
<li>The assault bike saddles are garbarge.</li>
<li>Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &ldquo;normal&rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me.
<ul>
<li>&hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>After getting <code>wlziipsrv</code> built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv">https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv</a></li>
<li>Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MacOS/comments/18g4vxn/cannot_remap_keys_on_macbook_pro_with_hidutils_in/">bug in macOS 17.2</a>) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS!</li>
<li>Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 <em>and</em> GOU#2 ❤️</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #189: All systems green.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 21:57:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/</guid><description> The first Weekly Head Voices of 2020 is almost two months late.
When there&amp;rsquo;s any sort of significant WHV hiatus, you can bet your lucrative blogging career that there&amp;rsquo;s something important afoot in the life of the person owning the head that mostly contains the eponymous voices featuring at the core of this blog&amp;rsquo;s business.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/bettys_jock_fishing.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/bettys_jock_fishing_hu_fa2f219a0dfa1404.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/bettys_jock_fishing_hu_6a9f46750668957b.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/bettys_jock_fishing_hu_a01ad30734bb2fae.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/bettys_jock_fishing_hu_8a1c89e605e7a693.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/bettys_jock_fishing_hu_6a9f46750668957b.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

</figure>
<p>The first Weekly Head Voices of 2020 is almost two months late.</p>
<p>When there&rsquo;s any sort of significant WHV hiatus, you can bet your lucrative
blogging career that there&rsquo;s something important afoot in the life of the
person owning the head that mostly contains the eponymous voices featuring at
the core of this blog&rsquo;s business.</p>
<p>If you prefer that I misuse a pet-related metaphor instead, WHV breaks are
almost like dry noses in dog world.</p>
<p>Indeed, I chose the start of this year to deal with a long-standing health
issue which I had been avoiding and/or postponing for a few years now, thanks
to irrational anxiety. (The irony of this does not escape me.)</p>
<p>I am <em>quite</em> happy to report that, in an utterly unsurprising non-turn of
events, science and modern medicine prevailed. Hard.</p>
<p>Please don&rsquo;t get the wrong impression.</p>
<p>I am utterly grateful for the predictability, and for the science, and for
modern medicine and its precise practitioners.</p>
<p>As I sit here, my internal sensors report all systems greener than they have
been in quite a while.</p>
<p>At this moment, life is truly brilliant.</p>
<h2 id="gou-1-is-now-a-high-schooler">GOU #1 is now a high-schooler.</h2>
<p>At the end of last year, <a href="/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">I wrote about GOU #1 finishing primary
school</a>.</p>
<p>In the meantime, the pace of development seems to have picked up even more.</p>
<p>GOU #1 is now getting on the bus at Super Early O&rsquo; Clock every morning to go to
her new high school, which sometimes reminds me of a sort of Hogwarts for young
power women.</p>
<p>It feels like she is growing more independent by the day, regularly surprising
us with new skills and capabilities.</p>
<p>Perhaps more importantly, she seems to be handling all of these changes, both
external and internal, with grace and a gratifying helping of reason.</p>
<h2 id="the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">The whole cpbotha.net-hive has been migrated to a small Hetzner server.</h2>
<p>For the past days I&rsquo;ve been quite busy migrating this website, along with a
number of others (<a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>,
<a href="https://medvis.org/">medvis.org</a> and about 10 more), away from WebFaction
(RIP) to a new Hetzner server in Nuremberg.</p>
<p>GoDaddy acquired WebFaction, and they have made clear that they will at some
unknown time in the nearish future pull the plug on the whole WebFaction
setup.</p>
<p>For the 12 years that I was a customer, it was the perfect hoster: The ideal
combination of managed and unmanaged hosting for a very reasonable price.</p>
<p>Although this migration led to quite a bit of work, I am happy that all of the
ported sites are running slightly leaner on the new VPS.</p>
<p>Also, I made use of the opportunity to outfit each ported site with a Let&rsquo;s
Encrypt certificate, meaning we now have 100% SSL.</p>
<p>I would like to note the following possibly helpful learnings:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://wordpress.org/plugins/duplicator/">Duplicator</a>, a wordpress plugin,
is the perfect solution for transporting a wordpress site from one corner of
the planet to another.</li>
<li>You can use <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/02/22/supervisor-fastcgi-nginx/">supervisor to run non-php fastcgi processes behind
nginx</a>.</li>
<li>After the first wordpress migration, I had a checklist in Emacs Orgmode with
which I could migrate the other 7 in my sleep, and almost did. See below for
a Real World Example™.</li>
</ul>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-org" data-lang="org"><span style="display:flex;"><span>**<span style="color:#0a3069"> DONE</span> vxuni.com [8/8] [2020-02-22 Sat 15:06]
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">CLOSED: </span><span style="color:#57606a">[2020-02-22 Sat 15:43]</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">- [X]</span> duplicator the site on the source end
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">- </span>disable jetpack image caching, any other caching, as many plugins as you can
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">- </span>ensure theme is supported on php 7.x
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">- [X]</span> setup nginx for new wordpress site
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">- [X]</span> rewrite your laptop&#39;s hosts files so you can access the new site
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">- [X]</span> create database and user
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">- [X]</span> install duplicate on destination
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">- [X]</span> redo the DNS
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">- [X]</span> certbot
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">- [X]</span> activate jetpack protect / jetpack -&gt; settings -&gt; security -&gt; brute force
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  attack protection.
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">#+begin_src </span><span style="color:#57606a">sql</span><span style="color:#57606a">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">create</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span><span style="color:#cf222e">database</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span>wordpress_blabla<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span><span style="color:#fff">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">GRANT</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span><span style="color:#cf222e">ALL</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span><span style="color:#cf222e">PRIVILEGES</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span><span style="color:#cf222e">ON</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span>wordpress_blabla<span style="color:#1f2328">.</span><span style="color:#0550ae">*</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span><span style="color:#cf222e">TO</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;u_blabla&#34;</span><span style="color:#0550ae">@</span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;localhost&#34;</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span>identified<span style="color:#fff"> </span><span style="color:#cf222e">by</span><span style="color:#fff"> </span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;difficult password&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span><span style="color:#fff">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>flush<span style="color:#fff"> </span><span style="color:#cf222e">privileges</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span><span style="color:#fff">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>exit<span style="color:#fff">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">#+end_src</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">#+begin_src </span><span style="color:#57606a">shell</span><span style="color:#57606a">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>certbot certonly -d vxuni.com,www.vxuni.com --nginx --dry-run
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">#+end_src</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="would-you-like-to-split-the-universe-theres-an-app-for-that">Would you like to split the universe? There&rsquo;s an app for that.</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently reading <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/09/13/760545897/in-something-deeply-hidden-sean-carroll-argues-there-are-infinite-copies-of-you"><em>Something Deeply Hidden: Quantum Worlds and the
Emergence of Spacetime</em> by Sean
Carroll</a>.</p>
<p>Somewhere in there, Carroll mentions the iPhone app <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/universe-splitter/id329233299"><em>Universe
Splitter</em></a>, which
you can use to split the whole universe into copies of itself.</p>
<p>It starts more mundanely, when you have to make a difficult decision between
two options.</p>
<p>Fear no more, because now you can just start up that app, and use quantum
mechanics to make the decision.</p>
<p>As a side effect, you end up splitting the universe.</p>
<p>When you submit your choice, a message is sent to a lab in Switzerland, where a
photon is sent toward a beam splitter.</p>
<p>According to Schrödinger&rsquo;s equation, the splitter turns the photon&rsquo;s wave
function into two components going left <em>and</em> right, each of which ends up at a
different detector.</p>
<p>When either detector picks up the photon, it produces a readout that becomes
entangled with its environment (whoops!), quickly leading to decoherence and a
branching of the wave function into two universes.</p>
<p>Now there are two copies of you.</p>
<p>One copy of you will see choice A, and the other will see choice B.</p>
<h2 id="its-what-future-you-would-want-quote-edition">It&rsquo;s what future you would want, quote edition.</h2>
<p>All the way back in March of &lsquo;19, <a href="/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/#thinking-of-future-you">I wrote about the suggestion to try to
predict which tasks the completion of which would satisfy future you the most
at the end of the
day</a>.</p>
<p>Well, the other day as I was aimlessly browsing twitter, something which was
decidedly NOT a task that future me would have approved of, or a task anyone
could conceivably ever complete, I came across <a href="https://twitter.com/bitfield/status/1219309618813337601">this jewel tweeted by John
Arundel</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If we are ever in doubt about what to do, it is a good rule to ask ourselves
what we shall wish on the morrow that we had done.  &ndash; John Lubbock</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Although the message is the same, I find Lubbock&rsquo;s formulation more elegant.</p>
<p>Folks, have a great week, full of satisfied future yous, in all of the
universes that you are about to inhabit!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>