<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>emacs on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/emacs/</link><description>Recent content in emacs on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2022 17:39:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/emacs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #249: Self-discipline</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2022 17:39:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/</guid><description> Welcome to WHV #249, covering the two weeks from Monday November 7 to Sunday November 20, 2022.
Figure 1: Photo of many Watsonias (up from last week!), taken by partner on a hike.
Emacs Mastodon server was irresistible A week or two ago, I was still chatting with friends about how to respond to the currently in-progress Twitter Muskification.
At that point, largely due to all of the great connections and positive experience I&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying on twitter (howto: follow only kind humans who are involved in your fields of interest; in my case visualization, machine learning, data, mobility), I commented that I had no plans yet and preferred waiting for a bit to see how it would pan out.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to WHV #249, covering the two weeks from Monday November 7 to Sunday
November 20, 2022.</p>








<figure><a href="watsonias_pano_thanks_stella.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/watsonias_pano_thanks_stella_hu67a842a09de0660ba33e5f5aa4572cc4_4076687_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/watsonias_pano_thanks_stella_hu67a842a09de0660ba33e5f5aa4572cc4_4076687_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/watsonias_pano_thanks_stella_hu67a842a09de0660ba33e5f5aa4572cc4_4076687_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/watsonias_pano_thanks_stella_hu67a842a09de0660ba33e5f5aa4572cc4_4076687_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/watsonias_pano_thanks_stella_hu67a842a09de0660ba33e5f5aa4572cc4_4076687_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo of many Watsonias (up from last week!), taken by partner on a hike."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo of many Watsonias (up from last week!), taken by partner on a hike.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="emacs-mastodon-server-was-irresistible">Emacs Mastodon server was irresistible</h2>
<p>A week or two ago, I was still chatting with friends about how to respond to
the currently in-progress Twitter Muskification.</p>
<p>At that point, largely due to all of the great connections and positive
experience I&rsquo;ve been enjoying on twitter (howto: follow only kind humans who
are involved in your fields of interest; in my case visualization, machine
learning, data, mobility), I commented that I had no plans yet and preferred
waiting for a bit to see how it would pan out.</p>
<p>The topic of <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">Mastodon</a> did come up, but the feeling in that tech-savvy group was
that it was perhaps a bit complicated.</p>
<p>In the days since then, the developments at Twitter seemed to have accelerated,
but it&rsquo;s still extremely tricky to predict where all of this will end up.</p>
<p>Also in the days since then, a Swiss gentleman named <a href="https://emacs.ch/@louis">Louis</a> had the nerve ;) to
setup a Mastodon server called <a href="https://emacs.ch">emacs.ch</a>, catering to Emacs enthusiasts&hellip;</p>
<p>CURSES!</p>
<p>I see Emacs, I move.</p>
<p>My account was created a few minutes later, and suddenly Mastodon was not
complicated at all y&rsquo;all!</p>
<p>Things that I really like so far:</p>
<ul>
<li>Anyone can setup an independent yet connected server that caters to a
specific interest group, such as Emacs users.</li>
<li>Much more engagement and connectedness with other users, thanks to the server
focus.</li>
<li>Early internet feelings: Optimism, grassroots, people.</li>
<li>Fantastic Emacs support. I can <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/109337719793270417">read and post directly from Emacs, using the
amazing <code>mastodon.el</code></a>.</li>
<li>No algorithm that re-arranges the posts that you see. What you see is what
your timeline posted, when they posted it.</li>
<li>No ads!</li>
<li>Yes, here you <strong>can</strong> edit your posts after you&rsquo;ve posted them. IT&rsquo;S TRUE.</li>
<li>NO ADS!</li>
</ul>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been having fun tracking down friends and colleagues on their various
mastodon servers, and re-making connections.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re also interested, my advice would be to start by <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/servers">searching for a
server</a> (or more than one!) that really suits you.</p>
<p>Then, if you like, you can find <em>me</em> at <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha">@cpbotha@emacs.ch</a> !</p>
<h2 id="quarto-dot-qmd-looks-like-the-answer-to-my-dot-ipynb-prayers">Quarto .qmd looks like the answer to my .ipynb prayers</h2>
<p>Back in 2018 I talked about <a href="/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/#vacation-based-thinking-driven-tool-sharpening-aka-the-wvv-2018-data-science-toolboxtm">my complicated feelings for Jupyter Notebooks</a>.</p>
<p>To elaborate a bit, I still do think notebooks are amazing, but they are so
amazing that their design limitations can get in the way.</p>
<p>Most recently, the .ipynb format, which is standard .json representing the
various input cells (code and markdown mainly) and also their outputs (yikes!),
caused issues at work.</p>
<p>Although it&rsquo;s convenient from a notebook user standpoint that you can open up
an ipynb and see the last rendered version of the notebook, it really
complicates source control (diffs), and opening the .ipynb up in a normal
editor to debug issues is not fun at all.</p>
<p>Well, recently, spurred on by the below provocative tweet by Chelsea
Parlett-Pelleriti (who is now also on Mastodon as
<a href="https://nerdculture.de/@chelseaparlett">@chelseaparlett@nerdculture.de</a>):</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Friendship ended with .rmd<br><br>now .qmd is my best friend <a href="https://t.co/7ETH4o2KUH">pic.twitter.com/7ETH4o2KUH</a></p>&mdash; Chelsea @chelseaparlett@nerdculture.de (@ChelseaParlett) <a href="https://twitter.com/ChelseaParlett/status/1591505992805543936?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November 12, 2022</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; I decided to take a deeper look at Quarto and especially .qmd.</p>
<p>In short, .qmd is markdown with executable code-cells!</p>
<p>If you take a look at the VSCode-based <a href="https://quarto.org/docs/get-started/hello/vscode.html">Get Started guide</a>, you&rsquo;ll see that can
type up .qmd files in any text editor, and then have the quarto cli tool show
you a continuous preview of your work.</p>
<p>The examples they show look <em>really</em> attractive folks!</p>
<p>One of the fundamental improvements here, is that by design outputs are not
stored inside the .qmd file format.</p>
<p>An addition, the top-to-bottom execution of one&rsquo;s notebook is the primary mode
of operation, although cell-based execution is also possible. This is the
opposite of normal notebooks, where the default interactive cell-based
execution often results in the top-to-bottom not being tested, and hence often
being broken.</p>
<p>For my current analytics applications, it looks like we&rsquo;ll be able to use .qmd
as a drop-in replacement for .ipynb.</p>
<p>Although Org mode and org-babel have been doing this (plaintext file with
executable code cells) for a long time now, I am really excited that there&rsquo;s
now a more accessible solution that will hopefully become very popular.</p>
<p>P.S. After all of that, I was additionally thrilled to discover that Dr Carlos
Scheidegger, a brilliant and friendly colleague from the the data visualization
world, was on the core developer team. Here he is <a href="https://emacs.ch/@scheidegger@mastodon.social/109343921680547594">announcing, on Mastodon, the
just-released v1.2 of Quarto</a>!</p>
<h2 id="self-discipline">Self-discipline</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>You wake up in the morning, refreshed and ready to take on the day.</p>
<p>With your mind as clear as it&rsquo;ll ever be, you make a list of the things that
you know that you should work on today: Let&rsquo;s call them Things A, B, C and H.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;re really passionate about A, but you realise that B and C are at least as
important to your and your family&rsquo;s well-being.</p>
<p>H is just something urgent that you&rsquo;ve postponed for too long and now really
has to be taken care of, or perhaps the H stands for Harbinger.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Harbinger of what?&rdquo; I hear you think&hellip;</p>
<p>Shortly after this moment of clarity, the day (on some days aka &ldquo;all Hell&rdquo;)
breaks loose and you suddenly have to deal with all of the vagaries of modern
work and life.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s starting to feel like the crystalline clarity of a few moments ago might
be just a little too brittle to resist the deluge of chaos.</p>
<p>On your <em>better</em> days, you will be able to keep your eye on Thing A, in spite of
all of the obstacles that stand in your path. Your passion for A helps you to
power through.</p>
<p>On your <em>best</em> days, you will find that quiet determination inside, that modest
but diamond-hard resolve that will enable you to tend to Things B and C in
addition to A, with deliberateness and diligence.</p>
<p>In my view, being able to focus on your passions in spite of challenges on your
path sounds like <strong><em>grit</em></strong>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; grit is a positive, non-cognitive trait based on an individual&rsquo;s
perseverance of effort combined with the passion for a particular long-term
goal or end state (a powerful motivation to achieve an objective). This
perseverance of effort promotes the overcoming of obstacles or challenges that
lie on the path to accomplishment and serves as a driving force in achievement
realization. Distinct but commonly associated concepts within the field of
psychology include &ldquo;perseverance&rdquo;, &ldquo;hardiness&rdquo;, &ldquo;resilience&rdquo;, &ldquo;ambition&rdquo;, &ldquo;need
for achievement&rdquo; and &ldquo;conscientiousness&rdquo;. These constructs can be
conceptualized as individual differences related to the accomplishment of work
rather than talent or ability. &ndash; <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grit_(personality_trait)">Wikipedia on &ldquo;grit&rdquo;</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Whereas I would label the characteristic of being able to continue paying
attention to things that are important but not necessarily your areas of
passion <strong><em>self-discipline</em></strong>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Resolute adherence to a regimen or course of action in order to achieve one&rsquo;s
goals. &ndash; <a href="https://dictionary.apa.org/self-discipline">definition #2 from the APA Dictionary of Psychology</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>(Definition #1 on that page is <em>self-control</em>, which seems to be the passive
counterpart (or component) of <em>self-discipline</em>, based on what I can find
online. Unfortunately, what I can find online are mostly second- and third-hand
observations, see e.g. <a href="https://fredericksburg.com/self-control-and-self-discipline-arent-the-same/article_9e91991c-81e8-5a8f-bca0-972e025fbe24.html">quote by Dr. Julia-Marie O&rsquo;Brien #1 without citation</a>,
<a href="https://matthogan.blog/self-discipline-vs-self-control/">same quote #2</a>, <a href="https://selfctrl.com/3-lessons-learned-on-building-self-control/">same quote #3</a> or <a href="https://www.quora.com/Whats-the-difference-between-self-control-and-self-discipline">quora, sorry!</a> &ndash; &ldquo;Self-control says no, or
stop. Self-discipline says go, and keep it going.&rdquo; &ndash; Although I would like to
find better discussion about this, the distinction does make sense.)</p>
<p>Self-discipline is one of those skills that can be practised.</p>
<p>By applying it more often, and especially so when it feels like the going has
gotten tough, you&rsquo;ll be able to apply it more reliably and more consistently in
the future.</p>
<p>Self-discipline is the reliable bridge linking you and your goals, at your
absolute best, with you at all other points.</p>
<p>It can be difficult to keep on practising, but when you can look back on one of
<em>those</em> days, and see how you even managed to take care of Things B and C, in
addition to A, in spite of the adversities on your path, you will experience
quiet satisfaction.</p>
<p>Savour the moment.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #240: I am just a copy of a copy of a copy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 21:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</guid><description> Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three weeks instead of one.
I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking
back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of
the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three
weeks instead of one.</p>
<p>I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about
alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more
resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough
time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</p>
<p>(Some more famous bloggers that I follow manage to put out a paragraph or two
every single day. It would be interesting to try an experiment like that.)</p>
<p>Anyways, switching out of meta mode back to the mishmash of on-topics for edition
240:</p>
<h2 id="blood-flowers">Blood flowers</h2>
<p>During a recent karma-restoring family beach walk, we came across the following
pretty striking flowers:</p>








<figure><a href="blood-flowers.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu62a0bda24605aea4c6487fae60149992_3195515_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Blood flowers in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Blood flowers in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The <a href="http://pza.sanbi.org/haemanthus-coccineus">PlantZAfrica website tells us</a> that these are examples of <em>Haemanthus
coccineus</em>, also known as &ldquo;March flower&rdquo; (no idea why) or &ldquo;blood flower&rdquo;, the
latter which is more in line with the meaning of its Greek genus (haima =
blood, anthos = flower), and its Latin species.</p>
<p>We are not the first or only people to find it quite striking:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It was probably the first flower to be collected from Table Mountain and,
probably also the first illustration of a South African flower to appearin a
European publication. The illustration was by the Flemish botanis de L&rsquo;Obel
in 1605. &ndash; PlantZAfrica</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, as if the name &ldquo;Blood Flower&rdquo; is not metal enough, it turns out
<em>Haemanthus coccineus</em> lives fully underground in the form of a large bulb for
the dry summer months, only revealing its brilliant red flower when the rainy
season is about to start.</p>
<h2 id="fantastic-karma-and-how-to-destroy-it">Fantastic karma and how to destroy it</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s Friday evening. We&rsquo;ve just had a brilliant edition of our Friday evening
family braai tradition, and everyone starts retiring to their various
individual relaxation activities.</p>
<p>I decide that it&rsquo;s a great idea to forge ahead with the <a href="https://github.com/vega/react-vega/tree/master/packages/react-vega">react-vega</a> and <a href="https://redux-toolkit.js.org/rtk-query/overview">RTK
Query</a> visualization functionality I had ended my work week with.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d successfully worked with a previous version of the former, and my
confidence in RTKQ&rsquo;s quality was trending upwards due to recent experience in
one of our products.</p>
<p>I had already made a start with this new instance, and surely my first fully
backend-data-driven visualization was only an hour or two away, giving me a
final Friday evening boost.</p>
<p>Well friends, in hindsight I should have stopped right there and then.</p>
<p>Sure, it was the sort of gamble that had often paid off in the past &ndash; who does
not like to start their weekend with the dopamine rush that comes with the
solving of a little technical puzzle, especially one that results in pretty
pictures?! &ndash; but in this case it was doomed to failure.</p>
<p>The later it got, the less able I was to debug the issue, and the less
emotional control I was able to exert over my growing frustration.</p>
<p>(I am still less than happy with the new react-vega&rsquo;s limited documentation,
error handling and examples.)</p>
<p>I went to bed far later than normal, frustrated, and with no solution in sight.</p>
<p>All of this continued to affect my Saturday (grumpy with capital G&hellip; no wait,
all capitals&hellip;), until I finally made the conscious decision to disconnect
from the technical problem completely.</p>
<p>Anyways, I&rsquo;m writing this down as a reminder to me to be really, really careful
with the work-to-weekend transition.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-1-make-my-home-smart-but-do-it-really-slowly">Techno interlude #1: Make my home smart, but do it really slowly</h2>
<p>I finally got around to hooking up one (1) of the <a href="https://shelly.cloud/products/shelly-1-smart-home-automation-relay/">Shelly 1 smart relays</a> I
bought at the end of 2020.</p>
<p>My whole family is now able to open the main yard gate using&hellip; THEIR PHONES.</p>
<p>Noteworthy here is how easily the Shelly switches can be flashed, over the air
(OTA) no less, with the third party <a href="https://github.com/mongoose-os-apps/shelly-homekit">shelly-homekit firmware</a> to make them
natively Apple homekit compatible.</p>
<p>You can read about the how and the what in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/03/05/connecting-the-shelly-1-to-an-et-systems-gate-motor-for-apple-homekit-control/">this vxlabs post</a>.</p>
<p>Shortly after that post appeared, we held a <a href="https://fb.me/e/30MWR7Rq3">&ldquo;home automation&rdquo;-themed Helderberg
Software Developers and Entrepreneurs meetup</a>. Thanks to current interest in the
topic, and the three absolutely brilliant speakers who were willing to take us
along on their HA adventure, it was the biggest and most active we&rsquo;ve had in
years, by far!</p>
<p>In another probably surprising move, we are currently moving the meetup group
away from meetup.com and onto facebook as a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/helderberg.swdev.entrep.meetups/">group</a> (join if you&rsquo;re on fb!) from
where we can easily setup events.</p>
<p>Since 2019, meetup.com has been charging a pretty ridiculous $50 / 6-months fee
for a 100% free meetup with 0 commercial intent. In return for that, they
handle attendance (ish, we ofen had &gt;50% no-shows) and supply a bit of
discoverability.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, we now fortunately also have a snazzy website at
<a href="https://helderberg.dev/">https://helderberg.dev/</a> where you&rsquo;ll always be able to find the meetup, no
matter the events platform <em>du jour</em>.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-2-make-emacs-more-prettier">Techno interlude #2: Make Emacs More Prettier</h2>
<p>In spite of general business, I did have to make time for some <code>init.el</code>
wrangling, as is the privilege and sworn duty of every Emacs user.</p>
<p>This time, I refined my font and specifically <code>variable-pitch</code> setup.</p>
<p>I settled on the <a href="https://www.figma.com/blog/the-birth-of-inter/">Inter font</a> because I liked the look of <a href="https://obsidian.md/">obsidian.md</a>, where it&rsquo;s
the default. Then I discovered that it was designed (based on the Roboto font)
by Figma designer Rasmus Andersson as &ldquo;a font meant to make it easier to read
text on computer screens&rdquo; (hey, that&rsquo;s exactly what I need!), and is now also
the default on github, mozilla, and notion. Pretty good typographic company
right there.</p>
<p>The other small change I made which was much more satisfying than I expected,
was setting the default font size based on the estimated pixel density of the
current screen.</p>
<p>This means that my Emacs will render its default fonts at sizes that make sense
on whichever display I&rsquo;m using it.</p>
<p>Yes, I know that we should have been able to specify <a href="https://github.com/kickingvegas/12pt-should-be-the-same-everywhere/blob/master/absoluteMeasurementDPI.md">resolution invariant font
sizes by now</a>, but until that future arrives, my Emacs config will just have to
compensate.</p>
<p>The screenshot below shows an example of variable-pitch rendering on the left
(org-roam entry at the bottom, automatic topic backlinks at the top) and in the
centre (a slightly earlier draft of this post) and fixed-pitch on the right,
the relevant parts of my <code>init.el</code> showing the font and (<a href="https://github.com/humanoid-colors/emacs-humanoid-themes">humanoid</a>) theme setup.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu3aeba2f1eca743fd6d05e82290a2b27e_886657_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Emacs screenshot. No, I don&amp;rsquo;t like dark themes."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Emacs screenshot. No, <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">I don&rsquo;t like dark themes</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="permutation-city">Permutation City</h2>
<p>When I saw a recommendation for <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156784.Permutation_City">Permutation City, a 1994 sci-fi novel by the
Australian author Greg Egan</a>, I was hesitant.</p>
<p>Would a novel, written more than 25 years ago, about uploading digital copies
of humans to virtual reality (I wrote a bit about that in <a href="/2020/07/01/weekly-head-voices-199-a-bit-stubborn/#a-totally-unexpected-ramble-on-cycles-patterns-and-teleportation">WHV #199</a> back in
2020), still be up to date with the latest ideas on the topic, seeing that
several adjacent fields of research have been advancing at a break-neck pace in
recent decades?</p>
<p>Weeeeell&hellip;.</p>
<p>It turns out great sci-fi has no problem reaching ahead through a quarter
century of modern technological development and then blowing my mind several
times.</p>
<p>With Permutation City, Egan has written the book I would have wanted to write,
in my wildest fantasies of course, about humans, and copies of humans, and the
philosophically indistinguishable self-awareness and consciousness of the
copies, and of their copies, and so on, literally ad infinitum.</p>
<p>Fortunately this is my first Egan novel, and even more fortunately it turns out
that he has produced a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/32699.Greg_Egan">considerable collection of stories</a> which I now have the
privilege to proceed to assimilate!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2021 to 2022 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</guid><description> Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.
I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to 2014 (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and 2015 (no real excuse).
Much later, on Sunday January 23: It could very well still win the Most Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&amp;rsquo;s done.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition
post</a>!</p>








<figure><a href="20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to
<a href="/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/">2014</a> (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and <a href="/2015/01/21/weekly-head-voices-88-just-be-yourself-they-said/">2015</a> (no real
excuse).</p>
<p><em>Much later, on Sunday January 23:</em> It could very well still win the Most
Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Emacs and <code>M-x count-words</code> (on a temporary buffer copied over from <a href="/archive/#2021">the 2021
blog post archive</a>) tells me that I published 28 posts on this blog, and 8
technical posts over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>Just like with the running below, but for different reasons, I lost a lot of
steam during the last few months of the year.</p>
<p>In a truly surprise twist, in 2022 I will again attempt to write regularly, and
to write more, and to keep it up until the end.</p>
<h3 id="stats-addendum">Stats addendum</h3>
<p>Applying the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess log analyzer</a> to this blog&rsquo;s log files with the following
invocation:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#859900">for</span> i in {2..13..1}; <span style="color:#859900">do</span> <span style="color:#cb4b16">echo</span> cpbotha.net.access.log.<span style="color:#268bd2">$i</span>.gz; <span style="color:#859900">done</span>) | xargs zcat -f -- | goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; tells me that in 2021 cpbotha.net welcomed over 115000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>The same tool reports that <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a> clocked in at just under 165000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>Even if the real number of actual human visits is a quarter of what the tool is
reporting, I am ecstatic!</p>
<p>The three most popular cpbotha.net posts based on hits during 2021 were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">Dear USA, my data has left your building</a></li>
<li><a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">Note-taking strategy 2019</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>Thanks to Strava&rsquo;s handy training calendar shown below, we can see that I spent
125 hours last year (mostly, about 4 hours was spent on hiking just over 20km)
running a bit over 1300km.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can also see quite clearly that I lost steam in November and especially in
December.</p>
<p>This was initially due to work getting quite busy, and then later in December a
bout with Omicron (highly probably) and also less than run-friendly weather in
St. Francis.</p>
<p>I am always happy when I manage to average 100km or more per month, and I&rsquo;ll
probably try to do that again in 2022.</p>
<h3 id="possibly-tmi-read-on-at-your-own-risk">Possibly TMI, read on at your own risk</h3>
<p>Those of you who know me, will also know about my giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunion">bunion</a>, or hallux
valgus as it prefers to be called.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&amp;rsquo;s complicated." width="240px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyways, Mr Valgus is unfortunately playing an increasingly frequent role in my
attempts at running, often starting to complain at N kilometres where N is
fortunately still higher than most of my attempts, but still affecting a
worrying number of them.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to push on, until Mr Valgus overstays its welcome, at which point
it will be time to explore invasive corrective procedures.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Probably my most redeeming habit of them all, is reading books every night in
bed until I fall asleep.</p>
<p>Even if the day has been less than satisfactory, ending it with an entirely
deliberate and focused reading session tends to make up for quite a lot.</p>
<p>Although I was planning to do more book summaries in 2021, I managed to
complete only one. At least it was a good one, namely <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Seven
and a Half Lessons About the Brain&rdquo; by Lisa Feldman Barrett</a>, which I can
strongly recommend if you have not checked it out yet.</p>
<p>Thanks to strong contenders like the one above, the competition was fierce, but
in the end the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em> could go to nothing other
than Oliver Burkeman&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08FGV64B1/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</em></a>.</p>
<p>Burkeman, he of the <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">importance of being able to put <em>down</em> your work</a> and of <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">more
appearances on this blog</a>, has created a beautifully written ode to our terribly
limited lifespans (4000 weeks if you&rsquo;re lucky, you can almost hear them ticking
away&hellip;), and to our terribly limited capacity to make the most of the time
that we do get, and to really just giving up the fight to <em>get everything done</em>,
because we will never ever win the battle against the law of perpetually
filling inboxes of various kinds, and because it&rsquo;s so much better to simply
<em>disconnect</em> from the firehose (which we can&rsquo;t get rid of completely) in order to
spend time on no-excuses leisure, and especially on our loved ones.</p>
<p>My favourite fiction book by far was <em>The Anomaly</em> by Hervé le Tellier, as
translated by Adriana Hunter.</p>
<p>After having just grudgingly finished Elizabeth Bear&rsquo;s Ancestral Night (first
novel in the White Space series; some interesting ideas, but just too pulpy,
clumsy and exposition-rich for my taste, in spite of space opera being a guilty
pleasure&hellip;), the light literariness and French cynicism of The Anomaly was a
<em>delightful</em> and refreshing breeze that I was unable to put down until it was
done.</p>
<p>In 2022, I&rsquo;m planning to read more than in 2021, and publish more of those
summaries.</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#mindfulness">daily meditation streak that started in 2020</a> continued for most of 2021,
until the end-of-year school vacation started. I am not yet sure how I&rsquo;ll be
able to fit this into my new 2022 work-routine.</p>
<h2 id="worst-habit-of-2021">Worst habit of 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV Award for Worst Habit of 2021 By Far goes, without a doubt, to my old
friend TwiFRaF-Yo, although this time around the main culprits were Twitter,
Reddit and YouTube.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know exactly when I fell out of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">the previous social media fast</a>, but I
fell out with a vengeance.</p>
<p>Although I subscribe almost entirely to technical communities on reddit (Emacs,
Orgmode, Org-roam, keyboards, etc.), there are enough of them to keep a person
busy.</p>
<p>If you add to that my twitter feed, where I&rsquo;ve also taken care to remove the
noise, subscribing largerly to high-signal science-, technology- , and
engineering-related feeds, there&rsquo;s a great deal of valuable-seeming information
that one feels compelled to get through every day&hellip;</p>
<p>(It feels like I&rsquo;ve told this story before&hellip;)</p>
<p>Anyways, every time I manage to disconnect (it&rsquo;s been a few weeks now, I think
Monday January 3 was the official start date of the current fast), only then am
I able to recognise (where by &ldquo;recognise&rdquo;, I mean that friends say this to me,
and this is when I&rsquo;m able to admit that they&rsquo;re right) that the net value for
me is highly probably negative.</p>
<p>While there is certainly valuable information that enters via those streams, it
costs so much attention and emotional energy that it&rsquo;s not really worth it.</p>
<p>So.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m back on the no-social-media cart until next time.</p>
<p>Just like the previous time, I&rsquo;m limiting myself to the brilliant Inoreader RSS
subscription service (which I pay for) to keep up to date with 99% long-form
blogs, and two Twitter accounts that are worth too much to me to disconnect
from (<a href="https://twitter.com/erictopol">Eric Topol</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/alper">Alper Çuğun-Gscheidel</a>).</p>
<p>Although I sometimes think this makes me slower, because I don&rsquo;t have all of
the current happenings at my fingertips all the time, I&rsquo;m hoping this gives me
more space and time for reading, thinking and writing.</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">Systems and tools for running this human (PKM baby)</h2>
<p>In the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">2018 to 2019 transition post</a> I mentioned the &ldquo;The System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This time, for this section, I would like to limit it to tools for knowledge
management and task management (this is not my favourite term, but I&rsquo;m erring
on the side of familiarity here) .</p>
<p>All of Emacs and Orgmode and Org-roam is still going strong, although I waver
quite a bit sometimes when I see some of the shiny new things, like <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>,
which I would probably be using if it wasn&rsquo;t for Emacs.</p>
<p>However, when I sometimes dive into my notes, I can see the difference it makes
when you stick to a single tool for longer than a few years. The amount of
knowledge keeps on growing, and I am slowly getting better at linking it all
together and&hellip;  sometimes even using it.</p>
<p>The picture below shows the graph created, by the <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> package, of a
sub-section of my notes network:</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Before I got side-tracked by the pretty picture, I was planning to dedicate
this section to a new WHV award, namely the Award for the Most Unexpectedly
Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021.</p>
<p>This year the award goes to&hellip; <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper/guide">Dropbox Paper</a>!</p>
<p>Back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">WHV #233</a> I listed many of the reasons why. In the few months since then
it has become only more useful to me as the go-to mobile tool for checklists
(especially useful when we go on trips), lists of books, movies and music
recommended by people in person, and so on.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualifier features, such as its markdown DNA and its
usability on mobile for idea capturing, the fact that Paper documents show up
in Dropbox searches, which is how I usually search when I <span class="underline">really</span> need to find a
specific file (versus ripgrep searches in Orgmode), is the deal maker.</p>
<p>(My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">strange scheme for continuously converting all org files to docx</a> for
searching and reading on the iPhone is also still going strong.)</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I had a piece written here with more details about what exactly was happening
at work, but I decided to nuke that and instead keep it more personal by
mentioning that thanks to great big dollops of serendipity and people, I find
myself, with a number of levers at my disposal, right in the middle of an
organization which, after a few months of reconfiguration and preparation, has
embarked on a genuinely exciting, and importantly more unified, course.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not mention the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">discomfort and stress</a> I was
experiencing at the start of the current personal phase, most probably due to
trying to adapt quickly to my new circumstances and responsibilities.</p>
<p>In the time since then, my stress levels have returned to more acceptable
levels, but expectations remain high.</p>
<h2 id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<p>One of the most positive changes I made in the past year, was to put more
effort into making regular and active (virtual) contact with friends whom I
don&rsquo;t see in person regularly enough.</p>
<p>THANKS INTERNET YOU DA BEST.</p>
<p>This year, I want to try harder to do more of that.</p>
<p>More generally, I made a note (yes, again, one has to keep doing this until the
end) to celebrate any of my peeps and our relationships whenever there&rsquo;s a
chance.</p>
<p>Secret message for my innner INNER circle: You are my energy and my joy, I am
here to be yours.</p>
<p>Whatever else happens, these precious relationships are all we have.</p>
<h2 id="even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">Even more plans for 2022: Continue trying</h2>
<p>First off, I would really like to get this blog post here done and
published. (it wants to be too much, or rather I want it to be too much, and so
we sit here staring at each other instead of just getting on with it so I can
try again to write a good post for once)</p>
<p>Second, EAZ is back on, since Monday January 10. EAZ means no alcohol until at
least February 10. As has been the case previously, my sleep quality is
subjectively better, and it seems like my energy levels are more consistent
throughout the week.</p>
<p>I just looked back at last year&rsquo;s transition post, and especially at the <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">final
sections, including the neatly documented Life Systems 2021</a>. That guy
(<a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">apparently we share only about 2% of our atoms</a>) really seemed to have his
stuff together, on paper at the very least.</p>
<p>As I write this (22:38 on Saturday, January 22), I have just realised that <em>this</em>
&ldquo;I&rdquo; definitely needs to spend some more time thinking about &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo; (The WHV
approach to life, the universe and everything, the one with the pillars (love
and science, that&rsquo;s the easy and reliable bit) and the rules) and specifically
if and how to revise the daily life direction clusters.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll have it on your desk by Monday.</p>
<p>Until then, the one thing I&rsquo;m sure about, is that I wish you and your loved
ones the best 2022 possible.</p>








<figure><a href="stormsriver-mouth.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #230: Follow your blisters</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="van_breda_cottage_angles.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&amp;rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &amp;ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&amp;rdquo; (I didn&amp;rsquo;t and I don&amp;rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV covers the three weeks from Monday July 26 to Sunday August 15.</p>
<h2 id="why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">Why I don&rsquo;t like dark mode anymore</h2>
<p>As you might know, I spent most of my working (and sometimes hobby, we&rsquo;ll get
back to that further down) hours in front of this screen or some other screen.</p>
<p>Up to now, I was really convinced that I preferred dark mode everywhere, until
recently two events transpired:</p>
<p>I started noticing more eye-strain than usual, even on my 27&quot; screen, something
which had a perceptible effect on my productivity. This I resignedly ascribed
to my advancing age, although I did find the suddenness quite surprising,
especially since I recently had my glasses updated.</p>
<p>Then, after years with only the admittedly brilliant <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">zenburn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/fniessen/emacs-leuven-theme">Leuven (dark)</a>
Emacs themes checking all of the boxes for me, I finally ran into a really
interesting and usable theme called <a href="https://github.com/kunalb/poet">Poet</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s interesting, because it uses variable pitched fonts for everything but
code, tables and elements of the fixed width domain, where most Emacs fonts
stick to the traditional all-fixed-width approach.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="20210822-poet-theme-screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can probably understand that for someone who uses Emacs almost primarily
for technical notes and other writing, this book-like appearance could work
really well.</p>
<p>The theme was even more interesting for me personally, as it suddenly became
clear as day that I experienced almost no eye-strain when using Emacs with this
lighter theme than when I used any of my other usually dark-themed tools!</p>
<p>It became obvious that poet-theme&rsquo;s lighter background was much easier on my
eyes than dark mode in vscode. (No, this specific advantage can&rsquo;t be ascribed
to Emacs itself I&rsquo;m afraid.)</p>
<p>Reading pages such as <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/digital-eye-strain/is-dark-mode-better-for-eyes/">this</a> explains that dark mode leads to pupils having to
dilate more to let in more light, which there is less of with dark themes.</p>
<p>This leads to, just like with cameras and any other optics with lenses and
apertures, a shortened depth of field, and hence more difficulty focusing on
the screen!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/dark-mode/">This article by the well-known Nielsen Norman Group</a> nicely summarises research
on this topic. In short:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In people with normal vision (or corrected-to-normal vision), visual
performance tends to be better with light mode, whereas some people with
cataract and related disorders may perform better with dark mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Up until recently, I did not experience a qualitative difference in vision
between dark and light, but I sit here relieved that my eye-strain issue has
been resolved by an Emacs theme!</p>
<h2 id="know-how-to-put-down-your-work">Know how to put down your work</h2>
<p>The following take from <a href="https://twitter.com/brandsrock/status/1426163442256330753">a recent tweet by mike joubert</a> struck me
(tweet-take-strike! words are funny&hellip;):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly valuable skill isn&rsquo;t the capacity to push yourself harder, but to
stop and recuperate despite the discomfort of knowing that work remains
unfinished, emails unanswered, other people&rsquo;s demands unfulfilled.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">article, titled <em>The three-or-four-hours rule for getting creative work
done</em></a>, is itself a good read about the observation that creative types (amongst
which I count engineers) have at their best three to four hours of focus time
per day &mdash; so it is crucially important that their days are structured such
that there is an <strong>uninterrupted</strong> block of three to four hours inside of which
that lovely focus has the possibility of appearing.</p>
<p>The tweet-extract focuses on the similarly important but more subtle art of
being able to put one&rsquo;s work down, completely, when that block of time is over,
even when it feels like the work is far from complete.</p>
<p>I especially like that it also explicitly mentions the illusions created by
one&rsquo;s perception of &ldquo;other people&rsquo;s demands&rdquo;, something that ironically becomes
even harder to walk away from when one is more tired at the end of the work
day.</p>
<p>For me, becoming better at putting work down has pleasant echoes of running
slower to run faster, of emptiness in art and more broadly, <a href="https://zenhabits.net/work-less/">choosing fewer f*cks
to give</a>.</p>
<h2 id="follow-your-blisters">Follow your blisters</h2>
<p>On the topic of choosing your ducks&hellip;</p>
<p>I initially did not like <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/what-you-should-follow-instead-of-your-passion">this HBR</a> post when it first crossed my stream, because
it smacks a bit too much of the current social media style of &ldquo;wisdom&rdquo;, namely
&ldquo;everything you need to know in 280 characters&rdquo;, or &ldquo;this 1 minute tiktok video
will change your life&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the title is pretty clickbaity: <em>What You Should
Follow Instead of Your Passion</em>.</p>
<p>However, the core message of the post, which I could not help reading, did
stick with me, and after a few days I realised that I would have to go find the
article again in order to talk about it here.</p>
<p>The core message is to replace <em>find your passion</em> with <strong><em>Find your blisters.</em></strong></p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s point is that folks often get the wrong idea with <em>passion</em> as
something that is simply always delightful, whilst the thing you should
actually be looking for, is that activity that you simply are unable to stop
doing, even when you try, and especially even when you don&rsquo;t directly derive
pleasure from it, for example because you feel that you&rsquo;re not that good at it.</p>
<p>They give the personal example of writing.</p>
<p>Although they&rsquo;ve been at it for years, it&rsquo;s still a difficult and laborious
process, and they are often not happy with the results.</p>
<p>However, they have been unable to stop from returning to writing projects again
and again over the years.</p>
<p>Ironically, even although they find that they are still bad at it, they have in
fact become really good, simply because they have been pushing through and
practising more than almost anyone else over the years.</p>
<p>I really like this down-to-earth view.</p>
<p>One can indeed source almost unlimited amounts of energy from one&rsquo;s &ldquo;blisters&rdquo;,
but true benefits will for a large part be brought about by a <a href="/tags/practice/">lifetime of often
challenging practice</a>.</p>








<figure><a href="flowers_everywhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &amp;ldquo;blommetjieskyk&amp;rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>New Emacs-capable hardware: M1 MacBook Air</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 21:49:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</guid><description><![CDATA[ You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I usually write a little something about it.
These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&rsquo;ve back-tagged most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient &ldquo;new computer&rdquo; tag list!
Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of the new Apple M1 chip and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I
usually write a little something about it.</p>
<p>These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&rsquo;ve back-tagged
most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient <a href="/tags/new-computer/">&ldquo;new computer&rdquo; tag
list</a>!</p>
<h2 id="fast-cheap-and-energy-efficient-choose-three">Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three</h2>
<p>This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of
the new <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple%5FM1">Apple M1 chip</a> and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great
performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.</p>








<figure><a href="m1-macbook-air-about.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_huf0cf78004650233083ccbdd28c330650_588664_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_huf0cf78004650233083ccbdd28c330650_588664_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_huf0cf78004650233083ccbdd28c330650_588664_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_huf0cf78004650233083ccbdd28c330650_588664_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;m still <em>quite</em> happy with the <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1 Extreme Gen1</a> as my main
workstation, but although classed as thin-and-light it <em>is</em> still a
workstation.</p>
<p>Specifically, due to the fact that it takes at least a minute or two to resume
from sleep, and the fact that its performance on battery is substantially
slower than on AC, it&rsquo;s not the sort of machine that you can flip open to work
on when inspiration strikes.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, it&rsquo;s a really effective lap warmer, and so gets
uncomfortable <em>quite</em> quickly.</p>
<p>In sharp contrast, the performance of this MacBook Air is the same, namely
&ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;, whether it&rsquo;s on AC or on battery, the laptop resumes from
standby faster that I&rsquo;m able to open the lid, and it hardly ever gets warm.</p>
<p>In short, I can bust this out of my bag and be typing on my lap in under 3
seconds, and this is something that has already started paying off in terms of
my writing.</p>
<h2 id="this-might-be-the-best-emacs-host-i-ve-ever-used">This might be the best Emacs-host I&rsquo;ve ever used</h2>
<p>This very post is currently being typed on <code>GNU Emacs 27.1.91 (build 1, arm-apple-darwin20.3.0, Carbon Version 164 AppKit 2022.3) of 2021-03-15</code> on the
device in question.</p>
<p>Have I mentioned &ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;?</p>
<p>By the way, if you build Emacs like this on the M1:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew tap railwaycat/emacsmacport
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew install --formula emacs-mac --HEAD
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; you should be good to go.</p>
<h3 id="update-on-2021-04-15">Update on 2021-04-15</h3>
<p>A few days ago, I started seeing the following error during homebrew Emacs update:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-text" data-lang="text"><span style="display:flex;"><span>./temacs --batch  -l loadup --temacs=pbootstrap
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>make[1]: *** [bootstrap-emacs.pdmp] Killed: 9
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>make: *** [src] Error 2
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This looks similar to <a href="https://github.com/d12frosted/homebrew-emacs-plus/issues/292">this github issue on emacs-plus</a>, which was fixed on emacs
master.</p>
<p>It was easiest for me to switch to emacs-plus, which went like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew uninstall emacs-mac
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew tap d12frosted/emacs-plus
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew install emacs-plus@28 --with-no-titlebar
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="quo-vadis-one-device-to-rule-them-all">Quo vadis, one device to rule them all?</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s a pity that the ThinkPad, although powerful enough to satisfy <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#the-story-behind-this-story-one-context-to-rule-them-all">my single
computing device / single context requirement</a>, and with <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 becoming
increasingly useful</a> and hence addressing the dual-boot issue, does not satisfy
the <em>instantly available</em> requirement.</p>
<p>Fortunately the two devices cater for complementary contexts.</p>
<p>The Air is for instant-on writing, communication, admin and maybe a tiny bit of
development, whilst the ThinkPad is for all of the heavy lifting, but who knows
how these lines are going to be blurred in the coming months?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #210: MiniBurn 2020</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 09:50:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/</guid><description> Welcome back to the WHV blogging clubhouse, gang!
Somewhat inspired by Descartes, I can say with a fair amount of confidence that you are now reading these words, and for that I am grateful.
This post covers the weeks from Monday, November 9 to Sunday, November 22 of the year 2020.
papercite_static: put some bibtex into your Hugo After languishing for almost a year on my todo list, I finally got around to cleaning up and making available my Python script for embedding your BiBTeX bibliographies in your markdown files.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="dirt_road_to_stanford.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu0d74330c058446a99ca5dd87a0591421_1983338_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Welcome back to the WHV blogging clubhouse, gang!</p>
<p>Somewhat inspired by Descartes, I can say with a fair amount of confidence that
you are now reading these words, and for that I am grateful.</p>
<p>This post covers the weeks from Monday, November 9 to Sunday, November 22 of
the year 2020.</p>
<h2 id="papercite-static-put-some-bibtex-into-your-hugo">papercite_static: put some bibtex into your Hugo</h2>
<p>After languishing for almost a year on my todo list, I finally got around to
cleaning up and making available my Python script for embedding your BiBTeX
bibliographies in your markdown files.</p>
<p>The script is called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/papercite%5Fstatic">papercite_static</a>, because it was inspired by <a href="https://wordpress.org/plugins/papercite/">the papercite
Wordpress plugin</a> that I previously used, but it was built for use in static
websites.</p>
<p>Catchy right?</p>
<p>This is pretty useful when you are academically inclined, or just really like
managing BiBTeX files.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re one of those people, you can go check it out at <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/papercite%5Fstatic">the papercite_static
github page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="save-image-from-clipboard">save_image_from_clipboard</h2>
<p>From the Department of Catchy Names, the same one that brought you the script
above, comes <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/save%5Fimage%5Ffrom%5Fclipboard">save_image_from_clipboard</a>!</p>
<p>I wrote this to scratch my own extremely niche itch (scranitch-ware!), but it
could be useful in other slightly less niche contexts.</p>
<p>My Emacs is configured with the org-download package so that I can use any
system tool to screenshot an arbitrary region of my screen to the clipboard,
and then tell Emacs to attach whatever is in the clipboard to the current
Orgmode heading.</p>
<p>This is something I use really often during daily note-taking and task
management.</p>
<p>The org-download package expects a PNG image to be available on the
clipboard. When this is not the case, because the screenshotting or other image
copying workflow instead copied a JPG or a BMP (long story, starts with a W,
ends with SL&hellip;), I get a blank attachment which makes me sad, and costs me
more time.</p>
<p>On macOS, I used <a href="https://github.com/jcsalterego/pngpaste">pngpaste</a> for this, a tool that ensures that whatever image
format is in the clipboard gets converted to PNG.</p>
<p>Well, <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/save%5Fimage%5Ffrom%5Fclipboard">save_image_from_clipboard</a> does exactly this, and a little more by simply
converting whatever&rsquo;s on the clipboard to the format that you specify.</p>
<p>This has already saved me countless SECONDS of time, and a substantial amount
of frustration.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;ve again been spending more hobby time with <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a>, which would have
resulted in a much smaller and faster binary in this case, but the Python
version wrote itself fairly quickly, with both of my hands behind my back.</p>
<p>P.P.S. nim is <em>so</em> hard to resist, in spite of what <a href="/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/#nimfatuation-is-now-over">I wrote about nimfatuation
being over, back in WHV #169</a>. It combines much of the expressiveness and some
of the batteries-included of Python, paired with the generation of tiny
self-contained binaries.</p>
<h2 id="my-emacs-is-now-all-in-on-ivy">My Emacs is now all-in on Ivy</h2>
<p>As you will <em>most probably</em> remember from <a href="/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/#you-can-easily-dired-jump-to-the-currently-ivy-readd-file-in-emacs">WHV #171</a>, my Emacs configuration used
a mishmash of <a href="https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm">Helm</a> and <a href="https://github.com/abo-abo/swiper">Ivy</a>.</p>
<p>Helm and Ivy are two great, but different, examples of Emacs completion /
selection frameworks, something that is really important to any disciple of
this amazing religion.</p>
<p>In something that is probably some sort of reflection of my character, I was
happily using both of them simultaneously for quite a while.</p>
<p>However, waking up one morning with the realisation that this was yet another
small context switch that was costing me time and focus, in one of my highest
ROI tool workflows to boot, I decided that it was time to excise Helm from my
configuration.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a few hours of Lisp-driven terraforming, and I was all-in on my
Ivy.</p>
<p>During this terraforming I ran into some undesired behaviour in ivy-rich, which
resulted first in me writing <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/11/15/fix-ivy-rich-switch-buffer-directories-display-in-emacs/">a blog post documenting the work-around</a>, then
noticing that ivy-rich&rsquo;s astute author had subsequently integrated part of my
fix, and finally authoring a <a href="https://github.com/Yevgnen/ivy-rich/pull/92">github pull request (PR)</a>, merged shortly after to
fix the remaining issues.</p>
<p>P.S. I sometimes wonder whether people outside of the open source world
understand how much github contributed to the software world by streamlining
the process whereby random developers are able to contribute lines of source
code into open source projects like this.</p>
<p>WELL DO YA?!</p>
<h2 id="mynoise-dot-net-is-an-amazing-soundscape-generator">mynoise.net is an amazing soundscape generator</h2>
<p>In the past few weeks, Lazar Focus has rescued my days so often.</p>
<p>What usually happens is that I get distracted&hellip; no wait, I fall down a
rabbit-hole&hellip; no wait, I actually get violently pulled into a rabbit
<strong>singularity</strong> from whence no productivity can escape.</p>
<p>The best I can do at that point, is to pour all will power into my puny arm and
click on that FOCUS button in Lazar Focus, at which point it instantly kills
everything that&rsquo;s sapping my attention, and then I again have a chance to save
the day.</p>
<p>Thanks to a recommendation by Noeska which ended up languishing in my
sub-conscious but then fortunately managed to bubble to the top, I found myself
on a wonderful site called <a href="https://mynoise.net/">myNoise</a>.</p>
<p>This is the creation of <a href="https://stephanepigeon.com/">Dr. Ir. Stéphane Pigeon</a>, a research engineer &amp; sound
designer from Belgium, who has combined noise generation as well as a library
of the highest quality recording of samples from the world over with a system
for composing these into the most amazing sound-scapes.</p>
<p>Why is this interesting, you might ask?</p>
<p>Well, in one&rsquo;s quest to block distractions of all kinds, finding the perfect
aural stimulus that is pleasant, but does not soak up attention itself, and is
also able to mask both external and internal (tinnitus, e.g.) sounds, myNoise
is exactly what the doctor ordered!</p>
<p>To give you a taste of Dr Pigeon&rsquo;s attention to detail, see for example the
<a href="https://mynoise.net/NoiseMachines/singingBowlsDroneGenerator.php">singing bowls generator</a>, and then the <a href="https://mynoise.net/NoiseMachines/enliaVocalSoundscape.php">Free-falling with vocalist Enlia
soundscape</a>.</p>
<p>Notice that in both cases you are able to customise different elements of each
soundscape with the sliders, or even press <code>A</code> to have them animate randomly
over time, morphing the landscape as you work.</p>
<p>What I only recently learned, is that Dr Pigeon designed the soundscapes to
work also simultaneously. In other words, keep the two soundscapes above open
in two browser tabs, and note how wonderfully they mesh.</p>
<p>It really feels like my brain is starting to associate high attention mode with
the mynoise soundscapes.</p>
<p>Between that and LF, we might be going places!</p>
<p>P.S. Narrator: <em>Yes, he did make a small donation to mynoise, and based on the
value he has derived since, will probably make another.</em></p>
<h2 id="what-does-it-mean-for-humanity-when-the-ai-can-derive-your-talking-face-from-your-voice-alone">What does it mean for humanity when the AI can derive your talking face from your voice alone?</h2>
<p>You might have read about <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/5/21502003/nvidia-ai-videoconferencing-maxine-platform-face-gaze-alignment-gans-compression-resolution">NVIDIA&rsquo;s new AI-based video conferencing bag of
tricks, called Maxine</a>.</p>
<p>An interesting part of this is that they use a technique, similar to deepfakes,
to send only the pose of your face over the internet, and then reconstruct a
high quality version of it on the other side.</p>
<p>From the article:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Instead of streaming the entire screen of pixels, the AI software analyzes the
key facial points of each person on a call and then intelligently re-animates
the face in the video on the other side,&rdquo; said the company in a blog
post. &ldquo;This makes it possible to stream video with far less data flowing back
and forth across the internet.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This made me think:</p>
<p>Soon the AI will be good enough that it can reconstruct your face from just the
audio, or maybe even text that you type.</p>
<p>This idea started as a half-serious joke, but it does raise really interesting
questions around the implications of this technology. (BTW, it is technically
entirely possible.)</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re having a conversation with someone, and both of your faces are
indistinguishable <em>simulations</em> of the real thing, and hence help the quality
of the conversation, what does that mean for the conversation that&rsquo;s happening?</p>
<p>In other words, imagine for a second that you&rsquo;re having an intense (emotional)
conversation with someone, but the faces that both of you are seeing, are 100%
synthesised.</p>
<p>They reflect almost exactly how your faces would have looked had you had a
video link, but they are estimated by the AI.</p>
<p>Did you really have that intense conversation?</p>
<h2 id="miniburn-2020">MiniBurn 2020</h2>
<p>As you might remember from <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#sht-gets-real-in-mzansi">WHV #191</a>, AfrikaBurn 2020 was one of the first group
events down here that was cancelled by the pandemic.</p>
<p>Months after that, and with stats looking almost reasonable, the local subset
of our camp (THE BURNIVERSITY) decided to celebrate life together, as
responsibly as possible (which mostly comes down to: stay outside, keep your
distance), by gathering at some secret but beautiful location for the weekend.</p>
<p>(You might have deduced by now that this is one of those Burny situations where
I have no choice but to keep things as vague as they are. I still wanted to
write <strong>something</strong> as a beacon for future me. Future me, when you read this:
Read our private notes man. I left you something there.)</p>
<p>We sort of modeled the weekend like a whole Burn: Friday is arrival, setup, and
first small celebrations. Saturday represents the body of the week: Running,
workshops, celebration. Sunday is, just like it is for the full Burn, the
slightly depressing but already nostalgic clean-up, pack-up and leave the
desert stage. It&rsquo;s surprising how well this whole sequencing worked.</p>
<p>Thanks to the awe-inspiring talents of specific camp members, the cuisine was
divine and the music beautiful. Combined with the personalities and shared
memories of our small ensemble, the resultant experience was nothing short of
magic.</p>
<p>P.S. Ironically, <a href="/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/#thank-you-joris">GU43 <strong>is</strong> turning into the 2020 soundtrack that I wanted</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #204: What is your purpose?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 22:22:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</guid><description> Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September 13, 2020.
Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.
Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.
Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices,
examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September
13, 2020.</p>
<p>Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more
subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being
outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.</p>








<figure><a href="guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with Microsoft Research&amp;rsquo;s Image Composite Editor, and the power of math."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/product/computational-photography-applications/image-composite-editor/">Microsoft Research&rsquo;s Image Composite Editor</a>, and the power of math.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="sleep-update">Sleep update</h2>
<p>With our teenager back in school, we have to get up at 5:45, mercifully only
for two days of the week with the school in COVID-19-mode.</p>
<p>On other days we get to sleep in until 6:45. LUXURY!</p>
<p>(The lock-down also saved us from a few months of 5:45 wake-ups 5 time per
week during the darkest part of the winter, so there&rsquo;s that.)</p>
<p>This, together with increased pressure at work, has again brought into sharp
focus my sleep hygiene.</p>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t been doing too badly during the past months, but the current period
seemed to require a tad more attention to good sleep.</p>
<p>After reading the disappointing news that the promised first-party (Apple, in
other words) sleep-tracking in the new WatchOS 6 release was not going to be
much more than tracking time in bed, I searched around for the best third-party
sleep tracking app.</p>
<p>Well folks, after a few weeks of testing, I think that <a href="http://autosleep.tantsissa.com/">AutoSleep</a> is it!</p>
<p>(Beware, there&rsquo;s a straight rip-off app in the Google Play store. It&rsquo;s not even
in the same reality as the real thing, although the scammers have stolen a
bunch of visual elements and even copy from the real autosleep website. Oh
Android&hellip;)</p>
<p>The app appears to be almost too full of complicated-looking visual gizmos, so
much so that initially I was not as positive about it. See below for an example
of my sleep history overview:</p>








<figure><a href="autosleep_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot_huce0efa54e288cea4a99599142a3b63a7_817330_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot.png"
            

         width="240px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>However, after using it for a while, and coming to grips with the various
pieces of feedback, this app has turned out to be a great tool in my quest for
sleep hygiene nirvana.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I did have to change my watch charging habits by charging my watch
in the evening hours, so that I can sleep with it on my wrist, and I also have
to remember to tap the &ldquo;lights out&rdquo; button when I attempt to start my sleep
(you don&rsquo;t have to do this, but it gives more accurate tracking that way).</p>
<p>Now I have measurements to show how important the wind-down routine is (if I
can fit in some book-reading in bed, I can fall asleep after that in almost no
time); how some nights when it feels like I&rsquo;m quite restless, I actually do get
quite an amount of sleep; and finally how a drink or two on a weekend night can
affect my average heart rate through the night (+5 beats, oof), and more.</p>
<h2 id="wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 and nativecomp Emacs workflow update</h2>
<p>The following is for my more nerdy readers.</p>
<p>After running into <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/WSL/issues/4619#issuecomment-678652118">this comment</a> on a github issue I am subscribed to, I learned
that you can use the versatile <a href="http://www.dest-unreach.org/socat/">socat</a> tool to forward connections from a unix
socket on WSL2, via the WSL bridge and a WSL1 instance, to a TCP port on
localhost.</p>
<p>The upshot of this is that I now have a robust X11 connection from WSL2 to X410
running on my Windows laptop.</p>
<p>This is possible without socat, but you either need to forward ports using SSH
(which I&rsquo;ve done), or punch holes in the firewall, and then, as if that&rsquo;s not
bad enough, deal with a connection that breaks every time the laptop goes into
suspend.</p>
<p>With the socat X11 connection in place, I decided that it was time to go
further around the WSL2 bend and replace my complicated rsync-based scripts for
copying source code from the Windows host to the WSL2-native filesystem with a
second instance of dropbox running directly on WSL2, with a severe selective
sync configuration.</p>
<p>By the way, after <a href="https://dropbox.tech/infrastructure/rewriting-the-heart-of-our-sync-engine">Dropbox rewrote their sync engine (in Rust)</a>, nothing else
even comes close in terms of performance.</p>
<p>Thanks to this perfect storm of socat-X11-boosted WSL2 and MULTI-dropbox, I
decided that it was finally time to commit to <a href="https://akrl.sdf.org/gccemacs.html">the new nativecomp Emacs &ldquo;capable
of compiling and running Emacs Lisp as native code&rdquo;</a>, so I busted out my
slightly modified version of <a href="https://masteringemacs.org/article/speed-up-emacs-libjansson-native-elisp-compilation">Mickey Petersen&rsquo;s</a> Dockerfile and compiled me one.</p>
<p>This very post is being written on native-compiled Emacs Lisp, running on WSL2,
displaying via socat to X410.</p>
<p><code>#feelsgoodman</code></p>
<p>(P.S. I&rsquo;ve been running like this for about three weeks, with nary an
issue. The future is now.)</p>
<h2 id="keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">Keyboard update: Unicorns-with-RGB</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/#my-attempt-at-dipping-my-toes-carefully-into-the-world-of-mechanical-keyboards">WHV #200 how I carefully started dipping my toes in the
clickity-clackety waters of mechanical keyboards</a> by acquiring a cheap keyboard
with hot-swappable <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile-clicky/outemu-blue/">Outemu blue switches</a>.</p>
<p>What I did not tell you then, was that shortly after acquiring that keyboard, I
had already ordered the <a href="https://youtu.be/e9gRESbY-e8">Womier K87 all-acrylic RGB-overload keyboard</a> from
Banggood.</p>
<p>My reason for ordering that specific board was not so much the lighting (WHICH
IS FREAKING SPECTACULAR BUT BACK THEN I DID NOT KNOW THIS), but rather because
it was the most affordable mechanical keyboard with universal(-ish)
hotswappable switches.</p>
<p>You see, the Outemu board can only take Outemu switches, while with a board
with universal sockets, you have access to a whole smorgas(key)bord of
different switches!</p>
<p>The Womier finally arrived after slightly more than a month, with <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile/gateron-brown/">Gateron brown
switches</a> installed as I had requested.</p>
<p>Probably due to both the brown switches (rated 45g actuation force but probably
less, tactile but not clicky) and due to the board&rsquo;s far more solid
composition, my typing comfort and speed on this thing are close to what I
usually have on my Microsoft Sculpt ergonomic.</p>
<p>Because of this, I don&rsquo;t swap back to the Sculpt nearly as often.</p>
<p>Together with the fact that the keyboard has an impressive and varied
collection of intricate animated lighting patterns thanks to the RGB LED behind
each and every single key, and a whole bunch of extra LEDs in the acrylic body,
this leads to a great deal of typing fun.</p>
<p><code>#feelsbrightman</code></p>
<h2 id="running-update">Running update</h2>
<p>Back in <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">WHV #177</a> I embraced the space and acquired my first pair of Altras, a
pair of road shoes named Escalante 1.0, for a good price, because the 1.5 had
already been released.</p>
<p>Recently I was again in the fortunate position to buy a pair of 1.5s for a good
price, as, you guessed it, the 2.0 had already been released.</p>
<p>The new babies look like this:</p>








<figure><a href="altra_escalante_1.5.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Running in them has been super enjoyable.</p>
<p>(The 1.0s are at about 700km, which is usually a good time to retire them from
running. Now they are just for cocktail parties and business meetings.)</p>
<p>On a more philosophical note, with the aforementioned improving weather, the
aforementioned increased pressure at work, and the non-aforementioned abundance
of mountains all around me, I have taken to randomly taking a few hours off
from aforementioned work to go run in the now aforementioned mountains.</p>
<p><code>#feelslifeaffirmingman</code></p>
<h2 id="what-is-your-purpose">What is your purpose?</h2>
<p>We have a great tradition here at the WHV of revising our official and utterly
complete life philosophy based on discussions with wise friends.</p>
<p>See for example <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">WHV #124</a> where I had to add a third rule to <em>WHV&rsquo;s Two Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em>.</p>
<p>Quite poetically, the additional rule was &ldquo;Evolve&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(FYI, the current official WHV approach to life, the universe and everyhing is
summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.)</p>
<p>During the beautifully-surrounded lunch discussion with longest-time friend
(LTF, henceforth), as depicted in the panoramic photo at the start of this
post, we also spent some time talking about life directions vs. goals.</p>
<p>As you know, I am <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">not a fan of life goals, instead opting for life directions</a>.</p>
<p>LTF agreed with some of my reasoning, but made the valid point that goals were
required to measure and maintain velocity along one&rsquo;s chosen directions, or
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">systems</a>.</p>
<p>In principle we agree on this point also, but I believe that the conversation
will have to continue, as we still need to define and then articulate a
closed-form solution to the directions vs goals issue, or rather a guideline
that can be used to determine the correct relative dosage.</p>
<p>Probably more important was LTF&rsquo;s contribution of the concept of &ldquo;purpose&rdquo;.</p>
<p>One could argue that life directions form one&rsquo;s purpose, but that would be
missing an opportunity I think.</p>
<p>As LTF later quipped:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Purpose = the reason you get up in the morning. Goals = help you go to sleep at
night.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At least in my case, I have a number of life directions, but I think a purpose
is a higher-level, mostly singular, desired outcome of your life&rsquo;s work.</p>
<p>Ideally, <em>life directions</em> should be set in order to orient one towards
fulfilling one&rsquo;s <em>purpose</em>, with continuously evolving <em>goals</em> punctuating the way
there.</p>
<p>What is <em>your</em> purpose?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Note-taking strategy 2019.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 16:19:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/</guid><description><![CDATA[ At the start of 2016, I published an overview of my note-taking strategy then.
In the intervening three and a half years, my note-taking has further evolved to adapt to my changing environment, and the underlying &ldquo;system&rdquo; has co-evolved to support this.
Although note-taking is at the core of the system, a more accurate description of its current purpose would be personal knowledge management.
What you&rsquo;ll also find in this post, is the culmination of many years of lessons learned trying to &ldquo;keep a lab journal&rdquo;.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>At the start of 2016, I published an <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">overview of my note-taking strategy
then</a>.</p>
<p>In the intervening three and a half years, my note-taking has further evolved
to adapt to my changing environment, and the underlying &ldquo;system&rdquo; has co-evolved
to support this.</p>
<p>Although note-taking is at the core of the system, a more accurate description
of its current purpose would be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_knowledge_management"><em>personal knowledge
management</em></a>.</p>
<p>What you&rsquo;ll also find in this post, is the culmination of many years of lessons
learned trying to <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#three">&ldquo;keep a lab
journal&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<h2 id="highest-level-overview-of-note-taking-system">Highest level overview of note-taking system.</h2>
<p>My approach consists of four main components:</p>
<p>At the core of everything is <a href="https://orgmode.org/"><strong>1. Emacs Org mode</strong></a>.</p>
<p>As you might know, Org mode is infinitely flexible. This is where all of my
projects and tasks are tracked. This is also where I keep my daily personal and
work journals.</p>
<p>I describe the specific directory structure and orgfile setup in the sections
below.</p>
<p>I continually and actively search for and find interesting <strong>2. Web-pages and
Articles</strong>, both academic and less so, which I convert to PDF and store in a
year-stamped directory inside of my
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">JBOP</a>.</p>
<p><strong>3. Academic articles</strong> that I plan to refer to in my own writings graduate into my
Zotero bibliographic database, which is synced together with everything else.</p>
<p>On <strong>4. Mobile</strong> (phone and watch, oh my!), I use the Dropbox app for capturing
and for limited access to my notes database via a small subset of markdown
files, PDFs and exported HTML, and I use the new WatchOS 6 voice notes if I&rsquo;m
not able to use my phone.</p>
<h3 id="other-noteworthy-characteristics">Other noteworthy characteristics.</h3>
<p>Everything mentioned above lives on local drives, synced with Dropbox and also
automatically and continuously backed-up to a removable disk at my office.</p>
<p>The Org mode part of the system has been in use since 2014. I have also
imported a few years of Simplenote text notes into Org mode, so its memory
stretches a bit further back still.</p>
<p>The longer the system lasts, the more valuable it gets.</p>
<p>It has now happened more than once that I could help someone with the same
advice I helped someone else with 4 years ago, simply because the real-time
text search found the relevant snippet of code or attachment in my Org mode
database.</p>
<p>Even if I were ever to change tools, the current single source of truth is a
collection of plaintext org files and PDF files which can easily be further
processed and imported into some new system.</p>
<h2 id="the-components-in-slightly-more-detail">The components in slightly more detail.</h2>
<p>In the following sections, I explain each of the four components in more detail
than in the overview above.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-org-mode">Emacs Org mode.</h3>
<p>The heart of my knowledge management system, let&rsquo;s call it <code>pkb4000</code>, is <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Emacs
Org mode</a>. Org mode, or &ldquo;Your life in plaintext&rdquo;, is a
powerful text-file-based system for managing notes, task lists, projects and
even authoring documents.</p>
<p>Once you get used to the programmable flexibility it offers, you will find it
hard to go back to any conventional system.</p>
<h4 id="monthly-journal-files">Monthly journal files.</h4>
<p>In my main Org mode directory, I have a subdirectory named <code>journals</code>, which
contains a directory for each year.</p>
<p>Each of these year directories contains an <code>.org</code> file for each month, so we would have for example
<code>journals/2019/2019-09-Sep.org</code>.</p>
<p>Each month file follows the structure showed in the following redacted version
of my current journal file:</p>
<!-- I used M-x htmlize-region-save-screenshot to get this HTML representation of a real org file onto the clipboard. -->
<pre style="color: #DCDCCC; background-color: #3F3F3F;">
<span style="color: #b3b3b3;">#+TITLE:</span> <span style="color: #8CD0D3; background-color: #3F3F3F; font-weight: bold;">2019-09 September month journal
</span>
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Vitals</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Focus items</span>
Topics and reminders I would like to spend a few minutes on during every
morning review: High value time, always be compounding, always be in a focus
block, etc.
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tired list</span>
A general list of valuable activities for when I have some time, but brain too
tired to come up with anything.
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Planning / overview / major done list</span>
Check lists with books, courses, etc.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Projects</span>
A list of current major projects, with links to each project's dedicated org
file.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks</span>
A list of Org mode tasks that are not associated with specific projects. This
list is reviewed at the start of every month, as I have to manually copy across
those tasks that are still relevant and important.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019-09 September</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">**</span><span style="color: #7CB8BB; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019-09-19 Thursday (example day)</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">***</span><span style="color: #D0BF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Day planning </span><span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-09-19 Thu 09:17]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Done list / thoughts / diary</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks for today </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[/]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[/]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Focus blocks</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Sleep</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Review </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[3/8]</span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> <span style="color: #D0BF8F; text-decoration: underline;"><a href="*Vitals">Month vitals</a></span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> Calendar
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> Org tasks
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> <span style="color: #D0BF8F; text-decoration: underline;"><a href="file:~/Dropbox/notes/mobile/inbox/">dropbox mobile inbox</a></span>
      - ...

<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Habits / important </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[7/12]</span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> 7.5 hrs sleep last night
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> are you satisfied with number of pomodori? = 0 (v R)
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> did you write stuff down?
      - ...
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">***</span><span style="color: #D0BF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* is dropbox better than evernote for mobile capturing? </span><span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">&lt;2019-09-19 Thu 22:16&gt;</span>

     in ios, with any page in safari, I can do "save to dropbox" and get a PDF
     version of the page for the <span style="color: #b3b3b3;">=notes/mobile/inbox=</span>.
</pre>
<p>As you can see from the example above, the monthly journal file is the main
index to my current high-level goals and focus items, my currently running work
and personal projects, miscellaneous tasks, and my detailed daily journalling
and habit tracking.</p>
<h5 id="daily-review">Daily review.</h5>
<p>When I start the day, I instantiate a new org-capture &ldquo;day planning&rdquo; template
by pressing <code>C-c c p</code>.</p>
<p>This creates the <code>Day planning</code> subsection with all of its subsections and
checklists. As you will see, this guides me through the morning review, which
in turn has me check each of those additional sources of incoming information
and tasks.</p>
<p>New bits of information are filed into their correct place, whilst the task
review shows me a list of tasks, extracted from the month file and the list of
current project files, so that I can decide which ones should be taken on.</p>
<p>I list tasks which should preferably be taken care of today under <code>Tasks for today</code>, whilst any really high-value high-satisfaction tasks go under <code>Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl</code>.</p>
<h5 id="during-the-day">During the day.</h5>
<p>During the rest of the day, I&rsquo;ll write short diary-like notes under <code>Done list / thoughts / diary</code> and log pomodori (focus blocks) under, you guessed it,
<code>Focus blocks</code>, either using the <code>org-pomodoro</code> package, or plain Org mode
clocking in and out functions.</p>
<p>I use additional custom org-capture templates, via keyboard shortcuts, to
create more extensive timestamped journal entries (see the <code>is dropbox better ...</code> example) and to create new timestamped and logged Org mode <code>TODO</code> entries.</p>
<h5 id="kill-your-darlings-during-the-monthly-review">Kill your darlings (during the monthly review).</h5>
<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned this before, but it&rsquo;s just an important aspect of my &ldquo;system&rdquo;
that I would like to mention it again.</p>
<p>When I still used primitive task management systems such as <em>everything else</em>
that&rsquo;s not Org mode, the collection of more mature tasks would soon grow out of
control.</p>
<p>However, because I create a new Org mode file for every month, I have to copy
across manually any tasks that have not been completed yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WHY IS THAT NOT AUTOMATED YET?!&rdquo; you are probably thinking.</p>
<p>Well, the advantage of having to copy each task over manually is that it is the
ideal opportunity to evaluate the task and ask some hard questions as to its
continued relevance&hellip;</p>
<p>When a task gets too old, I will often make the decision to change its status
to <code>CANC</code> (for cancelled), sometimes with the reason for the cancellation
explained in the task body, and then just leave it there in the old month file.</p>
<p>With most of these task systems, regular reviews are of crucial importance. The
monthly start-over is a great, almost enforced, opportunity for review, as is
the morning routine when I instantiate the day planner template.</p>
<h5 id="what-about-email">What about email?!</h5>
<p>An important part of knowledge and task management is one&rsquo;s emails.</p>
<p>Although I currently prefer processing my email using
<a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email"><code>mu4e</code></a>,
an email client which lives inside of Emacs, I have used other tools in the
past, and will probably use new tools in the future.</p>
<p>Also, even at this moment I alternate between <code>mu4e</code> and the
<a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">FastMail</a>
web-interface.</p>
<p>Long story short, I have it setup so that I can easily convert any email in
<code>mu4e</code> into a universal <code>message://message-id</code> link to be integrated with a
new task or note entry.</p>
<p>When I later open that link using a shortcut, I have programmed it so that
<code>mu4e</code> will open the relevant email if it is active, or the <code>FastMail</code> webmail
when it is not. From here I can either review the email to see what the
associated task requires, or respond to it, if the task has been completed.</p>
<p>Some of these <code>message://</code> links were created using macOS mail and they still
work. In future, if I add a new mail client to the mix, I will still be able to
jump to specific old emails, no matter where they find themselves inside of my
FastMail mailboxes.</p>
<h4 id="core-notes-database">Core notes database.</h4>
<p>With <code>database</code> I of course refer to hundreds of org and markdown files, most
of which find themselves in the top-level <code>pkb4000</code> directory, one level up
from the <code>journals</code> directory containing all of the monthly journal files.</p>
<p>There are files on various <code>rsync</code> or <code>ffmpeg</code> invocations, files on
programming languages, software tools, note-taking strategies, personal
information on each of my kids, and much more.</p>
<p>Org mode enables me to combine document structure, math, vector and bitmap
images and executable source code in many different languages.</p>
<p>I have configured my Emacs (where by &ldquo;configured&rdquo; I mean &ldquo;coded up the emacs
lisp for&rdquo;) to invoke ripgrep on different subsets of my notes database, and to
proffer up the results in different ways.</p>
<p>I can usually find anything that went in to this database at any point.</p>
<p>What I really like, is also being able to tell you on which day, and during
which hour, I learned this or that, or experimented with something or the
other.</p>
<h4 id="project-files">Project files.</h4>
<p>Work and personal projects each get their own Org file. Some projects even get
a whole directory to themselves, in cases where the project will have many more
files than just the main Org file.</p>
<p>In all cases, the project org file will live somewhere below a year-stamped
directory, e.g. <code>work/projects/2019/project-name/</code>.</p>
<p>Some projects go over year boundaries, but their files and directories remain
in the year that they started in. The project org also has <code>Tasks</code> and a
datetree section, similar to the month journal.</p>
<p>All current project files, along with my the current month file, are configured
to be part of the <code>org-agenda-files</code> variable.</p>
<p>This means that when I activate the <code>org-agenda</code> view, I see a unified list of
all tasks as extracted from all current project files and the current monthly
journal file.</p>
<p>When a project is completed, it is of course removed from <code>org-agenda-files</code>.</p>
<h3 id="web-pages-and-articles">Web-pages and articles.</h3>
<p>As mentioned in the short system overview, I store all web-pages and articles I
come across as date-stamped PDF files in a set of year-stamped directories.</p>
<p>For more detail, please refer to the
<a href="/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">JBOP</a>
section of WHV#165 on this blog.</p>
<p>In short, I use good ad-blocking and <em>mostly</em> the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/">printfriendly browser
extension</a> in Brave or Chromium to convert any
interesting web-pages to PDF. PDF articles from journals and other reputable
sources obviously don&rsquo;t have to be converted.</p>
<p>I name and save these PDFs into my <code>refs</code> hierarchy, for example
<code>Dropbox/refs/2019/20190518 Measles and Immune Amnesia - asm.pdf</code>.</p>
<p>Usually, to win any argument, I can find the pertinent reference on my phone or
my laptop in 30 seconds or less.</p>
<p>(I used to be a paying Pocket subscriber. However, as you will read in WHV#165
cited above, I was disappointed by the super important search function. The
advantages of having Just a Bunch of PDFs on your (synced) disc are many.)</p>
<h3 id="zotero">Zotero.</h3>
<p>The <code>refs</code> directory hierarchy described above is great for quickly storing an
article in the right place with a suitable name, ready for search-based
retrieval later.</p>
<p>However, in cases where one needs to cite any academics works, having these
articles in a good reference manager is important.</p>
<p>Zotero is in my view one of the best reference managers out there, and it&rsquo;s open
source!</p>
<p>The reasons I prefer zotero are:</p>
<ul>
<li>You can make use of their synchronisation service, or you can do it
yourself. I have about 2.3GB of additional articles in zotero, so this is
great.</li>
<li>Zotero uses your browser to retrieve fulltexts automatically when you import
any web-page with bibliographic information using the browser extension. This
is great when you have access via your institution. Competing cloud services
would historically use <em>their</em> servers to retrieve the fulltext, which would
often not work.</li>
<li>Zotero is open source. To me this is important, <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/zotero/">because on more than one
occasion</a> I have been able to make small
modifications to make it perform peculiar tricks I needed at that point.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="mobile">Mobile.</h3>
<p>This has always been the weakest part of my whole knowledge management system.</p>
<p>Ideally, I would have easy access to my complete org database and any related
files. Ideally, it would be possible to store any interesting tidbits I come
across whilst browsing using my phone.</p>
<p>So far I have invested time in the following apps and ecosystems:</p>
<ul>
<li>iCloud Notes: This was great, until <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/#so-tell-me-why-did-your-somewhat-stylish-macbook-phase-have-to-come-to-an-end">I sold my
MacBook</a>. iCloud
Notes web-access is terribly slow and more or less unusable. Whatever I have
on mobile, needs to interoperate smoothly with desktop.</li>
<li>Google Keep: This worked pretty well on mobile and via the web, but it&rsquo;s a
closed off ecosystem. You can
<a href="https://takeout.google.com/settings/takeout">&ldquo;takeout&rdquo;</a> your data, but you
end up with ginormous HTML files (images are base64-encoded and included)
that are not straight-forward to work with.</li>
<li>OneNote: This has SO MUCH potential (free-form note-taking, drawing with
Apple Pencil, apps for so many platforms, great organization, etc. etc.) but
is just so frustratingly unusable due to syncing issues everywhere, even on
my true-blue Windows 10 laptop with the true-blue official gold star
Microsoft OneNote application. Microsoft is doing fantastic work in some
domains (Visual Studio Code, .net core, WSL, etc. etc.) but in some others
not so much it seems.</li>
<li>Evernote: I recently just gave up and bought a premium subscription for the
year, because Evernote is the industry standard and it had Apple Watch voice
notes even before WatchOS 6 was released. In any case, although initially
promising, Evernote is unfortunately quite slow at unpredictable moments
(sharing web-page with evernote mobile app for storage can sometimes take 20
second or more&hellip;) so I&rsquo;ve had to ditch it. Again.</li>
</ul>
<p>During all of this experimentation, I started storing mobile discoveries in a
new section called &ldquo;inbox&rdquo; in the relevant note-taking app&rsquo;s organizational
structure. During morning review, I go through the relevant inbox, and
re-convert the relevant page into PDF for my more permanent archive.</p>
<p>It dawned on me that this approach could also be applied with just the Dropbox
app! It would be klunky, but at least not disappointing.</p>
<p>So, when I want to store something from the phone, I either print to PDF or
make use of the &ldquo;Save to Dropbox&rdquo; app extension, and then store the resultant
PDF in <code>Dropbox/notes/inbox</code>. During morning review, PDFs in this directory are
re-converted if required, and then stored in their more permanent home.</p>
<p>Using the Dropbox app, I can also create markdown text files in the <code>inbox</code>
directory.</p>
<p>If I have something a little more extensive, I have the option of using the
&ldquo;Voice Memos&rdquo; app, either on the phone, or even via the Apple Watch.</p>
<p>In <code>Dropbox/notes/mobile</code> I keep items I often need to access from the phone:
Think loyalty cards, markdown files with IP numbers and configuration of my
home network, and so on. This directory is marked as &ldquo;available offline&rdquo;, so I
can access its contents even when there&rsquo;s no data connection.</p>
<p>Other than that, I do an export of my whole org database to HTML now and then,
following a procedure similar to the one I used <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">to use for exporting Org mode
to iCloud
Notes</a>. The
HTML versions are searchable on the phone.</p>
<p>What would be better, is if the Dropbox iOS app would start recognising .org
files as plaintext files, much like what it already does for markdown .md
files. As it stands, I keep a small subset of my notes as markdown, instead of
the superior org, for mobile editing.</p>
<h4 id="drawing-with-apple-pencil-on-the-ipad-using-notability">Drawing with Apple Pencil on the iPad using Notability.</h4>
<p>Sometimes one does need to sketch.</p>
<p>This could be a rough UI, an architecture diagram, a data flow chart, or just
doodling.</p>
<p>Since about the end of 2018, I&rsquo;ve been using the <a href="https://apps.apple.com/za/app/notability/id360593530">Notability
app</a> along with an iPad
6th gen (2018 entry-level, the first non-Pro to support the Pencil) to doodle
electronically.</p>
<p>Notability automatically syncs all of these drawings as fully vectorised PDFs
to my Dropbox. All handwritten text is quite smartly OCRd, and the OCRd version
is stored as correctly positioned metadata behind my ugly scribbles.</p>
<p>I would have liked Notability even more if it supported arbitrary canvas sizes
(as it stands, only standard paper size in protrait mode), and had an always
visible overview minimap.</p>
<h4 id="signal-messaging-apps-brilliant-note-to-self-contact">Signal messaging app&rsquo;s brilliant &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo; contact.</h4>
<p>The <a href="https://signal.org/">Signal messaging app</a>, which you should all be using,
has a built-in contact called &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As of late (since about December 2019) this has become my main <em>capturing tool</em>
when I&rsquo;m on the phone.</p>
<p>You can share links, media, photos, voice notes or a plain old text message,
all of which will be securely stored, neatly timestampted to boot, in your
conversation with this silent but very useful &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo; character.</p>
<p>During the morning review, I go through each of the shared items, processing
them, and then add the message &ldquo;DONE =====&gt;&rdquo; to indicate that they have been
completed.</p>
<h2 id="limitations-and-points-for-improvement">Limitations and points for improvement.</h2>
<p>The current system is great for capturing and search-based retrieval of
personal knowledge.</p>
<p>However, I miss functionality for making some of the higher-level patterns and
networks more <em>discoverable</em>.</p>
<p>For example, as I create a new orgmode entry, the system could show me related,
older nodes (that is something I could implement&hellip;).</p>
<p>Furthermore, it would have been great to see some form of visual representation
of the associations between nodes, and of how they fit into higher-level
concepts. This bit is slightly far-fetched.</p>
<p>Interestingly, I just ran into the following paragraph at the end of <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">my 2016
note-taking post</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>However, I think that there might be room for a fourth type of tool that is
more visual, supports rich and graphical linking between data items and even
between sub-components of such items and, perhaps most importantly, enables
us to build note landscapes that are natively as non-linear as our thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let&rsquo;s see what happens over the next few years!</p>
<h2 id="appendix">Appendix</h2>
<h3 id="redacted-emacs-orgmode-capture-template">Redacted Emacs Orgmode capture template</h3>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; normally I construct current-journal-filename using mix of expand-file-name and concat</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#cb4b16">setq</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">current-journal-filename</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;/full/path/to/current/month-journal/&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; %i = selected text, %a org-store-link, %U created timestamp, %? place cursor here</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#cb4b16">setq</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">org-capture-templates</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      &#39;((<span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;t&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;Todo&#34;</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">entry</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">file+headline</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">current-journal-filename</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;Tasks&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;* TODO %?\n:LOGBOOK:\n- Created \&#34;TODO\&#34; %U\n:END:\n%i\n%a\n\n&#34;</span> 
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#cb4b16">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#2aa198;font-weight:bold">1</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        (<span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;j&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;Journal&#34;</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">entry</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">file+olp+datetree</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">current-journal-filename</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;* %? %T\n&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#cb4b16">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#2aa198;font-weight:bold">1</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        (<span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;p&#34;</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;Day planning&#34;</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">entry</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">file+olp+datetree</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">current-journal-filename</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;* Day planning %U
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Done list / thoughts / diary
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- %?
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Tasks for today [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Experiment: Articulate your directions / systems.
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Focus blocks
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Review [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] [[*Vitals][Month vitals]]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] Org sub-projects
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] Calendar
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] ...
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">** Habits / important [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] 7.5 hrs sleep last night
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] are you satisfied with number of pomodori? = 0 (v R)
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] did you write stuff down?
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">- [ ] ...
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#cb4b16">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#2aa198;font-weight:bold">1</span>)))
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>
<h3 id="sunday-2020-01-12">Sunday 2020-01-12</h3>
<ul>
<li>Add <a href="#redacted-emacs-orgmode-capture-template">example of orgmode capture template
configuration</a> in appendix.</li>
<li>Add <a href="#drawing-with-apple-pencil-on-the-ipad-using-notability">section about iPad, Notability and Apple
Pencil</a>.</li>
<li>Add <a href="#signal-messaging-apps-brilliant-note-to-self-contact">section about Signal&rsquo;s Note to Self
contact</a>.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #177: Streakers.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 22:26:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</guid><description> A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly challenging post-Sunday-lunch run. This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to Sunday September 8, 2019.
On friendship, 25 years later. The birthday mentioned previously, along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends for more than 25 years now.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="lourensriver_at_vergelegen.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly
challenging post-Sunday-lunch run.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to
Sunday September 8, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="on-friendship-25-years-later">On friendship, 25 years later.</h2>
<p>The birthday <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/#celebration">mentioned
previously</a>,
along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two
small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends
for more than 25 years now.</p>
<p>In the bigger scheme of things, it&rsquo;s not <em>that</em> long, but what I would like to
mention here is how much such friendships can grow into the most honest of
human connections.</p>
<p>It is as if with the passing years, one is able to shed all of the unnecessary
baggage one tends to carry around as a beginner human.</p>
<p>What is left, is pure human warmth, unconditional support and, perhaps most
significantly, the effortless loss of self.</p>
<p><em>You</em> fade away, quite happily so, when one of your friends gets up in the
light to tell a story.</p>
<p>For a while at least, one&rsquo;s only representative in the conversation is one&rsquo;s
undivided recognition of and attention to the other.</p>
<p>This is certainly not reserved for 25+ year friendships, although this
pre-requisite seems to facilitate the process to the point of effortlessness.</p>
<h2 id="nested-headings-of-miscellany-nhom-nhom">Nested Headings of Miscellany (NHoM-NHoM).</h2>
<h3 id="org-pdf-tools-for-constructing-unifying-notes">org-pdf-tools for constructing unifying notes.</h3>
<p>Recently, I had to work through a stack of regulatory documents in PDF format.</p>
<p>The challenge was that the documents described different aspects of a single,
complicated procedure, but were severely lacking in overview-engendering
outlines or, even better, diagrams.</p>
<p>I did what I mostly do when faced with any research-related complexity: BUST
OUT SOME MORE OF THAT EMACS!</p>
<p>I found the Emacs package
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/">org-pdftools</a>, which I then
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/pull/4">PRd to work on my newer
Orgmode</a> (github makes
this sort of collaboration so easy!) and then integrated into my workflow.</p>
<p>org-pdftools enables one to link to specific annotated extracts, created
on-demand inside Emacs, from one&rsquo;s orgmode notes.</p>
<p>I used this to synthesise an overview document explaining the whole process,
linking to different parts of multiple PDFs explaining each aspect in more
detail.</p>
<p>Being able to jump effortlessly from a central overview document to specific
positions in reference PDFs is a huge boon to the research process.</p>
<h3 id="escalante">Escalante!</h3>
<p>One friend of work pointed me at an online source of affordable Altras.</p>
<p>I have secretly been pining for a pair of these shoes.</p>
<p>I was planning to use them for the longer runs when I can feel that my feet
need a little more support than my sandals are able to provide.</p>
<p>However, my feet have really gotten used to the wide open spaces of sandals, or
even better, of going barefoot.</p>
<p>Altras are zero-drop shoes, with <em>ginormous</em> toe boxes. Their motto is &ldquo;Embrace
the Space&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It seems like I have found some shoes with the right motto&hellip;</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://altrarunning.com/">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/altra-foot-space.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>Friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation had shoes that were semi-affordable, contrary to my
expectation.</p>
<p>When I pointed friend #2 from work at friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation, he pointed me
at an even <em>more</em> affordable source.</p>
<p>I <em>could</em> have continued with this iterative process, but I was unable to delay
this purchase any longer.</p>
<p>My new pair of Altra Escalante 1.0s arrived the next day.</p>
<p>(Yes, I know, 1.5 and 2.0 are available. However, <a href="https://runrepeat.com/altra-escalante">the stellar reviews of
1.0</a> have not changed, and did I say
&ldquo;affordable&rdquo;?!)</p>
<p>On Friday I broke them in, and on Sunday I made a slightly longer than normal
run (see in-progress photo above) to see how they did.</p>
<p>Anyways, in spite of the rest of me taking quite a beating on the second run, I
can happily report that the shoes did a marvellous job of balancing support
on the one hand and foot-freedom on the other.</p>
<h2 id="life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">Life optimisation tip #73: Streak more.</h2>
<p>As I was scrolling aimlessly through my facebook feed during my last session
before the Great Social Media Fast of September 2019 (see next section), I
quite ironically ran into a truly interesting post by a Swedish visualization
colleague (SVC).</p>
<p>In this post, he talked about his hobby and progress as a <em>run streaker</em>.</p>
<p>It turns out that there are runners with the <em>excellent</em> additional hobby of
<em>streaking</em>, which in <em>this</em> context refers to the act of running every single
day of their lives, and trying to do these daily runs for the longest
continuous streak possible.</p>
<p>The streakers know of each other, almost like Highlander, and are in a friendly
competition, very much unlike Highlander.</p>
<p>SVC now has a single uninterrupted streak, spanning multiple years, of daily
running behind him. He has friends in his city who have also been streaking for
multiple years now.</p>
<p>I find this fantastic, both specifically as a running and fitness feat, and
more generally as a brilliant human optimisation trick.</p>
<p>The longer your streak, the harder it&rsquo;s going to become to break that
streak. Add in the friendly competition element, and you have become an
accomplishment machine.</p>
<p>I see great potential here in the context of
<a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">compounding</a>
more consistently, and for longer.</p>
<p>What else could we streak folks?</p>
<h2 id="the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">The Great Social Media Fast of 2019.</h2>
<p>Twitter, Facebook, Reddit and friends&hellip; hot durnit.</p>
<p>Because I recently re-acquired the habit of checking reddit and twitter
multiple times during the day, I again examined the mechanisms driving this
undesirable behaviour.</p>
<p>The insidiousness, at least for me, lies in the fact that TwiFRaF (twitter,
facebook, reddit and friends) always has something looking like new information
on tap, where with tap, I mean firehose.</p>
<p>At any given moment during the day, when brain desires new input, or is just
tired and would like to take a break, TwiFRaF firehoses are ready to spew
something that appears to be new information but is only a very convincing
analogue.</p>
<p>Brain thinks it&rsquo;s getting what it wanted, plus a tiny and uninspired spurt of
discovery-dopamine here and there, which helps to keep up the illusion.</p>
<p>Any chance of real curiousity taking its natural course is cancelled.</p>
<p>Instead of pondering a question, and then going out on a slow and deliberate
search for information and later enlightenment, the firehose is opened, because
it&rsquo;s easier.</p>
<p>Furthermore, brain is unnecessarily exhausted trawling through a mix of mostly
generic rubbish with, granted, an interesting nugget every blue moon.</p>
<p>Hot durnit.</p>
<p>Fortunately, I like experiments, and Cold Turkey is my middle name!</p>
<p>So, on Saturday I decided to cut out TwiFRaF completely.</p>
<p>Initially I thought it would be an experiment until the end of September, but
now I&rsquo;m thinking that streaking might be an even better option.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;ll see.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #173: I know.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</guid><description> Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm still quite bad. Let&amp;rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:
Well hello there folks!
A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not have much to report on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="helderberg_protea.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By
the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm
still quite bad.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:</p>
<p>Well hello there folks!</p>
<p>A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not
have much to report on.</p>
<p>However, it&rsquo;s funny how these things go. One week nothing&hellip; Then it&rsquo;s just a
single week later and there&rsquo;s almost a bit too much that I would like to talk
about.</p>
<p>It seems to have been a mix of more writing, but also just more doing.</p>
<p>So, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 1 to Sunday July 14, 2019, I
would like to present the following notes.</p>
<h2 id="bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Bullet List of Miscellany (BLoM).</h2>
<ul>
<li>GOU#1, age 13, is on a week-long school trip in a different time zone
(GMT+8). I am super happy that she can have this experience, but durnit, one
misses one&rsquo;s genetic offspring units dearly!</li>
<li>Remember that I told you about our <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">solar inverter not talking to the
battery&rsquo;s BMS</a>?
Well, one small recommended firmware upgrade later, from 151507 to 151508,
and the whole system is completely down. Please cross your fingers, because
we&rsquo;ve tried <strong>everything</strong> else.</li>
<li>I regularly get accosted by off-leash dogs whilst running. There are
incredibly clear by-laws down here which absolutely forbid any dog ever being
off-leash in any public space which is not a designated off-leash zone. I
recently made the mistake (twice) of trying to explain this to the relevant
dog-owners. Well, dog-owners seem to be quite sadly under-endowed in the area
of introspective capability, but at least I&rsquo;m getting a lot better at
unprepared debates in public spaces. (Psychologists in the audience, help me
out here with any tips please!)</li>
<li>I really enjoyed <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/162-medical-intelligence/">this Sam Harris podcast with Eric
Topol</a>. <a href="https://www.scripps.edu/faculty/topol/">Eric
Topol</a> is a cardiologist and the
founder and director of the Scripps Research Translational Institute in the
US. Apart from the main topic of the discussion, namely Topol&rsquo;s
well-developed and articulated view of AI in medicine (well, his books on
this topic are quite influential, so there&rsquo;s that), I was struck and inspired
by the humble gentleness of this impressive intellect. Furthermore, although
we are not supposed to use twitter anymore (in some circles, it has been
dubbed &ldquo;road rage of the internet&rdquo;), <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Prof Topol&rsquo;s tweet
stream</a> is a shining example of how twitter
could be used more constructively.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email">Would you like some more Emacs with that Email?</h2>
<p>During the past two weeks I published two blog posts on my nerd blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/03/send-queued-mails-in-background-with-mu4e/">Sending queued mails in the background with
mu4e.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/05/mbsync-vs-offlineimap-speed/">Is mbsync really faster than offlineimap? A
measurement.</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Based on these, you might come to the conclusion that I&rsquo;m processing email
inside of Emacs
<a href="/2014/05/24/weekly-head-voices-71-vote-for-the-future/">again</a>.</p>
<p>I can confirm that this is indeed the case.</p>
<p>Probably for a large part due to the popularity of google&rsquo;s gmail, the growth
of the rest of the email ecosystem seems to have been stunted to a significant
degree.</p>
<p>In this specific case, I am referring to the dearth of really good email
clients for Windows.</p>
<p>(By the way, Thunderbird, still my fallback, usually makes the top of any
Windows email client lists. However, if it weren&rsquo;t for GMail, Thunderbird
would probably also be miles better than it is today.)</p>
<p>After losing more hours than I could afford trying to find that perfect email
client (I would have settled for &ldquo;still has all of its own teeth&rdquo;), I realised
that I would just have to buckle down and get <a href="/tags/mu4e/">mu4e</a>, my favourite
Emacs email client, working well enough on Windows, which I currently <em>prefer</em>
(DID I JUST SAY THAT?!) due to my <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1E
baby</a>.</p>
<p>That was of course a whole different wormhole to get sucked into.</p>
<p>Well, more of those precious hours later, I have a Frankensteined concoction
consisting of Emacs running on the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL),
displaying to the Windows desktop via <a href="https://token2shell.com/x410/">X410</a>,
and opening email and orgmode attachments, and dired files, using the native
Windows handlers via an
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Xdg-utils#xdg-open">xdg-open</a> work-alike
I coded up in Python.</p>
<p>(I am planning to release my xdg-open clone along with a more detailed howto
blog post. Let me know if you would like advanced access.)</p>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. after all of that effort I am now back more or less to where I
started in 2014.</p>
<p>(To be honest, Emacs is near the top of my list of compounding activities. The
fact that it&rsquo;s back in my email workflow, combined with five years of
compounded Emacs skills, has resulted in further increased efficiency.)</p>
<h3 id="sticking-it-to-the-man-gmail-with-fastmail">Sticking it to the Man (GMail) with FastMail.</h3>
<p>Wrapping up that email workflow reconfiguration frenzy, I did spend some
minutes doing a quick survey of fastmail alternatives which might have email
servers somewhat closer to the Southern tip of Africa and hence shave off a few
seconds of latency.</p>
<p>I found nothing that came close in terms of features and price. Except for one
outage, <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">I&rsquo;ve been a really happy fastmail camper for the last three
years</a>.</p>
<p>All of that, together with the fact that gmail&rsquo;s continued dominance is
unhealthy for the world of email, convinced me to stick with fastmail for the
conceivable future.</p>
<h2 id="stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">Stone Three Healthcare is now a thing.</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.stonethree.com/healthcare/">Stone Three Healthcare</a>, until recently
a business unit within Stone Three Venture Technology, has now been officially
spun out.</p>
<p>In other words, S3HC is now a more-or-less independent company that will
henceforth have to create its own success.</p>
<p>As some of you know, this project has been cooking for a few years now.</p>
<p>We have a really great team, products with customers and a market, and a
respectable patch of runway.</p>
<p>There are worse ways for a startup to start up.</p>
<p>P.S. if you have any golden tips for startup dummies, I (and probably others)
would be super grateful if you could let &rsquo;em loose in the comments!</p>
<h2 id="always-be-compounding-the-side-project-edition">Always Be Compounding: The side-project edition.</h2>
<p>In the previous WHV, I <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">started going on about the principle of ABC, or Always Be
Compounding</a>.</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been spending a great deal of mental cycles on finding more
ways to ABC.</p>
<p>Besides the more general examples I mentioned there, another method is to
design some long-running project that can function as a container for all of
the work that you&rsquo;ll have to do in any case.</p>
<p>A perhaps slightly flawed personal example is DeVIDE, an open source
visualization and image processing tool that started life somewhere in 2001,
<a href="/2003/12/19/the-visualisation-and-image-processing-platform-formerly-known-as-dscas3/">was renamed to DeVIDE at the end of
2003</a>,
open-sourced in 2007 and had its last release in 2012.</p>
<p>Although it did see some use after that, the project went into hibernation
(weeeelll&hellip;.) when I left academia.</p>
<p>My point is that, for about 10 years, I had a single technical <em>artifact</em> with
a name that became slowly better known (even if it was often by its alias &ldquo;Not
Responding&rdquo;), into which I could integrate all the other new work I was doing.</p>
<p>This enabled me to enjoy some of the advantages of compounding effort, in the
shape of DeVIDE, even although the work I was doing over the years necessarily
had to change.</p>
<p>(A really nice additional benefit was that some students sometimes found the
software useful! I do wish that that part could have continued for a little
longer.)</p>
<p>Setting aside my
<a href="/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/#a-strange-thing-happened-this-weekend">DeVIDE-nostalgia</a>
(and a bit of sadness) for a moment, I would like to apply some of this
learning to my current (and perhaps your) situation.</p>
<p>My idea would be to define a new side-project that can act as the slightly
longer-lived container for some of the smaller side-projects and learnings I
sometimes manage to spend time on.</p>
<p>It would have to be a technology / thematic fit for many of my other
side-projects. It would of course constitute a double-whammy if this
side-project had commercial potential.</p>
<p>Well, SURPRISE!</p>
<p>I do have at least one side-project that ticks a number of these boxes, and
could <em>potentially</em> serve as such a vehicle.</p>
<h3 id="aikno">AIKNO</h3>
<p>The side-project in question is called AIKNO, which is pronounced &ldquo;I know&rdquo;, but
which somehow expands to <em>AI organizational knowledge base</em>. Magic!</p>
<p>It eats all of your organization&rsquo;s emails for breakfast, and then uses
different methods, both algorithmic and crowd/team-sourced, to sort and
organize those emails and all of their attachments, and then makes those easily
and attractively (hey, data visualization!) accessible by that organization.</p>
<p>Think of it as an almost zero-effort always-up-to-date organizational knowledge
base.</p>
<p>Besides having slots for various machine learning and visualization techniques,
it fits nicely into my overgrown knowledge management hobby.</p>
<p>The first commit in the AIKNO repo was in November of 2017. Oof. The prototype
is able to import emails and attachments into its structured database, and
already does funky stuff with similarity searches and whatnot.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, it has also suffered from my regular technology stack
changes, and it&rsquo;s currently languishing while I write blog posts.</p>
<p>My previous failed side-project was called <em>TableTops</em>, or <em>Paradigm Desktop</em> by
the same people who dubbed DeVIDE &ldquo;Not Responding&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It was a free-form canvas / whiteboard tool for the free-form storage and
linking of <em>anything</em>. For example, it had relational data structures for
linking specific coordinates or regions in photos to centralised concepts, and
other interesting things that will probably never see the light of day.</p>
<p>It went through seven tech-stack-change-induced rewrites before being obsoleted
by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">my growing Emacs Orgmode powers</a>. (first
commit October 2013, last commit August 2017, now on the backest back
burner. the one that&rsquo;s not burning.)</p>
<p>I did learn a <em>tremendous</em> amount.</p>
<p>Maybe <em>that</em> is the real reason for doing these things?</p>
<h2 id="always-be-learning">Always Be Learning.</h2>
<p>Thanks for joining me on that trip folks.</p>
<p>I hope to see you soon. Until then, make an amazing time!</p>
<figure>
<a href="coffee_company_belgian_brownie.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
100% amazing Belgian brownie and delectable flat white at the
Coffee Company on Lourensford this past weekend.
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>