<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>conference on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/conference/</link><description>Recent content in conference on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 13:10:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #206: Mount Ceder</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 13:10:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/</guid><description> Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder.
Welcome, dear readers, to the 206th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the two weeks from Monday September 21 to Sunday October 4, 2020.
Mount Ceder beauty The weather prediction for the September 25 long weekend did not look good at all.
Temperatures in the low single digits, and rain.
We were unable to reschedule our reservation, and so, with significant trepidation, we packed our things for the weekend and made the drive to Mount Ceder.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="mount_ceder_4873_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome, dear readers, to the 206th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering
the two weeks from Monday September 21 to Sunday October 4, 2020.</p>
<h2 id="mount-ceder-beauty">Mount Ceder beauty</h2>
<p>The weather prediction for the September 25 long weekend did not look good at
all.</p>
<p>Temperatures in the low single digits, and rain.</p>
<p>We were unable to reschedule our reservation, and so, with significant
trepidation, we packed our things for the weekend and made the drive to Mount
Ceder.</p>
<p>As we entered the valley right before arriving at our destination, the rugged
and wonderful beauty of the surroundings quickly started dispelling our puny
expectations.</p>
<p>The weather did turn out almost exactly as was predicted, but our time there
ended up being the brilliant opposite of what we had feared.</p>
<p>In between spells of rain, there was plenty of fresh sunshine outside, with a
super effective little closed combustion fireplace inside the house to keep it
toasty.</p>








<figure><a href="mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a hike up the mountain with the whole fam-jam."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: View from a hike up the mountain with the whole fam-jam.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The outside jacuzzi which we discovered late on the Saturday afternoon might
also have played a role in the amount of fun that was had.</p>
<p>It does also need to be said that the fact that there&rsquo;s no telephone reception
is a massive perk for us visitors.</p>
<p>The older I get, the more I enjoy disconnecting.</p>
<h2 id="vcbm-2020-virtually">VCBM 2020, virtually</h2>
<p>Thanks to the modern miracle that is virtual conferences, I was able to attend
a large part of the <a href="https://www.gcpr-vmv-vcbm-2020.uni-tuebingen.de/">Visual Computing in Biology and Medicine (VCBM) 2020
conference</a>.</p>
<p>Although I am super interested in the themes and people of this conference, it
is <em>usually</em> not possible for me to fly around the globe to take part in this
or any other relevant academic gathering.</p>
<p>However, the current pandemic has brought with it a whole host of changes, not
least of which is the concept of being able to participate, as a first class
citizen, in an international conference.</p>
<p>It was really great, although slightly nostalgic, connecting with friends and
colleagues from years ago.</p>
<p>Just being able to join in on the post-talk question sessions, and in the
surreal social rooms on discord where you find yourself in a grid of talking
heads, was super enjoyable.</p>
<p>(It has to be noted here that the technical aspects of VCBM 2020 were also
top-class. Everything, from the interactive block-based conference programme
with downloadable papers, to the youtube streams for each session, to the
discord channels for real-time discussion and the discord channels for social
video conferencing, was simply top notch!)</p>
<h3 id="multi-tasking-virtual-meetings-quo-vadis">Multi-tasking virtual meetings: Quo vadis?</h3>
<p>What was also interesting to hear, was a possibly less positive aspect of
virtual conferencing, specifically that academic peeps were now in the
situation where they often had to multi-task whilst taking part in the
conference.</p>
<p>In the old days, pre-COVID, it could definitely happen that folks had to take
care of a few emails or perhaps even a video meeting, but the majority of the
day would be spent conferencing.</p>
<p>That is, people from potentially right around the globe would be chatting
face-to-face about anything and everything, an activity which is truly
important for collaboration, and friendship.</p>
<p>Now it seems that this ratio has changed, where most of the time folks are
expected to be available online for additional tasks and interactions, while
conferencing in parallel.</p>
<p>In my day job I&rsquo;ve noticed a similar phenomenon, where one can often notice
that people taking part in a meeting are only partially present.</p>
<p>Whilst this is perhaps a good thing for a number of meetings that are by their
nature not that efficient, I think that it&rsquo;s a dangerous habit to
cultivate.</p>
<p>Imagine that by default, every meeting means your poor cognition trying to keep
up with multiple streams of information at the same time. Looking at it from a
different perspective, now you have even less confidence that your
collaborators are paying attention to what is being discussed.</p>
<p>This might be yet another reason to <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">favour asynchronous offline communication</a>,
that is, writing long-form messages on message boards, with synchronous
face-time being reserved more and more for purely social reasons.</p>
<h2 id="on-thursday-october-1-too-much-distraction-was-too-much">On Thursday October 1, too much distraction was too much</h2>
<p>Seguing right on from the synchronous communication point above, On October 1 I
unfortunately needed to be jacked-in to Teams, WhatsApp <em>and</em> Discord for the
whole day, for various good reasons.</p>
<p>It was only around 16:20 that I was able to snap out of all of this and jack
out again, with <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a> helping to bring a bit of welcome rest and,
surprise(!), focus.</p>
<p>Before that, anxiety about possibly missing something kept me from plugging out
for even short bursts to be able to do work.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s funny how the expectations, real or perhaps more often just perceived, of
one&rsquo;s surroundings make it extremely difficult to disconnect, which leads to
more time lost to these various forms of distraction, which leads to further
anxiety, which further complicates just taking those few steps back and pulling
the plug.</p>
<p>I wish I had a trick to manage all of this better.</p>
<h2 id="that-time-i-nuked-all-of-my-computers-with-a-partition-resize-and-move-that-should-have-taken-no-more-than-5-minutes">That time I nuked all of my computers with a partition resize and move that should have taken no more than 5 minutes</h2>
<p><em>Massive nerd warning: If you don&rsquo;t want to know about filesystems, feel free</em>
<em>to skip this section. Before you do however, take this advice from me: Avoid</em>
<em>AOMEI.</em></p>
<p>My goal was simple: Move the newly appeared recovery partition (in addition to
the one at the start of the disk) to its end, so that I can grow my main system
partition to fill the available space on the drive.</p>
<p>Some years ago I had used EaseUs for something similar, but they wanted payment
for this task, and current reviews were pointing quite convincingly in the
direction of AOMEI.</p>
<p>Narrator: <em>The reviews were all tragically wrong.</em></p>
<p>My specific use case is even documented exactly on the AOMEI website, see <a href="https://www.diskpart.com/windows-10/windows-10-move-recovery-partition-4348.html">this
page</a>.</p>
<p>I followed those steps exactly.</p>
<p>My computer rebooted twice in order to perform the two actions:</p>
<ol>
<li>move recovery partition, and</li>
<li>resize system partition&hellip;</li>
</ol>
<p>&hellip; to conclude finally by leaving my laptop in a 100% unusable state.</p>
<p>No boot, no nothing.</p>
<p>I tried various combinations of booting into safe mode, which worked at first
but showed me the full drive&rsquo;s space available, meaning that the filesystem had
probably been damaged.</p>
<p>Hard.</p>
<p>I later booted with Windows installation media, from where I launched various
rescue attempts, including the stalwart <code>bootrec /rebuildbcd</code> and all of its
friends.</p>
<p>Nothing.</p>
<p>AOMEI had done a pretty great job in completely destroying my partition table
and filesystem.</p>
<p>Narrator: <em>He got what he paid for!</em></p>
<p>I ended up installing Windows 10 twice, the second time with the
soon-to-be-released 20H2 install media, because installing the old 1909 and
then upgrading was taking far too long.</p>
<p>The whole exercise, or should I say &ldquo;lesson&rdquo;, cost me about a day.</p>
<p>Stoic narrator: <em>Fortunately, the situation afterwards was better than it was before.</em></p>
<ul>
<li>My main WSL2 ubuntu 20.04 image, where most of my development work happens,
remained untouched on the second SSD and was up and running pretty quickly
after the Windows re-install.</li>
<li>My backups demonstrably work, although Windows File History is truly klunky
compared to Apple&rsquo;s Time Machine.</li>
<li>In the chaos of trying to get my work environment back up and running, I also
had to upgrade my deep learning Linux desktop machine to Ubuntu 20.04. (It
started as a Murphy&rsquo;s law situation, where both my laptop <em>and</em> the desktop
were unusable, the latter due to a stupid Ubuntu bug manifesting as a
non-working keyboard)</li>
<li>A fresh install of Windows feels really fresh.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">My mind is a slippery eel</h2>
<p>Recently I had to work on a chunk of software system design.</p>
<p>It starts with nothing laid down, just a general idea of what this pretty
significant feature should be able to do.</p>
<p>Pulling yourself up by your bootstraps, you have to start laying down the
bottom-most levels of the design that will eventually be able to make those
high-level desired features a reality.</p>
<p>This whole growing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rube%5FGoldberg%5Fmachine">Rube Goldberg machine</a> has to stay in your mind for a large
part of the day, as you&rsquo;re mentally twisting, turning and replacing bits here
and there.</p>
<p>Most of these days, getting my brain to stay focused felt a lot like trying to
hold on to a really slippery eel, and, if that wasn&rsquo;t tricky enough, trying to
aim the sporadically working laser, badly mounted on its slippery head, to try
and carve something recognisable from a block of slowly melting ice.</p>
<p>By the end of most days, it would mostly not feel like it had been very
productive.</p>
<p>I tried to make peace with the fact that some sorts of work, coupled with all
of the usual emotional interactions, would often result in this sort of
feeling.</p>
<p>In that moment, this did also help me to get back into the habit of daily
meditation practice. Fortunately there&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.wakingup.com/">the Waking Up app by Sam Harris</a> which
is perfect for this. Using this, I am usually able to squeeze in a 10 minute
practice before work starts, which subjectively seems to bring a little more
equanimity into each day.</p>
<p>Looking back at this experience now, it also seems like a strong vote for
paying more attention to the daily &ldquo;done&rdquo; list.</p>
<p>Although I mostly remember to journal every day, I often forget to look at it
also from the perspective of compactly listing the little tasks that have been
completed.</p>
<p>This could be tricky when working on an amorphous project like &ldquo;design this
vague thing&rdquo;, but I think that it&rsquo;s more about the ritual of formulating and
then reviewing a small but plausible thing that is now apparently done.</p>
<p>This seems to fool the anxious parts of one&rsquo;s brain into a semblance of
temporary calm, enabling some of the other parts to get back to work.</p>
<p>This too I shall file this under <a href="/tags/101-mind-tricks">&ldquo;101 stupid but effective tricks to fool your
mind into being more useful&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. I just discovered that some part of <a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/#do-you-write-stuff-down">January-2019-Charl already did</a>.</p>
<p>P.P.S. &ldquo;Fool your mind&rdquo;, although it sounds much less awesome than &ldquo;free your
mind&rdquo;, seems to be a recurring aspect of effectively operating the human
machine.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>EuroVis 2011</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/26/eurovis-2011/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2011 11:25:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/26/eurovis-2011/</guid><description> I’ve written before about EuroVis, the most important European scientific conference on visualisation. In 2009, it took place in Berlin, in 2010 it was in Bordeaux, and, an a surprise non-twist of alliteration, the 2011 edition was held in Bergen, Norway. With 216 attendees and a practically perfect organization, this year’s edition has been described as the biggest and the best EuroVis ever. In a bid to save some time (I still owe you a mega-edition of the Weekly (actually Monthly) Head Voices), I’m going to give my biased account in bullet-list form:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve written before about EuroVis, the most important European scientific conference on visualisation. In <a href="/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/" title="blog post on eurovis 2009">2009, it took place in Berlin</a>, in <a href="/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/" title="blog coverage of eurovis 2010">2010 it was in Bordeaux</a>, and, an a surprise non-twist of alliteration, the <strong>2011 edition was held in Bergen, Norway.</strong> With 216 attendees and a practically perfect organization, this year’s edition has been described as the biggest and the best EuroVis ever. In a bid to save some time (I still owe you a mega-edition of the Weekly (actually Monthly) Head Voices), I’m going to give my biased account in bullet-list form:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>On Tuesday evening, we were welcomed by the very charismatic vice mayor of Bergen in the Tårnsalen of the Lysverket building of the Bergen Art Museum. It seems the photo I took of the inside of the art deco tower, built in 1938, is quite a popular shot. The food was divine, thank you very much.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/tarnsalen.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/tarnsalen-1024x612.jpg"
        
            alt="Art Deco tower from the inside in the Tårnsalen, Lysverket."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Art Deco tower from the inside in the Tårnsalen, Lysverket.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The next morning, during the conference opening, the following Bergen (rainiest city in Europe) joke was told: <em>A visitor asks a local boy in exasperation “Does it rain like this all the time?” and the little boy answers “I don’t know, I’m only 12 years old!”</em>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/speakers.php#mcCloud" title="conference keynote page">conference keynote</a> was given by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_McCloud" title="Wikipedia page on Scott McCloud">Scott McCloud</a>, American cartoonist and comic theorist, on aspects of visual communication. This was most probably the best presentation I’ve ever had the privilege of experiencing. Besides brilliant oratorship, his slides are somehow more a visual stream of consciousness affair than discrete quanta of information. When I grow up, I’m going to present like that.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As per usual, I get to award the <strong>Weekly Head Voices Best Paper awards</strong>, and they go to the following papers:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.mevis-research.de/~crieder/pdf/EuroVis2011_paper175.pdf" title="fulltext of Rieder 2011 eurovis paper">A Shader Framework for Rapid Prototyping of GPU-Based Volume Rendering</a> by Christian Rieder, Stephan Palmer, Florian Link and Horst K. Hahn. Rieder and his colleagues have constructed a full GPU-based volume rendering pipeline in MeVisLab of which the various shader based components are modifiable at runtime. This means that you can prototype your GPU-based volume rendering ideas in no time flat!</li>
<li><a href="http://www.ii.uib.no/vis/publications/publication/2011/lampe11curveDensity" title="curve density estimates website">Curve Density Estimates</a> by Ove Daae Lampe and Helwig Hauser. Back to basics and really important work on the effective visualisation of complex curves at any resolution, with smooth scaling between levels.</li>
<li><a href="http://vgl.serc.iisc.ernet.in/pdf/pub/MultifieldComparisonMeasureEUROVIS2011.pdf" title="fulltext gradient-based comparison metric paper">A Gradient-Based Comparison Measure for Visual Analysis of Multifield Data</a> by Suthambhara Nagaraj, Vijay Natarajan and Ravi S. Nanjundiah. Another back-to-basics paper in which the authors show how to find the agreement between hundreds of scalar fields and visualise this agreement, thus enabling comparison.</li>
</ul>
<p>The slightly less prestigious EuroVis 2011 Best Paper awards went to:</p>
<ol>
<li>Uncertainty-Aware Exploration of Continuous Parameter Spaces Using Multivariate Prediction  by Wolfgang Berger, Harald Piringer, Peter Filzmoser, Eduard Gröller. I was unfortunately in the other session, but was told by numerous colleagues that this was indeed an award-winning presentation as well.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.sci.utah.edu/publications/anderson11/Anderson_eurovis2011.pdf" title="fulltext of Anderson's paper">A User Study of Visualization Effectiveness Using EEG and Cognitive Load</a> by Erik Anderson, Kristin Potter, Laura Matzen, Jason Shepherd, Gilbert Preston, Claudio Silva. This was presented in the Evaluation session which I had the privilege of chairing. It is indeed a very compelling idea to measure the effectiveness of a visualisation through cognitive load and this paper documents the first very important steps in this direction.</li>
<li>A Gradient-Based Comparison Measure for Visual Analysis of Multifield Data by Suthambhara Nagaraj, Vijay Natarajan and Ravi S. Nanjundiah. This was also amongst the more prestigious WHV best paper award winners, see above!</li>
</ol>
<p>The rest of the conference featured the following bullets:</p>
<ul>
<li>During the social event on Thursday evening, Frits Post (my boss), was elevated to the rank of Eurographics Honorary Fellow, recognizing his service to and standing in the visualisation community. Including this newest addition, there are only <a href="http://www.eg.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=90&amp;Itemid=52" title="list of EG honorary fellows">five (5!) EG Honorary Fellows</a> in the world today. I am very proud!</li>
<li>During the first session of the morning after the social event, I had the exquisite privilege of presenting the work of my Brazilian colleagues: <a href="http://www.lcad.icmc.usp.br/~nonato/pubs/plp.pdf" title="fulltext PLP paper">Piecewise Laplacian-based Projection for Interactive Data Exploration and Organization</a> by Fernando V. Paulovich, Danilo M. Eler, Jorge Poco, Charl P. Botha, Rosane Minghim, Luis G. Nonato. I really do like presenting at events like these, and it’s been a while. Do read and cite the paper, it documents a practical way of reducing any set of high-dimensional data points to the visual space, and enabling interaction with those points on the visual space!</li>
<li>The <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/speakers.php#groller" title="capstone page">capstone of the conference</a> was presented by the legendary Prof. E. Gröller, also known by the whole community as <em>Meister</em>. In typical style, the title of his talk was only announced during the talk itself. The title was <em>The Haunted Swamps of Heuristics</em>. In this philosophical and visionary contribution, it was argued that algorithms and parameters are too deeply intertwined to focus only on the former, but that it was more important to study, in detail, the exact behaviour of the latter. More broadly speaking, we need to accept the fact that there is a great deal of uncertainty also in the parameter spaces of our algorithms, but that this uncertainty can and should be dealt with correctly.</li>
</ul>
<p>That thought-provoking capstone and this blog post will share the same concluding quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Doubt is not a pleasant condition, but certainty is absurd. — Voltaire / Gröller</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I hope to see you in the comments below! You could also opt to click on my shiny new +1 button, or my slightly older but no less shiny retweet or facebook share buttons.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Schloss Dagstuhl: Computer Scientist Heaven</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/19/schloss-dagstuhl-computer-scientist-heaven/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2011 19:56:43 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/06/19/schloss-dagstuhl-computer-scientist-heaven/</guid><description> Somewhere in a remote but picturesque location in southern Germany, there’s a special castle called Schloss Dagstuhl. Every week, the castle fills up with a smallish group of Exceptionally Privileged Computer Scientists, who can only go there Because They Have Been Invited. Every week hosts a different field; In my case this was the Scientific Visualization seminar, one of the oldest participating groups. Everything has been setup just so to guarantee a perfect computer sciencey week for all guests.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Somewhere in a remote but picturesque location in southern Germany, there’s a special castle called Schloss Dagstuhl. Every week, the castle fills up with a smallish group of Exceptionally Privileged Computer Scientists, who can only go there Because They Have Been Invited. Every week hosts a different field; In my case this was the Scientific Visualization seminar, one of the oldest participating groups. Everything has been setup <em>just so</em> to guarantee a perfect computer sciencey week for all guests. Because I’ve already been boring too many people with this story in person, I thought it prudent to write it up. Let’s hope it’s not a first (and second!) rule of Fight Club situation, in which case posting frequency over here might drop <em>quite</em> drastically.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Dagstuhl_DSC02285.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/Dagstuhl_DSC02285-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Schloss Dagstuhl, picture courtesy of Wikipedia."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Schloss Dagstuhl, picture courtesy of Wikipedia.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>To begin with, the meals are exquisite, three times a day, every day. As we all know, the path to a computer scientist’s heart is through buying them new gadgets, but feeding them well is a great backup plan. Another very nice touch is the fact that seating is deliberately randomised, meaning that your introvert self is forced to sit at the table with a different group of guests during each lunch and dinner, in turn meaning that even if you try otherwise, you will probably get to have a good conversation with every one of the fifty attendees.</p>
<p>In the case of our seminar, the working day consists of presentations in blocks of three or four, followed by a longer block of discussion on all the preceding presentations, panel style. Attendees were all asked not just to give a standard scientific presentation, but to discuss open problems and future challenges in their respective sub-fields. I (and many others, judging by the aggregated post-meeting feedback) really enjoyed this format. The presentations made one think, and the discussion blocks were long enough to really get into the details. You can check out abstracts and slides on <a href="http://www.dagstuhl.de/mat/index.en.phtml?11231" title="site with Dagstuhl SciVis 2011 materials">the seminar website</a>.</p>
<p>After a full day of quite intensive discussion, there were breakout sessions during which four subgroups started working on the various chapters of a new Springer book that should appear sometime early in next year. The book will deal with multi-field, uncertainty, biomedical and scalable visualization, and it has the makings of being a keeper.</p>
<p>The other extremely important magic bit about this castle is the abundance of real coffee machines (ones that grind coffee beans for every cup), snack corners and, uhm, beer fridges. You can’t really go anywhere, as you’re in the middle of nowhere, so after dinner the conversations tend to continue till late in the night, conversant stamina enhanced by said coffee and beer facilities. Evil science plans were made, good old-fashioned deep conversations were had and the early next morning consequences were flatly ignored. I haven’t laughed quite so much in a long time, but <em>that</em> part of the programme prefers, and has the right, to remain completely silent.</p>
<p>If you ever get <em>the</em> invitation, don’t hesitate for a second to accept: You shall return an exhausted but terribly happy computer nerd.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Future is Sick [Weekly Head Voices #36]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/23/the-future-is-sick-weekly-head-voices-36/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2011 21:12:30 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/23/the-future-is-sick-weekly-head-voices-36/</guid><description> Post summary: Conference, VXLabs, SIP, boots, backyard philosophy on you the consumer, dramatic reading. Read on for more!
Just before the weekend I spent two days at the Dutch Bio-Medical Engineering Conference in Egmond aan Zee, in a ginormous seaside hotel. Probably because I attempted to keep up with the young ones during their nightly escapades, I’m currently dealing quite badly with a serious cold, which is why this is the first sick blog post of 2011.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Conference, VXLabs, SIP, boots, backyard philosophy on you the consumer, dramatic reading. Read on for more!</em></p>
<p>Just before the weekend I spent two days at the Dutch Bio-Medical Engineering Conference in Egmond aan Zee, in a ginormous seaside hotel. Probably because I attempted to keep up with the young ones during their nightly escapades, I’m currently dealing quite badly with a serious cold, which is why this is the first sick blog post of 2011.  Besides all those germs, I also brought you this photo of said seaside right after sunset:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/egmond_aan_zee_bme2011.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/egmond_aan_zee_bme2011.jpg"
        
            alt="Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The conference was an energetic and motivating affair, at which yours truly even got to chair a session, during which I tried, in spite of not getting to bed all that early the night before, to Keep Things Extremely Punctual As Well As Mildly Entertaining. I succeeded in the former, you’ll have to ask the audience about the latter.</p>
<p>The absolute highlight, for me at least, was the capstone on Friday by <a href="https://depts.washington.edu/biointel/" title="Prof. Satava's website">Professor Richard Satava</a>, a surgeon with an amazing vision of the future. Bordering on science fiction but for a large part backed by his own and other groups’ research, his superbly delivered presentation touched on surgical operating rooms completely staffed by robots (some elements remotely controlled by a surgeon), cell engineering, surgery robots that heal troops at the scene of the crime (hehe), genetic engineering, cloning and a healthy dash of trans-humanism. By the end the whole room was collectively straining at the leash to go and genetically upgrade anything and anyone they could find. With a room full of BME researchers, that’s more dangerous than it sounds. :)</p>
<p>Other note-worthy items of the past two weeks can be summarised in the following neat bullet list:</p>
<ul>
<li>I’ve started a new blog, called VXLabs, for matters that are too nerdy even for this blog. If you’re interested, you can start by reading the <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/01/22/htc-desire-z-an-in-depth-and-nerdy-review/" title="in-depth and nerdy review of the HTC Desire Z at VXLabs">HTC Desire Z (my lovely new smartphone) review</a> I’ve recently gotten around to writing. If you’re nerdy enough, you might consider subscribing VXLabs as well!</li>
<li>There are far cheaper ways than Skype to call telephones around the world. With SIP software, such as SIPDroid on Android, you can use cheap SIP servers that even offer free calls to many destinations. See <a href="http://www.backsla.sh/betamax" title="table of betamax providers">this page</a> for a list of just the betamax (German VOIP company) providers and the free countries that they support.</li>
<li>I was approached by a company producing Ugg-like boots to review their boots, get a free pair in the process, and get a good deal for my readers. This is probably because I went on about those BEAUTIFUL Timberland boots in one of my previous posts. Although I was flattered that the gentleman in question thought my widely-read (haha) opinion would be good for his brand and he called this a <em>fashion blog</em> (!!), I declined, stating that my readership probably is more into Timberlands than Uggs. That’s true, readership? Right?!</li>
<li><strong>Micro Backyard Philosophy</strong>: After one of those late nights refreshing my Twitter, Facebook, Google Reader and GMail for the Nth time, I got to thinking about how the internet sometimes turns us into 100% consumers, leaving <strong>no room for creativity</strong>. It’s insidious, because we believe that the internet will give us exactly what we crave if we just know how to search for it, and that it should do so with that next press on the refresh button, when in fact this is hardly ever the case, especially when that which you crave is in fact to create. Remember this the next time it’s getting late and you think Just One More Refresh. Don’t push that button. <strong>Sit back and think about what you really want to do</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it boys and girls, thank you very much for reading this far! You go and have yourselves a fabulous and especially creative week. If you get lonely waiting for the next edition of the Weekly Head Voices, marvel at this dramatic reading of a bad user game review, creativity at its finest:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Z2Z23SAFVA?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>VCBM 2010 [Weekly Head Voices #26]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/07/08/vcbm-2010-weekly-head-voices-26/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2010 09:58:51 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/07/08/vcbm-2010-weekly-head-voices-26/</guid><description> (This post is a slightly longer than average report detailing our trip to the EG VCBM 2010 conference. It’s of course super-entertaining, but if you still do wish to skim through it, I’ve bolded the per-paragraph themes. If you’re not sure what these danged conferences are about, see my recent EuroVis 2010 post for a general introduction.)
Last week, I accompanied Peter Schaafsma (he of the orbital fat mobility paper), Bastijn Vissers and André van Dixhoorn (they of the resting state fMRI brain connectivity paper) to Leipzig, where they had been selected to present their work at the second Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine (VCBM).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This post is a slightly longer than average report detailing our trip to the EG VCBM 2010 conference. It’s of course super-entertaining, but if you still do wish to skim through it, I’ve bolded the per-paragraph themes. If you’re not sure what these danged conferences are about, see my <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/" title="my EuroVis 2010, with general introduction to scientific conferences">recent EuroVis 2010 post</a></em> <em>for a general introduction.)</em></p>
<p>Last week, I accompanied Peter Schaafsma (he of the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Schaafsma2010" title="orbital fat mobility paper">orbital fat mobility paper</a>), <a href="http://www.bastijn.nl/" title="Bastijn Visser's website">Bastijn Vissers</a> and André van Dixhoorn (they of the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Dixhoorn2010" title="rs-fMRI connectivity paper">resting state fMRI brain connectivity paper</a>) to Leipzig, where they had been selected to present their work at the <a href="http://vcbm.org/2010/" title="VCBM 2010 website">second Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine (VCBM)</a>.








<figure><a href="http://vcbm.org/2010/">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/newlogo-270x150.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty VCBM logo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty VCBM logo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Things got off to a great start when, as we were travelling there by speeding bullet (okay, it was just a brand-new rental Opel, but the Autobahn turns any car into a Speeding Bullet!), we managed to <strong>strike, at high speed, a high-quality German plastic bucket that had suddenly appeared right in the middle of the road</strong>. After a few more kilometres of noticing that our speeding bullet was not able to pass the very slowly accelerating bullet stage and was making strange disconcerting noises to boot (excuse the automotive pun), we stopped to investigate, noticing to our shock that the bucket, having been very badly burnt, <a href="http://www.moviedeaths.com/austin_powers:_international_man_of_mystery/mustafa/" title="Mustafa?">Mustafa-style</a>, was still lodged under the car.</p>
<p>After carefully dislodging the remaining half of the bucket, we were even more shocked to notice that the car was dripping concerning amounts of liquid more or less from the spot where the bucket had been stuck. Further on-site and online investigation by the crew brought to light the following observations: 1) The liquid was not hot, and so probably did not come from the engine. 2) The liquid was tasteless (don’t ask). 3) The air-conditioner had been running all the time, and certainly would have to get rid of water condensate from the cooled air. This latter observation was to us not immediately obvious, but now is, and hopefully to you as well: <strong>Automobile air-conditioners often get rid of condensed water through outlets under the car.</strong> Phew.</p>
<p>Our speeding bullet tore through the remaining 200 kilometres in record time, where <a href="http://simvis.at/" title="Link to SimVis, Helmut's company.">my man Helmut from Vienna</a> <em>and</em> these <strong>wonderful brain-boosters</strong> were waiting for us on the <a href="http://maps.google.nl/maps?f=q&amp;source=s_q&amp;hl=en&amp;geocode=&amp;q=Nikolaikirchhof,+Leipzig,+Deutschland&amp;sll=51.34071,12.378302&amp;sspn=0.000678,0.001742&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;hq=&amp;hnear=Nikolaikirchhof,+04109+Leipzig,+Germany%E2%89%AA=51.340525,12.378309&amp;spn=0.001356,0.003484&amp;t=h&amp;z=19" title="Google Maps link to Nikolaikirchhof">Nikolaikirchhof</a>:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/leipzig_4x1l.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/leipzig_4x1l.jpg"
        
            alt="Leipzig&#39;s famous 1 litre brain boosters. Image deliberately deFaced. The arms in the photo might or might not belong to anyone that you know."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Leipzig's famous 1 litre brain boosters. Image deliberately deFaced. The arms in the photo might or might not belong to anyone that you know.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  The conference kicked off the next morning bright and early with a <strong>brilliant keynote by </strong><strong><a href="http://webstaff.itn.liu.se/~andyn/ITN/Home.html" title="website prof. Anders Ynnerman">Prof. Anders Ynnerman</a></strong>.  This was related to the great talk he gave in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/06/28/sometimes-being-in-academia-rules-weekly-head-voices-25/" title="blog post including Prof. Ynnerman's talk in Delft">Delft the week before</a>, but even better, as, amongst other things, he had had the Virtual Autopsy multi-touch table shipped all the way to Leipzig to be able to demo live during his presentation. He even managed to undo the evil our projector in Delft had wrought on his laptop’s colour profiles and finally showed his visualisations in their full glory on the projector in the <a href="http://www.mediencampus-villa-ida.de/" title="link to Mediencampus Villa Ida website">Mediencampus Villa Ida</a>.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  The <strong>second keynote, given by <a href="http://rsl.stanford.edu/bammer/" title="homepage Dr Roland Bammer">Dr Roland Bammer</a></strong><strong>, focused on their work on eliminating motion artefacts in brain MRI</strong>, both by image post-processing but also, and this is the really cool bit, by mounting a special marker on the forehead of the subject that allows real-time 3D motion tracking and linked real-time low-level correction of the MRI acquisition process. They are currently working hard on getting their tech into users’ hands. Help them by bugging your local Radiology Department about this! :)
</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/virtual_autopsy_at_vcbm2010.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/07/virtual_autopsy_at_vcbm2010.jpg"
        
            alt="The multi-touch virtual autopsy table was available throughout the conference to try out. Two observations: 1. Sometimes the glass surface of the multitouch.fi table is harder to work with than the MS Surface&#39;s matt finish. 2. It&#39;s hard to use the table in environments with too much lighting."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The multi-touch virtual autopsy table was available throughout the conference to try out. Two observations: 1. Sometimes the glass surface of the multitouch.fi table is harder to work with than the MS Surface's matt finish. 2. It's hard to use the table in environments with too much lighting.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
 
<p>The rest of the scientific program was perfectly varied, consisting of paper presentations, an invited talks session and a posters session, including a plenary fast-forward where each poster author was given three minutes to promote their work.  What really shone throughout the two days, was the <strong>superb organisation in Leipzig</strong>: Thanks to <a href="http://www.cbs.mpg.de/staff/wiebel-11088" title="website Dr Alex Wiebel">Dr Alex Wiebel</a> and colleagues, the conference was a text-book example of conference organisation, with each event occurring at exactly the right time, not a moment too soon or a moment too late.  The <a href="http://www.mediencampus-villa-ida.de/" title="Mediencampus Villa Ida website">Mediencampus Ida Villa</a> was the ideal location for the conference, not in the least due to its air-conditioned auditorium shielding us from the more than 30 degrees Celsius outside temperatures. Another important manifestation of the superb organisation were the magical coffee breaks, always taking place exactly when <em>you</em> needed them, with copious amounts of cookies to boot!</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  Erik Pernod and Herve Delingette won the <strong>VCBM 2010 Best Paper award</strong> with their paper titled <em>Interactive real time simulation of cardiac radio-frequency ablation</em>, really great work combining elements of simulation, visualisation and a clear clinical application.  The best paper committee had a relatively easy choice, as the reviews (3 to 4 per submission) were also unanimous about this paper’s ranking. As an added bonus, the work is available within the open-source <a href="http://www.sofa-framework.org/" title="SOFA framework website">SOFA framework</a>.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  My personal and completely biased <strong>Head Voices VCBM 2010 Best Talk Award</strong> however, goes to the invited talk by <a href="http://www.icg.tu-graz.ac.at/Members/streit" title="website Marc Streit">Marc Streit</a> and <a href="http://www.icg.tugraz.at/Members/alex" title="website Alexander Lex">Alexander Lex</a> on <em>Caleydo: Visual Analysis of Biomolecular Data</em>. The presentation was an extremely entertaining show by two skilled speakers, striking just the right balance between focus and variety as they demonstrated several aspects of their Caleydo visual analysis software.  At several points, for example the explicit visual linking of different heterogeneous data sources (paper <a href="http://www.caleydo.org/publication/2010_GI_VisualLinksAcrossApplications.pdf" title="caleydo: linking different applications paper">here</a>, youtube video <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4uXvxAeb5xA" title="Caleydo: Linking different applications video.">here</a>, see <a href="http://www.caleydo.org/publications.html" title="All Caleydo publications">here</a> for other publications.), I had the typical reaction to good scientific contributions: Now why didn’t I think of that?!
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  Three to four of the VCBM 2010 papers (this includes the best paper of course) will soon be selected to submit an extended version to the <strong>forthcoming special issue in the Computers and Graphics journal on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine</strong>.  Very importantly: <em>Everyone is welcome to submit an aptly themed paper to this special issue!</em> See the <a href="http://vcbm.org/2010/cagissue/" title="C&amp;G special issue on VCBM call for papers">C&amp;G special issue on VCBM call for papers</a> for more information.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  On a more personal note: This was the second VCBM workshop, with the first having been held in Delft in 2008, organised by yours truly. It was really great in Leipzig experiencing the growing community around this event and especially connecting with some of my favourite people. I’m greatly looking forward to future VCBM workshops, which makes it doubly cool that  VCBM 2012 will be hosted by Prof. Anders Ynnerman in Linköping (Sweden) and that after that, it will become a yearly phenomenon.
</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">
  Will you join us?
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>EuroVis 2010 [Weekly Head Voices #24]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2010 10:13:19 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/19/eurovis-2010-weekly-head-voices-24/</guid><description> Welcome all to the latest edition of the Weekly Head Voices! In a bid to get more numbers into my titles (oh who am I kidding, I’m clearly trying to slightly injure or preferably frighten two birds with a single stone, splitting infinitives as I go along), this WHV is dedicated to the EuroVis 2010 conference, which on its part is the reason I spent most of last week in Bordeaux.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome all to the latest edition of the Weekly Head Voices!  In a bid to get more numbers into my titles (oh who am I kidding, I’m clearly trying to slightly injure or preferably frighten two birds with a single stone, splitting infinitives as I go along), this WHV is dedicated to the EuroVis 2010 conference, which on its part is the reason I spent most of last week in Bordeaux.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/chateau_faugeres-1024.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/chateau_faugeres-1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Château Faugères, youngest of the chateaux. Photo by Peter Krekel."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Château Faugères, youngest of the chateaux. Photo by Peter Krekel.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>EuroVis is definitely the most important European scientific conference on Visualisation. For detailed and complete coverage, see <a href="http://www.cse.msstate.edu/~tjk/" title="T.J. Jankun-Kelly's website">T.J. Jankun-Kelly’s</a> (he was also the uncontested tweetmaster of the conference) detailed blog posts on the <a href="http://www.vizworld.com/2010/06/eurovis2010-day-1-wrapup/" title="tj's blog post on eurovis 2010 day 1">first</a>, <a href="http://www.vizworld.com/2010/06/eurovis2010-day-2-wrapup/" title="TJ's blog post on eurovis 2010 day 2">second</a> and <a href="http://www.vizworld.com/2010/06/eurovis2010-day-3-wrapup/" title="tj's blog post on day 3 of eurovis 2010">third</a> days of the conference. The post you are reading now is my very own extremely biased and mostly incomplete view of the conference and of conferences in general, which can sometimes be interesting.  Or just very misleading.</p>
<p>Let’s start with the basics: A scientific conference is where a bunch of mostly scientists get together somewhere in the world, ostensibly to present recent results of their research to each other. Work certainly gets presented, and in some cases it’s a treat seeing a gifted orator giving a superb presentation.</p>
<p>However, in my mind the primary reason to go to a conference is not to discuss work that was submitted half a year ago, but to meet with colleagues and <em>friends</em> and to discuss important things, such as life, science in general and the research that has not yet been published or even started up yet. It is a hugely important element of the social goo that keeps a research field coherent and cooperative.</p>
<p>There are numerous overlapping interest and social groups that continuously split off to discuss something or just socialise, and then merge back into the larger group. The various attendees each has their own character and associated mode of operation: Some flit around, speaking to all and sundry, some stick to and act as the backbone of the subgroup that they belong to, some walk around and think, sometimes being approach by yet another type of agent. It’s interesting to watch from the corner of one’s eye whilst one is also <em>enjoying</em> taking part in this system. Sometimes the backyard anthropologist in me wonders how exactly the nature of this social fabric affects the performance of science. I imagine that it would be cool to put together a taxonomy of social conference types and even map their behaviour during a single conference such as this.</p>
<p>In any case, at EuroVis there were, the same as <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/" title="link to eurovis 2009 post">last year in Berlin</a>, 190 attendees.  Three days of presentations, with a poster session and a visit to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint-%C3%89milion" title="wikipedia page on Saint-Emilion">Saint-Émilion</a> thrown in for good measure.</p>
<p>With regard to the presentations, I seemed to notice an ever-so-slight upwards trend in the number of papers accompanied by open source software implementations (both <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Krekel2010a" title="Link to MotionVA paper">MotionVA</a> and <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Busking2010" title="Link to SSX paper">ShapeSpaceExplorer</a> by respectively our very own Peter Krekel and Stef Busking are open source, but there were more examples). This is really a great development, as it is an important component of the whole open science idea. With the implementations available, colleagues can reproduce one’s results and thus have a greater chance of being able to improve on them. Also, new implementations can be directly compared to existing ones, something which is currently incredibly hard.</p>
<p>Two of my favourite presentations were the following:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Visual Support for Interactive Post-Interventional Assessment of Radiofrequency Ablation Therapy</em> by Christian Rieder, Andreas Weihusen, Christian Schumann, Stephan Zidowitz, Heinz-Otto Peitgen: I really like this genre of solutions, where complex 3D problems are reduced to normalised 2D representations. A previous example is the <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/" title="my eurovis 2009 blog post">work of Neugebauer et al. at EuroVis 2009</a>. In this case, the authors presented “tumor maps”, a 2D map-style representation of the tumor and its surroundings which greatly facilitates the post-therapy tumor assessment. The fulltext paper will hopefully be linked on <a href="http://www.mevis-research.de/~crieder/" title="Christian Rieder's website">Christian’s website</a> soon.</li>
<li><em><a href="http://www.cs.sfu.ca/~torsten/Publications/Papers/ev10-3.pdf" title="Link to fulltext PDF">Estimation and Modeling of Actual Numerical Errors in Volume Rendering</a></em> by Joel Kronander, Jonas Unger, Anders Ynnerman, Torsten Möller: Although this is not my personal favourite type of research, I think the work (and work like it) is tremendously important. The authors meticulously measure the impact of different precision and sampling strategies on the volume rendering pipeline, and, as if that wasn’t enough, derive a mathematical model with which the role of these variables can be predicted in unseen volume rendering problems. In my view, this is a great example of research towards deriving elements of that elusive visualisation <em>theory</em>. Just to help ram the point home, the presentation was <em>extremely</em> well executed.</li>
</ul>
<p>On a slightly higher level, what I’ve also started noticing is the different <em>styles</em> of visualisation.  Many research groups have a distinct style of visually representing their data: One can easily recognise a <a href="http://www.cg.tuwien.ac.at/research/vis/" title="Link to TU Wien vis group">Viennese design</a>, and sometimes even notice how elements thereof have been subtly adapted by a faction of ex-Viennese scientists in Bergen.  The <a href="http://www.ii.uib.no/vis/" title="link to Bergen vis group">Bergenesque style</a> is still quite young, but will probably soon spread to different groups.  Of course not all groups are that easy: Our own style is heterogeneous, although I’m glad to see at least the blue-to-yellow more-or-less perceptually linear colour-scale starting to permeate our work. It would still be interesting to start a kind of genealogical tree showing the various styles and also how they spread along with the persons practising them.</p>
<p>On the topic of Saint-Émilion: 1000 vineyards covering 95% of the available land, oldest of the vineyards 2000 years old, number of beautiful old Chateaux (castles man, castles!) each having on average 6 hectares of land. 5 different classes of wine produceds, ranging from 5 euros per bottle (hello there!) up to 7000 euros per bottle. It’s a beautiful piece of country.  In fact, it reminded me very strongly of the Western Cape in South Africa,where I grew up.</p>
<p>My group ended up visiting <a href="http://www.chateau-faugeres.com/" title="website chateau">Château Faugères</a>, by far the youngest of the chateaux, but awesomely cool nonetheless, as it was designed by a Swiss-Italian architect by the awesomely cool name of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mario_Botta" title="Mario Botta's wikipedia page">Mario Botta</a>. We got to taste one (1) wine. This was slightly less reminiscent of the vineyards of the Western Cape in South Africa, where one can taste wines until one starts developing very entertaining coordination problems. Fortunately, this very small oversight was more than compensated for by the subsequent visit to the town of Saint-Émilion, its monolithic church and the catacombs, all narrated by an extremely gifted and humorous guide, and finally by the marvelous concluding dinner, done as only the French can.</p>
<p>So kids, that it was it for this week’s lecture on Further Mystifying Scientific Conferences!  I have to go, as I have to start thinking about the next Weekly Head Voices.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Futuristic Betting at VisWeek 2009.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2009 12:26:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/</guid><description> So I went to IEEE VisWeek 2009, and it was far more awesome and enjoyable than even my most optimistic expectations. Besides contributing to the tweetstorm (see #visweek) but not being able to liveblog due to higher priority activities, attending paper presentations and chatting with as many cool people as possible (much higher priority activities), this year I&amp;rsquo;ve also made a number of elaborate bets with a subset of said cool people concerning the future of our technology.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>So I went to IEEE VisWeek 2009, and it was far more awesome and enjoyable than
even my most optimistic expectations. Besides contributing to the tweetstorm
(see <a href="http://twitter.com/#search?q=%23visweek" title="link to visweek hashtag search">#visweek</a>) but not being able to liveblog due to higher priority
activities, attending paper presentations and chatting with as many cool people
as possible (much higher priority activities), this year I&rsquo;ve also made a
number of elaborate bets with a subset of said cool people concerning the
future of our technology. If all goes according to plan, the bets&rsquo;ll end
up being visionary, if not, they might be slightly embarrassing and we&rsquo;ll
have a good laugh at VisWeek 2019.</p>
<p>Because these bets only realise in 10 or 20 years, I&rsquo;ve told my betting
partners that I would write it up on my blog so that we could check in that
much time, and that they would then owe me copious amounts of beer. This also
gives them the opportunity to check my wording for suitability, as we might
have to cleave hairs when the time comes.</p>
<h2 id="bet-1-huds">Bet #1: HUDs.</h2>
<p><em>Bet #1: At VisWeek 2019, I and at least one other person will be wearing a HUD
pretty much all the time, OR I will have at least one bionic eye.</em></p>
<figure>
<a href="http://www.popsci.com/gear-amp-gadgets/article/2009-06/heads-display-embedded-glasses">
<img src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/interactive-data-eyeglasses.jpg" style="margin: 0px;"/>
</a>
<figcaption>Courtesy of Fraunhofer-Gesellschaft.</figcaption>
</figure> 
<p>I made this bet with the infamous Dr. Bob Laramee, proprietor of the <a href="http://www.winslam.com/rlaramee/star/index.html" title="5-star webpage">5-star
webpage</a>. This came up in a conversation about having some form of
non-intrusive display device always available with which things could be looked
up, relatively unobtrusively, during for example a conversation.</p>
<p>I do expect that sometime within the next 10 years, HUDs (heads-up display)
will be offered as an option with every new set of spectacles. This is
definitely not a push-over bet, but that makes it all the more exciting.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure how the bionic eye clause slipped in there, honestly!</p>
<h2 id="bet-2-the-future-of-cars">Bet #2: The future of cars.</h2>
<p><em>Bet #2: 19.5 years from now, there will be more cars with alternative propulsion systems than there are cars with fossil-fuel based internal combustion engines.</em></p>
<p>This one was made with Dr Helmut Doleisch, linked view data analysis guru and
now CEO of <a href="http://www.simvis.at/" title="SimVis website">SimVis</a> (hey man, BUY THEIR SOFTWARE!). He is concerned with all
the vested interests in fossil-fuel combustion, whereas I think that 19.5 years
is more than enough time to introduce non-fossil fuel based propulsion systems
on the road, so much so that less than 50% of cars on the road will have need
of fossil fuel.</p>
<p>Brazil with its 190 million inhabitants is an interesting example in this
regard: A large number of their cars already run on either gasoline or
sugarcane ethanol &mdash; clearly a great step in the direction of non-fossil
fuel options.</p>
<h2 id="bet-3-the-future-of-conferences">Bet #3: The future of conferences.</h2>
<p><em>Bet #3: In 2029, distributed conferences with tele-presence will be common.</em></p>
<p>In this case, the beer-donor is Dr Stefan Bruckner, master of all things volume
visualisation and father of the VolumeShop software system. My contention is
that in 20 years, conferences where attendees take part via tele-presence
systems, whatever they may be, will be common-place.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve called one of the models I envision of this &ldquo;clustered telepresence&rdquo;,
which would entail that groups of attendees would indeed gather physically, but
that these remote clusters would be connected by advanced tele-presence
systems, involving advanced displays (think very large, or perhaps even some
form of mobile volumetric displays) and distributed and mobile sound.</p>
<p>During the discussion preceding the making of this bet, valid concerns were
raised with regard to the efficacy of remote socialising, especially
beer-drinking. I agree that this is an issue of utmost importance, but still
contend that technology and efficiency concerns will conspire to address this
problem in a way that is at least good enough to fool, to a sufficient extent,
all parties involved.</p>
<h2 id="update-on-2019-10-27">Update on 2019-10-27</h2>
<p>On Friday, October 25, Dr DataVis Bob of Bet #1, Dr Helmut Doleisch of Bet #2
and <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/">Prof Noeska Smit</a> (representing both me and Prof
Bruckner of Bet
#3), the former three all present at VisWeek 2019, recorded a three-part video
message to me, and to the world, in which they declared that I had definitely
lost bet #1.</p>
<p>I do agree fully with their judgement.</p>
<p>As far as they could establish, there was no-one else at VisWeek 2019 with any
form of HUD&hellip;  WHICH THEY COULD DETECT!</p>
<p>However, I was definitely not present at VisWeek.</p>
<p>Even if I had been there, I don&rsquo;t own any of the spectacle-integrated HUDs that
I predicted in 2009, and I still have both my own organic eyes.</p>
<p><strong>Anyways, the fact of the matter is that I now owe Dr Bob an unspecified
amount of beer.</strong></p>
<p>More seriously, a few years after my 2009 prediction of HUDs in spectacles,
Google released <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_glass">Google Glass</a>. At
that point, I thought that things were going to go my way.</p>
<p>However, after the initial hype,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_glass#Criticism">criticism</a> started
piling up, and the project was shelved a few years later.</p>
<p>That being said, recent developments such as Microsoft&rsquo;s augmented reality
<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/hololens">Hololens</a>, the great deal of R&amp;D
effort Apple is pouring into augmented reality in all of their hardware, and
other movements in the technology landscape, lead me to think that this
discussion about omni-present non-intrusive personal displays is not completely
over.</p>
<h3 id="bets-2-and-3">Bets #2 and #3</h3>
<p>There are still 9.5 years left for bet #2.</p>
<p>I have asked Dr Helmut if we could amend the bet to specify cars in the EU.</p>
<p>Even if he agrees, there&rsquo;s indeed not that much time in car-years for more than
half of the cars on roads in the EU to have non-fossil-fuel propulsion systems.</p>
<p>However, if the bet were too easy, it would not be as much fun, now would it?</p>
<p>For bet #3 I am also still going to hang on.</p>
<p>The ongoing deterioration of our environment is one of multiple factors putting
more weight behind the movement for better tele-conferencing.</p>
<p>In addition to that, people keep on comparing face-to-face meetings with
terrible tele-conference setups.</p>
<p>Of course face-to-face is better than your laptop&rsquo;s sub-par camera, woefully
inadequate sound and embarrassing lack of robot legs!</p>
<p>I am really curious as to the limits and parameters of human immersion.</p>
<p>Who knows what clever tricks can be done to fool the highly gullible human
psyche into believing that it&rsquo;s actually present and interacting with other
humans somewhere thousands of kilometres away?</p>
<p>Anyways, I digress.</p>
<p>More importantly than everything I have written in this update, receiving this
video message from the future, made by friends who live and work a world away,
absolutely made my day.</p>
<p>Friends, I almost felt like I was sitting there with you at VisWeek 2019. Thank
you!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #3: Powerless meat Zen, Xi leaves, NFBI, Motek</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/13/weekly-head-voices-3-powerless-meat-zen-xi-leaves-nfbi-motek/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2009 08:56:04 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/13/weekly-head-voices-3-powerless-meat-zen-xi-leaves-nfbi-motek/</guid><description> HI KIDS!!
You thought I’d forgotten all about you, dintcha? Nope, not that easily.
Because this edition of the Weekly Head Voices is the most unorganised ever, the trick of bolding the most representative words in each paragraph simply won’t fly. So instead I’ll just highlight some random words, and you can pretend that they actually mean something. Think of it as a post-modernistic exercise in missing the point. I’ll try and be more organised next week.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>HI KIDS!!</p>
<p>You thought I’d forgotten all about you, dintcha?  Nope, not that easily.</p>
<p>Because this edition of the Weekly Head Voices is the <strong>most unorganised ever</strong>, the trick of bolding the most representative words in each paragraph simply won’t fly.  So instead I’ll just highlight some random words, and you can pretend that they actually mean something.  Think of it as a post-modernistic exercise in missing the point.  I’ll try and be <strong>more organised</strong> next week.</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/delft_bicycles_1024.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/delft_bicycles_1024.jpg"
        
            alt="The most post-relevant image I could find: The overfull bicycle parking behind Delft station on Thursday just after noon, right before leaving for the NFBI meeting in Leiden (see later in this post). Turns out that in the Netherlands, there&#39;s on average slightly more than one bicycle for each and every inhabitant."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The most post-relevant image I could find: The overfull bicycle parking behind Delft station on Thursday just after noon, right before leaving for the NFBI meeting in Leiden (see later in this post). Turns out that in the Netherlands, there's on average slightly more than one bicycle for each and every inhabitant.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The past week, #37 of the year 2009, started really quietly with only two regular, but interesting, progress meetings on the Monday.  On Tuesday, things started heating up with another two meetings (nice ones) and a 2-hour long Medical Visualisation demo to a friendly gentleman from <a href="http://visibletv.nl/" title="VisibleTV website">VisibleTV</a>, a production company that has been contracted by my employer to put together an 8-minute video showcasing all medically-oriented research at the TU.  Due to the chaos of trying to book <em>affordable</em> plane tickets to Atlantic City that <em>don’t</em> involve 3 days of transit via donkey and a stint on the back of a <strong>livestock truck</strong>, I found myself in a slightly <strong>ruffled state</strong> by the end of the day.</p>
<p>I <em>detest</em> ending my day in a ruffled state, even if it is an ever so slight ruffle.</p>
<p>However, fate (we’ll talk about that <em>much</em> later) had conspired to return me forcibly to my preferred Zen state via three powerful avenues: I had to go BBQ at home with family and an <a href="http://gerwindehaan.nl/" title="Website of my extremely welcome guest">extremely welcome guest</a>, and, to make sure that the BBQ had the desired effect, the whole of Westland (my region) lost electricity from right about when I started the fire until midnight.  Just to make sure that the message hit home, the weather was perfect.  Picture this: Darkened houses, perfect dusk, balmy weather, superb quiet except for people all keeping each other company outside.  <strong>Complete Zen.</strong></p>
<p>The next day was predictably a winner.  Now Zen-powered, I managed to kill off a scarily big chunk of my over-engineered todo list, in spite of 5 meetings and Xi’s farewell occasion.  Yes, I’m afraid that after a year of visiting our group, doing great work and generally integrating just perfectly, <strong>Xi has gone back to Beijing</strong>.  We are definitely going to miss her.</p>
<p>The highlight of Thursday was the bi-annual meeting of the <a href="http://nfbi.nl/" title="website of the nfbi">Netherlands Forum for Biomedical Imaging</a>, or the <strong>NFBI</strong>, an acronym that is in fact a significant improvement over NVPHBV (man, what an inside joke).  The NFBI is where all Dutch research groups that do something in biomedical imaging get together to discuss that something.  The meetings usually consist of a number of research presentations.  On Thursday, these were mostly given by post-doctoral researchers.  One thing that struck me was that although the content was of a consistently high quality, the presentations themselves sometimes were amenable to improvement.  I understand that the biggest challenge is actually doing the research, but <strong>the value of presenting that research in an accessible and entertaining way should not be underestimated</strong>.</p>
<p>My personal favourite, and probably <em>not</em> amenable to all that much improvement :), was the presentation by <a href="http://www.mate.tue.nl/mate/showemp.php/2146" title="Bram Platel's work page"><strong>Dr Bram Platel</strong></a> of his group’s work on <strong>Deep Brain Stimulation</strong> (DBS) of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subthalamic_nucleus" title="Wikipedia page on the STN">sub-thalamic nucleus</a> (STN).  Turns out that by stimulating this peanut-sized part of the basal ganglia system (by sticking an electrode deep into the brain, hence the name), you can for example remedy some of the motoric symptoms of Parkinson’s disease.  The problem is that if you stimulate the non-motor parts of the STN, this can result in acute depression.  Bram and his group are trying to solve this problem by figuring out the patient-specific layout of the STN via high angular resolution diffusion imaging (HARDI), an MRI-based imaging technique that is able to show structural connectivity in the brain.  Man, I thought that that was going to be a nice and short explanation…  In sharp contrast to my paraphrased version, the presentation entertained, edified and engaged.  To compensate, I alliterate.</p>
<p>Friday morning started with two meetings in Leiden: One concerning starting up new neuro-imaging research together with the LUMC and an <a href="http://gpsgek.nl/" title="Martijn's website">extremely capable M.Sc. student</a>, and the other concerning productising existing research.  The former is still in stealth mode, the latter involves putting the <strong>motion capture and visualisation software</strong> developed by two groups of bachelor students (and ourselves) into production use, first in the LUMC Motion Laboratory, and finally in other labs as open source.</p>
<p>The work week was concluded with a <strong>fantastic visit at </strong><a href="http://www.motekmedical.com/" title="Motek Medical website"><strong>Motek Medical</strong></a> in Amsterdam, together with <a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/franssteenbrink" title="Frans's LinkedIn profile">Frans</a>, motion scientist extraordinaire, who was the primary guest and graciously invited us along, and <a href="http://articulis.nl/" title="Peter's website">Peter</a>, surgical planning guru and motion visualiser of note.  Motek makes and advises on a number of different motion platforms (think for example a 2m conveyor belt on top of a flight-simulator-like collection of hydraulics), matching giant screens and various motion capture setups that enable all kinds of virtual reality and motion measurement magic.  The embedded YouTube clip below shows a demo of their HBM system, that’s able to estimate muscle activation from motion capture in real time:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ooIJIIAG_VQ?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>At the core of all their products is the <a href="http://www.motekmedical.com/dflow.html" title="More concerning the CAREN system">CAREN software system</a>.  This is an impressive data-flow framework with a visual programming front-end that enables real-time communication with all kinds of sensors and actuators, from humble rotation sensor all the way up to multi-camera optical tracking and industrial-grade hydraulics.  Our gracious hosts, Erwin Albers and Thomas Geijtenbeek, demonstrated by linking up a fresh rotation sensor with collision detection in all of 2 minutes.</p>
<p>So, that was it for this week boys and girls!  I was still planning a short bit on the evolutionary basis of music and dance (seems to be an interesting mystery), but the current post already seems to have outgrown my intentions.   See you in a week, most probably with a much smaller edition of the WHV (Weekly Head Voices man!).  I’m planning a quiet week, at least in terms of bloggable highlights. :)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices for Week 36</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2009 08:35:28 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/</guid><description> Dear readers,
The time has come for the second installment of the exciting new Weekly Head Voices feature! My PR people tell me that this is a roaring success and that I am rapidly on my way to becoming an A-List blogger. My therapist tells me that I should find a good psychiatrist.
Before starting, I’d like to show the following photo (will get back to it later):
In order to facilitate your reading experience, I have bolded in each paragraph some words that represent, with differing levels of effectiveness, the theme of that paragraph.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear readers,</p>
<p>The time has come for the second installment of the exciting new Weekly Head Voices feature!  My PR people tell me that this is a roaring success and that I am rapidly on my way to becoming an A-List blogger. My therapist tells me that I should find a good psychiatrist.</p>
<p>Before starting, I’d like to show the following photo (will get back to it later):</p>
<p><a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:The_Tropicana.JPG" title=""><img alt="The_Tropicana_400" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-581" data-attachment-id="581" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"5.34","credit":"","camera":"FinePix A345","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1147716095","copyright":"","focal_length":"7.8","iso":"64","shutter_speed":"0.0024003840614498","title":""}' data-image-title="The_Tropicana_400" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400-300x225.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400.jpg" data-orig-size="400,300" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/the_tropicana_400/" height="300" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 85vw, 400px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400.jpg 400w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400-300x225.jpg 300w" title="The_Tropicana_400" width="400"/></a></p>
<p>In order to facilitate your reading experience, I have bolded in each paragraph some words that represent, with differing levels of effectiveness, the theme of that paragraph.  This way, you can easily skip ahead, keeping in mind that you’re probably skipping over some truly inspiring writing.</p>
<p>During the past week, I had 11 face-to-face <strong>meetings</strong> with students, colleagues and collaborators.  Apart from these meetings, I presented the MedVis group’s research to a group of new postgrads on Tuesday and hosted, together with colleagues from the LUMC, a visit by <a href="http://www.tornier.com/site" title="Tornier website">Tornier</a> on Friday.  It turns out that this job does in fact require a seemingly paradoxical mix of computer nerd and social butterfly.</p>
<p>On Monday, I acted as external member in the M.Sc. opposition of a thesis titled “In vivo identification of short range stiffness in the human wrist” – the student managed to figure out internal wrist muscle characteristics by applying external angular displacement and measuring effective torque.  Reviewing the work was an interesting experience, as biomechanical modelling is not one of my research foci.  All in all, very good work, although it did remind me again of why <strong>one should not typeset longer documents with a sans serif font</strong>.</p>
<p>The highlight of the week is surely <a href="http://gerwindehaan.nl/" title="Gerwin's website"><strong>Gerwin de Haan</strong></a><strong>‘s</strong> <a href="http://visualization.tudelft.nl/People/GerwinDeHaan/thesis" title="Gerwin's PhD page"><strong>PhD defense</strong></a>.  An exemplary opposition, with solid attacks by the committee (6 full professors and 1 associate professor) and great defensive moves by the intrepid candidate, made for an entertaining morning.  The day was concluded with a celebratory party during which the candidate, besides consuming amounts of beer fit for a fresh doctor, received congratulatory loot fit for a PS3 and Rockband-addicted pirate!</p>
<p>In other nerd-worthy news: I am now the proud owner of an <a href="http://www.cnet.com.au/asus-eee-pc-1005ha-h-339297780.htm" title="asus eeepc 1005ha-h cnet review"><strong>Asus 1005HA-H Netbook</strong></a>, rated with 10.5 hours of battery life.  I can confirm that the battery life is indeed awe-inspiring, also in practice.   The little beast easily lasts a whole day, and then some.  The only issue so far has been choosing a <strong>good encryption solution</strong>.  The little Atom N280 doesn’t manage much more than 30MB/s in the Truecrypt encryption benchmark, and about 38MB/s even with the optimised Diskcryptor implementation.  The Windows XP Home that this netbook ships with of course does not support EFS.  In the end, I went for Truecrypt (I use it everywhere else) and just copied over the 25G encrypted container from my Big Laptop.</p>
<p>Getting back to the photo above:  Boys and girls, thanks to my generous leader and the TU Delft, I get to join said generous leader and <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/~jorik/" title="Jorik's homepage">Jorik</a> on a trip to <a href="http://vis.computer.org/VisWeek2009/" title="VisWeek 2009"><strong>IEEE Visualization 2009</strong></a> in Atlantic City!  For the socially more well-adjusted readers, this is like Visualisation Nerd Heaven: A whole week of mingling with technically creative colleagues, discussing the latest visualisation tidbits, following paper presentations and Sleeping Much Less(tm).  Brilliant!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Bill Buxton at CARS 2009</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/06/25/bill-buxton-at-cars-2009/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2009 21:31:04 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/06/25/bill-buxton-at-cars-2009/</guid><description> Courtesy of an invitation by Prof. Bernhard Preim and the CARS (Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery) organization to give the Visualization and Virtual Reality in Medicine tutorial together with the good professor, I got to go to CARS 2009 in (you guessed it) Berlin. It was an honour and a pleasure to present this tutorial together with the author of The Book currently defining my research field.
What was completely unexpected though, was being completely blown away by Bill Buxton’s keynote.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Courtesy of an invitation by Prof. Bernhard Preim and the <a href="http://cars-int.org/" title="Link to the CARS website.">CARS (Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery)</a> organization to give the <em>Visualization and Virtual Reality in Medicine</em> tutorial together with the good professor, I got to go to CARS 2009 in (you guessed it) Berlin.  It was an honour and a pleasure to present this tutorial together with the author of <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Visualization-Medicine-Algorithms-Applications-Kaufmann/dp/0123705967/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=books&amp;qid=1245963398&amp;sr=8-1" title="Link to Visualization in Medicine book on Amazon">The Book</a> currently defining my research field.</p>
<p>What was completely unexpected though, was being completely blown away by <a href="http://www.billbuxton.com/" title="Bill Buxton's website">Bill Buxton’s</a> keynote.</p>
<p><a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://www.billbuxton.com/bBuxton.jpg" title=""><img alt="bBuxton-small" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-539" data-attachment-id="539" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":""}' data-image-title="bBuxton-small" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/bBuxton-small.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/bBuxton-small-269x300.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/bBuxton-small.jpg" data-orig-size="480,534" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2009/06/25/bill-buxton-at-cars-2009/bbuxton-small/" height="320" sizes="(max-width: 288px) 85vw, 288px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/bBuxton-small.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/bBuxton-small.jpg 480w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/bBuxton-small-269x300.jpg 269w" style="border: 0px;" title="bBuxton-small" width="288"/></a></p>
<p>I have to admit that I was not aware of this distinguished gentleman or his credentials (amongst other things, xerox parc in its absolute heyday, later chief scientist of alias wavefront and of SGI, now principal scientist at Microsoft, and much more) before yesterday.  This <em>dude</em> shows up on stage, and in a totally relaxed and understated way, manages to blow my mind a number of times.</p>
<p>He started by casually telling us that he’d already been playing around with multi-touch displays (now all the rage in the UI world) in 1985, using it to design digital percussion instruments.  Then he demonstrated, with a number of examples, a significant number of which he had personally been involved with (the multi-touch just mentioned among others), his “20 year long nose” observation.  Innovations that eventually make it, take on average 20 years to get from the lab to main-stream, where main-stream is defined as being a billion dollar industry.  The mouse took even longer: 30 years.</p>
<p>Before getting to the next important and extremely provocative point, he showed us this video (I’ve made you a nice crappy mobile phone cam version):</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6nerac6i3FE?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>(<a href="http://krekel.nl/" title="Peter Krekel's website">Peter Krekel</a> managed to find the original Microsoft demo-reel on youtube and shared:)</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DQdGvfV4WnU?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>His provocative statement was that screen real estate will essentially be free in 5 years, based on the rapid evolution of manufacturing technology, customer demand, and the trends in analogous examples, such as bandwidth.  If somebody had told you 10 years ago that internet bandwidth today, in 2009, would be essentially free and available in copious amounts, you would have spat out your morning coffee.  I know I would have… in ’99 we were still dealing with dial-up.  Coming from Bill Buxton, and also based on all his examples, this made me sit up straight and think.  We’re going to have really big screens.  Think metres by metres at a resolution of at least 100 DPI.  Think walls covered with screens, because it’s cheaper than putting up a whiteboard.  We have to rethink everything that we know about interfacing with the digital world…</p>
<p>Another tantalising prediction (and I’ve heard this from more people than Buxton) is that soon mobile phones will have as standard equipment a micro laser projector.  This will allow us to project on arbitrary curved surfaces (it’s coherent light, so always in focus!) when we want to show something to anyone else and, even cooler, it will allow us to perform 3D colour scans of anything we see.  At this stage I had the distinct feeling of my hair being blown back.  <em>I’m going to be living inside Star Trek!</em></p>
<p>There was much more (including personal devices that are more aware of their context: think cell phone automatically speaking to television and computer as you enter a room), but I’d like to conclude this post with one of his more profound lessons: Innovation is hardly ever about coming up with something completely new.  That sometimes does happen, but is a fluke.  Real innovation is about taking one of the dimensions defining an existing technology (size, speed, price, resolution, simplicity, intelligence, and many more subtle dimensions) and expanding that dimension by at least an order of magnitude.  Doing this in fact yields a completely new technology.  The really clever people have learned how to identify the more subtle dimensions and expand them.</p>
<p>I’m going to think about that for a while. :)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>