<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>focus on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/focus/</link><description>Recent content in focus on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 09:08:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/focus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #216: Sup?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</guid><description> Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.
Figure 1: Sup?
The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard with Lots of Focus.
I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily application of the One Main Thing idea, but experience has taught me that it&amp;rsquo;s probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&amp;rsquo;ll be solidly back in the arms of my old friend the really slippery eel.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks
from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="sup_bettys.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sup?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Sup?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard
with Lots of Focus.</p>
<p>I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily
application of <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">the One Main Thing idea</a>, but experience has taught me that it&rsquo;s
probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure
factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&rsquo;ll be solidly
back in the arms of my old friend the <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">really slippery eel</a>.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I have been making good use of the (temporarily?)
increased capacity.</p>
<h2 id="fresh-from-the-oven-vxlabs-software-development-handbook">Fresh from the oven: vxlabs software development handbook</h2>
<p><a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/">The vxlabs software development handbook</a>, at the time of this writing about 65%
complete (that&rsquo;s a random number that my brain gives me every time I publish a
new version), is now available over on my nerdy blog.</p>
<p>If you are working with a smaller development team, or you&rsquo;re starting with a
new dev team, the handbook is not the worst place to look for development
process tips. Furthermore, it&rsquo;s available under the Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License, so you can copy and paste and rebrand to
your heart&rsquo;s content as long as you give due credit somewhere to the original
author (me and vxlabs).</p>
<p>In the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll be trying to complete more sections to get closer to
that mythical 100% completion grade.</p>
<h2 id="two-miscellaneous-tips-for-nerds">Two miscellaneous tips for nerds</h2>
<h3 id="printfriendly-on-your-phone">PrintFriendly on your phone</h3>
<p>You might remember from my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#web-pages-and-articles">2019 note-taking strategy post</a> that I convert all
interesting web pages I come across to PDF and dump them in my dropbox.</p>
<p>This has turned out to be the best way to store web-pages for later searching,
reference and winning of arguments.</p>
<p>However, the mobile part of that strategy was traditionally weak, as is also
discussed in that post.</p>
<p>The problem was that Safari on iPhone has a great reading mode that strips ads
and other unnecessary bits, but when you print from reading mode, the PDF is
formatted for mobile, and, more importantly, there&rsquo;s no way to get the source
URL embedded in the PDF.</p>
<p>Anyways, after years of using the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/">PrintFriendly</a> browser extension on the
desktop (as is also explained in the note-taknig post), I finally got around to
installing their mobile bookmarklet on the iPhone. (this should work on any
mobile browser)</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/extensions/iOS">instructions are a bit finicky</a>, but one ends up with a bookmark that you
can activate on any page to have the printfriendly service pre-process that
page for reading, from which you can tap on the print icon to get a mostly
perfect PDF that is also stamped with the source URL!</p>
<h3 id="fish-shell">Fish shell</h3>
<p>After years of resisting all the zsh blog posts and especially the pretty
oh-my-zsh powerline prompts and sticking to my stock standard bash because
get-off-my-lawn, I finally broke down and installed&hellip;</p>
<p><a href="https://fishshell.com/">fish!</a></p>
<p>fish shell is a &ldquo;smart and user-friendly command line shell for Linux, macOS,
and the rest of the family&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I like it because one of its goals is to be more useful with hardly any extra
configuration, but you can also install <a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/oh-my-fish">oh-my-fish</a> with my new favourite theme
<a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/theme-bobthefish">bobthefish</a>.</p>
<p>I <em>was</em> planning to convince you of my choice with a number of technical
reasons, but it is now clear to me that technical arguments are irrelevant when
you can rock a theme called &ldquo;bobthefish&rdquo;.</p>
<p>P.S. Let me know in the comments if you would still prefer to talk about
technical reasons.</p>
<h2 id="a-brief-pause">A brief pause</h2>
<p>Since we <a href="/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/#gou-1-s-growing-running-habit">last spoke about GOU#1&rsquo;s running habit</a>, it gives me great pleasure to
report that she has, quite routinely if I may add, done another two or three
10k runs, one of them even up to eleven by accident.</p>
<p>Folks I wish you all the best. I look forward to our next connection!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #214: One Main Thing</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/</guid><description> WELCOME BACK EVERYONE TO THIS WARM AND WELCOMING CIRCLE OF WEEKLY HEAD VOICES!
Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded.
You are reading the 214th edition of the WHV, the first of 2021 (hurrah), and spottily covering the intersections of my consciousness with the period of time from Monday, January 11 to Sunday, January 24 of the year 2021.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>WELCOME BACK EVERYONE TO THIS WARM AND WELCOMING CIRCLE OF WEEKLY HEAD VOICES!</p>








<figure><a href="hermanus_coastal_walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You are reading the 214th edition of the WHV, the first of 2021 (hurrah), and
spottily covering the intersections of my consciousness with the period of time
from Monday, January 11 to Sunday, January 24 of the year 2021.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not entirely happy with the water-tightness of this coverage, but <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/">the
2020-2021 year transition post</a>, which I hope you&rsquo;ve read or at least heard
about, is probably worth this bit of start-point haziness.</p>
<h2 id="first-rule-of-blogging-we-don-t-blog-about-blogging">First rule of blogging: We don&rsquo;t blog about blogging</h2>
<p>As you know, <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">I <strong>really</strong> love Hugo</a>, the software tool with which I can write
these posts in Emacs (text editor, you heathens) and then convert them to the
fast static pages that you are now reading.</p>
<p>The one thing I <em>was</em> a bit disappointed with, was the lack of some form of
built-in yearly post archives.</p>
<p>Well, while writing the year transition post, this disappointment spiked into
action, and so I applied just enough internet and elbow grease to scratch my
yearly archive itch on this blog.</p>
<p><a href="/2021/01/10/super-simple-yearly-post-archives-hugo/">This post shows you how to do it</a>, and <a href="/archive/">here you can see the result, yearly
archives for all of the posts on this blog</a>!</p>
<p>As a first step on <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#comms-upgrade">my path to become better at asynchronous communication</a>, I
wrote <a href="/2021/01/16/intro-asynchronous-communication/">an introductory blog post on the topic</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not as happy with it as I would have liked to be, but it&rsquo;s the line in the
sand that I really wanted to draw.</p>
<p>More importantly, I&rsquo;ve been able to get a few people to read it.</p>
<h2 id="signal-i-told-you-so">Signal: I told you so</h2>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2021/01/whatsapp-users-must-share-their-data-with-facebook-or-stop-using-the-app/">WhatsApp recently making clear that they will be sharing increasing
amounts of the massive amounts of your data at their disposal with all other
companies in the Facebook family</a>, many folks have been looking for
alternatives.</p>
<p>Even more fortunately, many of those folks have been choosing the most
pragmatically private alternative, namely Signal.</p>
<p>You might recall that <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">I started recommending that we use Signal back in January
of 2016</a>, which is infinity years ago in internet time.</p>
<p>Telegram does indeed count as an alternative to WhatsApp, but its chats are by
default not end-to-end encrypted, and it&rsquo;s still backed by a for-profit
company. There&rsquo;s nothing wrong with this, but if your concern is privacy now
and in the future, Signal is by far the better choice.</p>
<p>Anyways, I am happy to see more of my contacts appear in the Signal list.</p>
<h2 id="one-main-thing">One Main Thing</h2>
<p>In 2011, <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#pro-tip-2">I wrote about starting the day by writing down concretely the tasks
one would like to complete by the end of the day</a>.</p>
<p>A few years later, <a href="/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/#thinking-of-future-you">I picked up a tip from a podcast with Sam Harris and Derren
Brown that one should explicitly ask the question which tasks would satisfy you
the most at the end of the day</a>.</p>
<p>(Interestingly, in the 2018 post above I misquoted my 2011 post as suggesting
that one writes down &ldquo;the two to three really important tasks for the
day&rdquo;. That &ldquo;two to three&rdquo; came from some other memory which I can&rsquo;t track down
right now.)</p>
<p>Last year <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#its-what-future-you-would-want-quote-edition">I ran into Lubbock&rsquo;s far more eloquent formulation</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If we are ever in doubt about what to do, it is a good rule to ask ourselves
what we shall wish on the morrow that we had done. &ndash; John Lubbock</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the comments to that post, friend AJ added the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Another iteration of what to do next that I recently heard was Gary Kellers
version: The One Thing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have not yet gotten around to reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%5FOne%5FThing%5F(book)">The One Thing</a>, but I think AJ&rsquo;s comment
did plant a seed&hellip;</p>
<p>Fast forward a few months, and I have started to realise that my most
productive and satisfying days often coincide with the days when I have the
guts in the morning to commit to one main thing for the day.</p>
<p>Conversely, when I don&rsquo;t select and commit to One Main Thing, but due to
deadlines and other expectations put more than two or more bigger items on my
list, that day has a high probability of leaving me quite frazzled by its end.</p>
<p>One Main Thing days are scary, because I feel like there is always a long list
of things I&rsquo;m not going to get to, and people I&rsquo;m going to have to disappoint.</p>
<p>However, selecting that One Main Thing wisely, explicitly committing to it, and
then knocking it off after a few hours of focus is undeniably satisfying, and
will probably help a bunch of people.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it turns out that even with this commitment, one does still manage
to get some of the little things done in the scraps of left-over time.</p>
<p>You know, just after lunch, just before dinner and so on.</p>
<p>Pay some bills, answer a few emails, and then dive back into your One Main
Thing.</p>
<h3 id="interstitial-projects">Interstitial projects</h3>
<p>In addition to this, it turns out some of my projects can be specifically
treated as <em>interstitial</em>.</p>
<p>This is the label I&rsquo;ve chosen for those projects that 1. are supported by
low-friction tools that are instantly available and 2. benefit from slivers of
thought.</p>
<p>For example, I&rsquo;m working on a few blog posts dealing with issues I come across
during my work.</p>
<p>During the day, I see something that warrants a section in one of the blog
posts&hellip;</p>
<p>Switch to Emacs, hotkey search the relevant notes file, hotkey search the
relevant section in that file, type the sentence or two in your head, switch
back to work.</p>
<p>That took all of a minute or two, but now there are two new sentences, and we
all know what sentences do, right? They <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a> into blog posts!</p>
<h2 id="do-you-want-to-produce-or-consume">Do you want to produce or consume?</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m technically not allowed to write about something that appeared after the
published timespan of a WHV, but I would be remiss if I did not mention the
nudge that got WHV #214 off the ground.</p>
<p>That nudge is <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/recommendations/">this post by Noeska</a>, and specifically these words:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Do I want to produce or consume?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You should really go read the post for context, but if you need to hear that
sentence, you&rsquo;ll probably understand exactly what it means.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #208: Stilbaai</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 10:59:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</guid><description> Welcome back folks!
Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.
It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.
Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.
Running and reading I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, GOU #1 (14) completed her first (virtual) 10km race.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks!</p>
<p>Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.</p>
<p>It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period
Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="skulpiesbaai_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="running-and-reading">Running and reading</h2>
<p>I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> (14) completed her
first (virtual) 10km race.</p>
<p>Her journey started when a friend from school invited her to join the race, at
which point GOU #1 suddenly became much more enthusiastic about running
regularly with her old dad. (that&rsquo;s me)</p>
<p>There is something pretty primal about running with your offspring, an
observation that I might have mentioned before on these pages.</p>
<p>Anyways, after her race she was visibly happy, and also relieved that, in her
words, &ldquo;she didn&rsquo;t die&rdquo;.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m perhaps even more happy about than the preparatory runs together, and
her completing the race, is that since the race we&rsquo;ve been out together for a
run or three.</p>
<p>(Running and reading are two of the most important low-level habits I would
like to try and get my offspring hooked on.)</p>
<h2 id="ieee-vis2020">IEEE VIS2020</h2>
<p>At the start of October, I had a great experience <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#vcbm-2020-virtually">virtually attending the VCBM
2020 conference</a>.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough grade A1 10/10 conferencing for one year, my other
favourite conference, IEEE VIS (for visualization) was also fully virtual this
year in the week of October 26, so again I dove into YouTube streams and
well-organised discord rooms, and again this experience was highly edifying and
enjoyable.</p>
<p>Somehow, it was even <em>more</em> fun than my already optimistic expectations to run
into friends at the conference.</p>
<p>I would like to transfer this one piece of sage advice given by the amazing
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%5Fvan%5FWijk">Prof. Jarke van Wijk</a> during the panel on &ldquo;Why should I stay in academia&rdquo; when
the discussion treated the issue of dealing with rejection, something that is
unfortunately a regular part of most academic careers.</p>
<p>At this point, he was referring specifically to accepted papers and proposals,
but the advice should really be applied to any victory, large or small, in all
walks of life:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Celebrate your victories.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="cycles">Cycles</h2>
<p>You will of course remember that we were fortunate enough to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">spend our last few
days of freedom in Stilbaai,</a> as autumn was arriving, and more acutely right
before the first lockdown started on March 26,</p>
<p>It was really great going back to the exact same house (thanks kind host!),
after months of various levels of lockdown, this time just as spring was really
getting off the ground.</p>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_0181.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I did take work with me for the long weekend, but this time, and quite
unexpectedly, the important <a href="/tags/disconnecting">disconnect</a> happened quite quickly without too much
conscious effort from my side.</p>
<p>If I had to put my finger on it, I would say that getting everyone to go
outside as often as possible on little adventures of various sizes was the
catalyst.</p>
<h2 id="back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">Back to reality: An 18-minute plan for managing your day</h2>
<p>I could not imagine a more sudden transition from the long weekend zen above
than this jump to Peter Bregman&rsquo;s 18 minute plan for planning your work day.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Sometimes, fortunately mostly later in the afternoon, I wonder why my systems
have failed in helping me to keep my eye on that ball for longer. (See <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">my
slippery eel</a> for more struggles.)</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s when I procrastinate quasi-productively by searching online for any new
self-optimisation tricks that I might have missed, and which might constitute
that Last Piece of The Puzzle that will fix this once and for all.</p>
<p>This time, to my great surprise, I did actually run into something 1. that was
written aaaaaall the way back in 2009 and 2. that contained something new that
I had not run into before, namely the &ldquo;refocus&rdquo; reminder.</p>
<p>The refocus reminder is literally an alarm that goes off every hour on the
hour, at which point you explicitly take a step back for a whole minute to
review the past hour, and, if required (most probably the case the later it is
in the day), to re-commit to the following hour.</p>
<p>This reminded me specifically about mindfulness&rsquo;s <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#therunning-and-the-mindful">&ldquo;Each breath a new beginning;
each out-breath a letting go&rdquo;</a>, and more generally about <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">life as eternal
practice</a>.</p>
<p>You can use any sort of timer to do this, but this seemed like a great feature
for the little Lazar Focus app, so I implemented it along with a nice
mindfulness bell sound to add some gravitas to the moment.</p>
<p>If you like, you can read the short summary I wrote about the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/10/24/peter-bregmans-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day-and-the-surprising-power-of-refocus-reminders/">18-minute plan
and refocus reminders over on the LazarFocused blog</a>. There are some other more
widely known but great tips for running your work days more efficiently.</p>
<h2 id="kind-regards">Kind regards</h2>
<p>Folks, thank you very much for joining me here.</p>
<p>The comments section below is ready for your thoughts, if you would like to
externalise them.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #206: Mount Ceder</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 13:10:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/</guid><description> Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder.
Welcome, dear readers, to the 206th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the two weeks from Monday September 21 to Sunday October 4, 2020.
Mount Ceder beauty The weather prediction for the September 25 long weekend did not look good at all.
Temperatures in the low single digits, and rain.
We were unable to reschedule our reservation, and so, with significant trepidation, we packed our things for the weekend and made the drive to Mount Ceder.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="mount_ceder_4873_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu9f5ab36a16a3a4a8dc06baccb8e6eb94_2331181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome, dear readers, to the 206th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering
the two weeks from Monday September 21 to Sunday October 4, 2020.</p>
<h2 id="mount-ceder-beauty">Mount Ceder beauty</h2>
<p>The weather prediction for the September 25 long weekend did not look good at
all.</p>
<p>Temperatures in the low single digits, and rain.</p>
<p>We were unable to reschedule our reservation, and so, with significant
trepidation, we packed our things for the weekend and made the drive to Mount
Ceder.</p>
<p>As we entered the valley right before arriving at our destination, the rugged
and wonderful beauty of the surroundings quickly started dispelling our puny
expectations.</p>
<p>The weather did turn out almost exactly as was predicted, but our time there
ended up being the brilliant opposite of what we had feared.</p>
<p>In between spells of rain, there was plenty of fresh sunshine outside, with a
super effective little closed combustion fireplace inside the house to keep it
toasty.</p>








<figure><a href="mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu4df34106958282f19ae7aa2ef8f3ca59_2644231_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a hike up the mountain with the whole fam-jam."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: View from a hike up the mountain with the whole fam-jam.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The outside jacuzzi which we discovered late on the Saturday afternoon might
also have played a role in the amount of fun that was had.</p>
<p>It does also need to be said that the fact that there&rsquo;s no telephone reception
is a massive perk for us visitors.</p>
<p>The older I get, the more I enjoy disconnecting.</p>
<h2 id="vcbm-2020-virtually">VCBM 2020, virtually</h2>
<p>Thanks to the modern miracle that is virtual conferences, I was able to attend
a large part of the <a href="https://www.gcpr-vmv-vcbm-2020.uni-tuebingen.de/">Visual Computing in Biology and Medicine (VCBM) 2020
conference</a>.</p>
<p>Although I am super interested in the themes and people of this conference, it
is <em>usually</em> not possible for me to fly around the globe to take part in this
or any other relevant academic gathering.</p>
<p>However, the current pandemic has brought with it a whole host of changes, not
least of which is the concept of being able to participate, as a first class
citizen, in an international conference.</p>
<p>It was really great, although slightly nostalgic, connecting with friends and
colleagues from years ago.</p>
<p>Just being able to join in on the post-talk question sessions, and in the
surreal social rooms on discord where you find yourself in a grid of talking
heads, was super enjoyable.</p>
<p>(It has to be noted here that the technical aspects of VCBM 2020 were also
top-class. Everything, from the interactive block-based conference programme
with downloadable papers, to the youtube streams for each session, to the
discord channels for real-time discussion and the discord channels for social
video conferencing, was simply top notch!)</p>
<h3 id="multi-tasking-virtual-meetings-quo-vadis">Multi-tasking virtual meetings: Quo vadis?</h3>
<p>What was also interesting to hear, was a possibly less positive aspect of
virtual conferencing, specifically that academic peeps were now in the
situation where they often had to multi-task whilst taking part in the
conference.</p>
<p>In the old days, pre-COVID, it could definitely happen that folks had to take
care of a few emails or perhaps even a video meeting, but the majority of the
day would be spent conferencing.</p>
<p>That is, people from potentially right around the globe would be chatting
face-to-face about anything and everything, an activity which is truly
important for collaboration, and friendship.</p>
<p>Now it seems that this ratio has changed, where most of the time folks are
expected to be available online for additional tasks and interactions, while
conferencing in parallel.</p>
<p>In my day job I&rsquo;ve noticed a similar phenomenon, where one can often notice
that people taking part in a meeting are only partially present.</p>
<p>Whilst this is perhaps a good thing for a number of meetings that are by their
nature not that efficient, I think that it&rsquo;s a dangerous habit to
cultivate.</p>
<p>Imagine that by default, every meeting means your poor cognition trying to keep
up with multiple streams of information at the same time. Looking at it from a
different perspective, now you have even less confidence that your
collaborators are paying attention to what is being discussed.</p>
<p>This might be yet another reason to <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">favour asynchronous offline communication</a>,
that is, writing long-form messages on message boards, with synchronous
face-time being reserved more and more for purely social reasons.</p>
<h2 id="on-thursday-october-1-too-much-distraction-was-too-much">On Thursday October 1, too much distraction was too much</h2>
<p>Seguing right on from the synchronous communication point above, On October 1 I
unfortunately needed to be jacked-in to Teams, WhatsApp <em>and</em> Discord for the
whole day, for various good reasons.</p>
<p>It was only around 16:20 that I was able to snap out of all of this and jack
out again, with <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a> helping to bring a bit of welcome rest and,
surprise(!), focus.</p>
<p>Before that, anxiety about possibly missing something kept me from plugging out
for even short bursts to be able to do work.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s funny how the expectations, real or perhaps more often just perceived, of
one&rsquo;s surroundings make it extremely difficult to disconnect, which leads to
more time lost to these various forms of distraction, which leads to further
anxiety, which further complicates just taking those few steps back and pulling
the plug.</p>
<p>I wish I had a trick to manage all of this better.</p>
<h2 id="that-time-i-nuked-all-of-my-computers-with-a-partition-resize-and-move-that-should-have-taken-no-more-than-5-minutes">That time I nuked all of my computers with a partition resize and move that should have taken no more than 5 minutes</h2>
<p><em>Massive nerd warning: If you don&rsquo;t want to know about filesystems, feel free</em>
<em>to skip this section. Before you do however, take this advice from me: Avoid</em>
<em>AOMEI.</em></p>
<p>My goal was simple: Move the newly appeared recovery partition (in addition to
the one at the start of the disk) to its end, so that I can grow my main system
partition to fill the available space on the drive.</p>
<p>Some years ago I had used EaseUs for something similar, but they wanted payment
for this task, and current reviews were pointing quite convincingly in the
direction of AOMEI.</p>
<p>Narrator: <em>The reviews were all tragically wrong.</em></p>
<p>My specific use case is even documented exactly on the AOMEI website, see <a href="https://www.diskpart.com/windows-10/windows-10-move-recovery-partition-4348.html">this
page</a>.</p>
<p>I followed those steps exactly.</p>
<p>My computer rebooted twice in order to perform the two actions:</p>
<ol>
<li>move recovery partition, and</li>
<li>resize system partition&hellip;</li>
</ol>
<p>&hellip; to conclude finally by leaving my laptop in a 100% unusable state.</p>
<p>No boot, no nothing.</p>
<p>I tried various combinations of booting into safe mode, which worked at first
but showed me the full drive&rsquo;s space available, meaning that the filesystem had
probably been damaged.</p>
<p>Hard.</p>
<p>I later booted with Windows installation media, from where I launched various
rescue attempts, including the stalwart <code>bootrec /rebuildbcd</code> and all of its
friends.</p>
<p>Nothing.</p>
<p>AOMEI had done a pretty great job in completely destroying my partition table
and filesystem.</p>
<p>Narrator: <em>He got what he paid for!</em></p>
<p>I ended up installing Windows 10 twice, the second time with the
soon-to-be-released 20H2 install media, because installing the old 1909 and
then upgrading was taking far too long.</p>
<p>The whole exercise, or should I say &ldquo;lesson&rdquo;, cost me about a day.</p>
<p>Stoic narrator: <em>Fortunately, the situation afterwards was better than it was before.</em></p>
<ul>
<li>My main WSL2 ubuntu 20.04 image, where most of my development work happens,
remained untouched on the second SSD and was up and running pretty quickly
after the Windows re-install.</li>
<li>My backups demonstrably work, although Windows File History is truly klunky
compared to Apple&rsquo;s Time Machine.</li>
<li>In the chaos of trying to get my work environment back up and running, I also
had to upgrade my deep learning Linux desktop machine to Ubuntu 20.04. (It
started as a Murphy&rsquo;s law situation, where both my laptop <em>and</em> the desktop
were unusable, the latter due to a stupid Ubuntu bug manifesting as a
non-working keyboard)</li>
<li>A fresh install of Windows feels really fresh.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">My mind is a slippery eel</h2>
<p>Recently I had to work on a chunk of software system design.</p>
<p>It starts with nothing laid down, just a general idea of what this pretty
significant feature should be able to do.</p>
<p>Pulling yourself up by your bootstraps, you have to start laying down the
bottom-most levels of the design that will eventually be able to make those
high-level desired features a reality.</p>
<p>This whole growing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rube%5FGoldberg%5Fmachine">Rube Goldberg machine</a> has to stay in your mind for a large
part of the day, as you&rsquo;re mentally twisting, turning and replacing bits here
and there.</p>
<p>Most of these days, getting my brain to stay focused felt a lot like trying to
hold on to a really slippery eel, and, if that wasn&rsquo;t tricky enough, trying to
aim the sporadically working laser, badly mounted on its slippery head, to try
and carve something recognisable from a block of slowly melting ice.</p>
<p>By the end of most days, it would mostly not feel like it had been very
productive.</p>
<p>I tried to make peace with the fact that some sorts of work, coupled with all
of the usual emotional interactions, would often result in this sort of
feeling.</p>
<p>In that moment, this did also help me to get back into the habit of daily
meditation practice. Fortunately there&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.wakingup.com/">the Waking Up app by Sam Harris</a> which
is perfect for this. Using this, I am usually able to squeeze in a 10 minute
practice before work starts, which subjectively seems to bring a little more
equanimity into each day.</p>
<p>Looking back at this experience now, it also seems like a strong vote for
paying more attention to the daily &ldquo;done&rdquo; list.</p>
<p>Although I mostly remember to journal every day, I often forget to look at it
also from the perspective of compactly listing the little tasks that have been
completed.</p>
<p>This could be tricky when working on an amorphous project like &ldquo;design this
vague thing&rdquo;, but I think that it&rsquo;s more about the ritual of formulating and
then reviewing a small but plausible thing that is now apparently done.</p>
<p>This seems to fool the anxious parts of one&rsquo;s brain into a semblance of
temporary calm, enabling some of the other parts to get back to work.</p>
<p>This too I shall file this under <a href="/tags/101-mind-tricks">&ldquo;101 stupid but effective tricks to fool your
mind into being more useful&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. I just discovered that some part of <a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/#do-you-write-stuff-down">January-2019-Charl already did</a>.</p>
<p>P.P.S. &ldquo;Fool your mind&rdquo;, although it sounds much less awesome than &ldquo;free your
mind&rdquo;, seems to be a recurring aspect of effectively operating the human
machine.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #203: Spiritual</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 10:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</guid><description> Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&amp;rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&amp;rsquo;s magic.
Dear friends,
It brings me joy to meet you here again.
Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10 to Sunday September 6, 2020.
If I were in your shoes, I would hop skip and jump selectively over the hopefully not too unhelpfully titled headings.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="jonkershoek_magic_20200901.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&amp;rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&amp;rsquo;s magic."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&rsquo;s magic.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>It brings me joy to meet you here again.</p>
<p>Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will
attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10
to Sunday September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>If I were in your shoes, I would hop skip and jump selectively over the
hopefully not too unhelpfully titled headings.</p>
<p>In order to reduce this wall of text somewhat, I have pre-emptively moved a
sub-section or two to the next edition of the WHV.</p>
<p><em>Dear Charl of the Future,</em></p>
<p><em>You have no choice. (also no free will haha) I am writing this for you, so you
better read every last bit.</em></p>
<p><em>I am watching you.</em> 👀</p>
<h2 id="i-m-sorry-but-it-really-is-just-quite-complicated">I&rsquo;m sorry, but it really is just quite complicated</h2>
<p>I would like to kick this off with the following cartoon by Wiley Miller, which
entered my information field of view via dr topol&rsquo;s tweet stream. (don&rsquo;t worry,
this came in via my rss reader. i have not returned to twitter.)</p>








<figure><a href="science_vs_everything_else.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It is ironic that the people who get it, already got it, but that the people who
really should get it, won&rsquo;t get it.</p>
<p>As is the case with many of these efforts, i guess that the best we can hope
for is that some of those on the borders between the aforementioned two groups
might be gently encouraged to gravitate towards the light.</p>
<h3 id="the-giant-band-aid-phenomenon">the giant band-aid phenomenon</h3>
<p>Related to the cartoon above, it is quite interesting to me how often
well-meaning people desire to come up with a giant band-aid for any current
problem.</p>
<p>Climate change? Inequality? Surely if we just find a band-aid big
enough we can make the problem go away!</p>
<p>There really is no band-aid.</p>
<h2 id="on-the-minimum-unit-of-focus">On the minimum unit of focus</h2>
<p>Somewhere in week 34 i was struggling to wrap up a piece of programming work
that i had been struggling with for a few days, in-between meetings and a whole
smorgasbord of other modern interruptions.</p>
<p>Finally i decided to bust out the little focus tool that i shall not name here,
because that&rsquo;s not the point.</p>
<p>The point is rather that i created an interruption-free block of time and then
wrapped up the stupid programming problem decisively, there and then.</p>
<p>Relieved that it was finally done, I did feel stupid that it had taken me that
long to just shut off those damn interruptions.</p>
<p>The experience did remind me of the following cartoon by <a href="https://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/">the slightly
disgruntled scientist</a>. It describes <strong>extremely</strong> well how a single little
interruption can derail a whole constellation of mental models in an instant.</p>
<p>Click or tap to zoom in, or skip past if you know this:</p>








<figure><a href="ProgrammerInterrupted.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted_hu3267a53534c5d7f823d13c1b76e71025_414884_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted.png"
            

         width="30%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>I have found that the absolute minimum block of distraction-free time i need to
do reliably something worthwhile is about an hour.</p>
<p>A large part of my job is indeed handling the information that arrives via all
of the those pesky interruptions, but sometimes i wonder if there&rsquo;s not a
better way to reconcile these two facets.</p>
<p>Very much related to this phenomenon, is falling into the morning distraction
trap, something which is probably familiar to a number of you. (future charl,
you don&rsquo;t count.)</p>
<p>It goes like this: i arrive at work (or these days, i walk a few metres on from
the kitchen into the guest bedroom / home office), and then i start the day
with meetings, microsoft teams chats, and emails.</p>
<p>If I&rsquo;m not careful, I get stuck in this reactive mode, forgetting until far too
late in the day to eject from the reactive-jet for some of them juicy focus
hours.</p>
<p>#feelsbadman</p>
<p>Just this past week, I decided on Thursday and Friday to start work directly on
my main project, ignoring emails and chats and any other distractions until the
first stand-up meeting at 9:00.</p>
<p>Just priming my mind like this for slightly more than an hour was enough to
give the whole day a flavour of focus and intentionality.</p>
<p>It feels like I forget this lesson every other day.</p>
<p>How do you manage this?</p>
<h2 id="on-the-opposite-of-focus">On the opposite of focus</h2>
<p>Sort of inspired by <a href="https://youtu.be/0m3hGZvD-0s">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s deliberate scheduling of a shallow work
session</a> after the day&rsquo;s deep work, I was pleasantly surprised during a past few
evening sessions where I combined an entertaining DJ Set on the second screen
with some actual programming work on the main.</p>
<p>Somehow the fully intentional addition of distracting entertainment, and
importantly the <em>acceptance</em> that the work would necessarily be approached with
a leisurely attitude, I got a surprising amount of extra work done, and
experienced the whole session as relaxing.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to file this under &ldquo;101 stupid but effective tricks to fool your mind
into being more useful&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Let me know if you try this, or if you knew this all along and <em>that&rsquo;s</em> how you
manage everything so well!</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://lexfridman.com/podcast/">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s podcasts</a> are edifying and humanity-affirming. Try them if
you haven&rsquo;t yet.</p>
<h2 id="on-divide-and-conquer-for-the-email">On divide and conquer for the email</h2>
<p>Spontaneously in the night somewhere during the past weeks, I had the idea that
it was time to split my <a href="https://www.stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> work email account from the rest of my
email empire (which is partially also work, because vxlabs, but not my main
job).</p>
<p>I did this because the account I use to manage everything, the <a href="/tags/fastmail/">fastmail one</a>,
was becoming far too chaotic.</p>
<p>(Back in the TU Delft days, an adventure that ended now almost 7 years ago, I
also used to sport an e-mail split.)</p>
<p>My perception now is that I&rsquo;m working against the idea of the whole being
greater than the sum of the parts, i.e. the whole chaos is perhaps worse than
the two smaller chaos explosions by themselves.</p>
<p>(That&rsquo;s a pretty convoluted way to think about &ldquo;divide and conquer&rdquo;, isn&rsquo;t it?)</p>
<p>Also, the dream of being able to search through all of my email and actually
finding stuff is not being realised.</p>
<p>Email searching these days is usually a last resort, because I have a pretty
good <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">personal knowledge management system</a>. It could also be that fastmail
search is not as clever as gmail search.</p>
<p>In the weeks since I did this split (my notes tell me this happened on Friday,
August 21, 2020 at around 8:30 in the morning), I have noticed that my Stone
Three email is now under control, while my personal email is slightly out of
control, which is an improvement.</p>
<p>I have noticed that I do in fact apply a whole different mode of cognition and
context to the handling of work email than I do to personal/work-ish email.</p>
<p>A further advantage is that I can now focus on mastering the way of life that
is called Outlook. The first artifact I have to show for this is a pretty
complicated blog post in the drafts folder that shows how you can link to
arbitrary outlook items (in the latest outlook) from anywhere, in my case of
course Emacs.</p>
<h2 id="life-progress-update">Life progress update</h2>
<p>During the past several weeks, I passed a birthday.</p>
<p>As one bestie remarked, I am now just past the halfway mark, at least by one
pretty optimistic estimate of the total duration of me.</p>
<p>Anyways, moving on&hellip;</p>
<p>I took the largest part of the day off to go run the in the mountains here in my
backyard.</p>
<p>The route that I took for the first time, and which caused a considerable
amount of enjoyment, could be described by Watsonia, Baboon traverse, Leopard
Loop, Caracal, Protea, Sugarbird.</p>
<p>Making time for outdoorsy activities on your birthday: Two WHV thumbs up, would
do again.</p>
<p>Thanks to the <a href="http://www.workoutdoors.net/">WorkOutDoors Apple Watch app</a>, which I bought two years ago but
have never used, I did not get lost like I usually do when attempting trail
runs.</p>
<p>The app displays brilliant vector maps on your watch, optionally overlaid with
GPX routes supplied by generous friends.</p>
<p>After the birthday run, I use it again on more trails (see photo at start of
post) to run almost like someone who actually possesses a sense of
direction.</p>
<p>Technological augmentation FTW!</p>
<h2 id="here-s-to-a-more-regular-return">Here&rsquo;s to a more regular return</h2>
<p>Thank you for working through this mishmash with me!</p>
<p>We are now caught up until Sunday, September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>At this stage, I would have preferred to post more coherent little posts more
often, but I seem to find myself in a loop of slightly too much busyness (and
other issues), which ironically is contributing to my need to write more, but
which is taking up so much time and so many mental cycles that blog-writing
opportunities are hard to create and make use of.</p>
<p>Anyways&hellip; at least the overfull post-pipeline fence has now been cleared.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you equanimity, kindness and health.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next connection.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #197: How to ship side-projects</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 22:28:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/</guid><description> Hello friends!
Weekly Head Voices #197 looks back at the week from Monday June 1 to Sunday June 7.
Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect.
Work-work is quite high intensity at the moment.
I really would not mind a bit of respite any time soon now.
In the meantime, let me look back, and by the crazy laws of metaphysics also inwards, at the previous week:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello friends!</p>
<p>Weekly Head Voices #197 looks back at the week from Monday June 1 to Sunday June 7.</p>








<figure><a href="morgenster.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Work-work is quite high intensity at the moment.</p>
<p>I really would not mind a bit of respite any time soon now.</p>
<p>In the meantime, let me look back, and by the crazy laws of metaphysics
also inwards, at the previous week:</p>
<h2 id="on-slipping-and-shipping-a-side-project">On slipping and shipping a side-project</h2>
<p>I have <a href="/2018/05/13/weekly-head-voices-142-theory-of-mind/#the-side-project-dilemma">written</a> <a href="/2018/09/03/weekly-head-voices-152-a-small-but-highly-trained-team-of-11-year-olds/#au-revoir">before</a> about nerds and their side-projects.</p>
<p>You might recall that I said that they mostly don&rsquo;t ever see the light of day,
although they still have indirect benefits.</p>
<p>In any case, the two I linked to above both failed, so at least that&rsquo;s nice for
consistency.</p>
<p>However, on Friday I went and bucked the trend ever so slightly by
soft-launching the Lazar Focus app and website distraction blocker for Windows.</p>
<p>I <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">mentioned LF last week</a>, but it now has a website, called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">lazarfocused.com</a>,
and it has a <a href="https://gumroad.com/l/yExQgr">product page on gumroad</a>.</p>
<p>It has a <em>substantially</em> smaller number of bugs thanks to brilliant beta
testing by multi-modal medical visualization expert and productivity app
<em>connoisseuse</em> <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/">Noeska</a>.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re on Windows, this is exactly the little app you need to block
distractions, only when you say so of course, so that you can focus on all of
The Important Stuff™ you undoubtedly would rather get done, so that you
can get back to goofing off.</p>
<p>AMIRITE?!</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re one of those people who don&rsquo;t need any help to help focusing and to
stay in the zone, but you work with people who might, the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/06/06/the-philosophy-behind-lazar-focus/">philosophy behind
Lazar Focus</a> blog post is a good introduction to share with them. (Also, could I
interview you? :)</p>
<h2 id="dry-january-finally-ends--or-maybe-not--with-rochefort">Dry January finally ends (or maybe not) with Rochefort</h2>
<p>This year, I <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">started Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) on January 6</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m happy to report that this was interrupted only once for a superb glass of
my favourite Chardonnay (that&rsquo;s the Haskell Anvil, see <a href="/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/#what-i-did-in-week-41">WHV #181</a> for the first
encounter) with besties, right at the source.</p>
<p>Other than that, I remained in EAZ until Saturday, June 6, when the St
Bernhardus Abt 12 and the Trappistes Rochefort #8 and #10 that a friend had
brought for me all the way from The Netherlands and that had been waiting
patiently for me in the cupboard, had just been sitting there waiting for long
enough.</p>
<p>(By the way, the St Bernhardus Abt 12 is a taste clone of the Westvleteren, the
pretty expensive king of the Trappist beers, as a drunk gentleman once
explained to me in the Doerak in Delft late one evening. He was right, as my
companion and I subsequently confirmed when we acquired both beers for a
comparative tasting on the spot.)</p>
<p>The time, but far more pertinently the opportunity, had come to end (or was it
merely to interrupt&hellip;) EAZ 2020.</p>
<p>Friends, that Rochefort is simply packed with a multitude of sweet, warm
memories of days and evenings in my other home, with my other family.</p>








<figure><a href="rochefort_8_action_shot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Just in case you needed reminding, the Rochefort 8 looks like this. Memories of a lifetime not pictured."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Just in case you needed reminding, the Rochefort 8 looks like this. Memories of a lifetime not pictured.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>(Going even further back, I have <a href="/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/">mentioned before</a> that this blog contains <a href="/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/">a
written record of my very first encounter with Rochefort</a>, all the way back in
2003, right in the town of La Roche-en-Ardenna, about 30 minutes away from
Rochefort itself. Reading that post now, it really was a sort of WHV avant la
lettre!)</p>
<h2 id="the-last-bit">The last bit</h2>
<p>Ok folks, it is now 22:17 on Thursday evening, and I&rsquo;m at that super difficult
&ldquo;HOW IN THOR&rsquo;S NAME DO I CONCLUDE THIS THING?!&quot;-stage, a problem which I seem
to be solving with the &ldquo;I KNOW LET&rsquo;S BREAK THE FOURTH WALL / SIMPLY TALK
ABOUT HOW WE DON&rsquo;T KNOW HOW TO END THIS THING&rdquo;-manoeuvre.</p>
<p>On the bright side, I think we did <em>just</em> make the deadline with this edition
of the WHV, narrowly avoiding postponement and a larger-than-normal next post.</p>
<p>Have a brilliant rest of the week and weekend. I look forward to seeing you
again, here and anywhere!</p>
<p>P.S. I still don&rsquo;t know how to ship side-projects.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #196: Get focused</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 22:27:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</guid><description> Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&amp;rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&amp;rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&amp;rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.
Well hello there folks, please make yourself at home!
This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday May 18 to Sunday May 31 of the extremely strange year of 2020.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="sylvia_draws_family_20200531.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_huca2519a06503f1c6214cd27e29fdc471_13081135_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&amp;rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&amp;rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&amp;rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there folks, please make yourself at home!</p>
<p>This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday May 18 to Sunday May 31 of the
extremely strange year of 2020.</p>
<p>That effort of looking back has resulted in the following three items.</p>
<h2 id="when-building-automatic-analysis-pipelines-get-your-batch-accuracy-testing-up-as-soon-as-you-can">When building automatic analysis pipelines, get your batch accuracy testing up as soon as you can</h2>
<p>A substantial part of my work hours these past two weeks went into working on a
automatic medical image analysis pipeline, with machine learning
inside™. (I mean &ldquo;AI&rdquo;, of course. And drones.)</p>
<p>I really do love this stuff, but sometimes it ends up coming down to putting
your head down and keeping it down, in order to grind out every percent or two
in improved accuracy.</p>
<p>The tip I wanted to offer here is the following: Even when you think your
pipeline is way too far from &ldquo;done&rdquo;™, get your batch accuracy testing up
and running.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a double whammy:</p>
<ol>
<li>You and your team get early and regular feedback on how your performance is
going.</li>
<li>You are forced to have the whole concept working from end-to-end. It can be
surprising how many little issues you still need to solve, and running into
them sooner rather than later is only good.</li>
</ol>
<p>By the way, the practical machine learning icon <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew%5FNg">Professor Andrew Ng&rsquo;s</a> free book
<a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/machine-learning-yearning/">Machine Learning Yearning</a> is filled to the brim with practical tips for
implementing ML in practice.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">Lazar Focus: The super tiny Windows app and website distraction blocker that you&rsquo;ve always wanted</h2>
<p>Back at the <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">start of 2018 I wrote the following about the macOS app and website
distraction blocker called Focus</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>After years of resisting these types of software tools due to my belief that I
should simply apply more grit and will power to squeeze out more focus hours,
I finally broke down and purchased the macOS app called Focus. You click its
pretty icon, and then your computer goes into focus mode: The Mail application
and a bunch of other non-focus-related apps all get killed, and a bunch of
websites (reddit, youtube, work chat, etc) are blocked for a user-configurable
block of time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even if you skipped that extract, please read the following one about the
<em>idea</em> behind such a focus app:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It usually takes a single moment of weakness for a distraction to terminate a
valuable block of focus. It takes a single moment of strength for this tool to
start a valuable block of focus.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Anyways, I was really missing this functionality on Windows, and so I busted
out my trusty <a href="https://www.lazarus-ide.org/">Lazarus IDE</a> (who <em>didn&rsquo;t</em> make apps back in the day with the old
win32 Delphi?!) and figured out the various required Windows APIs to create
this brand new super tiny but super effective app and website blocker:</p>








<figure><a href="lazar_focused_screenshot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hue09d8364f67da37dd1b1e7072b20e694_168782_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As shown in the screenshot, it&rsquo;s sitting at 5 MB of memory use. In the age of
Electron apps, that&rsquo;s really small.</p>
<p>When you activate focus mode, it&rsquo;ll prevent your browser (Chrome, Brave,
Firefox or Edge) from viewing any distracting website (you get to configure the
list) by redirecting to a local web page with an inspiring quote, e.g.:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Concentration can be cultivated. One can learn to exercise willpower,
discipline one&rsquo;s body and train one&rsquo;s mind. &ndash; Anil Ambani</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It will also terminate any distracting apps, and helpfully prevent you from
starting them up during your focus session.</p>
<p>The convenient progress bar shows how far you are on your way to a 25 minute
pomodoro, but that is purely for motivation, and not enforced.</p>
<p>The total focus blocks and hours at the top should also help to keep us
motivated and&hellip; <strong>LAZAR FOCUSED!</strong></p>
<p>So, because there are probably (hopefully?) at least two other people who&rsquo;ll
find this as useful as I do, and because shipping and selling software that you
made yourself is awesome especially when it&rsquo;s a hobby project, I have decided
to try and sell Lazar Focus using something like <a href="https://gumroad.com/">gumroad</a>.</p>
<p>Hopefully soon with a hobby hour or three I can finish the installer and the
website, and then make the beta available at a reduced rate.</p>
<p>Because I prefer it for apps like this when I am the buyer, I have decided to
make it available as a one-time purchase, no eval but money-back, with
time-limited upgrades (probably a year?), but with your last licensed version
obviously remaining fully functional until the end of The Windows API.</p>
<h2 id="art-fun-with-portrait-ai">Art fun with Portrait AI</h2>
<p>Ever since I spent a bit of time better curating my twitter subscriptions,
getting rid of the vitriol and adding much more STEM (shout out to <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Eric Topol</a>
&ndash; you could install twitter <em>just</em> for him and you would be great), they often
bring me shiny treasures.</p>
<p>Recently, it was <a href="https://portraitai.com/">portraitai.com</a> which brought a great deal of mirth to my home
as we made authentic looking portraits of each other. (We&rsquo;re just a bunch of
silly primates with amazing gadgets.)</p>
<p>It didn&rsquo;t seem to work all that well on me however, until I started pulling
funny faces:</p>








<figure><a href="charl_portraitai.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu52de41eab52d80ae9174daa293863901_294774_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>With that, dear friends, I bid you kindness, happiness and health.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #193: COVID-19 part 3.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2020 15:33:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/</guid><description> Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.
The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12 to Sunday May 2.
This post has a strong nerd flavour. If that is not your inclination, please use the table of contents (to your right) to navigate to the bits that you do find interesting.
If you&amp;rsquo;re in a rush, and can only select one section, I would recommend the one on Niklas Luhmann.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/stilbaai-preekstoel-panorama_hu73502fd35e27f9d31902eaf7617a9c24_1947631_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another Stilbaai beach scene, this time in panaroma format, taken a day before the SA lockdown.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!--
2020-05-02 21:38 Boiler Room Solomun 2015 playing on the second screen while
I'm typing this.  I was hoping to understand why this has 43M views, and my
favourite boiler room of all time, Maceo Plex in Berlin in 2015, has "only"
11M.

Let me know in the comments if you read this. :)
-->
<p>The Weekly Head Voices #193 looks back at the three weeks from Monday April 12
to Sunday May 2.</p>
<p>This post has a strong nerd flavour. If that is not your inclination, please
use the table of contents (to your right) to navigate to the bits that you do
find interesting.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re in a rush, and can only select one section, I would recommend <a href="#the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">the
one on Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Have fun!</p>
<h2 id="covid-19-status-update">COVID-19 status update</h2>
<p>On Friday, May 1, <a href="https://www.businessinsider.co.za/lockdown-level-4-what-is-now-allowed-2020-4">the South African lockdown was slightly lifted from level 5
to level
4</a>.</p>
<p>This means that a part of the workforce will start returning to work, and that
citizens are allowed slightly more freedom of movement.</p>
<p>If safety had been the only requirement, we should probably have had to
continue with level 5 for a while longer, but that darned economy unfortunately
also has to be kept afloat.</p>
<p>In spite of this, I was super pleased to read the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Masks are obligatory.</strong> Everyone has to wear cloth face masks outside their
homes. If you don&rsquo;t yet have a cloth mask, you can wear a scarf or a t-shirt
wrapped around your mouth and nose, says Dlamini-Zuma.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This might end up being the thing that gets us through this in something that
resembles one piece.</p>
<p>The second announcement I was super happy with, was that we would be allowed
outside for exercise between 6 and 9 in the mornings.</p>
<p>So on Saturday morning I went out for my first post-level-5 run, ON THE
OUTSIDE. (It does feel strange going out on the street for the first time in
five weeks.)</p>
<p>The majority of people I saw actually had some form of face mask going on.</p>
<p>I had expected otherwise, because doing cardiorespiratory exercise with a mask
on is not easy, and people can be stubborn.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/advanced/a20842404/product-review-buff-headwear/">Buffs</a>
are these fantastically useful &ldquo;seamless tubular garments made from
high-performance microfibre&rdquo; that many runners swear by.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out you can <em>also</em> use them as as-running-proof-as-possible face
masks:</p>








<figure><a href="cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask_hu815c169f7dc006fef835eddef66e09fe_118854_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/cpbotha_running_with_buff_mask.jpg"
            

         width="240"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>Pro-tip: If there&rsquo;s a runner in your life, and you&rsquo;re on the lookout for a
gift, just get them a buff. You can <em>never</em> have too many buffs.</p>
<h2 id="gou-2-is-10">GOU #2 is 10</h2>
<p>My most favourite middle child in the whole world recently hit the double
digits, and she was suitably chuffed with this.</p>
<p>It must be strange experiencing your 10th birthday under these truly surreal
conditions.</p>
<p>On the other hand, when you&rsquo;re 10, you probably don&rsquo;t dwell on thoughts like
that for too long.</p>
<h2 id="miscellaneous-catch-up">Miscellaneous catch-up</h2>
<p>In the past weeks, I wrote a number of other blog posts, started a new blog,
and discovered an obscure but fantastic new blogging tool.</p>
<p>Oh, and my expensive ergonomic keyboard broke.</p>
<h3 id="fantastic-blogging-tools-and-where-to-find-them">Fantastic blogging tools and where to find them</h3>
<p>It all started when I finally got around to exploring
<a href="https://ox-hugo.scripter.co/">ox-hugo</a>, the Emacs package for writing Hugo
posts using Org mode.</p>
<p>You might not recall this, but the mere <em>existence</em> of <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/#build-and-upload-the-new-static-hotness">ox-hugo was the reason
I chose
Hugo</a>
when it was time to leave Wordpress behind.</p>
<!--
Hey there friends reading these hidden messages!

There are multiple explicit and implicit streams of connection running through
these channels and it's lovely.

Anyways, it is now 22:44 and I finished the Solomun boiler room set.

There are indeed so many stories happening in those frames, many of which will
only become apparent after more viewings.

I'm now back to the Maceo Plex set, with a smile of recognition on my face.
-->
<p>Well, it turns out that, <em>if</em> you&rsquo;re an Emacs Org mode user, ox-hugo is pretty
close to blogging nirvana.</p>
<p>In the past few days, I&rsquo;ve used it to turn arbitrary Org mode entries from my
month journal into blog posts, to send the exact same Org mode file to two
different blogs with different sets of title and metadata, and to assert
Neo-in-the-matrix-style control over what goes where and how.</p>
<p>If I have to put my finger on the core of ox-hugo&rsquo;s extreme utility, I would
say that <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi">Kaushal Modi</a>, the brains behind
ox-hugo, has managed to create a perfect coupling between Org mode on the one
hand and Hugo on the other, a coupling that maximally leverages the strengths
of each.</p>
<p>(I will probably be writing more about this, but &hellip; elsewhere. <em>[queue
suspenseful music here]</em>)</p>
<h3 id="other-mostly-very-nerdy-blog-posts">Other mostly very nerdy blog posts</h3>
<p>As part of the ox-hugo investigation, I had to figure out how to <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/04/26/cite-consistently-between-org-ref-and-ox-hugo/">cite
consistently between straight Org mode and
ox-hugo</a>
for automatic bibtex-backed bibliographies.</p>
<p>Inspired by friend <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2020/04/28/voice-capture-org-tasks-on-android/">Stéfan&rsquo;s post on voice capturing and automatically
transcribing notes to Org
mode</a>,
I figured out how to <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/2020/04/30/voice-capture-org-mode-notes-and-more-using-siri-shortcuts-on-ios/">do the same on iOS and wrote it all
up</a>.</p>
<p>If you clicked on that second link, you will have discovered my brand new blog,
the hopefully catchily titled <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">Org Mode
Exocortex</a>. I will be posting <em>ultra</em>-nerdy Emacs
Org mode content over there.</p>
<p>(Friend Stéfan is the very first guest blogger, with a re-post of his Android
speech recognition post linked above. BTW, that was my first guest blogging
experience ever. Life for the Z-list blogger does not move fast.)</p>
<p>Finally, also thanks to ox-hugo&rsquo;s motivation, I figured (haha, now I see what I
did there) out how to make and publish a new <a href="/2020/05/02/drop-in-replacement-for-hugo-figure-shortcode-with-responsive-img-srcset/"><code>figure</code> shortcode for Hugo that
automatically resizes images and gets your browser to download only the best
one</a>!</p>
<h3 id="microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-desktop-at-4-years-rip">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic Desktop at 4 years: RIP</h3>
<p>After all of that good news, I do have to report the following not-so-great news:</p>
<p>After just under four years of approximately one half of my typing, the
<a href="/2016/05/22/weekly-head-voices-107-balance/">Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboard I welcomed into my home at the start of
May of 2016</a>, has developed a key
failure.</p>
<p>More specifically, the physical &ldquo;G&rdquo;, which is my &ldquo;I&rdquo; (thanks
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dvorak_keyboard_layout">Dvorak</a>), fails about
30% of the time, with that duty cycle slowly growing.</p>
<p>(You may bring your jokes about why specifically the &ldquo;I&rdquo; is failing first to
the comment section below!)</p>
<p>I opened up the keyboard following <a href="http://emmanuelcontreras.com/how-to/how-to-disassemble-microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-keyboard-and-make-it-wired/">the instructions and photos of Emmanuel
Contreras</a>.</p>
<p>(What I can add to Contreras&rsquo;s information, is that the palm rest is held fast
by no less than 12 little screws, some odd-sized. Pro-tip: When you remove all
of these, put them down in the same pattern as the holes, so that you can get
them back in later.)</p>
<p>However, one unfortunately ends up at the metal backing which is attached to
the top-plate with about 30 or more plastic pop-rivet like mechanisms.</p>
<p>Information online also seems to indicate that once a single key goes, you have
to replace the whole board.</p>
<p>Some more searching brought me to <a href="https://youtu.be/x09inK8-G1Y">this obscure but helpful YouTube
review</a> where Kevin explains that although
everyone at his company loved the keyboard, they had simply accepted it as part
of their business expense to replace them every 6 months to a year.</p>
<p>If you search through <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Microsoft-Ergonomic-Keyboard-Business-5KV-00001/product-reviews/B00CYX26BC/ref=cm_cr_arp_d_viewopt_kywd?pageNumber=1&amp;filterByKeyword=durability">the Amazon reviews for
&ldquo;durability&rdquo;</a>,
it really starts to look like a case of a fantastic keyboard marred by issues
with its durability.</p>
<p>However, if you need a relatively affordable &ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; keyboard, where with
&ldquo;ergonomic&rdquo; I mean shaped in such a way that your wrists get to stay more or
less straight while typing, with really great feel and low-impact typing, the
Sculpt comes out on top.</p>
<p>Although it goes against my grain, I should probably be happy with the above
average 4 years that this one managed, and start finding a local source for its
inevitable replacement.</p>
<p>Nerds in the audience: I am very curious to hear about your keyboard
preferences in the comments. Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="two-lessons-learnt-from-how-to-take-smart-notes">Two lessons learnt from How to Take Smart Notes</h2>
<p>On March 31 I quickly read through <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/34507927-how-to-take-smart-notes">Sönke Ahrens&rsquo;s book, How to Take Smart
Notes</a>.</p>
<p>(The full title is actually &ldquo;How to Take Smart Notes: One Simple Technique to
Boost Writing, Learning and Thinking &ndash; for Students, Academics and Nonfiction
Book Writers&rdquo;)</p>
<h3 id="the-most-portable-cross-platform-ebook-format-with-self-contained-annotations-is">The most portable cross-platform ebook format with self-contained annotations is&hellip;</h3>
<p>I bought the Kindle book on Amazon, because that&rsquo;s how I&rsquo;ve been doing it for
years.</p>
<p>However, although I prefer reading novels on my Kindle e-Ink device, for
reference works it&rsquo;s a deal breaker that my highlights and notes are not in a
standards compliant format that integrates nicely with <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing personal
knowledge management system</a>.</p>
<p>My goal was to find an alternative format for these books with the following features:</p>
<ul>
<li>Before you answer PDF, which I use extensively for academic papers, typeset
books, and many other things: The alternative format should be fully
reflowable, like the source Kindle book.</li>
<li>Readable and annotations editable on all my non-Kindle devices (Windows,
Linux, macOS, iOS).</li>
<li>Most importantly: Flexible annotations, including at least highlighting and
positional notes, that are stored within the file itself, so they can never
be lost.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t expect this to be too much of a challenge.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<p>After a number of hours spent spelunking down a number of different
rabbit-holes, with epub3 being the greatest disappointment (the spec has all
the features, but the implementations largely lack good annotation support), I
ended up in a place where you probably would not expect to find me&hellip;</p>
<p>Dear readers, the best format that satisfies all requirements above
is&hellip; <code>&lt;FRITS_DRUMROLL /&gt;</code> &hellip; <strong>Microsoft DOCX</strong>!</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been DeDRM&rsquo;ing (google it) the Kindle reference books I
purchase in order to be able to read and annotate them across all my platforms.</p>
<p>For this, the iPad is pretty great.</p>
<p>Once read, the DOCX files, including all of the annotations I made, are stored
in the correct place in my synchronised file hierarchy, and are fully
searchable and accessible with standard tools.</p>
<h3 id="the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">The amazing Niklas Luhmann and his Zettelkasten</h3>
<p>The book itself, <em>How to Take Smart Notes</em>, spends well-deserved time on the
phenomenon that was the prodigiously productive German sociologist Professor
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niklas_Luhmann">Niklas Luhmann</a>.</p>
<p>Over his career, Prof. Luhmann wrote more than 70 books and published almost
400 research articles.</p>
<p>He made a massive impact on the world of sociology and systems theory.</p>
<p>When asked in <a href="https://www.uni-bielefeld.de/soz/luhmann-archiv/pdf/jschmidt_zettelkasten-als-uberraschungsgenerator.pdf">a 1997
interview</a>
how he managed to this productive, he answered:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Ich denke ja nicht alles allein, sondern das
geschieht weitgehend im Zettelkasten. [&hellip;]
Meine Produktivität ist im wesentlichen aus dem
Zettelkasten-System zu erklären. [&hellip;]
Der Zettelkasten kostet mich mehr Zeit als das
Bücherschreiben</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Translated this is probably something like (German readers, help me out here
please):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think everything by myself, but that largely happens in the slip box. [&hellip;]
My productivity is essentially due to that slipbox system. [..]
The slipbox costs me more time than that writing books</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <em>zettelkasten</em> he referred to were quite simply a set of wooden slipboxes,
in which he could store pieces of paper (the &ldquo;slips&rdquo;), each of which had a
single idea written on it.</p>
<p>It looked more or less exactly like this:</p>








<figure><a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu61195ac08eb6003207b1b95bfe6dfa0b_91461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu61195ac08eb6003207b1b95bfe6dfa0b_91461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/zettelkasten_hu61195ac08eb6003207b1b95bfe6dfa0b_91461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Photo of Luhmann&amp;rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Photo of Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten. Click to go to the fully online Niklas Luhmann-Archiv.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Over the course of his career, he managed to write about 90000 (yes, ninety
thousand) of these notes, all of which you can now <a href="https://niklas-luhmann-archiv.de/">browse online at the Niklas
Luhmann-Archiv</a>.</p>
<p>Importantly, he had come up with an ingenious numbering system for linking each
new note to its chain of predecessors, and also to other related chains
anywhere in the zettelkasten.</p>
<p>When it was time to write a book or a paper, he would dive into his this
collection, and then take a stroll through his amazing web of interlinked
thoughts, some of them having matured for years.</p>
<p>Putting together the publication became an exercise in harvesting index cards
from his slipboxes, instead of a positively intimidating mountain of writing,
thinking and rewriting.</p>
<p>This is such a boss-level example of the principle of
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/compounding/">compounding</a>, and one which is
definitely worth trying to follow.</p>
<p>Since reading Ahrens&rsquo;s book, I have started extending <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">my existing note-taking
universe</a> to be more Zettelkasten-like,
when appropriate.</p>
<p>Org mode is a great basis for this, and packages like
<a href="https://github.com/jethrokuan/org-roam">org-roam</a> help us to get closer to our
90-thousand-notes-dreams.</p>
<p>On a higher level, I have been thinking and writing a great deal about how to
merge effectively the Zettelkasten one-idea-per-note approach into the full
spectrum of writing complexity that Org mode supports.</p>
<p>It is important to be mindful of the <em>mode</em> of documentation that you need to
apply at any give point.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about the Luhmann&rsquo;s Zettelkasten, <a href="https://writingcooperative.com/zettelkasten-how-one-german-scholar-was-so-freakishly-productive-997e4e0ca125">this Writing
Cooperative article in
English</a>
and <a href="https://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Missing-Link-Luhmanns-Denkmaschine-endlich-im-Netz-4364512.html">this Heise article in
German</a>
are a great start.</p>
<p>This might not be the last time that you&rsquo;ll hear me talking about Luhmann and
his Zettelkasten.</p>
<h2 id="uitzwaaien">Uitzwaaien</h2>
<p>Thank you friends for reading this and connecting with me here!</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #185: Starship GOU #1.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 22:35:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</guid><description> Welcome back friends!
It&amp;rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.
Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file two weeks ago, but then I didn&amp;rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).
In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more
precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.</p>
<p>Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file
two weeks ago, but then I didn&rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then
everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).</p>
<p>In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time
right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look
back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view from a Friday afternoon arrival run along the Langebaan Lagoon in the West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="lecturing-old-school">Lecturing, old school.</h2>
<p>On Thursday, November 21, I gave a two hour lecture titled &ldquo;IoMT in Healthcare
Innovation&rdquo; at the <a href="https://www.usb.ac.za/">University of Stellenbosch Business
School</a>.</p>
<p>IoMT expands to the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/bernardmarr/2018/01/25/why-the-internet-of-medical-things-iomt-will-start-to-transform-healthcare-in-2018/#46f18c694a3c">&ldquo;Internet of Medical
Things&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>My knowledge of IoT is spotty, and before giving this lecture I didn&rsquo;t even
know that the term &ldquo;IoMT&rdquo; existed.</p>
<p>Fortunately, it turns out that a lot of what we&rsquo;re currently doing at Stone
Three Healthcare (connecting patients with specialist care through
diagnostic-grade streaming of auscultation (and soon other modalities) device
data) can in fact be classified as IoMT.</p>
<p>Phew.</p>
<p>I would like to make the following observations based on this experience:</p>
<ol>
<li>I still really love getting up in front of a group of people to present
something. There are so many things that could go wrong, but when they go
right, the experience is great.</li>
<li>A two hour lecture is quite long, for both the students, even when they&rsquo;re
as advanced as this, <em>and</em> for the lecturer, especially when he is as out of
practice as this.
<ul>
<li>If there&rsquo;s a next time, I will either insert my own 15 minute break, or I
will get the class to break out into some sort of topic-strengthening
activity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I had somehow forgotten how much time lecture preparation could take up,
even when you just had to present your own day-to-day reality.
<ul>
<li>BIG UP TO THE LECTURERS IN THE WHV AUDIENCE!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="productivity-system-tuneup">Productivity system tuneup.</h2>
<p>Last Sunday morning, as the family took a last swim at Kraalbaai before we had
to return home, I tried to apply some serious thinking (well, I did this by
stringing together a series of normal thinking moments) to the problem of
increasing my efficiency and focus at work.</p>
<p>At that moment, the scenery outside looked like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view of the Preekstoel from Kraalbaai beach, West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Regular readers will know that coming up with new ways to increase and maintain
focus is a life-long endeavour, which my subconscious self enjoys inventing
interesting new ways to subvert.</p>
<p>Conscious me has made peace with the fact that it has no choice but to keep on
working at its end of the bargain, until the very end.</p>
<p>With the opposing forces involved, my focus seems to oscillate with varying
frequencies between terrible and not too bad.</p>
<p>Anyways, having had a few days of fresh air and majestic scenery to jog the
neural circuitry, I applied myself, again, to the problem at hand.</p>
<p>I thought that sketching could help, so I was scribbling using a rather
impressive electronic pencil-analogue on a glass screen.</p>
<p>After several focused minutes (SEVERAL MINUTES, I TELL YOU!), I had a mindmap
with &ldquo;increase efficiency&rdquo; in a little oval at the center, arrows pointing
outwards into three terribly familiar habits, each in a rectangle <em>this</em> time,
and finally more connecting lines to lists of pretty plausible sounding reasons
for the three well-known habits.</p>
<p>The three rectangles were:</p>
<ol>
<li>Morning planning.</li>
<li>Inbox 0.</li>
<li>Pomodoro always.</li>
</ol>
<p>Over the years, these three items have made pretty regular appearances, in
various different forms, on this blog.</p>
<p>(I laughed when I just looked up <a href="/2010/09/20/an-indecent-proposal-weekly-head-voices-31/">this old 2010
post</a> and found a
pretty effective focus technique in the comments.)</p>
<p>Anyways, although the little thinking and drawing session documented here
seemingly did not result in any new revelations, the act of going through the
whole thought process, and documenting the results (again), seemed to have
contributed to a pretty great week in terms of focus.</p>
<p>I wrote down a little mantra for myself (definitely not fit for publication),
weaving together the three points above and the reasoning behind them, almost
like the affirmation in Wreckit Ralph&rsquo;s bad guy support group:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m bad, and that&rsquo;s good. I will never be good, and that&rsquo;s not bad. There&rsquo;s
no one I&rsquo;d rather be than me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have <em>chosen</em>
to take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having <em>decided</em>
to <em>commit</em>, i.e. active.</p>
<p>My humble focus mantra is following in this tradition.</p>
<p>(I really hope that my subversive sub-conscious is not paying attention right
now&hellip;)</p>
<h2 id="starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">Starship GOU #1, taxiing on the runway.</h2>
<p>Wednesday, December 4, was officially <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU
#1&rsquo;s</a> last day of primary school.</p>
<p>Although she seemed to navigate this emotional event with her customary
even-keeled demeanour, some of the moments were really just too big to let go by
without a good cry or two.</p>
<p>I was also happy to observe the level of retrospection and sunny candour she
applied to her informal post hoc analyses of above-mentioned crying moments.</p>
<p>I really hope that she strengthens and maintains this important human ability.</p>
<p>From our perspective as parents, it feels like the stakes are being raised
quite significantly.</p>
<p>The thing is, our oldest is now quite obviously becoming an adult.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like that scene at the end of the brilliant 2015 movie <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2096673/">Inside
Out</a>, where the protagonist&rsquo;s brain
console is suddenly upgraded to one with at least 9000 new knobs and dials.</p>
<p>Up to now, we (the parents) were GOU #1&rsquo;s only control system.</p>
<p>Now it is becoming quite clear that she is increasingly forming her own
opinions, and making her own decisions.</p>
<p>In most cases, the physical constraints of a 13 year old living in her parent&rsquo;s
house still afford us some level of control.</p>
<p>However, relying on that would be missing the point entirely.</p>
<p>You see, we find ourselves in the moment of truth, when the past 13 years of
mostly gentle programming has to start executing all by itself.</p>
<p>Our little GOU #1, our first co-created human intelligence, is preparing to go
out into the world.</p>
<p>She has not taken off yet, so we do our best to apply the final touches to her
already promising software.</p>
<p>We exhort her regularly: <em>Be useful. Use your (rational) brain. Be kind. Find
the kindness in others.</em></p>
<p>In the darkness, when we are at our weakest, stripped down to our core, we do
what all parents do:</p>
<p>We worry, and we hope with a passion, the intensity of which it is difficult to
describe, that our offspring units do manage to <a href="/2012/03/04/rhythm-of-the-night-weekly-head-voices-66/#life-philosophy-that-works">generate their own motivation,
to manufacture meaning, and to create
love</a>.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
This could be a runway, but it is the entrance to Vergelegen Wine Estate. At
this point, I was in fact running on this way.
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #171: ICEMiRB.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 22:38:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/</guid><description> Down here, you never know what sort of fantastic beasts you could run into. I met this particular fullmetal creature right about here.
Dear friends,
In this post, I do a particularly lossy review of my trip through time, from Monday May 6 to Sunday May 19, 2019.
First we talk about sleep, then a long part on technical tricks, then a slightly more backyard philosophical piece on human tool sharpening, and finally the announcement of a new academic event somewhere in the far or near or medium term future.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="fullmetal_baboon.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
<p>Down here, you never know what sort of fantastic beasts you could run into. I
met this particular fullmetal creature <a
href="https://goo.gl/maps/KpcQGa6hEcbd87mF7">right about here</a>.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>In this post, I do a particularly lossy review of my trip through time, from
Monday May 6 to Sunday May 19, 2019.</p>
<p>First we talk about sleep, then a long part on technical tricks, then a
slightly more backyard philosophical piece on human tool sharpening, and
finally the announcement of a new academic event somewhere in the far or near
or medium term future.</p>
<h1 id="sleep">Sleep.</h1>
<p>If you were one of the people who found themselves in my company for more than
about 10 nanoseconds during the past weeks, I probably tried to get you to
listen to <a href="/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/#the-easiest-but-most-high-impact-measure-you-can-take-to-not-die-too-soon-go-to-bed-on-time">the 6-hour long podcast between Peter Attia and Matthew Walker on
the topic of
sleep</a>.</p>
<p>Usually I&rsquo;m able to get something sufficiently out of my system by writing
about here. I do this quite deliberately to try and spare my innocent
bystanders.</p>
<p>This time, either it didn&rsquo;t really help, or I underestimate how much I would
have blabbed about it had I not let off some of the sleep steam here.</p>
<p>IN ANY CASE&hellip;</p>
<p>During the past weeks I have been paying more attention than usual to sleep, in
terms of quality, quantity and consistency.</p>
<p>Because I also decided to take more notes than usual during the day, I could
see quite acutely the effects of good sleep vs bad sleep on my performance and
energy levels the next day.</p>
<p>If sleep was good the night before, my exercise the next day seemed to take
much less effort, I still seemed to have more than enough energy at the end of
the afternoon, and, most importantly, I had almost no trouble with that
ever-important f-word:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>FOCUS.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Conversely, if I let sleep-onset slip by as little as half an hour, my brain
would be in three thousand pieces by three &lsquo;o clock the next afternoon.</p>
<p>It is starting to dawn on me that all of those evenings where I tried to borrow
an hour or even two from my sleep had a far greater cost the day after than I
ever realised.</p>
<p><strong>I can only conclude, that to experience the highest quality and intensity
waking hours, one simply has no choice but to pay the full 33% sleep tax.</strong></p>
<h2 id="damnit-coffee">Damnit coffee.</h2>
<p>Caffeine has a quarter life of 12 hours.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re positively buzzing at 1PM, 25% of that caffeine is still active in
your system at 1AM and absolutely will interfere with your sleep quality.</p>
<p>I have compromised by having my last shot before lunch, or in extreme cases
right after.</p>
<h1 id="til-things-i-learned">TIL: Things I learned.</h1>
<p>This WHV is one week late, because it seemed like nothing happened in the first week.</p>
<p>However, it seems I did learn quite few new technical tricks. In the
subsections below, I share a selection of these with you.</p>
<h2 id="remarkjs-is-great-for-quickly-building-technical-presentations">remarkjs is great for quickly building technical presentations.</h2>
<p>At <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Helderberg-Software-Developers-and-Entrepreneurs/">my favourite local
meetup</a>,
I was planning to give a talk on <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a>, the static website
generator which is powering this site, and which I&rsquo;m increasingly using instead
of wordpress.</p>
<p>Because every new project is an opportunity to check and perhaps upgrade one&rsquo;s
tools (see below for how this can also sometimes backfire), I set aside the
trusty <a href="https://revealjs.com/">reveal.js</a> and <a href="https://github.com/yjwen/org-reveal">ox-reveal Emacs orgmode
interface</a> I usually bust out, and paddled
out onto rough internet seas, on the lookout for an alternative solution.</p>
<p>(Now that I think back, I had no good reason to search for an alternative,
except that my pre-configured reveal.js style and formatting never made me
really happy.)</p>
<p>Fortunately, after not too long I ran into <a href="https://remarkjs.com">remark</a>, an
HTML- and markdown-based presentation tool that seems simpler than reveal, but
still quite attractive, as you&rsquo;ll be able to see on the demo site above.</p>
<p>At this point, I was pleasantly surprised that this distraction had not cost
more than about 30 minutes.</p>
<p>At least, that <em>was</em> the case until I ran into <a href="https://github.com/torgeir/remark-mode.el">remark-mode for
Emacs</a>!</p>
<p>As you can see from the screenshot, this enables a pretty smooth
generate-as-you-type workflow.</p>
<p>Also noteworthy, is the great built-in presenter mode. Press <code>C</code> to clone the
window into a new linked presentation which you can move off to the external
display, and then press <code>P</code> to switch to presenter mode where you can see all
of the comments you have left in the markdown.</p>
<p>I made two small fixes in <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/remark-mode.el">my own
fork</a> to enable seeding with your
own HTML template, and to enable the generate-as-you-type to work also on
straight <code>.md</code> files. I prefer keeping my presentations as <code>.md</code> (vs <code>.remark</code>)
as most of the search logic I have built in Emacs assumes <code>.org</code> and <code>.md</code>
files for my notes.</p>
<p>By choosing remarkjs instead of my existing revealjs workflow I did manage to
exhaust the short block of time I had allocated to prepare for the talk, and so
the talk morphed into a more spontaneous affair, dealing with orgmode, remarkjs
and in the end, also a bit of hugo.</p>
<h2 id="pybtex-is-a-pure-python-bibtex-parser-and-renderer">pybtex is a pure-Python bibtex parser and renderer.</h2>
<p>One of the sites getting the wordpress-to-hugo upgrade treatment was my
internet persona placeholder, the almost completely unknown
<a href="https://charlbotha.com/">charlbotha.com</a>.</p>
<p>The upgrade of this tiny site would have gone quite easily, were it not for the
fact that I was using the wordpress papercite plugin to publish a list of all
of the publications, including fulltexts in most cases, that I&rsquo;ve had the
pleasure to be involved in over the years.</p>
<p>I could not find any tool which could give me exactly the sort of publication
lists that papercite was able to.</p>
<p>To me it was clear that yet another tool was required. (&ldquo;my god, it&rsquo;s full of biases!&rdquo;)</p>
<p>Fortunately, <a href="https://mentat.za.net">@stefanvdwalt</a> very quickly pointed me at
the Python package <a href="https://pybtex.org">pybtex</a> when he saw that I was
careening off into the dark side with <a href="https://citation.js.org">citation.js</a>.</p>
<p>A few hours later I had built a script which was able to eat my
Zotero-generated bibtex file and spit out different lists of publications with
linked PDFs straight into a Hugo-edible markdown file.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://charlbotha.com/publications/">charlbotha.com/publications</a> for the
result.</p>
<p>P.S. Making it available to a broader audience is on my todo-list.</p>
<h2 id="asciidoc-is-one-of-your-best-choices-to-write-software-manuals">asciidoc is one of your best choices to write software manuals.</h2>
<p>We are currently working hard towards the release of version 2.0 of our
flagship FDA-certified cardiology product,
<a href="https://www.telesensi.com">TeleSensi</a>.</p>
<p>Because updating the user manual with every release is not as fun as it could
be, I had the idea to convert the doc-format source file to some text-based
document authoring system.</p>
<p>Again, in spite of past positive experience writing manuals with
<a href="http://docutils.sourceforge.net">reStructuredText</a> and LaTeX, I made use of
the opportunity to try out
<a href="https://asciidoctor.org/docs/what-is-asciidoc/">asciidoc</a>.</p>
<p>In <em>this</em> case, I am happy to report that the choice of asciidoc ended up
beating all of the alternatives by a mile.</p>
<p>I started by <a href="https://pandoc.org">pandoc</a>-ing the docx to asciidoc, and then
manually (ha ha, it&rsquo;s a joke we writers tell) fine-tuned the document until, in
a few hours, the new manual looked significantly better than the original.</p>
<p>Long story short, our manual is now part of the software source repository and
hence version-locked, it can be automatically built for new releases, and parts
of the manual can be linked programmatically to form parts of our compliance
documentation.</p>
<p>With the manual now essentially being a software construct, there are many more
tricks we can do (and already do, but I&rsquo;m not allowed to say much more).</p>
<h2 id="you-can-build-self-contained-installers-with-legacy-non-modular-apps-and-recent-modular-java">You can build self-contained installers with legacy non-modular apps and recent modular Java.</h2>
<p>In a rather surprising (to me) turn of events, I had to convert some legacy
(read: non-modular) Java code from a product component to a self-contained
installer on Windows and macOS so that our users never even have to <em>think</em>
about JREs.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s possible that the following magical recipe could help you, should you ever
find yourself in a similar predicament:</p>
<ul>
<li>Install <a href="https://adoptopenjdk.net">AdoptOpenJDK</a> 11 (LTS)</li>
<li>Retrieve and extract this <a href="https://mail.openjdk.java.net/pipermail/openjfx-dev/2018-September/022500.html">backport of the new
javapackager</a>
from the yet to be released Java 13 into your OpenJDK 11.</li>
<li>Build your legacy <a href="https://imagej.net/Uber-JAR">uber-JAR</a> with the freshly
installed OpenJDK11.</li>
<li>Use <code>jdeps</code> to determine the list of modular dependencies of your uber-JAR.</li>
<li>Armed with this knowledge, build a mini java-runtime using <code>jlink</code>.</li>
<li>Now feed your uber-jar and the freshly created java-runtime to <code>jpackager</code> in
order to construct a fully self-contained executable or platform-specific
installation package.</li>
</ul>
<p>Much, but not all, of that comes from <a href="https://medium.com/@adam_carroll/java-packager-with-jdk11-31b3d620f4a8">this blog
post</a>.</p>
<h2 id="you-can-easily-dired-jump-to-the-currently-ivy-readd-file-in-emacs">You can easily dired-jump to the currently ivy-read&rsquo;d file in Emacs.</h2>
<p>I mix and match <a href="https://github.com/abo-abo/swiper">ivy</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm">helm</a> in my Emacs.</p>
<p>When you&rsquo;re helming for a file, you can usually press <code>F5</code> to open dired
(Emacs&rsquo;s built-in filemanager) on that file&rsquo;s directory.</p>
<p>This is quite convenient, and something I was missing in ivy, which I use for
example as part of <code>find-file-in-project</code>.</p>
<p>Weeeeell, by adding the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; for any ivy-read, press M-o to get action menu,</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; then &#39;d&#39; to start dired with that file selected</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#268bd2">ivy-add-actions</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#268bd2">t</span> <span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; add for all types</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; (cdr x) gets the full filename, not just relative</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> `((<span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;d&#34;</span> ,(<span style="color:#cb4b16">lambda</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">x</span>) (<span style="color:#268bd2">dired-jump</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">nil</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">cdr</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">x</span>))) <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;dired&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   ))
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; you get to select <code>d</code> from the <code>M-o</code> action menu to <code>dired-jump</code> (a
wonderful command by itself, usually bound to <code>C-x C-j</code>) to the currently
focused file.</p>
<h1 id="sharpening-these-rocks">Sharpening these rocks.</h1>
<p>All of that brings us to this.</p>
<p>I spent quite a few hours last week performing meta-work: That is, not doing
the work itself, but rather sharpening the tools required to do that work.</p>
<p>As with all important matters, there&rsquo;s an XKCD comic about this topic too:</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://xkcd.com/1205/">
<img src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/is_it_worth_the_time.png" alt="xkcd on
tool sharpening">
</a>
<figcaption>
Incredibly useful visualization by XKCD: How much time will your tool
sharpening save per event, and how frequently does that event occur? The
cross-indexed block is how much time this could save you over 5 years.
</figure>
<p>Besides the mostly defensible tricks mentioned in the previous section, I did
also invest hours in attempting to update the mobile and email-based parts of
my personal knowledge management strategy (because
<a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">Windows</a>), but these hours led to a less than
satisfactory solution.</p>
<p>If I have to be honest, it feels like those hours were wasted, although it was
impossible to say beforehand that the effort to outcome ratio was going to be
that bad.</p>
<p>(To make it all a bit more interesting, a few days later some of the dead-ends
explored during those wasted hours led to coincidental improvements of other
frequently occurring (on the order of 5 times per day) components of my
workflow.)</p>
<p>Some folks double down on their workflows, rather taking the small hits and
spending the time doing their actual work.</p>
<p>I find it difficult to resist an opportunity for streamlining.</p>
<p>Sometimes this pays off, not in the least because of the compounding effects of
frequently applicable optimisations, and other times I fall down the rabbit
hole.</p>
<p>In my dreams, I am able to reach a sort of workflow optimisation pinnacle,
where all inefficiencies have been excised from the system. In reality, goal
posts like to move it move it, and so the scramble never ends.</p>
<p>How do you approach this?</p>
<h1 id="icemirb">ICEMiRB</h1>
<p><em>The International Conference on Emacs, Minimal Running and Blogging</em>, or
ICEMiRB, is a new meeting of minds and legs that the aforementioned and
indomitable <a href="https://mentat.za.net">@stefanvdwalt</a> and I are currently bouncing
around.</p>
<p>I actually just want the t-shirt, but the more I think about this, the more I
think it&rsquo;s something that one day really has to happen.</p>
<p>Please let me know in the comments if you would be interested in taking part.</p>
<p>I imagine we will go all out in terms of the various forms of attendance and
participation that we accommodate.</p>
<p>Have a beautiful week folks, I hope to see you again soon!</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>@stefanvdwalt just reminded me that Mindfulness is to be the fourth main topic
of the ICEMiRB.</p>
<p>Because the acronym is already of substantial girth (yes, we know that
Mindfulness and Minimal could co-habit the same part of the
acronym. coincidence?!), we will try to settle for one of two conference
taglines:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ICEMiRB - A Mindful(TM) Conference.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>or</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ICEMiRB - The Mindfulness is silent.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>or not.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>