<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>TISA on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/tisa/</link><description>Recent content in TISA on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 10:29:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/tisa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Back in South Africa</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 10:29:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/</guid><description>(I was supposed to publish this around the start of February, but then life happened, and I didn’t get to quite finish it.)
For the first time in the three weeks after having arrived back on South African soil, we find ourselves in something that we’re going to call home for the coming months. Until now we have been living out of our suitcases, spending time with various grandpas and grandmas somewhere in the Boerewors Gordyn (the Northern ‘burbs of Cape Town, to those of you not in the know), The Oven (I just made that up. It’s Paarl, the town where I grew up thinking that 40 Celsius was a normal temperature to be wearing a blazer and a tie. 40 Celsius is now my preferred outside temperature.) and in Betty’s Bay (that’s its real name. It’s really cute that way. Look at me walking the thin line of apostrophe (ab)use.) We’ve been doing our fair share of early-to-bed-early-to-rise makes John cranky and not very wise, because Genetic Offspring Unit #1 had to be taken to school in our current town of residence, from our at that point temporary residence. So you’re really planning to publish that blog post, but then you take a walk instead. TISA.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(I was supposed to publish this around the start of February, but then life happened, and I didn’t get to quite finish it.)</em></p>
<p>For the first time in the three weeks after having arrived back on South African soil, we find ourselves in something that we’re going to call home for the coming months. Until now we have been living out of our suitcases, spending time with various grandpas and grandmas somewhere in the Boerewors Gordyn (the Northern ‘burbs of Cape Town, to those of you not in the know), The Oven (I just made that up. It’s Paarl, the town where I grew up thinking that 40 Celsius was a normal temperature to be wearing a blazer and a tie. 40 Celsius is now my preferred outside temperature.) and in Betty’s Bay (that’s its real name. It’s really cute that way. Look at me walking the thin line of apostrophe (ab)use.) We’ve been doing our fair share of early-to-bed-early-to-rise makes John cranky and not very wise, because Genetic Offspring Unit #1 had to be taken to school in our current town of residence, from our at that point temporary residence.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/taking_a_walk_bbay.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/taking_a_walk_bbay-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="So you’re really planning to publish that blog post, but then you take a walk instead. TISA."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>So you’re really planning to publish that blog post, but then you take a walk instead. TISA.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>At the moment I’m sitting in our new home behind an extremely shaky cellular data connection (the house is like the Bermuda triangle of mobile reception. Even in this carefully chosen spot the signal dances a really silly tap dance between H, 3G and EDGE. EDGE is NOT nice, trust me. I think EDGE is actually a synonym for “no connection at all, but we just like to make you think that there has to be something”. At some vague point in the future, ADSL will hopefully be installed. Africa does not care about the timeliness of your internet connection, deal with it.).</p>
<p>So we have our suitcases, and a whole bunch of borrowed items until Our Ship Comes In. No really, we have a ship that’s coming in with all of our old stuff on it. Until that moment, we have a special place where meat can be scorched, also in a social context. This is quite grand.</p>
<p>There is also a mountain in my backyard which I can’t help gawking at whenever I return home. The mountain is majestic, and that is even more grand than the place where you can scorch your meat. I have promised myself to retain and cultivate my awe at this mountain, and at all the mind-blowing natural majesty surrounding me wherever I go in this place, for as long as I can.</p>
<p>See you later everyone!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>