<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Berlin on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/berlin/</link><description>Recent content in Berlin on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2009 08:27:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/berlin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Eurovis 2009</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2009 08:27:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/</guid><description>On Friday I returned, by jet-powered flying device, from Yet Another Visit To Berlin. :) Berlin still exudes cool like nothing else, and I got to spend my time there in the company of more than 190 other Visualisation people, many of whom have become friends over the past years. The three days were filled with presentations, but more importantly (sorry presenters!) good conversations, new friends (contacts?) and not too much sleep. This was, without a doubt, my best Eurovis conference so far!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>On Friday I returned, by jet-powered flying device, from Yet Another Visit To Berlin.  :)  Berlin still exudes cool like nothing else, <em>and</em> I got to spend my time there in the company of more than 190 other Visualisation people, many of whom have become friends over the past years.  The three days were filled with presentations, but more importantly (sorry presenters!) good conversations, new friends (contacts?) and not too much sleep.  This was, without a doubt, my best <a href="http://www.zib.de/eurovis09/" title="eurovis 2009 website">Eurovis conference</a> so far!</p>
<p>The conference was held in the historically and scientifically significant <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harnack_House" title="Wikipedia article on the Harnack House">Harnack House</a>, located in the academia-dominated Dahlem district of Berlin.  For a time, the Harnack House was the home of brilliant German scientists such as Einstein, the guy who invented the dish-washer (as you all know).  The unique setting definitely contributed to the particularly unique feel of this year’s event.</p>
<p><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/~stef/" title="Stef Busking's work homepage">Stef</a> did a sterling job presenting our paper on the scientific comparison of Smurfs (will add link to paper later):</p>
<p><a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/stef_smurfs.jpg" title=""><img alt="stef_smurfs" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-525" data-attachment-id="525" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"3.2","credit":"","camera":"E71","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1244649720","copyright":"","focal_length":"4.9","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":""}' data-image-title="stef_smurfs" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/stef_smurfs.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/stef_smurfs-300x225.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/stef_smurfs.jpg" data-orig-size="1024,768" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/stef_smurfs/" height="225" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/stef_smurfs-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/stef_smurfs-300x225.jpg 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/stef_smurfs.jpg 1024w" title="stef_smurfs" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>In spite of the importance of Smurf comparison, the best paper award was awarded to our friends from Swansea for their work on the <a href="http://www.cs.swan.ac.uk/~csbob/research/biologySensor/" title="Link to paper + movies of Eurovis 2009 best paper.">Visualisation of Sensor Data from Animal Movement</a>!  Remember to keep an eye out for our soon-to-appear InfoVis 2009 paper on the same topic, in cooperation with them.</p>
<p>Other papers / presentations that somehow stuck with me are (this is mostly due to my medvis bias and is not any reflection on the quality of the papers I do NOT list):</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.cg.tuwien.ac.at/research/publications/2009/bruckner-2009-IVV/" title="Link to MIDA paper">Instant Volume Visualization using Maximum Intensity Difference Accumulation</a> by Bruckner and Gröller (Vienna): By a continuous combination of DVR and MIP, this technique overcomes problems of both techniques.  Minimal futzing with transfer functions, better depth than MIP, 35% improvement!</li>
<li>Map Displays for the Analysis of Scalar Data on Cerebral Aneurysm Surfaces (no link available yet) by Neugebauer, Gasteiger, Beuing, Diehl, Skalej and Preim (<a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/04/25/my-first-sabbatical/" title="magdeburg sabbatical posting">Magdeburg</a>): This is a great example of combining 3D with 2D to effectively visually represent complex simulation data.  Also, much like our shoulder work, this is a text book example of the medical visualisation pipeline (acquisition, image processing, simulation / modelling, visualisation / interaction, evaluation).</li>
</ul>
<p>The <a href="http://www.zib.de/eurovis09/?page_id=689" title="Eurovis 2009 capstone webpage">capstone</a> on Friday by <a href="http://www.mpibpc.mpg.de/home/grubmueller/ihp/hgrubmu/index.html" title="Website Grubmueller">Helmut Grubmüller</a> on <em>Watching Biomolecular Nanomachines at Work</em> was inspiring.  Besides the fact that he seems to publish papers with beautiful visualisations in Science every second week, he’s a fantastic speaker who was able to impress on us his wonder at these almost unfathomably tiny protein-component machines, with their rotating axes and all.  Here’s another bad mobile phone photo of the man in action:</p>
<p><a data-rel="lightbox-image-1" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/grubmueller.jpg" style="text-decoration: none;" title=""><img alt="grubmueller" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-527" data-attachment-id="527" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"3.2","credit":"","camera":"E71","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1244833330","copyright":"","focal_length":"4.9","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":""}' data-image-title="grubmueller" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/grubmueller.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/grubmueller-300x225.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/grubmueller.jpg" data-orig-size="1024,768" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/grubmueller/" height="225" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/grubmueller-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/grubmueller-300x225.jpg 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/06/grubmueller.jpg 1024w" title="grubmueller" width="300"/></a></p>
<p>P.S. Of course our paper wasn’t <em>really</em> on Smurf comparison.</p>
<p>P.P.S. <a href="http://pages.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/~pneumann" title="Petra Isenberg's homepage">Petra Isenberg</a> (winner of the 3d best paper award!) and Christopher Collins made <a href="http://infosthetics.com/archives/2009/06/eurovis_2009_conference_coverage.html" title="Link to Information Aesthetics Eurovis 2009 write-up.">a really cool and detailed write-up of Eurovis 2009</a> (slightly infovis-biased) at Information Aesthetics.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>