<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Wine on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/wine/</link><description>Recent content in Wine on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:43:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/wine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #168: Postcards from the edge.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:43:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</guid><description> Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek, Stellenbosch. My friend showed me a photo and said &amp;ldquo;Here&amp;rsquo;s a picture of me when I was younger&amp;rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger. &amp;ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="postcard_cafe_view.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_26018b0fceb30a76.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_87e9e2aa3c21a470.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_6ea8632f8eccd251.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_a8a05038b55a128d.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_87e9e2aa3c21a470.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



</a>
<figcaption> 
Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes
you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek,
Stellenbosch.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<blockquote>
<p>My friend showed me a photo and said &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s a picture of me when I was
younger&rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger.
&ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this edition of the WHV, I cast my now older eyes back on the week starting
on Monday, April 1 and ending on Sunday, April 7, 2019.</p>
<p>I have to apologise for the extremely high nerd content. There will be wine at
the end to make up for it!</p>
<h2 id="working-late-like-its-1998">Working late like it&rsquo;s 1998.</h2>
<p>At the start of the week, I had resolved to get more sleep.</p>
<p>It seems that when I have a good night&rsquo;s sleep, really working that
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glymphatic_system">glymphatic system</a> (I&rsquo;m
currently fascinated by the glymphatic system, I hope you like it too),
amongst other nightly repair activities, there is a greater probability that I
am able to hold my focus the next day.</p>
<p>This was going swimmingly.</p>
<p>At least that was the case until Wednesday, when I decided that the time had
come to port <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs</a>, the far more nerdy sister of this
blog, from <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">wordpress to hugo as
well</a>.</p>
<p>One thing led to another, and by 1:00AM (on a school night no less!) I was
busy wrapping up the isso commenting system configuration.</p>
<p>(We&rsquo;re able to use free and ad-free disqus over here because this is a
personal blog. vxlabs on the other hand is strictly speaking a commercial
site, even although it&rsquo;s filled with non-commercial blog posts.)</p>
<p>One of the many funny things about being a nerd, is that it&rsquo;s almost
impossible to go to bed before a technical thing like this has been
convincingly put to bed.</p>
<p>Fortunately this late night indiscretion yielded a working self-hosted
commenting system, and, far more importantly, a <a href="/2019/04/06/isso-on-webfaction/">rather attractively styled
post, thanks to the Hugo-port, detailing the whole
installation</a>.</p>
<p>In entirely predictable fashion, the next day was not the best focus-wise.</p>
<p>P.S. 1998 - first postgrad year in the DSP lab. All-nighters all the way down&hellip;</p>
<figure>
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu_6310bbae4beb617d.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu_e19b97d20468d2b7.jpg 800w
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu_e19b97d20468d2b7.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



<figcaption>DSP lab, somewhen between 97 - 99.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="nim-surprise">nim-surprise.</h2>
<p>I chose Isso because it&rsquo;s Python.</p>
<p>DayJob(tm) is all about Python, so this was a great choice in terms of time
savings.</p>
<p>With all of the time I had saved, I decided that I would experiment with
re-implementing parts of Isso in <a href="https://fsharp.org/">f#</a>, my current hobby
functional language.</p>
<p>Setting aside the irony here, I learned after some time that getting f#, the
impressive looking <a href="https://fsprojects.github.io/SQLProvider/">SQLProvider</a> and
sqlite (isso&rsquo;s database) all working together on Linux was <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/fsharp/comments/8ufvzz/how_can_i_add_sqlprovider_to_my_existing_project/e1idy1o/">&ldquo;probably the
single most complicated thing that you can do with a F# project, when it comes
to
tooling&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>In this case, I was thankfully able to switch gears and did a brief review of
possible candidates for a functional(ish), memory efficient, fast(ish)
compilation languages that could be used to implement an Isso web-service
replacement.</p>
<p>Somehow I ended up with <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a>.</p>
<p>This has been on my radar for a while now, but there were always shinier
things to try.</p>
<p>I think what might have put me off was the similarity to Python.</p>
<p>So, with the rest of the time I had saved choosing Isso, I got up to
speed(ish) with nim by starting to implement a replacement for parts of the
isso commenting system.</p>
<p>I was quite positively surprised by the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Compilation speed: The nim compiler transforms my webservice code into C and
then compiles that in about 1.2 seconds.</li>
<li>Performance and memory size of resultant binary: This is not a fair
comparison to Python, but the multi-threaded nim service consumes a few
megabytes in total.</li>
<li>Availability of packages especially for building a web service like this:
Using the nimble package manager, I could install
<a href="https://github.com/dom96/jester">jester</a> and had my first running
web-service in a few minutes.</li>
<li>Built-in sqlite support.</li>
<li>Real macros: I used the list comprehension one in the <code>sugar</code> module.</li>
</ul>
<p>This was really just an exercise (for now), but I have a new tool for whenever
I need to write a fast and compact compiled web-service again!</p>
<p>P.S. Learning new programming languages is one of my favourite things.</p>
<p>P.P.S. Thanks to the internet and open source, and especially tools like
github, we are currently going through a sort of programming language Cambrian
explosion. See this <a href="http://fll.presidentbeef.com/">Fledgling Languages List</a>
for example. Pony!</p>
<h2 id="decompression">Decompression.</h2>
<p>On Sunday, we made the drive out to Jonkershoek in Stellenbosch.</p>
<p>Even although it&rsquo;s only 40 minutes away, I haven&rsquo;t been there in far too
long. It&rsquo;s a truly beautiful corner of the planet.</p>
<p>At the Postcard Café, after some internal deliberation, I made the decision
that the moment was special enough to interrupt LAZ
(lifestyle-alcohol-zero(tm)) with an all the more special glass of the
<a href="https://winemag.co.za/stark-conde-the-field-blend-2014/">Stark-Condé Field Blend white
wine</a>.</p>
<p>This is a hyper-local blend of Chenin Blanc, Rousanne, Verdelho and Viognier,
all four varietals which grow on the mountain-side right across from the
Café&rsquo;s veranda.</p>
<p>It really was divine.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #76: Someone is wrong on the internet.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/07/01/weekly-head-voices-76-someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 19:11:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/07/01/weekly-head-voices-76-someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet/</guid><description> I must be getting older.
During the past week, there were at least three or four occasions where someone was clearly wrong on the internet, and I dutifully started carefully crafting that brilliant corrective response which would inevitably spiral downward into the fiery depths of idiocy.
However, each time I stopped mid-answer, long before clicking the post button or sending the email, and switched to some other more valuable and less pointless activity. It was a strange feeling, but the eerie sense of having saved a bunch of time made up for it generously.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <div class="figure">
<p>
<a href="http://xkcd.com/386/"><img alt="duty_calls.png" src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/duty_calls.png"/></a>
</p>
</div>
<p>I must be getting older.</p>
<p>During the past week, there were at least three or four occasions where someone was clearly <em>wrong</em> on the internet, and I dutifully started carefully crafting that <em>brilliant</em> corrective response which would inevitably spiral downward into the fiery depths of idiocy.</p>
<p>However, each time I stopped mid-answer, long before clicking the post button or sending the email, and switched to some other more valuable and less pointless activity. It was a strange feeling, but the eerie sense of having saved a bunch of time made up for it generously.</p>
<p>(I have to admit that there was one occasion, call it the fifth, where I couldn’t help myself and briefly took part in a Facebook discussion around a photo of a young man with some rather extreme facial piercings. I felt that I really needed to <em>correct</em> the other participants: I might not have any of my own body modifications, but I feel strongly about encouraging self-expression, and I think that the variety that it brings is important. There are <em>other</em> things that unify us, like love, respect and intellect. Yes, I’m a Vulcan Hippie. LLAP you fools!)</p>
<p>On the topic of age and the inevitable mid-life crisis, it seems technology has brought us the cure. GIANT WATER-JET-POWERED HOVERBOARDS!!</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gMaDhkNJA2g?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>After a week of not-correcting-the-internet (good), lots of Python (good) and much face-palming at the South African Reserve Bank’s archaic view on intellectual property and exchange control (hopefully much more on that later), my weekend was of the fabulous middle-of-the-Cape-winter variety.</p>
<p>It started with some of this on Friday: <figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-jack_black_skeleton_coast_ipa.jpg" title=""></p>
<p><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-jack_black_skeleton_coast_ipa-225x300.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Skeleton Coast IPA, brewed by Jack Black in Cape Town. Highly recommended! Fire and wine not too bad either.</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>On Saturday, a completely unplanned and somewhat impulsive turnoff from the R44 right before Stellenbosch brought us to the <a href="http://www.dornier.co.za/">vineyard Dornier</a>. Some of it looks like this: <figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-1" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-dornier_20140629.jpg" title=""></p>
<p><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-dornier_20140629-300x225.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">In the Cape, the summer is always trying to break through, even in the middle of winter.</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>Having <em>arrived</em> there, it doesn’t take much convincing to end up dining in restaurant Bodega, where the wine is <strong>very</strong> local (hey, it says Dornier on the bottles!) and is artfully paired with the delicious food. My lunch ended with these delectable cheeses, preserves and the <a href="http://www.dornier.co.za/wines/donatus-white">Dornier Donatus White</a>. I can’t remember the year, but it was a fabulous Chenin Blanc and Semillon blend which <a href="http://dewijnrecensent.nl/">the DWR</a> will hopefully soon be able to judge. I fortunately <em>just</em> managed to snap this picture in the midst of a gorgonzola-induced mini pleasure seizure: <figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-2" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-dornier_20140629_cheese.jpg" title=""></p>
<p><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-dornier_20140629_cheese-300x225.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Gorgonzola is my kryptonite.</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>(We spent the rest of the seemingly endless weekend scorching various types of meat, drinking craft beer and baking in the winter sun in Paarl. You can say many things about Paarl, but you can’t deny that it has a most <em>excellent</em> climate.)</p>
<p>Apparently, a few of this blog’s readers have been wondering what I really look like. (Well, actually no-one has. Ever. But they could have!) Clamour no more, small group of fictitious readers! This week, my youngest genetic offspring unit, or GOU#1 as we lovingly call her, brought me a drawing that she made. Internet, I give you <em>me</em>, through my daughter’s eyes:</p>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-sylvia_draws_charl_2014061.jpg" title=""><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-sylvia_draws_charl_2014061-300x205.jpg"/></a>
</p>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #69: No sugar added.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/04/29/weekly-head-voices-69-no-sugar-added/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2014 21:03:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/04/29/weekly-head-voices-69-no-sugar-added/</guid><description>This time, the head voices are echoing the span of time ending strictly on Sunday, April 27 at 23:59.
I have to break my rule and reach through past the start of that week however. On Wednesday April 16 I had quite a heavy sugar crash. After about 12 cups of coffee, each with a spoon of sugar (as per usual), some chocolates from the Stone Three sweetie jar during lunch ,and two giant coconut crunches at about TU Delft sugar fix time (yes children, I do my best to commemorate the sugar fix, even at 11000 km distance from you), my energy levels dropped through the floor and no amount of coffee could get them close to normal again.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This time, the head voices are echoing the span of time ending strictly on Sunday, April 27 at 23:59.</p>
<p>I have to break my rule and reach through past the start of that week however. On Wednesday April 16 I had quite a heavy sugar crash. After about 12 cups of coffee, each with a spoon of sugar (as per usual), some chocolates from the Stone Three sweetie jar during lunch ,and two giant coconut crunches at about TU Delft sugar fix time (yes children, I do my best to commemorate the sugar fix, even at 11000 km distance from you), my energy levels dropped through the floor and no amount of coffee could get them close to normal again.</p>
<p>That’s when I decided to stop taking sugar.</p>
<p>On Thursday April 17 I went cold turkey. I’m not taking any table sugar at all, no cookies or sweets (ARGH), and I’m even steering clear of breakfast cereals. Pretty boring, I know. After more than a week of completely unscientific N=1 case “study” experience, I can report that:</p>
<ul>
<li>It took some getting used to my coffee without any sugar.</li>
<li>NO MORE  COOKIES. ARGH ARGH ARGH. COME CLOSER SO I CAN BITE YOU.</li>
<li>My perceived energy levels seem significantly more stable, and I remain all energetic until late at night. Sometimes I don’t sleep, because I run around in the neighbourhood making growling noises. Sometimes I wake up, miles away from home, with all kinds of gunk under my finger nails. Oh well.</li>
</ul>
<p>On the topic of quitting, let’s talk about all of those lists we love so much. You should really go read Noeska’s presentation on Productivity, Project Management and Other Important Stuff in her <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/weekly-status-update-3/" title="Noeska's Weekly Status Update #3">latest status update blog post</a>. Besides all of the Getting Things Done and Pull Yourself Together tools and systems she presents, I was happy to see her talk about the dangers of productivity tools on slide 23, and especially the “doing the right things vs doing things right” dilemma.</p>
<p>You see, I’ve been thinking much about this lately. Usually when I’m doing the most valuable and important things (designing and building new products, learning new programming languages, coming up with brand new ideas for artefacts to build) my email inbox starts overflowing and my todo system (currently <a href="http://todoist.com/" title="todoist website">todoist</a>, which I do like) stagnates (my todoist karma is currently ZERO. I’m at KARMA ZERO damnit!!). Conversely, when I’m almost at inbox zero and my todoist is under control, it feels great, but I’m tired because I’ve spent all of that time taking care of a bunch of emails and mostly urgent but almost no important tasks.</p>
<p>Some people I’ve chatted with are hardcore enough to make the classification between important and urgent in their lists. However, when I see that list of tasks, my OCDs take over and I go into 100% reactive mode. NO ROOM FOR CREATIVITY.</p>
<p>I’m still thinking about how to solve this problem. I do think that the lists and the systems are really important, because some things do really need doing at certain points in time. For now, I’m still picking the three (or two, or one) most important things to do per day (see Noeska’s presentation, also <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/" title="old blog post: write down most important things to do each day">see pro tip #2 in this 2011 post of mine</a>). Also, what does work remarkably well for me, is maintaining a daily “done” or “I did it” list. <a href="http://jamesaltucher.quora.com/The-I-Did-List-%E2%80%93-I-Did-It" title="Altucher: I did it list.">Go read this</a>, you can thank me later.</p>
<p>After all of that, the weekend took us to Vaalvlei, a picturesque wine farm just outside of Stanford:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/vaalvlei.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/vaalvlei-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Vaalvlei wine farm, just outside of Stanford."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Vaalvlei wine farm, just outside of Stanford.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Here we were treated to a super-exclusive wine tasting of the Vaalvlei Sauvignon Blanc, 2012 Shiraz Reserve, 2011 Shiraz, Shiraz port, and the top TOP secret Shiraz cognac right from the cask (don’t tell anyone, ok?):










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/vaalvlei_tasting.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/vaalvlei_tasting-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Vaalvlei wine and cognac tasting"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Vaalvlei wine and cognac tasting</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I can report that these hand-crafted wines and the cognac were all beautiful, but I trust that my friend <a href="http://dewijnrecensent.nl/" title="De Wijnrecensent">De Wijnrecensent</a> (aka <em>the Tall Philisophical Neighbour!</em> all secrets are revealed on this blog.) will have more to say about this in a few months time.</p>
<p>Enjoy the rest of the week kids!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>