<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Writing on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/writing/</link><description>Recent content in Writing on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 23:23:25 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #194: 136 words a day</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 23:19:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/</guid><description> Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&amp;rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&amp;rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="afrikaburn2017-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_375a1371e2dd1a54.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_fdd86842f9ddcde0.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_7249dd9600e79b87.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_48c0abab619b5985.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu_fdd86842f9ddcde0.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This post quite compactly gazes back at the week from Monday May 4 to Sunday
May 10.</p>
<p>It starts with a short summary of my work week, followed by a story which you
will hopefully enjoy.</p>
<h2 id="how-was-your-week-honey">How was your week honey?</h2>
<p>I hacked on and fixed iPad microphone support in our direct-to-patient
TeleMedicine app.</p>
<p>If you are a programmer, or you have programmers in your life, you&rsquo;ll hopefully
understand the absolute catnip of technical rabbit holes that suck you in for
hours on end, only to eject you on a beautiful but extremely short-lived
dopamine deluge of discovery.</p>
<p>We integrated <a href="https://casual-effects.com/markdeep/">markdeep</a> into the performance tracking component of one of our
medical image processing pipelines.</p>
<p>Having a format, namely .md.html, which is this easy to generate
programmatically from some computational pipeline, yet results in such
attractive output documents is a great boon.</p>
<h2 id="gou-1-reveals-her-plans-and-makes-us-think--more">GOU #1 reveals her plans and makes us think (more)</h2>
<p><a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> turned another year older.</p>
<p>At the dinner table on the big day, we were having a conversation about further
education in general and about postgraduate studies and PhDs in particular.</p>
<p>(She is now in high school, so these conversations are happening more often.)</p>
<p>I said that she will have to get a PhD in Physics or Math, but that I would
probably be able to make peace with a PhD in Engineering also.</p>
<p>She asked us how the PhD works, and so we explained the background as well as
we could.</p>
<p>We spent quite some time on the observation that the most important part of a
successful PhD is just never giving up.</p>
<p>Although never giving up is a chronic aspect, many PhD-veterans will tell you
that this adventure often includes a fairly acute existential crisis, mostly at
about the halfway mark.</p>
<p>This is when the candidate asks pertinent questions like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Why, oh why did I ever think this was a good idea?</li>
<li>Is this work really worth <em>anything</em>?</li>
<li>Does anyone really care about this?</li>
<li>I wonder what the non-academic job market is like at this moment?!</li>
</ul>
<p>Fortunately in many cases, the candidate gets through this process and emerges
from the other side of the ordeal ever so slightly stronger and wiser.</p>
<p>(For those of you who have been paying attention, this crisis is like the super
deluxe version of the <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">5-stage Creative Process</a>.)</p>
<p>I digress&hellip;</p>
<p>Talking more about the mechanics, GOU #1 asked how long a PhD thesis usually
is.</p>
<p>Off the top of my head I said: &ldquo;Around 50 thousand words, but there is of
course huge variation&rdquo;.</p>
<p>At that point she got out her phone (well, it&rsquo;s actually never not out) and
made a quick calculation, after which she quipped: &ldquo;Well, that&rsquo;s
straight-forward then. I&rsquo;ll spend one year planning, then I&rsquo;ll spend the year
after that writing only 136 words per day, and the year after that revising
everything to make it perfect.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was a simply lovely and humorous conversation to have at that moment, but
what a great point she made: If you can manage to write 136 words per day for a
year, you&rsquo;ll have 50000 words.</p>
<h3 id="the-slightly-modified-136-word-plan">The slightly modified 136 word plan</h3>
<p>136 words is really not that much if you look at it in isolation. The text
above, from right after &ldquo;I digress&hellip;&rdquo; until right before the heading above, is
exactly 136 words (if Emacs can be trusted).</p>
<p>To me the <a href="/tags/compounding/">compounding</a> nature of this act of writing such a paltry number of
words every day, but simply keeping at it for months and years, is quite
amazing.</p>
<p>So, thanks to my daughter&rsquo;s inspiration, I added a daily item to <a href="/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/">my habit
tracker</a> that says <em>Write 100 words towards publication</em>.</p>
<p>I hope she won&rsquo;t mind that I changed the limit to 100, simply because I would
like to increase my chances of being consistent and maintaining those <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">streaks</a>.</p>
<p>I have added the explicit qualifier that the 100 words I write should be
towards publication: This means that my intention should be for them to end up
either in a blog post, or perhaps a future book project, or any other form of
publication that is intended for public consumption.</p>
<p>Wish me luck folks! Even better, why not join me on this journey?!</p>
<h2 id="friendly-wishes">Friendly wishes</h2>
<p>Thank you friends for meeting me here.</p>
<p>I wish you all health and kindness and contentment.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>