<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Glymphatic System on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/glymphatic-system/</link><description>Recent content in Glymphatic System on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:43:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/glymphatic-system/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #168: Postcards from the edge.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:43:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</guid><description> Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek, Stellenbosch. My friend showed me a photo and said &amp;ldquo;Here&amp;rsquo;s a picture of me when I was younger&amp;rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger. &amp;ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="postcard_cafe_view.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_26018b0fceb30a76.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_87e9e2aa3c21a470.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_6ea8632f8eccd251.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_a8a05038b55a128d.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu_87e9e2aa3c21a470.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



</a>
<figcaption> 
Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes
you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek,
Stellenbosch.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<blockquote>
<p>My friend showed me a photo and said &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s a picture of me when I was
younger&rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger.
&ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this edition of the WHV, I cast my now older eyes back on the week starting
on Monday, April 1 and ending on Sunday, April 7, 2019.</p>
<p>I have to apologise for the extremely high nerd content. There will be wine at
the end to make up for it!</p>
<h2 id="working-late-like-its-1998">Working late like it&rsquo;s 1998.</h2>
<p>At the start of the week, I had resolved to get more sleep.</p>
<p>It seems that when I have a good night&rsquo;s sleep, really working that
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glymphatic_system">glymphatic system</a> (I&rsquo;m
currently fascinated by the glymphatic system, I hope you like it too),
amongst other nightly repair activities, there is a greater probability that I
am able to hold my focus the next day.</p>
<p>This was going swimmingly.</p>
<p>At least that was the case until Wednesday, when I decided that the time had
come to port <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs</a>, the far more nerdy sister of this
blog, from <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">wordpress to hugo as
well</a>.</p>
<p>One thing led to another, and by 1:00AM (on a school night no less!) I was
busy wrapping up the isso commenting system configuration.</p>
<p>(We&rsquo;re able to use free and ad-free disqus over here because this is a
personal blog. vxlabs on the other hand is strictly speaking a commercial
site, even although it&rsquo;s filled with non-commercial blog posts.)</p>
<p>One of the many funny things about being a nerd, is that it&rsquo;s almost
impossible to go to bed before a technical thing like this has been
convincingly put to bed.</p>
<p>Fortunately this late night indiscretion yielded a working self-hosted
commenting system, and, far more importantly, a <a href="/2019/04/06/isso-on-webfaction/">rather attractively styled
post, thanks to the Hugo-port, detailing the whole
installation</a>.</p>
<p>In entirely predictable fashion, the next day was not the best focus-wise.</p>
<p>P.S. 1998 - first postgrad year in the DSP lab. All-nighters all the way down&hellip;</p>
<figure>
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu_6310bbae4beb617d.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu_e19b97d20468d2b7.jpg 800w
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu_e19b97d20468d2b7.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



<figcaption>DSP lab, somewhen between 97 - 99.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="nim-surprise">nim-surprise.</h2>
<p>I chose Isso because it&rsquo;s Python.</p>
<p>DayJob(tm) is all about Python, so this was a great choice in terms of time
savings.</p>
<p>With all of the time I had saved, I decided that I would experiment with
re-implementing parts of Isso in <a href="https://fsharp.org/">f#</a>, my current hobby
functional language.</p>
<p>Setting aside the irony here, I learned after some time that getting f#, the
impressive looking <a href="https://fsprojects.github.io/SQLProvider/">SQLProvider</a> and
sqlite (isso&rsquo;s database) all working together on Linux was <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/fsharp/comments/8ufvzz/how_can_i_add_sqlprovider_to_my_existing_project/e1idy1o/">&ldquo;probably the
single most complicated thing that you can do with a F# project, when it comes
to
tooling&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>In this case, I was thankfully able to switch gears and did a brief review of
possible candidates for a functional(ish), memory efficient, fast(ish)
compilation languages that could be used to implement an Isso web-service
replacement.</p>
<p>Somehow I ended up with <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a>.</p>
<p>This has been on my radar for a while now, but there were always shinier
things to try.</p>
<p>I think what might have put me off was the similarity to Python.</p>
<p>So, with the rest of the time I had saved choosing Isso, I got up to
speed(ish) with nim by starting to implement a replacement for parts of the
isso commenting system.</p>
<p>I was quite positively surprised by the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Compilation speed: The nim compiler transforms my webservice code into C and
then compiles that in about 1.2 seconds.</li>
<li>Performance and memory size of resultant binary: This is not a fair
comparison to Python, but the multi-threaded nim service consumes a few
megabytes in total.</li>
<li>Availability of packages especially for building a web service like this:
Using the nimble package manager, I could install
<a href="https://github.com/dom96/jester">jester</a> and had my first running
web-service in a few minutes.</li>
<li>Built-in sqlite support.</li>
<li>Real macros: I used the list comprehension one in the <code>sugar</code> module.</li>
</ul>
<p>This was really just an exercise (for now), but I have a new tool for whenever
I need to write a fast and compact compiled web-service again!</p>
<p>P.S. Learning new programming languages is one of my favourite things.</p>
<p>P.P.S. Thanks to the internet and open source, and especially tools like
github, we are currently going through a sort of programming language Cambrian
explosion. See this <a href="http://fll.presidentbeef.com/">Fledgling Languages List</a>
for example. Pony!</p>
<h2 id="decompression">Decompression.</h2>
<p>On Sunday, we made the drive out to Jonkershoek in Stellenbosch.</p>
<p>Even although it&rsquo;s only 40 minutes away, I haven&rsquo;t been there in far too
long. It&rsquo;s a truly beautiful corner of the planet.</p>
<p>At the Postcard Café, after some internal deliberation, I made the decision
that the moment was special enough to interrupt LAZ
(lifestyle-alcohol-zero(tm)) with an all the more special glass of the
<a href="https://winemag.co.za/stark-conde-the-field-blend-2014/">Stark-Condé Field Blend white
wine</a>.</p>
<p>This is a hyper-local blend of Chenin Blanc, Rousanne, Verdelho and Viognier,
all four varietals which grow on the mountain-side right across from the
Café&rsquo;s veranda.</p>
<p>It really was divine.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #98: Lemons.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/16/weekly-head-voices-98-lemons/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 20:08:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/16/weekly-head-voices-98-lemons/</guid><description>This, the ninety eighth edition of the WHV, looks back at the week of Monday August 10 to Sunday August 16, 2015.
Today we took a brief walk up into the mountain, as one does around these parts. This is what False Bay looks like from the Helderberg Nature Reserve:
When life hands you lemons, build a battery Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #1 had to do a show and tell at school, so I helped her to construct a battery from 4 lemons. Besides that because of this I got to refresh my own knowledge (can you remember exactly why a battery such as this works?!) we got to chat about molecules, atoms, protons, neutrons, electrons, atomic numbers and the periodic table.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the ninety eighth edition of the WHV, looks back at the week of Monday
August 10 to Sunday August 16, 2015.</p>
<p>Today we took a brief walk up into the mountain, as one does around these
parts. This is what <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_Bay">False Bay</a> looks like from the Helderberg Nature
Reserve:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-false_bay_from_helderberg_nature_reserve.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-false_bay_from_helderberg_nature_reserve.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="when-life-hands-you-lemons-build-a-battery">When life hands you lemons, build a battery</h2>
<p>Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #1 had to do a show and tell at school, so I
helped her to construct a battery from 4 lemons. Besides that because of this I
got to refresh my own knowledge (can <i>you</i> remember exactly why a battery
such as this works?!) we got to chat about molecules, atoms, protons, neutrons,
electrons, atomic numbers and the periodic table.</p>
<p>The next day she quite coolly took the whole kit to school, proceeded to
connect up the disassembled kit before the class, and got the little LED to
switch on, all the while explaining in high-level 9-year-old-ish how it worked.</p>
<p>In case you’re wondering, the experiment looked like this:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-lemon_battery.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-lemon_battery.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>With zinc-covered screws and heavy duty stripped copper wire, we got about 0.9V per lemon. There was enough current to light up a small 3V LED.</p>
<p>(Will GOU#1 one day become an engineer? Stay tuned to this blog for the next 10 years to find out!)</p>
<h2 id="taking-a-break-from-facebook">Taking a break from Facebook</h2>
<p>One of my more interesting Facebook friends announced that she was taking a break from Facebook, because “this stuff is toxic and no good”.</p>
<p>This made me evaluate what I thought of FB at the moment.</p>
<p><i>Toxic</i> is a strong word, but after thinking about this for a while, I have to admit that a large part of the time I spend on the site is probably not that good for my karma. The problem is that there are a whole bunch of friends I really would like to stay in contact with, but for the most part they are quite silent. The people that do pipe up the most on FB are people with some or other silly and/or misguided agenda.</p>
<p>Although <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2014/07/01/weekly-head-voices-76-someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet/">I have learnt to stop correcting the infinite number of people who are wrong on the internet</a>, I’m still reading their contributions, getting slightly worked up, formulating a response, and then resisting posting it, all of this a number of times per day.</p>
<p>To the question whether seeing the one or two positive and life-affirming posts is justified by a seemingly much larger number of the opposite, my response has also become to take a break from Facebook and to see for myself.</p>
<p>I’m not going to cancel my account, so I will receive notifications for example when people message me, but I’m just going to stop checking the site completely. I am also giving myself permission to post new WHV editions there now and then: It’s sometimes the best way to reach some of those silent but desirable FB friends I mentioned, because not all of them are subscribed to this blog. THAT’S A SUBTLE HINT SILENT BUT DESIRABLE FRIENDS.</p>
<p>(BTW, I’m almost 3 days in now, so far no problems. I’ll report back in future WHVs.)</p>
<h2 id="the-mind-is-a-terrible-thing-to-taste">The mind is a terrible thing to taste</h2>
<p>This week I learned about <a href="http://www.nih.gov/researchmatters/october2013/10282013clear.htm">fascinating sleeping brain research</a> (that summary is from the NIH, also see <a href="http://news.sciencemag.org/brain-behavior/2013/10/sleep-ultimate-brainwasher">this one by Science Magazine</a>) that was published in 2013.</p>
<p>In short, when mice sleep, the area between their brain cells is temporarily increased by 60% (!!), and the cerebro-spinal fluid between the cells flows much more rapidly than when they’re awake. This rapid flow literally flushes out of the brain the toxins that build up during the waking hours. HOW COOL IS THAT?!</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-sciencemag_brainwash.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-sciencemag_brainwash.jpg"
        
            alt="Toxins flushed out via bright blue channels between brain cells. Image from Science Mag summary linked above."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Toxins flushed out via bright blue channels between brain cells. Image from Science Mag summary linked above.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Going down one detail level, the researchers showed that the glial cells (the non-neuronal cells in the brain) control the flow of cerebro-spinal fluid through channels in their cell membranes. By using different coloured dyes, they showed that there was significantly more flow during sleeping than when awake, clearing out toxins twice as quickly.</p>
<p>This research took place in mice, but the researchers hypothesise that this same mechanism operates in humans, and <a href="https://www.urmc.rochester.edu/labs/nedergaard-lab/projects/glymphatic_system">are working on verifying that this is the case</a>.</p>
<p>Original article full text: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3880190/"><i>Sleep Drives Metabolite Clearance from the Adult Brain</i></a>, Xie et al., 2013, Science.</p>
<h2 id="this-is-the-end-my-friends">This is the end my friends</h2>
<p>Have a great week kids, and do remember to get your sleep!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>