<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Note-Taking on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/note-taking/</link><description>Recent content in Note-Taking on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 12:58:37 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/note-taking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Note-taking strategy 2023</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2023 13:48:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/</guid><description> I wrote about my note-taking approach for the first time in 2016 (read for fun), and then pretty expansively about its evolved version in 2019.
In spite of the title of these posts, already in 2019 it had become more a system for personal knowledge management than just for note-taking.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure class="flush-left"><a href="emacs-user-dalle.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/emacs-user-dalle_hu_e56ee92c05542946.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/emacs-user-dalle_hu_fedc46e03857ec89.jpg 800w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/emacs-user-dalle_hu_fedc46e03857ec89.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Painting of an Emacs user making notes using Emacs with Org mode (dall-e via chatgpt.el)" width="320px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>I wrote about my note-taking approach for <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">the first time in 2016</a> (read for
fun), and <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">then pretty expansively about its evolved version  in 2019</a>.</p>
<p>In spite of the title of these posts, already in 2019 it had become more a
system for <em>personal knowledge management</em> than just for note-taking.</p>
<p>It is now again three years later (3.5 to be slightly more accurate), and the
system has continued on its path of steady evolution.</p>
<p>It currently contains thousands of interlinked notes, as well as hundreds of
saved articles and web-pages. It also tracks of all of my projects and tasks,
both work and personal.</p>
<p>The purpose of this post is to document the <em>current</em> state of the system. You
don&rsquo;t need any prior knowledge from the other posts; this post should be
self-contained.</p>
<h2 id="high-level-overview">High level overview</h2>
<p>The system has to satisfy the following functional requirements:</p>
<ol>
<li>Fast capture of any information on desktop and mobile, including free-form
notes, web-pages and other media.</li>
<li>Tracking of projects, tasks and metadata such as due dates and schedules.</li>
<li>Fast and accurate retrieval of any information relevant to the current
situation.</li>
<li>Potentially serendipitous surfacing of assets that might be relevant to the
main search focus, for example through linking or through search.</li>
</ol>
<p>The system should have the following two characteristics:</p>
<ol>
<li>There should be a single search interface that can in theory find everything
that was ever stored in the system. This is to prevent the situation where
you urgently need some document and can&rsquo;t remember into <em>which</em> notes app you
stored it so many years ago. (True story)</li>
<li>As far as possible, the canonical source of everything should be plain old
files on local drives, and be synchronized with a tool like Dropbox or
OneDrive. In this way, the system is robust to the whims of a note-taking
SaaS. The litmus test for this is that you are able to change out sync
services and still remain with a working system. (True story)</li>
</ol>
<p>At the highest level, my system, which satisfies the requirements and
characteristics above, consists of the following components:</p>
<dl>
<dt>Emacs with Org-mode and Org-roam</dt>
<dd>This is the nexus of the whole thing. It
tracks projects, tasks and notes, spread out over just over a thousand
org-files, each of them containing one or more (org-roam) notes, all linked
together.</dd>
<dt>Mobile device for capturing and access</dt>
<dd>In my case that&rsquo;s an iPhone with a
number of additional apps for the capturing into and accessing of my notes
database. See figure below, and explanation further down.</dd>
<dt>Reproducible digital filing system</dt>
<dd>This just refers to the fact that over
the years I&rsquo;ve evolved a recipe for &ldquo;where to put that file&rdquo; which is
reproducible in the sense that if I receive the same file a year later, my
brain will automatically follow the same logic and end up in the same
spot. Over the past year or two, I have started applying aspects of the <a href="https://fortelabs.com/blog/para/">PARA
method</a> to a subset of my files, and a heavily modified <a href="https://johnnydecimal.com/">Johnny•Decimal</a> to
the &ldquo;areas&rdquo; in PARA. I am happy with the results so far.</dd>
<dt>PDF&rsquo;d web-pages and articles (JBOP)</dt>
<dd>Locally stored PDF versions of
reference-worthy web-pages and articles can be annotated, linked and shared,
and they remain usable long after the source website has disappeared.</dd>
<dt>Academic articles managed with Zotero</dt>
<dd>Zotero is one of the best ways to
manage all of your academic literature and metadata. As if that&rsquo;s not enough,
it&rsquo;s fully open source. Since I&rsquo;m doing less academia these days, this is
seeing minimal use.</dd>
<dt>OneDrive (previously Dropbox) for cloud synchronization and searching</dt>
<dd>This
infrastructural component is critical. It ensures that all of the files are
synced and available on all devices that I use, and, quite importantly, it
indexes everything so that I can interactively search through the contents of
hundreds of thousands of files. There are some work-arounds and caveats which
I will get into further down.</dd>
<dt>SyncThing</dt>
<dd>Having a local version of my whole notes database, both in its
native Org format as well as an automatically updated Obsidian Vault version,
gives the best experience on mobile.</dd>
</dl>
<p>The following figure is a different view of the Rube Goldberg machine described
above:</p>










<figure><a href="cpbotha-pkm-2023.excalidraw.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/cpbotha-pkm-2023.excalidraw_hu_befb16bc9676e148.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/cpbotha-pkm-2023.excalidraw_hu_c5b4472c7e72470.png 800w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/cpbotha-pkm-2023.excalidraw_hu_c5b4472c7e72470.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Selected apps forming my note-taking approach on desktop and mobile."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Selected apps forming my note-taking approach on desktop and mobile.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="some-of-the-components-in-more-detail">Some of the components in more detail</h2>
<h3 id="emacs-with-org-mode-and-org-roam">Emacs with Org-mode and Org-roam</h3>
<p>At the <strong>heart of my knowledge management system</strong>, let&rsquo;s call it <code>pkb4000</code>, is
<a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a>, together with the venerable <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Org mode</a> package, its more recent
augmentation <a href="https://www.orgroam.com/">Org-roam</a>, and a whole zoo of finely tuned packages.</p>
<p>Org mode, or &ldquo;Your life in plaintext&rdquo;, is a powerful text-file-based system for
managing notes, task lists, projects and even authoring documents.</p>
<p>Once you get used to the programmable flexibility that it and especially Emacs
itself are able to offer, you will find it hard to go back to any conventional
system.</p>
<p>After some years of trial and error, I have settled on using the following main
Org-mode sub-components:</p>
<dl>
<dt>monthly journal files</dt>
<dd>a diary-like setup where I try to document every
single day, and where I keep track of personal tasks and projects.</dd>
<dt>notes database</dt>
<dd>consisting of hundreds of interlinked notes about people,
things and tricks. Thanks to the magic of org roam, notes can live as files
or as headings in a month or project file.</dd>
<dt>project / area of responsibility files</dt>
<dd>where each org-file contains or
links all information related to a specific project, product or area of
responsibility.</dd>
<dt>org-agenda</dt>
<dd>This Org mode feature dynamically creates a view of all of my
projects and tasks, extracted from a subset of the files mentioned above.</dd>
</dl>
<h4 id="monthly-journal-files">Monthly journal files</h4>
<p>In my main Org mode directory, I have a subdirectory named <code>journals</code>, which
contains a directory for each year.</p>
<p>Each of these year directories contains an <code>.org</code> file for each month, so we
would have for example <code>journals/2022/2022-06-Jun.org</code>.</p>
<p>Each month file follows the structure showed in the following redacted version
of my current journal file:</p>










<figure><a href="2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot_hu_33a64c0e5a682456.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot_hu_3725d935171f0730.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot_hu_e610321c99d9886.png 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot_hu_3725d935171f0730.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A simplified example of a month journal file"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A simplified example of a month journal file</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Aside from the Hugo properties which mean I&rsquo;m ready to publish any heading as a
blog post (this is usually how <a href="/categories/weekly-head-voices/">WHVs</a> are done), my Life Systems 2022 aka
personal philosophy reminder, and the clock table where I get a complete
break-down of all work-time spent, I would like to mention the following two
aspects of the month journal.</p>
<!--list-separator-->
<ul>
<li>
<p>Day planning</p>
<p>When I start the day, I instantiate a new org-capture &ldquo;day planning&rdquo; template
by pressing <code>C-c c p</code>.</p>
<p>This creates the <em>Day planning</em> subsection with all of its subsections and
checklists. As you will see, this guides me through the morning review, which
in turn has me check each of those additional sources of incoming information
and tasks.</p>
<p>New bits of information are filed into their correct place, whilst the
org-agenda-powered task review shows me a list of tasks, extracted from the
month file and the list of current project files, so that I can decide which
ones should be taken on.</p>
<p>I list tasks which should preferably be taken care of today under <em>Tasks for
today</em>, whilst any really high-value high-satisfaction tasks go under <em>One Main
Thing and Task(s) that will satisfy end-of-day Charl</em>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<!--list-separator-->
<ul>
<li>
<p>Kill your darlings (during the monthly review).</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned this before, but it&rsquo;s just an important aspect of my &ldquo;system&rdquo;
that I would like to mention it again.</p>
<p>When I still used primitive task management systems such as <strong>everything else</strong>
that&rsquo;s not Org mode, the collection of more mature tasks would soon grow out of
control.</p>
<p>However, because I create a new Org mode file for every month, I have to copy
across manually any tasks that have not been completed yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WHY IS THAT NOT AUTOMATED YET?!&rdquo; you are probably thinking.</p>
<p>Well, the advantage of having to copy each task over manually is that it is the
ideal opportunity to evaluate the task and ask some hard questions as to its
continued relevance&hellip;</p>
<p>When a task gets too old, I will often make the decision to change its status
to <code>CANC</code> (for cancelled), sometimes with the reason for the cancellation
explained in the task body, and then just leave it there in the old month file.</p>
<p>With most of these task systems, regular reviews are of crucial importance. The
monthly start-over is a great, almost enforced, opportunity for review, as is
the morning routine when I instantiate the day planner template.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="org-agenda">Org-agenda</h4>
<p>Org-agenda is a standard Org mode feature which extracts, filters and then
shows a dynamic summary of projects and tasks from an arbitrary subset of org
files that you specify.</p>
<p>In my case, there are currently 15 org files that are consulted. This
collection evolves over time as projects and areas of responsibility come and
go.</p>
<p>I use <a href="https://github.com/alphapapa/org-super-agenda">org-super-agenda</a> for additional filtering and grouping, so that on an
average weekend day my agenda looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_21c3c5c773b616f5.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_a1ad2b977f25ead1.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_bcc9819fd36978b5.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_3ebda4b9a037d53e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_a1ad2b977f25ead1.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Semi-anonymised screenshot of my org-agenda on 2023-04-09"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Semi-anonymised screenshot of my org-agenda on 2023-04-09</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>One noteworthy extra here is that I have two lists of respectively my highest
level work and personal projects or areas of responsibility.</p>
<p>Sometimes when I get lost in the weeds, it helps to pull back to that level to
get a summary of <em>everything</em>.</p>
<p>Also, it really helped me to distinguish between projects (something with a
clear end and expected end date) vs areas of responsibility, something that
could continue indefinitely.</p>
<p>This distinction was inspired by the <a href="https://fortelabs.com/blog/para/">PARA method</a>, which has also influenced how
I organise a large subset of my filesystem.</p>
<p>On my better days, I manage to start work with a few minutes of active task and
project review (see <a href="#day-planning">Day planning</a>), and then Org agenda is incredibly useful.</p>
<h4 id="core-notes-database">Core notes database</h4>
<p>With &ldquo;database&rdquo; I of course refer to just over a thousand org (and a few
markdown, which form part of my org-roam database via <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">my md-roam changes</a>)
files, most of which find themselves in the top-level <code>pkb4000/pages</code> directory
(for logseq compatibility, story for a different time), adjacent to the
<code>journals</code> directory containing all of the monthly journal files.</p>
<p>There are files on various <code>rsync</code> and <code>ffmpeg</code> invocations, files on programming
languages, software tools, note-taking strategies, personal information on each
of my kids, and much more.</p>
<p>Org mode enables me to combine document structure, math, vector and bitmap
images and executable source code in many different languages.</p>
<p>I have configured my Emacs (where by &ldquo;configured&rdquo; I mean &ldquo;coded up the emacs
lisp for&rdquo;) to invoke ripgrep on different subsets of my notes database, and to
proffer up the results in different ways.</p>
<p>I can usually find anything that went in to this database at any point.</p>
<p>What I really like, is also being able to tell you on which day, and during
which hour, I learned this or that, or experimented with something or the
other.</p>
<p>On <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#isso-2654">February 26, 2020, a commenter on the 2019 post asked if I&rsquo;d taken a look at
org-roam</a>, a question to which my answer at that point was that I had looked
but not really gotten into it yet.</p>
<p>I just checked my notes (an <code>org-roam</code> buffer with backlinks, which sort of gives
away the story), and it turns out that a week later on March 3 of 2020 I indeed
got <code>org-roam</code> configured and running.</p>
<p>From that point on, it pretty much took over the <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#core-notes-database">core notes database</a> function
of my PKM.</p>
<p>Fortunately <code>org-roam</code> relies as much as possible on standard Org-mode
functionality while adding all of the instantaneous note searching, creation
and linking that has succeeded in drastically upgrading my Org-mode
implementation to a increasingly densely linked, tagged and far more useful
exocortex.</p>
<p>Although I <em>can</em> use <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> to visualize graphically the linkage in my
notes database, as shown below, I don&rsquo;t often do it. However, I <em>do</em> really often
follow internal links around, so I do my best to create them when and where I
can.</p>










<figure><a href="2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_40728afff6cb72c1.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_e5f7f59d0dd72b3f.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_731f5640e231f1ed.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_7c90998ffb6d57fd.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_e5f7f59d0dd72b3f.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 4: A screenshot of org-roam-ui showing a part of my knowledge base in February of 2022."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 4: </span>A screenshot of org-roam-ui showing a part of my knowledge base in February of 2022.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I really appreciate and use the flexibility that org-roam offers in having
notes either be complete files, or headings within larger files.</p>
<h4 id="project-files">Project files</h4>
<p>Work and personal projects, and areas of responsibility, each get their own Org
file. Some projects even get a whole directory to themselves, in cases where
the project will have many more files than just the main Org file.</p>
<p>Each project / area org file has its own <code>Tasks</code> and datetree sections, similar
to the month journal.</p>
<h4 id="email-linking">Email linking</h4>
<p>An important part of knowledge and task management is one&rsquo;s emails.</p>
<p>Although I currently prefer processing my email using <a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email"><code>mu4e</code></a>, an email client
which lives inside of Emacs, I have used other tools in the past, and will
probably use new tools in the future.</p>
<p>Even at this moment I alternate between <code>mu4e</code> and the <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">FastMail</a> web-interface.</p>
<p>Long story short, I have it setup so that I can easily convert any email in
<code>mu4e</code> into a universal <code>message://message-id</code> link to be integrated with a new
task or note entry.</p>
<p>When I later open that link using a shortcut, I have programmed it so that <code>mu4e</code>
will open the relevant email if it is active, or the <code>FastMail</code> webmail when it
is not. From here I can either review the email to see what the associated task
requires, or respond to it, if the task has been completed.</p>
<p>Some of these <code>message://</code> links were created using macOS mail and they still
work. In future, if I add a new mail client to the mix, I will still be able to
jump to specific old emails, no matter where they find themselves inside of my
FastMail mailboxes.</p>
<h3 id="mobile">Mobile</h3>
<p>My workflow  on mobile can be summarised as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Rapidly find info that I need from my notes using the converted Obsidian
Vault (see below).</li>
<li>Very occasionally I edit org files using <a href="https://plainorg.com/">PlainOrg</a>. Once this app gets the
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/plainorg/comments/rfivtn/feature_request_search_directory/">often-requested directory search function</a>, I hope to use it more for
retrieval as well.</li>
<li>Keep up to date with online material via paid-for <a href="https://www.inoreader.com/">InoReader</a> (RSS), <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha">Mastodon</a>,
and reddit (tiny &ldquo;argh&rdquo; there).</li>
<li>Either save interesting articles as PDF into <code>03-Resources/refs/YEAR</code> via the OneDrive
Files integration, or send the link into
<code>pkb4000/journals/YEAR/inbox-mobile.org</code> via <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/2020/04/30/voice-capture-org-mode-notes-and-more-using-siri-shortcuts-on-ios/">my Siri shortcut</a> automation,
slightly modified to write to the local org file which will be synced via
SyncThing.
<ul>
<li>On mobile, I strongly recommend the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/extensions/safari">Print Friendly &amp; PDF bookmarklet</a> to
strip out all of the cruft, yielding PDFs that focus on the content.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Scan and OCR any invoices and other physical documents to PDF using
<a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/microsoft-lens-for-ios-fbdca5f4-1b1b-4391-a931-dc1c2582397b">Microsoft Lens</a>. Previously I used the Dropbox scan app for this.</li>
<li>There are a small number of markdown files which I mostly need to edit on
mobile. <a href="https://1writerapp.com/">1writer</a> is great for this, thanks to preview, directory search,
favourited directories and files.</li>
<li>I keep a small subset of ephemeral notes (think loyalty cards, shopping
lists) in Apple Notes because it&rsquo;s still the quickest to open up to the note
that I need, almost in one action.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="syncthing">SyncThing</h4>
<p>An important improvement here over my 2019 setup is the addition of the
paid-for <a href="https://www.mobiussync.com/">Möbius Sync</a> iPhone app in order to keep full copies of my read/write
org database and its read-only Obsidian Vault version (see below) on the phone.</p>
<p>Apps like <a href="https://plainorg.com/">PlainOrg</a> and <a href="https://1writerapp.com/">1writer</a> work really well, even rendering image
attachments (which I use often), when you have a fully local copy of the files.</p>
<h4 id="obsidian-for-efficient-notes-access-on-mobile">Obsidian for efficient notes access on mobile</h4>
<p>Recently, inspired by Jethro Kuan&rsquo;s braindump scripts, I created <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/braindump4000">braindump4000</a>,
which I have hooked up to a cronjob to convert (incrementally of course) my
whole org mode database into an Obsidian Vault.</p>
<p>This vault is synced to the correct location on my phone using the Möbius Sync
SyncThing app so that I can use the Obsidian mobile app to access my whole
database.</p>
<p>Due to much better UX, this has (fortunately) almost completely replaced the
use of <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">my slightly strange system for converting my org database into docx
files</a>, although said strange system is still useful to ensure that OneDrive&rsquo;s
lacklustre search is able to find notes when I do a global search.</p>
<h2 id="noteworthy-changes-since-the-2019-version">Noteworthy changes since the 2019 version</h2>
<h3 id="replacing-dropbox-with-onedrive">Replacing Dropbox with OneDrive</h3>
<p>After more than a decade, I switched out Dropbox for OneDrive. You can <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#byeeeeee-dropbox">read
more about the switch in this post</a>, but in short:</p>
<ul>
<li>I <strong>really</strong> enjoyed using Dropbox Paper, but it meant I had a bunch of info
stuck in the Dropbox cloud (not synced file on disk).</li>
<li>Dropbox were really dragging their feet migrating us loyal customers to the
2020 Paper version, and they were being <em>frustratingly</em> opaque about it. This
was a reminder to take and maintain control of one&rsquo;s own files.</li>
<li>For the record, Dropbox&rsquo;s syncing is substantially faster (lower latency)
than OneDrive, and, although I have not yet had any issues with OneDrive,
Dropbox has been extremely solid for me for over a decade, in spite of my
over half a million files, <a href="/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/#yes-you-can-keep-your-checked-out-source-code-in-dropbox-or-onedrive">including many active git repos</a>.</li>
<li>However, I was already paying $80 / year for Microsoft 365 Family, which
includes Office software licenses for the whole family (initially the main
reason to get it) and 6 x 1 TB OneDrive accounts vs. a minimum of $120 / year
for Dropbox for me only&hellip; Currently, the difference in practical functioning
does not justify that extra money, plus that I felt I had to vote with my
wallet re the frustrating Dropbox Paper situation.</li>
<li>On the bright side, being able to switch out the main cloud sync layer of my
system ensures that it&rsquo;s just a sync layer, and not sync-layer plus services
which subtly lock you in.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="org-roam-for-interlinked-atomic-notes">org-roam for interlinked atomic notes</h3>
<p>I have already written about this, but org-roam more than deserves a place on
this list for the drastic way in which it improved how I take and use notes.</p>
<h3 id="braindump4000-obsidian-to-access-notes-on-the-go">braindump4000: Obsidian to access notes on the go</h3>
<p>Over the years I have attempted to compensate for the lack of a worthy Emacs
representative on the iPhone first by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">importing my database to Apple Notes</a>
(updates are very tricky), then through <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">a bulk docx conversion</a> (klunky and
ugly, but updates work, and I <em>can</em> find stuff in a pinch) and now finally using
<a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/braindump4000">braindump4000</a>, in obsidian mode, to convert to and update an Obsidian Vault
which is synced to my phone via SyncThing.</p>
<p>Note that you can also use braindump4000 to generate a Hugo website with all of
your notes, which was initially the main motivation to build it!</p>
<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</h2>
<p>One of the aspects which has convincingly remained the same in my whole
personal knowledge management setup is&hellip;</p>
<p>Emacs.</p>
<p>Over the years I have seen, and sometimes been thoroughly tempted, by all of
the brilliant new tools that have gone by: Roam, Notion, Dendron, LogSeq,
Obsidian and many more.</p>
<p>However, the power of a tool which can be so thoroughly shaped as Emacs should
not be under-estimated.</p>
<p>The more I use it, the more I learn how to make it sing in new and interesting
ways.</p>
<p>The other advantage of this constant in particular, is that the utility of a
knowledge base can grow tremendously when you can consistently work on that
same system, accruing knowledge whilst all the while evolving the system itself
to remain useful in an ever-changing environment.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #233: Atomic party sections</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</guid><description> Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.
Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hu_b43453af35cff7b1.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hu_f377c56d7e1c1f0d.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hu_afbc71f86a8d1b07.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hu_5accfc89c195f3c8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hu_f377c56d7e1c1f0d.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering
the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="don-t--stress-for-success--aka-4000-weeks-at-60">(Don&rsquo;t) Stress for success (aka 4000 weeks at 60%)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s really quite busy at work, perhaps even verging on the slightly too busy
territory.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m consistently putting in stretches of focused, high intensity work to help
push us into calmer waters.</p>
<p>However, in spite of all of this, my stress levels seem to have have subsided
to quite an extent over the last few weeks.</p>
<p>This could be ascribed to me slowly moving out of <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">new challenge discomfort
territory</a>, because I&rsquo;m either getting better at what I&rsquo;m supposed to be doing,
or, if you want to be cynical, I just care a little less.</p>
<p>Maybe these two are the same.</p>
<p>I like to think that it could also be the growing effect of <em>Four Thousand
Weeks: Time and How to Use It</em>, <a href="/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/#how-i-m-putting-down-my-work">the book I mentioned in WHV-231</a> that so
eloquently and quite urgently makes the case that because life is so stupidly
short, and you&rsquo;re not even going to get close to Getting your Things Done, and
that working hard so that you can relax at some future point in time is a
terribly imprudent approach forced upon us by our instrumentalist society, you
should instead do your best extracting every bit of enjoyment from every moment
that you get, when you get it.</p>
<p>Every morning is an opportunity for a mini coffee and breakfast party, and
every evening is an opportunity for a mini dinner party, both of these with the
people, big and small, I hold the most dear.</p>
<p>Every day I do need to work, but there is ample opportunity for curiosity, for
learning, and for offering a helping hand.</p>
<p>There is generally also time to go out for a wide-open-perception run in the
sun.</p>
<p>All of this is available to you if you can just learn how to keep your own set
of instrumentalising demons safely locked up in their cages. (these are the
gremlins who keep on bugging you to try to finish one more thing.)</p>
<p>As Burkeman writes on page 144:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To the philosophers of the ancient world, leisure wasn&rsquo;t the means to some
other end; on the contrary, it was the end to which everything else worth doing
was a means.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Back in <a href="/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/#flip-it">WHV #222, I tried to say something similar, just far less eloquently</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve completed only a pinch over 60% of the book. I might have more to say when
it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">Dropbox Paper (aka mobile note-taking evolving)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s no secret around these parts that <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#mobile">the mobile aspects of my otherwise
pretty respectable note-taking game are weak</a>. (In short: Emacs Org mode is
amazing and can do <em>anything</em>, <strong>except</strong> when on my iPhone. Moar shorter: iPhone =
Org mode Kryptonite)</p>
<p>Somehow, in spite of being so deep in with Dropbox, and in spite of using
<a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper">Dropbox Paper</a> for other things, I overlooked it when evaluating solutions for
mobile note capture all the way back in 2019.</p>
<p>This weekend, because I had to scrounge around for an important bit of
information I <em>knew</em> I had stored somewhere (it turned out to be in my Apple
Notes doh), I spent some time trying to find a tool that would give me
mobile-editable notes that would turn up more readily in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that Dropbox Paper documents turn up in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Who would have guessed?!</p>
<p>In addition to that, Paper has:</p>
<ul>
<li>markdown support</li>
<li>syntax highlighting of triple-backtick source code blocks</li>
<li>LaTeX math!</li>
<li>embedding of arbitrary media which gets automatically uploaded to dropbox on
drag and drop</li>
<li>easy linking to other Paper docs</li>
<li>checklists</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Cue sound of another personal knowledge management puzzle piece snapping into place&hellip;</em></p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m not allowed to talk about it here, because the blog post in question
happened <em>after</em> this blog post&rsquo;s legally allowed observed timespan, but shortly
in the future, I will also solve the issue of being able to search through and
preview all of my Org mode notes on the iPhone.</p>
<p>Post is on vxlabs if you&rsquo;re from the (near) future.</p>
<h2 id="a-truly-spectacular-long-weekend-in-betty-s">A truly spectacular long weekend in Betty&rsquo;s</h2>
<p>The second week ended with a weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay that was so spectacular
that it deserves its own section in this blog post.</p>
<p>Well this is it. The section dedicated to the weekend. I hope you like it.</p>
<h2 id="the-section-at-the-end">The section at the end</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this.</p>
<p>I wish you continuous and consistent atomic party moments.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #216: Sup?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</guid><description>Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.
Figure 1: Sup?
The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard with Lots of Focus.
I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily application of the One Main Thing idea, but experience has taught me that it&amp;rsquo;s probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&amp;rsquo;ll be solidly back in the arms of my old friend the really slippery eel.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks
from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="sup_bettys.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_fb2d17c10710e237.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_44250e253e07a2d6.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_f280c2aa6b5952a1.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_229a3bd50666e81d.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_44250e253e07a2d6.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sup?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Sup?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard
with Lots of Focus.</p>
<p>I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily
application of <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">the One Main Thing idea</a>, but experience has taught me that it&rsquo;s
probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure
factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&rsquo;ll be solidly
back in the arms of my old friend the <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">really slippery eel</a>.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I have been making good use of the (temporarily?)
increased capacity.</p>
<h2 id="fresh-from-the-oven-vxlabs-software-development-handbook">Fresh from the oven: vxlabs software development handbook</h2>
<p><a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/">The vxlabs software development handbook</a>, at the time of this writing about 65%
complete (that&rsquo;s a random number that my brain gives me every time I publish a
new version), is now available over on my nerdy blog.</p>
<p>If you are working with a smaller development team, or you&rsquo;re starting with a
new dev team, the handbook is not the worst place to look for development
process tips. Furthermore, it&rsquo;s available under the Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License, so you can copy and paste and rebrand to
your heart&rsquo;s content as long as you give due credit somewhere to the original
author (me and vxlabs).</p>
<p>In the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll be trying to complete more sections to get closer to
that mythical 100% completion grade.</p>
<h2 id="two-miscellaneous-tips-for-nerds">Two miscellaneous tips for nerds</h2>
<h3 id="printfriendly-on-your-phone">PrintFriendly on your phone</h3>
<p>You might remember from my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#web-pages-and-articles">2019 note-taking strategy post</a> that I convert all
interesting web pages I come across to PDF and dump them in my dropbox.</p>
<p>This has turned out to be the best way to store web-pages for later searching,
reference and winning of arguments.</p>
<p>However, the mobile part of that strategy was traditionally weak, as is also
discussed in that post.</p>
<p>The problem was that Safari on iPhone has a great reading mode that strips ads
and other unnecessary bits, but when you print from reading mode, the PDF is
formatted for mobile, and, more importantly, there&rsquo;s no way to get the source
URL embedded in the PDF.</p>
<p>Anyways, after years of using the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/">PrintFriendly</a> browser extension on the
desktop (as is also explained in the note-taknig post), I finally got around to
installing their mobile bookmarklet on the iPhone. (this should work on any
mobile browser)</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/extensions/iOS">instructions are a bit finicky</a>, but one ends up with a bookmark that you
can activate on any page to have the printfriendly service pre-process that
page for reading, from which you can tap on the print icon to get a mostly
perfect PDF that is also stamped with the source URL!</p>
<h3 id="fish-shell">Fish shell</h3>
<p>After years of resisting all the zsh blog posts and especially the pretty
oh-my-zsh powerline prompts and sticking to my stock standard bash because
get-off-my-lawn, I finally broke down and installed&hellip;</p>
<p><a href="https://fishshell.com/">fish!</a></p>
<p>fish shell is a &ldquo;smart and user-friendly command line shell for Linux, macOS,
and the rest of the family&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I like it because one of its goals is to be more useful with hardly any extra
configuration, but you can also install <a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/oh-my-fish">oh-my-fish</a> with my new favourite theme
<a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/theme-bobthefish">bobthefish</a>.</p>
<p>I <em>was</em> planning to convince you of my choice with a number of technical
reasons, but it is now clear to me that technical arguments are irrelevant when
you can rock a theme called &ldquo;bobthefish&rdquo;.</p>
<p>P.S. Let me know in the comments if you would still prefer to talk about
technical reasons.</p>
<h2 id="a-brief-pause">A brief pause</h2>
<p>Since we <a href="/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/#gou-1-s-growing-running-habit">last spoke about GOU#1&rsquo;s running habit</a>, it gives me great pleasure to
report that she has, quite routinely if I may add, done another two or three
10k runs, one of them even up to eleven by accident.</p>
<p>Folks I wish you all the best. I look forward to our next connection!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #209: Blogging like it's 2009</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 10:08:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/</guid><description> Figure 1: Surprise sun in the second half of a rainy run
Two days ago, as I pressed the &amp;ldquo;publish&amp;rdquo; button on WHV #208 (well, it&amp;rsquo;s actually more me doing the t d C-c C-e H H shortcut key sequence in Emacs, but OK), I knew that #209 was going to be a problem.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="lourensford_sun_peeking_out.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/lourensford_sun_peeking_out_hu_f935d35d84ea853.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/lourensford_sun_peeking_out_hu_636d933e0af96445.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/lourensford_sun_peeking_out_hu_b9e0af4cdb5ea75c.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/lourensford_sun_peeking_out_hu_c5fec5f8df53cd0e.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/lourensford_sun_peeking_out_hu_636d933e0af96445.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Surprise sun in the second half of a rainy run"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Surprise sun in the second half of a rainy run</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Two days ago, as I pressed the &ldquo;publish&rdquo; button on WHV #208 (well, it&rsquo;s
actually more me doing the <code>t d C-c C-e H H</code> shortcut key sequence in Emacs,
but OK), I knew that #209 was going to be a problem.</p>
<p>Although the past week, from Monday November 2 to Sunday November 8, certainly
had its share of events quite important to me, none of them are fit for
publication, and none of the concomitant observations can be abstracted
concretely enough (yes, I see what I did there :) to appear here.</p>
<h2 id="searching-for-balance-014-in-2020">Searching for Balance 014 in 2020</h2>
<p>So I considered either postponing a week, or perhaps just mentioning the fact
that Joris Voorn released, on November 6, a brand new album with tracks and
mixes, this time the collection titled <a href="https://www.globalunderground.co.uk/product/gu43-deluxe-edition/">&ldquo;GU43: Joris Voorn, Rotterdam&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>(Thank you <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">TPN</a> for again bringing this musical gift under my attention.)</p>
<p>This new release is an important event to me, because I have been wondering for
quite a number of years now if we&rsquo;d ever be graced by a spiritual follow-up to
Voorn&rsquo;s Balance 014.</p>
<p>You see, if my life in 2009 had had a soundtrack, Balance 014 would be it.</p>
<p>It was an important part of the flavour of that whole sweet year, and to a
certain extent also of that of the year after that.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s jump back there for a spell:</p>
<h2 id="my-2009-year-mix">My 2009 year mix</h2>
<p>2009 was the year of my first mini-sabbatical, a <a href="/2009/04/25/my-first-sabbatical/">month-long academic visit to
the University of Magdeburg</a>.</p>
<p>That period in my memory is enveloped in the warm fuzzies, for the largest part
thanks to the lovely people I had the privilege of sharing a bit of life with
there in the spring.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think the comparative visualization tool I started working on as main
goal of the sabbatical ever led to anything directly. I do regret that the
abbreviation I came up with, namely &ldquo;CoMedI&rdquo;, for &ldquo;Compare Medical Images&rdquo;, did
not see any further use.</p>
<p>Anyways, I remember a number of multi-hour train trips between Delft,
Magdeburg, Berlin and elsewhere, almost always with Balance 014 on my
headphones.</p>
<p>2009 was also the year of:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">me getting on twitter for the first time</a></li>
<li><a href="/2009/05/21/you-must-vaccinate/">my slightly angry pro-vaccination post</a>, mostly because I was quite surprised
(actually a bit shocked) that even people in <em>my</em> circles were doubting
this. If I could only have known&hellip;</li>
<li><a href="/2009/06/14/eurovis-2009/">EuroVis 2009 in Berlin</a></li>
<li><a href="/2009/06/25/bill-buxton-at-cars-2009/">CARS 2009 and Bill Buxton in Berlin</a></li>
<li><a href="/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/">friend and TU Delft roomie TNR&rsquo;s PhD defence</a></li>
<li><a href="/2009/09/20/weekly-head-voices-4-the-new-roomie-medvis-at-mevis-fairy-tale-beach/">visit to MeVis in Bremen</a></li>
<li><a href="/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/">a number of infamous bets made at IEEE VIS in Atlanta</a>. Although I lost the
heads-up display bet (at one point right before Google Glass didn&rsquo;t really
make it, it looked like I could have won) and I&rsquo;m probably going to lose bet
#2 as well, do take note of <a href="/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/#bet-3-the-future-of-conferences">&ldquo;Bet #3: In 2029, distributed conferences with
tele-presence will be common.&rdquo;</a>  How things have changed in the past few
months&hellip;</li>
</ul>
<p>I left by far the most relevant year 2009 event for last:</p>
<p><a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">2009 was also the birth of the Weekly Head Voices</a>, shortly after the Lowlands
festival of that year, which coincidentally was a positively <em>ridiculous</em>
amount of fun.</p>
<p>So, GU#43 this year leads me, via Balance 014, all the way back to the origin
of the WHV in the year 2009.</p>
<p>Did you notice the number of this edition of the WHV?</p>
<p>Entirely coincidentally, it&rsquo;s 209!</p>
<h3 id="tangent-a-life-without-notes">Tangent: A life without notes</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s quite shocking how little I have in my notes (or anywhere for that matter)
about that year.</p>
<p>After quite some digging, I finally discovered where I kept my notes then: I
was going through my google docs phase (HEY IT WAS REALLY SHINY!), with bunches
of draft blog posts imported from another much-loved but long-dead google
product called google notebook.</p>
<p>For the past few years now, I have journals of almost every single day, and I
can find any of them pretty quickly.</p>
<p>It feels strange, perhaps even a little scary, trying to page back into 2009,
and finding only a few google docs, backed-up photos from the Nokia E71 I used
then, a few blog posts, and what I could extract from my own imperfect wetware.</p>
<h2 id="thank-you-joris">Thank you Joris</h2>
<p>So, is GU43 the spiritual successor I&rsquo;ve been waiting for?</p>
<p>No dreamy brain, of course it isn&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>What would that even mean, for a favourite artist&rsquo;s new work to be a spiritual
successor of a particular previous work?</p>
<p>Thanks to my memories of 2009 and its music and its <em>feelings</em> pleasantly
echoing over the years in some subset of the trillions of synapses in my head,
I had imagined that this new work, the successor, might be able to bring those
feelings back to life, magically.</p>
<p>It can&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>The musical echoes of Balance 014 can certainly be heard in GU43, inevitably
transmitted through the hands of the artist, but this is a new soundtrack
waiting for new adventures.</p>
<p>Memory neurons fire pleasantly, until they are repurposed for new experiences,
forever forgetting their history.</p>
<p>I am grateful for the music, both for remembering, and for forgetting.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #180: EnsembleYou and The Describers.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 22:08:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/</guid><description> Dear friends,
Welcome to this, the 180th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I perform retrospection on the week from Monday September 30 to Sunday October 6, 2019.
To be more specific, this is mostly indirect retrospection, meaning that I think about and attempt to describe the thoughts I had about topics and events that might or might not have occurred in the period of time that this post is ostensibly looking back on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="vergelegen_running_shot.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_5bcfc02c2265e1df.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_4c46c4ed0b003324.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_b5c11d35c063a837.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_9f8c2d4bb52b3f6.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/vergelegen_running_shot_hu_4c46c4ed0b003324.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>Welcome to this, the 180th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I
perform retrospection on the week from Monday September 30 to Sunday October 6,
2019.</p>
<p>To be more specific, this is mostly indirect retrospection, meaning that I
think about and attempt to describe the thoughts I had about topics and events
that might or might not have occurred in the period of time that this post is
ostensibly looking back on.</p>
<h2 id="twifraf-progress-report">TwiFRaF progress report.</h2>
<p>Almost a month ago, all the way back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">WHV
#177</a>,
I announced that I would be cutting out TwiFRaF (Twitter, Facebook, Reddit and
Friends) from my information diet.</p>
<p>This has been going quite well.</p>
<p>Subjectively, I&rsquo;ve been spending substantially more time on more constructive
activities. Also important, my work-day focus has improved; there seems to be
more of it to go around.</p>
<p>However&hellip; A part of the vacuum left by TwiFRaF was being sneakily filled by
YouTube recommender riding.</p>
<p>You know, load the YouTube main page, SEE ALL THOSE SUPER INTERESTING RANDOM
CLIPS WHICH THE YOUTUBE AI <em>KNOWS</em> WILL GET YOU (in my case movie trailers,
movie reviews and analyses, comics, <a href="https://youtu.be/T_rDA-7E_ys">running</a>,
HOW TO GET CHISELED (no idea how that got in there), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/SaturdayNightLive">Saturday Night Live
clips</a>, running really terribly
far, some programming or computer thing) and middle-click on about five of &rsquo;em.</p>
<p>Watch the clips, reload the main page, repeat!</p>
<p>As entertaining as this was, most of it couldn&rsquo;t really count as a constructive
use of my time, and so, at the start of October, TwiFraF was summarily upgraded
to TwiFraF-Yo.</p>
<p>For the past week, I have observed a further uptick in the quantity and quality
of my focus.</p>
<h2 id="the-describers">The Describers.</h2>
<p>Thanks to an <em>excellent</em> recommendation by friend PK (he of <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/">the introducing of
the rider and the
elephant</a>, I&rsquo;m
currently reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stumbling_on_Happiness"><em>Stumbling on
Happiness</em></a> by the
Harvard psychologist Daniel Gilbert.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m only about a third of the way through, but so far this tome is filled to
the brim with knowledge about the thinking and feeling parts of the human
machine.</p>
<p>(As an aside, the topic of <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/#life-is-but-a-dream">the story I wrote in WHV #174 which no-one
noticed</a>,
you know the one about your experience of reality being mostly synthesised and
hallucinated in real-time, was discussed at length by Gilbert (the topic, not
my story of course). According to Gilbert, this is what the philosopher
Immanuel Kant introduced into the world under the label <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transcendental_idealism">(Transcendental)
Idealism</a>. Knowing this,
I feel like slightly less of a barbarian now.)</p>
<p>What I would like to focus on here though, is <em>The Describers</em>.</p>
<p>Gilbert talks about their research on <em>focalism</em>, the human tendency to place
too much weight on one piece of information when making a prediction or a
decision.</p>
<p>In <a href="http://people.virginia.edu/~tdw/wilson,focalism.pdf">their 2000 paper</a>,
they discuss an experiment where they compared two groups of college students
(psychology research, also the important parts, is positively riddled with
experiments on college students) with regard to their ability to predict the
future emotional impact of a negative event, in this case, losing some
important (just run with it, please) football match to some rival college.</p>
<p>The difference between the two groups is that they asked the one group, which
they named <em>The Describers</em> (capitals and emphasis mine, I like all of the
story-telling possibilities), to describe the events of a typical day (see p823
in the paper, this was a structured questionnaire), <em>before</em> predicting the
impact of that future negative event.</p>
<p>In the end, the non-describers over-estimated the impact of the loss on their
happiness, whilst the describers predicted much more accurately.</p>
<p>Although the main reason I&rsquo;m writing about this here is that I&rsquo;ve really taken
a liking to the name <em>The Describers</em>, it will not have escaped you, astute
readers, that this is yet another convoluted reason <a href="/tags/note-taking/"><em>to write stuff
down</em></a>.</p>
<p>If the research above can be believed, and here I have to divulge that my life
(debating) partner is still highly sceptical, journalling could contribute
positively to the quality of your prediction and decision-making.</p>
<p>At the very least, the hypothesis that taking the time to re-process and
document one&rsquo;s thoughts, observations and reasoning could contribute positively
to one&rsquo;s judgement seems eminently plausible to me.</p>
<h2 id="ensembleyoutm">EnsembleYou(tm).</h2>
<p>In machine learning, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ensemble_learning">ensemble
methods</a> combine multiple
different classifiers or algorithms, which in many cases comes down to simply
averaging their output predictions, in order to obtain better accuracy than any
of the constituent classifiers.</p>
<p>As I was chatting with a mathematical friend from work the other day, I rambled
on and on (sorry mathematical friend) right into the idea of EnsembleYou(tm).</p>
<p>It was actualy the unsurprising admission that the in-the-moment me is really
not very good at predictions, decisions or anything else.</p>
<p>However, continuously writing everything down is one practical way of averaging
out the observations and decisions of a whole bunch of instantaneous mes, or
yous.</p>
<p>(More specifically, this was about the fact that the &ldquo;Vitals&rdquo; section of <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#monthly-journal-files">my
monthly journal
files</a>,
containing lists of reminders for a good life, is copied from month to month,
evolving slowly as I add, remove and incrementally improve its contents.)</p>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through
time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less
faulty entity.</p>
<p>I am calling this specific composite entity EnsembleCharl, but because I would
like to give the <em>idea</em> to you, <em>that</em> will go through life as EnsembleYou(tm)!</p>
<h2 id="friendly-wishes">Friendly Wishes.</h2>
<p>Friends(es), I wish you effortless connectivity, and great wisdom in your
multiplicity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Note-taking strategy 2019.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 16:19:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/</guid><description>At the start of 2016, I published an overview of my note-taking strategy then.
In the intervening three and a half years, my note-taking has further evolved to adapt to my changing environment, and the underlying &amp;ldquo;system&amp;rdquo; has co-evolved to support this.
Although note-taking is at the core of the system, a more accurate description of its current purpose would be personal knowledge management.
What you&amp;rsquo;ll also find in this post, is the culmination of many years of lessons learned trying to &amp;ldquo;keep a lab journal&amp;rdquo;.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>At the start of 2016, I published an <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">overview of my note-taking strategy
then</a>.</p>
<p>In the intervening three and a half years, my note-taking has further evolved
to adapt to my changing environment, and the underlying &ldquo;system&rdquo; has co-evolved
to support this.</p>
<p>Although note-taking is at the core of the system, a more accurate description
of its current purpose would be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_knowledge_management"><em>personal knowledge
management</em></a>.</p>
<p>What you&rsquo;ll also find in this post, is the culmination of many years of lessons
learned trying to <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#three">&ldquo;keep a lab
journal&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p><em>Note: You can now also read my more recent post <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/">Note-taking strategy
2023</a>.</em></p>
<h2 id="highest-level-overview-of-note-taking-system">Highest level overview of note-taking system.</h2>
<p>My approach consists of four main components:</p>
<p>At the core of everything is <a href="https://orgmode.org/"><strong>1. Emacs Org mode</strong></a>.</p>
<p>As you might know, Org mode is infinitely flexible. This is where all of my
projects and tasks are tracked. This is also where I keep my daily personal and
work journals.</p>
<p>I describe the specific directory structure and orgfile setup in the sections
below.</p>
<p>I continually and actively search for and find interesting <strong>2. Web-pages and
Articles</strong>, both academic and less so, which I convert to PDF and store in a
year-stamped directory inside of my
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">JBOP</a>.</p>
<p><strong>3. Academic articles</strong> that I plan to refer to in my own writings graduate into my
Zotero bibliographic database, which is synced together with everything else.</p>
<p>On <strong>4. Mobile</strong> (phone and watch, oh my!), I use the Dropbox app for capturing
and for limited access to my notes database via a small subset of markdown
files, PDFs and exported HTML, and I use the new WatchOS 6 voice notes if I&rsquo;m
not able to use my phone.</p>
<h3 id="other-noteworthy-characteristics">Other noteworthy characteristics.</h3>
<p>Everything mentioned above lives on local drives, synced with Dropbox and also
automatically and continuously backed-up to a removable disk at my office.</p>
<p>The Org mode part of the system has been in use since 2014. I have also
imported a few years of Simplenote text notes into Org mode, so its memory
stretches a bit further back still.</p>
<p>The longer the system lasts, the more valuable it gets.</p>
<p>It has now happened more than once that I could help someone with the same
advice I helped someone else with 4 years ago, simply because the real-time
text search found the relevant snippet of code or attachment in my Org mode
database.</p>
<p>Even if I were ever to change tools, the current single source of truth is a
collection of plaintext org files and PDF files which can easily be further
processed and imported into some new system.</p>
<h2 id="the-components-in-slightly-more-detail">The components in slightly more detail.</h2>
<p>In the following sections, I explain each of the four components in more detail
than in the overview above.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-org-mode">Emacs Org mode.</h3>
<p>The heart of my knowledge management system, let&rsquo;s call it <code>pkb4000</code>, is <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Emacs
Org mode</a>. Org mode, or &ldquo;Your life in plaintext&rdquo;, is a
powerful text-file-based system for managing notes, task lists, projects and
even authoring documents.</p>
<p>Once you get used to the programmable flexibility it offers, you will find it
hard to go back to any conventional system.</p>
<h4 id="monthly-journal-files">Monthly journal files.</h4>
<p>In my main Org mode directory, I have a subdirectory named <code>journals</code>, which
contains a directory for each year.</p>
<p>Each of these year directories contains an <code>.org</code> file for each month, so we would have for example
<code>journals/2019/2019-09-Sep.org</code>.</p>
<p>Each month file follows the structure showed in the following redacted version
of my current journal file:</p>
<!-- I used M-x htmlize-region-save-screenshot to get this HTML representation of a real org file onto the clipboard. -->
<pre style="color: #DCDCCC; background-color: #3F3F3F;">
<span style="color: #b3b3b3;">#+TITLE:</span> <span style="color: #8CD0D3; background-color: #3F3F3F; font-weight: bold;">2019-09 September month journal
</span>
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Vitals</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Focus items</span>
Topics and reminders I would like to spend a few minutes on during every
morning review: High value time, always be compounding, always be in a focus
block, etc.
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tired list</span>
A general list of valuable activities for when I have some time, but brain too
tired to come up with anything.
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Planning / overview / major done list</span>
Check lists with books, courses, etc.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Projects</span>
A list of current major projects, with links to each project's dedicated org
file.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks</span>
A list of Org mode tasks that are not associated with specific projects. This
list is reviewed at the start of every month, as I have to manually copy across
those tasks that are still relevant and important.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019-09 September</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">**</span><span style="color: #7CB8BB; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019-09-19 Thursday (example day)</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">***</span><span style="color: #D0BF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Day planning </span><span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-09-19 Thu 09:17]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Done list / thoughts / diary</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks for today </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[/]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[/]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Focus blocks</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Sleep</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Review </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[3/8]</span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> <span style="color: #D0BF8F; text-decoration: underline;"><a href="*Vitals">Month vitals</a></span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> Calendar
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> Org tasks
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> <span style="color: #D0BF8F; text-decoration: underline;"><a href="file:~/Dropbox/notes/mobile/inbox/">dropbox mobile inbox</a></span>
      - ...

<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Habits / important </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[7/12]</span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> 7.5 hrs sleep last night
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> are you satisfied with number of pomodori? = 0 (v R)
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> did you write stuff down?
      - ...
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">***</span><span style="color: #D0BF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* is dropbox better than evernote for mobile capturing? </span><span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">&lt;2019-09-19 Thu 22:16&gt;</span>

     in ios, with any page in safari, I can do "save to dropbox" and get a PDF
     version of the page for the <span style="color: #b3b3b3;">=notes/mobile/inbox=</span>.
</pre>
<p>As you can see from the example above, the monthly journal file is the main
index to my current high-level goals and focus items, my currently running work
and personal projects, miscellaneous tasks, and my detailed daily journalling
and habit tracking.</p>
<h5 id="daily-review">Daily review.</h5>
<p>When I start the day, I instantiate a new org-capture &ldquo;day planning&rdquo; template
by pressing <code>C-c c p</code>.</p>
<p>This creates the <code>Day planning</code> subsection with all of its subsections and
checklists. As you will see, this guides me through the morning review, which
in turn has me check each of those additional sources of incoming information
and tasks.</p>
<p>New bits of information are filed into their correct place, whilst the task
review shows me a list of tasks, extracted from the month file and the list of
current project files, so that I can decide which ones should be taken on.</p>
<p>I list tasks which should preferably be taken care of today under <code>Tasks for today</code>, whilst any really high-value high-satisfaction tasks go under <code>Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl</code>.</p>
<h5 id="during-the-day">During the day.</h5>
<p>During the rest of the day, I&rsquo;ll write short diary-like notes under <code>Done list / thoughts / diary</code> and log pomodori (focus blocks) under, you guessed it,
<code>Focus blocks</code>, either using the <code>org-pomodoro</code> package, or plain Org mode
clocking in and out functions.</p>
<p>I use additional custom org-capture templates, via keyboard shortcuts, to
create more extensive timestamped journal entries (see the <code>is dropbox better ...</code> example) and to create new timestamped and logged Org mode <code>TODO</code> entries.</p>
<h5 id="kill-your-darlings-during-the-monthly-review">Kill your darlings (during the monthly review).</h5>
<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned this before, but it&rsquo;s just an important aspect of my &ldquo;system&rdquo;
that I would like to mention it again.</p>
<p>When I still used primitive task management systems such as <em>everything else</em>
that&rsquo;s not Org mode, the collection of more mature tasks would soon grow out of
control.</p>
<p>However, because I create a new Org mode file for every month, I have to copy
across manually any tasks that have not been completed yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WHY IS THAT NOT AUTOMATED YET?!&rdquo; you are probably thinking.</p>
<p>Well, the advantage of having to copy each task over manually is that it is the
ideal opportunity to evaluate the task and ask some hard questions as to its
continued relevance&hellip;</p>
<p>When a task gets too old, I will often make the decision to change its status
to <code>CANC</code> (for cancelled), sometimes with the reason for the cancellation
explained in the task body, and then just leave it there in the old month file.</p>
<p>With most of these task systems, regular reviews are of crucial importance. The
monthly start-over is a great, almost enforced, opportunity for review, as is
the morning routine when I instantiate the day planner template.</p>
<h5 id="what-about-email">What about email?!</h5>
<p>An important part of knowledge and task management is one&rsquo;s emails.</p>
<p>Although I currently prefer processing my email using
<a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email"><code>mu4e</code></a>,
an email client which lives inside of Emacs, I have used other tools in the
past, and will probably use new tools in the future.</p>
<p>Also, even at this moment I alternate between <code>mu4e</code> and the
<a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">FastMail</a>
web-interface.</p>
<p>Long story short, I have it setup so that I can easily convert any email in
<code>mu4e</code> into a universal <code>message://message-id</code> link to be integrated with a
new task or note entry.</p>
<p>When I later open that link using a shortcut, I have programmed it so that
<code>mu4e</code> will open the relevant email if it is active, or the <code>FastMail</code> webmail
when it is not. From here I can either review the email to see what the
associated task requires, or respond to it, if the task has been completed.</p>
<p>Some of these <code>message://</code> links were created using macOS mail and they still
work. In future, if I add a new mail client to the mix, I will still be able to
jump to specific old emails, no matter where they find themselves inside of my
FastMail mailboxes.</p>
<h4 id="core-notes-database">Core notes database.</h4>
<p>With <code>database</code> I of course refer to hundreds of org and markdown files, most
of which find themselves in the top-level <code>pkb4000</code> directory, one level up
from the <code>journals</code> directory containing all of the monthly journal files.</p>
<p>There are files on various <code>rsync</code> or <code>ffmpeg</code> invocations, files on
programming languages, software tools, note-taking strategies, personal
information on each of my kids, and much more.</p>
<p>Org mode enables me to combine document structure, math, vector and bitmap
images and executable source code in many different languages.</p>
<p>I have configured my Emacs (where by &ldquo;configured&rdquo; I mean &ldquo;coded up the emacs
lisp for&rdquo;) to invoke ripgrep on different subsets of my notes database, and to
proffer up the results in different ways.</p>
<p>I can usually find anything that went in to this database at any point.</p>
<p>What I really like, is also being able to tell you on which day, and during
which hour, I learned this or that, or experimented with something or the
other.</p>
<h4 id="project-files">Project files.</h4>
<p>Work and personal projects each get their own Org file. Some projects even get
a whole directory to themselves, in cases where the project will have many more
files than just the main Org file.</p>
<p>In all cases, the project org file will live somewhere below a year-stamped
directory, e.g. <code>work/projects/2019/project-name/</code>.</p>
<p>Some projects go over year boundaries, but their files and directories remain
in the year that they started in. The project org also has <code>Tasks</code> and a
datetree section, similar to the month journal.</p>
<p>All current project files, along with my the current month file, are configured
to be part of the <code>org-agenda-files</code> variable.</p>
<p>This means that when I activate the <code>org-agenda</code> view, I see a unified list of
all tasks as extracted from all current project files and the current monthly
journal file.</p>
<p>When a project is completed, it is of course removed from <code>org-agenda-files</code>.</p>
<h3 id="web-pages-and-articles">Web-pages and articles.</h3>
<p>As mentioned in the short system overview, I store all web-pages and articles I
come across as date-stamped PDF files in a set of year-stamped directories.</p>
<p>For more detail, please refer to the
<a href="/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">JBOP</a>
section of WHV#165 on this blog.</p>
<p>In short, I use good ad-blocking and <em>mostly</em> the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/">printfriendly browser
extension</a> in Brave or Chromium to convert any
interesting web-pages to PDF. PDF articles from journals and other reputable
sources obviously don&rsquo;t have to be converted.</p>
<p>I name and save these PDFs into my <code>refs</code> hierarchy, for example
<code>Dropbox/refs/2019/20190518 Measles and Immune Amnesia - asm.pdf</code>.</p>
<p>Usually, to win any argument, I can find the pertinent reference on my phone or
my laptop in 30 seconds or less.</p>
<p>(I used to be a paying Pocket subscriber. However, as you will read in WHV#165
cited above, I was disappointed by the super important search function. The
advantages of having Just a Bunch of PDFs on your (synced) disc are many.)</p>
<h3 id="zotero">Zotero.</h3>
<p>The <code>refs</code> directory hierarchy described above is great for quickly storing an
article in the right place with a suitable name, ready for search-based
retrieval later.</p>
<p>However, in cases where one needs to cite any academics works, having these
articles in a good reference manager is important.</p>
<p>Zotero is in my view one of the best reference managers out there, and it&rsquo;s open
source!</p>
<p>The reasons I prefer zotero are:</p>
<ul>
<li>You can make use of their synchronisation service, or you can do it
yourself. I have about 2.3GB of additional articles in zotero, so this is
great.</li>
<li>Zotero uses your browser to retrieve fulltexts automatically when you import
any web-page with bibliographic information using the browser extension. This
is great when you have access via your institution. Competing cloud services
would historically use <em>their</em> servers to retrieve the fulltext, which would
often not work.</li>
<li>Zotero is open source. To me this is important, <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/zotero/">because on more than one
occasion</a> I have been able to make small
modifications to make it perform peculiar tricks I needed at that point.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="mobile">Mobile.</h3>
<p>This has always been the weakest part of my whole knowledge management system.</p>
<p>Ideally, I would have easy access to my complete org database and any related
files. Ideally, it would be possible to store any interesting tidbits I come
across whilst browsing using my phone.</p>
<p>So far I have invested time in the following apps and ecosystems:</p>
<ul>
<li>iCloud Notes: This was great, until <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/#so-tell-me-why-did-your-somewhat-stylish-macbook-phase-have-to-come-to-an-end">I sold my
MacBook</a>. iCloud
Notes web-access is terribly slow and more or less unusable. Whatever I have
on mobile, needs to interoperate smoothly with desktop.</li>
<li>Google Keep: This worked pretty well on mobile and via the web, but it&rsquo;s a
closed off ecosystem. You can
<a href="https://takeout.google.com/settings/takeout">&ldquo;takeout&rdquo;</a> your data, but you
end up with ginormous HTML files (images are base64-encoded and included)
that are not straight-forward to work with.</li>
<li>OneNote: This has SO MUCH potential (free-form note-taking, drawing with
Apple Pencil, apps for so many platforms, great organization, etc. etc.) but
is just so frustratingly unusable due to syncing issues everywhere, even on
my true-blue Windows 10 laptop with the true-blue official gold star
Microsoft OneNote application. Microsoft is doing fantastic work in some
domains (Visual Studio Code, .net core, WSL, etc. etc.) but in some others
not so much it seems.</li>
<li>Evernote: I recently just gave up and bought a premium subscription for the
year, because Evernote is the industry standard and it had Apple Watch voice
notes even before WatchOS 6 was released. In any case, although initially
promising, Evernote is unfortunately quite slow at unpredictable moments
(sharing web-page with evernote mobile app for storage can sometimes take 20
second or more&hellip;) so I&rsquo;ve had to ditch it. Again.</li>
</ul>
<p>During all of this experimentation, I started storing mobile discoveries in a
new section called &ldquo;inbox&rdquo; in the relevant note-taking app&rsquo;s organizational
structure. During morning review, I go through the relevant inbox, and
re-convert the relevant page into PDF for my more permanent archive.</p>
<p>It dawned on me that this approach could also be applied with just the Dropbox
app! It would be klunky, but at least not disappointing.</p>
<p>So, when I want to store something from the phone, I either print to PDF or
make use of the &ldquo;Save to Dropbox&rdquo; app extension, and then store the resultant
PDF in <code>Dropbox/notes/inbox</code>. During morning review, PDFs in this directory are
re-converted if required, and then stored in their more permanent home.</p>
<p>Using the Dropbox app, I can also create markdown text files in the <code>inbox</code>
directory.</p>
<p>If I have something a little more extensive, I have the option of using the
&ldquo;Voice Memos&rdquo; app, either on the phone, or even via the Apple Watch.</p>
<p>In <code>Dropbox/notes/mobile</code> I keep items I often need to access from the phone:
Think loyalty cards, markdown files with IP numbers and configuration of my
home network, and so on. This directory is marked as &ldquo;available offline&rdquo;, so I
can access its contents even when there&rsquo;s no data connection.</p>
<p>Other than that, I do an export of my whole org database to HTML now and then,
following a procedure similar to the one I used <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">to use for exporting Org mode
to iCloud
Notes</a>. The
HTML versions are searchable on the phone.</p>
<p>What would be better, is if the Dropbox iOS app would start recognising .org
files as plaintext files, much like what it already does for markdown .md
files. As it stands, I keep a small subset of my notes as markdown, instead of
the superior org, for mobile editing.</p>
<h4 id="drawing-with-apple-pencil-on-the-ipad-using-notability">Drawing with Apple Pencil on the iPad using Notability.</h4>
<p>Sometimes one does need to sketch.</p>
<p>This could be a rough UI, an architecture diagram, a data flow chart, or just
doodling.</p>
<p>Since about the end of 2018, I&rsquo;ve been using the <a href="https://apps.apple.com/za/app/notability/id360593530">Notability
app</a> along with an iPad
6th gen (2018 entry-level, the first non-Pro to support the Pencil) to doodle
electronically.</p>
<p>Notability automatically syncs all of these drawings as fully vectorised PDFs
to my Dropbox. All handwritten text is quite smartly OCRd, and the OCRd version
is stored as correctly positioned metadata behind my ugly scribbles.</p>
<p>I would have liked Notability even more if it supported arbitrary canvas sizes
(as it stands, only standard paper size in protrait mode), and had an always
visible overview minimap.</p>
<h4 id="signal-messaging-apps-brilliant-note-to-self-contact">Signal messaging app&rsquo;s brilliant &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo; contact.</h4>
<p>The <a href="https://signal.org/">Signal messaging app</a>, which you should all be using,
has a built-in contact called &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As of late (since about December 2019) this has become my main <em>capturing tool</em>
when I&rsquo;m on the phone.</p>
<p>You can share links, media, photos, voice notes or a plain old text message,
all of which will be securely stored, neatly timestampted to boot, in your
conversation with this silent but very useful &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo; character.</p>
<p>During the morning review, I go through each of the shared items, processing
them, and then add the message &ldquo;DONE =====&gt;&rdquo; to indicate that they have been
completed.</p>
<h2 id="limitations-and-points-for-improvement">Limitations and points for improvement.</h2>
<p>The current system is great for capturing and search-based retrieval of
personal knowledge.</p>
<p>However, I miss functionality for making some of the higher-level patterns and
networks more <em>discoverable</em>.</p>
<p>For example, as I create a new orgmode entry, the system could show me related,
older nodes (that is something I could implement&hellip;).</p>
<p>Furthermore, it would have been great to see some form of visual representation
of the associations between nodes, and of how they fit into higher-level
concepts. This bit is slightly far-fetched.</p>
<p>Interestingly, I just ran into the following paragraph at the end of <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">my 2016
note-taking post</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>However, I think that there might be room for a fourth type of tool that is
more visual, supports rich and graphical linking between data items and even
between sub-components of such items and, perhaps most importantly, enables
us to build note landscapes that are natively as non-linear as our thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let&rsquo;s see what happens over the next few years!</p>
<h2 id="appendix">Appendix</h2>
<h3 id="redacted-emacs-orgmode-capture-template">Redacted Emacs Orgmode capture template</h3>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; normally I construct current-journal-filename using mix of expand-file-name and concat</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">setq</span> <span style="color:#953800">current-journal-filename</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;/full/path/to/current/month-journal/&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; %i = selected text, %a org-store-link, %U created timestamp, %? place cursor here</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">setq</span> <span style="color:#953800">org-capture-templates</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#0550ae">&#39;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">((</span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;t&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;Todo&#34;</span> <span style="color:#953800">entry</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">file+headline</span> <span style="color:#953800">current-journal-filename</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;Tasks&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;* TODO %?\n:LOGBOOK:\n- Created \&#34;TODO\&#34; %U\n:END:\n%i\n%a\n\n&#34;</span> 
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#6639ba">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">1</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;j&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;Journal&#34;</span> <span style="color:#953800">entry</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">file+olp+datetree</span> <span style="color:#953800">current-journal-filename</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;* %? %T\n&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#6639ba">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">1</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;p&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;Day planning&#34;</span> <span style="color:#953800">entry</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">file+olp+datetree</span> <span style="color:#953800">current-journal-filename</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;* Day planning %U
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Done list / thoughts / diary
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- %?
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Tasks for today [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Experiment: Articulate your directions / systems.
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Focus blocks
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Review [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] [[*Vitals][Month vitals]]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] Org sub-projects
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] Calendar
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] ...
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Habits / important [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] 7.5 hrs sleep last night
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] are you satisfied with number of pomodori? = 0 (v R)
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] did you write stuff down?
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] ...
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#6639ba">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">1</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)))</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>
<h3 id="sunday-2020-01-12">Sunday 2020-01-12</h3>
<ul>
<li>Add <a href="#redacted-emacs-orgmode-capture-template">example of orgmode capture template
configuration</a> in appendix.</li>
<li>Add <a href="#drawing-with-apple-pencil-on-the-ipad-using-notability">section about iPad, Notability and Apple
Pencil</a>.</li>
<li>Add <a href="#signal-messaging-apps-brilliant-note-to-self-contact">section about Signal&rsquo;s Note to Self
contact</a>.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #132: Potato deadline.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/02/18/weekly-head-voices-132/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2018 20:45:08 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/02/18/weekly-head-voices-132/</guid><description> Fragment of potato skin, taken with phone camera through GOU#2’s microscope at 100x.
We have a serious deadline coming up on Tuesday, so I’m going to make these few WHV minutes count.
BULLET LIST TO THE RESCUE!
Day zero has again been postponed, this time to June 4. We continue with our water saving efforts.
That unexpected side-project I mentioned in last week’s post did end up going live that very night. Armed with the Django Rest Framework and plenty of battle scars, it took about 17 hours from idea to fully deployed REST API, a large part of which was debugging the paper’s math and spreadsheets.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/IMG_3247.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/IMG_3247-1024x930.jpg"
        
            alt="Fragment of potato skin, taken with phone camera through GOU#2’s microscope at 100x."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Fragment of potato skin, taken with phone camera through GOU#2’s microscope at 100x.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>We have a serious deadline coming up on Tuesday, so I’m going to make these few WHV minutes count.</p>
<p>BULLET LIST TO THE RESCUE!</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Day zero has again been <a href="https://mg.co.za/article/2018-02-13-day-zero-pushed-back-to-june-as-drought-declared-a-national-disaster/">postponed, this time to June 4</a>. We continue with our water saving efforts.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>That <a href="/2018/02/11/weekly-head-voices-131-function-over-form/#tool-belts-for-humanity">unexpected side-project I mentioned in last week’s post</a> did end up going live that very night. Armed with the Django Rest Framework and plenty of battle scars, it took about 17 hours from idea to fully deployed REST API, a large part of which was debugging the paper’s math and spreadsheets.</p>
<ul>
<li>Django might be a slow runner relative to some of the other kids on the block (go with any of its web frameworks, nginx with openresty (lua right in your web server!), even apistar with uvicorn), but the completeness and maturity of Django and its ginormous ecosystem are hard to beat when it comes to development velocity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>There’s a <a href="http://takingnotenow.blogspot.co.za/">whole blog on the nature of note-taking</a>. I arrived there via <a href="https://github.com/rudolfochrist/interleave">interleave</a> and <a href="https://github.com/weirdNox/org-noter">org-noter</a>, both emacs packages for keeping text (orgmode) notes synchronised with PDFs, both found via <a href="http://irreal.org/blog/?p=6954">irreal</a>, a great Emacs blog.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In the extra lessons I have with GOU#1, we studied electrical current from basic (atomic) principles. As I was getting all excited about the outer electrons being passed on from copper atom to copper atom (Khan Academy and I tag team these lessons), GOU#1 had to laugh at the goose flesh on my arms.</p>
<ul>
<li>The Khan Academy lecture seemed to imply that Benjamin Franklin started us down the not-quite-correct path of conventional current (from positive to negative), whereas the electrons being passed on imply current flow from negative to positive, aka electron current. However, <a href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/a/17131">this physics StackOverflow answer</a> more completely explains that current is defined as <em>the flow of electric charge</em>, with electron flow being one example, and hence both directions are correct.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>To be honest, I became ever so slightly irritated with an episode of one of my favourite podcasts, CPPCast, as the guest said “like” so often that I had trouble following what he was <em>actually</em> like trying to say. This like led me to using Google’s machine-learning-based speech to text API one night to like transcribe the audio of the podcast to speech so that I could like count the number of like utterances. There were not as many as I thought, but still a whole lot. If you’re curious as to the stats, I wrote everything up in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/02/15/use-the-google-cloud-speech-api-to-transcribe-a-podcast/">this nerdy vxlabs blog post</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>On the topic of note-taking: Because I make lab notes of everything in my Emacs, including late night speech recognition experiments, publishing a blog post is a question of some copy pasting, and then telling Emacs to publish to the blog.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>On Thursday, some dudes came to my house and, after somehow switching seamlessly from pick-axe to optic fibre splicer and back several times, left me with this (and more):

  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/IMG_3241.jpg">
      <img
          
              
              src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/IMG_3241-1024x819.jpg"
          
              alt="Two fibre strands into my house. They tell me one is for backup."/> </a><figcaption>
              <p>Two fibre strands into my house. They tell me one is for backup.</p>
          </figcaption>
  </figure>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>These are strange Gibson-esque times when there’s now permanently a laser transmitting all of these packets to you via the network of glass strands encircling the Earth, whilst many of us are still struggling to grasp the difference between fact and fiction.</p>
<ul>
<li>“The future is already here — it’s just not very evenly distributed”, William Gibson, probably ’93.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>We have a new president: President <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyril_Ramaphosa">Cyril Ramaphosa!</a> He was Mandela’s choice to become president of this country, but it was Thabo’s turn, and then things went pear-shaped with Zuma. Years later, the situation is quite dire, but so far there are many indications that Ramaphosa has the makings of a great leader (I have become convinced that we humans, all of us, need great leaders to advance as humanity; I hope to write a post about that some day). After Friday’s state of the nation (SONA) address by present Ramaphosa, I, along with many fellow South Africans, are hopeful for our future.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Ok peeps, have a wonderful week! I’ll see you NEXT TIME!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>nvpy 1.0.0 has been released!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/12/02/nvpy-1-0-0-has-been-released/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 10:19:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/12/02/nvpy-1-0-0-has-been-released/</guid><description>Oh happy day!
Last night I released version 1.0.0 of nvpy, a cross-platform (linux, mac, windows) simplenote-syncing note-taking app. nvpy is also my most popular open source baby, at least by github stars and forks. Screenshot of nvpy 1.0.0 with a demo database of notes.
Since I first released nvpy in 2012, automattic have released their own official open source desktop app for simplenote. Although the official app is prettier (it is electron-based), nvpy is faster and uses a fraction of the RAM (70MB RSS vs 1000MB+ RSS). Furthermore, nvpy’s syncing is more deterministic: You can see exactly when and how it syncs.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Oh happy day!</p>
<p>Last night <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/nvpy/9r3ED7w3axs">I released version 1.0.0</a> of <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/nvpy">nvpy</a>, a cross-platform (linux, mac, windows) simplenote-syncing note-taking app. nvpy is also my most popular open source baby, at least by github stars and forks.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/2016-12-02-115217_1032x679_scrot.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/12/2016-12-02-115217_1032x679_scrot-1024x674.png"
        
            alt="Screenshot of nvpy 1.0.0 with a demo database of notes."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Screenshot of nvpy 1.0.0 with a demo database of notes.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Since I first released nvpy in 2012, <a href="https://automattic.com/">automattic</a> have released their own official open source desktop app for simplenote. Although the official app is prettier (it is electron-based), nvpy is faster and uses a fraction of the RAM (70MB RSS vs 1000MB+ RSS). Furthermore, nvpy’s syncing is more deterministic: You can see exactly when and how it syncs.</p>
<p>Personally, I use nvpy on my Linux and Mac workstations and laptops, and the official simplenote apps on my Android devices for the text-only notes <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">I always need to be with me</a>.</p>
<p>I am currently planning to write a new sqlite-based storage backend for nvpy, which should greatly speed up its interactive note-searching.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Note-taking strategy early 2016</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2016 20:23:48 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/</guid><description>I’m probably what one might call an obsessive note-taker.
I’ve talked in the past about the importance of keeping a lab journal. Initially I produced a stack of books filled with hand-scribbled notes. Although this is my favourite authoring modality, the fact that such notes can’t be easily indexed and queried (maybe one day?!) soon leads one to try electronic solutions. Over the years I’ve experimented with a number of different tools (see under “Nerd News”) to do this.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’m probably what one might call an obsessive note-taker.</p>
<p>I’ve <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/">talked in the past about the importance of keeping a lab journal.</a> Initially I produced a stack of books filled with hand-scribbled notes. Although this is my favourite authoring modality, the fact that such notes can’t be easily indexed and queried (maybe one day?!) soon leads one to try electronic solutions. Over the years I’ve <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2011/07/02/the-monthly-weekly-head-voices-50/">experimented with a number of different tools</a> (see under “Nerd News”) to do this.</p>
<p>This post summarises my current selection of tools.</p>
<p>For making notes with a visual aspect, for example photos of beers that I’ve tasted, and sometimes screenshots of websites, I use <a href="https://www.google.com/keep/">Google Keep</a>. This has a really great Android app with which you can easily save a website, including screenshot, using the Android “share with” functionality. On the desktop, this has a web-app that looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/keep_screenie.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/keep_screenie-790x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>One of the neat features of Keep is that you can easily have it extract and OCR text from images, for example if you’ve taken a photo of a business card. Unfortunately, the web-app is quite sluggish (this could be because I live in a bandwidth-constrained world here at the southern tip of Africa), and there’s no web clipper with which I can easily save web pages whilst on the desktop. Furthermore, I find the layout to be quite chaotic, and therefore I treat it more like my similarly chaotic digital cork board.</p>
<p>After a two year hiatus, I’ve returned to the <a href="http://simplenote.com/">SimpleNote universe</a> as my <strong>core mobile and desktop note-taking tool</strong>. They have great apps on IOS, Android, Mac and Web. I use the super sleek, some might say austere, <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.automattic.simplenote">SimpleNote Android app</a> (recently rewritten when <a href="https://automattic.com/">Automattic</a>, makers of WordPress, bought Simperium, makers of SimpleNote) and on the desktop I mostly use <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/nvpy">nvpy, my open source SimpleNote client</a>. The latest greatest version (0.10.0, soon to be released) looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/nvpy_screenie.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/nvpy_screenie.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Because SimpleNote is text-only, and it’s a fully synced offline-capable tool, it’s nice and fast. This is the tool you want to use to store those small but useful factoids, quotes and code snippets.</p>
<p>For more in-depth and technical lab journals, I use GNU Emacs with <a href="http://orgmode.org/">Org mode</a>. This enables me to write documents with beautifully typeset math, syntax-highlighted and in some cases even live-evaluated code blocks, and good document structure, all in plain text. Here’s a sample of my November 2015 lab journal where I started reading about and experimenting with a bit of D language:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/emacs_orgmode_screenie.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/emacs_orgmode_screenie.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Parts of these journals <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2014/05/25/emacs-24-with-prelude-org2blog-and-wordpress/">can be sent directly to your WordPress blog from within Emacs</a>, and you can generate high quality PDFs at the press of a typical simple 12 key Emacs shortcut combo. This being Emacs, the experience can be easily customised to emulate SimpleNote in terms of interactivity, but this will not easily compete with SimpleNote proper in terms of transparent syncing between all devices and in terms of accessibility on mobile.</p>
<p>Using these three tools together currently takes good care of my note-taking requirements. However, I think that there might be room for a fourth type of tool that is more visual, supports rich and graphical linking between data items and even between sub-components of such items and, perhaps most importantly, enables us to build note landscapes that are natively as non-linear as our thoughts.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Monthly [Weekly Head Voices #50]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/07/02/the-monthly-weekly-head-voices-50/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2011 15:00:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/07/02/the-monthly-weekly-head-voices-50/</guid><description>HEY!
I’m still here, and it seems I really have to catch up on my backlog of WHVs, all the more as I was starting to notice the beginnings of BPP (Backlogged Posting Paralysis, of course). So I’ve spent a few minutes gathering a selection of life snippets of the past six weeks (week 21 through week 26) and will now proceed blasting them out this old Web 1.0 exhaust. I wasn’t completely idle blog-wise, however. I did write a post about my EuroVis 2011 and my Schloss Dagstuhl SciVis seminar adventures.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>HEY!</p>
<p>I’m still here, and it seems I really have to catch up on my backlog of WHVs, all the more as I was starting to notice the beginnings of BPP (Backlogged Posting Paralysis, of course). So I’ve spent a few minutes gathering a selection of life snippets of the past six weeks (week 21 through week 26) and will now proceed blasting them out this old Web 1.0 exhaust. I wasn’t completely idle blog-wise, however. I did write a <a href="/2011/06/26/eurovis-2011/" title="eurovis 2011 post">post about my EuroVis 2011</a> and my <a href="/2011/06/19/schloss-dagstuhl-computer-scientist-heaven/" title="dagstuhl scivis 2011 post">Schloss Dagstuhl SciVis seminar</a> adventures.</p>
<p>Before the blasting commences, I would like to present some relaxing visual input brought to you via my cell phone camera, which at the time of capturing found itself in my hand, itself being inside the chapel in <a href="http://maps.google.nl/maps?q=Herberg+Op+Hodenpijl,+Rijksstraatweg,+Schipluiden&amp;hl=en%E2%89%AA=51.987252,4.321012&amp;spn=0.002355,0.005348&amp;sll=51.986948,4.321007&amp;sspn=0.004711,0.010697&amp;t=h&amp;z=18" title="google maps of herberg op hodenpijl">Herberg op Hodenpijl</a>, a short westward cycle from my house:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/herberg_op_hodenpijl2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/herberg_op_hodenpijl2-1024x608.jpg"
        
            alt="Herberg op Hodenpijl chapel roof detail."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Herberg op Hodenpijl chapel roof detail.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The picturesque surroundings are home to the chapel, which hosted an art exhibition at that point, and an organic restaurant and grocer. Most (all?) of the produce comes from a small farm across the road that you can also visit. The goats are really friendly. You could do worse than popping by on a sunny day.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/herberg_op_hodenpijl1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/herberg_op_hodenpijl1-1024x608.jpg"
        
            alt="Herberg op Hodenbijl chapel roof detail."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Herberg op Hodenbijl chapel roof detail.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The rest of this post has been categorised, with nice headings, so that you can skim through it even faster.</p>
<h4 id="health-and-well-being">Health and well-being</h4>
<ul>
<li>In a recent cooking insert on the television, <a href="http://dewerelddraaitdoor.vara.nl/Video-detail.628.0.html?&amp;tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=22570&amp;tx_ttnews%5BbackPid%5D=626&amp;tx_ttnews%5Bcat%5D=148&amp;cHash=ab10fe812f48fd43e838df03ffa6cf31" title="DWDD video clip">two chefs prepared <em>Loup farci en croûte</em></a>, or sea bass filled with julienne vegetables in a pastry of a thousand layers. Take a look at the video clip: The chefs put an amazing amount of effort into preparing this visually beautiful and apparently delectable dish.</li>
<li>My <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">TNR</a> and since recently also business partner, who can often be found hurtling down mountains on various and high-speed forms of personal transportation, and when he’s not is involved in a number of other extreme sports activities, managed to break two fingers on his right hand cycling over the flat and otherwise uneventful piece of earth between the computer science and physics buildings on our campus. Go figure.</li>
<li>In a <a href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/news/fullstory_112161.html" title="medlineplus article on coffee vs prostate cancer">recent study</a> with 48000 (yes, that’s fourty eight thousand) men followed over a period of 22 years, a strong correlation was found between drinking six cups of coffee per day and a lowered risk of prostate cancer. Also men (but can you still call them men?) drinking fewer than 6 cups of coffee per day had a lower risk. The study did correct for other lifestyle factors. The linked summary also mentions other studies in which coffee drinking has been associated with lower risk of Parkinson disease, type 2 diabetes and liver cancer. I guess I can worry less about this addiction than, euhm, the other ones.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="nerd-news">Nerd News</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dropbox has recently activated functionality they call shareable links, meaning that you can request a unique <a href="http://db.tt/some_code">http://db.tt/some_code</a> link for any file or directory anywhere in your dropbox and share it with anyone else (also non-dropbox users), who is then able to download said file or directory given the link. There’s a page on the website where you can manage all of your shared links, for example deactivating ones you don’t want people to access anymore. Read the <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/help/167" title="dropbox help on sharable links">help on shareable</a> links for more information.</li>
<li>As you <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/" title="blog post on the importance of taking notes">might know</a>, I keep a lab journal documenting in some detail my daily work activities. I also maintain a personal journal, mostly for dumping stuff that might be interesting for this blog. I used to do all of this in Google Docs, but for the past few weeks I’ve experimenting using <a href="http://www.tiddlywiki.com/" title="tiddlywiki website">TiddlyWiki</a> (this is a single file JavaScript-heavy wiki implementation) on my Dropbox for all my journaling and personal knowledge base needs. It’s been going swimmingly for at least two reasons: 1) It’s available also when I’m offline. 2) The idea of being able to break out into a new wiki page (called a tiddler) at the drop of a hat takes some getting used to, but fits the non-linear nature of my journal and personal knowledge base entries much better than the mostly linear google docs.</li>
<li>I’ve settled on using the free <a href="http://www.tonido.com/" title="tonido website">tonido personal cloud software</a> to make all the files on my home server available via the internets. This means I can get to all of my music, photos are whatever no matter where I am. Pretty neat! (I have too much to fit on my 50G dropbox account. There’s also the PogoPlug software, but the free version has its limitations.)</li>
<li>Just a few days before Google+ (Google’s new social networking religion, in case you’ve been sleeping for the past week) hit the internets, I installed the Google +1 button on this blog, see right at the bottom of every post. So now you know what to do with every post: Click my +1 button, then click my facebook like button, then leave me some snarky comment right here. Easy as 123, and I’m a happy camper.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="comedy">Comedy</h4>
<p>Whilst flipping through channels one Saturday night,  I flipped right into the stand-up comedian <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Demetri_Martin" title="demetri martin wikipedia page">Demetri Martin</a>. I made a note of it in my journal, and now here we are. Watch him present his research findings on his large pad, with his pointer:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vaGa3kjRS7o?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>That’s it for now dear readers. I really do hope to be back soon, and I hope to do so with a slightly more focused contribution. See you on <a href="http://plus.google.com/" title="google plus">Google+</a>!</p>
<p><strong>UPDATE 2011-07-23 note-taking strategy</strong></p>
<p>To you I might appear fickle, but I guarantee that it’s just hyperactivity. I’ve since adjusted my note-taking strategy again. As you will have seen in the comments, Pieter Kitslaar subtly influenced me to go searching for a note-taking solution that syncs between phone and everywhere else. Fortunately, I ran into the <a href="http://simplenoteapp.com/" title="simplenote universe">SimpleNote universe</a> and I’m now officially in <strong>note-taking heaven</strong>. I have <a href="https://market.android.com/details?id=com.teragadgets.android.notes" title="flick note market page">Flick Note</a> on my Android, the SyncPad extension on Chrome (for sometimes) and <a href="http://www.resoph.com/" title="resoph notes website">ResophNotes</a> on Windows and on Linux with Wine. All apps work exactly as I would expect a super-fast and efficient note-taking app to work, with real-time incremental searching, hotkeys <strong>everywhere</strong>, and best of all, offline use and transparent syncing. <strong>ResophNotes is especially cool, definitely give it a shot.</strong></p>
<p>So I’m using this SimpleNote setup for all my personal knowledge base and general note-taking needs. For detailed work and lab journaling, I’m now using linear OpenDocument files on my Dropbox, which solves the offline problem I had with Google Docs, which I do still adore for collaborative work.</p>
<p>Lemme know in the comments what you think!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>