<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Deep Thought on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/deep-thought/</link><description>Recent content in Deep Thought on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2012 22:23:13 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/deep-thought/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Slow philosophy. [Weekly Head Voices #64]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2012 22:23:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/</guid><description>I’ve spent days writing this post in my head, and now it’s taken more than two weeks to get done. It’s not that I have something complicated or difficult to tell you, it’s just that I was privy to three absolutely awesome weeks of vacation in an undisclosed location to the very far south of my current coordinates, during which I attained ultimate levels of relaxation that caused my brain to shut-down large parts of itself. The only parts that managed to remain online were those dedicated to slow living, appreciation of people and surroundings and, finally, deep thought. My brain is currently taking its sweet time to come fully online again.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve spent days writing this post in my head, and now it’s taken more than two weeks to get done. It’s not that I have something complicated or difficult to tell you, it’s just that I was privy to three absolutely awesome weeks of vacation in an undisclosed location to the very far south of my current coordinates, during which I attained ultimate levels of relaxation that caused my brain to shut-down large parts of itself. The only parts that managed to remain online were those dedicated to slow living, appreciation of people and surroundings and, finally, deep thought. My brain is currently taking its sweet time to come fully online again.</p>
<p>Oh well.</p>
<p>I <em>did</em> bring you a photo of Disa Uniflora, a special little orchid that likes living close to little waterfalls, for example just like the one that can be found on your hike up Leopard’s Kloof. Look:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/disa_uniflora_leopards_kloof.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/disa_uniflora_leopards_kloof-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty Disa in Leopard&#39;s Kloof."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty Disa in Leopard's Kloof.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>As is usual for sunny vacations during which we transition into a new year, a number of realizations and resolutions slowly bubbled up to the surface from some usually submerged part of my consciousness. I’d like to share some of them with you:</p>
<p><em>Life goals are bad.</em> Let’s stop doing them. The problem is that humans are awesome at adaptation. Unfortunately this means that two days after having celebrated your latest epic life achievement, you’re bored with it. Some people even get bored with their lives in general, and then buy a leather jacket and a motorbike because they think that <em>that’ll</em> somehow solve the problem, only to get bored with their new image soon after. Fortunately, there is a way to sidestep the problem quite elegantly. Don’t set life goals, but rather set life directions. Instead of defining the point that you want to go towards, define your preferred direction. If you do it right, you’ll pass those points as you go along in any case, except you won’t land in the depressing goal vacuum right after reaching the point that you’ve been moving towards for so long, because you’re motoring along in a direction, and that’s what’s important. To those more mathematically inclined, ignore the life function, rather design its derivatives. This is a practical way of <em>applying</em> the well-known addage that life is about the journey, and not the destination.</p>
<p><em>Disconnecting is good.</em> I do love the internet. I also think it’s one of the most awesome achievements of the whole of humankind ever, and it really empowers humans everywhere. I’m more or less addicted to being constantly connected, having constant access to the sum total of human knowledge and in principle to a large percentage of my fellow humans. However, there is a fine line between having constant access and being constantly interrupted by too many not necessarily valuable packets of data. We’re very vulnerable to this latter situation, due to <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/science/2009/08/seeking.html" title="slate article dealing with brain chemistry and internet interruption">our brain chemistry being optimized by all of evolution for novelty</a>, and for foraging, so we keep on clicking on “refresh”, and our ears perk up whenever a phone goes “ping”. However, when not being interrupted, human thought gets the room it needs to grow and deepen, into importance and into impact.</p>
<p>I’ve also been thinking about consumption. I’d like to do much less of that, and when I do, I’d prefer to consume quality. In my thoughts, it was primarily about information, but it applies to many other things. It’s an ongoing process.</p>
<p>I’m adding all of these to my growing list of little life tips. As regular readers of this blog, you know some of these by now: Keep on  <a href="/2011/08/28/the-lowlands-tooth-fairy-37-weekly-head-voices-55/" title="balance and harmony mentioned, has to bemore">striving for balance and harmony</a>, <a href="/2011/03/19/drown-in-the-now-weekly-head-voices-42/" title="drown in the now">focus on the now</a>, <a href="/2011/11/05/happiness-slingshot-weekly-head-voices-61/" title="create value">create value</a>, <a href="/2010/08/01/the-human-animal-post/" title="the human animal post">study your manual</a>, and, most importantly, <a href="/tag/coffee/" title="posts tagged with coffee">drink lots of coffee</a>. One day I’m going to combine them all nicely into the Unified Dogma of  Me (UDM) and then I’ll start a sect. Seriously though, it’s quite challenging keeping these and the other ones in the front of my mind all the time. The UDM would definitely help. And I could start a sect.</p>
<p>One more thing before you go: I came across <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2012/01/10/1115323109" title="Ratcliff 2012 in PNAS">this recent PNAS article</a> via the science pages of my newspaper. William Ratcliff and colleagues at the Michigan State University showed with a terribly simple experiment that single-celled yeast cells can evolve into multi-cellularity quite quickly. Pouring yeast from one test tube into another about 60 times, an action that favours, or selects, yeast cells that clump together, resulted into a multi-celled organism: The clumped together yeast cells started showing internal specialization. Pretty awesome results, especially considering the fact that you could probably reproduce this experiment in your kitchen.</p>
<p>That’s all for this week kids. Have fun evolving!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>