<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>contentment on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/contentment/</link><description>Recent content in contentment on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 22:29:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/contentment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #250: Durable, blissful contentment</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 22:29:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/</guid><description> This, the quarter-thousandth edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covers two weeks from Monday November 21 to Sunday December 4, 2022.
Figure 1: The sunset colours in Betty&amp;rsquo;s were beautiful that day.
I am happy that my ever-evolving life philosophy (as well as my approach to health and wellness) includes a growing section on the importance of hard and challenging work with great colleagues, because these past few weeks have really been delivering in that respect.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the quarter-thousandth edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covers two
weeks from Monday November 21 to Sunday December 4, 2022.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys-sunset-colours.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/bettys-sunset-colours_hu7b1dbb48e547631cc63340847f0e1193_1297113_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/bettys-sunset-colours_hu7b1dbb48e547631cc63340847f0e1193_1297113_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/bettys-sunset-colours_hu7b1dbb48e547631cc63340847f0e1193_1297113_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/bettys-sunset-colours_hu7b1dbb48e547631cc63340847f0e1193_1297113_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/bettys-sunset-colours_hu7b1dbb48e547631cc63340847f0e1193_1297113_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: The sunset colours in Betty&amp;rsquo;s were beautiful that day."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>The sunset colours in Betty&rsquo;s were beautiful that day.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I am happy that my ever-evolving life philosophy (as well as my approach to
health and wellness) includes a growing section on the importance of hard and
challenging work with great colleagues, because these past few weeks have
really been delivering in that respect.</p>
<p>The rest of this post consists of two main parts: The first is a nerdy bit
about the ease of doing state-of-the-art multi-lingual speech-to-text
transcription on your own computer, and the second is about not being happy.</p>
<h2 id="an-applied-machine-learning-prelude">An applied machine learning prelude</h2>
<p>A few months ago, I listened to a podcast with Sam Harris and Morgan Housel,
titled, quite uncharacteristically for Harris podcasts, &ldquo;Wealth Matters&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Hidden between all of the money- and economics-related information, they
started to talk about human well-being, and specifically about happiness vs
contentment.</p>
<p>As I was driving, a few specific words by Sam Harris dealing with the modest
but robust bliss in everyday contentment really hit home for me.</p>
<p>I made a mental note to find the spot in question later, and then to transcribe
it for this blog.</p>
<p>It went the way of many of my mental notes made while driving and listening to
podcasts&hellip; floating peacefully and oblivious somewhere in my brain.</p>
<p>&hellip; until last week, when the mental note surfaced (!!).</p>
<p>First I graduated the mental note into my Emacs Org mode notes. A few days
later I tracked down the interview in question (man, that Waking Up app has
great content, but it&rsquo;s usability has much room for improvement (low hanging
fruit include 1. automatically continuing current listening and 2. better
search)) and made another note, which on its part led to me sitting down a bit
later with my phone, trying to find the correct spot in the 2 hour podcast.</p>
<p>Fortunately, two attempts got me to the desired segment at 48m55s.</p>
<p>At that point, I could have just manually transcribed the speech in question,
but it turned out to be a longer segment than expected, and then a little voice
(haha) reminded me of <a href="https://openai.com/blog/whisper/">the recent release of OpenAI&rsquo;s multi-lingual
text-to-speech neural network model called Whisper</a>.</p>
<p>In spite of XKCD&rsquo;s extremely valuable <a href="https://xkcd.com/1205/">lessons on when you should or shouldn&rsquo;t
automate a thing</a>, I decided that there was a learning opportunity here and so
I git cloned (nerd for &ldquo;downloaded&rdquo;) the <a href="https://github.com/openai/whisper">Whisper source code</a>.</p>
<p>It took me the most of the time to get the required GPU-capable packages on
Windows, where my RTX 2070 lives (I had to revert to miniforge and conda, see
<code>environment.yml</code> below), and then to record the 6.5 minute audio segment from my
phone using the external microphone on my PC with Audacity (this was the only
way to get the audio out of the app).</p>
<p>Once that was done, Whisper took about a minute (64 seconds to be exact) to
transcribe the 6.5 minutes into absolutely <em>flawless</em>, timestamped English text.</p>
<p>I was quite flabbergasted.</p>
<p>It is now possible to download a pretty compact neural network to your own PC,
and then to use that model to transcribe automatically any number of spoken
languages, optionally also translating in the process.</p>
<h3 id="environment-dot-yml-for-mamba">environment.yml for mamba</h3>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-yaml" data-lang="yaml"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic"># mamba env update</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic"># conda activate whisper</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic"># whisper --language English name_of_your.mp3</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#268bd2;font-weight:bold">name</span>: <span style="color:#2aa198">whisper</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#268bd2;font-weight:bold">channels</span>:
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  - <span style="color:#2aa198">pytorch</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  - <span style="color:#2aa198">nvidia</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#268bd2;font-weight:bold">dependencies</span>:
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  - <span style="color:#2aa198">python=3.10</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  - <span style="color:#2aa198">pip</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  - <span style="color:#2aa198">pytorch</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  - <span style="color:#2aa198">torchvision</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  - <span style="color:#2aa198">torchaudio</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  - <span style="color:#2aa198">pytorch-cuda=11.7</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  - <span style="color:#268bd2;font-weight:bold">pip</span>:
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    - <span style="color:#2aa198">git+https://github.com/openai/whisper.git</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="happiness-is-a-joke">Happiness is a joke</h2>
<p>The section that really hit home for me is the one in response to this
statement by Morgan Housel, the interview guest:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That difference between happiness and satisfaction is really key and easy to
overlook.  Happiness, like I said earlier, is a very fleeting emotion.</p>
<p>I use the example of, like, if I told you the funniest joke in the world,
you&rsquo;ve never heard a funniest joke, you would laugh for 30 seconds, and then
you&rsquo;d be over it.</p>
<p>And if I told you that joke every day, you&rsquo;d get sick of it, even if it was the
best joke in the world.</p>
<p>Happiness is like that as well, and therefore I think the most that we can aim
for, the best we can aim for, is contentment.</p>
<p>&hellip;</p>
<p>But when people chase happiness, I think that&rsquo;s when people are setting
themselves up for disappointment, because no matter how funny the joke is, so
to speak, it&rsquo;s a fleeting emotion that sticks around for just very brief
moments before you revert to something else.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m not a fan of analogies, because they have the tendency to distract folks
from the core of the discussion at hand. In the worst case, people think they
understand the issue because they understand the analogy.</p>
<p>However, here we can say that the world&rsquo;s funniest joke would indeed probably
be as fleeting as that feeling of happiness.</p>
<p>I have heard people joke about Sam Harris, saying he is one of the few humans
who is able to &ldquo;speak in full paragraphs&rdquo;.</p>
<p>His off-the-cuff response, the transcription of which is shown below with my
emphasis, indeed seems to demonstrate that quality.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Yeah, I&rsquo;m a big fan of thinking of well-being in terms of a kind of a <strong>larger
footprint of contentment and equanimity and peace</strong>, you know, non-conflict, as
opposed to the more transitory, hotter experiences of joy and happiness.</p>
<p>I mean, joy is a fleeting emotion.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not to say it&rsquo;s not important, and we don&rsquo;t love it.  But there&rsquo;s a kind
of a background context of just not having a problem, which is certainly
underrated.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not something people tend to, when they think of living their best
possible life, people tend to think about joy and fun and even, you know,
ecstasy, and they get bored with words like contentment or peace or equanimity.</p>
<p>And yet, really, when you just look at it, when you study the nature of your
own psychological suffering, really, <strong>the thing that is durable, the thing that
is achievable and, you know, truly enviable</strong>, if you don&rsquo;t have it, <strong>is
contentment</strong>, and it can <strong>deepen to the point where, you know, there&rsquo;s a blissful
component to it</strong>, and it&rsquo;s born of <strong>not craving things that are not here in this
moment</strong>, right?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">mentioned at least once before my preference for contentment over
happiness</a>, although I then also cited opinions to the effect that even
contentment was not possible, but I really like the way Sam so eloquently
combines the achievability, the robustness, and <em>especially</em> the bliss that can
be obtained through contentment, which itself can be cultivated through the
active practice of filling the current moment with your full and deliberate
presence.</p>
<h2 id="p-dot-s-dot-about-a-dot-i-dot">P.S. about A.I.</h2>
<p>With the current excitement over all of the applied Large Language Models
(LLMS), especially around the meteoric rise of <a href="https://openai.com/blog/chatgpt/">ChatGPT</a>, I have resolved to
maintain this blog as a shining example of 100% ad-free and human (namely
me)-generated content.</p>
<p>I have nothing against applying ML, but personally I prefer my blogs as
personal as possible.</p>
<p>It is quite poetic that after making that resolution, I did enlist the help of
an ML model to transcribe the speech in the previous section.</p>
<p>Thinking about this some more, who knows how I might use ML in the future to
help me answer questions, whilst still experiencing that it is truly <em>me</em> who
ends up writing these words.</p>
<p>These distinctions are already quite blurry.</p>
<p>With the technology and its context evolving so rapidly, there&rsquo;s no telling
where this journey will take us.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #125: Buddy.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 20:45:58 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/</guid><description> Monday, July 30 to Sunday, September 3, 2017.
(This post has turned into a huge ramble. It starts with parking, makes a quick visit to Yurp, buys a new laptop, compulsively measures time to try and increase quality of life, and then bounces like a hyperactive pinball between a book, a video and a blog post, all three about either not being special, not being happy or both. ENJOY!)
Parking Because I would prefer that you perceive the time that you invest in reading these posts as time also usefully spent, allow me to start with a visual exposition of the pleasantly straight-forward geometry of parallel parking.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Monday, July 30 to Sunday, September 3, 2017.</p>
<p>(This post has turned into a huge ramble. It starts with parking, makes a quick visit to Yurp, buys a new laptop, compulsively measures time to try and increase quality of life, and then bounces like a hyperactive pinball between a book, a video and a blog post, all three about either not being special, not being happy or both. ENJOY!)</p>
<h2 id="parking">Parking</h2>
<p>Because I would prefer that you perceive the time that you invest in reading these posts as time also usefully spent, allow me to start with a visual exposition of the pleasantly straight-forward <strong>geometry of parallel parking</strong>.</p>
<p>In other words, if you&rsquo;re like me and your parallel parking performance could do with some improvement (mine oscillates between “I am the best parallel parker in the world, wheels perfectly aligned 5mm from the pavement” and “ABORT ABORT!! Oh well, we will find parking another day.”), the following animation might be of assistance:</p>
<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" data-id="2g5Bzi9" lang="en"><a href="//imgur.com/2g5Bzi9">Parallel Parking</a></blockquote><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js"></script>
<h2 id="yurp">Yurp</h2>
<p>In an astonishingly fortunate confluence of events, I ended up again in <strong>my other home country</strong>. Although time was short, business was executed, and a great deal of highly concentrated joy was artfully squeezed from every minute.</p>
<p>Thank you Dutch family. I hope to see you again soon!</p>
<h2 id="new-laptop">New laptop</h2>
<p>Back home, it was time for me to add another life year to my steadily growing collection.</p>
<p>My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">gracious employer</a> thought that the big day was an as good moment as any to equip me with a <strong>brand new work machine</strong>.</p>
<p>Up to then, I had been working on all of three different machines: <a href="/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/">Linux-running i7 desktop</a> (acquired in Feb of 2015), <a href="/2015/06/14/weekly-head-voices-91-theyre-back/">early 2015 13″ retina MacBook Pro</a> (acquired in June of 2015) and my <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2013/03/24/acer-v3-571g-fullhd-ips-superb-priceperformance-linux-development-laptop/">trusty old klunky i7 Acer Linux-running laptop</a> (acquired around March 2013).</p>
<p>Data is kept in sync, but context switching between different projects with different development environments on different machines at home and at work does seem to take up more time than I would care to admit.</p>
<p>Having everything on a single <em>powerful</em>-enough laptop would indeed make the most sense from a time-efficiency perspective.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m typing on the thing now. The keyboard&rsquo;s second-generation butterfly switches do take a little getting used to, but I believe I may have been converted.</p>
<p>Importantly, I&rsquo;ve already started seeing the advantages of always having all my work (and all my computer-based hobby-related toys) with me. No more context-switching means more time available for what happens between the switches.</p>
<p>(My more nerdily inclined readers, you can probably guess exactly which laptop this is. Ask me in the comments why this and not the alternatives!)</p>
<h2 id="measure-all-the-things">Measure all the things</h2>
<p>On the topic of <strong>time efficiency</strong>, in an attempt to better understand what I was doing with my free time, and how exactly I was spending time at work, I put in some extra effort <strong>to record more accurately every minute of my time awake</strong>. I dream about being able to squeeze out more value from each day by being able to measure and review.</p>
<p>This is an extension to establishing a <a href="/2017/06/28/weekly-head-voices-123-a-semblance-of-a-cadence/">cadence of accountability for deep work</a>, where one looks not only at deep work performed, but general value contributed and derived.</p>
<p>Watching SNL or College Humor clips on YouTube is fun, but can&rsquo;t really be considered high value. In terms of R&amp;R, reading a book, writing a blog post, learning something new and spending time with your family are all of high value.</p>
<p>Recording time like this does seem ever so slightly OCDish, but it was really for science, and mostly for evolution (see <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">rule #3 of <em>WHV’s Two Rules for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em></a>).</p>
<p>I did only manage to keep it up for slightly over two weeks.</p>
<p>What was interesting, was that the act of having to specify and record each block of time forced me to be much more <em>deliberate</em> about everything I did.</p>
<p>All of a sudden, even goofing off could only happen if I explicitly spent time deciding that goofing off was really justified. Furthermore, the fact that I knew exactly how many minutes I was goofing off, tended to keep these distractions short.</p>
<p>The problem with this experiment quite unsurprisingly turned out to be the overhead of mechanically having to record every minute. That being said, I think the availability of a practical, highly private and practical mechanism (unlike the one I tried) for the real-time and aggregated measurement and reporting of “time value” could be a substantial help in the continuous optimisation of one&rsquo;s days.</p>
<h2 id="happy-not-happy">Happy not happy</h2>
<p>On the topic of quality of life, I recently read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Subtle-Art-Not-Giving-Counterintuitive/dp/0062457713"><em>The Subtle Art of Not Giving a F*ck: A Counterintuitive Approach to Living a Good Life</em> by Mark Manson</a>. I was involuntarily eye-rolling quite regularly through the first 3/4 of the book, but by that time either Manson had just worn me down, or his writing had in fact greatly improved.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I think the message is an important one, especially for young(er) people: You&rsquo;re not special, so make peace with that as soon as you can. Accept that life is really just a series of problems that you have to solve, so at least pick the interesting ones. <strong>You probably won&rsquo;t ever be happy or content for more than a few moments</strong> (<a href="/2011/04/07/happinessexception-weekly-head-voices-44/">sounds familiar, doesn&rsquo;t it?</a>) because that&rsquo;s quite logically been evolved out of us. Pick the few things that you really care about, and commit to them.</p>
<p><a href="https://sivers.org">Derek Sivers</a>, himself no slouch when it comes to modern survival, summarises the book with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The opposite of every other book. Don’t try. Give up. Be wrong. Lower your standards. Stop believing in yourself. Follow the pain. Each point is profoundly true, useful, and more powerful than the usual positivity. Succinct but surprisingly deep, I read it in one night.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(Interestingly, the first of the four noble truths of <strong>Buddhism</strong> is that <strong>life is suffering</strong>. “Human beings are subject to desires and cravings, but even when we are able to satisfy these desires, the satisfaction is only temporary. Pleasure does not last; or if it does, it becomes monotonous.” see <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/buddhism/beliefs/fournobletruths_1.shtml">this BBC entry</a> for more happy thoughts about Buddhism. In fact-checking my summary up above, I just saw in Manson&rsquo;s book that he does in fact explicitly tell the story of Buddha, in chapter 2 already. Doh.)</p>
<p>On the topic of not being special, I recently stumbled upon this interview with Simon Sinek. It&rsquo;s all about the phenomenon of millenials in the workplace. Many of us around here (hey, we read long form blogs, this means we&rsquo;re probably old-school) don&rsquo;t classify as millenials, but the points Sinek makes about the role of old-school patience and focus in the work-place as opposed to the millenial-era instant gratification attention economy resonated with me.</p>
<p>Also, we&rsquo;re still not special. :)</p>
<p>Try and make time for the first 3 to 4 minutes of the video. That&rsquo;s what
I did, because I&rsquo;m not a millenial and I don&rsquo;t like watching
YouTube videos of what could have been blog posts, but then I just had to
finish the whole 18 minutes (dangit youtube! video was pulled so I had to
replace with 15 minute version on 2019-04-16:</p>
<iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hER0Qp6QJNU" width="560"></iframe>
<p>It would be remiss of me not to mention Wait but Why&rsquo;s brilliant and complementary exposition of <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/2013/09/why-generation-y-yuppies-are-unhappy.html">Why Generation Y Yuppies Are Unhappy</a>.</p>
<p>Whatever shall we do with this information?</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re not special (phew, that&rsquo;s a weight off one&rsquo;s shoulders!), and we can&rsquo;t ever attain more than fleeting happiness or contentment.</p>
<p>What we <em>can</em> do is to make peace, and to savour with wide open senses the fractal infinity hidden in the moments that we are blessed with.</p>
<p>P.S. Buddha also had a <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/buddhism/beliefs/fournobletruths_1.shtml">number of great tips</a>.</p>
<p>P.P.S. During the night I started worrying that readers, especially my mom (hi mom!), might think that I&rsquo;m unhappy, and that this post is a cry for help. I would like to assure you all that I&rsquo;m currently enjoying life more than ever before, at least as far as my failing old memory is concerned. I can personally vouch for the making-peace-and-savouring-moments approach.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. Statistically, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/08/24/under-50-you-still-havent-hit-rock-bottom-happiness-wise/">humans hit happiness rock bottom</a> at around about 50, see the u-shaped graph below (thanks <a href="http://francoismalan.com">FM</a> for sending). A number of us are hiding here in the we&rsquo;ve-made-our-peace-thanks-for-all-the-fish long tails of the distribution, where we plan to ride this one out. Join us!</p>








<figure><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/08/24/under-50-you-still-havent-hit-rock-bottom-happiness-wise/">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/wapo-happy-graph.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #124: Ceci n’est pas d’ennui.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 12:16:28 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/</guid><description> This edition of the Weekly Head Voices is a retrospective of the period from Monday June 26 to Sunday July 30, where with weekly I mean regular(ish), which is still better than absent. :)
We spent the first week of July about 100km to the south of Durban.
It was an epic winter break-away with the conditions so summery that we forgot that it’s technically speaking the middle of winter. Down to the beach every day, balmy evenings spent outside, brilliant runs through the KwaZulu-Natal hills and a holiday destination that has mastered the arts of happy-children-happy-parental-units all contributed to a brilliant week.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices is a retrospective of the period from Monday June 26 to Sunday July 30, where with <em>weekly</em> I mean <em>regular(ish)</em>, which is still better than <em>absent</em>. :)</p>
<p>We spent the first week of July about 100km to the south of Durban.</p>
<p>It was an epic winter break-away with the conditions so summery that we forgot that it’s technically speaking the middle of winter. Down to the beach every day, balmy evenings spent outside, brilliant runs through the KwaZulu-Natal hills and a holiday destination that has mastered the arts of happy-children-happy-parental-units all contributed to a brilliant week.</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/IMG_0476.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/IMG_0476-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>On the way back to the airport, we squeezed in a visit to uShaka Marine World, where we visited the dolphins, the aquarium and I joined the two oldest genetic offspring units <a href="https://www.chimpandzee.co.za/ushaka/">zip-lining all over the water park</a>.</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/IMG_0720.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/IMG_0720-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The week after it was off to The Hague for mostly work and a few maximally cromulent social sessions with my besties.</p>
<p>Plans were made. Philosophical discussions were had. Fortunately, no planes were missed.</p>
<p>During all of this, <a href="http://openserve.co.za/open/">OpenServe’s elves</a> were busy digging up my neighbourhood installing these magical green <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Series_of_tubes">tubes</a> everywhere. They’re magical because soon they will be filled with super thin glass fiber, and then lit up with lovely lovely internet.</p>
<p>I really can’t wait.</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/IMG_0821-2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/07/IMG_0821-2-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>On the evening before taking chances but not missing my flight home, the conversation spent a good amount of time on the topics of happiness, contentment and life goals.</p>
<p>As a reader of this blog, you will know by now that we’re not big fans of happiness. See the last bit of <a href="/2011/04/07/happinessexception-weekly-head-voices-44/">Weekly Head Voices #44</a> (6+ years ago…) which has what I think is a good summary of why we are not.</p>
<p>On the other hand, we have always thought that <em>contentment</em> is perhaps a more practical state to try and work towards.</p>
<p>There are however those who <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2016/aug/17/psychology-happiness-contentment-humans-aspire-goals-accomplish-evolution">make the logical argument</a> that contentment has been evolved out of us a long time ago, and that we are thus doomed never to find contentment for more than a few moments.</p>
<p>In <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">WHV #64</a>, following an old tradition of hiding backyard philosophy in arb blog posts, I suggested side-stepping the issue by not focusing on life goals, which are in essence a sort of end point which will invariably lead to post-achievement ennui, but instead focusing on setting and following a certain direction.</p>
<p>Life directions don’t have to have endpoints, but they can have waypoints. The difference is that you know that these are waypoints, and you accept that the journey continues until it finally stops forever.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the conversation motivated me to start a new search for more scientifically-oriented literature on the topics of human happiness, contentment, life goals and so forth.</p>
<p>Up to now my search has not turned up very much. In a surprising turn of events, it seems that there is no shortage of people who are willing to sell you the literature-equivalent of snake-oil, in some cases knowingly but in most cases utterly oblivious.</p>
<p>Somewhere else during this same evening (it was a productive night), we provisionally added a third rule to the <em>WHV’s Two Rules for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em>.</p>
<p>The rules are now: 1. Be useful. 2. Be likeable. 3. Evolve.</p>
<p>I have been using rules 1 and 2 of the hitherto bi-ruled WHV’s TRAGSL-JS-WCF (pronounced TRAGSL-JS-WCF) as a central component in my GOUs education.</p>
<p>Rule 3 should be understood as actively and continuously upgrading oneself based on continuous introspection and retrospection.</p>
<p>I was initially hesitant to add a third rule to the previously perfect two-rule combo, but wise friend made good arguments for reminding system users of the important of deliberate and continuous self-improvement.</p>
<p>In 25 years I hope to be able to report back on the efficacy of this system based on a smallish but long-term study with N=3.</p>
<p>What do you think?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>