<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Transition on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/transition/</link><description>Recent content in Transition on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/transition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2024 to 2025 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to the year 2025!
We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this traditional yearly transition blog post here to keep you busy in the meantime.
The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2025!</p>
<p>We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this <a href="/tags/transition">traditional yearly transition blog post</a> here to keep you busy in the meantime.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20241228-st-francis-light-house.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a7c8fad0a4fb3336.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_c471bba5b301f4e3.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_7e36ecc6dd88d868.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp"
            

        
            alt="The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For those of you who are new here, 1) welcome! and 2) the traditional yearly transition post is where I both ramble semi-coherently on about the year that is closest to its conclusion and also speculate a bit about the year that is closest to its inception.</p>
<p>The main audience for this post is me &ndash; writing this up and the concomitant thinking and formulating bits form an important part of my maintenance process &ndash; but to anyone else who is reading this, there is hopefully something of value (or just a bit of entertainment) for you in these words. In any case, I am super happy that you&rsquo;re here!</p>
<h2 id="life-events">Life events</h2>
<p>In 2024, <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#i-turned-50">I turned 50</a> while <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#gou-1-turned-18">GOU#1 turned 18</a>, finished high school and is now on her way to university.</p>
<p>I mention these two in the same breath, because looking back it feels like the 5 years of her high school, a substantial chunk of time in terms of her development, went by in a flash.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s almost like we blinked <a href="/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">when she was still our little girl going to high school</a> and now suddenly she is an adult, and we finally feel like actual adults (aka old people) ourselves.</p>
<p>Although these have been amazing years for us, this experience of a whole period of life flashing by, through the lense of our children&rsquo;s development into adults, is a stark reminder to strive even harder to experience the living daylights out of every single moment that we are blessed with.</p>
<p>If all goes according to plan, we will have two more blink-blink-another-high-school-journey-is-complete experiences (GOU#2 is now in her second year of that journey, GOU#3 has a few years to go before she can start) so we should probably try to blink far less often.</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>After the dip both this blog and I went through in 2023 (total of 3 WHV posts&hellip;) and a very slow blogging start in 2024, it does feel like I might slowly be getting my WHV groove back, which seems to be evidenced by 66% more WHV posting in 2024, i.e. a whole 5 WHV posts! (Contrast this with the historic average of one post every two weeks.)</p>
<p>In the introduction to <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/">WHV #255 You lift me up</a> I speculate a bit about the reasons for my hiatus (I didn&rsquo;t mention there that maybe 2023 was actually just a real downer for me) and the current potential revival.</p>
<p>In addition to the posts here, I published <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">12 technical posts over on at the vxlabs</a> and a whole bunch of short howtos / recipes in the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">brand new TiL section of my other-OTHER website</a>. WHV #255 <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">explains the motivation behind the TiL section</a>.</p>
<p>I am also quite happy about the fact that I wrote a daily entry in my private diary for a large part of 2024, and this is something that I would like to continue, hopefully for an even larger part of 2025.</p>
<p>Spending some time every day to review that day, where the review is enriched by the deliberate activitity of trying to formulate everything into a story that I can write down, helps me to make sense of everything.</p>
<p>Writing in general seems to modulate positively my experience of reality.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a lot about this idea in various posts on this blog, but allow me to surface <a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#the-describers">two relevant sections from WHV 180</a>, and especially the quote below (but you should go read those two sections):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less faulty entity.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>My secret running goal for 2024 was to do 25km of running every week. In my head this was auto-simplified to 1200km for the year (you know, the way one often calculates a month as 4 weeks), but of course we&rsquo;re talking 1300km.</p>
<p>Well, I failed at all of these goals!</p>
<p>However, I did manage to run a total of 1149.7km over the year, which comes to an average of 22.1km per week, which I am pretty OK with. I had over 100 hours of fun (I truly enjoy running) and no injuries that I can remember.</p>
<p>The training calendar below shows that August was my laziest month, but that&rsquo;s because August has the worst weather, and because I was away for a week visiting my Dutch family and getting many tens of thousands of dancing steps instead. The calendar also shows how I made a last ditch effort in December to close the gap with my goal as much as possible.</p>










<figure><a href="20250101-strava-training-calendar.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_e13adc1c4101c63a.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_2caa5fcc1a219359.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_57229ed99a10234e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You might remember <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">my three metrics-focused goals from last year&rsquo;s post</a>, namely 50 consecutive push-ups, VO<sub>2</sub> Max of at least 50 and a resting state heart rate of 50 or under&hellip;</p>
<p>Well, 50 consecutive push-ups was not that hard, Apple Health reports my average resting state heart rate for 2024 as 48 BPM (this would be mostly via my Garmin Forerunner 245 and more recently 265) but my VO<sub>2</sub> briefly peaked at 49 (some time after I turned 50) before settling back on 48. I  would have loved that 50, but <a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/blog/fitness/whats-a-good-vo2-max-for-me/">48 is not the worst for a man of my age</a>.</p>
<p>My real goal for the coming year is the same as last year: I want to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>The older I get and the more I learn, the more I understand that with exercise, the more hours I can spend every week doing it, of course maintaining balance with the rest of my life (see life systems further down), the better my meat-coated skeleton will work, and the happier the ghost driving it will be.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’re a ghost driving a meat-coated skeleton made from stardust; what do you have to be scared of?</p>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2022/10/13/ghost-stardust/">@rat_sandwich on twitter, January 31, 2013</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>P.S. of course I will again go for 25km of running per week. I think logging substantially more than 120 hours of activities in Strava will be good. I might even give that VO<sub>2</sub> Max goal another shot.</p>
<p>P.P.S. I read <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/outlive/">Peter Attia&rsquo;s book Outlive</a> a few months ago. This is a detailed and practical manual for healthy living. There&rsquo;s a lot in there, but at the core he wants you, while you still have any say in the matter, to become as fit (measured by our friend VO<sub>2</sub> Max) and as strong (measured by grip strength) as you possibly can. You see, from middle age we&rsquo;re all on a downward curve, and there&rsquo;s not much we can do about it, except ensuring that we start as high as possible.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. It&rsquo;s funny; back in school, I thought little of athleticism, because it was a jock thing, and the jocks were generally not very kind to nerd-kind (my people). Now that I&rsquo;m older and quite ironically due to my nerdy lifelong learning habits, I strive for us much athleticism as I can &ldquo;fit&rdquo; in (jock joke harr harr).</p>
<h3 id="diet">Diet</h3>
<p>During this post&rsquo;s generously long incubation, I thought it worth adding here my approach to eating.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been practising 16-8 time-restricted eating (intermittent fasting in some circles) about 95% of the time since somewhere in 2019. I first <a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">wrote about it in WHV 186</a>, and then in <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#i-really-don-t-like-breakfast">WHV 221 I came out and stated the beef I have with breakfast</a> (that pun might be too heavy for this post).</p>
<p>Anyways, while I still believe that breakfast is bad for most people, I know that the scientific world has not yet reached consensus on time-restricted eating for healthy folks.</p>
<p>However, there is considerably more consensus that lowering daily caloric intake is good for most people.</p>
<p>For me, 16-8 TRE, where I simply don&rsquo;t ingest anything besides water and black coffee from about 7 in the evening until about noon the next day, is an extremely practical and especially low-effort way to reduce caloric intake.</p>
<p>When I do eat, the portions are modest, I try to stick to natural and unprocessed where I can and I keep an eye on protein.</p>
<p>When I do break these rules, I do so with deliberation. Great food, great wine, great beer and the company of friends and family, especially when combined, constitute a perfect reason to break all of these rules.</p>
<p>In short, reduce caloric intake, increase per-calorie value and/or enjoyment!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and Tools</h2>
<p>This is the place where I summarise (read: ramble on about) the current state of my digital tools and systems. If you&rsquo;re going to skip a (nerdy) section, this is the one! You can dive back in at <a href="#life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</a>.</p>
<p>I am one of those people who <em>regularly</em> finds and uses information from notes that I made.</p>
<p>If I have the note, and I often do because I make an effort to write stuff down with the lowest possible friction but the highest possible chance of being found again, this is generally miles faster than finding the information online, even with tools like the <a href="https://kagi.com/">premium search engine Kagi</a> which I have been using regularly for a few weeks now.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-and-obsidian">Emacs and Obsidian</h3>
<p>A year ago I <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#systems-and-tools">experienced a bit of a crisis of (Emacs) faith</a>.</p>
<p>Whilst that was more of a clash between the either-or poles of Emacs and Obsidian, I am now at a place where I&rsquo;m finding increasing uses for Obisidian as an <em>additional</em> note-taking tool, working on the same collection of hundreds of org-mode and a growing number of markdown files.</p>
<p>Emacs and org-roam treat <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">markdown files as if they are native org-roam nodes</a>. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/BBazard/obsidian-orgmode-cm6">Benoit Bazard&rsquo;s fantastic new CodeMirror 6 org-mode plugin for Obsidian</a> and my <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Monitor-rclone-cron-job-with-Home-Assistant">rclone + syncthing syncing setup for iPhone</a>, I have semi-usable org database support on my phone.</p>
<p><a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> and since recently <a href="https://orgro.org/">Orgro</a> are great for editing org files in the iPhone, but they are missing the searching and discovery, let&rsquo;s call it <em>note management</em>, aspects of a tool like Obsidian.</p>
<p>Long but quite important-to-me story short, it looks like for the time being I&rsquo;ll continue to use both Emacs and Obsidian for note-taking. Because interoperability is not perfect, there will be some natural gravitational pull towards the one or the other which I have decided to explore.</p>
<p>At the moment, it looks like I might be writing more of my atomic notes as markdown files, whilst using org for the lab journal / logbook and project management type of notes.</p>
<p>On a deeper note, the Obsidian team is doing fantastic work.</p>
<p>Apart from their <a href="https://stephango.com/file-over-app"><em>file over app</em> philosophy</a>, Obsidian is <em>programmable</em> as can be witnessed by the thriving extension ecosystem.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?id=ai-chat-as-md">written a modest extension</a> to test this out from the inside. The programmability is not as extensive as that of Emacs, but it runs everywhere, even on mobile devices, and it might be extensive enough for the note-taking platform that Obsidian has become.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Emacs on and off since the late 90s, but for the past 10 years it has become an always-running and integral part of my life. It feels really strange, disconcerting if I&rsquo;m being honest, that it seems to be losing its core spot.</p>
<p>I console myself in these moments with the observation that science must trump dogma, always.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m writing this post in Emacs.</p>
<h4 id="til">TiL</h4>
<p>Thanks to Obsidian, my other, OTHER website <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">now has a &ldquo;today I learned&rdquo; (TIL) section</a> at <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">charlbotha.com/til</a>, published directly from a sub-directory of my main notes directory.</p>
<p>The benefit is that there is even less friction than usual and, perhaps more importantly, the psychological friction has also been reduced because I have convinced myself that the posts there are just notes and not true blog posts.</p>
<h3 id="honorable-tool-mentions-zotero-and-quarto">Honorable tool mentions: Zotero and Quarto</h3>
<p>After <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#omnivore-is-no-more">my distastrous recommendation of Omnivore turned into a disaster</a>, it is with some emotional trepidation but intellectual confidence (thanks to file over app and its staunchly open source nature) that I can re-recommend Zotero as a reference (of all kinds!) management tool for the long term.</p>
<p>After I last mentioned it on my blog, I have been using it quite intensively, and <a href="https://bsky.app/hashtag/zotero?author=charlbotha.com">I keep on running into delightful features</a>, like the built-in PDF reader&rsquo;s pop-up visualization of citations and image references.</p>
<p>A more recent but high power entry into my toolbelt is <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, which I will contend strikes a fantastic usability-power balance in the world of technical document and presentation authoring. I&rsquo;ve now used it, in anger, to write a fairly extensive technical document, along with the afore-mentioned Zotero and <a href="https://retorque.re/zotero-better-bibtex/">Better BibTeX</a> for reference management, and the experience was magically smooth. To seal the deal, by the end I used Quarto to generate an attractive-looking docx for interoperability with the other stakeholders, but my contact time with Word was mercifully minimised.</p>
<h3 id="my-micro-blogging-history-2008---2025">My micro-blogging history 2008 - 2025</h3>
<p>Twitter says I created my account there in December of 2008. However, <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">this blog here says I only started using it in April of 2009</a>. (Twitter first launched in July of 2006.)</p>
<p>Some years later in 2016, coincidentally right before the previous Trumpocalypse, I wrote a post naively suggesting that we should <a href="/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/">replace twitter with something better (blogs&hellip;)</a> due to the risk of Twitter possibly going bad (ahem) and to the observation then that it was (then already) doing a crappy job keeping out abusive users (AHEM).</p>
<p>That post <a href="/2016/11/20/look-mom-hacker-news-front-page/">reached the front page of Hacker News</a>, and was thus read and discussed over there (and probably in the comments here) by tens of thousands of nerds, and a surprisingly small share of the usual &ldquo;Ackchyually&rdquo;-Bros.</p>
<p>(Please allow me this little tangent: A mental model that will really ease your time on sites like HN and reddit, is that the person on the other side, especially when they come across as super confident and assertive, is probably <strong>not</strong> an expert, not even by a long shot, on the topic that they are so confidently mansplaining. In fact, they are probably the least qualified to say anything. ChatGPT avant le lettre one might say. Ok back to your regular programming&hellip;)</p>
<p>Needless to say, my specific idea of replacing twitter with&hellip; blogs and rss was not implemented by the internet, at least not at that point&hellip;</p>
<p>When Musk acquired Twitter in October of 2022, the writing started appearing on the wall, at first vaguely, but with more and more definition as the months went on. I started looking for micro-blogging alternatives that were not twitter.</p>
<p>At first Mastodon looked too complicated, but then someone setup a <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#emacs-mastodon-server-was-irresistible">mastodon server dedicated to Emacs and I was immediately sold</a>.</p>
<p>However, Mastodon indeed turned out to be too complex and fundamentally quite fragile (all but the larger instances have a just a volunteer human or two behind them), leading to the owner of my favourite instance bascially being harassed to such an extent that it was better for him to get out of this business and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@cpbotha/113340325817581254">shut the Emacs mastodon server down</a>.</p>
<p>When I saw this announcement, I was disheartened.</p>
<p>When I read that Mastodon supports message export, but not message import, meaning that my posts would languish in a sad archive file somewhere, I was convinced that I had to try something out that was not Mastodon.</p>
<p>In parallel to my Mastodon efforts, I did also try Threads and was quite enthusiastic about its scale, and the speed with which Meta managed to build it, but I didn&rsquo;t manage to get any sort of interaction there. I think that it might be more geared for the Instagram model of influencers broadcasting to large groups of followers, in contrast to a more collaborative setup. (Urgh, the recent news about Meta&rsquo;s new &ldquo;free speech&rdquo; overhaul is additional motivation for me to spend even less energy there.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, it turns out that the newer and shinier microblogging service Bluesky was conceived in 2019 with the goal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluesky">&ldquo;to find or develop an open and decentralized standard for social media that would give users more control over their data and experience&rdquo;</a>, precisely the sort of thing that has suddenly become even more painfully relevant with the advent of the Trumpocalypse part deux, now with more Musk-power.</p>
<p>Long story short, in a very short time, Bluesky has proven to be almost exactly the microblogging platform that I enjoy participating in. Lots of human interaction, no ads, many different user-contributed algorithms to choose from, including just seeing the stuff your people post, in the order that they post it &ndash; it really feels like the thing was put together with semi-normal human interaction as the central concern.</p>
<p>Up to now, it also feels like <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#bluesky-is-my-new-micro-blogging-thing-of-choice">many folks on there prefer being decent to each other</a>, something I militantly (haha) support.</p>
<p>Some mastodon folks are downright unhappy with bluesky, because they feel that it&rsquo;s not truly decentralized like mastodon.</p>
<p>Thing is, Bluesky has chosen a different spot on the usability - decentralization spectrum, and and my opinion is exactly usable and decentralised enough for what it needs to be and do at this moment in time.</p>
<p>Looking slightly further into the future, there are well-funded initiatives like <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/13/24342799/free-our-feeds-social-media-ecosystem-at-protocol-bluesky">Free our feeds</a>, ideologically and technologically supported by the Bluesky company but otherwise unconnected, which has amongst its <a href="https://freeourfeeds.com/">goals to &ldquo;build independently hosted infrastructure (a second &lsquo;relay&rsquo;) so that Bluesky users, developers and researchers always have full access to the stream of content and data no matter what the company decides to do in future&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>If you would like to know more, Faine Greenwood has written <a href="https://little-flying-robots.ghost.io/the-great-bluesky-migration-i-answer-some-of-your-questions/">this great Bluesky explainer</a>.</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</h2>
<p>My Life Systems are the guiding principles, rules, personal values and bags of tips that I have explicitly defined and refined over the years to help me be the best human that I can be.</p>
<p>Note: I write these up primarily as a reminder to myself. If it comes across as prescriptive, please remember that I&rsquo;m telling <em>me</em> how to live my life. I can do this, because I <em>am</em> the boss of me.</p>
<h3 id="core">Core</h3>
<p>You&rsquo;ll be happy to hear that the core of my Life Systems 2025 is exactly the same as the previous edition <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">Life Systems 2024</a>, except for the version number increase, and the concomitant price increase. (taking a leaf here from the Intel playbook!)</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to read <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">the 2024 write-up</a>, here is the compressed version:</p>
<p><em>Guiding principles:</em> 1. Love 2. Science. <em>Two no three rules for achieving great success in life, or just surviving, whichever comes first:</em> 1. Be useful. 2. be likable and 3. evolve. <em>Personal values:</em> 1. Be kind. 2. Be grateful. 3. Attend fully to the now. 4. Enjoy life with family and with my friends. 5. Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers. 6. Be there for my family. 7. Add value through work. 8. Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise. 9. Build and/or fix something. 10. Learn new things. 11. Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</p>
<h3 id="balance">Balance</h3>
<p>What I have been thinking about this year, especially when things get quite busy, is the sometimes tricky practice of applying balance to one&rsquo;s personal values.</p>
<p>A straight-forward example is when important work obligations start impacting my sleep or exercise schedule, in which case I have to apply balance and tone down slightly the ambition to fulfil personal value no 7.</p>
<p>It can easily get more tricky however; when something on that list of personal values, which is important to you, starts taking up more than its fair share of energy, that will come at the cost of all of the other endeavours that you value.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have a hard and fast rule for this, only the measure of remembering to <em>pay attention</em> also at that meta-level so that one can make suitable balancing adjustments when required.</p>
<h3 id="work-hard-party-hard-rest-hard">Work hard. Party hard. Rest hard.</h3>
<p>A lesson that has only become clearer for me over the years is that we humans function best when we are able to focus on one thing at a time, and when we have as few things as possible on the list that we select from.</p>
<p>This works at all scales of life, from what task do I work on during this half-hour all the way up to my main priority for today, or my three main priorities for this year.</p>
<p>The challenge in applying this lesson is three-fold:</p>
<ol>
<li>Know which thing to focus on at any time,</li>
<li>reduce switching between things and yet</li>
<li>get to all of the things that you should get to.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you have all three of these covered, then comes the truly difficult part: <strong>Attend fully to the now.</strong></p>
<p>Those of us who are lucky get about 4000 weeks of life.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not truly present in the thing that you&rsquo;ve chosen at this moment, you are not using that allotted time to its fullest extent.</p>
<p>You can never ever get that time back.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like you&rsquo;re in a Michelin-starred restaurant, and instead of going power level 9000 with all of your senses and your thoughts and your whole being into <em>experiencing</em> that food with your favourite human(s), you&rsquo;re scrolling on your phone, absent-mindedly shovelling forkfuls into your mouth.</p>
<p>Do the opposite.</p>
<p>Pick your battles, but sometimes also choose a party if you can and don&rsquo;t forget to rest like your life depends on it. Whatever you do, be the most maximally present in the thing you&rsquo;ve chosen. Presence and attention improve with regular practice.</p>
<p>In short: Work hard, party hard, rest hard.</p>
<!-- be maximally present to use that time right; do everything HARD -- came during my 2025-01-11 morning run -->
<h2 id="my-2024-to-2025-transition-wishes">My 2024 to 2025 transition wishes</h2>
<p>Humans<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> <em>at their peak</em> are a thing of beauty.</p>
<p>Above all they are truly kind.  They live and breathe the knowledge that we <em>homo sapiens</em> are at our absolute best when we connect with each other.</p>
<p>Peak humans are graceful, and they are elegant, and they are in harmony &ndash; the best sort of balance &ndash; with their surroundings, with those around them and with themselves.</p>
<p>Attaining this peak is hard. Maintaining it is nigh impossible. Best we can go for is <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">the never-ending practice</a> of these characteristics, and an eternal striving for moments to <em>become them</em>.</p>
<p>Friends, I wish you and your connected ones the willpower to strive for grace and elegance and harmony, and the presence of mind to attend fully to those perfect moments when they occur.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, you might be one of these&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2023 to 2024 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 15:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2024 everyone, and especially to this traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: View from first morning of the Cape of Good Hope hiking trail with family and friends. The 3-in-1 hill climb in the summer sun at the end of day 2 almost took me out.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2024 everyone, and especially to this <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="2023-12-16-cape-point-hike.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_e736f7a9c5849337.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_5d2baa1368199c5d.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_92dc0cc764247a73.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_878bfcc0c607f876.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_5d2baa1368199c5d.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from first morning of the Cape of Good Hope hiking trail with family and friends. The 3-in-1 hill climb in the summer sun at the end of day 2 almost took me out."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>View from first morning of the Cape of Good Hope hiking trail with family and friends. The 3-in-1 hill climb in the summer sun at the end of day 2 almost took me out.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="overview-and-a-warning">Overview, and a warning</h2>
<p>While the year transition posts down here are usually an optimistic and upbeat affair, I have to warn you that this year&rsquo;s edition is a bit different.</p>
<p>Most of the possibly depressing stuff is in the first section, all about aging and cancer and mortality, which you probably could have guessed based on the title, and if not, now on the summary here. Consider strongly skipping the section if you prefer a more optimistic reading of this post.</p>
<p>After the aforementioned <em>harshing of the vibe</em>, I give an extremely spotty review of the physical (running and exercise), the cerebral (writing) and the virtual (systems and tools) aspects of the past year.</p>
<p>I conclude the post with some backyard philosophical ramblings on my continuing efforts at being a good human, and my wishes for you and your loved ones.</p>
<h2 id="aging-is-rough">Aging is rough</h2>
<p>For me, 2023 was the year of really getting in touch with my mortality.</p>
<p>In August of 2023, I <em>started</em> my 50th revolution around the sun.</p>
<p>My birthday might have been enough of a reminder, but the message was made unquestionably clear with <a href="/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/">my prostate cancer</a> diagnosis in February. No thanks to mother nature, and all thanks to science and modern healthcare, the surgical treatment was swift and as effective as we are able to measure.</p>
<p>Love, by all of my friends and family supporting me throughout all of this, and science, see modern healthcare above, got me through this whole adventure with only a small number of scars to show for it. Besides the physical scars, my previously strong trust in my physical robustness took a really big knock.</p>
<p>Much more recently, as in a day or two ago, the pathology results for two recently excised suspicious skin growths came back from the pathology lab.</p>
<p>Both are basal cell carcinoma (BCC), but while the one was completely excised, the other was not, and was also classified as morpheaform BCC, the rarest and more aggressive form of the three.</p>
<p>To the best of my current knowledge, we just need to remove the rest and I should be mostly derisked, but dangit, I had really hoped not to have to think about any form of cancer again for a little while longer.</p>
<p>So, people, please take the following advice as seriously as you possibly can:</p>
<ul>
<li>The sun, especially down here, is amazing but also quite dangerous. Lotion up as often as possible, wear that stupid hat, spend more time in the shade.</li>
<li>All of you, especially younger readers: Use hearing protection at music events. Last year before Lowlands I acquired <a href="https://eargasm.com/products/eargasm-high-fidelity-earplugs">Eargast High Fidelity Earplugs</a>, only about 20 years too late! (like skin canccer, tinnitus is another one of those things you have to start actively preventing decades before it possibly starts)</li>
<li>Over 40? Get your PSA tested.</li>
</ul>
<p>On a more philosophical and hopefully not too depressing note: It has become viscerally clear to me that once one is past reproductive age, one has irrevocably entered the domain of borrowed time.</p>
<p>If you think about evolution and more specifically selection, you can see that survival traits, by the power of math, could only really be encouraged in the young. After the reproductive phase, with <em>genes already passed on</em>, there could be no <em>effective</em> reward or punishment for respectively beneficial and detrimental traits.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the antagonistic pleiotropic (AP) hypothesis posits that there are genes which control more than one trait &ldquo;where at least one of these traits is beneficial to the organism&rsquo;s fitness early on in life and at least one is detrimental to the organism&rsquo;s fitness later on due to a decline in the force of natural selection&rdquo; (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antagonistic_pleiotropy_hypothesis">AP - wikipedia</a>, <a href="https://www.nature.com/scitable/knowledge/library/the-evolution-of-aging-23651151/">The Evolution of Aging - Nature</a>)</p>
<p>An interesting recent example is <a href="https://alzres.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13195-020-00740-0">this 2021 study of apolipoprotein E (APOE ε4)</a>, which is the strongest genetic risk factor for late onset Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease, but at the same time is also associated with cognitive benefits earlier in life.</p>
<p>From the discussion in the linked paper:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>These results taken together provide support for the antagonistic pleiotropic hypothesis as cognitive performance was better at younger ages in APOE ε4 heterozygotes and both heterozygous and homozygous APOE ε4 carriers also had higher risk of dementia at older ages.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So&hellip; about &ldquo;mother&rdquo; nature.</p>
<p>Nature is beautiful, but absolutely ruthless.</p>
<p>The mental model of &ldquo;natural&rdquo; being beneficial for us humans is at best only coincidentally and very partially useful. For the most part, it&rsquo;s wrong and quite dangerous.</p>
<p>In the end, we can only rely on science, and on each other, to survive and flourish.</p>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>In last year&rsquo;s transition post, I was <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#running">hoping for an average of 25km per week in 2023</a> which would have meant about 1200km for the year.</p>
<p>However, I did not plan on being taken out of the&hellip; running for 6 weeks by my prostate before being allowed to start slowing picking it up again.</p>
<p>In spite of that, I was super happy to see a bit later in the year that 1000km was still in reach, and so I went for that.</p>
<p>Something that looks like it could be my gluteus medius attempted to sabotage my efforts during the final weeks, but on December 30 I pushed through with a last run of the year. 1000km in the pocket!</p>










<figure><a href="strava-fitness-2023.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_fda5ac701be2142f.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_c8669b3c69d1229.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_e07f5d05f7cfd8af.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_9f954c3d4f0bafc3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_c8669b3c69d1229.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: The smooth part of the curve from the start of April until mid-May was for surgery and recovery. I&rsquo;m happy with the gradual build-up after that and the big push at the end of the year!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>The smooth part of the curve from the start of April until mid-May was for surgery and recovery. I&rsquo;m happy with the gradual build-up after that and the big push at the end of the year!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Regular running is the mechanical backbone of my life.</p>
<p>Even when the stress is great and it feels like stuff is falling apart, those clockwork runs bring peace and perspective. When it&rsquo;s going really great, they bring exhilaration and they feel like a celebration of life!</p>
<p>Although I am hopeful that the current injury resolves itself, which it should if it is in fact my gluteus medius, I might start looking into cross-training this year. It would be great to have an alternative exercise modality to tide me over when injuries happen and to keep me out of the sun a part of the time.</p>
<p>My only running-specific desire is to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>For you numbers-people, that&rsquo;s probably not the most interesting goal.</p>
<p>As a hopefully more satisfying alternative, I would like to offer my super-secret exercise goal for 2024:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be able to do 50 consecutive push-ups,</li>
<li>have a VO₂ Max of at least 50 and</li>
<li>a resting state heart rate of 50 or under.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>For reasons that I&rsquo;ve now mentioned often enough, I produced only a small number of longer blog posts in 2023, namely the <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/">transition post</a>, three (3) weekly head voices posts (including the cancer one), and the <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/">2023 note-taking strategy post</a> which I&rsquo;m really happy with.</p>
<p>Besides that, there were a few short technical postlets over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>On November 14, faced by this barren landscape of almost no blogging, I thought it was worth trying to break through the concomitant writer&rsquo;s block by putting out a <em>daily</em> bullet list of life minutiae: Experiences, learnings and observations that might be interesting to Someone on the Internet.</p>
<p>By reducing the expectation to a straight-forward list of daily miscellanea it would in theory be substantially easier and faster to produce said list.</p>
<p>Further, I deliberately did so on my favourite mastodon server, namely <a href="https://emacs.ch/">emacs.ch</a>, because I trusted that the obscurity of mastodon would mean that not many people would actually see my daily lifelogs, which would further reduce posting friction.</p>
<p>In a surprising turn of events, all of this seemed to work!</p>
<p>As I <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/issues/26868">can&rsquo;t directly link to a mastodon search yet</a>, you will have to go to <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha">my profile</a> or to <a href="https://emacs.ch/tags/lifelog">the #lifelog tag</a> and browse back if you are interested in the first 30 (thirty!) posts, starting on November 14.</p>
<p>On <a href="/2023/12/18/daily-head-voices-on-monday-2023-12-18/">December 18 I decided to move the Daily Head Voices back here</a> because reasons (which you can read about in that post). Since then I have really been enjoying keeping them going during the Christmas break, and I&rsquo;ve also made some tweaks to the technical setup in order to be able to publish them more efficiently.</p>
<p>Although I would really like to work on more substantial posts in the future, recent experience has shown that it might be a while before I can make the space that that requires. The <a href="/categories/lifelog/">lifelog posts</a> are an enjoyable way for me to keep the writing pipes open in the meantime!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and tools</h2>
<p>A core part of my functioning is <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human">the system of software tools and other tricks</a> that I use to work and live better. Other names that people use to describe this thing include second brain, <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">exocortex</a>, or just a really big pile of lists.</p>
<p>Shortly after my pretty detailed <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/">Note-taking strategy 2023</a> blog post, I underwent what I can only describe as some form of Emacs crisis of faith.</p>
<p>During this period, I experienced deep doubt in my current system, and came pretty close to jumping ship.</p>
<p>My crisis was largely due to three things:</p>
<ol>
<li>The shiny webkit-based rendering engines in many of the competitors, enabling useful-looking visualizations and interesting new visual interaction approaches.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins">vibrant extension community of the local-first Obsidian note-taking tool</a> where many enthusiasts were tapping into the enormous javascript / typescript library ecosystem, and shiny webkit-rendering mentioned above.</li>
<li>Emacs and org-mode&rsquo;s comparatively weak mobile support. (yes, I&rsquo;ve tried, and purchased were relevant, <a href="#d41d8c">beorg</a>, plain.org, organice, orgro and probably many more.)</li>
</ol>
<p>After months of cogitation, I fortunately convinced myself to first test the waters before jumping, where my usual style is just to throw <strong>everything</strong> out and start over, and extremely quickly ran into the glaring weakness that is Obsidian&rsquo;s lack of first class support for the humble timestamp&hellip;</p>
<p>This is something that we Orgmode users take for granted, but man, the Orgmode timestamp is actually pretty amazing.</p>
<p>This textual analogue of an inverted ice bucket seemed to shock me out of my daze, and suddenly I was again able to make peace with Old Reliable BFG9000, aka Emacs and Org.</p>
<p>As part of my atonement, and also to mitigate some of their perceived deficiencies, I coded up and published the following software upgrades to Emacs, Org-mode and Org-roam:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/braindump4000">braindump4000</a>: Convert any Org-mode database into a hyperlinked website, and also an Obsidian vault, so that you can browse it on your phone using the Obsidian app.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">org-roam-canvas</a>: Expose your whole org-roam database in such a way that you can embed org-roam notes as part of an Obsidian canvas. (see screenshots on the github)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity">org-roam-similarity</a>: Use AI-based similarity (i.e. learned document embeddings / vectors) to interactively list similar org-roam notes to the one that you are working on. This is something that I&rsquo;ve been dreaming about for years, and this is also something that I&rsquo;ve been using quite regularly and successfully to surface relevant information from the depths of my notes!</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-to-apple-notes">org-roam-to-apple-notes</a>: This was quite painful thanks to Apple&rsquo;s super bad AppleScript support of Apple Notes, but it has turned out to be quite useful. On macOS, you can export your whole org-roam database, or just the note that you&rsquo;re currently working on, straight into Apple Notes. Although I implemented base64 embedding of images as this was <em>rumoured</em> to work, images don&rsquo;t work because Apple.</li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_c599996d6ef5a83.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_bc73da04581f6dbb.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_e15f6dbc1a62ed46.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_910a12b14db41a96.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_bc73da04581f6dbb.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: A screenshot of org-roam-similarity showing similar notes in org-roam-buffer."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>A screenshot of <code>org-roam-similarity</code> showing similar notes in <code>org-roam-buffer</code>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I write this, it really feels like my faith has been fully restored.</p>
<h3 id="ai">AI</h3>
<p>2023 was the year when, through the astounding success and utility of large language models like ChatGPT and friends, as well as latent diffusion models like StableDiffusion, Dall-E and Midjourney, and many more examples of generative AI, we could finally start using the term &ldquo;AI&rdquo; almost completely unironically!</p>
<p>Thanks to Day Job, <a href="/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/#genai">I had the opportunity to go quite deep</a>, giving a number of pretty detailed talks on the nuts and bolts of transformer-based language models.</p>
<p>The reason I&rsquo;m mentioning it here though, is just to make a public note of the fact that I have been exploring and integrating these new tools into all of my workflows as much as makes sense, attempting to push the barriers here and there.</p>
<p>Like the preternaturally productive <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2023/Mar/27/ai-enhanced-development/">Simon Willison writes</a>, the current generation of AI coding assistance tools are enabling me to take on personal projects I previously would not have due to the time required, and to get those projects to a usable state far more quickly.</p>
<p>My own programming ability is still the driving force (this is the part in my brain that models and simulates software systems in wetware so that I can implement and debug them), but the AI takes care of so much boiler plate, and also helps quickly exploring multiple high probability solutions to the little problems that one invariably runs into.</p>
<p>Besides <a href="https://github.com/features/copilot">Github Copilot</a> which I use in VS Code and also in Emacs via <a href="https://github.com/copilot-emacs/copilot.el">copilot.el</a> to write, sort of ironically, better Emacs Lisp code more quickly, I am trying to integrate at least one AI assistant into my general daily workflow.</p>
<p>My current flavour is <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/">perplexity</a>, an LLM-based system that focuses on answering questions, using background web searches coupled with a current generation LLM.</p>
<p>Although perplexity works really well as a question answering tool, I am waiting for something that combines its talents with a more refined version of the already impressive but sometimes a bit wild <a href="https://github.com/KillianLucas/open-interpreter">Open Interpreter</a> (which I have obviously played with), and for that true AI assistant Jarvis-like tool to be always within reach&hellip;</p>
<p><a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2023/09/new-ray-ban-meta-smart-glasses/">Meta&rsquo;s new Ray Ban AI-powered smart glasses</a> look like a very interesting hardware step in this direction, and might even mean that while I lost <a href="/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/#bet-1-huds">that 2009 bet about HUDs</a> with regard to its timing, I was at least thinking in the right direction!</p>
<p>Please excuse the rambling; I am really quite excited about the now near future role of AI assistants in human culture!</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2024">Life systems 2024</h2>
<p>As <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">January 2022 Charl remarked</a>, <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">our January 2021 self really seemed to have everything figured out and organized</a>, at least in terms of life directions. Furthermore, if we&rsquo;re being honest with ourselves, <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#things-i-would-like-to-work-on-in-2023">January 2023</a> was also quite fuzzy&hellip;</p>
<p>Surprisingly to me however, this year, after spending some thinking time during the vacation, I have compiled a pretty organized-looking and hopefully practical list of personal values, which I will hereby add to the famous <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">WHV approach to life, the universe and everything (WALUE)</a>.</p>
<p>You might recall that our guiding principles were two-fold: 1. Love. 2. Science. (in that order)</p>
<p>.. while the <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">The WHV’s Two no Three Rules for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</a> were 1. Be useful, 2. be likable and 3. evolve.</p>
<p>Over the years I added six personal directions on top of all that, and then later, in a seemingly well-motivated but eventually unsuccessful attempt to apply those directions more successfully, I grouped them into two clusters, namely 1. Grow, learn, build, enjoy. (motion) and 2. Be useful. Be likeable. Be kind. (self-checks).</p>
<p>Well, <strong>this</strong> year I&rsquo;m replacing those two clusters with the following re-expanded list of my more concrete personal values and priorities.  In all cases, it should be possible to use these to check the desirability of any choice or activity.</p>
<ol>
<li>Be kind.</li>
<li>Be grateful.</li>
<li>Attend fully to the now.</li>
<li>Enjoy life with family and with my friends.</li>
<li>Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers.</li>
<li>Be there for my family.</li>
<li>Add value through work.</li>
<li>Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise.</li>
<li>Build or/or fix something.</li>
<li>Learn new things.</li>
<li>Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</li>
</ol>
<p>In summary, the shiny new 2024 life systems edition consists of the same old a) two guiding principles and the same old b) two no three rules, but now we&rsquo;ve added these c) 11 shiny new personal values all for the same low, low price.</p>
<p>There are no real surprises in this list, but hopefully keeping it close will help to bias daily action in the right directions.</p>
<p>P.S. Please don&rsquo;t forget the <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#learning-at-the-burning">PERMA</a> when thinking about your personal well-being.</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2024">Wishes for 2024</h2>
<p>Dear fellow human,</p>
<p>This is the end of this blog post.</p>
<p>Thank you for being here.</p>
<p>I wish you and your loved ones a year of learning, kindness, gratitude, health and happiness.</p>










<figure><a href="stilbaai-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_f4c4eedfe584fe5a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_8c04e2966d04c4f1.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_1a92a7bd1be2fa3d.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_2021f04e9c9f0447.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_8c04e2966d04c4f1.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2022 to 2023 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 16:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2023 everyone, and to the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis
I wish all of you all of the best for this shiny new year twenty-twenty-three!
(By the way, this, the first day of the year, is the earliest that the yearly transition post has ever appeared!)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2023 everyone, and to the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="20221220-cape-st-francis-walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_9aeb90d9d01a11e9.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_8678af152961e9a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_d62854548d79e21e.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_4e0ce1b965a24760.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_8678af152961e9a.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I wish all of you all of the best for this shiny new year twenty-twenty-three!</p>
<p>(By the way, this, the first day of the year, is the earliest that the
yearly transition post has ever appeared!)</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Over the past year, I published fifteen posts on this blog, 14 of which were
&ldquo;weekly&rdquo; head voices posts (#237 to #250), and one <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/">the 2022 transition post</a>.</p>
<p>In an ideal world where I get to divide up my time between family and friends,
blogging, running and Emacs, I might be able to get close to the mythical 52
WHVs per year.</p>
<p>However, for me 2022 was definitely The Year of a Whole Lot of Work.</p>
<p>You might remember <a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">WHV #239 Embarrassing finitude</a>, in which I observed that you
only get to choose a really small number (probably only two: family and
friends, and one additional project) of significant priorities that you can
effectively contribute to over any given stretch of time.</p>
<p>I mostly remember that I&rsquo;ve made peace with this limitation, and I am realising
that (good) Work might be a crucial and substantial component of a long and
good life.</p>
<h3 id="some-stats">Some stats</h3>
<p>Invoking the goaccess log analysis tool using the incantation below reports that
this site was visited by just over 126 thousand unique visitor IP numbers in
the year up to December 27.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#6639ba">export</span> <span style="color:#953800">DOMAIN</span><span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>cpbotha.net
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0550ae">(</span><span style="color:#cf222e">for</span> i in <span style="color:#0550ae">{</span>1..11<span style="color:#0550ae">}</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">do</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> <span style="color:#953800">$DOMAIN</span>.access.log.<span style="color:#953800">$i</span>.gz<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">done</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> <span style="color:#953800">$DOMAIN</span>.access.log<span style="color:#0550ae">)</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> xargs zcat -f -- <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format<span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The most popular posts also over 2022 were the very old <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">2013 usa my data has
left your building</a>, the still quite relevant <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">2016 migrating from gmail to
fastmail</a> and my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">2019 note-taking strategy post</a>.</p>
<p>From this it&rsquo;s clear that I really have to get around to completing that
started-month-ago-but-languishing 202x note-taking strategy update, as my
system has evolved quite substantially.</p>
<p>I did also publish five posts on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>, this site&rsquo;s nerdy sibling, which
in its turn attracted just over 147 thousand unique visitor IPs over the year.</p>
<p>The most popular posts from vxlabs were the following, in descending order:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/06/12/typescript-development-with-emacs-tree-sitter-and-lsp-in-2022/">TypeScript development with Emacs, tree-sitter and LSP in 2022</a> - with
tree-sitter having been merged with Emacs core in the meantime, this post
also needs a substantial update. Emacs is developing faster than ever!</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/12/06/wsl2-io-measurements/">Comparing WSL1 and WSL2 filesystem I/O performance on local and host files</a> &ndash;
still reasonably accurate, still relevant.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/11/21/using-kubernetes-for-development-containers/">Using Kubernetes for development containers</a> - I&rsquo;m surprised that this is
relatively popular. I thought that it would be super niche.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="selected-learnings-from-2022">Selected learnings from 2022</h3>
<p>I went through all of 2022&rsquo;s WHVs to make an <em>extremely critical</em> (haha)
selection of learnings that bear mention in this yearly overview.</p>
<p>Because I think all of them are worthy of a retrospection, they are
chronologically ordered.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237 Don&rsquo;t step over the thing</a> &ndash; <em>We’re constantly stepping over the thing that
we think we’re seeking in the act of seeking it.</em> &hellip; <em>You can’t actually
become happy. You can only be happy.</em>
<ul>
<li>Related: <a href="/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/#take-a-picture-with-your-mind">WHV #247 Take a picture with your mind</a> &ndash; Your narrating self, the
one that needs to take all of those photos, can also take you out of the
thing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">WHV #239 Embarrassing finitude</a> &ndash; I&rsquo;m going to summarise that post section
here with &ldquo;pick your battles&rdquo;, or for the more poetically inclined readers
&ldquo;choose your f*cks&rdquo;. Our time is extremely limited - it is best to make
extremely deliberate and economical choices about the things that we spend
our time and energy on at any point.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/">WHV #242 Multiplicity of me</a> &ndash; If you skip everything else, read this
one. It&rsquo;s like &ldquo;happiness for dummies, in 24 hours&rdquo;.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/#part-time--role--model">WHV #243 Part-time role model</a> &ndash; Some motivation to never stop trying to be the
best you, also when, inevitably, you&rsquo;ll only have occasional success.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">WHV #246 Call up your friends</a> &ndash; Do call up that friend you&rsquo;re thinking
up. Write thank-you notes. Send birthday messages. Make the connection!</li>
<li><a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#self-discipline">WHV #249 Self-discipline</a> &ndash; Take care of this personal engine and it will
take you places.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/#happiness-is-a-joke">WHV #250 Durable, blissful contentment</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="quo-vadis-2023">Quo vadis 2023</h3>
<p>Writing on this here blog, and specifically the WHVs, is important to me for
the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>They enable learning, through retro- and introspection.</li>
<li>Each successful post is an exercise in applied and externalised self-discipline.</li>
<li>I enjoy practising the dying art of writing.</li>
<li>They help to form a connection with other humans, both friends and strangers.</li>
</ul>
<p>The reason for this retro-retrospection here, is that I am evaluating the
(smouldering) results and implications of the tension between post regularity
on the one hand, and self-perceived post substance on the other, over the past
year.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve erred on the side of post substance, when regularity might have been the
better option.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not that I was able to control it that deftly; what we have here is merely
the result of trying to publish posts of a reasonable quality at a reasonable
cadence.</p>
<p>My current feeling is that I would like to increase regularity, in spite of
past performance.</p>
<p>To make this happen, I have to learn to be satisfied with somewhat less, and
more importantly, I have to come up with improvements to my blogging workflow
that enable a more predictable flow of material.</p>
<p>A new year won&rsquo;t be a true new year without overly ambitious resolutions, now
will it?</p>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>This year, I averaged 20km of running per week for a total of 1044km (118 runs,
just under 99 hours) over the whole year.</p>
<p>Last year I did 25km per week, which is what I would have liked for this year
as well, but this is fine. <em>Any</em> kilometres are better than no kilometres!</p>










<figure>
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_51b4310156cb6775.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_9b2d56329fea834b.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_44ff53ded7296414.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_b6f0d925e5348190.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_9b2d56329fea834b.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Random drop-outs in graph below. At least finished strong in last week of year."/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Random drop-outs in graph below. At least finished strong in last week of year.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I did three quick spot checks in my daily journals to see if I could determine
any specific reasons for the low / no-exercise weeks, but nothing jumped out.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to have to blame work for this one too.</p>
<p>Anyways, what I <em>can</em> say, without any hesitation, is that running made a massive
positive contribution to my physical and mental well-being this year.</p>
<p>The effects can generally be immediately felt (that beautiful bit when it feels
like all one&rsquo;s limbs are finally working together, rhythmically even, is
exhilarating), and usually signal another start of a cascade of positive
physiological and life-style factors.</p>
<p>Running resolutions for 2023: 0) Much enjoy. 1) Don&rsquo;t get injured. 2) Try <em>again</em> for the 25km/w average.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>I really enjoyed the following books:</p>
<h3 id="fiction">Fiction</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/54906250-project-hail-mary">Project Hail Mary by Andy Weir</a> - feel good edge of seat stranded in space but
have to save the earth human-alien-buddy movie -book. Great for engineers who
know how to suspend disbelief.
<ul>
<li>I could not remember that I had ever bought this book, but enjoyed the
living daylights out of it. Only later discovered that it was GOU #1 (who
shares my Kindle account)! 🥰 we enjoyed the same book!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57357418-termination-shock">Termination Shock by Neal Stephenson</a> - this is such a disciplined, detailed,
diligent piece of science fiction by someone who clearly has <em>practised</em> this
art and honed their craft to perfection. I enjoyed the story (it does require
some reader stamina) and appreciated the massive skills of the artist.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/#permutation-city">Permutation City by Greg Egan</a> - click on the link to the left to go to my
mini-review in WHV #240.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="non-fiction">Non-fiction</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/#projections">Projections: A Story of Human Emotions by Karl Deisseroth</a> - click on the link
to the left to go to my mini-review in WHV #244.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59516276-the-unseen-body">The Unseen
Body: A Doctor&rsquo;s Journey Through the Hidden Wonders of Human Anatomy by
Jonathan Reisman</a> - Join the doctor on a fascinating journey through each
and every organ in the human body, robustly spiced by his stories of travels
to some of the most remote corners of the globe, and of his experience
various medical emergencies.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="resolutions">Resolutions</h3>
<p>Somewhere in the second half of 2022, I somehow lost my <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#reading">reading-before-sleep
habit</a>.</p>
<p>I plan to reinstate this habit, and to install the new habit of reading more
books on my phone (vs being limited to my Kindle, which is not always with me).</p>
<p>Armed with these two life-hacks, I hope to finish reading 20 books in 2023.</p>
<p>Please send me your recommendations in the comments below!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human">Systems and tools for running this human</h2>
<p>As per tradition, I quote from previous transition posts my explanation of &ldquo;The
System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Similar to <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">last year</a>, Emacs, Orgmode and Org-roam are still going very strong,
and constitute the lion&rsquo;s share of my personal knowledge management system.</p>
<p>In fact, with the imminent Emacs 29 release, a recent build of which I&rsquo;m typing
this draft into (English is hard folks&hellip;), Emacs has only become <em>more</em>
compelling.</p>
<p>Amongst <a href="https://blog.phundrak.com/emacs-29-what-can-we-expect">many other improvements</a>, tree-sitter, eglot and use-package are now all
part of core.</p>
<h3 id="byeeeeee-dropbox">Byeeeeee Dropbox!</h3>
<p>However&hellip;</p>
<p>The time has finally come for me to drop (again) Dropbox.</p>
<p>Although I have been a paying customer for many years (see <a href="/2010/02/28/weekly-head-voices-15-auto-tune-my-cloud/">WHV #15</a> from
February of 2010 for a report close to the start of our commercial
relationship), in the end it was their intransigence and inscrutability around
the Dropbox Paper 2020 migration that broke the camel&rsquo;s back.</p>
<p>They have been promising since before 2020 that they would migrate all existing
users to the new 2020 edition of Dropbox Paper.</p>
<p>However, now all you can find about this are frustrated forum posts from
long-time customers. My direct support request to be migrated was promptly
answered, and then closed with the following message:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As much as I would like to help, currently, the latest version of Paper release
is available to new users only.</p>
<p>Our team is currently in the process of working on this new feature in order to
build the best Paper experience for all our users.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I still really love that tool (winner of the WHV Award for the Most
Unexpectedly Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021!), but the interaction above
only served as a reminder of the pitfalls of a relationship like this.</p>
<p>During the writing of my yet-to-appear 202x note-taking approach blog post, it
bugged me that I had to come up with a good explanation for why I allowed
Dropbox Paper to break my rule of everything-needs-to-be-a-file-I-could-sync.</p>
<p>Although my yearly Dropbox Paper subscription is only up for renewal in June of
&lsquo;23, I decided to bite the bullet and <a href="/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/#hell-freezes-over--again">migrate everything out to an extremely
frightening mix of OneDrive, syncthing and unison</a>.</p>
<p>As I write this, it&rsquo;s been just over two months with nary a hiccup.</p>
<p>In June, I&rsquo;ll let that Dropbox subscription lapse.</p>
<p>Dropbox Paper, RIP.</p>
<p>(With <a href="https://1writerapp.com/">1writer</a> and also <a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> on the iPhone, and <a href="https://syncthing.net/">syncthing</a> on my main desktop
at home, plus Apple Notes for the truly ephemeral stuff, I have a pretty
capable mobile response to Paper.)</p>
<h3 id="resolutions">Resolutions</h3>
<ol>
<li>I would really like to publish a blog post titled <em>Note-taking approach
2023</em>. Ideally, it should be full of information about my current PKM system.</li>
<li>Write more notes, including both journals and <a href="/tags/zettelkasten/">Zettelkasten-style</a> notes.</li>
<li>Stretch goal: Maybe get another useful patch into Emacs.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>2022 was my first year back in employment, after <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">eight years of freelancing</a>.</p>
<p>In this year, I have only become more deeply involved and invested in the
current <a href="https://stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> adventure.</p>
<p>As I mentioned previously, I have the privilege of working closely together
with extremely capable folks, in a high-trust setting.</p>
<p>Many of my colleagues are smarter than I am in their respective fields. Due to
that, and the fact that we are both growing and innovating, I am constantly
learning.</p>
<p>My personal responsibilities span the spectrum from programming, through
mentor- and leadership to management and org-level technical decisions. On the
other dimension, I am exposed to everything from software plumbing to data
science, engineering and visualization. (This is what&rsquo;s known as a
PiM-situation. PiM = pig in mud)</p>
<p>The work is hard, but it&rsquo;s varied, it&rsquo;s challenging, it&rsquo;s together with a group
of humans I like, and it feels meaningful.</p>
<p>I have written all these words to try and explain that although it&rsquo;s clear from
this post that Work(tm) took up significantly more time and space this year, it
has contributed substantially to my well-being.</p>
<p>Freelancing was less stressful &ndash; I could focus on the engineering tasks at
hand and usually deliver. Now I have more responsibility, which brings
substantially more stress but also more satisfaction.</p>
<p>Furthermore, in terms of maintaining the plasticity of my neural network,
something I do have to pay more and more attention to thanks to the advancing
years, the variation and challenges of my current work setting are great.</p>
<p>That being said, I definitely have to get better at controlling stress.</p>
<h2 id="things-i-would-like-to-work-on-in-2023">Things I would like to work on in 2023</h2>
<p>In addition to the blogging, running, reading and systems resolutions mentioned
above, I would like to work on the following bigger themes in 2023:</p>
<ol>
<li>Work(tm).</li>
<li>Self-discipline, <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#self-discipline">as featured in WHV #249</a>. I will implement this by writing
really stern messages to me in my diary.</li>
<li>Creating, restoring and maintaining good habits that <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a>: Reading,
writing, running, mindfulness practice.</li>
</ol>
<p>&hellip; and then finally, my central theme for 2023 will be:</p>
<h3 id="4-dot-expansiveness">4. Expansiveness</h3>
<p>Sometimes, most probably when you&rsquo;re out in nature, you experience your senses
really opening up.</p>
<p>It is as if the usually clearly defined borders between you and your
surroundings start to fade away.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve talked about this phenomenon before, in <a href="/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/#the-strange-continuum-of-consciousness">WHV #217&rsquo;s The Strange Continuum
of Consciousness</a> and in other places.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a great feeling, and it usually happens when you are fully present in that
moment.</p>
<p>For a while, you can get pleasantly lost in the infinite and fractal detail in
the moment and its participants.</p>
<p>For a while, you can truly appreciate the beauty of your surroundings, of the food
and drink you might be enjoying, and of the humans in your company.</p>
<p>In 2023, let us be expansive!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2021 to 2022 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.
I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to 2014 (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and 2015 (no real excuse).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition
post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_43b7cf87c31b21c0.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_fc6e5e937f90c6a9.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_12a18d122cde4000.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_5b0c7558e9575.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_fc6e5e937f90c6a9.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to
<a href="/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/">2014</a> (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and <a href="/2015/01/21/weekly-head-voices-88-just-be-yourself-they-said/">2015</a> (no real
excuse).</p>
<p><em>Much later, on Sunday January 23:</em> It could very well still win the Most
Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Emacs and <code>M-x count-words</code> (on a temporary buffer copied over from <a href="/archive/#2021">the 2021
blog post archive</a>) tells me that I published 28 posts on this blog, and 8
technical posts over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>Just like with the running below, but for different reasons, I lost a lot of
steam during the last few months of the year.</p>
<p>In a truly surprise twist, in 2022 I will again attempt to write regularly, and
to write more, and to keep it up until the end.</p>
<h3 id="stats-addendum">Stats addendum</h3>
<p>Applying the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess log analyzer</a> to this blog&rsquo;s log files with the following
invocation:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0550ae">(</span><span style="color:#cf222e">for</span> i in <span style="color:#0550ae">{</span>2..13..1<span style="color:#0550ae">}</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">do</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> cpbotha.net.access.log.<span style="color:#953800">$i</span>.gz<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">done</span><span style="color:#0550ae">)</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> xargs zcat -f -- <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format<span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; tells me that in 2021 cpbotha.net welcomed over 115000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>The same tool reports that <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a> clocked in at just under 165000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>Even if the real number of actual human visits is a quarter of what the tool is
reporting, I am ecstatic!</p>
<p>The three most popular cpbotha.net posts based on hits during 2021 were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">Dear USA, my data has left your building</a></li>
<li><a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">Note-taking strategy 2019</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>Thanks to Strava&rsquo;s handy training calendar shown below, we can see that I spent
125 hours last year (mostly, about 4 hours was spent on hiking just over 20km)
running a bit over 1300km.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_d8797d3ae69f2074.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_bcb23928a764c751.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_71b26fe22f2669f7.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_fd426be487962b7e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_bcb23928a764c751.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can also see quite clearly that I lost steam in November and especially in
December.</p>
<p>This was initially due to work getting quite busy, and then later in December a
bout with Omicron (highly probably) and also less than run-friendly weather in
St. Francis.</p>
<p>I am always happy when I manage to average 100km or more per month, and I&rsquo;ll
probably try to do that again in 2022.</p>
<h3 id="possibly-tmi-read-on-at-your-own-risk">Possibly TMI, read on at your own risk</h3>
<p>Those of you who know me, will also know about my giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunion">bunion</a>, or hallux
valgus as it prefers to be called.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated." width="240px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyways, Mr Valgus is unfortunately playing an increasingly frequent role in my
attempts at running, often starting to complain at N kilometres where N is
fortunately still higher than most of my attempts, but still affecting a
worrying number of them.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to push on, until Mr Valgus overstays its welcome, at which point
it will be time to explore invasive corrective procedures.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Probably my most redeeming habit of them all, is reading books every night in
bed until I fall asleep.</p>
<p>Even if the day has been less than satisfactory, ending it with an entirely
deliberate and focused reading session tends to make up for quite a lot.</p>
<p>Although I was planning to do more book summaries in 2021, I managed to
complete only one. At least it was a good one, namely <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Seven
and a Half Lessons About the Brain&rdquo; by Lisa Feldman Barrett</a>, which I can
strongly recommend if you have not checked it out yet.</p>
<p>Thanks to strong contenders like the one above, the competition was fierce, but
in the end the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em> could go to nothing other
than Oliver Burkeman&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08FGV64B1/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</em></a>.</p>
<p>Burkeman, he of the <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">importance of being able to put <em>down</em> your work</a> and of <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">more
appearances on this blog</a>, has created a beautifully written ode to our terribly
limited lifespans (4000 weeks if you&rsquo;re lucky, you can almost hear them ticking
away&hellip;), and to our terribly limited capacity to make the most of the time
that we do get, and to really just giving up the fight to <em>get everything done</em>,
because we will never ever win the battle against the law of perpetually
filling inboxes of various kinds, and because it&rsquo;s so much better to simply
<em>disconnect</em> from the firehose (which we can&rsquo;t get rid of completely) in order to
spend time on no-excuses leisure, and especially on our loved ones.</p>
<p>My favourite fiction book by far was <em>The Anomaly</em> by Hervé le Tellier, as
translated by Adriana Hunter.</p>
<p>After having just grudgingly finished Elizabeth Bear&rsquo;s Ancestral Night (first
novel in the White Space series; some interesting ideas, but just too pulpy,
clumsy and exposition-rich for my taste, in spite of space opera being a guilty
pleasure&hellip;), the light literariness and French cynicism of The Anomaly was a
<em>delightful</em> and refreshing breeze that I was unable to put down until it was
done.</p>
<p>In 2022, I&rsquo;m planning to read more than in 2021, and publish more of those
summaries.</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#mindfulness">daily meditation streak that started in 2020</a> continued for most of 2021,
until the end-of-year school vacation started. I am not yet sure how I&rsquo;ll be
able to fit this into my new 2022 work-routine.</p>
<h2 id="worst-habit-of-2021">Worst habit of 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV Award for Worst Habit of 2021 By Far goes, without a doubt, to my old
friend TwiFRaF-Yo, although this time around the main culprits were Twitter,
Reddit and YouTube.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know exactly when I fell out of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">the previous social media fast</a>, but I
fell out with a vengeance.</p>
<p>Although I subscribe almost entirely to technical communities on reddit (Emacs,
Orgmode, Org-roam, keyboards, etc.), there are enough of them to keep a person
busy.</p>
<p>If you add to that my twitter feed, where I&rsquo;ve also taken care to remove the
noise, subscribing largerly to high-signal science-, technology- , and
engineering-related feeds, there&rsquo;s a great deal of valuable-seeming information
that one feels compelled to get through every day&hellip;</p>
<p>(It feels like I&rsquo;ve told this story before&hellip;)</p>
<p>Anyways, every time I manage to disconnect (it&rsquo;s been a few weeks now, I think
Monday January 3 was the official start date of the current fast), only then am
I able to recognise (where by &ldquo;recognise&rdquo;, I mean that friends say this to me,
and this is when I&rsquo;m able to admit that they&rsquo;re right) that the net value for
me is highly probably negative.</p>
<p>While there is certainly valuable information that enters via those streams, it
costs so much attention and emotional energy that it&rsquo;s not really worth it.</p>
<p>So.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m back on the no-social-media cart until next time.</p>
<p>Just like the previous time, I&rsquo;m limiting myself to the brilliant Inoreader RSS
subscription service (which I pay for) to keep up to date with 99% long-form
blogs, and two Twitter accounts that are worth too much to me to disconnect
from (<a href="https://twitter.com/erictopol">Eric Topol</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/alper">Alper Çuğun-Gscheidel</a>).</p>
<p>Although I sometimes think this makes me slower, because I don&rsquo;t have all of
the current happenings at my fingertips all the time, I&rsquo;m hoping this gives me
more space and time for reading, thinking and writing.</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">Systems and tools for running this human (PKM baby)</h2>
<p>In the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">2018 to 2019 transition post</a> I mentioned the &ldquo;The System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This time, for this section, I would like to limit it to tools for knowledge
management and task management (this is not my favourite term, but I&rsquo;m erring
on the side of familiarity here) .</p>
<p>All of Emacs and Orgmode and Org-roam is still going strong, although I waver
quite a bit sometimes when I see some of the shiny new things, like <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>,
which I would probably be using if it wasn&rsquo;t for Emacs.</p>
<p>However, when I sometimes dive into my notes, I can see the difference it makes
when you stick to a single tool for longer than a few years. The amount of
knowledge keeps on growing, and I am slowly getting better at linking it all
together and&hellip;  sometimes even using it.</p>
<p>The picture below shows the graph created, by the <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> package, of a
sub-section of my notes network:</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_d1209fe41888514f.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_31ce23bcfd961e9f.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_950ec103a8bb11b5.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_df618e90e2d265e3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_31ce23bcfd961e9f.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Before I got side-tracked by the pretty picture, I was planning to dedicate
this section to a new WHV award, namely the Award for the Most Unexpectedly
Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021.</p>
<p>This year the award goes to&hellip; <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper/guide">Dropbox Paper</a>!</p>
<p>Back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">WHV #233</a> I listed many of the reasons why. In the few months since then
it has become only more useful to me as the go-to mobile tool for checklists
(especially useful when we go on trips), lists of books, movies and music
recommended by people in person, and so on.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualifier features, such as its markdown DNA and its
usability on mobile for idea capturing, the fact that Paper documents show up
in Dropbox searches, which is how I usually search when I <span class="underline">really</span> need to find a
specific file (versus ripgrep searches in Orgmode), is the deal maker.</p>
<p>(My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">strange scheme for continuously converting all org files to docx</a> for
searching and reading on the iPhone is also still going strong.)</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I had a piece written here with more details about what exactly was happening
at work, but I decided to nuke that and instead keep it more personal by
mentioning that thanks to great big dollops of serendipity and people, I find
myself, with a number of levers at my disposal, right in the middle of an
organization which, after a few months of reconfiguration and preparation, has
embarked on a genuinely exciting, and importantly more unified, course.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not mention the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">discomfort and stress</a> I was
experiencing at the start of the current personal phase, most probably due to
trying to adapt quickly to my new circumstances and responsibilities.</p>
<p>In the time since then, my stress levels have returned to more acceptable
levels, but expectations remain high.</p>
<h2 id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<p>One of the most positive changes I made in the past year, was to put more
effort into making regular and active (virtual) contact with friends whom I
don&rsquo;t see in person regularly enough.</p>
<p>THANKS INTERNET YOU DA BEST.</p>
<p>This year, I want to try harder to do more of that.</p>
<p>More generally, I made a note (yes, again, one has to keep doing this until the
end) to celebrate any of my peeps and our relationships whenever there&rsquo;s a
chance.</p>
<p>Secret message for my innner INNER circle: You are my energy and my joy, I am
here to be yours.</p>
<p>Whatever else happens, these precious relationships are all we have.</p>
<h2 id="even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">Even more plans for 2022: Continue trying</h2>
<p>First off, I would really like to get this blog post here done and
published. (it wants to be too much, or rather I want it to be too much, and so
we sit here staring at each other instead of just getting on with it so I can
try again to write a good post for once)</p>
<p>Second, EAZ is back on, since Monday January 10. EAZ means no alcohol until at
least February 10. As has been the case previously, my sleep quality is
subjectively better, and it seems like my energy levels are more consistent
throughout the week.</p>
<p>I just looked back at last year&rsquo;s transition post, and especially at the <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">final
sections, including the neatly documented Life Systems 2021</a>. That guy
(<a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">apparently we share only about 2% of our atoms</a>) really seemed to have his
stuff together, on paper at the very least.</p>
<p>As I write this (22:38 on Saturday, January 22), I have just realised that <em>this</em>
&ldquo;I&rdquo; definitely needs to spend some more time thinking about &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo; (The WHV
approach to life, the universe and everything, the one with the pillars (love
and science, that&rsquo;s the easy and reliable bit) and the rules) and specifically
if and how to revise the daily life direction clusters.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll have it on your desk by Monday.</p>
<p>Until then, the one thing I&rsquo;m sure about, is that I wish you and your loved
ones the best 2022 possible.</p>










<figure><a href="stormsriver-mouth.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_9489d85cd70e5f2e.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_ebadf81992f9fe5e.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_f4dbd9f895343922.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_cfb4aaba0c7a1dbd.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_ebadf81992f9fe5e.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2020 to 2021 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 15:19:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to the year 2021 friends.
Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.
You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to the &amp;ldquo;transition&amp;rdquo; tag page.
If you don&amp;rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through last year&amp;rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition.
This transition tradition started at the end of 2009, which coincidentally is also the year that the Weekly Head Voices was born.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2021 friends.</p>
<p>Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.</p>
<p>You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to <a href="/tags/transition/">the &ldquo;transition&rdquo;
tag page</a>.</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/">last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition</a>.</p>
<p>This transition tradition <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">started at the end of 2009</a>, which coincidentally is
also the year that <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">the Weekly Head Voices was born</a>.</p>
<p>The goal of the transition post is to do a really spotty year review, and then
to gaze unsuccessfully into the future.</p>










<figure><a href="leopards_kloof.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_a5029f88e36e0460.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_335ac2d3414debe5.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_2a0689e34a9c502a.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_dd9b132d68990a15.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_335ac2d3414debe5.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>More seriously, the ever-evolving network of posts on this website (there are
now literally hundreds of them), along with the ever-evolving but also fading
network of neurons in my head (probably at least a few hundred of them too!),
benefit from an occasional higher-level connecting of some of the dots.</p>
<p>In the introduction of the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/">2018 to 2019 transition post</a>, I ramble on slightly
more about the multiscalar nature of my subjective experience, and how that is
reflected in my notes database, of which this blog is one aspect.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s get on with it!</p>
<h2 id="noteworthy-snippets-through-the-lens-of-this-blog">Noteworthy snippets through the lens of this blog</h2>
<h3 id="covid-19">COVID-19</h3>
<p>One of the biggest issues for most people last year and still at this moment is
COVID-19.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested, you could take a look at the Weekly Head Voices posts
that had something to say about <a href="/tags/covid19/">COVID-19</a>, but you don&rsquo;t really have to.</p>
<p>Fortunately, world-wide vaccination has commenced. However, we have to keep our
fingers crossed that:</p>
<ol>
<li>The world succeeds in getting the vaccine to a sufficient number of humans
on time.</li>
<li>A vaccine-resistant strain does not happen. It could, because math, and
because evolution (selection pressure due to the vaccine, doh),</li>
</ol>
<p>Whether the above outcomes realise or not, I do also hope that we retain as
many as possible of the lessons we have been learning thanks to the pandemic.</p>
<ul>
<li>Mask-wearing and generally improved hygeine with the major goal of protecting
our fellow humans are great habits.</li>
<li>We have made great strides towards the future of work, where many workers (by
far not all, but it&rsquo;s a good meaningful chunk) are able to commute less,
pollute less, better organize the interaction of their work and family lives
and, importantly, their work is measured by its value and not by the number
of hours it takes place in.</li>
<li>We humans are in this (today pandemic, tomorrow something else!) together.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="lazar-focus-the-side-project-that-got-released">Lazar Focus: The side-project that got released</h3>
<p>Around these parts we have a rich tradition of starting but then never
finishing side-projects, and the concomitant giant side-project graveyard to
show for it.</p>
<p>This year, I did manage to ship the little distraction blocker tool I wrote,
called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a>. The <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">first WHV mentioning was #196</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the fact that this little tool has ended up helping me to rescue
many aspirant unproductive days, it has sold more than 10 copies, which was my
life goal for this project.</p>
<h3 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion effect</h3>
<p>From Adam Grant&rsquo;s book Give and Take, I learned about the <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#the-pygmalion-effect">Pygmalion effect</a>,
where a teacher&rsquo;s <em>belief</em> in the intrinsic capabilities of a student, whether
those were justified or not at the time, had a significant and enduring
positive, one could say potentially life-changing, effect on that student&rsquo;s
performance.</p>
<p>Besides the bit about the Pygmalion effect, <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/">that post (WHV #201)</a> contains a
micro-summary of the Shape Up book by Basecamp, which is also worth a look.</p>
<h3 id="take-the-day-off-to-go-run-in-the-mountain">Take the day off to go run in the mountain</h3>
<p>During the year, for example in <a href="/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/#life-progress-update">WHV #203</a> when I took my birthday off to go
running in the mountains, I learned that taking days off on the birthdays of you
and your loved ones to go do stuff outdoors is a Great Idea(tm).</p>
<p>(I also learned that sometimes you don&rsquo;t even need an excuse. Just take the day
off and go run in the mountains.)</p>
<h3 id="use-it-or-lose-it">Use it or lose it</h3>
<p>The human system is amazingly adaptable.</p>
<p>The price that we pay for that flexibility is that each and every one of our
learned capabilities requires continuous practice in order to be maintained.</p>
<p>In short humans, <a href="/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/#use-it-or-lose-it">use it, or lose it</a>.</p>
<h3 id="fool-your-mind">Fool your mind</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m making peace with the fact that I apparently need to apply, continuously,
various silly tricks to keep <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">the slippery eel that is my mind</a> on the
straight-and-narrow.</p>
<p>As a shining example, <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">the refocus reminder</a>, a bell that reminds you at hourly
intervals to focus, indeed sounds a bit silly but adds a great deal of value.</p>
<p>My favourite example from last year however is creating yet more (but smaller!)
habits to kickstart my bigger habits, in this case a <a href="/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/#wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">3-item morning checklist
to kickstart the more daunting full day checklist</a>.</p>
<p>The morning bootstrap checklist is, at the risk of sounding like a startup-bro:</p>
<ol>
<li>meditation,</li>
<li>deep reading and</li>
<li>planning.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="blogging-stats">Blogging stats</h2>
<p>Since February 17 of 2020 when I <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">migrated everything to a small Hetzner VPS</a>,
the server log files tell me that cpbotha.net saw just over 157000 unique
visitors, which is 492 per day on average.</p>
<p>I wrote 30 posts on cpbotha.net during 2020, of which 25 were editions of the
Weekly Head Voices.</p>
<p>Thanks to the shiny new archive page I put together today, you can now finally
<a href="/archive/#2020">see all of 2020&rsquo;s posts in one place</a>, or of any other year, should you be more
into the older stuff.</p>
<p>In addition to the cpbotha.net posts, I also published 11 posts over on
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the regular WHV posts, I&rsquo;m happy to have published what will
hopefully be only the first in a whole collection of book notes posts, namely
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Creativity, Inc.&rdquo; by Ed Catmull with Amy Wallace</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s chunky at just over 7000 words, but it will give you a pretty good idea of
the contents of the much more substantial book it is based on!</p>
<h3 id="details-for-nerds">Details for nerds</h3>
<p>This is the invocation I used to generate reports from the nginx log files
using the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess</a> tool:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>zcat -f -- /var/log/nginx/cpbotha.net.access.log.*.gz <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span><span style="color:#0a3069">\
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format<span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>In 2020 I seem to have run just 100 metres shy of 1100km. (Typical&hellip;)</p>
<p>More would have been good, but I&rsquo;m happy with this.</p>
<p>Exercise did take a bit of a hit due to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/#exercise">lockdown</a>, although I could definitely
have squeezed more in.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the aggregated amount of enjoyment and satisfaction
was astronomical.</p>
<p>A personal highlight was <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#random-notes-on-the-kogelberg-trail-adventure">running the 24km(ish) Kogelberg trail with a tiny
crew that included two of my Dutch family members</a>.</p>
<p>(These blog retrospectives are strange, because they are also life
retrospectives, but they shouldn&rsquo;t get too personal. I would be remiss however
if I did not mention that having these specific Dutch peeps here in 2020 was
magical. I am going to miss them terribly.)</p>
<p>Also thanks to said peeps, I did more trail running this year than ever before.</p>
<p>It turns out that I am surrounded by beautiful trails. WHO KNEW?!</p>
<p>The other highlight I want to mention was <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations">GOU#1</a> running her first race, the
distributed <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#running-and-reading">CTM 10km in Jonkershoek</a>. Here&rsquo;s to many more GOU kilometres!</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>Thanks to some strict words by friend PK during the year, I got solidly back on
the daily meditation train, which ended up being the start of a streak of
(workday) morning meditation longer than anything I&rsquo;ve been able to maintain up
to now.</p>
<p>(The bootstrap checklist in <a href="#fool-your-mind">Fool Your Mind</a> above might also have contributed to
this.)</p>
<p>The Waking Up course by Sam Harris has been amazing for more than two years
now, and even more so when trying to build and keep up a daily meditation
habit.</p>
<p>What I especially like about Waking Up is its focus on the explicit practice of
the experience of consciousness and the role (or non-role) of the self within
that. (for a tiny example, see <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#find-a-place-in-the-universe-that-is-your-consciousness">WHV #207</a>)</p>
<p>Practising this daily has been an experience that I can only recommend in the
strongest terms.</p>
<p>(Please let me know if you&rsquo;d like to try a month for free. As a subscriber, I
get to give these out to as many peeps as I want to.)</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV approach to life, the universe and everything (also known as &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo;,
but you have to over-emphasize the terribly soft &ldquo;W&rdquo;) has been evolving for a
few years now, but it was most recently summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.</p>
<p>At the basis of this approach we find the two formidable pillars of</p>
<ol>
<li><em>love</em> and</li>
<li><em>science</em>,</li>
</ol>
<p>and in that order. On top of these pillars rest <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">The WHV&rsquo;s Two no Three Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</a>.</p>
<p>The two no three rules are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be useful.</li>
<li>Be likable.</li>
<li>Evolve.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the previous transition post, I talked about <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">six personal daily life
directions</a>, the continuous reformulation of which I had integrated into my
morning routine.</p>
<p>It was a good start, but the life directions were a bit too specific, and six
separate things is too many to keep at the core of your thoughts.</p>
<p>Motivated by this, and also by <a href="https://lexfridman.com/chris-lattner-2/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Chris Lattner</a>
wherein Lattner, an amazing engineer, but more importantly such a kind human
being, underlined the importance to him of always continuing to grow and learn,
I mashed together everything I had to come up with two clusters of daily life
directions:</p>
<ol>
<li>Grow, learn, build, enjoy. (motion)</li>
<li>Be useful. Be likeable. Be kind. (self-checks)</li>
</ol>
<p>In the stupid-dimensional universe that is my mind, I know that these
directions are obviously in the spirit of WALUE, but I can&rsquo;t yet articulate
clearly how they relate to the pillars and the rules of WALUE.</p>
<p>Maybe they&rsquo;re just a neat little pile on top, or a little bit to the side,
leaning against the WALUE building?</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, they have been part of my daily checklist for a few
months now, and they seem to work in the sense of being practical, checkable
and tiny enough to keep in mind always.</p>
<h2 id="plans--for-tomorrow-at-least">Plans (for tomorrow, at least)</h2>
<p>This bit is quite scary.</p>
<p>I hardly know what&rsquo;s going to happen tomorrow, and here I wanted to talk about
plans for the whole year!</p>
<p>So, to be clear, what I&rsquo;ve listed below is limited to the concrete items that I
can see before me right now.</p>
<h3 id="the-absolute-basics">The absolute basics</h3>
<ul>
<li>Attempt to apply <a href="#life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</a> all of the time.</li>
<li>Practise mindfulness every day.</li>
<li>If I&rsquo;m wondering whether I should go run, the answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="comms-upgrade">Comms upgrade</h3>
<p>I would like to level up my communication game.</p>
<p>Work from home is here to stay, and that&rsquo;s a good thing, but it has muffled my
face-to-face communication modality, something that has had a profound impact
on my full communication suite.</p>
<p>Most of the clever folks now agree that <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">the correct answer is asynchronous
communication</a>. Future-facing companies like Basecamp and <a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/">Doist have been
preaching this long before COVID-19</a>.</p>
<p>To be more specific, I need to figure out first how to do asynchronous
communication in my daily work, and then to become really good at it.</p>
<h3 id="write-more-about-good-books">Write more about good books</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to publish more focused book notes like the recently appeared
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Creativity, Inc. post</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s great reading these books, but I&rsquo;ve noticed that if I&rsquo;m planning to
publish book notes, I read more intently, I take better notes, and the extra
processing stage before starting to put together a blog post really helps me to
integrate the knowledge contained in the book.</p>
<p>Every good book one is able to integrate is in fact a cheap, but possibly
game-changing firmware upgrade&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2021-for-you">Wishes for 2021, for you</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this. I am grateful that you&rsquo;re here.</p>
<p>I wish you and everyone you hold dear the best 2021 possible.</p>
<p>Quite concretely, we can all help to make this happen by being as kind as we
possibly can to as many fellow humans as we possibly can.</p>
<p>In the words of a fellow traveller: SMÉAGOL OUT!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2019 to 2020 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 11:03:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2020 folks!
In retrospect, I really should have written this post during the vacation, when it is substantially easier to wax all optimistic about the year to come.
As it stands, we&amp;rsquo;re slightly more than a week of work into the new year, and most of that vacation naiveté has been brought summarily crashing down to earth as part of a sort of planetary body check.
Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s better this way after all. Let&amp;rsquo;s keep it real.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2020 folks!</p>
<p>In retrospect, I really should have written this post during the vacation, when
it is substantially easier to wax all optimistic about the year to come.</p>
<p>As it stands, we&rsquo;re slightly more than a week of work into the new year, and
most of that vacation naiveté has been brought summarily crashing down to earth
as part of a sort of planetary body check.</p>
<p>Perhaps it&rsquo;s better this way after all. Let&rsquo;s keep it real.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_7ae0711e1ec24e44.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_9fec7f25ff8c1eda.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_b51b8f872c372a04.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_c9178771c548d66e.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_9fec7f25ff8c1eda.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
A sample of the view as I was walking to the main beach in Betty's Bay,
listening to a super entertaining <a
href="https://www.wnycstudios.org/podcasts/radiolab/articles/man-against-horse">radiolab
podcast about a recent 50 mile race between humans and horses</a>. (Hint: A human won!)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>During the vacation, I did manage to find all (most?) of <a href="/tags/transition/">the previous (year)
transition posts</a> all the way back to 2010 and retro-tag
them, for your and my reading pleasure, but mostly because I like to keep
things orderly around here.</p>
<p>The rest of this post is a very brief and spotty review of 2019, followed by my
far-more-grounded-than-usual (see above) hopes and dreams for 2020.</p>
<h2 id="learnings-and-events-that-i-found-important-through-the-lens-of-this-blog">Learnings and events that I found important, through the lens of this blog.</h2>
<p>I now find <a href="/tags/sleep/">sleep</a> <em>at least</em> as important as healthy eating (and
<a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">not
eating</a>)
and exercise for human wellness. I started writing about sleep in the <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 to
2018 transition post</a> after
reading about Matthew Walker for the first time in a Guardian interview.</p>
<p>In 2019 I got around to reading his book as well, and I now I&rsquo;m even more
scared of losing sleep over anything.</p>
<p>(For a giggle, contrast this with <a href="/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/#earlyish-morning-sessions">my early morning work sessions in WHV
#161</a>. On
second thought, in Summer time one could probably get this working again.)</p>
<p>Our home is <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">now solar
powered</a>. In fact,
this post is for the largest part made using power directly from the sun!</p>
<p><a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">Stone Three
Healthcare</a>,
a new med-tech company I am officially part of, was officially launched after
a great incubation period.</p>
<p>Exciting times lie ahead.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/#life-is-but-a-dream">Reality is just a different type of
dreaming</a>,
and other implications of brain-based reality simulation.</p>
<p>We are still feeling <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/#loss">the loss of a clan mother</a>.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">ABC stands for Always Be
Compounding</a>.</p>
<p>Maybe <em>that</em> will be my main theme for 2020.</p>
<h2 id="blogging-stats">Blogging Stats.</h2>
<p>In 2019 I published 35 posts on this blog, slightly down from 2019&rsquo;s 36 posts.</p>
<p>(I also published 12 more nerdy posts over on vxlabs, slightly up from 2019&rsquo;s 11 posts.)</p>
<p>The static log analyzer tool I installed in March of 2019 (awstats, if you have
to know) reports 37403 unique visitors reading just under 160000 pages between
them.</p>
<p>It could be that all of that is due to my small group of friends voraciously
re-reading everything on here, each time with a new dynamically assigned IP
address.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be (voracious) readers, thank you for reading the things
I write!</p>
<h2 id="technical-changes-to-the-site-with-implications-for-the-writing-process">Technical changes to the site, with implications for the writing process.</h2>
<p>In March of this year, I <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">ported this whole site from wordpress to the Hugo
static site generator</a>.</p>
<p>Although this has resulted in a significantly faster and more secure site, the
real benefits only dawned on me a few weeks in.</p>
<p>With Hugo, my main input modality is the humble text editor, where I write the
<a href="https://commonmark.org/help/">markdown</a>, that is semi-structured plaintext
with a few tricks, of each post before converting it to its final published
form.</p>
<p>In contrast to the WYSIWYG of Wordpress and especially of its new-fangled
Gutenberg visual editor, the latter which was probably the biggest reason for
me to make the jump, I see only text and the markdown heading structure when I
write posts, with very few other distractions.</p>
<p>This has magically resulted in me applying significantly more focus and
discipline to how I write these posts, which has further resulted in an
unexpected increase in writing satisfaction.</p>
<p>(I am carefully optimistic that it might even contribute ever so slightly to
post quality.)</p>
<p>In November of 2019, I also moved all 20 years of super valuable (to me) reader
comments <a href="/2019/11/10/we-now-have-self-hosted-isso-comments/">away from the Disqus silo and into a self-hosted open-source
commenting system called
isso</a>.</p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>In 2019, Strava says I ran 1086km, down from over 1200km in 2018.</p>
<p>I am happy with this.</p>
<p>At the start of 2019, <a href="/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/#running-inspiration">I slowed down a bit
(again)</a>
to help save my ankles.</p>
<p>That seemed to have worked, because I had no mentionable injuries for the rest
of the year, and <em>that</em> makes me happier than more distance would have.</p>
<p>For the sake of this retrospective, I do have to note that I did attain my
secret-until-unlock extra 2019 running goal, namely <a href="/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/#running">the casual 20km
jog</a> on one
not-too-hot Saturday morning in November.</p>
<p>For 2020, my main goal is simply to continue running throughout the year (see
ABC above) without injury.</p>
<p>The secret additional milestone has not yet been formulated.</p>
<p>(I still enjoy running the most on barefoot or sandals, but for the longer
runs, I am really happy to have made the <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#escalante">Altra connection in
September</a>.)</p>
<h2 id="plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">Plans and life directions for 2020.</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#other-plans-for-2019">January 6, 2019 transition WHV were definitely more
ambitious</a>
than I currently feel.</p>
<p>Traditionally, Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) starts around this time and then
continues for a month or more.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s a great tradition, so Monday, January 6, 2020 marks the date this time
around.</p>
<p>Other than EAZ and my humble running goals, it is probably relevant to mention
my recently started experimental daily list of life directions.</p>
<p>At the start of 2012, <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">I wrote the following about life
goals</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Don&rsquo;t set life goals, but rather set life directions. Instead of defining the
point that you want to go towards, define your preferred direction. If you do
it right, you&rsquo;ll pass those points as you go along in any case, except you
won&rsquo;t land in the depressing goal vacuum right after reaching the point that
you&rsquo;ve been moving towards for so long, because you&rsquo;re motoring along in a
direction, and that&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s important.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(I should have added then that life goals, especially the new year&rsquo;s resolution
variety, are also incredibly easy to fail at.)</p>
<p>Finally applying this advice concretely to my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019">note-taking / PKM
system</a>, I have recently added an
&ldquo;Experiment: Articulate your directions / systems&rdquo; heading to <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">the daily
planning template</a>.</p>
<p>In other words, every(ish) morning during day planning, I <em>attempt</em> to write
down (again&hellip;) my current life directions.</p>
<p>This is a neat trick to force me to be reminded multiple times per week of
these guidelines.</p>
<p>It also gives me the opportunity to adapt the wording, or even the list
itself. Your surroundings change continuously, and so do you.</p>
<p>The most recent version is as follows:</p>
<ol start="0">
<li>nurture your clan.</li>
<li>grow the business.</li>
<li>keep on writing, also for publication.</li>
<li>keep on programming, also for publication.</li>
<li>keep on learning, and sharpen tools.</li>
<li>optimise physiology.</li>
</ol>
<p>All of these are
<a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding"><em>compounding</em></a>.</p>
<p>None of them are concrete goals which I can quantitatively attain.</p>
<p>They are all <em>directions of movement</em>, along which any decision or action can
be measured.</p>
<p>If that action furthers one or more of the six directions above, we are good to
go.</p>
<p>If not, it&rsquo;s probably time to go to bed.</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2020">Wishes for 2020.</h2>
<p>Dear readers, <strong>thank you for being here</strong>.</p>
<p>I wish you a brilliant 2020.</p>
<p>I look forward to all of our meetings, both here on these pages, and everywhere
else where they may happen.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2018 to 2019 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 15:39:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</guid><description> The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house-1024x646.jpg"
        
            alt="The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to this, the most recent (as of this writing) instance of the venerable WHV year transition post tradition!</p>
<p>You can find previous editions here:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 to 2018</a> – short post, can be summarised as: “Sorry I stopped blogging for a while, I did run a bit, I’m going to blog more.”</li>
<li><a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">2016 to 2017</a> – substantial post (1800 words) with: “education will improve stupid politics; running, blogging, meditation; we made a new baby!!; kindness and gratefulness; life changes the whole time, deal with it.”</li>
<li><a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">2011 to 2012</a> – transition post disguised as WHV with: “stop doing life goals, disconnect more, list of miscellaneous life tips, because in 2011 I am not-even-40-yet Mr Wisdom”.</li>
<li><a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">2009 to 2010</a> – super short but sweet, I am clearly still new at this.</li>
</ul>
<p>Putting that list together just reminded me of an interesting observation: The more I try to take notes and document everything I see, the more I notice the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiscale_modeling">multiscalar</a> nature of my subjective experience being exposed.</p>
<p>I make detailed daily notes, all of them grouped in monthly text files.</p>
<p>At a slightly higher scale, the frequency of these WHV blog posts is somewhere between a post per week down to a post every three weeks.</p>
<p>When I write each blog post, I look back through the previous weeks, at a daily scale, and perform an extremely lossy summarisation.</p>
<p>When I write the year transitions, I perform an extremely lossy summarisation of the weekly-scale WHV posts.</p>
<p>The list above links together the various yearly transition posts, thus creating a lovely ball of multi-scalar confusion, which should not be confused with a lemur ball, shown below:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball-1024x682.jpg"
        
            alt="At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>WARNING: This post has grown into a long ramble over the past few days. I hope that you enjoy reading the ramble as much as I did thinking of you while writing it.</p>
<h2 id="focus-quantity-and-quality">Focus: Quantity and Quality.</h2>
<p>This post has been taking a while.</p>
<p>I am now back here at the start, after having been almost at the end, because I did not want you to have the idea that my 2018 did not have aspects I am not that happy with, or that I don’t use multiple negations in confusing ways often enough.</p>
<p><em>(As an aside, a friend and I have been exchanging photos of the less glamorous but entirely normal aspects of our vacations via WhatsApp: Plastic on the beach, the washing line, filthy toilets, truly terrible interior decor, and so on. What started as a joke has turned into an unintended but interesting psychological experiment in</em> <strong><em>reverse image crafting</em></strong><em>, strongly underlining the effect that this sort of communication can have.)</em></p>
<p>Back to my main story: During retrospection, I have the tendency to focus (sorry, couldn’t resist) on the good parts, because this is what I remember the best.</p>
<p>However, for the purpose of this post, I did want to spend some words on one of the (multiple!) issues that I struggled with in 2018.</p>
<p>Either I am getting worse at focusing, or I am getting better at noticing when I lose focus, or a combination of both.</p>
<p>At the very least <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">five of the posts I wrote in 2018 dealt in some way with</a> <em><a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">focus</a></em>.</p>
<p>The mentioned posts specifically and my thinking generally take the form of some analysis but mostly tools and tricks to try and improve the frequency, intensity and length of periods of focus.</p>
<p>(What you don’t read in the posts because of above-mentioned memory bias, is that there is usually a significant amount of inwardly-directed regret and disappointment involved.)</p>
<p>Even more subtle is the problem of selecting That One Most Suitable Thing to focus on. What’s going to have the most impact? What do I have capacity for at the moment? Can I trust my own subjective assessment of my current capacity, or is Lazy-Me being sneaky?</p>
<p>By the time I have made a decision, it’s probably wrong. <em>Sometimes</em> it’s a good decision, but by then the little block of time I had has flown away or has been blown to smithereens by the latest interruption, and so the quality of the decision is moot.</p>
<p>I would have expected that at this advanced age focus would come naturally and easily, and that I would know exactly what to do. However, I have had to accept that <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#slippery-slippery-focus">focus will probably remain this slippery</a> and require constant attention (haha I see what I did there) until the very end.</p>
<p>Besides eating well, sleeping well, exercising regularly and taking time to meditate (just in case!), our old friend <a href="https://cpbotha.net/?s=pomodoro">the pomodoro technique</a> is still the best tool in the box.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging.</h2>
<p>During 2018, 36 blog posts were published here, most of which were Weekly Head Voices. Those of you who have a math degree or two will not need much time to calculate that the “W” in “WHV” is at the moment mostly a little inside joke.</p>
<p>However, I did publish 14 more posts than I did in 2017, so there is hope for this year!</p>
<p>The wordpress.com statistics plugin reports just over 19000 visitors (unique IP numbers) who were responsible for just over 26000 page views for the whole year.</p>
<p>Because many people use some form of ad and/or tracking blocking these days, their visits won’t be counted, as the wordpress.com statistics relies on a tiny image which is hosted by wordpress.com, access to which is (rightfully) blocked by many blocker plugins.</p>
<p>In order to get a better idea of how many ad-blocker people read my stuff, I installed the <a href="https://wp-statistics.com/">wp-statistics</a> plugin, which locally tallies up all visits and hence is not blocked by blockers, at the start of March. For the period from March 2018 until the end of the year, it is reporting just over 74000 visitors and somewhere north of 390000 page hits.</p>
<p>Although to me this seems on the high side, I do think we can safely say that there were somewhere between 19000 and 74000 unique hosts, which to me is a very pleasant surprise.</p>
<p>However, I am by far the happiest due to all of the interactions I had with friends, mostly old and some new, on this blog. Most recently, the comments section of <a href="/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/">WHV #156</a> blew up in such a brilliant way!</p>
<p>More generally speaking, even when there are no comments, I know that throughout the year I am connecting with various subsets of my peeps through the posts on this blog. This acts as tremendous motivation to keep on writing. If even a single friend reads, it has been more than worth it.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, there is now a</em> <a href="https://t.me/headvoices"><em>telegram group, quite surprisingly called “headvoices”</em></a><em>, that you can join to receive a summary whenever a new post is published, and for general chitchat. Although so far only two of my most avant-garde friends have joined, this new form of blog-related communication excites me!)</em></p>
<h3 id="looking-forward">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>Surprisingly, I again will aim to write one WHV post per week.</p>
<p>I will probably fail again, but I believe that this is one of those cases of “aim for the stars, reach the moon”.</p>
<p>As mentioned above, writing these letters and writing them regularly is really important to me.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, I should probably have declared <strong>email bankruptcy</strong> years ago. I am</em> <strong><em>just</em></strong> <em>managing to keep head above water, but writing letters to friends like we used to do in the old days is becoming increasingly difficult. What is your feeling currently re email and how it has changed over the past few years?)</em></p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>Strava says I ran 1286km in 2018.</p>
<p>Seeing that I had set myself a private goal of 1000km for 2018 (2016 was 440km and <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 was 880km</a>), I am quite happy with this.</p>
<p>(As an aside, I spent 119 hours running, spread out over a total of 149 runs, which means 2.86 runs every week of the year.)</p>
<p>I did 770 of those 1286 kilometres in sandals, and a further 35km on barefoot.</p>
<p>More importantly, I had to learn the humbling lesson that no amount of stubborn, brute-force exercise could work around the fact I am flat footed (arch-challenged?), resulting in easily overworked posterior tibial tendons.</p>
<p>As I pushed my weekly distance up, my feet complained more loudly, until I was forced to go back to normal-person-running-shoes.</p>
<p>After a few weeks eating humble pie in running shoes, things are going much better, and I recently did my first short and careful run in sandals.</p>
<p>(Similar to the observation confirmed by <a href="https://veronikach.com/progress-reports/my-goals-for-2018-final-progress-report/">the pattern recognition heroine veronikach in her end-of-2018 post</a>, I too ran slower this year in order to run better. I did this for the largest part due to my temporarily busted ankles, but also because more experienced athletes at work recommended heart rate training. For the past few hundreds of kilometres, I have regulated my running speed to try and keep my heart rate within the 75% to 85% of maximum range, mostly ending up closer to 85% than 80%. This has increased the occurrence of those addictive perfect runs, and it has helped to keep my ankles out of trouble.)</p>
<h3 id="looking-forward-1">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>In 2019, I would be happy to <em>maintain</em> my 2018 monthly running quota, to remain injury-free, and to maximise my running zen.</p>
<p>(“Running slow” explained above can contribute substantially to the latter two goals.)</p>
<p>I do have an additional concrete (but very humble) running-related resolution for 2019, but I have decided to keep that quiet until it’s in the pocket. :)</p>
<h2 id="other-plans-for-2019">Other plans for 2019.</h2>
<h3 id="experiment-alcohol-zero">Experiment Alcohol Zero #2.</h3>
<p>Yesterday, which at the time of writing is January 4, 2019, was the first day of EAZ #2.</p>
<p>It has been two years since <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#experiment-alcohol-zero">the previous EAZ in 2016</a>. The previous experiment coincided with a significant jump in my running performance, the effects of which did not fade away after the end of the experiment.</p>
<p>This time around, the plan is to run EAZ for at least as long as in 2016, but hopefully a few days or weeks longer.</p>
<p>(I should probably call this EA&lt;0.5, as that is what my current favourite “alcohol-free” beer, Devil’s Peak Zero to Hero, claims.)</p>
<h3 id="ship-more-side-projects">Ship more side-projects.</h3>
<p>Most nerds I know have <em>side-projects</em>.</p>
<p>These are the technical artifacts, systems and machines one builds, because one can’t stop building stuff, even after work ends.</p>
<p>Like most nerds, I have a number of these that started with high momentum (new programming language, new tools, new problem, EXCITING! … 3 hours later … NOVELTY COMPLETELY WORN OFF doh.) and are now lying around gathering dust.</p>
<p>Inspired by a colleague who managed to ship <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/656740/Cosmonator/">a brilliant shooter game side-project on Steam</a> last year, I made myself the promise to ship more side-projects.</p>
<p>After that, I managed to ship two side-projects, one small and the other quite tiny.</p>
<p>This was a satisfying experience that I would like to continue in 2019.</p>
<p>(P.S. the problem with shipping side-projects, is that you now have more things that you actually have to look after. Next year I’ll think up a resolution for unmaintained shipped side-projects.)</p>
<h3 id="mindful-more">Mindful more.</h3>
<p>This is a simple one.</p>
<p>I used to spend a few minutes every second morning before work doing simple mindfulness breathing and focus exercises.</p>
<p>It was worth the modest time investment many times over, in terms of focus, and especially in terms of seeing life in perspective.</p>
<p>In the second half of 2018 I let this habit slip for some or other reason. I think it’s because I convinced myself that running time could also count as meditation time.</p>
<p>In 2019, I’m going to #bringbackthemeditation.</p>
<h3 id="learn-more">Learn more.</h3>
<p>During 2018, I started taking a more structured approach to the books I wanted to read, and the courses I wanted to follow, by tracking these in my <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">sneaky longer term goals which form part of my daily planning routine</a>.</p>
<p>More structure meant more books read to completion, and more courses followed, resulting in an Ever So Slightly Improved Me.</p>
<p>I am planning to continue and extend this practice in 2019.</p>
<h3 id="evolve-the-system">Evolve The System.</h3>
<p>The System.</p>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
<p>One step, and then another, and then another, until the lights finally go out.</p>
<h3 id="try-to-grow-a-tree">Try to grow a tree.</h3>
<p>I grew up with a fuerte avocado tree that gave us hundreds of the divine fruit every season.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 40 odd years, and my mom (HI MOM!) gave us a beautiful baby fuerte avocado tree for Christmas!









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree-805x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>We are currently trying to nurture it through its first few weeks of life in our garden.</p>
<p>With the summer sun, and the new environment, it’s a bit touch and go at the moment, but we’re really rooting for that baby tree! (bad pun quota exhausted now?!)</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This is it my friends.</p>
<p>You have made it to the end, an endeavour for which I am truly grateful.</p>
<p>I wish you a 2019 filled with growth, health and happiness.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2017 to 2018 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 11:46:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/</guid><description> My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis.
Does anything still work around here?
So much dust…
Is this thing on?
Testing… 123… tesssting… sound check sound check.
OH HI MARK.
(HELLO ALL MY OTHER FRIENDS WHO ARE NOT MARK!)
It’s been 4 months since the previous post (a Weekly Head Voices), due to reasons involving work (fortunately challenging and fun), genetic offspring units but especially the youngest one who is currently developing at a frightening speed, the South African climate, and my brain suddenly starting to refuse work any later than about 19:00 every day.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2827-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2827-PANO-1024x404.jpg"
        
            alt="My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Does anything still work around here?</p>
<p>So much dust…</p>
<p>Is this thing on?</p>
<p>Testing… 123… tesssting… sound check sound check.</p>
<p>OH HI MARK.</p>
<p>(HELLO ALL MY OTHER FRIENDS WHO ARE NOT MARK!)</p>
<p>It’s been 4 months since the previous post (a Weekly Head Voices), due to reasons involving work (fortunately challenging and fun), genetic offspring units but especially the youngest one who is currently developing at a frightening speed, the South African climate, and my brain suddenly starting to refuse work any later than about 19:00 every day.</p>
<p>My brain has good reasons I have to admit, having absorbed <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/sep/24/why-lack-of-sleep-health-worst-enemy-matthew-walker-why-we-sleep">this Guardian interview with Matthew Walker</a>, director of the Center for Human Sleep Science at the University of California, Berkeley. In short, the possible effects of sleeping anything less than 7 hours per night are simply terrifying. It made me, I mean my brain, really rethink its approach to grabbing-one-more-hour-from-sleep-because-this-stuff-is-really-super-interesting.</p>
<p>Anyhow, following the probably better and more beefy example set by my previous transition post, <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">2016-to-2017 that is</a>, I thought that a new edition would be the best way to get back into slightly more regular posting.</p>
<h1 id="2017-the-100-partial-and-spotty-review">2017: The 100% partial and spotty review</h1>
<p>I wrote 21 posts on this blog in 2017, 12 of which were Weekly Head Voices, which means I was about 23% (12 / 52) successful in terms of posting frequency with the WHV.</p>
<p>The most popular post over here was <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">Deep Work: A welcome kick in the butt</a>, published on January 9, which garnered just over 20 thousand views. From there my stats went all downhill. :)</p>
<p>More importantly than reader stats, each post, especially <a href="https://cpbotha.net/category/weekly-head-voices/">the Weekly Head Voices ones</a>, brought so much connection and satisfaction, which raises the question: Why am I not doing this more? (See my reasons above for not having posted for 4 months, I would have to guess.)</p>
<p>In 2017, I ran just over 800km, which, in contrast to my blogging frequency, is a nice improvement over the 440km I did in 2016. Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) of February last year contributed significantly to my average distance and speed. Those gains were maintained and slightly extended in spite of EAZ concluding in March of last year.</p>
<p>To get an idea of what I was up to work-wise in 2017, you could consider browsing <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/">the posts I wrote on my nerd-blog during 2017</a>.  This will give you a bad idea, but it’s probably better than no idea, if you really needed to know.</p>
<p>Life-wise, I might have mentioned <a href="/category/weekly-head-voices/">The Weekly Head voices posts</a> before. There aren’t that many of them for 2017, but the ones that there are, are not too bad.</p>
<h1 id="2018-again-not-much-planned-at-least-not-in-public">2018: Again not much planned, at least not in public.</h1>
<p>Following the shining example of <a href="http://www.veronikach.com/progress-reports/year-of-blogging/">Dr Cheplygina</a>, I would love to become a fully paid-up member of the <em>True</em> Weekly Bloggers Club.</p>
<p>For the past 6 months I sort of went Facebook cold turkey (because reasons, mostly to do with attention-abuse and above-mentioned time scarcity). That, in addition to my unplanned blogging hiatus, feels (yes, I have those, albeit in extremely limited quantities) like it’s caused a bit of a disconnect between me and friends around the world.</p>
<p>I have very recently returned to facebook via the mobile website, and only after extremely liberal application of the “unfollow” button to whittle my feed down to just the people I have a healthy connection with. This will help me te maintain connections with the friends who use that as platform.</p>
<p><strong>My reciprocation will have to take the form of weekly updates on this blog.</strong></p>
<p>I look forward to it, and I look forward even more to welcoming you here!










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2669.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2669-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from our cabin at Storms River Mouth Rest Camp. 12/10 will go again."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from our cabin at Storms River Mouth Rest Camp. 12/10 will go again.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2016 to 2017 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 11:05:01 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/</guid><description>Following the rich tradition over here of year transition posts, having just rounded off a brilliant outdoorsy take-your-mind-off-of-everything vacation with friends, and also inspired by wogan.blog’s nicely personal 2016 review post, I decided that a farewell-2016 how-you-doin’-2017 post was in order.
By the way, by rich tradition I mean that I wrote the grand total of one (1) similarly titled post previously, as the year ticked from 2009 to 2010, and at least one other, disguised as a weekly head voices, as we entered 2012. That last one is worth another read, early 2012 cpbotha had some really good tips. There might be more such posts, this blog has been around for more than 15 years and much of what I’ve written is not available from my short-term memory, which is nice.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Following the rich tradition over here of year transition posts, having just rounded off a brilliant outdoorsy take-your-mind-off-of-everything vacation with friends, and also inspired by <a href="https://wogan.blog/2017/01/01/2016-in-review/">wogan.blog’s nicely personal 2016 review post</a>, I decided that a farewell-2016 how-you-doin’-2017 post was in order.</p>
<p>By the way, by <em>rich tradition</em> I mean that I wrote the grand total of one (1) similarly titled post previously, <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">as the year ticked from 2009 to 2010</a>, and at least one other, disguised as a weekly head voices, <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">as we entered 2012</a>. <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">That last one</a> is worth another read, early 2012 cpbotha had some really good tips. There might be more such posts, <a href="/about/history/">this blog has been around for more than 15 years</a> and much of what I’ve written is not available from my short-term memory, which is nice.</p>
<p><em><strong>Warning:</strong> This post is long (1800 words+), rambly and sometimes even a bit mushy. I hope you enjoy it!</em></p>
<h1 id="2016-the-review">2016: The Review</h1>
<h2 id="the-bad-with-a-hopefully-slightlypositive-outlook-at-the-end">The bad, with a hopefully slightly positive outlook at the end</h2>
<p>Let’s get the bad stuff out of the way as soon as we can…</p>
<p>For me the biggest disappointments of 2016 were the double-whammy of the Brexit followed by the Trumpocalypse.</p>
<p>I really did not expect either of these events to go the way they did.</p>
<p>This is probably because I was, ever the optimist, over-estimating the level of human development of British and US voters.</p>
<p>The exclusionist, nationalist, xenophobic and in many cases even white supremacist thinking associated with Trump’s support in the US and the Leave vote in the UK are truly abhorrent.</p>
<p>I understand that there were many other factors at play. However, these voters were either throwing out the baby with the bath water, or, much much  worse, agreeing with the abhorrent sentiments mentioned above. Especially this second possibility depressed me greatly after the US election.</p>
<p>After such setbacks, one needs to look for solutions.</p>
<p>After Brexit, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/06/brexit-vote-statistics-united-kingdom-european-union/488780/">analysis showed that education level was the strongest indicator of a vote for leave or remain</a>. Higher education was strongly associated with remain, whilst the opposite was the case for leave.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Screen-Shot-2017-01-05-at-12.28.37-PM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Screen-Shot-2017-01-05-at-12.28.37-PM-709x1024.png"
        
            alt="Leave / remain voter analysis by The Atlantic. Click to go to article &#43; interactive version of this graphic."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Leave / remain voter analysis by The Atlantic. Click to go to article + interactive version of this graphic.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>For Trump voters, you probably guessed it, it was more or less the same idea. <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/education-not-income-predicted-who-would-vote-for-trump/">Less educated citizens voted for Trump, more educated citizens for Clinton</a>.</p>
<p>This is yet another strong indication that we should really be pouring every resource we have into the education of our people. (yes, correlation and causation, I know. hence the terms “strong indication”. discuss in the comments if you like.)</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrence_M._Krauss">Lawrence M. Krauss</a>, superstar theoretical physicist and author of the book A Universe from Nothing, <a href="https://twitter.com/LKrauss1/status/814947974203641857">recently tweeted</a> this <a href="http://www.quotationspage.com/quote/26977.html">1920 quote by H.G. Wells</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Human history has become, more and more, a race between education and catastrophe.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The way things are going now, that thought, and movements like #feesmustfall, are more important than ever. There can be absolutely no excuse for neglecting the highest quality and <strong>accessible</strong> education (basic up to tertiary) of future generations of humans whom we expect to further our civilization.</p>
<h2 id="therunning-and-the-mindful">The running and the mindful</h2>
<p>In 2016, I ran 440km.</p>
<p>There are a great deal of people who have run much more than that, but those are <em>my</em> 440 kilometers and somehow they brought me a great deal of deep satisfaction.</p>
<p>During the year, my per-run distance and speed have gradually increased.</p>
<p>Besides fitness gradually increasing, I discovered experimentally that shorter, quicker steps get me further and a higher pace. It took a biomechanical friend to explain to me that this was about muscles operating within the more efficient middle of their full extension/contraction ranges. I could probably just have read this somewhere, but doing it the hard way and then having a friend explain it on top of Table Mountain definitely added something to the experience.</p>
<p>For the last 200 kilometres or so, I have listened to the exact same album: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skin_(Flume_album)">Skin by Flume</a>. Every single run, I start that exact same album with the exact same sequence of tracks. As I learned from <a href="https://www.swimgeek.com/blog/2016/11/16/quick-update-445/">the SwimGeek’s blog</a>, <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/2113776/question-everything-tim-ferriss-fitness"><em>finding your soundtrack and putting it on repeat</em> whilst exercising is apparently a thing</a>.</p>
<p>With the surroundings over here being what they are, it does not take much to slip into a state of mindfulness.</p>
<p>No doing, no planning; just absorbing all of the surroundings, physical and mental, the music, and feeling how the meat-based machine that houses me propels us forward.</p>
<p>On the topic of mindfulness, for the last few months I added a repeat event to my todoist, helping me to spend five minutes every morning before work doing the breathing exercise. More recently I do this without any voice track, but previously Prof. Mark Williams at one point would say (original quote is due to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon_Kabat-Zinn">Jon Kabat-Zinn, PhD</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Each breath a new beginning; each out-breath a letting go.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There’s a whole lot in there. I have spent quite some time with it and I am far from done.</p>
<h3 id="the-blog">The blog</h3>
<p>The first rule of blogging: You don’t blog about blogging.</p>
<p>However, I hope you don’t mind me breaking that rule to mention that in 2016, this blog was viewed 133 thousand times. I already get happy when one other person reads a post. You can imagine how happy it makes me to know that there are even slightly more people who have come here to consume some of the words I have written, and even some who have taken the time to leave behind comments!</p>
<p>The lion’s share of those views were due to focused posts that got picked up by some of the more popular nerd sites. I have to admit that I derived the most enjoyment from the more personal posts that were only read by friends.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, this has to be my most satisfying hobby. Thank you for the crucial role that you who read play in it!</p>
<h3 id="the-new-life">The new life</h3>
<p>In early(ish) 2016, our third daughter, affectionately known as Genetic Offspring Unit #3 (GOU#3 for short) around these parts, <a href="/2016/05/05/weekly-head-voices-106-ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/">was born</a>.</p>
<p>This wonderful little cellular mega-cluster is currently making noises that have the primary purpose of being immensely cute, but are also slowly starting to make sense. Her ambulation capabilities have increased immensely, and she is on the verge of standing up by herself and so we will probably have to re-arrange our interior. Again.</p>
<p>Long ago, <a href="/2011/08/28/the-lowlands-tooth-fairy-37-weekly-head-voices-55/">I wrote here about my unexpected new role as someone else’s Tooth Fairy</a>. In the meantime, working as a part-time tooth fairy and a full-time papa to three little humans has turned out to be a more fulfilling career than I ever could have imagined.</p>
<h1 id="2017-not-much-planned-yet-you">2017: Not much planned yet, you?</h1>
<p>I prefer making resolutions in secret, then carrying them out or not, and only then reporting on them. However, that would mean that I would have to wrap up this post right now, and for that I’m not quite ready yet.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-alcohol-zero">Experiment Alcohol Zero</h2>
<p>One resolution that I am already executing on, is performing an interesting little experiment. After reading about <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/the-running-blog/2014/apr/23/how-does-alcohol-affect-athletic-performance">the effects of alcohol on one’s (running) performance and general energy levels</a>, I have decided to go for 30 days without a drop of alcohol to try and get a subjective idea of its potential impact.</p>
<p>Those of you who have spent more than 8 seconds in my or my blog’s vicinity know that I absolutely adore craft <a href="/tag/beer/">beer</a> (this includes local, but also special beers of the Belgian type) and local wines, both of which are regularly consumed by me and “business partners” during “business lunches” in the not-unattractive local surroundings.</p>
<p>This decision was not taken lightly.</p>
<p>It is mid-morning of day 2 of Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) as I write this. With the air full of smoke due to <a href="/2017/01/04/massive-fires-around-here-thanks-to-firefighters-my-neighbourhood-escaped/">local vegetation fires</a>, I have not been able to go running yet, but I am imagining that my energy lasted later last night, and I got up easier this morning. I have 29 more days to investigate.</p>
<h2 id="reminders-for-a-hopefully-better-life">Reminders for a hopefully better life</h2>
<p>Every day, I remind myself <a href="/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/">to be the kindest I can possibly be to everyone I come into contact with</a>. We have infinite amounts of kindness to spread.</p>
<p>I also remind myself to <a href="/2014/11/03/weekly-head-voices-84-on-being-grateful/">be grateful</a>. It takes continuous practice to identify the many things one can be grateful for every day, but it is definitely worth it.</p>
<p>I often remind GOU#1 (#2 and #3 are not old enough yet for this lesson) that, besides the guidelines above, we have to keep on working on two more related characteristics: being useful, and being likable.</p>
<p>Being useful means continuously developing and refining skills that enable one to contribute value to one’s surroundings. Being likable means understanding and appreciating how we humans stick together. Kindness, see above, is an important component of this.</p>
<p>In 2017, I would like to write more (on this blog probably), and read more.</p>
<h1 id="rapidly-morphing-goalpostsjumping-randomly-through-even-more-randomly-pulsating-hyperspace-with-a-slightly-positive-outlook-at-the-end">Rapidly morphing goalposts jumping randomly through even more randomly pulsating hyperspace, with a slightly positive outlook at the end</h1>
<p>Yes folks, this is going to be my parting thought.</p>
<p>When I was much younger, I used to believe that one’s life could be “cracked”. That is, if you searched, and you worked really hard at understanding yourself, your people and your surroundings, you could come up with some kind of answer with which you would be able to attain contentment.</p>
<p>In the meantime I’ve come to the realisation that that Much Younger Me, although quite dashing, was of course utterly wrong.</p>
<p>Life is utterly dynamic. You Now are a different person from You Last Year. The same goes for people around you, and the same goes for everything around you.</p>
<p>The goal posts are not just moving all the time, they are an illusion flashing in and out of an hallucinogenic and especially dynamic perception.</p>
<p>One trick to help one deal with this, is to stop thinking about goals in the first place, and instead <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">consider the directions of your movement</a>.</p>
<p>Also keep in mind that <a href="/2016/02/02/weekly-head-voices-103-chips/">there are no answers, only choices</a>. You work to make the best ones you can with the means at your disposal at that moment.</p>
<p>Importantly, in this restless environment, some peace can be found by realising that a large part of the restlessness originates from within you. Fortunately, you have slightly more say in you than you have in your surroundings.</p>
<p>What one can do then, is nicely summarised by Prof. Mark Williams in the audio accompanying <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mindfulness-Eight-Week-Finding-Peace-Frantic/dp/1609618955">his mindfulness book</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The deep stillness we seek does not arise because the world is still or the mind is quiet. Stillness is nourished when we allow things to be just as they are for now, in this moment, moment by moment and breath by breath.</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="the-end-for-now">The End (for now)</h1>
<p>Alright friends, that was it from me, for now. I hope that you have the best 2017 possible. I hope especially that your kindness and that of those around you flows deeply and freely.</p>
<p>As a parting gift, here is the high-resolution panoroma I made from the top of Table Mountain, after hiking up Platteklip Gorge with friends:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama-1024x325.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net. Click for high-res."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net. Click for high-res.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #100: Happy 2016!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/03/weekly-head-voices-100-happy-2016/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 09:20:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/03/weekly-head-voices-100-happy-2016/</guid><description> Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res.
I wish you a truly happy 2016, filled with learning and helping other people! Neil deGrasse Tyson, exemplary human, said it best:
For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And along the way, lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/table_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/table_mountain_view.jpg"
        
            alt="Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I wish you a truly happy 2016, filled with learning and helping other people! Neil deGrasse Tyson, exemplary human, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/qccer/i_am_neil_degrasse_tyson_ask_me_anything/c3wgffy">said it best</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And along the way, lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Time is fun when you&rsquo;re having flies! I can&rsquo;t believe that four months have flown by since <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/23/weekly-head-voices-99-no-lands/">the previous WHV</a>. Since then, quite a bunch has happened. Some highlights for me:</p>
<ul>
<li>I spent a week in The Netherlands, my other home, taking part in a second hackathon with the Evalueserve peeps (the previous one was in Gurgaon in India). This was again loads of fun, and we managed to build a significant new shippable feature (measurable value!) almost from scratch.</li>
<li>In October, I went back to The Netherlands (it&rsquo;s my other home, remember) for 2.5 days to take part in the Doctorification of <a href="http://francoismalan.com/">a friend</a>. Besides the doctorification process (I&rsquo;ve been out of academia for a while, so my terminology might not be 100%) which went swimmingly, I had so many high-intensity interactions with some of my favourite people that I literally almost missed my flight back. Just picture me waking up in Delft at 8:30 with a flight leaving from Amsterdam at 10:00…</li>
<li>For a work project,  I started programming in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swift_(programming_language)">Apple&rsquo;s Swift</a>. As compiled high-performance languages go, this one has a number of modern language features which make it a truly interesting addition to one&rsquo;s programming toolbox.</li>
<li>Further on the nerd-front, I&rsquo;m trying to get more of us to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">use Signal instead of WhatsApp</a> whenever possible.</li>
<li>We spent so many weekends and the Christmas vacation doing fun outdoorsy stuff (living at the southern tip of Africa has serious perks), not least of which was a trip up Table Mountain for the first time in 15 years. See the photo up top for an impression.</li>
</ul>
<p>I have some fun changes in mind for this blog in 2016, but you&rsquo;re going to have to stick around to find out what they are, so… see you later peeps!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>