<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>education on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/categories/education/</link><description>Recent content in education on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2009 16:47:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/categories/education/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #5: Google Docs, Bad Netbook Karma, Cold does not cause cold.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/27/weekly-head-voices-5-google-docs-netbook-karma-common-cold/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2009 16:47:36 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/27/weekly-head-voices-5-google-docs-netbook-karma-common-cold/</guid><description> It’s been a terribly quiet week blog-wise, but I did make that promise four weeks ago, and, seeing that I want to be a columnist when I grow up (hint hint employers of columnists) and those guys and girls simply HAVE to think up something interesting every single week, I too am going to do my best to add sweetness to the shortness that you see before you.
Speaking of shortness, I did get some off-blog (yes, face-to-face!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>It’s been a terribly quiet week blog-wise, but I did make that promise four weeks ago, and, seeing that I want to be a columnist when I grow up (hint hint employers of columnists) and those guys and girls simply HAVE to think up something interesting every single week, I too am going to do my best to add sweetness to the shortness that you see before you.</p>
<p>Speaking of shortness, I did get some off-blog (yes, face-to-face!) feedback on the previous edition of the WHV. Said (highly appreciated) feedback concerned the length of these posts, more specifically, that there was too much of it. It’s important to remember that I in fact do write these things with the chronically time-challenged in mind. One of the measures I take is to bold the most important themes in each paragraph, so that one can easily skip on to the next paragraph if the mentioned theme does not take one’s fancy. This week, I’m going even further by employing section headings! As always, <strong>please feel free to skip paragraphs and sections.</strong></p>
<p>Before jumping in, I give you the traditional WHV photo, this time of my little Weber doing its thing (thanks to some crucial material supplied by <a href="http://tokkiebytes.wordpress.com/" title="My friendly neighbour's blog.  He is in fact my only neighbour with a blog, as far as I know.">my friendly neighbour</a>) on the most brilliant of all South African celebrations: <a href="http://braai4heritage.co.za/" title="more info on national braai day">National Braai day!</a>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/national_braai_day.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/national_braai_day.jpg"
        
            alt="My humble little Weber on NBD 2009."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>My humble little Weber on NBD 2009.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p><strong>Geeky Google Docs love affair</strong></p>
<p><a href="http://docs.google.com/" title="Link to Google Docs">Google Docs</a> is Google’s fantastic attempt (well, it was initially developed by Writely, which was soon assimilated by and has since been happily functioning inside of The Google Supermind) at an office suite. The whole thing, including Documents, Spreadsheets, and Presentations, runs in your web browser. This means that you always have access to your stuff from anywhere, and you never have to install any extra software. With the offline functionality, you can continue working even without an internet connection.</p>
<p>This was already pretty neat, but then they had to go and make it even neater. In my line of business, one of the coolest features is the fact that you can <strong>concurrently edit the same document with any number of collaborators</strong>. I’ve written research proposals together with colleagues before, where at a number of occasions we were actually editing the same paragraph of text from two different cities, and Docs didn’t break a sweat merging our edits in real-time. This functionality also eliminates the very irritating “Could you send me the latest version of the proposal” emails, the subsequent waiting and then the infuriating expired time window when the latest version finally arrives in the email.</p>
<p>A recent feature which is admittedly less impressive to the public at large, but made my geek heart miss several beats, was the built-in equation editor. Imagine my surprise when I tried this out for the first time and realised that it is in fact a <strong>real-time LaTeX math typesetter</strong>: You type your incredibly complex formula in standard LaTeX, and Google Docs shows the typeset math updated in real-time. This is even useful if you’re NOT using Google Docs but just want to fine-tune the formulas in your LaTeX article.  Check the screenshot below:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/google_docs_ss1.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/google_docs_ss1.png"
        
            alt="Screenshot of Google Docs equation editor."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Screenshot of Google Docs equation editor.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>90% of MS Office users probably don’t use more than 10% of its functionality. Google Docs covers this 10% more than adequately, but without the complexity, the platform lock-in and the cost. Next time you’re considering emailing someone a Word document or Powerpoint, have a look at Google Docs first!</p>
<p><strong>Netbook Bad Karma</strong></p>
<p>On an extra partition, my netbook (Asus 1005HA-H, the computer I’m currently in love with) has the absolute latest development version of the Ubuntu Karmic Koala (9.10 – will be released at the end of October) Netbook Remix. Linux distributions, and especially Ubuntu, have been making great progress recently on state of the art hardware. On this netbook, suspend to ram for example works out of the box, which is quite an achievement for Linux-kind. However, whereas battery life under the bundled Windows with the Asus Super Hybrid Engine (don’t laugh, to me it sounds like some knid of giant fighting robot power source) is an astounding 9+ hours, under Linux it’s a quite disappointing 4 or 5 hours. One very obvious factor is the CPU running at 1GHz at idle under Linux and 850MHz at idle under Windows.</p>
<p>Even installing and configuring the latest eeepc acpi utilities, including kernel module, from the testing repository at StatUX <a href="http://www.statux.org/content?page=repo">http://www.statux.org/content?page=repo</a>, although enabling bunches of hotkeys, didn’t solve the battery problem. The CPU was still running at 1GHz.</p>
<p>I’m curious to see what the case will be at Karmic release, preferably with the stock Ubuntu Netbook Remix and not too much user fiddling. I’m considering writing a short review at that time, hopefully less critical than <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2007/04/10/a-critical-look-at-ubuntu-feisty-beta-on-an-hp-nc8430-laptop/" title="Previous review of Feisty on HP laptop.">my previous attempt</a> with Ubuntu Feisty beta (7.04) on my HP laptop.</p>
<p><strong>Brand new Visual Data Analysis lecture block</strong></p>
<p>For the past 4 years, I have been taking care of the Medical Visualisation parts (2 lecture blocks) of the TU Delft master-level Data Visualisation course (IN4086). Since the beginning of this year, I also give my very own dedicated 5 ECTS Medical Visualisation course (<a href="http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4307" title="IN4307 course website">IN4307</a>), which I have designed with the sole purpose of producing <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/05/01/i-have-an-official-course-code/#more-362" title="an old blog post of mine on the in4307 ninjas">MedVis NINJAS</a>. I take great joy in corrupting promising young minds with my special brand of evil science. :)</p>
<p>In a very recent development, it seems that <strong>I will now also be taking care of the Visual Data Analysis block of the general Data Visualisation course</strong>. I somehow blurted this out during a recent meeting, and now have the privilege of designing this one from scratch too.</p>
<p>This is quite interesting, because visual data analysis, or visual analytics as it’s sometimes called (urgh), is primarily associated with Information Visualisation, and being a MedVis fanatic I’m supposed to be a Scientific Visualisation guy. To cut a long story short, InfoVis and SciVis are two sub-fields in the broader field of Visualisation, but the communities behind them might as well come from different planets, in spite of the best efforts of some of my colleagues to unify everything. In any case, it turns out that we (when I say “we” I mean <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/~jorik/" title="Jorik's homepage">Jorik</a>) have been secretly publishing suspiciously infovis-friendly articles the past few years. Look:</p>
<ul>
<li>J. Blaas, C.P. Botha, E. Grundy, M.W. Jones, R.S. Laramee, and F.H. Post, <em><a href="http://cs.swan.ac.uk/~csmark/PDFS/blaas2009.pdf" title="Link to Jorik's higher-order smooth graphs vis 2009 article.">Smooth graphs for visual exploration of higher order state transitions</a></em>, <strong>IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</strong>, vol. 15, 2009.</li>
<li>J. Blaas, C.P. Botha, and F.H. Post, <em><a href="http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/publications/Blaas2008.pdf" title="LInk to Blaas 2008 PCP article PDF.">Extensions of Parallel Coordinates for Interactive Exploration of Large Multi-Timepoint Data Sets</a></em>, <strong>IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics</strong>, vol. 14, 2008, pp. 1436-1451.</li>
<li>J. Blaas, C.P. Botha, and F.H. Post, <em><a href="http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/publications/blaas2007.pdf" title="Link to feature space / physical space eurovis 2007 article by Blaas.">Interactive visualization of multi-field medical data using linked physical and feature-space views</a></em>, <strong>Proc. Eurographics / IEEE-VGTC EuroVis</strong>, K. Museth, A. Ynnerman, and T. Möller, 2007, pp. 123-130.</li>
</ul>
<p>I find this a very interesting and gratifying development. An increasing number of my research collaborations in the medical research field are also benefiting from visual data analysis techniques. Keeping in mind the clichéd but no less real data explosion, we, as visualisation people, can greatly increase our value to the client. The forthcoming Visual Data Analysis lecture block I’m designing is just one step in the evolution of our science.</p>
<p><strong>The End, my friend, also of your common cold misconceptions.</strong></p>
<p>Pressing Ctrl-Shift-C in this Google Doc draft (how’s that for subtle product placement?), I can see that I’ve once again passed the 1000 word mark (1200 to be more precise).</p>
<p>Whoops.</p>
<p>I had even more planned, but instead I’ll conclude with a hopefully useful snippet of information, especially in the light of the coming winter. Many people I run into still somehow believe that there’s a causal relationship between being cold, as in going outside in cold weather, and getting a cold, as in sneezing and having a running nose. Well, I’m here to tell you that it’s an age-old myth. A myth I say! See this quote from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_cold#Exposure_to_cold_weather" title="Wikipedia article on the common cold">the Wikipedia article on the common cold</a> (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>An ancient belief still common today claims that a cold can be “caught” by prolonged exposure to cold weather such as rain or winter conditions, which is where the disease got its name.<sup><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_cold#cite_note-8" style="text-decoration: none; color: #002bb8; background-image: none; background-repeat: initial; background-attachment: initial; -webkit-background-clip: initial; -webkit-background-origin: initial; background-color: initial; white-space: nowrap; background-position: initial initial;"><span>[</span>9<span>]</span></a></sup> Although common colds are seasonal, with more occurring during winter, experiments so far have failed to produce evidence that short-term exposure to cold weather or direct chilling increases susceptibility to infection, implying that the seasonal variation is instead due to a change in behaviors such as increased time spent indoors at close proximity to others.<sup><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_cold#cite_note-NIAID2006-5" style="text-decoration: none; color: #002bb8; background-image: none; background-repeat: initial; background-attachment: initial; -webkit-background-clip: initial; -webkit-background-origin: initial; background-color: initial; white-space: nowrap; background-position: initial initial;"><span>[</span>6<span>]</span></a></sup><sup><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_cold#cite_note-pmid13559211-9" style="text-decoration: none; color: #002bb8; background-image: none; background-repeat: initial; background-attachment: initial; -webkit-background-clip: initial; -webkit-background-origin: initial; background-color: initial; white-space: nowrap; background-position: initial initial;"><span>[</span>10<span>]</span></a></sup><sup><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_cold#cite_note-pmid12357708-10" style="text-decoration: none; color: #002bb8; background-image: none; background-repeat: initial; background-attachment: initial; -webkit-background-clip: initial; -webkit-background-origin: initial; background-color: initial; white-space: nowrap; background-position: initial initial;"><span>[</span>11<span>]</span></a></sup><sup><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_cold#cite_note-11" style="text-decoration: none; color: #002bb8; background-image: none; background-repeat: initial; background-attachment: initial; -webkit-background-clip: initial; -webkit-background-origin: initial; background-color: initial; white-space: nowrap; background-position: initial initial;"><span>[</span>12<span>]</span></a></sup><sup><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_cold#cite_note-12" style="text-decoration: none; color: #002bb8; background-image: none; background-repeat: initial; background-attachment: initial; -webkit-background-clip: initial; -webkit-background-origin: initial; background-color: initial; white-space: nowrap; background-position: initial initial;"><span>[</span>13<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just to ram that point home: <strong>Going outside in the cold, or being exposed to cold weather or direct chilling, very probably does not increase your chances of catching the common cold!</strong> Similar to this is the work on influenza. It turns out that there’s a <a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2009/02/090209205148.htm" title="article on link between flu and absolute humidity">link between the flu and absolute humidity</a>: The <em>lower</em> the humidity, the higher the chance of getting the flu. It’s quite probable that you catch the flu virus not from going outside in winter, but from staying inside your heated and hence slightly drier home.  Chalk one up for all the kids getting told, unfairly and without scientific basis, to dress up before going out or risk getting ill.</p>
<p>On that rebellious note, have a super duper week!  (… and please do your thing in the comments below …)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>You must vaccinate</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/05/21/you-must-vaccinate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2009 09:02:02 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/05/21/you-must-vaccinate/</guid><description> Image courtesy of dbtechno.com. I was mistakenly under the impression that, at least in my social circles, the whole vaccination issue had been put completely to rest, but based on the number of serious questions that I’ve been asked recently, this unfortunately does not seem to be the case.
For those of you who don’t have time, I’ll cut to the chase immediately:
Yes, you simply must vaccinate your children.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<img alt="" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/05/vaccine_autism_vaccinations.jpg" style="margin-left: 0px;"/>
<figcaption>Image courtesy of dbtechno.com.</figcaption>
</figure> 
<p>I was mistakenly under the impression that, at least in my social circles, the
whole vaccination issue had been put completely to rest, but based on the
number of serious questions that I’ve been asked recently, this
unfortunately does not seem to be the case.</p>
<p>For those of you who don’t have time, I’ll cut to the chase immediately:</p>
<p><strong>Yes, you simply <em>must</em> vaccinate your children.  This is the <em>best and
safest</em> choice, for both your child and your fellow humans.</strong></p>
<p><strong>No, there is no link between vaccination and autism. No, spreading out the
(MMR) vaccinations is not safer, it is in fact more dangerous.  Also, the
“vaccine overload” hypothesis is flawed.</strong></p>
<p>For those of you with a bit more time or those of you who are not willing to take me on my word, I’ll go into some more detail on each of the points mentioned above.  Most of what I write here is based on articles in the Wikipedia.  I’ve deliberately done this, because these articles are accessible and readable to everyone, and they do link to the original scientific articles that they are based on.  Feel free to jump to any section.  Also, each section ends with a short summary of its contents to make it easier for you to skip.</p>
<h1 id="recent-history">Recent history</h1>
<p><em>This section is based on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MMR_vaccine_controversy" title="Wikipedia article on MMR vaccine controversy">Wikipedia article on the MMR vaccine
controversy</a>.</em></p>
<p>In 1998, Andre Wakefield and co-authors published a paper in the Lancet where,
based on 12 case reports, they speculated on a possible link between the MMR
vaccination and autism, and also speculated that it might be better to space
out the vaccinations.  Of course the press and media picked this up and went
completely wild, causing a health scare in the UK.  It is important to note
that both of these claims were highly speculative.</p>
<p>It later turned out that Wakefield had received 55000 (fifty-five thousand) UK
pounds from Legal Aid Board solicitors who were gathering evidence to use in a
case against vaccine manufacturers, and that a number of parents of the
children taking part in Wakefield’s study were directly involved in the
law-suit.  Wakefield did not mention any of this at the time of publication. 
Ten of his 12 co-authors have since completely retracted their interpretation
of the paper.</p>
<p>In short, the author of the paper that started most of the modern vaccination-autism scare was completely corrupt, and his corruption directly affected this specific research.</p>
<p>He did manage to cause such a scare in the UK, that measles (one of the diseases that MMR vaccinates against) is for the first time in decades at almost epidemic levels.   Since then, there have been cases of measles killing children, something which would most probably not have happened had the vaccination compliance not been at an all-time low.  Isn’t that absolutely crazy when one considers that measles was all but eradicated?</p>
<p>In the years between 1998 and the present, there have been numerous extremely well-designed and large studies, none of which have been able to find <em>any</em> kind of link between vaccination and autism.</p>
<p><em>To summarise this section: The research that the vaccination scare is based
on, was deeply flawed and based on corruption, not science.</em></p>
<h1 id="spreading-out-of-vaccines">Spreading out of vaccines</h1>
<p><em>This section is based on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaccine_controversy#Vaccine_overload" title="Wikipedia article on Vaccine controversy.">Wikipedia article on the general Vaccine
Controversy</a>.</em></p>
<p>In some cases, parents opt for spreading out the vaccinations, because they
mistakenly think that this is safer than not doing so.  The flawed idea that
administering all these vaccines together could be dangerous is called the
“vaccine overload hypothesis”.  It is flawed for the reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Common childhood ilnesses represent a much heavier load on the infant immune system.</li>
<li>The vaccination cocktail given currently represents less than 10% of the immunological load of the vaccinations given to children in the 80s.</li>
<li>Numerous studies have shown that the combination of vaccinations does NOT damage the infant immune system.</li>
</ul>
<p>Importantly, if you spread out vaccines, you increase the time during which your child is susceptible to the diseases that are being vaccinated again, thus greatly increasing the health risk to your child and all other children it comes into contact with.  You are a bad parent if you do this.</p>
<p><em>To summarise this section:</em> <em>Administering the vaccinations together does not damage your child’s immune system.</em> <em>Spreading out vaccines is dangerous for both your child and all children it comes into contact with.</em></p>
<h1 id="celebrities-campaigning-against-vaccination">Celebrities campaigning against vaccination</h1>
<p>Recently, a number of celebrities, most prominent of which Jenny McCarthy and
her partner Jim Carrey, supported by Oprah, have been campaigning against
vaccination.  You have to remember that these are actors and entertainers,
with almost ZERO medical or scientific background or training.   McCarthy
dropped out of nursing school to become a Playboy Bunny: There’s nothing
wrong with that, but you really cannot base important medical decisions,
concerning the health and survival of your child (!!), on the opinions of an
erstwhile nude model!</p>
<p>_To summarise: Think carefully about the scientific and medical backgrounds of
actors telling you how to care for the health and well-being of your child,
even more so when it concerns life and death issues such as vaccination.</p>
<h1 id="the-logical-conclusion">The logical conclusion</h1>
<p>To the best of our scientific knowledge, vaccinations as they are administered today are safe and do not cause autism.  In spite of this, research continues day and night to make sure of this observation.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you don’t vaccinate, the risk of your child
getting ill and dying is <em>significantly</em> higher.  If a large enough number of
you don’t vaccinate, we lose our herd immunity and then there is a very
real risk that <em>many</em> more of our children will get ill and die due to your
inaction.  Do you seriously want to take this very real risk with your <em>and</em>
my children’s lives?</p>
<h1 id="post-scriptum">Post scriptum</h1>
<p>I hope that this has helped.  If there are any issues that are not clear, or
missing, or you are not convinced, please let me know so that we can discuss
and so that I can improve this article.</p>
<h1 id="extra-resources">Extra resources</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://tallguywrites.livejournal.com/148012.html" title="Andrew Wakefield comic">Brilliant comic</a> explaining how the corrupt Andrew Wakefield managed to cause this whole debacle.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.slate.com/id/2217798/" title="aritcle in slate criticising oprah for supporting mccarthy">Article in Slate</a> criticising Oprah’s support of Jenny McCarthy.</li>
<li>Popular <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2006/feb/12/health.medicineandhealth" title="Observer article about medical backlash over vaccine scare">article in the Guardian’s Observer</a> about spreading out vaccines.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nhs.uk/chq/Pages/1034.aspx?CategoryID=68&amp;SubCategoryID=154" title="statement on the NHS on why separate vaccinations are not necessary.">Clear statement by the NHS</a> on why there is no reason to offer MMR vaccine in a spaced / spread out fashion, and that spreading out is in fact dangerous.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="updates">Updates</h1>
<ul>
<li>July 25, 2012: <a href="http://io9.com/5928722/this-graph-of-whooping-cough-cases-in-washington-state-should-scare-the-crap-out-of-you" title="io9 article with increasing incidence of whooping cough in Washington State in 2012">Whooping Cough incidence in Washington State is up by 1300% in 2012</a> relative to 2011, most probably due to the anti-vaccination movement.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>I have an official course code!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2008/05/01/i-have-an-official-course-code/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2008 09:34:16 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2008/05/01/i-have-an-official-course-code/</guid><description> I am currently designing a new master-level course at the TU Delft, creatively named Medical Visualization, and it’s just been assigned an official course code: IN4307. Whooo!
Keep an eye out for IN4307: This 5 ECTS course will run in the 3d period (February to April) of the 2008/2009 academic year and it’s going to rule. I’m integrating more modern educational techniques (thank you TU Delft BKO for the inspiration) in that the whole course will be run as an interactive workshop (I lecture, you immediately try it out on your computer machine), and assessment will be based on weekly practice exercises as well as a more extensive project that will have to be orally defended at the end.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I am currently designing a new master-level course at the TU Delft, creatively named <em>Medical Visualization</em>, and it’s just been assigned an official course code: IN4307. Whooo!</p>
<p>Keep an eye out for IN4307: This 5 ECTS course will run in the 3d period (February to April) of the 2008/2009 academic year and <strong>it’s going to rule</strong>. I’m integrating more modern educational techniques (thank you <a href="http://bko.tudelft.nl/" title="Link to TU Delft BKO">TU Delft BKO</a> for the inspiration) in that the whole course will be run as an interactive workshop (I lecture, you immediately try it out on your computer machine), and assessment will be based on weekly practice exercises as well as a more extensive project that will have to be orally defended at the end. In other words, <strong>there will be no written exam</strong>.</p>
<p>My goal is to produce <strong>frikking medical visualisation ninjas</strong> that will hit the ground running when deployed in any academic or industrial projects. I have the technology to make you <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://youtube.com/watch?v=oGECJP3phyY" title="Link to Daft Punk live performance">harder, better, faster, stronger</a>, and I’m not afraid to use it.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Slashdot Idiots</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2002/04/03/slashdot-idiots/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2002 16:44:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2002/04/03/slashdot-idiots/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Today on Slashdot:
“I’m guessing that everyone here has a valid criticism of Microsoft’s attacks on, and approach towards the Open Source model. To me, that begs the question of what we think would be an “appropriate” reaction from Microsoft towards the Open Source model…” Article here.
This always makes me grind my teeth. No, you illiterate pseudo-intellectual idiot, you can not use that phrase like that. Let me quote from &lt;https: 05=&quot;&quot; 19=&quot;&quot; 2016=&quot;&quot; begs-the-question=&quot;&quot; brians.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Today on Slashdot:</p>
<p>“I’m guessing that everyone here has a valid criticism of Microsoft’s attacks on, and approach towards the Open Source model. To me, that <strong>begs the question</strong> of what we think would be an “appropriate” reaction from Microsoft towards the Open Source model…” Article <a href="http://slashdot.org/askslashdot/02/04/02/2346210.shtml?tid=109">here</a>.</p>
<p>This always makes me grind my teeth. No, you illiterate pseudo-intellectual idiot, you can not use that phrase like that. Let me quote from &lt;https: 05=&quot;&quot; 19=&quot;&quot; 2016=&quot;&quot; begs-the-question=&quot;&quot; brians.wsu.edu=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/https:&gt; (and the same information is available from a million other places):</p>
<p>“An argument which improperly assumes as true the very point the speaker is trying to argue for is said in formal logic to ‘beg the question.’ Here is an example of a question-begging argument: ‘This painting is trash because it is obviously worthless.’ The speaker is simply asserting the worthlessness of the work, not presenting any evidence to demonstrate that this is in fact the case. Since we never use ‘begs’ with this odd meaning (‘to improperly take for granted’) in any other phrase, many people mistakenly suppose the phrase implies something quite different: that the argument demands that a question about it be asked–raises the question. <strong>If you’re not comfortable with formal terms of logic, it’s best to stay away from this phrase, or risk embarrassing yourself.</strong>“</p>
<p>(P.S. in 2018: That last bolded sentence has been replaced with: <em>Although using the expression in its original sense is now rare, using it in the newer sense will cause irritation among traditionalists</em>. Oi.)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>