<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Programming on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/programming/</link><description>Recent content in Programming on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 07:42:28 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 6 of 2024: Head Like a Hole</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</guid><description>Why do I lifelog? One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&amp;rsquo;s not form their own mind.
Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="why-do-i-lifelog">Why do  I lifelog?</h2>
<p>One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&rsquo;s not form their own mind.</p>
<p>Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</p>
<h3 id="journalling-vs-lifelogging">Journalling vs lifelogging</h3>
<p>In my view, <em>journalling</em> is a more developed form of <em>lifelogging</em>. While the latter is just the direct jotting down of happenings and noteworthy items, the former, at least to me, entails more thinking and more processing, i.e. there is more retro- and introspection going on. I would prefer to be <em>journalling</em>, because that has even more benefits, but I&rsquo;ll take <em>lifelogging</em> when I can&rsquo;t make the prerequisite time to think, and really craft my words.</p>
<p>On to the lifelog:</p>
<h2 id="monday-2024-02-05">Monday 2024-02-05</h2>
<ul>
<li>Friend LM told me about wikitree.org, which is a collaborative online family tree thingy. I tried to import the myheritage.com exported GEDCOM, but wikitree.org wants me to reject or accept each and everyone of the hundreds of people in my database. This is understandable, but it&rsquo;s also a  blocker, exacerbated by the fact that wikitree&rsquo;s matching algorithm is quite bad.</li>
<li>Casey Neistat&rsquo;s Apple Vision Pro review is insightful. See the bit from 7:20 onwards: <a href="https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440">https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440</a> &ndash; &ldquo;&hellip; This is it. This is the future of computing&hellip;&rdquo;
<ul>
<li>also see my tweet embedded below</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>NVIDIA&rsquo;s GenAI competition <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/">https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/</a>
<ul>
<li>Use TensorRT or TensorRT-LLM on Windows to build something cool, submit by Feb 23, win RTX 4090 and GTC conf attendance. EZ PZ!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Remember that life is <em>supposed</em> to be just a long sequence of problems that you need to solve.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is such a fun &quot;review&quot; of the Apple Vision Pro by Casey Neistat, but his discussion at 7:20 on the significance of the product is so spot on.<br><br>I had similar ideas about ubiquitous face-computing back in 2009: <a href="https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc">https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc</a> <a href="https://t.co/au9RBh7as0">https://t.co/au9RBh7as0</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1754421449719193753?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 5, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>










<figure><a href="avp-angry-gf.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b5f62d2dc15edfd3.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b31467e1ec255b77.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_c35fee7f6f8120f9.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-06">Tuesday 2024-01-06</h2>
<ul>
<li>Using inkscape to draw SVG glyphs which can be converted with <a href="https://react-svgr.com/">svgr</a> into React components, for my visualization project. This works so well!</li>
<li>Definitely a bit stressed about tomorrow&rsquo;s surgery. Also little throat niggle, and as if that was not enough, stomach issues due to droëwors I ate in the afternoon to preload a bit for tomorrow&rsquo;s required fasting.
<ul>
<li>Narrator: This would be followed by one of <em>the</em> worst nights in a long time, including fever chills, nausea, and so on.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>My brain keeps on jumping on ideas for 3D / VR / AR / AI friendly / native ideas for managing personal knowledge / notes
<ul>
<li>on the one hand, it feels like the atomic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten">Zettelkasten</a> approach could work well here</li>
<li>on the other, we have chunking techniques to break up documents, so that we can extract the nuggets we want in order to embed them
<ul>
<li>this chunking can be dynamic and adaptive, perhaps even going down to sentences and individual diagrams, or dynamically constructed chunks consisting of sub-chunks merged from different sources</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>in the end, will it help  or even just be interesting to be able to walk / move through / manipulate different projections of your (or someone else&rsquo;s) thoughts, possibly even connected in different ways?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-07">Wednesday 2024-01-07</h2>
<ul>
<li>Microsoft Lens makes me login every single time, and is quite temperamental
<ul>
<li>alternatives are OneDrive app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo; or Files app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At Summerhill day clinic for the excision of the morpheaform basal cell carcinoma (BCC) on my forehead
<ul>
<li>Fortunately, the doctor decided the excision on my back (with clean borders pronounced by pathology lab) does not need to be re-excised.</li>
<li>Excision of 2cm x 1.5cm patch from my forehead via <a href="https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/conditions-and-diseases/mohs-surgery">Mohs surgery</a> is successful after first attempt, happiness!</li>
<li>Reconstructive surgeon however now has a challenge: How to close up hole with no loose skin in sight? (I am a tightly wrapped person)
<ul>
<li>problem is solved with step-wise incision from the top middle of my forehead all the way down to my right temple, about 20cm in total.</li>
<li>I look like I could be the son of Frankenstein and Harry Potter</li>
<li>The care at Summerhill is beyond excellent. Now I just have to follow instructions, drink many pills, and my new friend-for-life Scar should heal up nicely.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-08">Thursday 2024-01-08</h2>
<ul>
<li>Working from home because reasons</li>
<li>I have to work hard to focus, the medication seems to affect my concentration. I will grit my teeth harder.</li>
<li>In break time, tried out <a href="https://www.modular.com/blog/mojo-sdk-v0-7-now-available-for-download">Mojo v0.7.0 (released 2024-01-25)</a> through its REPL and also just a simple <code>hello.mojo</code>, which compiled into a nice 300kB binary on this MacBook! Cautiously excited for the future of this. (also&hellip;. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Lattner">Chris Lattner</a>! 😍)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-09">Friday 2024-01-09</h2>
<ul>
<li>In the morning, got mu4e setup and working on the new MacBook, although I thought I was not going to need this mail client
<ul>
<li>What is your favourite mail client?</li>
<li>I use the Fastmail web client, mu4e for Emacs and macOS Mail, but none of them is perfect. mu4e comes close. ;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Really struggled during the day with drowsiness, although I&rsquo;m sleeping extra well every night.</li>
<li>By the end, at least was able to make demo video of my in-progress visualization project.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-10">Saturday 2024-01-10</h2>
<ul>
<li>head still feeling quite woozy</li>
<li>happy to have kids at home, and have a pretty relaxed morning</li>
<li>I would really like to write / create something today. What?</li>
<li>family tree updates
<ul>
<li>tried out ancestris, which is unusably slow on my m1pro. just getting a context menu on a person in the tree, or scrolling around, has too much lag. Tried on my Windows desktop where it&rsquo;s better but still really slow.</li>
<li>Went back to wikitree (recommended by LM) where I updated some more records (extremely laboriously).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.familysearch.org/en/">https://www.familysearch.org/en/</a> has been really useful for scans of church registers and so on, confirming more of my earlier findings.
<ul>
<li>See for example <a href="https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910">https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910</a> which just came in as I was typing this. That&rsquo;s the death notice of my paternal great grandmother in 1919, very shortly after the birth of my grandfather.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I think I might have spent too much time on this today. There&rsquo;s a bit of a dopamine rush every time you solve a mini riddle. Here also I would like to have something shareable and reusable for other members of my family. For that, wikitree, although painful, seems like a good bet.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>mind wandered at 13:30ish, of course it ended up in infinite canvases and pkm
<ul>
<li>wanted to keep on letting it wander, but also wanted to use laptop to read about freeform
<ul>
<li>Apple Freeform looks like the pretty-ok-like-notes canvas solution: <a href="https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue">https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Instead of going to bed early, experimented with round-tripping markdown to docx and back with pandoc. See tomorrow for results.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-11">Sunday 2024-01-11</h2>
<ul>
<li>Briefly tried out the new(ish) built-in <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-za/guide/iphone/iph0e5ca7dd3/ios">iOS Journal app</a>
<ul>
<li>Super nice that it taps into your activities (photos, music, workouts, etc.) and makes recommendations for packets of media you could add to a journal, all of this entirely on-device.</li>
<li>Private, encourages folks to lock the app and so on.</li>
<li>No export capability, so your journals remain utterly locked in for now.</li>
<li>Makes it easy to configure reminders that will prompt you to write  a journal at specific moments during the week.</li>
<li>Minimalistic and well-executed app, will probably get quite a few iPhone users to start journalling, but not for me. I already have too many Apple apps in my personal system that I need to use (e.g. Apple Notes) but that don&rsquo;t interoperate particularly well with other systems.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent some more time on familysearch.org creating and attaching person records (from my family) to scans of old archive documents. Also uploaded a PDF of hand-written notes made by one of my family members from the headstones on a farm on which a number of my ancestors were buried.
<ul>
<li>Two-world problem. Bringing the physical into the digital.</li>
<li><strong>familysearch really does work better than wikitree&hellip;</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>About that Two World Problem. Had some thoughts about it in the context of my personal knowledge management, but it was slightly too much for the bullets I had allocated to it, and so it become a short post titled <a href="/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/">On the two world problem and personal knowledge management</a>.
<ul>
<li>In an ideal world, I am able to publish mini posts like that on a weekly basis.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Oh wait, I also made a short post on vxlabs with the results of last night&rsquo;s pandoc experiments, titled <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/02/11/pandoc-roundtrip-from-markdown-to-docx-and-back/">Pandoc roundtrip from markdown to docx and back</a>
<ul>
<li>In this case, I went direct to Hugo markdown instead of starting in Emacs Orgmode first, in order to further reduce activation energy. This makes sense for posts I want to get published where I don&rsquo;t necessarily need the benefit of having the content integrated with my main notes database.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #236: The surprising power of consistent chipping</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/</guid><description>This 236th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the three (sorry!) weeks from Monday October 25 to Sunday November 14, 2021.
What will the beholder think? First things first: Do you notice something different about me I mean my blog?
I don&amp;rsquo;t know how most readers respond to this sort of a thing, but I can really appreciate, in a non-professional way of course, good typography on a personal blog.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This 236th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the three (sorry!)
weeks from Monday October 25 to Sunday November 14, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="facing-strand.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_c50724b8184b629d.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_b0b8092f9b20be8a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_da4f1a8a09255adf.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_c738209363b258d5.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_b0b8092f9b20be8a.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="what-will-the-beholder-think">What will the beholder think?</h2>
<p>First things first: Do you notice something different about me I mean my blog?</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know how most readers respond to this sort of a thing, but I can really
appreciate, in a non-professional way of course, good typography on a personal
blog.</p>
<p>Over the past few years I&rsquo;ve been tweaking the CSS here and there to make small
improvements to the WHV typography, but I&rsquo;ve never been really happy with the
font.</p>
<p>That is, until I ran into <a href="https://alexanderobenauer.com/">Alexander Obenauer&rsquo;s blog</a> and just new that I had to
have the same serif on mine.</p>
<p>The font is called <a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Newsreader">Newsreader</a>. I&rsquo;m currently enjoying the subtly new look, I
hope you do too.</p>
<h2 id="new-diagramming-tool-of-the-insert-suitable-period-here">New diagramming tool of the [insert suitable period here]</h2>
<p>Via Hacker News (henceforth just &ldquo;HN&rdquo;) I ran into this <a href="https://offbyone.us/posts/why-is-excalidraw-so-good/">entertaining and
charming review of a drawing tool called &ldquo;excalidraw&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>Searching a little further, I could see that it had become in a relatively
short timespan a darling of the otherwise hyper-critical HN community.</p>
<p>Personally, I&rsquo;m always on the lookout for any tools which I think could help me
visualize some of my ideas or plans better.</p>
<p>Excalidraw is great at boxes and arrows, which is fortunate, since about 95% of
my ideas and plans are based on different ways of connecting boxes and arrows.</p>
<p>As an aside: So far, I&rsquo;ve gotten by far the most use out of Notability on the
iPad (with 1st gen Apple Pencil), but I never produce as many diagrams as I
keep on imagining that I should be doing.</p>
<p>Upon first use, Excalidraw indeed struck me with how little friction it offers
to the act of sketching out <em>stuff</em>.</p>
<p>I especially like how the authors have somehow managed to merge super-easy
drawing on the computer with the production of diagrams that look like they&rsquo;ve
been made on a paper notebook, whilst still remaining fully vectorized.</p>
<p>Let me know if you&rsquo;ve used this for anything interesting, or if you have any
other diagramming tricks you&rsquo;d like to share.</p>
<h2 id="ok-rust-i-give-up">Ok Rust, I give up</h2>
<p>Back in July of 2018, in <a href="/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/#programming-language-addiction-update">WHV #148</a>, I wrote that after noting the fact that Rust
was an expression-oriented language (I love those) and subsequently reading the
O&rsquo;Reilly <em>Programming Rust</em> book, I had filed away the language under
&ldquo;re-evaluate whenever you reach for your trusty C++&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As a programming language enthusiast, I should have know that that &ldquo;filing
away&rdquo; was merely a postponement of the inevitable.</p>
<p>Recently, in hobby time, probably because I had not yet selected a new book to
read, and because I&rsquo;m going through a bit of a programming phase (err&hellip;), I
unfiled Rust and started going through some more of the materials.</p>
<p>My current feeling is: Hot durnit! Rust may just be the fastest functional
language I have access to!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing a number of the <a href="https://exercism.org/tracks/rust">exercism exercises</a>, and after often pulling out
a pattern match for compact yet readable solutions, I&rsquo;ve been getting a strong
wolf-in-sheep&rsquo;s-clothing feeling.</p>
<p>Rust brings a number of core functional programming principles to an
exceptionally performant programming platform.</p>
<p>Sometimes there are still more nuts and bolts than I would like to see (to be
expected from a systems language that wants to give you full control), but this
mix of low-level and subjectively high-level functional programming is still a
remarkable achievement in my book.</p>
<p><em>Of course</em> I have no real-world applications in mind, unless <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">Advent of Code</a>
counts, but Rust currently makes for great programming practice.</p>
<h2 id="keep-on-keeping-on">Keep on keeping on</h2>
<p>In WHV #214 I wrote about <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">writing down that One Main Thing that you&rsquo;d like to
get done every day</a>.</p>
<p>Day job is currently not entirely conducive to this mode of work, and that&rsquo;s
putting it lightly.</p>
<p>Still, on most days I do remember to select and then write that thing down.</p>
<p>Most recently, I was dragging such an item along with me for what felt like
weeks.</p>
<p>Every morning I did the Alt-W Ctrl-Y finger dance (that&rsquo;s Emacs for copy
paste), and I experienced the concomitant pang of internally facing
embarrassment.</p>
<p>Often there would be no progress (because meetings and other non-maker work),
but on some days I would excavate the equivalent of a generously filled
teaspoon of dirt. (<a href="https://youtu.be/4_C86o5dE_c">Doctor Flammond&rsquo;s tunnel</a> anybody?)</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, the Thing neared completion, until one day (weirdly still to
my pleasant surprise) it was done, never to be copy-pasted again.</p>
<p>My happy little mental note was: Just keep on dragging One Main Thing with
you. It&rsquo;s not on the list because it&rsquo;s going to get completed, but rather
because it&rsquo;s the thing that you just have to keep on chipping away at,
<em>especially</em> when progress seems almost invisible.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #235: Speed silvers</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 08:39:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/</guid><description>Welcome to the 235th edition of the (secretly bi-)Weekly Head Voices!
This one looks back at the period from Monday October 11 to Sunday October 24, 2021.
Figure 1: None of my outdoors photos satisfied the WHV guidelines, and so now you get this collage. Notable here are the two artworks by GOU #2. It looks like she has discovered one of her blisters.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the 235th edition of the (secretly bi-)Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This one looks back at the period from Monday October 11 to Sunday October
24, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="whv-235-collage.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hu_66c7a780eb198332.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hu_7244186ea1c2933d.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hu_adb03d33fa353b45.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hu_51005b0b7d7904a1.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/10/28/weekly-head-voices-235-speed-silvers/whv-235-collage_hu_7244186ea1c2933d.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: None of my outdoors photos satisfied the WHV guidelines, and so now you get this collage. Notable here are the two artworks by GOU #2. It looks like she has discovered one of her blisters."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: None of my outdoors photos satisfied the WHV guidelines, and so now you get this collage. Notable here are the two artworks by GOU #2. It looks like she has discovered one of her <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/">blisters</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="yet-another--new-keyboard-yank">(Yet Another) New Keyboard #YANK</h2>
<p>You might remember my previous semi-accidental keyboard acquisition, namely the
<a href="/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/#keyboard-update-k1">Keychron K1 with low profile brown, no I mean red!, Gateron switches all the way
back in June</a>.</p>
<p>Well, the K1 turned out to be not my favourite keyboard.</p>
<p>Perhaps a bit more surprising, at least to me, was that I only discovered a
week or so ago that the keyboard had RED low-profile switches and not BROWN as
I had ordered.</p>
<p>As everyone knows, reds are usually linear and browns usually have a tactile
bump.</p>
<p>However, this confusion, that my brain expected a tactile bump all this time
and never got one, only partially explains my not-liking of this keyboard. I
think the low profile reds have too muc bounce at the bottom for the way that I
type.</p>
<p>Anyways, this discovery came just after I had already accidentally ordered
another keyboard, namely the <a href="https://www.ctrlshiftesc.co.za/product/varmilo-va87m-charcoal/">Varmilo VA87m with Cherry MX Speed Silvers</a>.</p>
<p>The accident was partially caused by the fact that this keyboard was available
from a local retailer named inexplicably <a href="https://www.ctrlshiftesc.co.za/">Ctrl.Shift.Esc</a>, who dispatched the
board in record time. (Super happy with their service, and of course joking
about the name)</p>
<p>Having discovered that I really don&rsquo;t like the red switches in the K1 with the
new keyboard in transit, I was in trepidation that it would arrive and that I
would not like the Speed Silver linears at all&hellip;</p>
<p>Well, it came as yet another surprise (that&rsquo;s the world of mechanical keyboards
for me, it seems) that the new switches actually felt quite amazing in this new
board.</p>
<p>TaeKeyboards, a YouTube keyboard reviewer whom I rate highly and I believe many
others do too, called it <a href="https://youtu.be/7b2G2%5FosvxY">one of the best prebuilts he&rsquo;s ever reviewed</a>, so it
seems I&rsquo;m in good company.</p>
<p>I think that it&rsquo;s probably due to the sensitivity of the keys, but I tend to
swap characters (a friend from work gave me the tip to &ldquo;just type better&rdquo;
haha).</p>
<p>Other than that, my only other criticism of the board is that the backlight,
which I often need in the evenings, does not shine through the lettering on the
keycaps, a specific example where function should perhaps have triumphed over
form.</p>
<p>At this moment my fingers seem to be luxuriating on this keyboard. If they can
start &ldquo;just typing better&rdquo; soon, their owner would be pretty chuffed as well.</p>
<h2 id="programming-languages-is-this-the-best-we-can-do">Programming languages: Is this the best we can do?</h2>
<p>I really love programming.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a large part of my job, but it also often features during hobby time
(often the same languages and tools, just different projects, somehow
refreshing!).</p>
<p>That being said, I wonder if this, i.e. &ldquo;programming languages&rdquo;, is really the
best we can do in terms of enabling creative folks to construct reliable
software systems.</p>
<p>Aspects of this topic came up during a recent local meetup, where I (perhaps
ironically) presented my blog post comparing API construction using three
different programming languages, namely Python, Go and C#. (This too was the
output of a hobby project.)</p>
<p>The discussion was about the fact that it is increasingly more difficult
acquiring and especially retaining programming talent.</p>
<p>There are more issues at play here, notably the fact that remote work has
really opened up the market (this has been greatly accelerated by the
pandemic), enabling programmers from around the globe to work for employers
anywhere else on the globe.</p>
<p>Whilst I think this is a healthy development, it has really exacerbated the
effects of the scarcity of good programmers.</p>
<p>Some of my business owner friends, who really do their best to create great
working environments, are feeling this crunch.</p>
<p>As programmers on the fortunate side of this see-saw, we could just call it a
day at this point and continue cashing our pay cheques.</p>
<p>However, as science-minded humans, we should also be thinking about the larger
space of software construction.</p>
<p>While programming skills can certainly be learned, there is a certain specific
set of personality traits that is almost required to become really good at
programming.</p>
<p>My contention is that whilst these traits often correlate with programming
ability, they don&rsquo;t necessarily correlate with the broader sort of structured
creativity required to construct software systems.</p>
<p>Empowering more humans to be able to construct reliable and delightful software</p>
<p>In fact, the world of so-called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No-code%5Fdevelopment%5Fplatform">no-code</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Low-code%5Fdevelopment%5Fplatform">low-code</a> has been heating up for a
few years now and is&hellip; so hot right now. Friend and reader of this blog, who
goes by the codename of KB, works on <a href="https://journeyapps.com/">what looks like a pretty good entry in
this arena</a>.</p>
<p>Is this the conclusion of that line of evolution, or is there more that can be
explored?</p>
<p>How can software construction be further democratized? Are there perhaps
software construction modalities that we are currently completely blind to?</p>
<p>Could it be that one day (maybe even soon) that we just explain to the AI what
the new (AI) software construct should be able to do?</p>
<h2 id="the-power-of-fika">The power of fika</h2>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/Helena%5FLB">the High Priestess of Fika and #scicomm</a>, I have learned about the
amazing Swedish custom called &ldquo;fika&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It seems that in Swedish companies, employees <strong>from all levels in the
organization</strong> take a morning and afternoon break from work (called <em>fikapaus</em>
or <em>fikarast</em>) to eat cake and drink coffee <em>together</em>.</p>
<p><a href="https://hejsweden.com/en/have-coffee-breaks-called-fika-swedish/">Hej Sweden</a> tells me:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Among the consensus-oriented Swedes, fika is a great way to exchange knowledge,
opinions about what&rsquo;s going on in the company, and generally bond with your
colleagues. Resulting in better productivity for the company and better
wellbeing for each employee.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&hellip; and then drops this sweet nugget (I see what I did there):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Swedes spend in total 9.5 days each year having fika.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Besides that this sounds like great fun, I think the idea of having an
equalizing cultural institution like this where folks from all levels of the
organization get to bond in a more social setting would contribute
substantially to knowledge and culture dissemination in the organization.</p>
<p>In neurological terms, this reminds me strongly of the growing understanding of
<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29739890/">the role of long-distance, interareal connections in the brain</a>.</p>
<p>You could almost imagine your neurons having coffee and cake together every day
at 10:00 and 15:00.</p>
<p>On some days, it feels like my neurons do nothing <em>but</em> drink coffee and eat
cake the whole day, while on other days, it feels like they decided during fika
to push my analogies far too far.</p>
<p>Folks have a really great week, and please beware those exploding analogies!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #229: Staycation PERMA-Station</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 21:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/</guid><description> Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&amp;rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="bettys_jocks.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_cd0e487bf3a491b3.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_fe1fd4e1918cf601.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_da4cbb1337c453aa.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_a75b8a71c1ebf5a5.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_fe1fd4e1918cf601.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the week from Monday July 19 to Sunday
July 25, 2021, a week of untold wonders and intense enjoyment, a week deserving
of the hallowed title of&hellip; <em>STAYCATION!</em></p>
<p>Jokes aside, it was a perfectly enjoyable week of time off, most of it spent at
home or close to it.</p>
<p>We spent time together, took care of hobby- and side-projects, and even had
time to daydream and come up with some wacky ideas which should probably never
see the light of day, but which one day just might.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-1-dot-3-released">Lazar Focus 1.3 released</h2>
<p>On the evening of Tuesday, July 20, after a flurry of programming and testing,
<a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2021/07/21/lazar-focus-1.3.0-released-real-time-focus-feedback/">Lazar Focus 1.3 was released</a>.</p>
<p>Noteworthy is its new ability to measure and give real-time feedback on your
current focus, as an easy to interpret percentage.</p>
<p>The more you resist distractions, the higher the focus percentage.</p>
<p>When developing this feature, I ended up selecting a 5 minute rolling window,
after I was initially planning a pomodoro length. Five minutes seem to be a
sort of sweet spot in terms of seeing one&rsquo;s distractions affect one&rsquo;s score,
but not having it immediately distroyed, so that there&rsquo;s still time to recover.</p>
<p>I wanted to mention here the interesting disconnect between the programming I
do for this completely disconnected hobby project in a language (Pascal-ish)
that I don&rsquo;t particularly prefer but don&rsquo;t mind on the one hand, and my day
job, for which I sometimes still get to program, on the other.</p>
<h2 id="perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA: The five building blocks of well-being</h2>
<p>So yeah, there&rsquo;s a pretty interesting disconnect&hellip;</p>
<p>Writing code for LF, in this case perhaps perhaps noteworthy the real-time
focus tracking data-structure, namely a run-length encoded series of (no)focus
time durations that automatically get truncated, lengthened and pruned as time
progresses, was 100% fun and relaxation.</p>
<p>This is not the most tricky thing to implement, but the process of first
cooking it up in my brain, and then later sitting down to implement it, and
seeing it work, was just challenging enough to result in several periods of
complete immersion in, or engagement with, the task.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Flourish-Visionary-Understanding-Happiness-Well-being/dp/1439190763/ref=sr%5F1%5F6?dchild=1&amp;qid=1627409990&amp;refinements=p%5F27%3AMartin+Seligman&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-6">Martin Seligman&rsquo;s book titled <em>Flourish</em></a>, which I&rsquo;m slowly working through
at the moment (he is a great and impactful psychologist, but perhaps not the
world&rsquo;s greatest story teller, sorry Prof Seligman), he explains that human
<a href="https://ppc.sas.upenn.edu/learn-more/perma-theory-well-being-and-perma-workshops">well-being, or flourishing, consists of five building blocks, namely</a>:</p>
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion: gratitude, savouring the present, hope and optimism,</li>
<li>Engagement: Lose oneself in a challenging (err) task,</li>
<li>Relationships: Love and be loved by friends and family,</li>
<li>Meaning: belonging to and serving some cause greater than oneself and</li>
<li>Accomplishment: Pursuing achievement and mastery for its own sake.</li>
</ol>
<p>My little LF programming exercise was <em>exactly</em> right for triggering a bit of
item number 2, namely engagement.</p>
<p>I am happy that I could slip a little PERMA in here on the back of Lazar Focus,
a little tool that is also proving useful in ways that I did not expect. ;)
Although the book is not the easiest going, it makes some valuable points if
you too are a fan of well-being.</p>
<h2 id="pfizer-jab-1-in-da-pocket">Pfizer jab #1 IN DA POCKET</h2>
<p>I really loves me some cutting edge science.</p>
<p>I know that the mRNA vaccines have been in development for decades now, but
they still represent such an amazing technological flex.</p>
<p>How fantastic is it that some of our cleverest humans have designed and tested
<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/different-vaccines/mrna.html">this vaccine that consists of usually unstable mRNA</a>, to be injected into human
cells where our the cellular machinery in our bodies will dutifully follow the
mRNA instructions to frikking synthesise and display a piece of spike protein
that looks enough like the COVID-19 spike protein so that our immune system
will notice and immediately start creating antibodies, all without us actually
getting infected.</p>
<p>As if that&rsquo;s not enough, the introduced mRNA is broken down ASAP after
synthesis.</p>
<p>HOT DAMN we live in the future and it&rsquo;s pretty awesome up here!</p>
<p>I AM EXCITE</p>
<p>I am also really happy with the super efficient walk-in vaccination procedure at the Town Hall here in Somerset West.</p>
<p>I would have been in and out in 30 minutes with Pfizer jab #1 had I not run
into and started chatting with friends in the side-effect waiting area.</p>
<p>Kudos to the Western Cape for running this like the Star Trek medical bay.</p>
<p>Still friends, how strange are the days that we find ourselves in?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #218: Back to the future</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/29/weekly-head-voices-218-back-to-the-future/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 21:41:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/29/weekly-head-voices-218-back-to-the-future/</guid><description>WELL HELLO DERE FRIENDS!
Welcome to the Weekly Head Voices #218, looking back at the week from Monday March 22 to Sunday March 28 of the year 2021.
Figure 1: A little forest on Vergelegen farm, close to where we had just enjoyed an absolutely fabulous Sunday lunch, with wine.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>WELL HELLO DERE FRIENDS!</p>
<p>Welcome to the Weekly Head Voices #218, looking back at the week from Monday
March 22 to Sunday March 28 of the year 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="vergelegen_somewhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/29/weekly-head-voices-218-back-to-the-future/vergelegen_somewhere_hu_24d3a75a08bba2e0.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/29/weekly-head-voices-218-back-to-the-future/vergelegen_somewhere_hu_b26d03a2071cc9f4.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/29/weekly-head-voices-218-back-to-the-future/vergelegen_somewhere_hu_3a2c7f0493b32378.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/29/weekly-head-voices-218-back-to-the-future/vergelegen_somewhere_hu_2928f7b46bee31d8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/29/weekly-head-voices-218-back-to-the-future/vergelegen_somewhere_hu_b26d03a2071cc9f4.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A little forest on Vergelegen farm, close to where we had just enjoyed an absolutely fabulous Sunday lunch, with wine."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A little forest on Vergelegen farm, close to where we had just enjoyed an absolutely fabulous Sunday lunch, with wine.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="two-worlds-collide">Two worlds collide!</h2>
<p>On the one hand I do worry about the number of hours I spent on this, but on
the other hand it&rsquo;s one of those time investments that should pay off
handsomely over the coming years.</p>
<p>My dream is that one day we&rsquo;ll have an organizational knowledge management
system in place that will enable the almost effortless creation, maintenance
and especially the effective retrieval of relevant documentation.</p>
<p>Because the organization in question lives in the Microsoft ecosystem, the
first laborious steps I have been taking were figuring out the various ways of
getting technical documentation from the hands of engineers all the way into
the company SharePoint.</p>
<p>(I hope you can forgive me, Charl of the past&hellip; I do have my reasons.)</p>
<p>Here I would like to share just one of the many dirty tricks I&rsquo;ve learned so
far: The easiest way to host a static (Hugo) web site on SharePoint, and hence
having it fully indexed by Microsoft Search, is simply to dump the whole thing
into any modern site&rsquo;s <code>Site Assets</code> library, but only after renaming all html
files to aspx.</p>
<p>As soon as I can get <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/powershell/sharepoint/sharepoint-pnp/sharepoint-pnp-cmdlets?view=sharepoint-ps">PnP PowerShell</a> to push updates to full sites a bit more
quickly, I&rsquo;ll hopefully be able to hook it up to <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/devops/pipelines/get-started/what-is-azure-pipelines">Azure pipelines</a>.</p>
<p>Engineers write markdown, documentation magically appear on company SharePoint!</p>
<h2 id="let-s-keep-it-compact">Let&rsquo;s keep it compact</h2>
<p>On Thursday November 14, 2019 at 17:48 I made a mental note, where by &ldquo;mental&rdquo;
I mean &ldquo;in my Emacs&rdquo;, to prefer <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zstandard">Zstandard (or zstd) compression</a> for everything,
based on a number of posts I had read when I was actually intending to look
into when xz should be preferred over bz2.</p>
<p>In the meantime, zstd&rsquo;s compression ratios, along with its multi-threaded
compression speed and especially its decompression speed, have helped me more
than once, which is why I&rsquo;m mentioning it here.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s the 2 second guide:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a"># compress using as many threads as there are CPU cores</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>tar cf - giant_directory <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> zstd -T0 -o giant_directory.tar.zst
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a"># decompress REALLY TERRIBLY QUICKLY</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>zstd -dc giant_directory.tar.zst <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> tar x
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>You can even get zstd to train on your type of data in order to build up a
domain-specific compression dictionary!</p>
<h2 id="can-type-systems-catch-bugs-science-says-yes">Can type systems catch bugs? Science says yes!</h2>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://forum.nim-lang.org/t/7705#48894">this forum post by Araq, the creator of the Nim programming language</a>,
I read <a href="https://earlbarr.com/publications/typestudy.pdf">this conference paper</a> describing this really neat research project where
the researchers retroactively type-annotated a random selection of publically
available bugs in un-typed JavaScript code, and then showed that about 15% of
of those bugs would have been caught.</p>
<p>In their words:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Evaluating static type systems against public bugs, which have survived testing
and review, is conservative: it understates their effectiveness at detecting
bugs during private development, not to mention their other benefits such as
facilitating code search/completion and serving as documentation. Despite this
uneven playing field, our central finding is that both static type systems find
an important percentage of public bugs: both Flow 0.30 and TypeScript 2.0
successfully detect 15%!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I found the simple but quite solid experimental methodology in the paper
delightful, over and above the fact that this is a great one to have in my
database for arguments about the utility of type systems.</p>
<p>(This would possibly have made dynamic-type-slinging Charl from the past go red
in the face.)</p>
<h2 id="science-doesn-t-give-a-s-t-about-my-beliefs-either">Science doesn&rsquo;t give a s***t about my beliefs either</h2>
<p>That makes for two (2) points in this short blog post that would have caused
Charl from the past to get <em>quite</em> unhappy.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s science for you folks: Reality develops, or it just stands there, really
really still, and/or observations yield new data, and then all of your models
have to be updated!</p>










<figure><a href="science_and_your_beliefs.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/29/weekly-head-voices-218-back-to-the-future/science_and_your_beliefs.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="forerunner-hot-takes">Forerunner hot takes</h2>
<p>The more-or-less free <a href="/2018/07/24/weekly-head-voices-149/#the-apple-watch-vitality-and-you">Apple Watch 3 that I acquired in July of 2018</a> has served
me really well over the years, but for mysterious reasons that I can&rsquo;t explain,
the time had come to upgrade to a <em>real</em> running watch.</p>
<p>After weeks of reading reviews, creating little comparison tables and
complaining to friend LM about the utterly devious way in which Garmin has
segmented their market into tiny little pieces with frustrating borders, I
finally settled on <a href="https://www.dcrainmaker.com/2019/04/garmin-forerunner-245-music-gps-watch-in-depth-review.html">the Garmin Forerunner 245 (without music)</a>.</p>
<p>I made sure that the watch would be delivered this past Friday so that I could
take it for a spin or two over the weekend.</p>
<p>My first observations are:</p>
<ul>
<li>One really notices all of the Apple polish when you have to give it up. It&rsquo;s
clear that the Forerunner is a robust tool for running, but heck is it
klunky. Every time I push one of the four physical buttons, I imagine the
watch going &ldquo;hooooonk!&rdquo;.</li>
<li>The device includes a whole bunch of advanced-looking new-to-me metrics by
<a href="https://www.firstbeat.com/">FirstBeat</a> (recently acquired by Garmin) like Stress measurement, the Body
Battery (taking into account sleep and stress to predict how much energy you
should have), advanced recovery time (this is pretty useful: how many hours
before my next run, based on how hard the previous one was, stress levels and
also on sleep quality in the meantime) and so on.
<ul>
<li>I knew about FirstBeat because the <a href="/2017/02/03/weekly-head-voices-115/#the-dutch-watch">TomTom Runner 3</a> I had before the Apple
Watch 3 used <a href="https://www.firstbeat.com/en/science-and-physiology/fitness-level/">their VO2 max estimation algorithm</a>. However, what I <strong>just</strong>
learned was that specifically <a href="https://www.firstbeat.com/en/blog/what-is-heart-rate-variability-hrv/">heart rate variability (HRV)</a> seems to play an
important role in much of FirstBeat&rsquo;s work.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I now have an optical <a href="https://www8.garmin.com/manuals/webhelp/forerunner245/EN-US/GUID-2EE28BB8-91F1-4BCE-AE13-6CAEF50AD5C4.html">pulse oximeter</a> on my arm, which, although far from
accurate, does give at least some estimate of my blood oxygen. This is
important to me especially to ensure that that aspect of my sleep is also
going as it should.</li>
<li>About that sleep tracking&hellip; the sleep onset detection must be a bit of an
embarrassment for at least some of the folks at Garmin. For example, last
night the watch detected onset of sleep while it was lying on the bedside
table during my pre-bedtime shower. Surely with that HR and PulseOx sensor,
the watch should know that it&rsquo;s not even on my arm? Apple Watch 3 does this
with 100% accuracy with only its HR sensor. (To add insult to injury, the
Garmin detected that onset an hour before my configured bedtime.)</li>
<li>On the other hand, the battery life on this thing is, as is to be expected
from a Garmin, quite phenomenal. (this is probably partly due to all of the
half-implemented algorithms haha)</li>
<li>More generally speaking, I&rsquo;ve disabled most of the notification features, so
that the thing on my arm is more like an old-fashioned, mild-mannered watch
that transforms into super-watch when running-related activities have to be
undertaken. That in itself is an improvement that is not to be sneezed at.</li>
<li>In summary: Acknowledging the multitude of biases at play, I am really
enjoying the new device. In addition, my Apple Watch 3 could hereby enter the
family pool, freeing up another AW3 which now lives on the proud arm of my
first running GOU.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="pompiedom">Pompiedom</h2>
<p>Thank you folks for reading these words, and especially for reconstituting
thoughts that are probably similar to the ones that happened at my end before
and during the production of said words.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;re more than welcome to add some words of your own in the comments section
below. (I literally installed and configured it for you. No pressure
though. You know me.)</p>
<p>On that note (specifically the note of adding your own words): A part of my
brain has been entertaining the idea of setting up a <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/what-is-discord?IR=T">discord server</a> called <em>The
Church of Love and Science and/or Friends of Charl</em>.</p>
<p>The brain part in question claims that it would be a place for friends, and for
any other fans of Love and Science, to hang out and sometimes make interesting
new connections, and to enjoy the existing ones.</p>
<p>What do you think?</p>
<p>Err, let me know in the comments, or via Signal, or via discord?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #148: Data stylist.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 07:22:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/</guid><description> Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)
This post covers the week from Monday July 9 to Sunday July 15.
The business part of my week was unfairly dominated by far too much after-work obsessing over programming languages, with which I seem to have an unhealthy (or perhaps not) obsession.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/drakenstein_trail.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/drakenstein_trail-1024x241.jpg"
        
            alt="Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Ridiculously fun trail in Paarl somewhere. (Photo taken by Trail Friend #1. Trail Friend #2 cropped from picture, because no permission to appear on the internets!)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This post covers the week from Monday July 9 to Sunday July 15.</p>
<p>The business part of my week was unfairly dominated by far too much after-work obsessing over programming languages, with which I seem to have an unhealthy (or perhaps not) obsession.</p>
<p>I will externalise some of these thoughts further down in this post.</p>
<p>I’m starting with a weekend / running update, which should be reasonably safe for non-nerds to read. However, after that, the nerd dial will go up to 11 with stuff about tools and programming languages right up to the end of the post.</p>
<p>I would have wanted to use the adjective “face-melting”, but I’m not sure if any intensity of nerdery could ever reach that level.</p>
<p>We can dream.</p>
<h1 id="weekend-running-update">Weekend running update</h1>
<p>Most fortunately the weekend had other plans and supplied us with at least 2.5 parties, the first of which even culminated in a <em>ridiculously</em> fun trail run in the mountains on the winter morning after.</p>
<p>The winter morning sun was just perfect, the company was great, and I had forgotten all forms of performance tracking devices at home.</p>
<p>Readers with bionic eyes might notice the Lunas on my feet.</p>
<p>I have now ran just over 260km in them, but, in a surprise twist to the regular readers of this blog, my biological equipment has still not yet completely adjusted to the new style of locomotion.</p>
<p>The latest victim seems to be one of Tom, Dick and Harry, the tendons running under the medial <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malleolus">malleolus</a> of my left foot, also known as that big knob on your inside ankle. Tom (the primary suspect in this case according to Trail Friend #1 who is knowledgable with regard to these matters, being a running foot surgeon and all), Dick and Harry <a href="https://radiopaedia.org/articles/posterior-ankle-tendons-mnemonic">are also known as the *T*ibialis posterior, flexor *D*igitorum longus and the flexor *H*allucis longus</a>.</p>
<p>They currently have to work extra hard to stabilise my feet while running, because, you know, no shoes.</p>
<p>Because doing this thing was not hard enough already, and because the Lunas are perhaps still a bit too cushiony, and because my friend the Very Flat Cat forgot that I’m very suggestible after 11:00 in the morning when my prefrontal cortex takes the rest of the day off, I am now also the very shy owner of a pair of <a href="https://xeroshoes.com/shop/genesis/genesis-men/">Xero Genesis running sandals</a>:</p>
<p><img src="https://xeroshoes.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/Genesis_Limeade-3-4-770x500.jpg" alt="Image result for xero genesis"></p>
<p>The soles are only 5mm thick, and quite hard, being <a href="https://xeroshoes.com/warranty/">rated for a few thousand miles</a> and all. The upshot of this is that one’s feet have to work even harder than in the Lunas.</p>
<p>My first run in these was amazing: I could feel my feet reacting to every little pebble, and my running style having to adapt even more to the terrain.</p>
<p>However, there was a price to pay for all of that additional terrain feel (and the fact that I took a much longer maiden run than I should have): The next day, the tendons in my feet felt even more (ab)used than usual.</p>
<p>WITH GREAT POWER COMES GREAT RESPONSIBILITY, it seems.</p>
<p>Due to these shoes being so powerful, I have had to resign to introducing Xero running far more gradually than I had initially thought.</p>
<h1 id="vacation-based-thinking-driven-tool-sharpening-aka-the-wvv-2018-data-science-toolboxtm">Vacation-based-thinking-driven tool sharpening aka The WVV 2018 Data Science Toolbox(tm).</h1>
<p>During the <a href="/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/">previously blogged-about</a> Mpumalanga vacation, the lack of alarms, devices, and other work accoutrements, resulted in there being ample time for staring-into-space-grade thinking sessions.</p>
<p>During one of these thinking sessions, I realised that I had somehow neglected my data science toolbox for a while.</p>
<p>At some point a few years back, I was so into ipython notebooks (what has now become jupyter) that I used them as my main work lab notes modality.</p>
<p>However, in the meantime I had fallen slightly out of love with the computational notebook style of data programming, because I had begun to develop doubts about their role in the analysis pipeline.</p>
<p><strong>interlude 1:</strong> <em>jupyter notebooks are nice for initial data exploration, and they’re especially useful for remote computation with embedded graphics. However, that initial momentum of discovery risks devolving into an unwieldy monolith of code snippets, data transformations and experiments. There’s a fine line to be walked between flexible experimentation on the one hand, and version-controlled, time-stamped, permutational and scientific rigour on the other.</em></p>
<p><strong>interlude 2:</strong> <em>I have to apologise for using the term “data science” in a non-comedic context. In spite of the inherent humour, it has turned into a usable blanket term for computational data understanding.</em></p>
<p>Due to my growing doubts in the order of Jupyter, and due to being occupied with less traditionally data sciencey work projects, I had unfortunately let my data science toolbox gather perhaps a bit too much dust.</p>
<p>Slightly more worrying than falling out of love with the Jupyter Notebooks (I still like them, I’m just not that madly in love anymore), was the more specific issue that I’d even let the datavis parts get a bit dusty.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Although I should probably write a more complete post about this, here is the list of ingredients of the official <em><strong>2018 WHV Data Science Toolbox(tm)</strong></em>:</p>
<h2 id="programming-language-and-library-ecosystem-python">Programming language and library ecosystem: Python.</h2>
<p>This language, in spite of its shortcomings, <em>dominates</em> the data science / machine learning world thanks to its STELLAR ecosystem.</p>
<p>numpy, pandas, scipy, scikit-*, tensorflow, pytorch, keras, cython… this snowball has turned into a pretty sizeable planet.</p>
<p>For this reason, it would be hard to justify any other choice for data science.</p>
<p>However, since I’ve been seeing more of Lisp and the rest of the ever-expanding programming language landscape, I can see (Python’s shortcomings as a programming language) clearly now.</p>
<p>In terms of interactive programming, Python beats the majority of practical programming languages, with Common Lisp being one notable exception.</p>
<p>However, it’s not functional enough, which engenders unnecessarily imperative, side-effecting code.  More specifically, it’s not expression-oriented.</p>
<p>More about this slightly further down. Maybe.</p>
<h2 id="datavis-anything-as-long-as-its-vega-or-vega-lite">Datavis: Anything, as long as it’s Vega or Vega-Lite.</h2>
<p>I spent a few years of my life wrangling <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a>, down to INNARD-LEVEL.</p>
<p>Mike Bostock’s idea of <a href="https://bost.ocks.org/mike/join/">data-element-joins</a> is genius, and internalising it was intellectually satisfying.</p>
<p>I thought that these d3 skillz would serve me well for decades (that’s WEEKS in javascript-time), but it turns out that there’s a new, even smarter kid in town.</p>
<p>(if it’s any consolation, the new kid can be considered the grand-child of d3.js.)</p>
<p><a href="https://vega.github.io/">vega and vega-lite</a> are so-called visualization grammars, or visualization DSLs (domain specific languages).</p>
<p>The upshot is that one codes up a chart, or a whole set of linked charts and their interactive behaviour, using a language that was designed for this purpose.</p>
<p>This chart code can be easily shared, or converted into interactive visual representations that can be embedded in applications, online or in print quality documents.</p>
<p>Genius!</p>
<p>With <a href="https://altair-viz.github.io/">Altair</a>, you can even send your pandas dataframes to vega and vega-lite charts all from the comfort of your slightly defective Python armchair.</p>
<h2 id="development-environment-pycharm">Development Environment: PyCharm.</h2>
<p>You knew it was not going to be Jupyter Notebooks, but you probably expected it to be <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tag/emacs/">Emacs</a>.</p>
<p>Well it’s not. Surprise!</p>
<p>The remote interpreter support in PyCharm enables me to connect to a Python virtual environment anywhere on the planet, which I often do.</p>
<p>The JetBrains wizards have optimised the remote communication of code intelligence, so completion, documentation and general code understanding is almost indistinguishable from that on a completely local project.</p>
<p>Being able to step through a <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/12/08/variational-autoencoder-in-pytorch-commented-and-annotated/"><em>remote</em> PyTorch neural network training iteration with the PyCharm debugger</a> or any other remote Python algorithmics is insightful.</p>
<p>Two notable drawbacks are visualization and long-running jobs.</p>
<p>For the long-running jobs I do tend to use Jupyter Notebooks or when at all possible <a href="https://mosh.org/">mosh</a>, which is amazing. However, because the primary modality is not the notebook, my code is versioned and organised into separate libraries which I can call into from notebook or mosh.</p>
<p>For visualization, it’s either connecting to the altair chart server via SSH pipe, dumping the chart to the unison-synced project, and/or a Jupyter Notebook.</p>
<h2 id="the-rest">The rest.</h2>
<p>Of course you use Postgres on an SSD for your data, and of course you know enough SQL to make short work of most of the heavy-weight transformations often required at the start your data crunching pipeline.</p>
<p>For all of my lab notes, reports, books, papers and blog posts, I use <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tag/orgmode/">Emacs Org mode</a>.</p>
<p>LaTeX math with live preview, live code snippets, SVG graphics, bibtex references, export to anything. This is one of the best ways to document your science.</p>
<h1 id="programming-language-addiction-update">Programming language addiction update.</h1>
<p>I spend far too much obsessing over programming languages, old and new.</p>
<p>For the past two weeks, I wasted even more precious time than usual reading up about programming languages.</p>
<p>Because I would really like to spend more of my time on other, perhaps more valuable activities, I’ve been trying to better define what it is I’m actually looking for.</p>
<p>Of course there is no single best programming language, but a whole set of good languages that map in intricate ways to different problem domains.</p>
<p>In spite of this, I have been pining for a language with, in order of importance:</p>
<ol>
<li>A Functional Programming DNA, with which I’m referring to a) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expression-oriented_programming_language">expression-orientedness</a>, b) a preference for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pure_function">pure functions</a>, and at a higher level, c) the modelling of reality as more or less explicit dataflows.</li>
<li>Interactive programming, with Common Lisp being the textbook example of this.</li>
<li>Great tooling and IDEs, meaning first-class support by something from JetBrains, Microsoft or Emacs.</li>
<li>Great concurrency and parallelism stories.</li>
<li>A great library ecosystem.</li>
<li>Modest memory use.</li>
</ol>
<p>Having just explicitly written this down for the first time (!! – it was consuming so much glucose just being kept amorphously swirling around in my brain) I can now mentally map some of my most recent language dalliances to these points.</p>
<h2 id="go">go</h2>
<p>This language is far too simple for my taste, but probably really great for teams.</p>
<p>I did recently take a more serious look when <a href="https://tutorials.botsfloor.com/develop-your-own-telegram-bot-with-golang-and-tbot-de726883b83c">setting up a telegram bot using tbot</a> and being amazed at how simple it was building web services like these using goroutines and channels.</p>
<p>Go satisfies points 3 to 6 from the list above. Makes sense that I decided to file this experiment away under “check when you need to put a webservice together REALLY QUICKLY”.</p>
<h2 id="rust">rust</h2>
<p>When I saw up that rust, surprisingly, is an expression-oriented language, I flew through the O’Reilly Programming Rust book I had bought previously as part of a bundle.</p>
<p>Evaluating rust by the list above, we award it a fractional 1 because expression-oriented, 3 due to jetbrains plugin amongst others, 4(ish) – great memory safety, but compared to clojure, concurrency and parallelism stories still have much room to grow, a solid 5 thanks to cargo and a very strong 6.</p>
<p>I filed this one away under “re-evaluate whenever you reach for your trusty C++”. (also, <a href="https://github.com/actix/actix-web">actix-web</a> looks amazing for super high performance microservices.)</p>
<h2 id="f">f#</h2>
<p>You didn’t see this one coming, did you?</p>
<p>Very strong 1 to 5 and a solid 6.</p>
<p>WAT?!</p>
<p>I’m currently working my way through <a href="https://pragprog.com/book/swdddf/domain-modeling-made-functional">Domain Modeling Made Functional</a> by Scott Wlaschin, who is also the author of the brilliant <a href="https://fsharpforfunandprofit.com/">f# for fun and profit</a> website.</p>
<p>In addition to f# hitting all 6 of my 2018 PL-requirements above, I’m slowly starting to see the advantages of having a real type system under the hood.</p>
<p>f# is a member of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ML_(programming_language)">ML-family</a> of functional languages, which have their origin in Lisp (some very naughty person removed all of the lovely parentheses I’m afraid…).</p>
<p>I hope that at some point I’ll have the opportunity to use f# in anger, at which point I’ll be able to report more concretely as to its suitability.</p>
<h1 id="the-end">The End</h1>
<p>Let me know in the comments what you think about any of this, or anything else.</p>
<p>I hope to meet you again in a few days, here or elsewhere.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>(more) music for programming</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/19/more-music-for-programming/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 12:38:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/19/more-music-for-programming/</guid><description>Currently listening to Chris Sneddon’s mix on musicForProgramming();
For this last hour it has been exactly the right levels of everything to drown out distractions from my surroundings whilst not acting as a distraction in itself.
(Yes, I’m doing small status updates here now. It’s an experiment.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Currently listening to <a href="http://datashat.net/music_for_programming_32-chris_seddon.mp3">Chris Sneddon’s mix</a> on <a href="http://musicforprogramming.net/">musicForProgramming();</a></p>
<p>For this last hour it has been exactly the right levels of everything to drown out distractions from my surroundings whilst not acting as a distraction in itself.</p>
<p>(Yes, I’m doing small status updates here now. It’s an experiment.)</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Swapping variables without a temporary</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2003/06/19/swapping-variables-without-a-temporary/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2003 18:00:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2003/06/19/swapping-variables-without-a-temporary/</guid><description>This is from the first recipe in my brand-new Python cookbook. It&amp;rsquo;s quite obvious, but it hasn&amp;rsquo;t really struck me before. Well doh.
In most languages, swapping the values in two variables means using an intermediate temporary variable, e.g.:
int a = 1; int b = 2; int temp; temp = a; a = b; b = temp; With the tuple packing and unpacking in Python however, we don&amp;rsquo;t need no steenking temporary variables!
a = 1 b = 2 b, a = a, b Obviously this principle scales to any number of variables, e.g.:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This is from the first recipe in my brand-new Python cookbook. It&rsquo;s quite
obvious, but it hasn&rsquo;t really struck me before. Well doh.</p>
<p>In most languages, swapping the values in two variables means using an
intermediate temporary variable, e.g.:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-c++" data-lang="c++"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">int</span> a <span style="color:#0550ae">=</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">1</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">int</span> b <span style="color:#0550ae">=</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">2</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">int</span> temp<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>temp <span style="color:#0550ae">=</span> a<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>a <span style="color:#0550ae">=</span> b<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>b <span style="color:#0550ae">=</span> temp<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>With the tuple packing and unpacking in Python however, we don&rsquo;t need no steenking temporary variables!</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><span style="display:flex;"><span>a <span style="color:#0550ae">=</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">1</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>b <span style="color:#0550ae">=</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">2</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>b<span style="color:#1f2328">,</span> a <span style="color:#0550ae">=</span> a<span style="color:#1f2328">,</span> b
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Obviously this principle scales to any number of variables, e.g.:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-python" data-lang="python"><span style="display:flex;"><span>a<span style="color:#1f2328">,</span> b<span style="color:#1f2328">,</span> c<span style="color:#1f2328">,</span> d <span style="color:#0550ae">=</span> d<span style="color:#1f2328">,</span> c<span style="color:#1f2328">,</span> b<span style="color:#1f2328">,</span> a
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>*sniff* That&rsquo;s just so sweet.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Python new-style objects and __slots__</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2003/06/16/python-new-style-objects-and-__slots__/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2003 17:37:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2003/06/16/python-new-style-objects-and-__slots__/</guid><description>This should be very useful:
In [5]: class oldObject: ...: ....def __init__(self): ...: ........self.someVar = 1 ...: In [6]: o1 = oldObject() In [7]: o1.someVar = 2 In [8]: o1.someOtherVar = 3 This is of course expected behaviour. Have a look at this though:
In [9]: class newObject(object): ...: ....__slots__ = [&amp;#39;someVar&amp;#39;] ...: ....def __init__(self): ...: ........self.someVar = 1 ...: In [10]: o2 = newObject() In [11]: o2.someVar = 2 In [12]: o2.someOtherVar = 3 AttributeError: &amp;#39;newObject&amp;#39; object has no attribute &amp;#39;someOtherVar&amp;#39; Neat huh? In short, deriving from the new Python class object means you have a &amp;ldquo;new-style&amp;rdquo; object. Amongs other things, this means that you can define a __slots__ list which will prevent the use of attributes not in that list. These objects are available from Python 2.2 onwards.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This should be very useful:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>In [5]: class oldObject:
   ...: ....def __init__(self):
   ...: ........self.someVar = 1
   ...:
In [6]: o1 = oldObject()
In [7]: o1.someVar = 2
In [8]: o1.someOtherVar = 3
</code></pre><p>This is of course expected behaviour. Have a look at this though:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>In [9]: class newObject(object):
   ...: ....__slots__ = [&#39;someVar&#39;]
   ...: ....def __init__(self):
   ...: ........self.someVar = 1
   ...:
In [10]: o2 = newObject()
In [11]: o2.someVar = 2
In [12]: o2.someOtherVar = 3
AttributeError: &#39;newObject&#39; object has no attribute &#39;someOtherVar&#39;
</code></pre><p>Neat huh? In short, deriving from the new Python class <code>object</code> means you have
a &ldquo;new-style&rdquo; object. Amongs other things, this means that you can define a
<code>__slots__</code> list which will prevent the use of attributes not in that
list. These objects are available from Python 2.2 onwards.</p>
<p>No, my books haven&rsquo;t arrived yet. :)</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>