<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Mother Nature on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/mother-nature/</link><description>Recent content in Mother Nature on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2011 12:38:43 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/mother-nature/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Coffee addiction potpourri. [Weekly Head Voices #57]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/09/18/coffee-addiction-potpourri-weekly-head-voices-57/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2011 12:38:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/09/18/coffee-addiction-potpourri-weekly-head-voices-57/</guid><description>Yes boys and girls, I was keeping back writing that Rebecca Black post, but now it’s 4 days later and I can let ‘er rip again, like I promised. This week’s post sort of reflects my week 37: Chock-full of super-dense life nuggets. Hmmm, sounds like a brilliant new high energy meta-physical chocolate bar that would probably be immediately declared illegal by the current conservative and non-thinking (excuse the tautology) batch of spineless politicians (excuse the tautology).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Yes boys and girls, I was keeping back writing <a href="/2011/09/14/rebecca-black-is-ok-weekly-head-voices-56/" title="Rebecca Black post">that Rebecca Black post</a>, but now it’s 4 days later and I can let ‘er rip again, like I promised. This week’s post sort of reflects my week 37: Chock-full of super-dense life nuggets. Hmmm, sounds like a brilliant new high energy meta-physical chocolate bar that would probably be immediately declared illegal by the current conservative and non-thinking (excuse the tautology) batch of spineless politicians (excuse the tautology).</p>
<p>Let’s get today’s life lessons started with Mitch Hedberg, Comic Genius (note the captital C, and the capital G):</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u6xaj2fC1jI?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Hedberg’s genius unfortunately could not save him from drug addiction and his overdose-related death in 2005.</p>
<p>On the topic of addiction, <a href="http://fpixel.wordpress.com/" title="fpixel website">fpixel</a> forwarded <a href="http://www.dutchdailynews.com/drinking-coffee-genes/">these new findings that coffee drinking is genetic</a>, both in terms of capacity and perhaps also in terms of addiction. Even my atoms are addicted to coffee, so that feels about right. What’s really interesting however, is that the documented study found that the genes involved in the metabolism of coffee (CYPIA1 and NRCAM, if I understand correctly) are also related to the onset of Parkinson’s disease. You see, coffee drinkers are less prone to Parkinson’s disease (<a href="/2011/07/02/the-monthly-weekly-head-voices-50/" title="a previous WHV including some coffee health tidbits">as well as a whole list of other diseases</a> including prostate cancer, type 2 diabetes and liver cancer). However, past studies of course show correlation and not causation, i.e. coffee drinking and low risk of disease X appear together, but that does not tell us anything about what causes what. This new study has made the first steps towards understanding the mechanism that actually links Parkinson’s disease and coffee drinking.</p>
<p>On the topic of coffee <em>and</em> addiction, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="abbreviations page">TNR</a> and I spent the Monday morning working (like animals) on our new parallel startup (there, I said it) at the <a href="http://www.coffeecompany.nl/" title="Coffee Company website">Coffee Company</a> in Delft. Two things:</p>
<ol>
<li>The Coffee Company makes a killer cappuccino. The milk is steamed to perfection, but it’s got the perfect espresso bomb exploding through all that milky goodness at just the right moment. BAM! HELLO THERE! Highly recommended. With every purchase, you get WiFi access for one hour, so no surprises or misunderstandings.</li>
<li>It’s amazing what such a change of working environment does for one’s creativity.</li>
</ol>
<p>On the topic of startups, Dr Jorik Blaas, ex PhDer, full-time genius and friend, is now the director of research and development at <a href="http://synerscope.com/" title="synerscope website">Synerscope</a> (probably no relation with sinister, but my subconscious is just not behaving today), a high-potential startup that makes visualisation-based tools for fraud detection in big data (big money, IOW). Synerscope has brought together some of the top visualisation brains in the country. Personally, I can’t help but imagine it like this:









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/Dr_Evil.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/Dr_Evil.jpg"
        
            alt="Are you in there somewhere?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Are you in there somewhere?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>On Tuesday and Wednesday, we made a quick train trip (*cough* 9 hours there due to delay thank you NS, 7+ hours back) to Magdeburg for the <a href="http://www.fg-medvis.de/" title="link to German MedVis group site">bi-annual German MedVis meeting</a>. You’ll recall that I spent <a href="/2009/04/25/my-first-sabbatical/" title="my magdeburg sabbatical">my first micro-sabbatical there</a>. The city almost feels like home, and it was really great seeing many of the Magdeburg peeps again. The meeting itself was of high quality, with a number of VisWeek contributions being presented. Thomas Kroes (should I start using fictitious names and acronyms again?) presented his <a href="http://exposure-render.googlecode.com/" title="exposure render website">interactive photo-realistic volume renderer</a> too! By the way, download it, use it (it makes fantastically beautiful renderings), spread it, and do cite the soon-to-appear article.</p>
<p>On Saturday, it rained (again, or still, I forget), so I decided to flip Mother Nature the bird by BBQing four juicy rib-eye steaks outside. Take that Mother Nature! The steaks were delicious, thank you. Mother Nature is not all bad though… Check this out: The Southern Lights. FROM SPACE!










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/aurora.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/aurora.jpg"
        
            alt="Aurora Australis (thanks Bart!) FROM SPACE, taken by Ron Garan. Click on the photo to go to the original."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Aurora Australis (thanks Bart!) FROM SPACE, taken by Ron Garan. Click on the photo to go to the original.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I’m going to wind down this post with two backyard philosophy-themed bits. The first is a quote by mathematician Alfred North Whitehead from this article on “The Skill that Matters Most” (found via <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/" title="joe's blog">Joe Botha</a>, serial entrepreneur, currently changing the world with <a href="https://www.trustfabric.com/">Trust Fabric</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Civilization advances by extending the number of important operations which we can perform without thinking about them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I haven’t thought about it that way before, but it does make complete sense. The more things we humans do well in a routine fashion, the better.  Otherwise, our inconsistency is prone to lead to problems. By the way, the mentioned skill is <em>self-control</em>.</p>
<p>Finally, <a href="http://www.flipangle.org/" title="AJ's site">AJ</a> forwarded this video called Disconnect to Connect. I’ll just let you watch and think about it for a while:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GnwNGNOv19A?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>I’ll be off now. Please do have an epic week, and think of me when your level of enjoyment is at a local maximum. At these points, you might also consider jumping around randomly.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>