<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>next on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/next/</link><description>Recent content in next on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/next/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2021 to 2022 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</guid><description> Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.
I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to 2014 (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and 2015 (no real excuse).
Much later, on Sunday January 23: It could very well still win the Most Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&amp;rsquo;s done.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition
post</a>!</p>








<figure><a href="20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to
<a href="/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/">2014</a> (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and <a href="/2015/01/21/weekly-head-voices-88-just-be-yourself-they-said/">2015</a> (no real
excuse).</p>
<p><em>Much later, on Sunday January 23:</em> It could very well still win the Most
Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Emacs and <code>M-x count-words</code> (on a temporary buffer copied over from <a href="/archive/#2021">the 2021
blog post archive</a>) tells me that I published 28 posts on this blog, and 8
technical posts over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>Just like with the running below, but for different reasons, I lost a lot of
steam during the last few months of the year.</p>
<p>In a truly surprise twist, in 2022 I will again attempt to write regularly, and
to write more, and to keep it up until the end.</p>
<h3 id="stats-addendum">Stats addendum</h3>
<p>Applying the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess log analyzer</a> to this blog&rsquo;s log files with the following
invocation:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#859900">for</span> i in {2..13..1}; <span style="color:#859900">do</span> <span style="color:#cb4b16">echo</span> cpbotha.net.access.log.<span style="color:#268bd2">$i</span>.gz; <span style="color:#859900">done</span>) | xargs zcat -f -- | goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; tells me that in 2021 cpbotha.net welcomed over 115000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>The same tool reports that <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a> clocked in at just under 165000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>Even if the real number of actual human visits is a quarter of what the tool is
reporting, I am ecstatic!</p>
<p>The three most popular cpbotha.net posts based on hits during 2021 were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">Dear USA, my data has left your building</a></li>
<li><a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">Note-taking strategy 2019</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>Thanks to Strava&rsquo;s handy training calendar shown below, we can see that I spent
125 hours last year (mostly, about 4 hours was spent on hiking just over 20km)
running a bit over 1300km.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can also see quite clearly that I lost steam in November and especially in
December.</p>
<p>This was initially due to work getting quite busy, and then later in December a
bout with Omicron (highly probably) and also less than run-friendly weather in
St. Francis.</p>
<p>I am always happy when I manage to average 100km or more per month, and I&rsquo;ll
probably try to do that again in 2022.</p>
<h3 id="possibly-tmi-read-on-at-your-own-risk">Possibly TMI, read on at your own risk</h3>
<p>Those of you who know me, will also know about my giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunion">bunion</a>, or hallux
valgus as it prefers to be called.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&amp;rsquo;s complicated." width="240px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyways, Mr Valgus is unfortunately playing an increasingly frequent role in my
attempts at running, often starting to complain at N kilometres where N is
fortunately still higher than most of my attempts, but still affecting a
worrying number of them.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to push on, until Mr Valgus overstays its welcome, at which point
it will be time to explore invasive corrective procedures.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Probably my most redeeming habit of them all, is reading books every night in
bed until I fall asleep.</p>
<p>Even if the day has been less than satisfactory, ending it with an entirely
deliberate and focused reading session tends to make up for quite a lot.</p>
<p>Although I was planning to do more book summaries in 2021, I managed to
complete only one. At least it was a good one, namely <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Seven
and a Half Lessons About the Brain&rdquo; by Lisa Feldman Barrett</a>, which I can
strongly recommend if you have not checked it out yet.</p>
<p>Thanks to strong contenders like the one above, the competition was fierce, but
in the end the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em> could go to nothing other
than Oliver Burkeman&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08FGV64B1/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</em></a>.</p>
<p>Burkeman, he of the <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">importance of being able to put <em>down</em> your work</a> and of <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">more
appearances on this blog</a>, has created a beautifully written ode to our terribly
limited lifespans (4000 weeks if you&rsquo;re lucky, you can almost hear them ticking
away&hellip;), and to our terribly limited capacity to make the most of the time
that we do get, and to really just giving up the fight to <em>get everything done</em>,
because we will never ever win the battle against the law of perpetually
filling inboxes of various kinds, and because it&rsquo;s so much better to simply
<em>disconnect</em> from the firehose (which we can&rsquo;t get rid of completely) in order to
spend time on no-excuses leisure, and especially on our loved ones.</p>
<p>My favourite fiction book by far was <em>The Anomaly</em> by Hervé le Tellier, as
translated by Adriana Hunter.</p>
<p>After having just grudgingly finished Elizabeth Bear&rsquo;s Ancestral Night (first
novel in the White Space series; some interesting ideas, but just too pulpy,
clumsy and exposition-rich for my taste, in spite of space opera being a guilty
pleasure&hellip;), the light literariness and French cynicism of The Anomaly was a
<em>delightful</em> and refreshing breeze that I was unable to put down until it was
done.</p>
<p>In 2022, I&rsquo;m planning to read more than in 2021, and publish more of those
summaries.</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#mindfulness">daily meditation streak that started in 2020</a> continued for most of 2021,
until the end-of-year school vacation started. I am not yet sure how I&rsquo;ll be
able to fit this into my new 2022 work-routine.</p>
<h2 id="worst-habit-of-2021">Worst habit of 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV Award for Worst Habit of 2021 By Far goes, without a doubt, to my old
friend TwiFRaF-Yo, although this time around the main culprits were Twitter,
Reddit and YouTube.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know exactly when I fell out of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">the previous social media fast</a>, but I
fell out with a vengeance.</p>
<p>Although I subscribe almost entirely to technical communities on reddit (Emacs,
Orgmode, Org-roam, keyboards, etc.), there are enough of them to keep a person
busy.</p>
<p>If you add to that my twitter feed, where I&rsquo;ve also taken care to remove the
noise, subscribing largerly to high-signal science-, technology- , and
engineering-related feeds, there&rsquo;s a great deal of valuable-seeming information
that one feels compelled to get through every day&hellip;</p>
<p>(It feels like I&rsquo;ve told this story before&hellip;)</p>
<p>Anyways, every time I manage to disconnect (it&rsquo;s been a few weeks now, I think
Monday January 3 was the official start date of the current fast), only then am
I able to recognise (where by &ldquo;recognise&rdquo;, I mean that friends say this to me,
and this is when I&rsquo;m able to admit that they&rsquo;re right) that the net value for
me is highly probably negative.</p>
<p>While there is certainly valuable information that enters via those streams, it
costs so much attention and emotional energy that it&rsquo;s not really worth it.</p>
<p>So.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m back on the no-social-media cart until next time.</p>
<p>Just like the previous time, I&rsquo;m limiting myself to the brilliant Inoreader RSS
subscription service (which I pay for) to keep up to date with 99% long-form
blogs, and two Twitter accounts that are worth too much to me to disconnect
from (<a href="https://twitter.com/erictopol">Eric Topol</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/alper">Alper Çuğun-Gscheidel</a>).</p>
<p>Although I sometimes think this makes me slower, because I don&rsquo;t have all of
the current happenings at my fingertips all the time, I&rsquo;m hoping this gives me
more space and time for reading, thinking and writing.</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">Systems and tools for running this human (PKM baby)</h2>
<p>In the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">2018 to 2019 transition post</a> I mentioned the &ldquo;The System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This time, for this section, I would like to limit it to tools for knowledge
management and task management (this is not my favourite term, but I&rsquo;m erring
on the side of familiarity here) .</p>
<p>All of Emacs and Orgmode and Org-roam is still going strong, although I waver
quite a bit sometimes when I see some of the shiny new things, like <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>,
which I would probably be using if it wasn&rsquo;t for Emacs.</p>
<p>However, when I sometimes dive into my notes, I can see the difference it makes
when you stick to a single tool for longer than a few years. The amount of
knowledge keeps on growing, and I am slowly getting better at linking it all
together and&hellip;  sometimes even using it.</p>
<p>The picture below shows the graph created, by the <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> package, of a
sub-section of my notes network:</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Before I got side-tracked by the pretty picture, I was planning to dedicate
this section to a new WHV award, namely the Award for the Most Unexpectedly
Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021.</p>
<p>This year the award goes to&hellip; <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper/guide">Dropbox Paper</a>!</p>
<p>Back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">WHV #233</a> I listed many of the reasons why. In the few months since then
it has become only more useful to me as the go-to mobile tool for checklists
(especially useful when we go on trips), lists of books, movies and music
recommended by people in person, and so on.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualifier features, such as its markdown DNA and its
usability on mobile for idea capturing, the fact that Paper documents show up
in Dropbox searches, which is how I usually search when I <span class="underline">really</span> need to find a
specific file (versus ripgrep searches in Orgmode), is the deal maker.</p>
<p>(My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">strange scheme for continuously converting all org files to docx</a> for
searching and reading on the iPhone is also still going strong.)</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I had a piece written here with more details about what exactly was happening
at work, but I decided to nuke that and instead keep it more personal by
mentioning that thanks to great big dollops of serendipity and people, I find
myself, with a number of levers at my disposal, right in the middle of an
organization which, after a few months of reconfiguration and preparation, has
embarked on a genuinely exciting, and importantly more unified, course.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not mention the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">discomfort and stress</a> I was
experiencing at the start of the current personal phase, most probably due to
trying to adapt quickly to my new circumstances and responsibilities.</p>
<p>In the time since then, my stress levels have returned to more acceptable
levels, but expectations remain high.</p>
<h2 id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<p>One of the most positive changes I made in the past year, was to put more
effort into making regular and active (virtual) contact with friends whom I
don&rsquo;t see in person regularly enough.</p>
<p>THANKS INTERNET YOU DA BEST.</p>
<p>This year, I want to try harder to do more of that.</p>
<p>More generally, I made a note (yes, again, one has to keep doing this until the
end) to celebrate any of my peeps and our relationships whenever there&rsquo;s a
chance.</p>
<p>Secret message for my innner INNER circle: You are my energy and my joy, I am
here to be yours.</p>
<p>Whatever else happens, these precious relationships are all we have.</p>
<h2 id="even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">Even more plans for 2022: Continue trying</h2>
<p>First off, I would really like to get this blog post here done and
published. (it wants to be too much, or rather I want it to be too much, and so
we sit here staring at each other instead of just getting on with it so I can
try again to write a good post for once)</p>
<p>Second, EAZ is back on, since Monday January 10. EAZ means no alcohol until at
least February 10. As has been the case previously, my sleep quality is
subjectively better, and it seems like my energy levels are more consistent
throughout the week.</p>
<p>I just looked back at last year&rsquo;s transition post, and especially at the <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">final
sections, including the neatly documented Life Systems 2021</a>. That guy
(<a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">apparently we share only about 2% of our atoms</a>) really seemed to have his
stuff together, on paper at the very least.</p>
<p>As I write this (22:38 on Saturday, January 22), I have just realised that <em>this</em>
&ldquo;I&rdquo; definitely needs to spend some more time thinking about &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo; (The WHV
approach to life, the universe and everything, the one with the pillars (love
and science, that&rsquo;s the easy and reliable bit) and the rules) and specifically
if and how to revise the daily life direction clusters.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll have it on your desk by Monday.</p>
<p>Until then, the one thing I&rsquo;m sure about, is that I wish you and your loved
ones the best 2022 possible.</p>








<figure><a href="stormsriver-mouth.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>