<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Meetup on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/meetup/</link><description>Recent content in Meetup on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2022 14:05:14 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/meetup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #240: I am just a copy of a copy of a copy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 21:06:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/</guid><description>Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three weeks instead of one.
I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to another tri-weekly edition of the weekly head voices, looking
back at the period of time from Monday February 28 to Sunday March 20.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been so busy at work that I was unable to create a sufficient amount of
the right sort of headspace to sit down and write a WHV, hence the gap of three
weeks instead of one.</p>
<p>I did spend a number of mental cycles (for the Nth time) thinking about
alternative and more compact post formats that would in theory be more
resilient to lack of time and headspace, but ironically there was not enough
time and headspace to come to any sort of conclusion.</p>
<p>(Some more famous bloggers that I follow manage to put out a paragraph or two
every single day. It would be interesting to try an experiment like that.)</p>
<p>Anyways, switching out of meta mode back to the mishmash of on-topics for edition
240:</p>
<h2 id="blood-flowers">Blood flowers</h2>
<p>During a recent karma-restoring family beach walk, we came across the following
pretty striking flowers:</p>










<figure><a href="blood-flowers.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_238a35b31dd55230.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_e403e50b40bb34ef.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_435955d294620145.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_51541743b6371d19.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/blood-flowers_hu_e403e50b40bb34ef.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Blood flowers in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Blood flowers in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. See text for (much) more details.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The <a href="http://pza.sanbi.org/haemanthus-coccineus">PlantZAfrica website tells us</a> that these are examples of <em>Haemanthus
coccineus</em>, also known as &ldquo;March flower&rdquo; (no idea why) or &ldquo;blood flower&rdquo;, the
latter which is more in line with the meaning of its Greek genus (haima =
blood, anthos = flower), and its Latin species.</p>
<p>We are not the first or only people to find it quite striking:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It was probably the first flower to be collected from Table Mountain and,
probably also the first illustration of a South African flower to appearin a
European publication. The illustration was by the Flemish botanis de L&rsquo;Obel
in 1605. &ndash; PlantZAfrica</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, as if the name &ldquo;Blood Flower&rdquo; is not metal enough, it turns out
<em>Haemanthus coccineus</em> lives fully underground in the form of a large bulb for
the dry summer months, only revealing its brilliant red flower when the rainy
season is about to start.</p>
<h2 id="fantastic-karma-and-how-to-destroy-it">Fantastic karma and how to destroy it</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s Friday evening. We&rsquo;ve just had a brilliant edition of our Friday evening
family braai tradition, and everyone starts retiring to their various
individual relaxation activities.</p>
<p>I decide that it&rsquo;s a great idea to forge ahead with the <a href="https://github.com/vega/react-vega/tree/master/packages/react-vega">react-vega</a> and <a href="https://redux-toolkit.js.org/rtk-query/overview">RTK
Query</a> visualization functionality I had ended my work week with.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;d successfully worked with a previous version of the former, and my
confidence in RTKQ&rsquo;s quality was trending upwards due to recent experience in
one of our products.</p>
<p>I had already made a start with this new instance, and surely my first fully
backend-data-driven visualization was only an hour or two away, giving me a
final Friday evening boost.</p>
<p>Well friends, in hindsight I should have stopped right there and then.</p>
<p>Sure, it was the sort of gamble that had often paid off in the past &ndash; who does
not like to start their weekend with the dopamine rush that comes with the
solving of a little technical puzzle, especially one that results in pretty
pictures?! &ndash; but in this case it was doomed to failure.</p>
<p>The later it got, the less able I was to debug the issue, and the less
emotional control I was able to exert over my growing frustration.</p>
<p>(I am still less than happy with the new react-vega&rsquo;s limited documentation,
error handling and examples.)</p>
<p>I went to bed far later than normal, frustrated, and with no solution in sight.</p>
<p>All of this continued to affect my Saturday (grumpy with capital G&hellip; no wait,
all capitals&hellip;), until I finally made the conscious decision to disconnect
from the technical problem completely.</p>
<p>Anyways, I&rsquo;m writing this down as a reminder to me to be really, really careful
with the work-to-weekend transition.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-1-make-my-home-smart-but-do-it-really-slowly">Techno interlude #1: Make my home smart, but do it really slowly</h2>
<p>I finally got around to hooking up one (1) of the <a href="https://shelly.cloud/products/shelly-1-smart-home-automation-relay/">Shelly 1 smart relays</a> I
bought at the end of 2020.</p>
<p>My whole family is now able to open the main yard gate using&hellip; THEIR PHONES.</p>
<p>Noteworthy here is how easily the Shelly switches can be flashed, over the air
(OTA) no less, with the third party <a href="https://github.com/mongoose-os-apps/shelly-homekit">shelly-homekit firmware</a> to make them
natively Apple homekit compatible.</p>
<p>You can read about the how and the what in <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/03/05/connecting-the-shelly-1-to-an-et-systems-gate-motor-for-apple-homekit-control/">this vxlabs post</a>.</p>
<p>Shortly after that post appeared, we held a <a href="https://fb.me/e/30MWR7Rq3">&ldquo;home automation&rdquo;-themed Helderberg
Software Developers and Entrepreneurs meetup</a>. Thanks to current interest in the
topic, and the three absolutely brilliant speakers who were willing to take us
along on their HA adventure, it was the biggest and most active we&rsquo;ve had in
years, by far!</p>
<p>In another probably surprising move, we are currently moving the meetup group
away from meetup.com and onto facebook as a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/helderberg.swdev.entrep.meetups/">group</a> (join if you&rsquo;re on fb!) from
where we can easily setup events.</p>
<p>Since 2019, meetup.com has been charging a pretty ridiculous $50 / 6-months fee
for a 100% free meetup with 0 commercial intent. In return for that, they
handle attendance (ish, we ofen had &gt;50% no-shows) and supply a bit of
discoverability.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, we now fortunately also have a snazzy website at
<a href="https://helderberg.dev/">https://helderberg.dev/</a> where you&rsquo;ll always be able to find the meetup, no
matter the events platform <em>du jour</em>.</p>
<h2 id="techno-interlude-2-make-emacs-more-prettier">Techno interlude #2: Make Emacs More Prettier</h2>
<p>In spite of general business, I did have to make time for some <code>init.el</code>
wrangling, as is the privilege and sworn duty of every Emacs user.</p>
<p>This time, I refined my font and specifically <code>variable-pitch</code> setup.</p>
<p>I settled on the <a href="https://www.figma.com/blog/the-birth-of-inter/">Inter font</a> because I liked the look of <a href="https://obsidian.md/">obsidian.md</a>, where it&rsquo;s
the default. Then I discovered that it was designed (based on the Roboto font)
by Figma designer Rasmus Andersson as &ldquo;a font meant to make it easier to read
text on computer screens&rdquo; (hey, that&rsquo;s exactly what I need!), and is now also
the default on github, mozilla, and notion. Pretty good typographic company
right there.</p>
<p>The other small change I made which was much more satisfying than I expected,
was setting the default font size based on the estimated pixel density of the
current screen.</p>
<p>This means that my Emacs will render its default fonts at sizes that make sense
on whichever display I&rsquo;m using it.</p>
<p>Yes, I know that we should have been able to specify <a href="https://github.com/kickingvegas/12pt-should-be-the-same-everywhere/blob/master/absoluteMeasurementDPI.md">resolution invariant font
sizes by now</a>, but until that future arrives, my Emacs config will just have to
compensate.</p>
<p>The screenshot below shows an example of variable-pitch rendering on the left
(org-roam entry at the bottom, automatic topic backlinks at the top) and in the
centre (a slightly earlier draft of this post) and fixed-pitch on the right,
the relevant parts of my <code>init.el</code> showing the font and (<a href="https://github.com/humanoid-colors/emacs-humanoid-themes">humanoid</a>) theme setup.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_11d3fdd8a77e004c.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_9340b6edcd6a7e76.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_5a93f6bca3ed7d30.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_ce3b5cd81ec4bea7.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/images/2022/2022-03-21_20-07-58_screenshot_hu_9340b6edcd6a7e76.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Emacs screenshot. No, I don&rsquo;t like dark themes."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Emacs screenshot. No, <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">I don&rsquo;t like dark themes</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="permutation-city">Permutation City</h2>
<p>When I saw a recommendation for <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/156784.Permutation_City">Permutation City, a 1994 sci-fi novel by the
Australian author Greg Egan</a>, I was hesitant.</p>
<p>Would a novel, written more than 25 years ago, about uploading digital copies
of humans to virtual reality (I wrote a bit about that in <a href="/2020/07/01/weekly-head-voices-199-a-bit-stubborn/#a-totally-unexpected-ramble-on-cycles-patterns-and-teleportation">WHV #199</a> back in
2020), still be up to date with the latest ideas on the topic, seeing that
several adjacent fields of research have been advancing at a break-neck pace in
recent decades?</p>
<p>Weeeeell&hellip;.</p>
<p>It turns out great sci-fi has no problem reaching ahead through a quarter
century of modern technological development and then blowing my mind several
times.</p>
<p>With Permutation City, Egan has written the book I would have wanted to write,
in my wildest fantasies of course, about humans, and copies of humans, and the
philosophically indistinguishable self-awareness and consciousness of the
copies, and of their copies, and so on, literally ad infinitum.</p>
<p>Fortunately this is my first Egan novel, and even more fortunately it turns out
that he has produced a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/author/show/32699.Greg_Egan">considerable collection of stories</a> which I now have the
privilege to proceed to assimilate!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #181: The Slow Ones.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 19:47:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/</guid><description>Welcome back everyone!
This edition of the WHV, #181, looks back at the period of time from Monday October 7 to Sunday October 13, 2019.
Compulsory running shot: Looking at Gordon's Bay from the Strand. This was on Thursday. I squeezed in another short run on Friday, which my legs definitely did not appreciate. Note to self: Laziness earlier in the week leads to skipped rest days and sore legs later. (cf. "A stitch in time saves nine." Also cf. Always Be Compounding.) Alternative WHV notification modalities. Shortly after publishing WHV #180, I decided (bolstered by the advice of my, err, advisor) to return to announcing new WHVs on Facebook and perhaps even on Twitter, in spite of TwiFRaF-YT.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>This edition of the WHV, #181, looks back at the period of time from Monday
October 7 to Sunday October 13, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_77e9f02865b47207.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_668df39896270fff.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_b72391f5381e5a66.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_2ae12fc41c639bc1.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_668df39896270fff.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Compulsory running shot: Looking at Gordon's Bay from the Strand. This was on
Thursday. I squeezed in another short run on Friday, which my legs definitely
did not appreciate. Note to self: Laziness earlier in the week leads to skipped
rest days and sore legs later. (cf. "A stitch in time saves nine." Also
cf. Always Be Compounding.)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="alternative-whv-notification-modalities">Alternative WHV notification modalities.</h2>
<p>Shortly after publishing WHV #180, I decided (bolstered by the advice of my,
err, advisor) to return to announcing new WHVs on Facebook and perhaps even on
Twitter, in spite of
<a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#twifraf-progress-report">TwiFRaF-YT</a>.</p>
<p>For the past months, the only place where you could opt in to be notified of
new WHVs was on the mailing list. (Well, that and RSS, which seems to be
becoming more niche with every passing day.)</p>
<p>Although the mailing list works for a number of people, I am interested in
adding other options that would make sense for WHV readers.</p>
<p>Readers, where else would be a good place to keep you up to date about new WHV
posts, should you like to be kept up to date?</p>
<h2 id="what-i-did-in-week-41">What I did in week 41.</h2>
<p>This was a great week for social events.</p>
<p>It was not the best week for avoiding amazing craft beer and even more amazing
wine.</p>
<p>(I knew what I was getting into when the week started. I committed to it.)</p>
<p>On Tuesday evening, I really enjoyed our local Helderberg business and nerdery
meetup.</p>
<p>Two &ldquo;lightning&rdquo; talks were given: The first on getting your podcasting game on
(microphones, syndication, oh my!), and the second on personal knowledge
management, based on the recently published <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">note-taking post on this
blog</a>.</p>
<p>Craft beer was enjoyed.</p>
<p>The next day, at a regular(ish) Top Secret Business Meeting (at the Thirsty
Scarecrow), I made use of the opportunity to drink my favourite IPA of all time
(so far), a beer which goes by the name of WARLORD, and a beer that has been
<a href="/2018/03/18/weekly-head-voices-136-slightly-more-than-nothing-much/#new-beer-warlord">documented before on these
pages</a>.</p>
<p>As the tasting ceremony started, I was greeted by this portentous sign:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_9df3cb3833e72e2f.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_6fcb5215693ddb6e.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_9d9262709756aa9c.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_64c6f6f1a80190f0.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_6fcb5215693ddb6e.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The name is BONECRUSHER, WARLORD BONECRUSHER.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Coincidence? I think not.</p>
<p>On Friday, we had lunch with friends from the Netherlands at the newly
re-opened Long Table restaurant at Haskell Winery.</p>
<p>The view from one&rsquo;s lunch table looked something like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_286fa91df2fcb999.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_36c973590ec6c78b.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_260eab87618f8b58.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_7f478114624e5f24.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_36c973590ec6c78b.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
For a whole while before the guests arrived and before I took this photo I just
sat there drinking in the view with my own eyes, like a crazy person.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>As if that was not enough, we had the exquisite pleasure of making the
acquaintance of the Haskell Anvil 2018, probably the best Chardonnay I have
ever tasted.</p>
<h3 id="running-with-fluids-and-fuel-1210-going-to-do-again">Running with fluids and fuel. 12/10 going to do again.</h3>
<p>On Sunday, I went out on a long run, partly to atone for my sins but mostly just
because I really like going on long runs.</p>
<p>What was special about this run, is that I took along extra fluids for the
first time ever.</p>
<p>Weekend runs these days are mostly longer than an hour.</p>
<p>After an hour of running on a sunny day down here, one loses quite an amount of
moisture. If this moisture is not replenished, one&rsquo;s running equipment starts
to malfunction.</p>
<p>To prevent this situation, I recently acquired a <a href="https://runnerclick.com/camelbak-circuit-vest-review/">Camelbak Circuit 1.5l
Hydration vest</a>.</p>
<p>On Sunday, I took this vest out for its maiden voyage. It had about a litre of
Game (local cheap isotonic drink) in the bladder, and two bananas stuffed in
the front pockets.</p>
<p>Subjectively, the run went better than usual and I was able to increase my
distance by a little, but gratifying, bit.</p>
<p>However, next time I&rsquo;m filling that bladder to capacity.</p>
<p>The angst-inducing sound which that thing makes when you suck out the last few
drops of drink with some distance still left to go is not something I want to
hear again soon.</p>
<h2 id="solar">Solar</h2>
<p>For the first time since <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">our house was
solarized</a>, this
thing happened on Saturday morning at 7:18:</p>
<figure style="width: 400px;">














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24.png">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24_hu_3849a9dd8612a7a7.png 480w
  
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24.png"
  

   />

</a>

</figure>
<p>The house&rsquo;s batteries were still at 24%, but the sun was already high enough to
meet our modest energy demands at that point.</p>
<p>In other words, for the first time, we had stored enough solar power the
previous day to get us 100% through the night and back into solar, without us
having to dip into the grid.</p>
<p>(The inverter is programmed not to let the lithium batteries discharge below
20%, in order to further increase their lifespan. When there&rsquo;s a real power
outage, it will go down to 10%.)</p>
<p>This should happen more often now that the days are getting longer.</p>
<p>I derive a <em>substantial</em> amount of pleasure from every single kilowatt-hour of
sunbeam-powered electricity that we generate and use.</p>
<h2 id="first-rule-of-blogging-you-dont-blog-about-blogging">First rule of blogging: You don&rsquo;t blog about blogging.</h2>
<p>According to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/oct/12/blogging-twenty-five-years-old-all-grown-up">this Guardian
article</a>,
blogging turned 25 on Monday, October 7, 2019.</p>
<p>They define the start of blogging as the birth of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Winer">Dave
Winer&rsquo;s</a> first blog post in 1994. It
turns out that Winer has posted to his blog on every single day since that very
first year.</p>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/QFKtHSlaMVI">RESTECP!</a></p>
<p>I like how the Guardian article juxtaposes blogging with modern social media.</p>
<p>Of course the truth is more complicated, but generally blogging is more about
the content, and the reasoning, albeit just as opinionated, behind it, whereas
social media is all about emotion-driven <em>engagement</em> and extremely short-term
gratification-analogues of some kind or another.</p>
<h2 id="the-slow-ones">The Slow Ones.</h2>
<p>Complementing <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">ABC</a>, I
feel another (old) theme brewing amongst the voices&hellip;</p>
<p>Deliberate, deep and slow thinking and doing, is an additional antidote to the
all-encompassing AI-optimised immediate gratification information environment
that we live in, and to humankind&rsquo;s concomitant addiction to all that is
instant.</p>
<p>In a science fiction world, we&rsquo;re going to end up with yet another
schism between humans.</p>
<p>There will be those who will hold conversations with ten others at the same
time, data streams coming in from twenty more sources in the background,
processing-processing-processing.</p>
<p>There will be a far smaller group of folks who still command the almost
forgotten art of focusing intently on a single thing for hours on end, without
swiping in any direction.</p>
<p>Communication between the two groups will become increasingly difficult.</p>
<p>Will this remain the stuff of fiction?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #78: Aeroimpressed.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/07/22/weekly-head-voices-78-aeroimpressed/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 19:53:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/07/22/weekly-head-voices-78-aeroimpressed/</guid><description>Up in the North, temperatures were in the mid to high twenties every day (yes, it’s the middle of Winter, and that’s how they roll in the North). Back home we had to deal with mid to high tens (sometimes in the twenties!), and then, because the houses are not built for winter and sport similar temperatures inside and outside, you resort to making a fire in yer office, because that’s how we roll!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><a href="http://cpbotha.net/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/">Up in the North</a>, temperatures were in the mid to high twenties every day (yes, it’s the middle of Winter, and that’s how they roll in the North). Back home we had to deal with mid to high tens (sometimes in the twenties!), and then, because the houses are not built for winter and sport similar temperatures inside and outside, you resort to making a fire in yer office, because that’s how we roll! <figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-fire_in_the_office.jpg" title=""></p>
<p><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-fire_in_the_office-300x186.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">My office is on fire! Note the interrogation lamp.</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>(don’t worry, our friendly electrician managed to get the underfloor heating working and now I don’t have to make fire in the office anymore. you can send donations towards my electricity bill via paypal.)</p>
<p>On Tuesday evening (after the fire), I decided to go to my <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Helderberg-Software-Developers-and-Entrepeneurs/events/191133432/">first MeetUp</a>. Although my main goal was to meet fellow software developers and entrepreneurs from my neighbourhood, I had a super enjoyable evening meeting said people, and learning about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Construct_(game_engine)">Construct 2</a> (the topic of the presentation). Now while I’m not into gaming at all, this did lead to evenings of reading about the various mobile game development libraries; there’s a whole universe of interesting cross-platform code out there! My search finally ended with <a href="http://getmoai.com/">Moai SDK</a>, an open source C++ engine with Lua bindings (Lua is awesome, before Moai I integrated it with my secret hobby project; for 200kBytes you get a whole super fast dynamic language in your C++ application!) that can be used to write 2D games for all of the desktop platforms, as well as for iOS and for Android.</p>
<p>I have too many hobby projects going, but the idea of writing a mobile app that’s actually enjoyed by a few people does sound like fun. (I do have an embarrassing app in the store. It’s been downloaded more than 10000 times, and many of the reviewers (more than 200 at last count) have turned superlative reviewing for the useless app into an art. (<a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/1779632/10-best-amazon-reviews-ever">Writing over the top funny reviews</a> is a thing, but you knew that.))</p>
<p>It was awesome seeing Colbert interviewing Vint Cerf, co-father of the internet:</p>
<p>(ARGH. Last Tuesday, this was <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ann2q4VPiF8">a working YouTube video</a> – tonight it claims to have been removed by the user. Also, none of the videos available from <a href="http://thecolbertreport.cc.com/videos/x9hnxr/vint-cerf-pt--2">The Colbert Report’s website</a> are viewable here in SA. I briefly considered hosting the video here for both of my readers, but instead I’ll just post this <a href="http://kickass.to/the-colbert-report-2014-07-15-vint-cerf-hdtv-x264-lmao-eztv-t9336913.html">other more useful link</a> here.)</p>
<p>The bit at 17m50 in the full episode, or at 20 seconds into the part 2 video hosted on the Colbert site, where Colbert asks Cerf about his resemblance to The Architect (of The Matrix) is priceless. <figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-1" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-colbert_vint_cerf_architect.jpg" title=""></p>
<p><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-colbert_vint_cerf_architect-300x223.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Vint Cerf on the left, The Architect on the right. (I had to watch this via US VPN due to geographic rights restrictions. Kind of ironic!)</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>Oh, it turns out that Al Gore <strong>did</strong> help to get NSFnet funded by the NSF, and so the running joke about him giving the world internet has a kernel of truth according to the gracious Vint Cerf. Here’s a cookie to feed to your trivia OCD: Vint Cerf and Robert Kahn started working on what would become the internet in 1973, and they switched it on in 1983.</p>
<p>GOU#1, all of 8 years old, is independently WhatsApping with her grandparents, from her own telephone. I find it really awesome that she’s making these connections with her extended family. I also find it awesome that she comes up with these kinds of constructions when we’re not in the mood to build a real fire: <figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-2" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-gou1_simulates_fire.jpg" title=""></p>
<p><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-gou1_simulates_fire-300x268.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Augmented reality, GOU#1 style.</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>(Now she just has to let me teach her to code.)</p>
<p>(I thought that this was going to be a really short post, but this time my notes had other ideas. We’re almost done…)</p>
<p>On Sunday, we went to <a href="http://lourensford.co.za/">Lourensford</a>, a well-known wine farm and cellar just down the road from me, and also the location of the <a href="http://www.coffeecompany.co.za/">Coffee Company roastery</a>, to acquire a supply of freshly roasted coffee beans to feed the <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2007/04/08/infinite-espressos/">a voracious bean-to-cup machine</a> which lives in my kitchen.</p>
<p>Sitting on the shelf above all of the lovely coffee beans was a newly delivered consignment of <a href="http://boingboing.net/2014/04/19/profile-of-aeropress-and-aerob.html">Aeropress coffee makers</a>. During a previous visit, I had managed to resist taking one, but this thing was now singing to the very warp core of my inner coffee nerd.</p>
<p>I could not resist its call anymore. <figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-aeropress_action2.jpg" title=""></p>
<p><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-aeropress_action2-184x300.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Giant coffee injection. Air-tight seal, column of air pushes water through coffee in 30 seconds. I haz it.</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>I can now report that with freshly ground Bugisu Arabica coffee, the liquid black gold emerging from this wondrous device is indeed some of the purest and best coffee that I’ve ever had. If you’re into coffee, get one of these. You can thank me at the next hipster meetup.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>