<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>books on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/books/</link><description>Recent content in books on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 15:19:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2020 to 2021 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 15:19:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Welcome to the year 2021 friends.
Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.
You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to the &ldquo;transition&rdquo; tag page.
If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition.
This transition tradition started at the end of 2009, which coincidentally is also the year that the Weekly Head Voices was born.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2021 friends.</p>
<p>Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.</p>
<p>You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to <a href="/tags/transition/">the &ldquo;transition&rdquo;
tag page</a>.</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/">last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition</a>.</p>
<p>This transition tradition <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">started at the end of 2009</a>, which coincidentally is
also the year that <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">the Weekly Head Voices was born</a>.</p>
<p>The goal of the transition post is to do a really spotty year review, and then
to gaze unsuccessfully into the future.</p>








<figure><a href="leopards_kloof.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&amp;rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>More seriously, the ever-evolving network of posts on this website (there are
now literally hundreds of them), along with the ever-evolving but also fading
network of neurons in my head (probably at least a few hundred of them too!),
benefit from an occasional higher-level connecting of some of the dots.</p>
<p>In the introduction of the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/">2018 to 2019 transition post</a>, I ramble on slightly
more about the multiscalar nature of my subjective experience, and how that is
reflected in my notes database, of which this blog is one aspect.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s get on with it!</p>
<h2 id="noteworthy-snippets-through-the-lens-of-this-blog">Noteworthy snippets through the lens of this blog</h2>
<h3 id="covid-19">COVID-19</h3>
<p>One of the biggest issues for most people last year and still at this moment is
COVID-19.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested, you could take a look at the Weekly Head Voices posts
that had something to say about <a href="/tags/covid19/">COVID-19</a>, but you don&rsquo;t really have to.</p>
<p>Fortunately, world-wide vaccination has commenced. However, we have to keep our
fingers crossed that:</p>
<ol>
<li>The world succeeds in getting the vaccine to a sufficient number of humans
on time.</li>
<li>A vaccine-resistant strain does not happen. It could, because math, and
because evolution (selection pressure due to the vaccine, doh),</li>
</ol>
<p>Whether the above outcomes realise or not, I do also hope that we retain as
many as possible of the lessons we have been learning thanks to the pandemic.</p>
<ul>
<li>Mask-wearing and generally improved hygeine with the major goal of protecting
our fellow humans are great habits.</li>
<li>We have made great strides towards the future of work, where many workers (by
far not all, but it&rsquo;s a good meaningful chunk) are able to commute less,
pollute less, better organize the interaction of their work and family lives
and, importantly, their work is measured by its value and not by the number
of hours it takes place in.</li>
<li>We humans are in this (today pandemic, tomorrow something else!) together.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="lazar-focus-the-side-project-that-got-released">Lazar Focus: The side-project that got released</h3>
<p>Around these parts we have a rich tradition of starting but then never
finishing side-projects, and the concomitant giant side-project graveyard to
show for it.</p>
<p>This year, I did manage to ship the little distraction blocker tool I wrote,
called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a>. The <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">first WHV mentioning was #196</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the fact that this little tool has ended up helping me to rescue
many aspirant unproductive days, it has sold more than 10 copies, which was my
life goal for this project.</p>
<h3 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion effect</h3>
<p>From Adam Grant&rsquo;s book Give and Take, I learned about the <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#the-pygmalion-effect">Pygmalion effect</a>,
where a teacher&rsquo;s <em>belief</em> in the intrinsic capabilities of a student, whether
those were justified or not at the time, had a significant and enduring
positive, one could say potentially life-changing, effect on that student&rsquo;s
performance.</p>
<p>Besides the bit about the Pygmalion effect, <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/">that post (WHV #201)</a> contains a
micro-summary of the Shape Up book by Basecamp, which is also worth a look.</p>
<h3 id="take-the-day-off-to-go-run-in-the-mountain">Take the day off to go run in the mountain</h3>
<p>During the year, for example in <a href="/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/#life-progress-update">WHV #203</a> when I took my birthday off to go
running in the mountains, I learned that taking days off on the birthdays of you
and your loved ones to go do stuff outdoors is a Great Idea(tm).</p>
<p>(I also learned that sometimes you don&rsquo;t even need an excuse. Just take the day
off and go run in the mountains.)</p>
<h3 id="use-it-or-lose-it">Use it or lose it</h3>
<p>The human system is amazingly adaptable.</p>
<p>The price that we pay for that flexibility is that each and every one of our
learned capabilities requires continuous practice in order to be maintained.</p>
<p>In short humans, <a href="/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/#use-it-or-lose-it">use it, or lose it</a>.</p>
<h3 id="fool-your-mind">Fool your mind</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m making peace with the fact that I apparently need to apply, continuously,
various silly tricks to keep <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">the slippery eel that is my mind</a> on the
straight-and-narrow.</p>
<p>As a shining example, <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">the refocus reminder</a>, a bell that reminds you at hourly
intervals to focus, indeed sounds a bit silly but adds a great deal of value.</p>
<p>My favourite example from last year however is creating yet more (but smaller!)
habits to kickstart my bigger habits, in this case a <a href="/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/#wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">3-item morning checklist
to kickstart the more daunting full day checklist</a>.</p>
<p>The morning bootstrap checklist is, at the risk of sounding like a startup-bro:</p>
<ol>
<li>meditation,</li>
<li>deep reading and</li>
<li>planning.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="blogging-stats">Blogging stats</h2>
<p>Since February 17 of 2020 when I <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">migrated everything to a small Hetzner VPS</a>,
the server log files tell me that cpbotha.net saw just over 157000 unique
visitors, which is 492 per day on average.</p>
<p>I wrote 30 posts on cpbotha.net during 2020, of which 25 were editions of the
Weekly Head Voices.</p>
<p>Thanks to the shiny new archive page I put together today, you can now finally
<a href="/archive/#2020">see all of 2020&rsquo;s posts in one place</a>, or of any other year, should you be more
into the older stuff.</p>
<p>In addition to the cpbotha.net posts, I also published 11 posts over on
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the regular WHV posts, I&rsquo;m happy to have published what will
hopefully be only the first in a whole collection of book notes posts, namely
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Creativity, Inc.&rdquo; by Ed Catmull with Amy Wallace</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s chunky at just over 7000 words, but it will give you a pretty good idea of
the contents of the much more substantial book it is based on!</p>
<h3 id="details-for-nerds">Details for nerds</h3>
<p>This is the invocation I used to generate reports from the nginx log files
using the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess</a> tool:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>zcat -f -- /var/log/nginx/cpbotha.net.access.log.*.gz |<span style="color:#2aa198">\
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198"></span>    goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>In 2020 I seem to have run just 100 metres shy of 1100km. (Typical&hellip;)</p>
<p>More would have been good, but I&rsquo;m happy with this.</p>
<p>Exercise did take a bit of a hit due to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/#exercise">lockdown</a>, although I could definitely
have squeezed more in.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the aggregated amount of enjoyment and satisfaction
was astronomical.</p>
<p>A personal highlight was <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#random-notes-on-the-kogelberg-trail-adventure">running the 24km(ish) Kogelberg trail with a tiny
crew that included two of my Dutch family members</a>.</p>
<p>(These blog retrospectives are strange, because they are also life
retrospectives, but they shouldn&rsquo;t get too personal. I would be remiss however
if I did not mention that having these specific Dutch peeps here in 2020 was
magical. I am going to miss them terribly.)</p>
<p>Also thanks to said peeps, I did more trail running this year than ever before.</p>
<p>It turns out that I am surrounded by beautiful trails. WHO KNEW?!</p>
<p>The other highlight I want to mention was <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations">GOU#1</a> running her first race, the
distributed <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#running-and-reading">CTM 10km in Jonkershoek</a>. Here&rsquo;s to many more GOU kilometres!</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>Thanks to some strict words by friend PK during the year, I got solidly back on
the daily meditation train, which ended up being the start of a streak of
(workday) morning meditation longer than anything I&rsquo;ve been able to maintain up
to now.</p>
<p>(The bootstrap checklist in <a href="#fool-your-mind">Fool Your Mind</a> above might also have contributed to
this.)</p>
<p>The Waking Up course by Sam Harris has been amazing for more than two years
now, and even more so when trying to build and keep up a daily meditation
habit.</p>
<p>What I especially like about Waking Up is its focus on the explicit practice of
the experience of consciousness and the role (or non-role) of the self within
that. (for a tiny example, see <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#find-a-place-in-the-universe-that-is-your-consciousness">WHV #207</a>)</p>
<p>Practising this daily has been an experience that I can only recommend in the
strongest terms.</p>
<p>(Please let me know if you&rsquo;d like to try a month for free. As a subscriber, I
get to give these out to as many peeps as I want to.)</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV approach to life, the universe and everything (also known as &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo;,
but you have to over-emphasize the terribly soft &ldquo;W&rdquo;) has been evolving for a
few years now, but it was most recently summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.</p>
<p>At the basis of this approach we find the two formidable pillars of</p>
<ol>
<li><em>love</em> and</li>
<li><em>science</em>,</li>
</ol>
<p>and in that order. On top of these pillars rest <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">The WHV&rsquo;s Two no Three Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</a>.</p>
<p>The two no three rules are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be useful.</li>
<li>Be likable.</li>
<li>Evolve.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the previous transition post, I talked about <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">six personal daily life
directions</a>, the continuous reformulation of which I had integrated into my
morning routine.</p>
<p>It was a good start, but the life directions were a bit too specific, and six
separate things is too many to keep at the core of your thoughts.</p>
<p>Motivated by this, and also by <a href="https://lexfridman.com/chris-lattner-2/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Chris Lattner</a>
wherein Lattner, an amazing engineer, but more importantly such a kind human
being, underlined the importance to him of always continuing to grow and learn,
I mashed together everything I had to come up with two clusters of daily life
directions:</p>
<ol>
<li>Grow, learn, build, enjoy. (motion)</li>
<li>Be useful. Be likeable. Be kind. (self-checks)</li>
</ol>
<p>In the stupid-dimensional universe that is my mind, I know that these
directions are obviously in the spirit of WALUE, but I can&rsquo;t yet articulate
clearly how they relate to the pillars and the rules of WALUE.</p>
<p>Maybe they&rsquo;re just a neat little pile on top, or a little bit to the side,
leaning against the WALUE building?</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, they have been part of my daily checklist for a few
months now, and they seem to work in the sense of being practical, checkable
and tiny enough to keep in mind always.</p>
<h2 id="plans--for-tomorrow-at-least">Plans (for tomorrow, at least)</h2>
<p>This bit is quite scary.</p>
<p>I hardly know what&rsquo;s going to happen tomorrow, and here I wanted to talk about
plans for the whole year!</p>
<p>So, to be clear, what I&rsquo;ve listed below is limited to the concrete items that I
can see before me right now.</p>
<h3 id="the-absolute-basics">The absolute basics</h3>
<ul>
<li>Attempt to apply <a href="#life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</a> all of the time.</li>
<li>Practise mindfulness every day.</li>
<li>If I&rsquo;m wondering whether I should go run, the answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="comms-upgrade">Comms upgrade</h3>
<p>I would like to level up my communication game.</p>
<p>Work from home is here to stay, and that&rsquo;s a good thing, but it has muffled my
face-to-face communication modality, something that has had a profound impact
on my full communication suite.</p>
<p>Most of the clever folks now agree that <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">the correct answer is asynchronous
communication</a>. Future-facing companies like Basecamp and <a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/">Doist have been
preaching this long before COVID-19</a>.</p>
<p>To be more specific, I need to figure out first how to do asynchronous
communication in my daily work, and then to become really good at it.</p>
<h3 id="write-more-about-good-books">Write more about good books</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to publish more focused book notes like the recently appeared
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Creativity, Inc. post</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s great reading these books, but I&rsquo;ve noticed that if I&rsquo;m planning to
publish book notes, I read more intently, I take better notes, and the extra
processing stage before starting to put together a blog post really helps me to
integrate the knowledge contained in the book.</p>
<p>Every good book one is able to integrate is in fact a cheap, but possibly
game-changing firmware upgrade&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2021-for-you">Wishes for 2021, for you</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this. I am grateful that you&rsquo;re here.</p>
<p>I wish you and everyone you hold dear the best 2021 possible.</p>
<p>Quite concretely, we can all help to make this happen by being as kind as we
possibly can to as many fellow humans as we possibly can.</p>
<p>In the words of a fellow traveller: SMÉAGOL OUT!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Rhythm of the Night. [Weekly Head Voices #66]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/03/04/rhythm-of-the-night-weekly-head-voices-66/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 12:49:36 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/03/04/rhythm-of-the-night-weekly-head-voices-66/</guid><description> (This post has an extremely high slightly-insane-rambling index (SIRI). You have been warned.)
The rhythm of life I love Unkle. Here’s the introduction to their song Back and Forth:
The only life you can get is one made up of ups and downs. The trick is in learning how to deal with the downs, increasing the number and duration of the ups, and enjoying every last drop out of them. This realisation was brought to the surface by a car advert in which the narrator claimed that time in the car equalled “quality time”.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This post has an extremely high slightly-insane-rambling index (SIRI). You have been warned.)</em></p>
<h1 id="the-rhythm-of-life">The rhythm of life</h1>
<p>I love Unkle. Here’s the introduction to their song Back and Forth:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TDVYJQPwHw0?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>The only life you can get is one made up of ups and downs. The trick is in learning how to deal with the downs, increasing the number and duration of the ups, and enjoying every last drop out of them. This realisation was brought to the surface by a car advert in which the narrator claimed that time in the car equalled “quality time”. I don’t like cars, but I love quality time. It usually comes in little bits and, as <a href="/2011/04/07/happinessexception-weekly-head-voices-44/" title="HappinessException blogpost">I’ve reported before on this very blog</a>, happiness and other important things also come in little bits, interspersed by other often less interesting bits. Although one has a limited extent of control over some parameters of this rhythm of ups and downs, of excitement and boredom, it can never be smoothed out. As is often the case, the best course of action is the zen one: Step outside and try to absorb completely the multi-factorial whole.</p>
<p><em>Intermezzo – this post’s title was inspired by this Italian masterpiece:</em></p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u3ltZmI5LQw?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<h1 id="selling-ones-soul-to-the-virtual">Selling one’s soul to the Virtual</h1>
<p>A week ago, I started going through my bookshelf trying to find books that could potentially be given away or sold, freeing up some space for I’m not sure exactly what. Here’s a photo of some of them:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/somebooks.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/somebooks.jpg"
        
            alt="Books traded for space."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Books traded for space.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Each of these gave me pleasure at some point in my life, taking me on journeys to faraway corners of my imagination. Each of these contributed in some way to the ball of thoughts that is me. Years ago, I would not have considered giving even a single book away. Now I do, because I convince myself that everything is available digitally. I do read on my Kindle, where everything is far more convenient and takes up zero real-world space. I can never lose anything again. If I want anything, I can either find it in my archives or acquire it anew.</p>
<p>Could this line of reasoning, this position, be something that’s really quite insidious? Besides containing information on their pages, the books are tangible and visible reminders of the knowledge that they represent. By getting rid of them, could it be that I’m exchanging parts of my soul for an empty, virtual promise, for oblivion? Maybe the books should remain there, on my bookshelf, as constant physical reminders of the knowledge that they brought me — of all the knowledge that I should continually cultivate and upgrade.</p>
<p>Maybe the time has finally come for the 21st century reboot of Microsoft BOB. :) Then a failed (and the brunt of many jokes) experiment, perhaps now the seeds of a solution to the problem of trading the physical for the virtual. Imagine a private room where you can walk between your virtual bookshelves, a virtual haven to keep your slow, real humanity intact.</p>
<h1 id="life-philosophy-that-works">Life philosophy that works</h1>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neil_deGrasse_Tyson" title="wikipedia page Neil deGrasse Tyson">Neil deGrasse Tyson</a> is a prominent American astrophysicist and science communicator. Recently he took part in a <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/qccer/i_am_neil_degrasse_tyson_ask_me_anything/" title="Neil deGrasse Tyson reddit IAmA">IAmA session</a> on reddit, where he answered the questions of random reddit users. To the question “What can you tell a young man looking for motivation in life itself?” his answer was the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The problem, often not discovered until late in life, is that when you look for things in life like love, meaning, motivation, it implies they are sitting behind a tree or under a rock. The most successful people in life recognize, that in life they create their own love, they manufacture their own meaning, they generate their own motivation.</p>
<p>For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This will definitely find its place in the Unified Dogma of Me (UDM). For now, I’m doing my best to fuse it permanently with my atoms.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Augmentation [Weekly Head Voices #23]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/05/29/augmentation-weekly-head-voices-23/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2010 18:37:03 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/05/29/augmentation-weekly-head-voices-23/</guid><description> (This edition is about babies, textbook Ph.D. defences and mind-viruses in Snow Crash, all of which can mostly be filed under backyard-philosophy(ish).)
On the theme of striving for The Next Level, my not-quite-1-month-old bundle of joy laughed out loud today for the first time! I&amp;rsquo;m sure that it was not a false alarm, as I was being my usual comedic genius self (I target the 1 to 3 month-old crowd), and the pattern of stimulus and reaction was just too well-coordinated and sustained to be coincidental.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This edition is about babies, textbook Ph.D. defences and mind-viruses in Snow Crash, all of which can mostly be filed under backyard-philosophy(ish).)</em></p>
<p><strong>On the theme of striving for</strong> <strong><a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/05/13/the-next-level-weekly-head-voices-22/" title="next level blog post">The Next Level</a></strong>, my
not-quite-1-month-old bundle of joy laughed out loud today for the first time!
I&rsquo;m sure that it was not a false alarm, as I was being my usual <em>comedic
genius self</em> (I target the 1 to 3 month-old crowd), and the pattern of stimulus
and reaction was just too well-coordinated and sustained to be coincidental.</p>
<p><strong>On the theme of really cool events</strong>, on Thursday I had the privilege of being part of the <em>Best Ph.D. Defence EVAR</em>. Seriously people, the day that my good friend Frans Steenbrink became my good friend Dr. Frans Steenbrink will pleasantly resonate in my mind for a long time to come.</p>
<figure>
<a href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2010/05/matrix_fight.jpg">
<img alt="" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2010/05/matrix_fight.jpg"/>
</a>
<figcaption>
A typical scene during an average Ph.D. defence. The candidate is in the
middle, surrounded by committee members on both sides. At this very moment, he
is investigating two possible lines of argument.
</figcaption>
</figure> 
<p>Here in NL, a Ph.D. defence is a fantastic affair: The candidate has to defend his work against the highly-experienced offensive mental manoeuvres of a committee consisting of around 7 wise men, most of them grizzled veteran professors who have eaten many a hapless candidate FOR BREAKFAST! As if that weren’t awe-inspiring enough, the defence usually takes place in some imposing building, preferably more than a few hundred years old (in this case, it was the <a href="http://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academiegebouw_(Leiden)" title="Wikipedia page for Academiegebouw">Academiegebouw in Leiden</a>, almost 500 hundred years old), the committee are in full academic (read: battle) garb, and the whole affair is public, so the candidate is joined by a potentially sizeable audience. Believe me, this can be a nauseatingly stressful experience.</p>
<p>Of course Dr. Steenbrink handled the whole affair with elegance and, extremely unusually, a healthy dose of humour. It might be the first time that I’ve ever seen a candidate disarm his opponents not only by artfully responding to their questions, but with an ever-so-slightly irreverent injection of humour. It was beautiful.</p>
<p>After the successful defence, we were all picked up by a boat and taken via the Leiden canals to <a href="http://www.poort.nl/content/view/12/26/" title="De Poort website">De Poort</a> for the after-party, and what an after-party it was… Besides the live performance of <a href="http://www.frederiksteenbrink.com/" title="Frédérik Steenbrink website">Frédérik Steenbrink</a>, the <a href="http://www.myspace.com/sonocracymain" title="Link to Sonocracy">two electro DJs</a>, the superb saxophonist who was able to accompany them musically (!!!), the Louis Theroux-style documentary put together by <a href="http://www.clinicalgraphics.com/" title="Website of Mr Cricket's business">Mr Cricket</a>, and copious amounts of free beer, it was positively life-affirming to see the Master of Good Karma (the freshly minted doctor goes by many names) being surrounded by his Karma-children, all emanating. You need to know him in order to understand this completely, but you have to trust me that it was beautiful.</p>
<p><strong>On the theme of understated super-heroes</strong>, I finally got around to reading Neal Stephenson’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snow_Crash" title="Wikipedia page explaining Snow Crash">Snow Crash</a>, triggered by a <a href="http://boingboing.net/2010/05/09/snow-crash-cosanostr.html" title="Cosa Nostra t-shirt on boingboing">Cosa Nostra t-shirt shown on boingboing</a>. I know I know, I could have lost my Cyberpunk Nerd membership card for only reading it this late in my life…</p>
<p>In any case, I really enjoyed the book, especially for the characters (the protagonist, called Hiro Protagonist, is naturally a half-African American half-Korean hacker / sword-fighter / pizza delivery guy), the far-out society (the world is run by private franchises, amongst others the Mafia, owner of the extremely influential Cosa Nostra pizza chain and run by the charismatic Uncle Enzo), the crazy technological artefacts (the Rat Things!) and for all the changes in society brought about by the crazy technology, not least of which the Metaverse. The Metaverse is the name Stephenson gave to his extrapolation of various phenomena present or considered in 1992: The internet, virtual reality, Gibsonian cyberspace. The protagonists spend a portion of their time not quite jacked in, but with augmented reality goggles and high-fidelity ear-phones, walking around as avatars in an artificial world with a total population of slightly less than what facebook has now, if I remember correctly.</p>
<p>Personally, I didn’t find Snowcrash quite as good as Gibson’s Neuromancer (see <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2002/08/15/william-gibson-knew-it-then/" title="Link to my Neuromancer blurb.">my 2003 ode here</a>. it still gives me goose-flesh…), but somehow, very sneakily, it has still managed to manoeuvre itself into my list of all-time favourite books.</p>
<p>The story is built around the interesting idea of a neuro-linguistic virus, that is a certain sequence of sounds that is somehow able to get into the human deep brain, screw things up royally and spread through verbal contact with other humans. It has a cyberspace equivalent called Snow Crash: If programmers in the Metaverse see this specially coded binary image (through their AR interfaces), their brains essentially crash and they’re turned into vegetables. It’s all very complex (see <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snow_Crash" title="Snow Crash wikipedia page">this wikipedia page</a>) and quite far fetched, but the idea of considering certain large-scale social phenomena as a kind of mind-virus, that is a potentially damaging entity that integrates at very low level with its host, is self-replicating and is able to spread to other humans, is intriguing to say the least.</p>
<p>Recall that Dawkins partly coined the by now well-known English term <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meme" title="Wikipedia page on memes">“meme”</a> in his 1976 book, The Selfish Gene, as it turns out that the concept was more or less first written about by Semon in 1904. A meme, analogous to a gene, is an element of social information, for example the mistaken idea that going outside in cold weather increases the chances of getting a cold (in this case, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/09/27/weekly-head-voices-5-google-docs-netbook-karma-common-cold/" title="my blog post on cold not causing colds">not true</a>, but still a meme). Analogous to a biological virus, a mind-virus would then be built up from various memes. Each meme would take care of a different function of the mind-virus, helping to guarantee its survival and proliferation throughout humankind, for example: Don’t question me (meme1), believe in me (meme2), spread me (meme3), be exclusively faithful to me (meme4), do this or you will be severely punished (meme5), do this and you will be greatly rewarded (meme6).</p>
<p>If you’re wondering what I mean by all of this, rest assured in the fact that <a href="http://zombo.com/" title="Zombo Com website">Zombo Com</a> has all the answers.</p>
<p>Kids, now go and have yourselves a fantastic week!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>