<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Yuval Harari on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/yuval-harari/</link><description>Recent content in Yuval Harari on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 21:27:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/yuval-harari/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #259: Backbone</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</guid><description> Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!
(I just learned that the English connoisseur comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved connaisseur (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little oi.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







    


<figure><a href="bettys_sunset.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_84d7d5fb2023d1f3.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_94ef9e4fb9dd976e.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_b061658b14bcf3ec.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!</p>
<p>(I <em>just</em> learned that the English <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/connoisseur"><em>connoisseur</em> comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling</a>. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved <em>connaisseur</em> (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little <em>oi</em>.)</p>
<h2 id="how-do-you-do-fellow-humans">How do you do, fellow humans?</h2>
<p>This Sunday morning I browsed through all of my Obsidian daily entries, starting from Monday January 20, the day after <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/">The 2024 to 2025 transition post</a> appeared, because the urge to write here has become quite persistent of late, an urge that is clearly quite oblivious to my feeling that it has become increasingly more tricky to make the time to sit down and focus on just this one thing.</p>
<p>I, very briefly I should add, considered feeding all of those daily posts to one of our artificial friends to extract highlights, but for the time-being, I really like that every word you read here was produced by my laborious and messy (fluids-based, for the most part) biology-based process.</p>
<p>This means that I read every single stupid word I wrote in those daily entries, re-experienced various emotions, some of them transformed by the ever-changing self, while I read them, and let those ideas all simmer for a while in the wetware mostly enclosed by my skull, before sitting down here and producing a new set of emotions whilst typing out a bunch of new words on this (mechanical) keyword.</p>
<p>Blood, sweat and tears my friends, blood sweat and tears.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Since my last entry here, I&rsquo;ve been reading a lot more, something that I&rsquo;m really happy about.</p>
<p>Besides the deep-seated and strong instinct that reading good books makes me a better human, it also turns out to be an <em>excellent</em> doom-scrolling suppressant, by virtue of simply pushing that activity out of one&rsquo;s daily schedule.</p>
<p>Apart from that motivation, what has made a huge difference in my reading volume was adding audiobooks as well as Zotero on my laptop to the reading modality mix.</p>
<p>Where I previously would only read on my Kindle e-reader, I&rsquo;ve discovered that picking the right medium for the right book means I can comfortably use these three channels during different phases of the day.</p>
<p>In the evening right before closing my eyes, I usually read fiction on the Kindle. After 10 to 20 minutes of reading, my eyes start closing of their own accord and my brain shuts down. Current Kindle book: <a href="https://www.gregegan.net/MORPHOTROPHIC/MORPHOTROPHIC.html">Morphotrophic by Greg Egan</a>. <a href="/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/#permutation-city">Egan has previously appeared on this blog</a> for a much older creation which I really loved.</p>
<p>During the day in the car on short commutes, I prefer to read non-fiction books like <a href="https://www.ynharari.com/book/nexus/">Nexus by Yuval Harari</a> (which I loved by the way). With Nexus at 1.5x speed, which is still very comfortable, it was around 17 hours of listening time which went by a lot faster than I expected. I&rsquo;m currently on [<em>Behave: The Biology of Humans at Our Best and Worst</em> by Robert M. Sapolsky] which is super entertaining and extremely successful at repeatedly blowing my mind.</p>
<p>Some non-fiction books deserve even closer attention, like <a href="https://www.abriefhistoryofintelligence.com/">Max Bennett&rsquo;s <em>A Brief History of Intelligence</em></a>, which I started reading on my Kindle but then completed on my laptop, using the fantastic epub reader in Zotero. With this tool I can make highlights and notes to my heart&rsquo;s content.</p>








    


<figure><a href="screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_fd5d3cc24c0400cb.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_ded6f76846ff592d.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_a10ae5587078729c.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>On the topic of Zotero, the two features that would make it even more perfect for me are <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/pull/836">the iOS epub support</a>, so I can open annotated epubs on the go, and <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/issues/597">iOS webpage snapshot support</a>, so that I can save <a href="https://github.com/gildas-lormeau/SingleFile">SingleFile</a> snapshots of web pages from my phone like on desktop, and not just the link.</p>
<h3 id="thanks-for-nothing-amazon">Thanks for nothing Amazon</h3>
<p>On that topic, <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/02/psa-amazon-kills-download-transfer-via-usb-option-for-kindles-this-week/">on February 26 Amazon killed the Kindle &ldquo;download &amp; transfer via USB&rdquo; feature</a>, the exact feature that I&rsquo;ve always used to make copies of Kindle titles for my own use, most often for highlighting and further study, sometimes leading to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/book/">book notes posts</a>.</p>
<p>Although I really appreciated the convenience of e.g. hearing about a book, and then being able to purchase and start reading that book within minutes, this user-hostile move by Amazon is the last straw for me.  All the way back in 2016, <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2016/08/21/amazon-owns-your-ebooks/">friend Stéfan warned us all about the Kindle Swindle</a>, i.e. the way that Amazon restricts ebook rights far more than necessary, and is in essence able to &ldquo;switch off&rdquo; all ebooks that you have bought.</p>
<p>For me personally, this latest move just means that I will drastically reduce my spending on Kindle books, and anything else from Amazon, as far as possible.</p>
<h2 id="101-productivity-hacks-for-stubborn-people">101 productivity hacks for stubborn people</h2>
<p>Also known as The Productivity Section!</p>
<h3 id="a-bientôt-monsieur-org">A bientôt monsieur Org</h3>
<p>In the 24/25 year transition post I talked about <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#emacs-and-obsidian">my apparently eternally brewing personal tension between Emacs and Obsidian</a>.</p>
<p>It looks like I might have found myself in the third <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_stages_of_grief">stage of grief</a>, namely <em>bargaining</em>, when I wrote that I would explore the interplay between the two poles of Emacs and Obsidian.</p>
<p>Well, as I write this, it feels like I might have reached the fifth and final stage, namely <em>acceptance</em>, acceptance of the fact that orgmode (note, not Emacs, but orgmode), although far more powerful and flexible, is probably always going to be the silo that it currently is, in contrast to markdown (note, not necessarily Obsidian) which, while functionality-wise is but a shadow of orgmode, is hugely more accessible and inter-operates with everyone and their dogs.</p>
<p>You see, since writing that transition post, I&rsquo;ve been creating more and more markdown notes, to the extent that I keep on running into the inconvenience of orgmode nexus nodes which I can in theory link to from markdown, but with links that are not as fully featured as markdown to markdown links.</p>
<p>It really does seem like &ldquo;interplay&rdquo; is turning into &ldquo;dominance&rdquo;, if you&rsquo;ll excuse my multiple layers of innuendo here.</p>
<p>And so after a really good 10 year run as orgmode-disciple, as chronicled by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">10+ years of vxlabs posts on the topic</a>, a bunch of <a href="/tags/orgmode/">appearances on this blog</a> and even <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">the orgmode-exocortex</a>, it&rsquo;s time to read the writing on the wall, writing that upon closer inspection has turned out to be in markdown format after all.</p>
<h3 id="productivity-hack-of-the-year">Productivity hack of the year</h3>
<p>In a textbook case of <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2024/06/07/report-death/">greatly exaggerated rumours of someone&rsquo;s demise</a>, my orgmode isn&rsquo;t completely dead yet&hellip;</p>
<p>By far the most effective productivity hack I&rsquo;ve implemented in many months, in terms of actual focus hours gained, has been the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar">orgmode-based pomodoro timer I hacked together and wrote about in my other OTHER website TIL section</a>.</p>
<p>While it was already helpful to have a boring text-based pomodoro-timer display a countdown on my macOS menubar, I had wildly underestimated how much impact the addition of <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar#double-bonus-macos-do-not-disturb-during-pomodoro">the automatic do-not-disturb mode</a> would have.</p>
<p>When I start the 25 minute pomodoro focus timer, my script automatically activates the so-called do-not-disturb &ldquo;focus&rdquo; across all of my (Apple) devices. For those 25 minutes, absolutely nothing pings or alerts, and only calls by my my inner-inner circle can get through. When the 25 minutes are up, DnD is disabled across all devices, and I can see to any emergencies that might have occurred.</p>
<p>(🍅 These particular paragraphs are being typed within such an interruption-proof pomodoro BTW.)</p>
<h2 id="how-are-the-children">How are the children?</h2>
<p>Why thank you for asking!</p>
<p>Here I would like to mention that Genetic Offspring Unit #1 (GOU#1) has now experienced the first few weeks of industrial engineering at university (which is the same as the first few weeks of most of the engineering disciplines) and seems to be loving it to bits.</p>
<p>It brings me great joy that, in spite of the fact that she is a wonderfully well-adjusted and socially graceful human, her engineering DNA is shining through brilliantly. This way of thinking suits her, she just seems to get it, and she&rsquo;s really <em>enjoying the work</em>.</p>
<p>P.S. It also brings me joy, but also a tiny bit of concern, that she really enjoys and also sometimes makes dad jokes <em>AT ME</em>.</p>
<h2 id="spiritual-hygiene-backbone">Spiritual hygiene backbone</h2>
<p>All of that reading I wrote about a few paragraphs back somehow happens even when my days seem to fall apart due to general life chaos, various distractions many of my own (unintentional design) and/or due to will power failure on my part.</p>
<p>So on those days, when I finally fall asleep reading, I console myself with the affirmation that the day was not <em>complete</em> chaos, at least I&rsquo;ve done some reading&hellip;</p>
<p>The same goes for my running.</p>
<p>A seemingly low-level function somewhere in my system <em>needs</em> to take me out running an average of three times a week.</p>
<p>Even when I don&rsquo;t want to, I often find myself standing outside in my shoes and ready to go.</p>
<p>It does help that I&rsquo;ve programmed myself with the mantra &ldquo;If you&rsquo;re wondering whether you should go run the answer is YES&rdquo;.</p>
<p>During my many low-power moments, that mantra often nudges me over the edge.</p>
<p>My daily writing habit also seems to be getting stronger.</p>
<p>I might be tired, or distracted, but <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#multiplicity-of-you">one of the voices</a> often gets me to write with mind-tricks like &ldquo;oh just a bullet or two man, surely you can manage that?&rdquo; to which my simple mind succumbs, and before I know it, I&rsquo;ve written a few more bullets, and maybe even a paragraph or two.</p>
<p>Unbeknownst to simple mind (shhhht), retro- and introspection have now been performed, and prepared for future review.</p>
<p>I have now come to realise that these three habits, namely reading, running and writing, and their various positive feedback loops, together form a pretty decent <em>spiritual hygiene backbone</em>.</p>
<p>Especially when the rest feels like it wants to flop around or even fall apart, this backbone is a robust, reliable and, quite importantly, <em>simple</em> construct that defines my desired internal structure, enabling me to maintain focus and humanity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #170: Yeet.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2019 22:02:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/</guid><description>Hello there friends!
This edition of the WHV, number 170, is how I choose look back at the three weeks from Monday April 15 to Sunday May 5, 2019.
This period was host to whooshing-by-deadline-induced stress, one amazing and thought-provoking wedding, the birthdays of two of my GOUs, and, a bit strangely part of this list, the acquisition of a new computing device.
At least we were able to pause everything for a sublime afternoon at a favourite vineyard close to my backyard:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello there friends!</p>
<p>This edition of the WHV, number 170, is how I choose look back at the three
weeks from Monday April 15 to Sunday May 5, 2019.</p>
<p>This period was host to whooshing-by-deadline-induced stress, one amazing and
thought-provoking wedding, the birthdays of two of my GOUs, and, a bit
strangely part of this list, the acquisition of a new computing device.</p>
<p>At least we were able to pause everything for a sublime afternoon at a
favourite vineyard close to my backyard:</p>
<figure>
<a href="lourensford_cellar_skies.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_20b2c5ad8d092c5e.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_d6f7ceb2c7fd7b01.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_6e561138cc326ce3.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_6e7ba6ca8a4e13aa.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_d6f7ceb2c7fd7b01.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
I ended the three week WHV-hiatus in this place, together with my
fam jam<sup>*</sup>. It was lit.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h1 id="a-brief-but-educational-interlude-how-to-speak-gen-z">A brief but educational interlude: HOW TO SPEAK GEN Z.</h1>
<p>I too did not know what &ldquo;fam jam&rdquo; meant until I viewed the educational video
below.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YtrxVWf91Jo" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>I feel like I understand my budding teenager (GOU#1) a little better now.</p>
<p>On a related note: GOU#1 and I went to watch End Game together, on her 13th
birthday.</p>
<p>This is the first time I&rsquo;ve been in a cinema since forever, as I usually find
it hard to justify the time expense.</p>
<p>In this case however, the film, but far more importantly my company and the
special occasion, made it doubly worth it.</p>
<p>P.S. Dumbledore doesn&rsquo;t make it. 😢</p>
<p>P.P.S. That emoji comes straight from my Emacs! (It comes as a bit of a
surprise to me that I am quite excited by how our systems of written
communication are evolving.)</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. If you too want your Emacs to do this, add the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; 💪💪💪</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">use-package</span> <span style="color:#953800">emojify</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#6639ba">:ensure</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">t</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#6639ba">:config</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">emojify-set-emoji-styles</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">&#39;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">unicode</span><span style="color:#1f2328">))</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">global-emojify-mode</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">global-set-key</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">kbd</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;C-x 8 e&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;emojify-insert-emoji</span><span style="color:#1f2328">))</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><h1 id="the-other-blog-posts-i-did-get-around-to-writing">The other blog posts I did get around to writing.</h1>
<p>Perhaps unbeknownst to you, I was not completely quiet on the blogging front.</p>
<p>I produced the following four posts, the latter three of which will have to
live on the nerdy sister blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">meepx1e: I haz new laptop!</a> - The traditional
welcome-new-computer-to-my-household post on this blog.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/16/dotnet-fsi-in-vscode/">Using the new dotnet fsi from .NET Core 3 Preview 3 in Visual Studio
Code</a> - A modest trick
for an improved F# repl.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/19/django-typescript-docker-compose-windows/">PyCharm and Docker Compose for Django and TypeScript development on Windows
10</a> -
You can run your Linux inside of Microsoft-supported Docker containers on
your Windows laptop. How times have changed&hellip;</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/20/link-thunderbird-emails-from-emacs-orgmode/">Link directly to emails from Emacs Orgmode using Thunderbird and
Thunderlink</a> -
This is a core part of my task management workflows. On macOS it worked more
or less out of the box, on Windows and Linux you have to get your hands
dirty.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="the-easiest-but-most-high-impact-measure-you-can-take-to-not-die-too-soon-go-to-bed-on-time">The easiest but most high impact measure you can take to not die too soon: Go to bed on time.</h1>
<p><a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">I&rsquo;ve mentioned Matthew Walker, the increasingly world-renowned Professor of
Sleep Science, on this blog
before</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently working through a three-part podcast between <a href="https://peterattiamd.com">Dr Peter Attia
MD</a>, life optimisation expert with the
hyper-analytical accent(tm), and Prof. Walker, and it is absolutely
<em>fascinating</em>.</p>
<p>Several times now, points discussed by the two gentleman have made me go
&ldquo;OH. MY. GOODNESS.&rdquo; in the car between home, the daily school-run and work.</p>
<p>The long and the short of it is that although we so easily trade away sleep for
an extra hour of work, or even worse to assuage pangs of guilt at not working
enough during the day, that sleep is one of the most crucial components of
one&rsquo;s health.</p>
<p>Looking at it from a different angle, and one which Walker is not scared to
take, probably because it is so critical, lack of sleep has terrifyingly
deleterious effects on human health.</p>
<p>Anyways, if you&rsquo;re looking for a thought-provoking conversation, you could
easily do worse than this.</p>
<ul>
<li>Part 1: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker1/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker1/</a></li>
<li>Part 2: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker2/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker2/</a></li>
<li>Part 3: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker3/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker3/</a></li>
</ul>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have the opportunity to listen to the podcast, perhaps because you
need to catch up on your sleep, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/sep/24/why-lack-of-sleep-health-worst-enemy-matthew-walker-why-we-sleep">this 2017 article in The
Guardian</a>
is a great summary.</p>
<h1 id="the-edge-of-humanity">The Edge of Humanity.</h1>
<p>(Not interested in hearing about sleep? How about existential risks that
threaten the continued existence of our species? Here at the WHV we like to
keep the issues light and light-hearted!)</p>
<p><em>Homo Deus</em> by Yuval Harari is one of those books I really think <em>everyone</em>
should read. This is such a fantastic and broad treatise on where we came from,
and where we might be going.</p>
<p>I am happy that we have the privilege of Harari as the superbly articulate
thinker that he is.</p>
<p>This discussion between Yuval Harari and Sam Harris, available as <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/138-edge-humanity/">podcast #138
on Sam Harris&rsquo;s website</a>, is
both valuable and highly entertaining.</p>
<p>Besides the moment at about 32 minutes in when Harari made the case that all of
the large scale media manipulation and user data mining demonstrate that the
human mind is now indeed hackable (!!), I wanted to mention the
thought-provoking topic of how comically out of their depth our political
leaders are.</p>
<p>They don&rsquo;t seem to be able to do much more than <em>react</em> to short-term fears and
impulses (which they also play to), and as if that was not bad enough, they do
so with an horizon of not much more than about four years.</p>
<p>How many of our leaders would be able to field convincingly the question of
what their plans were, what their <em>vision</em> is for humanity, for the coming 40
years?</p>
<p>What <em>is</em> our 40 year grand plan for energy, for the environment, for poverty,
and for preventing another world war?</p>
<p>Please give your answers in the comments.</p>
<h1 id="a-strange-thing-happened-this-weekend">A strange thing happened this weekend.</h1>
<p>During my time at the TU Delft, I made and maintained a software tool called
DeVIDE, or the <em>Delft Visualisation and Image Processing Development
Environment</em>, or <em>Not Responding</em> as it was called by <em>some</em> of its users.</p>
<p>Development started in 2002, the first open source release was in 2007 and the
last release was in 2012.</p>
<p>(You can still download working binaries of the 2012 release from the
<a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/devide/wiki/Downloads">downloads page</a>. It was
pretty strong on loading chaotic collections of DICOM images, and it was pretty
strong on enabling users to talk to almost any part of it in Python, at
runtime. Frits Post and I published a <a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Hybrid-Scheduling-in-the-DeVIDE-Dataflow-Botha-Post/a96cc2530609d46d9a39f5884d8a9f8192991114">paper in 2008 which nicely summarised
the interesting parts of the
software</a>.)</p>
<p>When <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">I left the TU and
academia</a>, my work
positively careened off in a different direction and it became more or less
impossible for me to justify continuing to maintain DeVIDE.</p>
<p>Fast forward a few years, and due to Project Z I&rsquo;m again all up in the
<a href="https://www.dicomlibrary.com/dicom/">DICOMs</a>.</p>
<p>More acutely however, I feel the need for creatively implemented projective
geometry.</p>
<p>Well, my weekend brain got behind the steering wheel, and before I knew it I
was staring at the DeVIDE UI, all prettied up with Python 3 and VTK 8.2:</p>
<figure>
<a href="devide2019-screenshot-20190505.png">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hu_e2661da33963fa84.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hu_9a4ca26d37fe4833.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hu_2d6809a082ccbefd.png 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hu_9a4ca26d37fe4833.png"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>At this moment it&rsquo;s only a limping shadow of its previous self, but it still
managed to bring back so many warm memories.</p>
<p>With a few hours more of work, it could start becoming useful again.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not entirely sure where weekend-brain wanted to go with this. We&rsquo;ll have to
wait until he gets back to see.</p>
<h1 id="heading">🙏🙏🙏</h1>
<p>Friends, thank you for connecting with me here in these words and symbols.</p>
<p>I am already looking forward to the next time that we meet!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #145: The Narrating Self.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2018 20:12:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/</guid><description> View of the False Bay from the Helderberg Nature Reserve.
The work part of the week flew by.
(I think this is the reason for the shortness of this post. As is often the case, we start with journal stuff, then nerd stuff and, hidden at the end, some backyard philosophy stuff.)
Dear diary The weekend part on the other hand started with a welcome-back-braai (HI MOM!) on Friday, followed by a sublime oxtail potjie on Saturday and concluded today with a sublime long(ish, by my standards as always) run in the morning (showing a little solidarity with the Comrades participants whilst not completely busting my barefoot-style-acclimatising feet and ankles) plus Helderberg stroll and lunch, and is now ending with a WHV writing session.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/false_bay_from_helderberg.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/06/false_bay_from_helderberg-1024x502.jpg"
        
            alt="View of the False Bay from the Helderberg Nature Reserve."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>View of the False Bay from the Helderberg Nature Reserve.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The work part of the week flew by.</p>
<p>(I think this is the reason for the shortness of this post. As is often the case, we start with journal stuff, then nerd stuff and, hidden at the end, some backyard philosophy stuff.)</p>
<h2 id="dear-diary">Dear diary</h2>
<p>The weekend part on the other hand started with a welcome-back-braai (HI MOM!) on Friday, followed by a sublime oxtail potjie on Saturday and concluded today with a sublime long(ish, by my standards as always) run in the morning (showing a little solidarity with the <a href="http://ewn.co.za/2018/06/10/it-was-an-emotional-race-says-2018comrades-winner">Comrades</a> participants whilst not completely busting my barefoot-style-acclimatising feet and ankles) plus Helderberg stroll and lunch, and is now ending with a WHV writing session.</p>
<p>(Sundays which start with a run, have family stuff in between, and end with WHV are automatically awarded a 12/10-would-do-again rating according to my patented How Was Your Day Honey evaluation system.)</p>
<h2 id="nerdy-pro-tip">Nerdy Pro-tip</h2>
<p>Just in case you missed it, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gboard/id1091700242?mt=8">Google’s Gboard keyboard for iOS</a> quietly shipped an update last week that includes as one of its new features support for Afrikaans. This brings the number of smart iOS keyboards (smart, as in AI-based) that support Afrikaans up to the total of two (2). The other is <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/za/app/swiftkey-keyboard/id911813648?mt=8">SwiftKey</a>, which has supported Afrikaans for some years now.</p>
<p>(The lack of a mobile keyboard with native support for one’s language can really complicate effective communication. Preferring fully formed sentences, I’ve never really gotten the hang of SMS-speak.)</p>
<h2 id="homo-deus">Homo Deus</h2>
<p>After a slight detour with a number of other books that have featured on this blog, I have returned to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2016/sep/11/homo-deus-brief-history-tomorrow-yuval-noah-harari-review">Yuval Harari’s Homo Deus</a>.</p>
<p>I am about 75% through, but I can already say that this is one of the best works I’ve read in the past decade.</p>
<p>The way in which Harari, a history professor, weaves together so many strands of history and present to extrapolate our planet’s future is nothing short of magical. Along the way, he takes the reader along on many mind-expanding tangents.</p>
<p>The one tangent I made note of to mention here, was his treatment of the illusion, which we are all brought up to entertain, that each human houses a single ego or individual.</p>
<p>By citing and discussing several examples of humans with separated brain hemispheres, he makes a strong case for the observation that most probably you house multiple identities.</p>
<p>There is a strong narrating self who tries to weave together the experiences and inputs of the other selves, and who will go to great lengths to make everything fit.</p>
<p>Thinking about all of the internal discussions one has throughout every day, and the seeming disagreements one can have between yesterday’s you and today’s you, Harari’s thesis starts to sound like a really good explanation.</p>
<p>This soon leads to interesting new questions: What would be the best way to manage one’s multiple aspects, especially in the light of the fact that “one” does not even know with certainty who is asking this question?</p>
<p>(Astute readers will have noticed that my choice of a title for this blog has finally been vindicated after all this time.)</p>
<p>See you next week, my suddenly multitudinous readers!</p>
<p>P.S. Harari says that intelligence and consciousness don’t necessarily go together. We are entering a future where many of us are going to be made obsolete by constructs which don’t possess consciousness but are far more intelligent than we are.</p>
<p>P.P.S. For one of the best hard sci-fi books dealing with our often-held but anthropocentrically flawed perspective that consciousness and intelligence go together, you can do a lot worse than <a href="https://books.google.co.za/books/about/Blindsight.html?id=FVMzz-xINLsC&amp;source=kp_cover&amp;redir_esc=y">Blindsight, by Peter Watts</a>.  Read that book.</p>
<p> </p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>