<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>gou-1 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-1/</link><description>Recent content in gou-1 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 22:21:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #228: Komkommertijd</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 22:21:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/</guid><description> Figure 1: On the side opposite to Map of Africa, on the grass that shall not be entered if one is not a club member.
This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number two tenny eight, covers the period of time from Monday June 28 to Sunday July 18 of the year 2021.
Bad glitch in the South African matrix Although I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say here (hence the title), the country has been all over the news for less than great reasons.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="map_of_africa_other_side.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/map_of_africa_other_side_hu66112c2b63cb1b236975a2550a96d472_2429329_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: On the side opposite to Map of Africa, on the grass that shall not be entered if one is not a club member."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: On the side opposite to Map of Africa, on the grass that shall not be entered if one is not a club member.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number two tenny eight, covers the
period of time from Monday June 28 to Sunday July 18 of the year 2021.</p>
<h2 id="bad-glitch-in-the-south-african-matrix">Bad glitch in the South African matrix</h2>
<p>Although I don&rsquo;t have much to say here (hence <a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Komkommertijd">the title</a>), the country has been
all over the news for less than great reasons.</p>
<p>Shortly after former president Zuma finally finally handed himself over to the
police on Sunday July 4 to serve his 15 month jail sentence for contempt of the
Constitutional court (there are more cases to come), looting, arson and
violence broke out primarily in Kwazulu-Natal, but also in Gauteng.</p>
<p>Various shopes and malls have been stripped bare and/or destroyed.</p>
<p>This looked like a perfect storm, initiated by Zuma&rsquo;s incarceration (he has a
great deal of support in Kwazulu-Natal), partially fanned on by his children
and allies on social media, and intensified by systemic poverty.</p>
<p>There were many videos on social media of folks with luxury items, some trying
to stuff flat-screen TVs into their cars, or crossing the street with a basket
full of goods to dump in their luxury Mercedes, but there were also many more
who are only trying to survive under the poverty line and can&rsquo;t be blamed for
any of this.</p>
<p>As far as I can see, our current president Ramaphosa has for years now been
doing his best to unravel the nest of corruption and dishonesty that his party
the ANC has unfortunately become.</p>
<p>This is tricky work, as he needs to circumnavigate and/or defuse the same
internal forces that managed to oust president Thabo Mbeki and usher in the
terrible era of Zuma.</p>
<p>The poor man has had to endure even more flak in these days, both from his
political enemies and from other commentators.</p>
<p>Until convincingly shown otherwise, my opinion is that president Ramaphosa is
the best shot we currently have at a better future.</p>
<p>You can read <a href="https://www.gov.za/speeches/president-cyril-ramaphosa-update-security-situation-country-16-jul-2021-0000">his July 16 speech about the unrest here</a>.</p>
<p>A slight silver edge is that these events have put more pressure on the
<a href="https://businesstech.co.za/news/finance/506914/government-considers-basic-income-grant-after-riots-and-looting-in-south-africa/">discussions around the possible implementation of a basic income grant</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. It seems that the looting was not disruptive enough for some folks, and so
now we are dealing with <a href="https://www.dailymaverick.co.za/article/2021-07-20-why-the-western-cape-is-being-rocked-by-taxi-violence/">taxi-company-related violence in the Western Cape</a>.</p>
<p>P.P.S. let me just hide this here: far more locally, we are dealing with some
pandemic-related stressors.</p>
<h2 id="reserve-bench-holidays">Reserve bench holidays</h2>
<p>As <a href="/2021/06/30/weekly-head-voices-227-reality-bending-security-blanket/#groundhog-lockdown">I supected in the previous WHV</a> (three weeks ago, ahem&hellip;), our country&rsquo;s
struggles with the pandemic did in fact manage to get our Kruger National Park
visit cancelled.</p>
<p>To be clear, I have no illusions about the relative importance of our holiday
under these circumstances and in this context (close to utterly unimportant, in
other words), but we humans are gonna human and I&rsquo;m not gonna lie, we were
really looking forward to that week of sun in Mpumalanga.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve often said that the winter down here is more bearable than one would
expect, due to it being quite often punctuated by brilliant and sunny days
outside, but this year I&rsquo;ve come to realise that I might have underestimated
the positive effects of <a href="/tags/knp/">spending the darkest week under the sun of the North</a>.</p>
<p>Anyways, we were super fortunate to be able to arrange for a long weekend in
another one of our favourite places, namely Wilderness, where we were treated
with absolutely balmy days, some of them on the Touw river (inflatable SUPs
FTW!), some of them on the most beautiful beaches, and some of them hiking and
running on various trails.</p>








<figure><a href="wilderness_running_rondevlei.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/wilderness_running_rondevlei_hu4b29d2ac23377683a456e1014f88657c_2560972_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Scene from one of my favourite running routes, this time with GOU #1!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Scene from one of my favourite running routes, this time with GOU #1!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>If it sounds to you like we had to go outside every day to warm up in the
winter sun, I can hereby confirm your astute observation.</p>
<p>To be fair, this was literally in the deepest part of winter, from which there
is no true escape if one remains within the Western Cape.</p>
<p>In spite of that, or perhaps because of it, we enjoyed the wonderful days to
bits.</p>








<figure><a href="kaaimans_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/21/weekly-head-voices-228-komkommertijd/kaaimans_pano_hu570988fdd284e76db557a9c7d039173d_2227820_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: The rail bridge over Kaaimansrivier. We have this on the todo list for next time."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 3: The rail bridge over <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaaimans%5FRiver">Kaaimansrivier</a>. We have this on the todo list for next time.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #225: Just a perfect weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</guid><description> Dear reader,
Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.
Keyboard update: K1 You&amp;rsquo;ll remember from WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the Womier K87 with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown switches.
That keyboard is so much fun to type on.
It&amp;rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear reader,</p>
<p>Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th
installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="la_autumn_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu2c92717c03fbdd0baeaf04b9d5a0a258_4865461_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="keyboard-update-k1">Keyboard update: K1</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll remember from <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the
Womier K87</a> with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown
switches.</p>
<p>That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt
Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the case that fingers also like the exercise, just like their
human owners.</p>
<p>I was not planning to buy any keyboards again soon, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was quite curious whether low profile key switches (that is, slightly less
finger travel) would be a good compromise between the fun of the Womier and the
efficiency of the Sculpt.</li>
<li>The K1 was on my list of candidates of keyboards with low-profile mechanical
switches.</li>
<li>I find it difficult to resist a good deal.</li>
</ul>
<p>You see, a friendly little bird (who also hangs out on the keyboards channel of
the zatech slack) told me about the extra-special Takealot birthday special
discount on <a href="https://www.imore.com/keychron-k1-v4-review">the Keychron K1 V4 87-key keyboard</a>.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a credit card transaction, a week of waiting for delivery and
another week of getting accustomed to the new board, and here we are, with at
least me typing these words on the new K1.</p>
<p>It took a while to get used to the keycaps, which can be a slippery sometimes
(or rather, my finger tip traction is variable), but my typing speed and
accuracy on this thing are in the neighbourhood of where they should be.</p>
<p>The thing is a great deal more <em>stylish</em> than my Womier; the Womier is that
guilty pleasure 80s disco that you really love, the K1 could work in a serious
coffee shop.</p>
<p>Also, having a keyboard which can switch this easily between wired operation
(the default for my desktop) and three different bluetooth connections is
pretty convenient. On trips where I usually only take the MacBook, I could
consider taking the K1 along when I have to do A Great Deal of Serious Typing.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I can&rsquo;t yet say if the low profile switches are indeed
the compromise that I wondered about. My subjective impression now is indeed
that my fingers don&rsquo;t get so physically tired as sometimes happens with the
Womier, but I&rsquo;ll have to switch between them a few times to get a better idea.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am certainly enjoying the experience of typing on
this thing, and I am certainly wondering about the interesting role that
different types of mechanical keyboards have begun to play in my computing
life.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-about-a-new-book-notes-post-about-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Lessons about a new book notes post about Seven and a Half Lessons about the Brain</h2>
<p>After two months of early(ish) morning typing on various keyboards, I finally
managed to wrap up <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">my book notes about Seven and a Half Lessons about the
Brain</a>, a fantastic book by neuro-scientist and psychologist Lisa Feldman
Barrett.</p>
<p>I had plans, in retrospect clearly too ambitious, to have at least two (2) book
notes posts out in Q1 of this year (after it took me months to complete <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my book
notes on Creativity, Inc.</a> by the end of last year).</p>
<p>That goal was necessarily postponed to Q2, and as we can all see now, there is
not enough time for a second post like this.</p>
<p>Either I have to change the format of the book notes to something more compact,
like a bunch of bullet lists, or I should make peace with the fact that I write
these like I write them, a little prose with quotes interspersed that can
generally be read like a mini story itself, and with the fact that they&rsquo;re
going to take as much time as they do.</p>
<p>Sometimes I have mixed feelings about the practice itself.</p>
<p>It takes fragments of hobby time spread out over weeks, fragments of time that
I could probably use for more reading, other interesting tidbits and, uhm,
extra work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it feels like a sort of a mini-rebellion doing exactly this,
assembling so many little pieces into something slightly more coherent and
significant, something that stands apart from work.</p>
<p>It seems I do know what to do.</p>
<p>Thanks for the chat!</p>
<h2 id="perfect-weekends-and-the-necessary-reminders-that-precede-them">Perfect weekends and the necessary reminders that precede them</h2>
<p>The weekend of June 4, 2021, was unexpectedly perfect, and I would like to make
note of that here for future me.</p>
<p>This is the recipe that we followed, utterly by happy accident:</p>
<ul>
<li>1x reminder during the week to really focus on the now.</li>
<li>1x absolutely perfect autumn weather package: balmy 20ish degrees Celsius,
lots of sun, very little wind.</li>
<li>3x braais, one per day, with various subsets of family.</li>
<li>2x runs: one a long weekend morning run, and the other an unplanned one
with GOU#1.</li>
<li>1x polishing and publishing of the blog post mentioned above.</li>
<li>1x unexpected Sunday evening star watching with GOU#2.</li>
</ul>
<p>One would think that daily practice would help, but it turns out that sometimes
a serendipitous reminder by a friend can help to switch one&rsquo;s brain into
exactly the right gear, right before the weekend.</p>
<p>During our Friday evening start-the-weekend ritual (it&rsquo;s a braai. surprise!), I
had my first quite visceral &ldquo;THIS, this is it, this is everything&rdquo;
experience. (so lovely)</p>
<p>From then on, brain remained in the right mode right through most of the
weekend.</p>
<p>If you ever run into me before the weekend (it&rsquo;s always before the weekend!), I
would be grateful if you could remind me that it is in fact now.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you much nowness.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #216: Sup?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</guid><description> Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.
Figure 1: Sup?
The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard with Lots of Focus.
I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily application of the One Main Thing idea, but experience has taught me that it&amp;rsquo;s probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&amp;rsquo;ll be solidly back in the arms of my old friend the really slippery eel.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks
from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="sup_bettys.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hua6953280791f991e1fffdd9f82837fa6_1293397_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sup?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Sup?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard
with Lots of Focus.</p>
<p>I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily
application of <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">the One Main Thing idea</a>, but experience has taught me that it&rsquo;s
probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure
factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&rsquo;ll be solidly
back in the arms of my old friend the <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">really slippery eel</a>.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I have been making good use of the (temporarily?)
increased capacity.</p>
<h2 id="fresh-from-the-oven-vxlabs-software-development-handbook">Fresh from the oven: vxlabs software development handbook</h2>
<p><a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/">The vxlabs software development handbook</a>, at the time of this writing about 65%
complete (that&rsquo;s a random number that my brain gives me every time I publish a
new version), is now available over on my nerdy blog.</p>
<p>If you are working with a smaller development team, or you&rsquo;re starting with a
new dev team, the handbook is not the worst place to look for development
process tips. Furthermore, it&rsquo;s available under the Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License, so you can copy and paste and rebrand to
your heart&rsquo;s content as long as you give due credit somewhere to the original
author (me and vxlabs).</p>
<p>In the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll be trying to complete more sections to get closer to
that mythical 100% completion grade.</p>
<h2 id="two-miscellaneous-tips-for-nerds">Two miscellaneous tips for nerds</h2>
<h3 id="printfriendly-on-your-phone">PrintFriendly on your phone</h3>
<p>You might remember from my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#web-pages-and-articles">2019 note-taking strategy post</a> that I convert all
interesting web pages I come across to PDF and dump them in my dropbox.</p>
<p>This has turned out to be the best way to store web-pages for later searching,
reference and winning of arguments.</p>
<p>However, the mobile part of that strategy was traditionally weak, as is also
discussed in that post.</p>
<p>The problem was that Safari on iPhone has a great reading mode that strips ads
and other unnecessary bits, but when you print from reading mode, the PDF is
formatted for mobile, and, more importantly, there&rsquo;s no way to get the source
URL embedded in the PDF.</p>
<p>Anyways, after years of using the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/">PrintFriendly</a> browser extension on the
desktop (as is also explained in the note-taknig post), I finally got around to
installing their mobile bookmarklet on the iPhone. (this should work on any
mobile browser)</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/extensions/iOS">instructions are a bit finicky</a>, but one ends up with a bookmark that you
can activate on any page to have the printfriendly service pre-process that
page for reading, from which you can tap on the print icon to get a mostly
perfect PDF that is also stamped with the source URL!</p>
<h3 id="fish-shell">Fish shell</h3>
<p>After years of resisting all the zsh blog posts and especially the pretty
oh-my-zsh powerline prompts and sticking to my stock standard bash because
get-off-my-lawn, I finally broke down and installed&hellip;</p>
<p><a href="https://fishshell.com/">fish!</a></p>
<p>fish shell is a &ldquo;smart and user-friendly command line shell for Linux, macOS,
and the rest of the family&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I like it because one of its goals is to be more useful with hardly any extra
configuration, but you can also install <a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/oh-my-fish">oh-my-fish</a> with my new favourite theme
<a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/theme-bobthefish">bobthefish</a>.</p>
<p>I <em>was</em> planning to convince you of my choice with a number of technical
reasons, but it is now clear to me that technical arguments are irrelevant when
you can rock a theme called &ldquo;bobthefish&rdquo;.</p>
<p>P.S. Let me know in the comments if you would still prefer to talk about
technical reasons.</p>
<h2 id="a-brief-pause">A brief pause</h2>
<p>Since we <a href="/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/#gou-1-s-growing-running-habit">last spoke about GOU#1&rsquo;s running habit</a>, it gives me great pleasure to
report that she has, quite routinely if I may add, done another two or three
10k runs, one of them even up to eleven by accident.</p>
<p>Folks I wish you all the best. I look forward to our next connection!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #215: Gateway to an unknown universe (aka Taalmonument)</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 09:48:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/</guid><description><![CDATA[ How do you do, fellow humans? (Sub-vocalise in Steve Buscemi voice for maximum effect.)
This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the week from Monday January 25 to Sunday January 31 of the year 2021.
 Figure 1: Weekend scene from the Afrikaans Language Monument (or &ldquo;Taalmonument&rdquo;, when you speak the lingo). Initially I thought about &lsquo;shopping out the photo-shooting couple, but I&rsquo;ve grown to like them now.
  My notes for the period don&rsquo;t have much that is WHV-worthy, except for the following two humble offerings:]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>How do you do, fellow humans? (Sub-vocalise in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve%5FBuscemi">Steve Buscemi</a> voice for maximum
effect.)</p>
<p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the week from Monday January 25
to Sunday January 31 of the year 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="taalmonument_front.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_front_huf555a7e5629744fbb3029a2fc07d9227_878259_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Weekend scene from the Afrikaans Language Monument (or &amp;ldquo;Taalmonument&amp;rdquo;, when you speak the lingo). Initially I thought about &amp;lsquo;shopping out the photo-shooting couple, but I&amp;rsquo;ve grown to like them now."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Weekend scene from the Afrikaans Language Monument (or &ldquo;Taalmonument&rdquo;, when you speak the lingo). Initially I thought about &lsquo;shopping out the photo-shooting couple, but I&rsquo;ve grown to like them now.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>My notes for the period don&rsquo;t have much that is WHV-worthy, except for the
following two humble offerings:</p>
<h2 id="gou-1-s-growing-running-habit">GOU #1&rsquo;s growing running habit</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned <a href="/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/#mafish">MAF (maximum aerobic function) before on this blog</a>, when I was
trying to nurse back to health an ankle I had injured.</p>
<p>More recently, <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/PhilMaffetone/">Peter Attia hosted Phil Maffetone, the inventor of the MAF idea,
on his podcast</a>. Relative to the normal Attia standards of multi-hour blog
posts, this one was quite compact, and definitely worth a listen if you&rsquo;re into
running.</p>
<p>Just to recap: Maffetone recommends running at a heart rate of 180 minus your
age (a rule of thumb, of course), in order to exercise at one&rsquo;s maximum aerobic
function (MAF).</p>
<p>This is usually lower than 80% of one&rsquo;s maximum, so think long and slow.</p>
<p>The goal of this is to increase the use of stored fat as the primary source of
fuel, the idea being that one would be able to go much further with reduced
effort.</p>
<p>Anyways, this running without too much effort simply sounded too good to GOU
#1, and so she asked me if we could try another 10k like this. (We usually do 5
to 6 together.)</p>
<p>As you might know, <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#the-absolute-basics">my rule for running</a> is that if there&rsquo;s a question about
whether to go run the answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;.</p>
<p>So an Saturday I started with my own 11k so that I would not mind slowing down
for the GOU-leg (I do realise that me slowing down for her is temporary&hellip;),
and then we set out for the MAF(ish) 10km.</p>
<p>She found it super tricky to maintain the lower-than-normal heart rate, which
is to be expected, and for the last few kilometres had no choice but to let it
increase quite a bit, but&hellip; she did a really comfortable 10km!</p>
<p>Since then she has asked if I&rsquo;m up for another one, which is of course the best
possible sign that this habit is being imprinted quite nicely.</p>
<p>(I was pretty tired after the whole episode, but don&rsquo;t tell anyone.)</p>
<h2 id="we-visited-a-gateway-to-another-dimension-and-didn-t-even-get-a-t-shirt">We visited a gateway to another dimension and didn&rsquo;t even get a t-shirt</h2>
<p>On Sunday we planned to take the family up Bretagne Rock (see <a href="/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/#getting-high">this 2017
vacation WHV for a photo</a>), but were met by closed gates, thanks to surprising
lockdown regulations.</p>
<p>Well, the journey there was picturesque (Paarl valley is beautiful, also from
up there), and we suddenly had the opportunity to visit another old favourite
instead: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afrikaans%5FLanguage%5FMonument">The Afrikaans Language Monument</a>!</p>
<p>If you grew up in Paarl like I did, and especially if your school was located
as close to the monument as mine was, you would have spent many hours of your
young life, both during terribly official ceremonies and outings, at this
impressive artifact.</p>
<p>I always did think it was a pretty science fiction design, especially taking
into account it was erected in 1975.</p>
<p>Well, to my pleasant surprise, it turns out that my Taalmonument featured in
season 12 of Dr Who, and <a href="https://screenrant.com/doctor-who-timeless-child-identity-time-lord-origin-explained/">specifically as the monument marking the location of a
gateway to &ldquo;another unknown dimension or universe&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>In an even more pleasant turn of events, the monument and the gateway played a
pivotal role in the fairly specific origins of The Doctor, the protagonist of
the series.</p>
<p>When the gateway is active, the Taalmonument apparently looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="taalmonument_from_below_gateway.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_from_below_gateway_hu88e74d0b4c5604d2173bc986e54e3230_23704_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_from_below_gateway.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Taalmonument in gateway to another universe mode. Image courtesy of screenrant post linked above."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Taalmonument in gateway to another universe mode. Image courtesy of screenrant post linked above.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a tweet about the relevant episode, with some more photos:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">The Gate where Tecteun found the Timeless Child is actually the Afrikaans Language Monument overlooking Paarl, in Western Cape Province, South Africa. The real setting is every bit as dramatic as any movie could envisage 😍 <a href="https://t.co/4IDJZc6C7O">pic.twitter.com/4IDJZc6C7O</a></p>&mdash; The Timeless Doctors (@Ten_Doctors) <a href="https://twitter.com/Ten_Doctors/status/1297283229712560136?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 22, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>Note: I grew up knowing what a Dalek was, but I&rsquo;ve never, as far as I can
remember, followed a Dr Who series. I might have seen snippets of old episodes
in the 80s.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s another view of the monument which you may not (yet) have seen in any
science fiction productions. I think its time will come.</p>








<figure><a href="taalmonument_spheres.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/taalmonument_spheres_hu4617c819c490892dad6b6e6b5c5a3674_562233_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: 1975 had some serious sci-fi architecture mojo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 3: 1975 had some serious sci-fi architecture mojo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>With that my friends, and my wish that you are really able to shine this week,
I declare this post concluded.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #208: Stilbaai</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 10:59:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</guid><description> Welcome back folks!
Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.
It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.
Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.
Running and reading I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, GOU #1 (14) completed her first (virtual) 10km race.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks!</p>
<p>Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.</p>
<p>It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period
Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="skulpiesbaai_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="running-and-reading">Running and reading</h2>
<p>I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> (14) completed her
first (virtual) 10km race.</p>
<p>Her journey started when a friend from school invited her to join the race, at
which point GOU #1 suddenly became much more enthusiastic about running
regularly with her old dad. (that&rsquo;s me)</p>
<p>There is something pretty primal about running with your offspring, an
observation that I might have mentioned before on these pages.</p>
<p>Anyways, after her race she was visibly happy, and also relieved that, in her
words, &ldquo;she didn&rsquo;t die&rdquo;.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m perhaps even more happy about than the preparatory runs together, and
her completing the race, is that since the race we&rsquo;ve been out together for a
run or three.</p>
<p>(Running and reading are two of the most important low-level habits I would
like to try and get my offspring hooked on.)</p>
<h2 id="ieee-vis2020">IEEE VIS2020</h2>
<p>At the start of October, I had a great experience <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#vcbm-2020-virtually">virtually attending the VCBM
2020 conference</a>.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough grade A1 10/10 conferencing for one year, my other
favourite conference, IEEE VIS (for visualization) was also fully virtual this
year in the week of October 26, so again I dove into YouTube streams and
well-organised discord rooms, and again this experience was highly edifying and
enjoyable.</p>
<p>Somehow, it was even <em>more</em> fun than my already optimistic expectations to run
into friends at the conference.</p>
<p>I would like to transfer this one piece of sage advice given by the amazing
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%5Fvan%5FWijk">Prof. Jarke van Wijk</a> during the panel on &ldquo;Why should I stay in academia&rdquo; when
the discussion treated the issue of dealing with rejection, something that is
unfortunately a regular part of most academic careers.</p>
<p>At this point, he was referring specifically to accepted papers and proposals,
but the advice should really be applied to any victory, large or small, in all
walks of life:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Celebrate your victories.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="cycles">Cycles</h2>
<p>You will of course remember that we were fortunate enough to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">spend our last few
days of freedom in Stilbaai,</a> as autumn was arriving, and more acutely right
before the first lockdown started on March 26,</p>
<p>It was really great going back to the exact same house (thanks kind host!),
after months of various levels of lockdown, this time just as spring was really
getting off the ground.</p>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_0181.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I did take work with me for the long weekend, but this time, and quite
unexpectedly, the important <a href="/tags/disconnecting">disconnect</a> happened quite quickly without too much
conscious effort from my side.</p>
<p>If I had to put my finger on it, I would say that getting everyone to go
outside as often as possible on little adventures of various sizes was the
catalyst.</p>
<h2 id="back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">Back to reality: An 18-minute plan for managing your day</h2>
<p>I could not imagine a more sudden transition from the long weekend zen above
than this jump to Peter Bregman&rsquo;s 18 minute plan for planning your work day.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Sometimes, fortunately mostly later in the afternoon, I wonder why my systems
have failed in helping me to keep my eye on that ball for longer. (See <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">my
slippery eel</a> for more struggles.)</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s when I procrastinate quasi-productively by searching online for any new
self-optimisation tricks that I might have missed, and which might constitute
that Last Piece of The Puzzle that will fix this once and for all.</p>
<p>This time, to my great surprise, I did actually run into something 1. that was
written aaaaaall the way back in 2009 and 2. that contained something new that
I had not run into before, namely the &ldquo;refocus&rdquo; reminder.</p>
<p>The refocus reminder is literally an alarm that goes off every hour on the
hour, at which point you explicitly take a step back for a whole minute to
review the past hour, and, if required (most probably the case the later it is
in the day), to re-commit to the following hour.</p>
<p>This reminded me specifically about mindfulness&rsquo;s <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#therunning-and-the-mindful">&ldquo;Each breath a new beginning;
each out-breath a letting go&rdquo;</a>, and more generally about <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">life as eternal
practice</a>.</p>
<p>You can use any sort of timer to do this, but this seemed like a great feature
for the little Lazar Focus app, so I implemented it along with a nice
mindfulness bell sound to add some gravitas to the moment.</p>
<p>If you like, you can read the short summary I wrote about the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/10/24/peter-bregmans-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day-and-the-surprising-power-of-refocus-reminders/">18-minute plan
and refocus reminders over on the LazarFocused blog</a>. There are some other more
widely known but great tips for running your work days more efficiently.</p>
<h2 id="kind-regards">Kind regards</h2>
<p>Folks, thank you very much for joining me here.</p>
<p>The comments section below is ready for your thoughts, if you would like to
externalise them.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #194: 136 words a day</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 23:19:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/</guid><description> Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&amp;rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&amp;rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies.
This post quite compactly gazes back at the week from Monday May 4 to Sunday May 10.
It starts with a short summary of my work week, followed by a story which you will hopefully enjoy.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="afrikaburn2017-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/afrikaburn2017-sunset_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_802509_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&amp;rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&amp;rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: From the oldies but goodies photo album, because I haven&rsquo;t been getting out much: Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2017. Also due to nostalgia, as our AB 2020 adventure was utterly understandably cancelled (UUC). There&rsquo;s nothing quite like ambulating amicably across that piece of desert with your homies.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This post quite compactly gazes back at the week from Monday May 4 to Sunday
May 10.</p>
<p>It starts with a short summary of my work week, followed by a story which you
will hopefully enjoy.</p>
<h2 id="how-was-your-week-honey">How was your week honey?</h2>
<p>I hacked on and fixed iPad microphone support in our direct-to-patient
TeleMedicine app.</p>
<p>If you are a programmer, or you have programmers in your life, you&rsquo;ll hopefully
understand the absolute catnip of technical rabbit holes that suck you in for
hours on end, only to eject you on a beautiful but extremely short-lived
dopamine deluge of discovery.</p>
<p>We integrated <a href="https://casual-effects.com/markdeep/">markdeep</a> into the performance tracking component of one of our
medical image processing pipelines.</p>
<p>Having a format, namely .md.html, which is this easy to generate
programmatically from some computational pipeline, yet results in such
attractive output documents is a great boon.</p>
<h2 id="gou-1-reveals-her-plans-and-makes-us-think--more">GOU #1 reveals her plans and makes us think (more)</h2>
<p><a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> turned another year older.</p>
<p>At the dinner table on the big day, we were having a conversation about further
education in general and about postgraduate studies and PhDs in particular.</p>
<p>(She is now in high school, so these conversations are happening more often.)</p>
<p>I said that she will have to get a PhD in Physics or Math, but that I would
probably be able to make peace with a PhD in Engineering also.</p>
<p>She asked us how the PhD works, and so we explained the background as well as
we could.</p>
<p>We spent quite some time on the observation that the most important part of a
successful PhD is just never giving up.</p>
<p>Although never giving up is a chronic aspect, many PhD-veterans will tell you
that this adventure often includes a fairly acute existential crisis, mostly at
about the halfway mark.</p>
<p>This is when the candidate asks pertinent questions like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Why, oh why did I ever think this was a good idea?</li>
<li>Is this work really worth <em>anything</em>?</li>
<li>Does anyone really care about this?</li>
<li>I wonder what the non-academic job market is like at this moment?!</li>
</ul>
<p>Fortunately in many cases, the candidate gets through this process and emerges
from the other side of the ordeal ever so slightly stronger and wiser.</p>
<p>(For those of you who have been paying attention, this crisis is like the super
deluxe version of the <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">5-stage Creative Process</a>.)</p>
<p>I digress&hellip;</p>
<p>Talking more about the mechanics, GOU #1 asked how long a PhD thesis usually
is.</p>
<p>Off the top of my head I said: &ldquo;Around 50 thousand words, but there is of
course huge variation&rdquo;.</p>
<p>At that point she got out her phone (well, it&rsquo;s actually never not out) and
made a quick calculation, after which she quipped: &ldquo;Well, that&rsquo;s
straight-forward then. I&rsquo;ll spend one year planning, then I&rsquo;ll spend the year
after that writing only 136 words per day, and the year after that revising
everything to make it perfect.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was a simply lovely and humorous conversation to have at that moment, but
what a great point she made: If you can manage to write 136 words per day for a
year, you&rsquo;ll have 50000 words.</p>
<h3 id="the-slightly-modified-136-word-plan">The slightly modified 136 word plan</h3>
<p>136 words is really not that much if you look at it in isolation. The text
above, from right after &ldquo;I digress&hellip;&rdquo; until right before the heading above, is
exactly 136 words (if Emacs can be trusted).</p>
<p>To me the <a href="/tags/compounding/">compounding</a> nature of this act of writing such a paltry number of
words every day, but simply keeping at it for months and years, is quite
amazing.</p>
<p>So, thanks to my daughter&rsquo;s inspiration, I added a daily item to <a href="/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/">my habit
tracker</a> that says <em>Write 100 words towards publication</em>.</p>
<p>I hope she won&rsquo;t mind that I changed the limit to 100, simply because I would
like to increase my chances of being consistent and maintaining those <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">streaks</a>.</p>
<p>I have added the explicit qualifier that the 100 words I write should be
towards publication: This means that my intention should be for them to end up
either in a blog post, or perhaps a future book project, or any other form of
publication that is intended for public consumption.</p>
<p>Wish me luck folks! Even better, why not join me on this journey?!</p>
<h2 id="friendly-wishes">Friendly wishes</h2>
<p>Thank you friends for meeting me here.</p>
<p>I wish you all health and kindness and contentment.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #185: Starship GOU #1.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Dec 2019 22:35:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/</guid><description> Welcome back friends!
It&amp;rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.
Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file two weeks ago, but then I didn&amp;rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).
In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back friends!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a lovely, laid-back Sunday morning (the 8th, at 11:16 to be slightly more
precise) as I sit down to write this paragraph right here.</p>
<p>Smatterings of this post were already jotted down in this markdown text file
two weeks ago, but then I didn&rsquo;t see enough that was noteworthy, and then
everything suddenly Got Really Busy(tm).</p>
<p>In the end, all of that led up to this perfect little moment in space-time
right here and right now, and now I am grateful that I can try again to look
back at the passage of time from Monday November 18 to Sunday December 8, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/church_haven_run_huec8c0cac5ad4881be4c628c3d2944eb4_2936997_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view from a Friday afternoon arrival run along the Langebaan Lagoon in the West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="lecturing-old-school">Lecturing, old school.</h2>
<p>On Thursday, November 21, I gave a two hour lecture titled &ldquo;IoMT in Healthcare
Innovation&rdquo; at the <a href="https://www.usb.ac.za/">University of Stellenbosch Business
School</a>.</p>
<p>IoMT expands to the <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/bernardmarr/2018/01/25/why-the-internet-of-medical-things-iomt-will-start-to-transform-healthcare-in-2018/#46f18c694a3c">&ldquo;Internet of Medical
Things&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>My knowledge of IoT is spotty, and before giving this lecture I didn&rsquo;t even
know that the term &ldquo;IoMT&rdquo; existed.</p>
<p>Fortunately, it turns out that a lot of what we&rsquo;re currently doing at Stone
Three Healthcare (connecting patients with specialist care through
diagnostic-grade streaming of auscultation (and soon other modalities) device
data) can in fact be classified as IoMT.</p>
<p>Phew.</p>
<p>I would like to make the following observations based on this experience:</p>
<ol>
<li>I still really love getting up in front of a group of people to present
something. There are so many things that could go wrong, but when they go
right, the experience is great.</li>
<li>A two hour lecture is quite long, for both the students, even when they&rsquo;re
as advanced as this, <em>and</em> for the lecturer, especially when he is as out of
practice as this.
<ul>
<li>If there&rsquo;s a next time, I will either insert my own 15 minute break, or I
will get the class to break out into some sort of topic-strengthening
activity.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I had somehow forgotten how much time lecture preparation could take up,
even when you just had to present your own day-to-day reality.
<ul>
<li>BIG UP TO THE LECTURERS IN THE WHV AUDIENCE!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="productivity-system-tuneup">Productivity system tuneup.</h2>
<p>Last Sunday morning, as the family took a last swim at Kraalbaai before we had
to return home, I tried to apply some serious thinking (well, I did this by
stringing together a series of normal thinking moments) to the problem of
increasing my efficiency and focus at work.</p>
<p>At that moment, the scenery outside looked like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/preekstoel_from_kraalbaai_hubcf18b3ba1eaaeea912d514daa764f3e_1435561_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The view of the Preekstoel from Kraalbaai beach, West Coast National Park.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Regular readers will know that coming up with new ways to increase and maintain
focus is a life-long endeavour, which my subconscious self enjoys inventing
interesting new ways to subvert.</p>
<p>Conscious me has made peace with the fact that it has no choice but to keep on
working at its end of the bargain, until the very end.</p>
<p>With the opposing forces involved, my focus seems to oscillate with varying
frequencies between terrible and not too bad.</p>
<p>Anyways, having had a few days of fresh air and majestic scenery to jog the
neural circuitry, I applied myself, again, to the problem at hand.</p>
<p>I thought that sketching could help, so I was scribbling using a rather
impressive electronic pencil-analogue on a glass screen.</p>
<p>After several focused minutes (SEVERAL MINUTES, I TELL YOU!), I had a mindmap
with &ldquo;increase efficiency&rdquo; in a little oval at the center, arrows pointing
outwards into three terribly familiar habits, each in a rectangle <em>this</em> time,
and finally more connecting lines to lists of pretty plausible sounding reasons
for the three well-known habits.</p>
<p>The three rectangles were:</p>
<ol>
<li>Morning planning.</li>
<li>Inbox 0.</li>
<li>Pomodoro always.</li>
</ol>
<p>Over the years, these three items have made pretty regular appearances, in
various different forms, on this blog.</p>
<p>(I laughed when I just looked up <a href="/2010/09/20/an-indecent-proposal-weekly-head-voices-31/">this old 2010
post</a> and found a
pretty effective focus technique in the comments.)</p>
<p>Anyways, although the little thinking and drawing session documented here
seemingly did not result in any new revelations, the act of going through the
whole thought process, and documenting the results (again), seemed to have
contributed to a pretty great week in terms of focus.</p>
<p>I wrote down a little mantra for myself (definitely not fit for publication),
weaving together the three points above and the reasoning behind them, almost
like the affirmation in Wreckit Ralph&rsquo;s bad guy support group:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m bad, and that&rsquo;s good. I will never be good, and that&rsquo;s not bad. There&rsquo;s
no one I&rsquo;d rather be than me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>One of the most valuable lessons I learned from a book I once read about
procrastination (I&rsquo;ll look up the name later), is that it can make all the
difference once you explicitly verbalise, to yourself, that you have <em>chosen</em>
to take on difficult task X or Y.</p>
<p>Just saying these words somehow changes one&rsquo;s perception from being stuck with
difficult task X or Y, i.e. passive, to having taken agency, and having <em>decided</em>
to <em>commit</em>, i.e. active.</p>
<p>My humble focus mantra is following in this tradition.</p>
<p>(I really hope that my subversive sub-conscious is not paying attention right
now&hellip;)</p>
<h2 id="starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">Starship GOU #1, taxiing on the runway.</h2>
<p>Wednesday, December 4, was officially <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU
#1&rsquo;s</a> last day of primary school.</p>
<p>Although she seemed to navigate this emotional event with her customary
even-keeled demeanour, some of the moments were really just too big to let go by
without a good cry or two.</p>
<p>I was also happy to observe the level of retrospection and sunny candour she
applied to her informal post hoc analyses of above-mentioned crying moments.</p>
<p>I really hope that she strengthens and maintains this important human ability.</p>
<p>From our perspective as parents, it feels like the stakes are being raised
quite significantly.</p>
<p>The thing is, our oldest is now quite obviously becoming an adult.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like that scene at the end of the brilliant 2015 movie <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2096673/">Inside
Out</a>, where the protagonist&rsquo;s brain
console is suddenly upgraded to one with at least 9000 new knobs and dials.</p>
<p>Up to now, we (the parents) were GOU #1&rsquo;s only control system.</p>
<p>Now it is becoming quite clear that she is increasingly forming her own
opinions, and making her own decisions.</p>
<p>In most cases, the physical constraints of a 13 year old living in her parent&rsquo;s
house still afford us some level of control.</p>
<p>However, relying on that would be missing the point entirely.</p>
<p>You see, we find ourselves in the moment of truth, when the past 13 years of
mostly gentle programming has to start executing all by itself.</p>
<p>Our little GOU #1, our first co-created human intelligence, is preparing to go
out into the world.</p>
<p>She has not taken off yet, so we do our best to apply the final touches to her
already promising software.</p>
<p>We exhort her regularly: <em>Be useful. Use your (rational) brain. Be kind. Find
the kindness in others.</em></p>
<p>In the darkness, when we are at our weakest, stripped down to our core, we do
what all parents do:</p>
<p>We worry, and we hope with a passion, the intensity of which it is difficult to
describe, that our offspring units do manage to <a href="/2012/03/04/rhythm-of-the-night-weekly-head-voices-66/#life-philosophy-that-works">generate their own motivation,
to manufacture meaning, and to create
love</a>.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/vergelegen_20191124_hu6063bec6cc249a2da3defeb612329a88_4314572_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
This could be a runway, but it is the entrance to Vergelegen Wine Estate. At
this point, I was in fact running on this way.
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>