<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Gou-1 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-1/</link><description>Recent content in Gou-1 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/gou-1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #261: Father's day</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</guid><description>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.
Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive
The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.
&amp;ndash; Marcel Proust
Bliss It&amp;rsquo;s father&amp;rsquo;s day today.
When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250428_clarence_pano.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_9407df7811cef8cf.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_4f5b997776ce1c56.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_72fa3b251facc47.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp"
            

        
            alt="Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<blockquote>
<p>The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.</p>
<p>&ndash; Marcel Proust</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="bliss">Bliss</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s father&rsquo;s day today.</p>
<p>When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</p>
<p>Hearing that we were up, GOU #2 came out of her room, with a beautiful illustration she had made for (and of!) me. (GOU #2 has found her passion in drawing. She practises on most days, and her skill and talent are very obvious.)</p>
<p>Soon after, GOU #1 arrived home with flat whites (my favourite), fresh ciabatta and croissants from the bakery, and hugs.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m trying to say here is that when your offspring units all tell you in their different ways that they appreciate you being their dad, when you&rsquo;re fundamentally dedicated to and deeply grateful for being just that, and those very offspring units constitute the whole focus of this important life endeavour, you better hope that you are able to keep those eyes dry.</p>
<h2 id="vo-max-redux">VO₂ Max redux</h2>
<p>One of my <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">exercise goals for 2024</a> was to reach a VO₂ Max of at least (HAHAHA) 50.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t make it in 2024, but I also didn&rsquo;t do anything other than just my normal running during the year. I know that I should probably engage in some high intensity interval training of some sort if I really want to move the needle, but I run because I like running and not because I want to be fit, although I do want to be fit. (It&rsquo;s complicated being a teenager.)</p>
<p>At the start of 2025, I stated, much more softly this time, that I would maybe <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">still like to hit that 50 VO₂ Max</a>.</p>
<p>Again I realized I would have probably have to <em>do</em> something interval-ly about it, but again I kept on postponing.</p>
<p>WELL KIDS it turns out that postponing can also be a winning strategy! On Monday, May 19, my Garmin reported that I had indeed hit a VO₂ Max of 50, which, <a href="https://www8.garmin.com/manuals/webhelp/GUID-C001C335-A8EC-4A41-AB0E-BAC434259F92/EN-US/GUID-1FBCCD9E-19E1-4E4C-BD60-1793B5B97EB3.html">according to its tables</a>, places me at the bottom of the coveted top-most category for my age and gender, namely <em>Superior</em>.</p>
<p>I always knew it, but thanks anyways Garmin!</p>
<p>P.S. I do have to deflate my <em>superiority</em> a bit by reminding us all that, in addition to finding myself at the bottom of the superior range, I have also only recently entered my current age section, giving me an extra advantage. Jokes aside, 50 at 50 is not bad, so allow me to bask for a while.</p>
<h2 id="org-mode-timestamps-in-obsidian">org-mode timestamps in obsidian</h2>
<p>One feature I have really been missing in Obsidian since <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my recent break-up with Org-mode</a> is the amazing org timestamps.</p>
<p>There is no real convention in Obsidian, whilst in Org-mode timestamps <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Timestamps.html">are well-defined and quite functional</a>. My &ldquo;old&rdquo; notes are scattered with them: time ranges, scheduled times, deadlines, random timestamps inside random text notes.</p>
<p>The time logging script <a href="/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/#loggin-time">I mentioned previously</a> made use of the dataview-convention of adding timestamps to work items for example:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 (start:: 2025-05-20T07:55) - (end:: 2025-05-20T08:10)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; which did work but was no fun to work with.</p>
<p>Long story short, I could not resist for much longer, and so I hacked together a new Obsidian plugin called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian-org-timestamps">Org timestamps</a>.</p>
<p>As you can see in the comparative screenshots below, I&rsquo;ve copied the org-mode timestamp and time range format verbatim, with the additional bonus of rendering these timestamps nicely in preview mode, inspired by <a href="https://github.com/minad/org-modern">the Emacs package org-modern</a>.</p>
<p>Deviating from org-mode proper, my plugin also renders date-less timestamps &ndash; I often use these when adding entries to daily file. Speaking of which, full org timestamps can have <code>[[...]]</code> links around the date parts so that they link back to the relevant daily file.</p>








    


<figure><a href="obsidian-org-timestamps.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_e1ef46eb4edabd57.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_2719acebe5e07bc9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_f52dbf2785777e5.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>In addition to the rendering, the plugin also offers commands to move any timestamps to the nearest 5 minutes forward or backward, similar to what org-mode does with <code>shift-up/down</code>, and a feature I have always used multiple times per day.</p>
<p>Putting all of this together, my monthly time logging files now has entries that look like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 &lt;2025-05-20 07:55-08:10&gt;
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; and I can tweak those timestamps with the adjustment commands.</p>
<p>I have adapted the logging script to support both the old dataview-style and org-timestamp-style timestamps, and now the barely usable UX has become a tad less barely.</p>
<p><em>(10 minutes later&hellip;)</em></p>
<p>Because I keep on mentioning the script, I guess it&rsquo;s time to <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian_dataview_timelogging">put it online</a>, albeit extremely barely. Let me know in the comments below if you are the one other user on the planet who would like to try this.</p>
<h2 id="my-friend-this-is-the-end-again">My friend this is the end again</h2>
<p>This was one of the most stubborn WHVs I have pushed out in a very long time.</p>
<p>Before it became this hard, it used to be easier: Somehow there was always something to talk about, either interesting or entertaining, or both.</p>
<p>Although this could also just be another symptom of  me getting older, it does feel like the whole online landscape has changed quite substantially.</p>
<p>Up until recently, it was only dopamine-targeting social media which affected the way people read (or don&rsquo;t) blog posts, but these days I imagine that I&rsquo;m also detecting a whiff of AI-nihilism. Although I still feel strongly about writing each of these words by myself, the experience of the resultant output happens on the background of machines that can now generate hundreds of perfectly-written versions of this post in an instant.</p>
<p>Anyways, I plan to continue with this labour of love, even as it becomes increasingly difficult.</p>
<p>P.S. My recent reading / book-listening has taken me on fascinating journeys through neuroscience and consciousness. Before reaching this point right here, I mistakenly thought that I would share more about them in this post. Instead I&rsquo;m going to leave you with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I am not a thing in the world; I am the space in which the world is happening.</p>
<p>&ndash; Richard Lang</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #259: Backbone</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</guid><description> Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!
(I just learned that the English connoisseur comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved connaisseur (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little oi.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







    


<figure><a href="bettys_sunset.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_84d7d5fb2023d1f3.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_94ef9e4fb9dd976e.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_b061658b14bcf3ec.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!</p>
<p>(I <em>just</em> learned that the English <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/connoisseur"><em>connoisseur</em> comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling</a>. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved <em>connaisseur</em> (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little <em>oi</em>.)</p>
<h2 id="how-do-you-do-fellow-humans">How do you do, fellow humans?</h2>
<p>This Sunday morning I browsed through all of my Obsidian daily entries, starting from Monday January 20, the day after <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/">The 2024 to 2025 transition post</a> appeared, because the urge to write here has become quite persistent of late, an urge that is clearly quite oblivious to my feeling that it has become increasingly more tricky to make the time to sit down and focus on just this one thing.</p>
<p>I, very briefly I should add, considered feeding all of those daily posts to one of our artificial friends to extract highlights, but for the time-being, I really like that every word you read here was produced by my laborious and messy (fluids-based, for the most part) biology-based process.</p>
<p>This means that I read every single stupid word I wrote in those daily entries, re-experienced various emotions, some of them transformed by the ever-changing self, while I read them, and let those ideas all simmer for a while in the wetware mostly enclosed by my skull, before sitting down here and producing a new set of emotions whilst typing out a bunch of new words on this (mechanical) keyword.</p>
<p>Blood, sweat and tears my friends, blood sweat and tears.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Since my last entry here, I&rsquo;ve been reading a lot more, something that I&rsquo;m really happy about.</p>
<p>Besides the deep-seated and strong instinct that reading good books makes me a better human, it also turns out to be an <em>excellent</em> doom-scrolling suppressant, by virtue of simply pushing that activity out of one&rsquo;s daily schedule.</p>
<p>Apart from that motivation, what has made a huge difference in my reading volume was adding audiobooks as well as Zotero on my laptop to the reading modality mix.</p>
<p>Where I previously would only read on my Kindle e-reader, I&rsquo;ve discovered that picking the right medium for the right book means I can comfortably use these three channels during different phases of the day.</p>
<p>In the evening right before closing my eyes, I usually read fiction on the Kindle. After 10 to 20 minutes of reading, my eyes start closing of their own accord and my brain shuts down. Current Kindle book: <a href="https://www.gregegan.net/MORPHOTROPHIC/MORPHOTROPHIC.html">Morphotrophic by Greg Egan</a>. <a href="/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/#permutation-city">Egan has previously appeared on this blog</a> for a much older creation which I really loved.</p>
<p>During the day in the car on short commutes, I prefer to read non-fiction books like <a href="https://www.ynharari.com/book/nexus/">Nexus by Yuval Harari</a> (which I loved by the way). With Nexus at 1.5x speed, which is still very comfortable, it was around 17 hours of listening time which went by a lot faster than I expected. I&rsquo;m currently on [<em>Behave: The Biology of Humans at Our Best and Worst</em> by Robert M. Sapolsky] which is super entertaining and extremely successful at repeatedly blowing my mind.</p>
<p>Some non-fiction books deserve even closer attention, like <a href="https://www.abriefhistoryofintelligence.com/">Max Bennett&rsquo;s <em>A Brief History of Intelligence</em></a>, which I started reading on my Kindle but then completed on my laptop, using the fantastic epub reader in Zotero. With this tool I can make highlights and notes to my heart&rsquo;s content.</p>








    


<figure><a href="screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_fd5d3cc24c0400cb.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_ded6f76846ff592d.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_a10ae5587078729c.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>On the topic of Zotero, the two features that would make it even more perfect for me are <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/pull/836">the iOS epub support</a>, so I can open annotated epubs on the go, and <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/issues/597">iOS webpage snapshot support</a>, so that I can save <a href="https://github.com/gildas-lormeau/SingleFile">SingleFile</a> snapshots of web pages from my phone like on desktop, and not just the link.</p>
<h3 id="thanks-for-nothing-amazon">Thanks for nothing Amazon</h3>
<p>On that topic, <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/02/psa-amazon-kills-download-transfer-via-usb-option-for-kindles-this-week/">on February 26 Amazon killed the Kindle &ldquo;download &amp; transfer via USB&rdquo; feature</a>, the exact feature that I&rsquo;ve always used to make copies of Kindle titles for my own use, most often for highlighting and further study, sometimes leading to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/book/">book notes posts</a>.</p>
<p>Although I really appreciated the convenience of e.g. hearing about a book, and then being able to purchase and start reading that book within minutes, this user-hostile move by Amazon is the last straw for me.  All the way back in 2016, <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2016/08/21/amazon-owns-your-ebooks/">friend Stéfan warned us all about the Kindle Swindle</a>, i.e. the way that Amazon restricts ebook rights far more than necessary, and is in essence able to &ldquo;switch off&rdquo; all ebooks that you have bought.</p>
<p>For me personally, this latest move just means that I will drastically reduce my spending on Kindle books, and anything else from Amazon, as far as possible.</p>
<h2 id="101-productivity-hacks-for-stubborn-people">101 productivity hacks for stubborn people</h2>
<p>Also known as The Productivity Section!</p>
<h3 id="a-bientôt-monsieur-org">A bientôt monsieur Org</h3>
<p>In the 24/25 year transition post I talked about <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#emacs-and-obsidian">my apparently eternally brewing personal tension between Emacs and Obsidian</a>.</p>
<p>It looks like I might have found myself in the third <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_stages_of_grief">stage of grief</a>, namely <em>bargaining</em>, when I wrote that I would explore the interplay between the two poles of Emacs and Obsidian.</p>
<p>Well, as I write this, it feels like I might have reached the fifth and final stage, namely <em>acceptance</em>, acceptance of the fact that orgmode (note, not Emacs, but orgmode), although far more powerful and flexible, is probably always going to be the silo that it currently is, in contrast to markdown (note, not necessarily Obsidian) which, while functionality-wise is but a shadow of orgmode, is hugely more accessible and inter-operates with everyone and their dogs.</p>
<p>You see, since writing that transition post, I&rsquo;ve been creating more and more markdown notes, to the extent that I keep on running into the inconvenience of orgmode nexus nodes which I can in theory link to from markdown, but with links that are not as fully featured as markdown to markdown links.</p>
<p>It really does seem like &ldquo;interplay&rdquo; is turning into &ldquo;dominance&rdquo;, if you&rsquo;ll excuse my multiple layers of innuendo here.</p>
<p>And so after a really good 10 year run as orgmode-disciple, as chronicled by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">10+ years of vxlabs posts on the topic</a>, a bunch of <a href="/tags/orgmode/">appearances on this blog</a> and even <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">the orgmode-exocortex</a>, it&rsquo;s time to read the writing on the wall, writing that upon closer inspection has turned out to be in markdown format after all.</p>
<h3 id="productivity-hack-of-the-year">Productivity hack of the year</h3>
<p>In a textbook case of <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2024/06/07/report-death/">greatly exaggerated rumours of someone&rsquo;s demise</a>, my orgmode isn&rsquo;t completely dead yet&hellip;</p>
<p>By far the most effective productivity hack I&rsquo;ve implemented in many months, in terms of actual focus hours gained, has been the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar">orgmode-based pomodoro timer I hacked together and wrote about in my other OTHER website TIL section</a>.</p>
<p>While it was already helpful to have a boring text-based pomodoro-timer display a countdown on my macOS menubar, I had wildly underestimated how much impact the addition of <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar#double-bonus-macos-do-not-disturb-during-pomodoro">the automatic do-not-disturb mode</a> would have.</p>
<p>When I start the 25 minute pomodoro focus timer, my script automatically activates the so-called do-not-disturb &ldquo;focus&rdquo; across all of my (Apple) devices. For those 25 minutes, absolutely nothing pings or alerts, and only calls by my my inner-inner circle can get through. When the 25 minutes are up, DnD is disabled across all devices, and I can see to any emergencies that might have occurred.</p>
<p>(🍅 These particular paragraphs are being typed within such an interruption-proof pomodoro BTW.)</p>
<h2 id="how-are-the-children">How are the children?</h2>
<p>Why thank you for asking!</p>
<p>Here I would like to mention that Genetic Offspring Unit #1 (GOU#1) has now experienced the first few weeks of industrial engineering at university (which is the same as the first few weeks of most of the engineering disciplines) and seems to be loving it to bits.</p>
<p>It brings me great joy that, in spite of the fact that she is a wonderfully well-adjusted and socially graceful human, her engineering DNA is shining through brilliantly. This way of thinking suits her, she just seems to get it, and she&rsquo;s really <em>enjoying the work</em>.</p>
<p>P.S. It also brings me joy, but also a tiny bit of concern, that she really enjoys and also sometimes makes dad jokes <em>AT ME</em>.</p>
<h2 id="spiritual-hygiene-backbone">Spiritual hygiene backbone</h2>
<p>All of that reading I wrote about a few paragraphs back somehow happens even when my days seem to fall apart due to general life chaos, various distractions many of my own (unintentional design) and/or due to will power failure on my part.</p>
<p>So on those days, when I finally fall asleep reading, I console myself with the affirmation that the day was not <em>complete</em> chaos, at least I&rsquo;ve done some reading&hellip;</p>
<p>The same goes for my running.</p>
<p>A seemingly low-level function somewhere in my system <em>needs</em> to take me out running an average of three times a week.</p>
<p>Even when I don&rsquo;t want to, I often find myself standing outside in my shoes and ready to go.</p>
<p>It does help that I&rsquo;ve programmed myself with the mantra &ldquo;If you&rsquo;re wondering whether you should go run the answer is YES&rdquo;.</p>
<p>During my many low-power moments, that mantra often nudges me over the edge.</p>
<p>My daily writing habit also seems to be getting stronger.</p>
<p>I might be tired, or distracted, but <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#multiplicity-of-you">one of the voices</a> often gets me to write with mind-tricks like &ldquo;oh just a bullet or two man, surely you can manage that?&rdquo; to which my simple mind succumbs, and before I know it, I&rsquo;ve written a few more bullets, and maybe even a paragraph or two.</p>
<p>Unbeknownst to simple mind (shhhht), retro- and introspection have now been performed, and prepared for future review.</p>
<p>I have now come to realise that these three habits, namely reading, running and writing, and their various positive feedback loops, together form a pretty decent <em>spiritual hygiene backbone</em>.</p>
<p>Especially when the rest feels like it wants to flop around or even fall apart, this backbone is a robust, reliable and, quite importantly, <em>simple</em> construct that defines my desired internal structure, enabling me to maintain focus and humanity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2024 to 2025 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to the year 2025!
We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this traditional yearly transition blog post here to keep you busy in the meantime.
The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2025!</p>
<p>We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this <a href="/tags/transition">traditional yearly transition blog post</a> here to keep you busy in the meantime.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20241228-st-francis-light-house.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a7c8fad0a4fb3336.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_c471bba5b301f4e3.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_7e36ecc6dd88d868.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp"
            

        
            alt="The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For those of you who are new here, 1) welcome! and 2) the traditional yearly transition post is where I both ramble semi-coherently on about the year that is closest to its conclusion and also speculate a bit about the year that is closest to its inception.</p>
<p>The main audience for this post is me &ndash; writing this up and the concomitant thinking and formulating bits form an important part of my maintenance process &ndash; but to anyone else who is reading this, there is hopefully something of value (or just a bit of entertainment) for you in these words. In any case, I am super happy that you&rsquo;re here!</p>
<h2 id="life-events">Life events</h2>
<p>In 2024, <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#i-turned-50">I turned 50</a> while <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#gou-1-turned-18">GOU#1 turned 18</a>, finished high school and is now on her way to university.</p>
<p>I mention these two in the same breath, because looking back it feels like the 5 years of her high school, a substantial chunk of time in terms of her development, went by in a flash.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s almost like we blinked <a href="/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">when she was still our little girl going to high school</a> and now suddenly she is an adult, and we finally feel like actual adults (aka old people) ourselves.</p>
<p>Although these have been amazing years for us, this experience of a whole period of life flashing by, through the lense of our children&rsquo;s development into adults, is a stark reminder to strive even harder to experience the living daylights out of every single moment that we are blessed with.</p>
<p>If all goes according to plan, we will have two more blink-blink-another-high-school-journey-is-complete experiences (GOU#2 is now in her second year of that journey, GOU#3 has a few years to go before she can start) so we should probably try to blink far less often.</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>After the dip both this blog and I went through in 2023 (total of 3 WHV posts&hellip;) and a very slow blogging start in 2024, it does feel like I might slowly be getting my WHV groove back, which seems to be evidenced by 66% more WHV posting in 2024, i.e. a whole 5 WHV posts! (Contrast this with the historic average of one post every two weeks.)</p>
<p>In the introduction to <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/">WHV #255 You lift me up</a> I speculate a bit about the reasons for my hiatus (I didn&rsquo;t mention there that maybe 2023 was actually just a real downer for me) and the current potential revival.</p>
<p>In addition to the posts here, I published <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">12 technical posts over on at the vxlabs</a> and a whole bunch of short howtos / recipes in the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">brand new TiL section of my other-OTHER website</a>. WHV #255 <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">explains the motivation behind the TiL section</a>.</p>
<p>I am also quite happy about the fact that I wrote a daily entry in my private diary for a large part of 2024, and this is something that I would like to continue, hopefully for an even larger part of 2025.</p>
<p>Spending some time every day to review that day, where the review is enriched by the deliberate activitity of trying to formulate everything into a story that I can write down, helps me to make sense of everything.</p>
<p>Writing in general seems to modulate positively my experience of reality.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a lot about this idea in various posts on this blog, but allow me to surface <a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#the-describers">two relevant sections from WHV 180</a>, and especially the quote below (but you should go read those two sections):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less faulty entity.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>My secret running goal for 2024 was to do 25km of running every week. In my head this was auto-simplified to 1200km for the year (you know, the way one often calculates a month as 4 weeks), but of course we&rsquo;re talking 1300km.</p>
<p>Well, I failed at all of these goals!</p>
<p>However, I did manage to run a total of 1149.7km over the year, which comes to an average of 22.1km per week, which I am pretty OK with. I had over 100 hours of fun (I truly enjoy running) and no injuries that I can remember.</p>
<p>The training calendar below shows that August was my laziest month, but that&rsquo;s because August has the worst weather, and because I was away for a week visiting my Dutch family and getting many tens of thousands of dancing steps instead. The calendar also shows how I made a last ditch effort in December to close the gap with my goal as much as possible.</p>










<figure><a href="20250101-strava-training-calendar.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_e13adc1c4101c63a.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_2caa5fcc1a219359.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_57229ed99a10234e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You might remember <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">my three metrics-focused goals from last year&rsquo;s post</a>, namely 50 consecutive push-ups, VO<sub>2</sub> Max of at least 50 and a resting state heart rate of 50 or under&hellip;</p>
<p>Well, 50 consecutive push-ups was not that hard, Apple Health reports my average resting state heart rate for 2024 as 48 BPM (this would be mostly via my Garmin Forerunner 245 and more recently 265) but my VO<sub>2</sub> briefly peaked at 49 (some time after I turned 50) before settling back on 48. I  would have loved that 50, but <a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/blog/fitness/whats-a-good-vo2-max-for-me/">48 is not the worst for a man of my age</a>.</p>
<p>My real goal for the coming year is the same as last year: I want to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>The older I get and the more I learn, the more I understand that with exercise, the more hours I can spend every week doing it, of course maintaining balance with the rest of my life (see life systems further down), the better my meat-coated skeleton will work, and the happier the ghost driving it will be.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’re a ghost driving a meat-coated skeleton made from stardust; what do you have to be scared of?</p>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2022/10/13/ghost-stardust/">@rat_sandwich on twitter, January 31, 2013</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>P.S. of course I will again go for 25km of running per week. I think logging substantially more than 120 hours of activities in Strava will be good. I might even give that VO<sub>2</sub> Max goal another shot.</p>
<p>P.P.S. I read <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/outlive/">Peter Attia&rsquo;s book Outlive</a> a few months ago. This is a detailed and practical manual for healthy living. There&rsquo;s a lot in there, but at the core he wants you, while you still have any say in the matter, to become as fit (measured by our friend VO<sub>2</sub> Max) and as strong (measured by grip strength) as you possibly can. You see, from middle age we&rsquo;re all on a downward curve, and there&rsquo;s not much we can do about it, except ensuring that we start as high as possible.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. It&rsquo;s funny; back in school, I thought little of athleticism, because it was a jock thing, and the jocks were generally not very kind to nerd-kind (my people). Now that I&rsquo;m older and quite ironically due to my nerdy lifelong learning habits, I strive for us much athleticism as I can &ldquo;fit&rdquo; in (jock joke harr harr).</p>
<h3 id="diet">Diet</h3>
<p>During this post&rsquo;s generously long incubation, I thought it worth adding here my approach to eating.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been practising 16-8 time-restricted eating (intermittent fasting in some circles) about 95% of the time since somewhere in 2019. I first <a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">wrote about it in WHV 186</a>, and then in <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#i-really-don-t-like-breakfast">WHV 221 I came out and stated the beef I have with breakfast</a> (that pun might be too heavy for this post).</p>
<p>Anyways, while I still believe that breakfast is bad for most people, I know that the scientific world has not yet reached consensus on time-restricted eating for healthy folks.</p>
<p>However, there is considerably more consensus that lowering daily caloric intake is good for most people.</p>
<p>For me, 16-8 TRE, where I simply don&rsquo;t ingest anything besides water and black coffee from about 7 in the evening until about noon the next day, is an extremely practical and especially low-effort way to reduce caloric intake.</p>
<p>When I do eat, the portions are modest, I try to stick to natural and unprocessed where I can and I keep an eye on protein.</p>
<p>When I do break these rules, I do so with deliberation. Great food, great wine, great beer and the company of friends and family, especially when combined, constitute a perfect reason to break all of these rules.</p>
<p>In short, reduce caloric intake, increase per-calorie value and/or enjoyment!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and Tools</h2>
<p>This is the place where I summarise (read: ramble on about) the current state of my digital tools and systems. If you&rsquo;re going to skip a (nerdy) section, this is the one! You can dive back in at <a href="#life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</a>.</p>
<p>I am one of those people who <em>regularly</em> finds and uses information from notes that I made.</p>
<p>If I have the note, and I often do because I make an effort to write stuff down with the lowest possible friction but the highest possible chance of being found again, this is generally miles faster than finding the information online, even with tools like the <a href="https://kagi.com/">premium search engine Kagi</a> which I have been using regularly for a few weeks now.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-and-obsidian">Emacs and Obsidian</h3>
<p>A year ago I <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#systems-and-tools">experienced a bit of a crisis of (Emacs) faith</a>.</p>
<p>Whilst that was more of a clash between the either-or poles of Emacs and Obsidian, I am now at a place where I&rsquo;m finding increasing uses for Obisidian as an <em>additional</em> note-taking tool, working on the same collection of hundreds of org-mode and a growing number of markdown files.</p>
<p>Emacs and org-roam treat <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">markdown files as if they are native org-roam nodes</a>. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/BBazard/obsidian-orgmode-cm6">Benoit Bazard&rsquo;s fantastic new CodeMirror 6 org-mode plugin for Obsidian</a> and my <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Monitor-rclone-cron-job-with-Home-Assistant">rclone + syncthing syncing setup for iPhone</a>, I have semi-usable org database support on my phone.</p>
<p><a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> and since recently <a href="https://orgro.org/">Orgro</a> are great for editing org files in the iPhone, but they are missing the searching and discovery, let&rsquo;s call it <em>note management</em>, aspects of a tool like Obsidian.</p>
<p>Long but quite important-to-me story short, it looks like for the time being I&rsquo;ll continue to use both Emacs and Obsidian for note-taking. Because interoperability is not perfect, there will be some natural gravitational pull towards the one or the other which I have decided to explore.</p>
<p>At the moment, it looks like I might be writing more of my atomic notes as markdown files, whilst using org for the lab journal / logbook and project management type of notes.</p>
<p>On a deeper note, the Obsidian team is doing fantastic work.</p>
<p>Apart from their <a href="https://stephango.com/file-over-app"><em>file over app</em> philosophy</a>, Obsidian is <em>programmable</em> as can be witnessed by the thriving extension ecosystem.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?id=ai-chat-as-md">written a modest extension</a> to test this out from the inside. The programmability is not as extensive as that of Emacs, but it runs everywhere, even on mobile devices, and it might be extensive enough for the note-taking platform that Obsidian has become.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Emacs on and off since the late 90s, but for the past 10 years it has become an always-running and integral part of my life. It feels really strange, disconcerting if I&rsquo;m being honest, that it seems to be losing its core spot.</p>
<p>I console myself in these moments with the observation that science must trump dogma, always.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m writing this post in Emacs.</p>
<h4 id="til">TiL</h4>
<p>Thanks to Obsidian, my other, OTHER website <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">now has a &ldquo;today I learned&rdquo; (TIL) section</a> at <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">charlbotha.com/til</a>, published directly from a sub-directory of my main notes directory.</p>
<p>The benefit is that there is even less friction than usual and, perhaps more importantly, the psychological friction has also been reduced because I have convinced myself that the posts there are just notes and not true blog posts.</p>
<h3 id="honorable-tool-mentions-zotero-and-quarto">Honorable tool mentions: Zotero and Quarto</h3>
<p>After <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#omnivore-is-no-more">my distastrous recommendation of Omnivore turned into a disaster</a>, it is with some emotional trepidation but intellectual confidence (thanks to file over app and its staunchly open source nature) that I can re-recommend Zotero as a reference (of all kinds!) management tool for the long term.</p>
<p>After I last mentioned it on my blog, I have been using it quite intensively, and <a href="https://bsky.app/hashtag/zotero?author=charlbotha.com">I keep on running into delightful features</a>, like the built-in PDF reader&rsquo;s pop-up visualization of citations and image references.</p>
<p>A more recent but high power entry into my toolbelt is <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, which I will contend strikes a fantastic usability-power balance in the world of technical document and presentation authoring. I&rsquo;ve now used it, in anger, to write a fairly extensive technical document, along with the afore-mentioned Zotero and <a href="https://retorque.re/zotero-better-bibtex/">Better BibTeX</a> for reference management, and the experience was magically smooth. To seal the deal, by the end I used Quarto to generate an attractive-looking docx for interoperability with the other stakeholders, but my contact time with Word was mercifully minimised.</p>
<h3 id="my-micro-blogging-history-2008---2025">My micro-blogging history 2008 - 2025</h3>
<p>Twitter says I created my account there in December of 2008. However, <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">this blog here says I only started using it in April of 2009</a>. (Twitter first launched in July of 2006.)</p>
<p>Some years later in 2016, coincidentally right before the previous Trumpocalypse, I wrote a post naively suggesting that we should <a href="/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/">replace twitter with something better (blogs&hellip;)</a> due to the risk of Twitter possibly going bad (ahem) and to the observation then that it was (then already) doing a crappy job keeping out abusive users (AHEM).</p>
<p>That post <a href="/2016/11/20/look-mom-hacker-news-front-page/">reached the front page of Hacker News</a>, and was thus read and discussed over there (and probably in the comments here) by tens of thousands of nerds, and a surprisingly small share of the usual &ldquo;Ackchyually&rdquo;-Bros.</p>
<p>(Please allow me this little tangent: A mental model that will really ease your time on sites like HN and reddit, is that the person on the other side, especially when they come across as super confident and assertive, is probably <strong>not</strong> an expert, not even by a long shot, on the topic that they are so confidently mansplaining. In fact, they are probably the least qualified to say anything. ChatGPT avant le lettre one might say. Ok back to your regular programming&hellip;)</p>
<p>Needless to say, my specific idea of replacing twitter with&hellip; blogs and rss was not implemented by the internet, at least not at that point&hellip;</p>
<p>When Musk acquired Twitter in October of 2022, the writing started appearing on the wall, at first vaguely, but with more and more definition as the months went on. I started looking for micro-blogging alternatives that were not twitter.</p>
<p>At first Mastodon looked too complicated, but then someone setup a <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#emacs-mastodon-server-was-irresistible">mastodon server dedicated to Emacs and I was immediately sold</a>.</p>
<p>However, Mastodon indeed turned out to be too complex and fundamentally quite fragile (all but the larger instances have a just a volunteer human or two behind them), leading to the owner of my favourite instance bascially being harassed to such an extent that it was better for him to get out of this business and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@cpbotha/113340325817581254">shut the Emacs mastodon server down</a>.</p>
<p>When I saw this announcement, I was disheartened.</p>
<p>When I read that Mastodon supports message export, but not message import, meaning that my posts would languish in a sad archive file somewhere, I was convinced that I had to try something out that was not Mastodon.</p>
<p>In parallel to my Mastodon efforts, I did also try Threads and was quite enthusiastic about its scale, and the speed with which Meta managed to build it, but I didn&rsquo;t manage to get any sort of interaction there. I think that it might be more geared for the Instagram model of influencers broadcasting to large groups of followers, in contrast to a more collaborative setup. (Urgh, the recent news about Meta&rsquo;s new &ldquo;free speech&rdquo; overhaul is additional motivation for me to spend even less energy there.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, it turns out that the newer and shinier microblogging service Bluesky was conceived in 2019 with the goal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluesky">&ldquo;to find or develop an open and decentralized standard for social media that would give users more control over their data and experience&rdquo;</a>, precisely the sort of thing that has suddenly become even more painfully relevant with the advent of the Trumpocalypse part deux, now with more Musk-power.</p>
<p>Long story short, in a very short time, Bluesky has proven to be almost exactly the microblogging platform that I enjoy participating in. Lots of human interaction, no ads, many different user-contributed algorithms to choose from, including just seeing the stuff your people post, in the order that they post it &ndash; it really feels like the thing was put together with semi-normal human interaction as the central concern.</p>
<p>Up to now, it also feels like <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#bluesky-is-my-new-micro-blogging-thing-of-choice">many folks on there prefer being decent to each other</a>, something I militantly (haha) support.</p>
<p>Some mastodon folks are downright unhappy with bluesky, because they feel that it&rsquo;s not truly decentralized like mastodon.</p>
<p>Thing is, Bluesky has chosen a different spot on the usability - decentralization spectrum, and and my opinion is exactly usable and decentralised enough for what it needs to be and do at this moment in time.</p>
<p>Looking slightly further into the future, there are well-funded initiatives like <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/13/24342799/free-our-feeds-social-media-ecosystem-at-protocol-bluesky">Free our feeds</a>, ideologically and technologically supported by the Bluesky company but otherwise unconnected, which has amongst its <a href="https://freeourfeeds.com/">goals to &ldquo;build independently hosted infrastructure (a second &lsquo;relay&rsquo;) so that Bluesky users, developers and researchers always have full access to the stream of content and data no matter what the company decides to do in future&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>If you would like to know more, Faine Greenwood has written <a href="https://little-flying-robots.ghost.io/the-great-bluesky-migration-i-answer-some-of-your-questions/">this great Bluesky explainer</a>.</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</h2>
<p>My Life Systems are the guiding principles, rules, personal values and bags of tips that I have explicitly defined and refined over the years to help me be the best human that I can be.</p>
<p>Note: I write these up primarily as a reminder to myself. If it comes across as prescriptive, please remember that I&rsquo;m telling <em>me</em> how to live my life. I can do this, because I <em>am</em> the boss of me.</p>
<h3 id="core">Core</h3>
<p>You&rsquo;ll be happy to hear that the core of my Life Systems 2025 is exactly the same as the previous edition <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">Life Systems 2024</a>, except for the version number increase, and the concomitant price increase. (taking a leaf here from the Intel playbook!)</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to read <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">the 2024 write-up</a>, here is the compressed version:</p>
<p><em>Guiding principles:</em> 1. Love 2. Science. <em>Two no three rules for achieving great success in life, or just surviving, whichever comes first:</em> 1. Be useful. 2. be likable and 3. evolve. <em>Personal values:</em> 1. Be kind. 2. Be grateful. 3. Attend fully to the now. 4. Enjoy life with family and with my friends. 5. Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers. 6. Be there for my family. 7. Add value through work. 8. Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise. 9. Build and/or fix something. 10. Learn new things. 11. Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</p>
<h3 id="balance">Balance</h3>
<p>What I have been thinking about this year, especially when things get quite busy, is the sometimes tricky practice of applying balance to one&rsquo;s personal values.</p>
<p>A straight-forward example is when important work obligations start impacting my sleep or exercise schedule, in which case I have to apply balance and tone down slightly the ambition to fulfil personal value no 7.</p>
<p>It can easily get more tricky however; when something on that list of personal values, which is important to you, starts taking up more than its fair share of energy, that will come at the cost of all of the other endeavours that you value.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have a hard and fast rule for this, only the measure of remembering to <em>pay attention</em> also at that meta-level so that one can make suitable balancing adjustments when required.</p>
<h3 id="work-hard-party-hard-rest-hard">Work hard. Party hard. Rest hard.</h3>
<p>A lesson that has only become clearer for me over the years is that we humans function best when we are able to focus on one thing at a time, and when we have as few things as possible on the list that we select from.</p>
<p>This works at all scales of life, from what task do I work on during this half-hour all the way up to my main priority for today, or my three main priorities for this year.</p>
<p>The challenge in applying this lesson is three-fold:</p>
<ol>
<li>Know which thing to focus on at any time,</li>
<li>reduce switching between things and yet</li>
<li>get to all of the things that you should get to.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you have all three of these covered, then comes the truly difficult part: <strong>Attend fully to the now.</strong></p>
<p>Those of us who are lucky get about 4000 weeks of life.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not truly present in the thing that you&rsquo;ve chosen at this moment, you are not using that allotted time to its fullest extent.</p>
<p>You can never ever get that time back.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like you&rsquo;re in a Michelin-starred restaurant, and instead of going power level 9000 with all of your senses and your thoughts and your whole being into <em>experiencing</em> that food with your favourite human(s), you&rsquo;re scrolling on your phone, absent-mindedly shovelling forkfuls into your mouth.</p>
<p>Do the opposite.</p>
<p>Pick your battles, but sometimes also choose a party if you can and don&rsquo;t forget to rest like your life depends on it. Whatever you do, be the most maximally present in the thing you&rsquo;ve chosen. Presence and attention improve with regular practice.</p>
<p>In short: Work hard, party hard, rest hard.</p>
<!-- be maximally present to use that time right; do everything HARD -- came during my 2025-01-11 morning run -->
<h2 id="my-2024-to-2025-transition-wishes">My 2024 to 2025 transition wishes</h2>
<p>Humans<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> <em>at their peak</em> are a thing of beauty.</p>
<p>Above all they are truly kind.  They live and breathe the knowledge that we <em>homo sapiens</em> are at our absolute best when we connect with each other.</p>
<p>Peak humans are graceful, and they are elegant, and they are in harmony &ndash; the best sort of balance &ndash; with their surroundings, with those around them and with themselves.</p>
<p>Attaining this peak is hard. Maintaining it is nigh impossible. Best we can go for is <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">the never-ending practice</a> of these characteristics, and an eternal striving for moments to <em>become them</em>.</p>
<p>Friends, I wish you and your connected ones the willpower to strive for grace and elegance and harmony, and the presence of mind to attend fully to those perfect moments when they occur.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, you might be one of these&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #255: You lift me up</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2024 17:11:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/</guid><description> Figure 1: Het Stadhuis, Delft, taken in August from a quick bicycle trip with my good friend the TPN. Mood: Enchanted. Part of me still lives there.
There is a nerd joke I could make about using a single byte to store the WHV post number, which would explain the long stretch of time between this edition and the previous one in March, itself also lamenting the growing interval between posts, but I&amp;rsquo;m not going to.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="delft_stadhuis.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/delft_stadhuis_hu_217501806467ed66.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/delft_stadhuis_hu_558845f596dc76de.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/delft_stadhuis_hu_d40060b970eda0f6.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/delft_stadhuis_hu_451737953b9c7c00.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/delft_stadhuis_hu_558845f596dc76de.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Het Stadhuis, Delft, taken in August from a quick bicycle trip with my good friend the TPN. Mood: Enchanted. Part of me still lives there."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Het Stadhuis, Delft, taken in August from a quick bicycle trip with my good friend the TPN. Mood: Enchanted. Part of me still lives there.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>There is a nerd joke I could make about using a single byte to store the WHV post number, which would explain the long stretch of time between this edition and the previous one in March, itself also lamenting the growing interval between posts, but I&rsquo;m not going to.</p>
<p>Instead, I would like to welcome you to this, the 255th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, a mere 6.5 months after the previous one.</p>
<p>On a more serious note, my reasons for almost never posting anymore, relative to years of averaging about one WHV every two weeks, are a mix of just being really busy with family, friends and work, and of realising that suddenly I have become quite old in terms of wall clock time.</p>
<p>Whist I <em>feel</em> young, and apart from <a href="/tags/cancer">a cancer or two</a> I am in pretty good health, in my head the WHV used to originate from the head of a much younger human.</p>
<p>This gave these posts a certain <em>flavour</em> of youthful optimism, perhaps blamelessness, or maybe we should just keep it at youthful <em>je ne sais quoi</em>. These thoughts subsequently graduated <em>summa cum laude</em> from the University of Analysis Paralysis, and so months of no blogging ensued.</p>
<p>As my thoughts did not stop thoughting, fortunately, but more probably because with advancing age some of us acquire the super power of realising how few f***s we have left to give, I&rsquo;m feeling increasingly less awkward about posting my Weekly Head Voices here again.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Write drunk, edit sober.</p>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2016/09/21/write-drunk/">Peter de Vries</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because I&rsquo;ve always liked for the WHVs to have full calendar coverage of my life, the rest of this post is a collection of noteworthy happenings and observations from my perspective, covering the period from April 1 to Sunday, November 17, 2024.</p>
<h2 id="i-turned-50">I turned 50</h2>
<p>In August, I completed my 50th ride around the sun.</p>
<p>I am truly an old guy now.</p>
<p>Somehow I still managed to convince myself otherwise during the whole of my 40s, but now there is no escaping.</p>
<p>22:00 is really late to go to bed. In the mornings, I am unable to see my phone screen without my spectacles. I am now at the age where I have to start being really careful about not falling. You just don&rsquo;t heal like you used to.</p>
<p>On the other hand, thanks to my family and to my friends, I am deeply and blissfully content.</p>
<p>The first of my kids is finishing with high school and going to university. Conversations about life partners and careers and families and grand kids are not uncommon. On that topic, many conversations with my children are epic. They are growing up to be such beautiful humans, and we are happy to be here to help them in their journeys.</p>
<p>P.S. It is no accident that my <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">personal values</a> include more than one entry focusing on children, family and friends.</p>
<p>P.P.S. The South African edition of my birthday party took the form of an outdoorsy weekend with some of my favourite people. The Cinque Terre-themed party on Saturday ended at 2 or 3 AM with Tool on the dance floor. Weekend parties are the best parties.</p>
<h2 id="brilliant-dutchie-reunion-in-august">Brilliant Dutchie reunion in August</h2>
<p>As part of my birthday celebration, I travelled for a weekend party with some of my Dutch family in August.</p>
<p>The weekend started with a fabulous visit to my friend and mentor FP and his partner AW right after landing on Thursday, by the end of which my long travels were in fact already worth it.</p>
<p>My subsequent short visit to Delft (my other home) was nostalgic and a bit magical (see photo above), and then, as per tradition, we were off to spend the rest of the weekend at <a href="/tags/lowlands/">Lowlands</a>.</p>
<p>Musically I was utterly satisfied with Soulwax, Skrillex (guest appearance Noisia!), Fred Again&hellip; and many more, but the vibe with my friends was the uncontested headliner. It does also need to be said that we were somehow able to keep the intensity up until the very last act, until the fat lady sang.</p>
<p>For those of you who were there with me, I would like to apologise, but I was applying the following advice at 120%:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’ve got to dance like nobody’s watchin’</p>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2014/02/02/dance/">Susanna Clark and Richard Leigh</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>P.S. When you&rsquo;re at a music festival, having more than one (or two&hellip;) mimosas with breakfast is not just allowed, but strongly encouraged!</p>
<h2 id="gou-1-turned-18">GOU#1 turned 18</h2>
<p>Throughout the years, Genetic Offspring Unit #1 aka GOU#1 has made a number of <a href="/tags/gou-1/">implicit appearances on this blog</a>.</p>
<p>Some of you have known her since she was just a baby.</p>
<p>A few months ago, she completed another ride around the sun and all of a sudden we have an 18 year old young adult!</p>
<p>GOU#1 has a sharp intellect, she loves people, and she has a preternatural talent for being in the moment, a state she cognitively understands.</p>
<p>I really love our discussions. A bit surprisingly, she is a dad joke connoisseur.</p>
<p>I have often told her that she will overtake me, both mentally and physically, which will mean that I have done my job.</p>
<p>My wish is that she will continue on her great trajectory. I have told her that I think she has figured a lot out about life, but that I will be there to remind her, if and when it&rsquo;s necessary.</p>
<p>GOU#1, maybe one day you will read this. I am a huge fan of your work. ❤️</p>
<h2 id="blom-bullet-list-of-miscellany">BLoM: Bullet List of Miscellany</h2>
<h3 id="omnivore-is-no-more">Omnivore is no more</h3>
<p>In WHV #254 (you know, all the way back in March of this year), I <a href="/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/#omnivore">recommended the read-it-later app Omnivore</a> to you.</p>
<p>It was such a great app, but I should have known better and I&rsquo;m sorry.</p>
<p>They were bought by elevenlabs, and all users had two weeks to export their data.</p>
<p>This was (yet) another lesson to me that I should never deviate from <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#high-level-overview">characteristic (requirement) #2 of my note-taking systems</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As far as possible, the canonical source of everything should be plain old files on local drives, and be synchronized with a tool like Dropbox or OneDrive. In this way, the system is robust to the whims of a note-taking SaaS. The litmus test for this is that you are able to change out sync services and still remain with a working system. (True story)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>After drying off my tears, I dusted off <a href="/2011/10/09/hell-yeah-weekly-head-voices-59/">my trusty old Zotero</a> config, noticed that the girls and boys of Zotero had been <em>really</em> busy making the software even better, and now I&rsquo;m using this for web page archiving and highlighting in addition to the academic article database duties I was already using it for.</p>
<p>It turns out there are fantastic tools with which you can import Zotero highlights from web-pages <em>and</em> academic articles into your Obsidian notes. See <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/11/02/template-for-zotero-obsidian-plugin-to-import-references-with-highlights/">my vxlabs post on the topic</a>.</p>
<h3 id="there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">There is a TiL section on my other website</h3>
<p>On the topic of Obsidian, and as part of my quest to reduce any friction preventing me from posting technical documentation, my profile website now has a <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/"><em>Today I Learned</em> aka TIL section</a>.</p>
<p>Thanks to the magic of <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Setup-Quartz-to-publish-single-Obsidian-folder">Obsidian and the Quartz publishing tool</a>, I can now publish a random technical note in minutes.</p>
<p>I would have to say that it&rsquo;s not just a technical friction reducer, it&rsquo;s also the idea of having a space where you encourage yourself to post work that is not worthy of blog post quality, but could be valuable to someone regardless.</p>
<p>All of that being said, in the WHV-break I did manage to publish nine (9) technical posts on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>. Underlining my point above, some of the vxlabs posts sucked up more preparation time than their content deserved, and conversely there were probably a few short tidbits that never saw the light of day.</p>
<h3 id="bluesky-is-my-new-micro-blogging-thing-of-choice">Bluesky is my new micro-blogging thing of choice</h3>
<p>In the past few days (from November 12), the micro-blogging service Bluesky has grown from 14 million to 18 million users, with about 10 million monthly active users at the time of writing.</p>
<p>Although Bluesky and its underlying AT Protocol (aka <a href="https://atproto.com/">atproto</a>) have been designed to be distributed (users can for example already set up a PDS server to host their own data), that is not the reason I am preferring this micro-blogging service over all others.</p>
<p>My main reason is that it seems that many users on Bluesky, maybe even most, currently prefer a more supportive and positive environment in which one can connect with other humans and perhaps even have fun together.</p>
<p>Conversely, people who prefer being unkind can go do so elsewhere. Bluesky&rsquo;s nuclear block and other tools enable users to control exactly what sorts of interactions they have, and many are choosing for friendly interactions.</p>
<p>In short, it almost looks like people there are preferring kindness.</p>
<p>I might write more about this in future, but this is absolutely what I would prefer spending my dwindling time on: Contributing to an environment where humans are kind to other kind humans. I really hope that Bluesky can stay true to this ideal.</p>
<h3 id="databricks-and-spark">Databricks and Spark</h3>
<p>This section almost did not make it in, but I feel like I should at least mention it here, because it took up a substantial share of my work time the past months.</p>
<p>We are upgrading our data engineering infrastructure at work. As part of this, I have <em>really</em> been enjoying learning about and applying Databricks and the underlying Apache Spark and Delta Lake tech to our data architecture.</p>
<p>You can AMA, but for now I think Databricks is a fantastic product that is not too expensive, and gives you plenty of ways to work with your data even when you don&rsquo;t want to switch on that sweet Databricks compute.</p>
<h2 id="the-end-my-friend">The end my friend</h2>
<p>Friends, thank you for joining me here again!</p>
<p>I really hope that I can come back here to share more of my old person life tips, because, you know:</p>










<figure><a href="https://xkcd.com/1827/">
    <img
        
            
            src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/survivorship_bias.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>On a more serious note, I wish you all the best until we see each other again, and I would like to leave you with the following.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Zen pretty much comes down to three things &ndash; everything changes; everything is connected; pay attention.</p>
<p>&ndash; Jane Hirshfield</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 7 of 2024: Rest For Success</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/18/daily-head-voices-week-7-2024/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 17:42:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/18/daily-head-voices-week-7-2024/</guid><description> Most people in high-stress, decision-making industries are always operating at this kind of simmering six, as opposed to the undulation between just deep relaxation and being at a 10. Being at a 10 is millions of times better than being at a 6. It’s just in a different universe. &amp;ndash; Josh Waitzkin (see Sunday below)
Monday 2024-02-12 I really enjoyed this Rolling Stone article about Nine Inch Nails&amp;rsquo; Head Like a Hole Yes, that&amp;rsquo;s also a subtle jab at those of you who read last week&amp;rsquo;s title and did not get the reference. :P Extreme almost asymptotic anger moment at Outlook PWA: Spent time crafting a detailed meeting description. Unrelated meeting notification came in, meeting edit dialog disappears, all of those beautiful words gone. Forever. Accidentally upgraded Emacs to 29.2 (brew upgrade if you must now, and there it went building emacs along with installing all the other smaller dependencies, the ones I actually had in mind) Added ad-hoc similar node search for org-roam-similarity (that links to the new function&amp;rsquo;s documentation) This means you can also select any text, or just use the whole current buffer as your input, and then get a completing read list of similar nodes to open The area of my forehead around the scar feels like it has substantial nerve drop-out. I can&amp;rsquo;t feel much there, and I also can&amp;rsquo;t actuate much. The reconstructive surgeon warned before the time that this might be the case. Thanks again cancer. I&amp;rsquo;m crossing my fingers that there&amp;rsquo;s still some recovery that needs to happen and this is not my forehead&amp;rsquo;s final form. bitbar is now xbar. It looks like xbar can eat RAM https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725 I looked this up, because during my previous macOS phase I contributed code to bitbar to support Lua plugins. That work is now gone. Oh well. What a craptastically unproductive day. I had all of the time, and in that time I utterly failed at my selected task. I did some other interesting and possibly valuable stuff, but the majority of the time was wasted. Old lesson on this blog: some days gonna be crap However, responded to this by reviving my old FocusApp licence (see pro-tip #2 in WHV #126) and installed on my machine Tuesday 2024-02-13 First day back at the office. Lots of conversations due to the giant scar criss-crossing over half my forehead. Implemented the new (but very very old) &amp;ldquo;avoid all social media during work hours except a little bit on your phone during real breaks&amp;rdquo; rule. Using terminal Emacs for some remote work, because reasons Bothersome delay when pressing escape to get out of insert mode into normal mode. IT WAS TMUX. https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868 Noticed how much I rely on the cursor shape to know in what mode (insert, normal, emacs) I am. Fortunately found https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer and it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;hellip; game changer. Today was much fun at the office. Also much higher productivity due to above-mentioned no-social-media-goofing-off-rule. Wednesday 2024-02-14 Happy Valentine&amp;rsquo;s day everyone! Utterly crazy this morning because load-shedding, but due to GOU#3 being so very on time we left at 7:05 and could avoid most of that chaos. 6.5km short run just to get back into it, after 1.5 weeks out thanks to surgery and recovery. Garmin not happy with my fitness, but man it felt good. Went to doctor&amp;rsquo;s rooms to have stitches removed. Kind and professional nurse left the stitches in the middle, because skin there still needed some time to relax into the new situation. Feels really good to have the others out. Will go back on Friday for the rest. Pro-tip: it was a bit of a change management challenge, but I&amp;rsquo;ve converted my household to the new shopping list support in Apple Reminders. If you&amp;rsquo;re an Apple family, this woks much better than a WhatsApp group named &amp;ldquo;Shopping&amp;rdquo;. True story. Thanks to said app, remembered to get flowers. FocusApp really did its work today. I&amp;rsquo;m a tiny little bit bummed that no-one picked up on the Head like a Hole reference from last week&amp;rsquo;s Daily Head Voices. Or maybe someone did, but they just have not contacted me about it. Hopefully this week&amp;rsquo;s title does better. SUCH A GOOD DAY today thank you! Thursday 2024-02-15 Pretty busy day with meetings (Thursday is secondary meeting day at work after all), good conversations with colleagues, and an internal product playbook workshop. Friday 2024-02-16 Sublime run in Land &amp;amp; Zeezicht (school district) right after dropping off GOU#3, which also helped to avoid most of the traffic back home, again utterly crazy due to the 6 - 8:30 AM load-shedding slot disabling some critical (for us) traffic lights. Best afternoon ever: Father and daughter picnic with GOU#1 (school event, so many other fathers and daughters) at Zorgvliet Wine Estate In the evening, got my work inbox unread email count to just under 4000. Thank you for coming to my TED talk. Spent a bit more time reading about the new and open source Observable Framework I&amp;rsquo;ve always liked the ObservableJS notebooks, but this new development which supports working locally and self-hosting is really exciting! marimo is very nice for experimentation, but big advantage of OF is that it builds a static site as output. marimo needs Python to be running on the server. Again that idea: How automatically could I push a completely new OF built dashboard to a newly allocated CloudFlare pages site? Tried it out on Sunday evening (IN THE FUTURE): Was really quick to get the intro dashboard going in my case with pnpm, but a big challenge at this moment is the developer experience: There is very little coding assistance of any kind as you work on the javascript code blocks in the markdown pages. Hopefully they will be able to improve this with a vscode extension and/or a web-based editing experience, like marimo. Tried out Thunderbird 115.7 on the macbook. Much better than the TB 115 experience I had just after its release on Windows, where its currently selected mail logic handled it very badly when I archived a mail. I am trying out TB, because I miss the today, yesterday, last week date grouping. Saturday 2024-02-17 Woke up with low body battery (Garmin). Somewhat surprised, because only two beers last night. Perhaps the stress of the arguments, and probably still the alcohol because I&amp;rsquo;m old now. Wrote some Mojo to see if I could create a Pandas DataFrame and write to disc as Parquet. I love parquet. Although Mojo is still missing some data structures, it was not too involved to use the imported numpy and pandas libraries to do this job. Smoked snoek braai (so good! 🤤) at friend LM&amp;rsquo;s place with more friends. Sunday 2024-02-18 Super enjoyable 13km run. Not too hot, just a little bit of wind, and enough energy to finish strong. George Mack makes the statement: &amp;ldquo;There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.&amp;rdquo; This might indeed be a controversial statement, but I really like that his advice is to focus on the quality and purity of one&amp;rsquo;s rest (a very mindful idea), leading to much more energy for intensity 10 work. See his tweet (also embedded below, but please do click on &amp;ldquo;show more&amp;rdquo;) for a bunch of interesting examples. Figured out that it&amp;rsquo;s pretty easy to setup &amp;ldquo;Smart Mailboxes&amp;rdquo; on Apple Mail for today, yesterday, last week and so on. Truly sublime lunch with family at Stables on Vergelegen wine estate. Semi-controversial opinion: There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.
1. Winston Churchill used to work 16 hours per day in his old age during the war — but he also worked in bed every day until 11am. He had a nap after lunch, and a 2 hour nap… pic.twitter.com/kyiAuTEwjA</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Most people in high-stress, decision-making industries are always operating at this kind of simmering six, as opposed to the undulation between just deep relaxation and being at a 10. Being at a 10 is millions of times better than being at a 6. It’s just in a different universe. &ndash; Josh Waitzkin (see Sunday below)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="monday-2024-02-12">Monday 2024-02-12</h2>
<ul>
<li>I really enjoyed this <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-features/nine-inch-nails-head-like-a-hole-anthem-900750/">Rolling Stone article about Nine Inch Nails&rsquo; Head Like a Hole</a>
<ul>
<li>Yes, that&rsquo;s also a subtle jab at those of you who read last week&rsquo;s title and did not get the reference. :P</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Extreme almost asymptotic anger moment at Outlook PWA: Spent time crafting a detailed meeting description. Unrelated meeting notification came in, meeting edit dialog disappears, all of those beautiful words gone. Forever.</li>
<li>Accidentally upgraded Emacs to 29.2 (<code>brew upgrade</code> if you must now, and there it went building emacs along with installing all the other smaller dependencies, the ones I actually had in mind)</li>
<li>Added ad-hoc similar node search for <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity?tab=readme-ov-file#key-bind-the-ad-hoc-similarity-search">org-roam-similarity</a> (that links to the new function&rsquo;s documentation)
<ul>
<li>This means you can also select any text, or just use the whole current buffer as your input, and then get a completing read list of similar nodes to open</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The area of my forehead around the scar feels like it has substantial nerve drop-out. I can&rsquo;t feel much there, and I also can&rsquo;t actuate much. The reconstructive surgeon warned before the time that this might be the case. Thanks again cancer. I&rsquo;m crossing my fingers that there&rsquo;s still some recovery that needs to happen and this is not my forehead&rsquo;s final form.</li>
<li>bitbar is now xbar. It looks like xbar can eat RAM <a href="https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725">https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725</a>
<ul>
<li>I looked this up, because during <a href="/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/#new-laptop">my previous macOS phase</a> I contributed code to bitbar to support Lua plugins. That work is now gone. Oh well.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What a craptastically unproductive day. I had all of the time, and in that time I utterly failed at my selected task. I did some other interesting and possibly valuable stuff, but the majority of the time was wasted.
<ul>
<li>Old lesson on this blog: <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning">some days gonna be crap</a></li>
<li>However, responded to this by reviving my old FocusApp licence (see pro-tip #2 in <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">WHV #126</a>) and installed on my machine</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-02-13">Tuesday 2024-02-13</h2>
<ul>
<li>First day back at the office. Lots of conversations due to the giant scar criss-crossing over half my forehead.</li>
<li>Implemented the new (but very very old) &ldquo;avoid all social media during work hours except a little bit on your phone during real breaks&rdquo; rule.</li>
<li>Using terminal Emacs for some remote work, because reasons
<ul>
<li>Bothersome delay when pressing escape to get out of insert mode into normal mode. IT WAS TMUX. <a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868">https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868</a></li>
<li>Noticed how much I rely on the cursor shape to know in what mode (insert, normal, emacs) I am. Fortunately found <a href="https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer">https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer</a> and it&rsquo;s a &hellip; game changer.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Today was much fun at the office. Also much higher productivity due to above-mentioned no-social-media-goofing-off-rule.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-02-14">Wednesday 2024-02-14</h2>
<ul>
<li>Happy Valentine&rsquo;s day everyone!</li>
<li>Utterly crazy this morning because load-shedding, but due to GOU#3 being so very on time we left at 7:05 and could avoid most of that chaos.</li>
<li>6.5km short run just to get back into it, after 1.5 weeks out thanks to surgery and recovery. Garmin not happy with my fitness, but man it felt good.</li>
<li>Went to doctor&rsquo;s rooms to have stitches removed. Kind and professional nurse left the stitches in the middle, because skin there still needed some time to relax into the new situation. Feels really good to have the others out. Will go back on Friday for the rest.</li>
<li>Pro-tip: it was a bit of a change management challenge, but I&rsquo;ve converted my household to the new shopping list support in Apple Reminders. If you&rsquo;re an Apple family, this woks much better than a WhatsApp group named &ldquo;Shopping&rdquo;. True story.
<ul>
<li>Thanks to said app, remembered to get flowers.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>FocusApp really did its work today.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m a tiny little bit bummed that no-one picked up on the Head like a Hole reference from last week&rsquo;s Daily Head Voices. Or maybe someone did, but they just have not contacted me about it.
<ul>
<li>Hopefully this week&rsquo;s title does better.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>SUCH A GOOD DAY today thank you!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-02-15">Thursday 2024-02-15</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pretty busy day with meetings (Thursday is secondary meeting day at work after all), good conversations with colleagues, and an internal product playbook workshop.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-02-16">Friday 2024-02-16</h2>
<ul>
<li>Sublime run in Land &amp; Zeezicht (school district) right after dropping off GOU#3, which also helped to avoid most of the traffic back home, again utterly crazy due to the 6 - 8:30 AM load-shedding slot disabling some critical (for us) traffic lights.</li>
<li>Best afternoon ever: Father and daughter picnic with GOU#1 (school event, so many other fathers and daughters) at Zorgvliet Wine Estate</li>
<li>In the evening, got my work inbox unread email count to just under 4000. Thank you for coming to my TED talk.</li>
<li>Spent a bit more time reading about the new and open source <a href="https://observablehq.com/framework/">Observable Framework</a>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve always liked the ObservableJS notebooks, but this new development which supports working locally and self-hosting is really exciting!</li>
<li>marimo is very nice for experimentation, but big advantage of OF is that it builds a static site as output. marimo needs Python to be running on the server.</li>
<li>Again that idea: How automatically could I push a completely new OF built dashboard to a newly allocated CloudFlare pages site?</li>
<li>Tried it out on Sunday evening (IN THE FUTURE): Was really quick to get the intro dashboard going in my case with <code>pnpm</code>, but a big challenge at this moment is the developer experience: There is very little coding assistance of any kind as you work on the javascript code blocks in the markdown pages. Hopefully they will be able to improve this with a vscode extension and/or a web-based editing experience, like marimo.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Tried out Thunderbird 115.7 on the macbook.
<ul>
<li>Much better than the TB 115 experience I had just after its release on Windows, where its currently selected mail logic handled it very badly when I archived a mail.</li>
<li>I am trying out TB, because I miss the today, yesterday, last week date grouping.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-02-17">Saturday 2024-02-17</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up with low body battery (Garmin). Somewhat surprised, because only two beers last night. Perhaps the stress of the arguments, and probably still the alcohol because I&rsquo;m old now.</li>
<li>Wrote some Mojo to see if I could create a Pandas DataFrame and write to disc as Parquet.
<ul>
<li>I love parquet.</li>
<li>Although Mojo is still missing some data structures, it was not too involved to use the imported numpy and pandas libraries to do this job.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Smoked snoek braai (so good! 🤤) at friend LM&rsquo;s place with more friends.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-02-18">Sunday 2024-02-18</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super enjoyable 13km run. Not too hot, just a little bit of wind, and enough energy to finish strong.</li>
<li>George Mack makes the statement: &ldquo;There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.&rdquo;
<ul>
<li>This might indeed be a controversial statement, but  I really like that his advice is to focus on the quality and purity of one&rsquo;s rest (a very mindful idea), leading to much more energy for intensity 10 work.</li>
<li>See <a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1759122352036577546">his tweet</a> (also embedded below, but please do click on &ldquo;show more&rdquo;) for a bunch of interesting examples.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Figured out that it&rsquo;s pretty easy to setup &ldquo;Smart Mailboxes&rdquo; on Apple Mail for today, yesterday, last week and so on.</li>
<li>Truly sublime lunch with family at <a href="https://vergelegen.co.za/restaurants/stables-at-vergelegen/">Stables on Vergelegen wine estate</a>.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-dnt="true"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Semi-controversial opinion: There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.<br><br>1. Winston Churchill used to work 16 hours per day in his old age during the war — but he also worked in bed every day until 11am. He had a nap after lunch, and a 2 hour nap… <a href="https://t.co/kyiAuTEwjA">pic.twitter.com/kyiAuTEwjA</a></p>&mdash; George Mack (@george__mack) <a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1759122352036577546?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 18, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 4 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-22 As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&amp;rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS! At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&amp;hellip; Short but really nice streamlit demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually played with it. Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3. In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola. Tuesday 2024-01-23 At the office nice and early (7:30). Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at react-flow and comfyui react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY! streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &amp;ldquo;things I learned&amp;rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document. Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&amp;rsquo;s a zero day vulnerability in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites. Wednesday 2024-01-24 8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW! Remember kids: Our spine&amp;rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally. This is also the reason why I&amp;rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair. Lovely working lunch with friend S at No Way José Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work: idea: make github so that people can pipx install marimo-turbo to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on. idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS &amp;hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844 (post is also embedded below) idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&amp;gt; nginx -&amp;gt; supervisord -&amp;gt; tornado systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation I would prefer to use supervisord for this This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick? ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &amp;ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&amp;rdquo; googling blog post: https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/ the kubernetes thing: https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&amp;rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via iframe.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-22">Monday 2024-01-22</h2>
<ul>
<li>As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &ldquo;When you&rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS!</li>
<li>At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&hellip;</li>
<li>Short but really nice <a href="https://streamlit.io/">streamlit</a> demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&rsquo;ve never actually played with it.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3.
<ul>
<li>In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-23">Tuesday 2024-01-23</h2>
<ul>
<li>At the office nice and early (7:30).</li>
<li>Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at <a href="https://reactflow.dev/">react-flow</a> and comfyui
<ul>
<li>react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see <a href="https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary">https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary</a>
<ul>
<li>it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster</li>
<li>marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &ldquo;things I learned&rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document.</li>
<li>Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&rsquo;s a <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/news/apple-issues-urgent-security-updates-to-fix-zero-day-flaw-update-your-iphone-and-mac-right-now">zero day vulnerability</a> in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-24">Wednesday 2024-01-24</h2>
<ul>
<li>8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot</li>
<li>dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work</li>
<li>right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW!
<ul>
<li>Remember kids: Our spine&rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally.</li>
<li>This is also the reason why I&rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lovely working lunch with friend S at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/NoWayJoseSomerset">No Way José</a></li>
<li>Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work:
<ul>
<li>idea: make github so that people can <code>pipx install marimo-turbo</code> to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on.</li>
<li>idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap
<ul>
<li>sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets</li>
<li>in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS
<ul>
<li>&hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844</a> (post is also embedded below)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&gt; nginx -&gt; supervisord -&gt; tornado
<ul>
<li>systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: <a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation">https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation</a></li>
<li>I would prefer to use supervisord for this</li>
<li>This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&rdquo; googling
<ul>
<li>blog post: <a href="https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/">https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/</a></li>
<li>the kubernetes thing: <a href="https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s">https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0" width="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><script src="https://emacs.ch/embed.js" async="async"></script>
<h3 id="til-mastodon-embeds-are-not-as-durable-as-twitter-embeds">TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds</h3>
<p>As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via <code>iframe</code>.</p>
<p>With twitter, you get more self-contained HTML which will render even when twitter or just the original tweet don&rsquo;t exist anymore.</p>
<p>This is probably just another reason to figure out how I can get more low-friction microblogging going on my own websites so that the embedding implementations of other microblogging sites become irrelevant.</p>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-25">Thursday 2024-01-25</h2>
<ul>
<li>Took a look at <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/connections/connect-networks/get-started/">cloudflare tunnels</a> to expose marimo and other dashboards to the internet
<ul>
<li>great that I can use my existing domains for this, and I can route between multiple domains to multiple locally running services</li>
<li>some more steps to setup, but it did not take more than about 5 minutes, and gives me even more options than tailscale funnels. OPTIONS MAN!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At work, quickly got react-flow&hellip; flowing. SHINY!</li>
<li>In the evening, found <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/">https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/</a> which is the new Shortcuts based way, based on the old AppleScript way, of getting a <code>message://</code> link onto the clipboard.
<ul>
<li>You <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#email-linking">might recall from this blog</a> that <code>message://</code> are the most durable and cross-platform way to link to emails from your notes (or anywhere else)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-26">Friday 2024-01-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up to cool, overcast weather, a big change from a series of 30℃ + days. Really had to resist going out for a run (normal run day + that amazing coolness), because of Wednesday&rsquo;s partially pulled back muscle not being 100% yet.</li>
<li>Worked on mystery visualization project (react-flow)</li>
<li>Lovely and energising lunch with previous colleague and friend. Happy that I reached out on Thursday although they have a packed schedule because only in country for limited time. I guess this is quite related to <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">calling up your friends</a>, with a ping of serendipity salt.</li>
<li>I was shocked by how well and fast <a href="https://ollama.ai/">ollama</a> worked on my MacBook. See embedded tweet below.</li>
<li>Almost at the end of the afternoon, friend S and I went to some more friends for the first Weiss-off, that is, a Weiss beer tasting contest. It was huge fun blind-tasting 10 different Weiss beers, ranking them, trying to identify them (so much harder than I thought!), and then having them revealed at the end.
<ul>
<li>Between the experts there (read: us), Stangen Weiss Bier came out on top, followed by Weisbier No5 and Jack Black Atlantic Weiss. The fourth place was shared by Erdinger and CBC Amber Weiss.</li>
<li>My favourite, Stellenbrau Jonkersweiss, is glaringly absent from the top. I&rsquo;ll live, probably consoled by just such a Jonkersweiss. Super happy that Amber Weiss and Atlantic are both present!</li>
<li>There was a trophy (for the taster who could blind-identify the most beers in the Weiss-off), which we have christened the <em>David Weisselhoff wisseltrofee</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">With <a href="https://twitter.com/MistralAI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@MistralAI</a>&#39;s Mistral 7B at Q4_0 on this MacBook M1 Pro 10C / 16C, <a href="https://twitter.com/ollama?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ollama</a> looks like it&#39;s easily 3 times faster than the new MLX 0.0.11 (with GGUF support).<br><br>It&#39;s subjectively (visually) faster, and the tokens/s measurements confirm this. <a href="https://t.co/9vyluimLKK">pic.twitter.com/9vyluimLKK</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1750824125419942036?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 26, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-27">Saturday 2024-01-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yesterday&rsquo;s Wonderful Weiss-off also had some, thankfully quite minor, effect the next morning, but I went out for a careful weekday distance run, which fortunately went without a hitch. Just very hot thanks.</li>
<li>Went to Buco and then to <a href="https://appletoolandgas.com/">Apple Tool and Gas</a> to find the rest of the screws I needed to repair the shower door. Friendly gentleman at Apple even sawed some of my screws to size! Shower door back in operation.</li>
<li>Updated my &ldquo;old&rdquo; M1 MBA to macOS 14.3 and then reset to transfer to GOU#1&rsquo;s iCloud. Say what you want about Apple, but that part of their stuff works <em>really</em> well.</li>
<li>Left for Betty&rsquo;s Bay at about 16:00 with GOUs #1 and #2. The rest of the family already there.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-28">Sunday 2024-01-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up in Betty&rsquo;s Bay after a longer than normal night of sleep, but Garmin body battery was still not completely happy.</li>
<li>In spite of having run yesterday and still feeling a bit tired (see body battery above), I had the best run of the month so far in Betty&rsquo;s. Go figure.</li>
<li>Spent some time with Canva &ndash; what a great resource for doing nice designs, even flow charts &ndash; but not sure where I could use this.</li>
<li>Background thought through the past weeks, and mentioned on Tuesday: I would really like to do (and promite) more TIL-style writing at work and at home. See <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/">Simon Willison&rsquo;s amazing TIL collection</a> for inspiration.</li>
<li>Ran into <a href="https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines">https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines</a> a Python library that can guarantee structured text generation from many LLMs, e.g. 100% valid JSON according to a specified schema. What makes it different from similar libraries? &ldquo;Unlike other libraries, regex-guided generation in Outlines is almost as fast as non-guided generation.&rdquo;</li>
<li>I already had <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/autogen">AutoGen</a> on my list for experimenting with multi-agent LLM applications, but now it has been joined by <a href="https://github.com/joaomdmoura/crewAI">crewAI</a> which I have also just ran into (thanks reddit!) and which seems to have significant support online.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 3 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 20:21:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-15 Discovered that we (at work) now have access to GPT-4 Turbo via Azure OpenAI: 128K context and much cheaper than the old GPT-4. Will have to upgrade our private internal assistant, code name StoneGPT. Inspired by stefanv, carefully trying out weekly planning, but in a slight deviation I&amp;rsquo;m doing this in addition to my daily planning, which I only get around to a fraction of the time in any case. I think that this sort of multi-scalar examination and planning will help. Went to Bloemhof for the welcoming of the new grade 8 learners. Was really great to see GOU#1 and GOU#2 there, on two very opposite ends of the spectrum. Tuesday 2024-01-16 MS Copilot Pro ($20) has been announced, and also Copilot 365 is now available for businesses of all sizes (not just enterprises who can commit to 300 seats): https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/ Copilot Pro not yet available in South Africa 😥 $20 per month for integration with some Office apps (which could be useful, will have to see), priority access to latest models such as GPT-4 Turbo, and custom Copilots. I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced, will stick to my perplexity.ai for now. Copilot for 365 can be purchased per seat, but minimum 1 year commitment which is $360 per person per year. Ouch. In addition to many meetings (Tuesday = meetings day), did manage to spend some quality time with a new visualization project. Slowly starting to use webcola again, but this time with d3@latest &amp;ndash; sorta works, but no dragging. Have found work-around, still need to test. Went to bed really early, because must be up at 5:30 to help GOU#2 get ready for school and get to the bus stop on time. (Slept super badly thanks.) Wednesday 2024-01-17 Up at 5:30 after a pretty restless night. GOU#2 on the bus at 6 after some serious morning prep multi-tasking, GOU#3 (age 7) so organized and independent, ready to leave for school at 7! Nice and early(ish) slightly longer weekday run before work. My hip sent me a Teams message &amp;ldquo;Hi&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; at about 80% of the route somewhere, but fortunately no follow-up. Colleagues on chat, haha. Got caught up in GEKKO Optimization Suite due to meetings with colleagues about various simulations. My initial enthusiasm was somewhat dampened upon learning that behind the Python API lies an admittedly useful but quite black-box compiled binary called apm.exe. TIL: John Lasseter drew the BSD daemon! See https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html &amp;ndash; I remember that daemon from the time when I had FreeBSD on my machine at home instead of Linux (somewhere in the 90s). You might remember that name from the Creativity Inc. book (the one about Pixar!) notes post on this blog Thursday 2024-01-18 AlphaGeometry from Google DeepMind is great work combining a symbolic math engine with a language model to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. See below for my breathless tweet. (twitter is still the uncontested ML firehose) News on our in-house GPT-wrapper front: Discovered that I now have to upgrade to the new tool_call api as the old functions one has been deprecated. Made use of the opportunity to improve our implementation of the supplied OpenAI type annotations Note to self, and to you: The *Params types are TypedDict declarations which you can use to work directly with JSON requests and responses, while the non-*Params types are pydantic models which you can use to (de)serialize JSON. Went to see a really good Mohs surgery dermatologist who will soon be removing my basal cell carcinomas. As always, AMA in the comments or via email. This is such fantastic work! Symbolic engine + language model working together to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. Also, beautiful illustrations in the paper and posts. https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-15">Monday 2024-01-15</h2>
<ul>
<li>Discovered that we (at work) now have access to GPT-4 Turbo via Azure OpenAI: 128K context and much cheaper than the old GPT-4. Will have to upgrade our private internal assistant, code name StoneGPT.</li>
<li>Inspired by stefanv, carefully trying out weekly planning, but in a slight deviation I&rsquo;m doing this <em>in addition</em> to my daily planning, which I only get around to a fraction of the time in any case. I think that this sort of multi-scalar examination and planning will help.</li>
<li>Went to Bloemhof for the welcoming of the new grade 8 learners. Was really great to see GOU#1 <em>and</em> GOU#2 there, on two very opposite ends of the spectrum.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-16">Tuesday 2024-01-16</h2>
<ul>
<li>MS Copilot Pro ($20) has been announced, and also Copilot 365 is now available for businesses of all sizes (not just enterprises who can commit to 300 seats): <a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/">https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/</a>
<ul>
<li>Copilot Pro not yet available in South Africa 😥
<ul>
<li>$20 per month for integration with some Office apps (which could be useful, will have to see), priority access to latest models such as GPT-4 Turbo, and custom Copilots. I&rsquo;m not convinced, will stick to my <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/">perplexity.ai</a> for now.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Copilot for 365 can be purchased per seat, but minimum 1 year commitment which is $360 per person per year. Ouch.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In addition to many meetings (Tuesday = meetings day), did manage to spend some quality time with a new visualization project. Slowly starting to use <a href="https://ialab.it.monash.edu/webcola/">webcola</a> again, but this time with d3@latest &ndash; sorta works, but no dragging. Have found work-around, still need to test.</li>
<li>Went to bed really early, because must be up at 5:30 to help GOU#2 get ready for school and get to the bus stop on time. (Slept super badly thanks.)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-17">Wednesday 2024-01-17</h2>
<ul>
<li>Up at 5:30 after a pretty restless night. GOU#2 on the bus at 6 after some serious morning prep multi-tasking, GOU#3 (age 7) so organized and independent, ready to leave for school at 7!</li>
<li>Nice and early(ish) slightly longer weekday run before work. My hip sent me a Teams message &ldquo;Hi&hellip;&rdquo; at about 80% of the route somewhere, but fortunately no follow-up. Colleagues on chat, haha.</li>
<li>Got caught up in <a href="#d41d8c">GEKKO Optimization Suite</a> due to meetings with colleagues about various simulations. My initial enthusiasm was somewhat dampened upon learning that behind the Python API lies an admittedly useful but quite black-box compiled binary called apm.exe.</li>
<li>TIL: John Lasseter drew the BSD daemon! See <a href="https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html">https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html</a> &ndash; I remember that daemon from the time when I had FreeBSD on my machine at home instead of Linux (somewhere in the 90s). You might remember that name from the <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/#the-story-is-more-important-than-the-technology">Creativity Inc.</a> book (the one about Pixar!) notes post on this blog</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-18">Thursday 2024-01-18</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>AlphaGeometry from Google DeepMind is great work</strong> combining a symbolic math engine with a language model to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. See below for my breathless tweet. (twitter is still the uncontested ML firehose)</li>
<li>News on our in-house GPT-wrapper front:
<ul>
<li>Discovered that I now have to upgrade to the new <code>tool_call</code> api as the old <code>functions</code> one has been deprecated. Made use of the opportunity to improve our implementation of the supplied OpenAI type annotations</li>
<li>Note to self, and to you: The <code>*Params</code> types are <code>TypedDict</code> declarations which you can use to work directly with JSON requests and responses, while the non-<code>*Params</code> types are pydantic models which you can use to (de)serialize JSON.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Went to see a really good <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mohs-surgery/about/pac-20385222">Mohs surgery</a> dermatologist who will soon be removing my basal cell carcinomas. As always, AMA in the comments or via email.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is such fantastic work! Symbolic engine + language model working together to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. Also, beautiful illustrations in the paper and posts. <a href="https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7">https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1747857845356298739?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 18, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-19">Friday 2024-01-19</h2>
<ul>
<li>Spent most of my working hours wrappng up and deploying the brand new version of our internal GPT. I read somewhere that you should <em>always</em> deploy on a Friday, as late as possible.</li>
<li>I was stressing quite a bit, as I had a great task before me:</li>
<li>Braaiing 200 boeries in the 39 degrees Celsius heat at the school in Stellenbosch, in order to feed the new grade 8 learners on the evening of their initiation.
<ul>
<li>All thanks to the fellow dad who joined me, the stress transformed completely into an enjoyable few hours taking care of this important duty, and I made a new friend!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The kids, including our very own GOU#2, were facing the challenging night before them&hellip;</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-20">Saturday 2024-01-20</h2>
<ul>
<li>woke up at 5:40 because was planning to fetch GOU#1 and GOU#2 after their eventful and successful night, but thankfully partner was willing to go!</li>
<li>me very tired the whole day, just hanging (literally) around with family, and spending too much time on twitter / threads / reddit / inoreader! (brain was not willing to do much else, at least learned new things, some of which are mentioned below)</li>
<li>Based on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39055139">this HN discussion</a> about <a href="https://delta.io/blog/delta-lake-vs-parquet-comparison/">this blog post comparing Delta Lake and Parquet</a>, learned that Delta Parquet aka Delta Tables (which I&rsquo;ve read about in the context of Azure) is just a bunch of parquet files with some json metadata!
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve been enjoying <a href="https://parquet.apache.org/">parquet</a> for years now, in the context of scipy and specifically pandas.</li>
<li>Indeed, OneLake, also part of Microsoft Fabric, has Delta Parquet at its core.</li>
<li>Apache Iceberg is a similar but more open source implemenation: <a href="https://iceberg.apache.org/">https://iceberg.apache.org/</a></li>
<li>Based on <a href="https://www.dremio.com/blog/exploring-the-architecture-of-apache-iceberg-delta-lake-and-apache-hudi/">this comparison between Iceberg, Delta Lake and Hudi</a> it looks like all of these data lake storage layers are just parquet files with metadata, and then some logic, to give database like semantics over distributed object stores. Neat!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In bed last night, falling asleep, I had the following idea:
<ul>
<li><em>My Current Life Canvas</em> is a 3D bubble (off to my right for some reason&hellip; and moving with me as I walk) the interior of which I can view using my phone via AR (have to move phone in space to view inside of bubble, with current topics arranged in familiar spots; I thought having a world map would help, because well-known and memorable locations for your topics / priorities / ideas) or any of these amazing new VR headsets, BUT you can also interact with it via computer because inside of bubble can just be projected to surface using any of the well-known <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Map_projection">map projection techniques</a>.</li>
<li>CLC does not have a regular cadence like the daily or weekly plan, but is revised or redone a few times per year. It focuses on your major life priorities at any one point in time.</li>
<li>Although this was just a dreamy idea, I do like that it offers multi-modal interaction on the spectrum from AR/VR to more conventional desktop paradigms</li>
<li>&hellip; of course there should be some kind of friendly AI floating in the bubble with you :P (Microsoft Bob?)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-21">Sunday 2024-01-21</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super enjoyable weekend long(ish) run.</li>
<li>Tried out Omnivore&rsquo;s PDF annotation support, see screenshot below. Pretty impressive, and very cool that the highlights sync into my Emacs-based notes setup via markdown. Have slightly mixed feelings, because now will have to come up with new rule for when a paper goes into Zotero (fully local, full citations, but no automatic highlights sync) and when it goes into Omnivore (good sort of cloud but not local, no full citations, automatic sync into my notes)</li>
<li>Extended family Sunday lunch at our place was great, but me not at normal energy levels yet.</li>
<li>One of my goals for this week was &ldquo;Get through the week, especially Friday braai&rdquo;. Mission successful!</li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_8552fa2e79f0c31.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_d562277b8133fec1.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_70c21750f4c22771.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_3fd7290a1dd605.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_d562277b8133fec1.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Sunday 2024-01-07</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:48:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</guid><description> Last day of my vacation. 🥹 Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder than rest in the &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; periods instead. The assault bike saddles are garbarge. Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me. Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me. &amp;hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so. After getting wlziipsrv built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&amp;hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (bug in macOS 17.2) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS! Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 and GOU#2 ❤️</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Last day of my vacation. 🥹</li>
<li>Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes
<ul>
<li>Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder  than rest in the &ldquo;rest&rdquo; periods instead.
<ul>
<li>The assault bike saddles are garbarge.</li>
<li>Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &ldquo;normal&rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me.
<ul>
<li>&hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>After getting <code>wlziipsrv</code> built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv">https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv</a></li>
<li>Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MacOS/comments/18g4vxn/cannot_remap_keys_on_macbook_pro_with_hidutils_in/">bug in macOS 17.2</a>) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS!</li>
<li>Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 <em>and</em> GOU#2 ❤️</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Friday 2024-01-05: Café Zest</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-05/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 21:24:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-05/</guid><description> Woke up to gorgeous day in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay, spent first half on the beach Spent second half of the day slowly packing up all of our stuff (not my favourite vacation phase), some drinks, and working in-between on stuffing the archaic wlziipsrv.fcgi into a debian bookworm aarch64 image. Mostly bunches of ugly new hacks to work around some of the ugly old hacks in wlziipsrv. Scenic Clarence Drive route home, stopped at Café Zest in Gordon&amp;rsquo;s Bay for dinner. Yellowtail there was absolutely amazing! (thanks to GOU#1 who picked this jewel of a restaurant and made a reservation for us, all from the car) At home, finally got wlziipsrv built. Am secretly hopeful it might even work. (need to hook it up to supervisord, then nginx, then all of the microscopy data)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Woke up to gorgeous day in Betty&rsquo;s Bay, spent first half on the beach</li>
<li>Spent second half of the day slowly packing up all of our stuff (not my favourite vacation phase), some drinks, and working in-between on stuffing the archaic <a href="https://github.com/ma-tech/WlzIIPSrv">wlziipsrv.fcgi</a> into a debian bookworm aarch64 image. Mostly bunches of ugly new hacks to work around some of the ugly old hacks in wlziipsrv.</li>
<li>Scenic Clarence Drive route home, stopped at <a href="https://zestdining.co.za/">Café Zest in Gordon&rsquo;s Bay</a> for dinner. Yellowtail there was absolutely amazing! (thanks to GOU#1 who picked this jewel of a restaurant and made a reservation for us, all from the car)</li>
<li>At home, finally got wlziipsrv built. Am secretly hopeful it might even work. (need to hook it up to supervisord, then nginx, then all of the microscopy data)</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Monday 2024-01-01</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/02/daily-head-voices-on-monday-2024-01-01/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 17:36:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/02/daily-head-voices-on-monday-2024-01-01/</guid><description> Typing this note in the fresh new 2024-01-Jan.org file, in the completely fresh new journals/2024/ directory. Had to fetch GOU#1 from her NYE party in Hermanus, where they had been focusing more on the party parts and less on the sleeping parts. On the way back, stopped at my aunt and uncle in Onrust to give best wishes for the new year in person. Slipped and talked about AI a bit. Oops. Back home, read to GOU#3 (now 7) what I wrote about her in this blog when she was born, and at various points since then. Seeing her reaction makes this activity even more worth it. (pro-tip: Tag post with the GOU in question!) Read about the evolution of aging, the mutation accumulation (MA) and the antagonistic pleiotropy (AP) hypotheses in https://www.nature.com/scitable/knowledge/library/the-evolution-of-aging-23651151/ during the preparation of my traditional year transition blog post. Not depressing at all! Reclining on sofa, back almost horizontal, with laptop on lap, is an underrated ergonomic lifehack.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Typing this note in the fresh new <code>2024-01-Jan.org</code> file, in the completely fresh new <code>journals/2024/</code> directory.</li>
<li>Had to fetch GOU#1 from her NYE party in Hermanus, where they had been focusing more on the party parts and less on the sleeping parts.</li>
<li>On the way back, stopped at my aunt and uncle in Onrust to give best wishes for the new year in person. Slipped and talked about AI a bit. Oops.</li>
<li>Back home, read to GOU#3 (now 7) what I wrote about her in this blog when she was born, and at various points since then. Seeing her reaction makes this activity even more worth it. (pro-tip: Tag post with the GOU in question!)</li>
<li>Read about the evolution of aging, the mutation accumulation (MA) and the antagonistic pleiotropy (AP) hypotheses in <a href="https://www.nature.com/scitable/knowledge/library/the-evolution-of-aging-23651151/">https://www.nature.com/scitable/knowledge/library/the-evolution-of-aging-23651151/</a> during the preparation of my <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional year transition blog post</a>. Not depressing at all!</li>
<li>Reclining on sofa, back almost horizontal, with laptop on lap, is an underrated ergonomic lifehack.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>