<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>fastmail on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/fastmail/</link><description>Recent content in fastmail on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 21:53:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/fastmail/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #173: I know.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</guid><description> Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm still quite bad. Let&amp;rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:
Well hello there folks!
A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not have much to report on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="helderberg_protea.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By
the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm
still quite bad.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:</p>
<p>Well hello there folks!</p>
<p>A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not
have much to report on.</p>
<p>However, it&rsquo;s funny how these things go. One week nothing&hellip; Then it&rsquo;s just a
single week later and there&rsquo;s almost a bit too much that I would like to talk
about.</p>
<p>It seems to have been a mix of more writing, but also just more doing.</p>
<p>So, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 1 to Sunday July 14, 2019, I
would like to present the following notes.</p>
<h2 id="bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Bullet List of Miscellany (BLoM).</h2>
<ul>
<li>GOU#1, age 13, is on a week-long school trip in a different time zone
(GMT+8). I am super happy that she can have this experience, but durnit, one
misses one&rsquo;s genetic offspring units dearly!</li>
<li>Remember that I told you about our <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">solar inverter not talking to the
battery&rsquo;s BMS</a>?
Well, one small recommended firmware upgrade later, from 151507 to 151508,
and the whole system is completely down. Please cross your fingers, because
we&rsquo;ve tried <strong>everything</strong> else.</li>
<li>I regularly get accosted by off-leash dogs whilst running. There are
incredibly clear by-laws down here which absolutely forbid any dog ever being
off-leash in any public space which is not a designated off-leash zone. I
recently made the mistake (twice) of trying to explain this to the relevant
dog-owners. Well, dog-owners seem to be quite sadly under-endowed in the area
of introspective capability, but at least I&rsquo;m getting a lot better at
unprepared debates in public spaces. (Psychologists in the audience, help me
out here with any tips please!)</li>
<li>I really enjoyed <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/162-medical-intelligence/">this Sam Harris podcast with Eric
Topol</a>. <a href="https://www.scripps.edu/faculty/topol/">Eric
Topol</a> is a cardiologist and the
founder and director of the Scripps Research Translational Institute in the
US. Apart from the main topic of the discussion, namely Topol&rsquo;s
well-developed and articulated view of AI in medicine (well, his books on
this topic are quite influential, so there&rsquo;s that), I was struck and inspired
by the humble gentleness of this impressive intellect. Furthermore, although
we are not supposed to use twitter anymore (in some circles, it has been
dubbed &ldquo;road rage of the internet&rdquo;), <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Prof Topol&rsquo;s tweet
stream</a> is a shining example of how twitter
could be used more constructively.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email">Would you like some more Emacs with that Email?</h2>
<p>During the past two weeks I published two blog posts on my nerd blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/03/send-queued-mails-in-background-with-mu4e/">Sending queued mails in the background with
mu4e.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/05/mbsync-vs-offlineimap-speed/">Is mbsync really faster than offlineimap? A
measurement.</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Based on these, you might come to the conclusion that I&rsquo;m processing email
inside of Emacs
<a href="/2014/05/24/weekly-head-voices-71-vote-for-the-future/">again</a>.</p>
<p>I can confirm that this is indeed the case.</p>
<p>Probably for a large part due to the popularity of google&rsquo;s gmail, the growth
of the rest of the email ecosystem seems to have been stunted to a significant
degree.</p>
<p>In this specific case, I am referring to the dearth of really good email
clients for Windows.</p>
<p>(By the way, Thunderbird, still my fallback, usually makes the top of any
Windows email client lists. However, if it weren&rsquo;t for GMail, Thunderbird
would probably also be miles better than it is today.)</p>
<p>After losing more hours than I could afford trying to find that perfect email
client (I would have settled for &ldquo;still has all of its own teeth&rdquo;), I realised
that I would just have to buckle down and get <a href="/tags/mu4e/">mu4e</a>, my favourite
Emacs email client, working well enough on Windows, which I currently <em>prefer</em>
(DID I JUST SAY THAT?!) due to my <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1E
baby</a>.</p>
<p>That was of course a whole different wormhole to get sucked into.</p>
<p>Well, more of those precious hours later, I have a Frankensteined concoction
consisting of Emacs running on the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL),
displaying to the Windows desktop via <a href="https://token2shell.com/x410/">X410</a>,
and opening email and orgmode attachments, and dired files, using the native
Windows handlers via an
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Xdg-utils#xdg-open">xdg-open</a> work-alike
I coded up in Python.</p>
<p>(I am planning to release my xdg-open clone along with a more detailed howto
blog post. Let me know if you would like advanced access.)</p>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. after all of that effort I am now back more or less to where I
started in 2014.</p>
<p>(To be honest, Emacs is near the top of my list of compounding activities. The
fact that it&rsquo;s back in my email workflow, combined with five years of
compounded Emacs skills, has resulted in further increased efficiency.)</p>
<h3 id="sticking-it-to-the-man-gmail-with-fastmail">Sticking it to the Man (GMail) with FastMail.</h3>
<p>Wrapping up that email workflow reconfiguration frenzy, I did spend some
minutes doing a quick survey of fastmail alternatives which might have email
servers somewhat closer to the Southern tip of Africa and hence shave off a few
seconds of latency.</p>
<p>I found nothing that came close in terms of features and price. Except for one
outage, <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">I&rsquo;ve been a really happy fastmail camper for the last three
years</a>.</p>
<p>All of that, together with the fact that gmail&rsquo;s continued dominance is
unhealthy for the world of email, convinced me to stick with fastmail for the
conceivable future.</p>
<h2 id="stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">Stone Three Healthcare is now a thing.</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.stonethree.com/healthcare/">Stone Three Healthcare</a>, until recently
a business unit within Stone Three Venture Technology, has now been officially
spun out.</p>
<p>In other words, S3HC is now a more-or-less independent company that will
henceforth have to create its own success.</p>
<p>As some of you know, this project has been cooking for a few years now.</p>
<p>We have a really great team, products with customers and a market, and a
respectable patch of runway.</p>
<p>There are worse ways for a startup to start up.</p>
<p>P.S. if you have any golden tips for startup dummies, I (and probably others)
would be super grateful if you could let &lsquo;em loose in the comments!</p>
<h2 id="always-be-compounding-the-side-project-edition">Always Be Compounding: The side-project edition.</h2>
<p>In the previous WHV, I <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">started going on about the principle of ABC, or Always Be
Compounding</a>.</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been spending a great deal of mental cycles on finding more
ways to ABC.</p>
<p>Besides the more general examples I mentioned there, another method is to
design some long-running project that can function as a container for all of
the work that you&rsquo;ll have to do in any case.</p>
<p>A perhaps slightly flawed personal example is DeVIDE, an open source
visualization and image processing tool that started life somewhere in 2001,
<a href="/2003/12/19/the-visualisation-and-image-processing-platform-formerly-known-as-dscas3/">was renamed to DeVIDE at the end of
2003</a>,
open-sourced in 2007 and had its last release in 2012.</p>
<p>Although it did see some use after that, the project went into hibernation
(weeeelll&hellip;.) when I left academia.</p>
<p>My point is that, for about 10 years, I had a single technical <em>artifact</em> with
a name that became slowly better known (even if it was often by its alias &ldquo;Not
Responding&rdquo;), into which I could integrate all the other new work I was doing.</p>
<p>This enabled me to enjoy some of the advantages of compounding effort, in the
shape of DeVIDE, even although the work I was doing over the years necessarily
had to change.</p>
<p>(A really nice additional benefit was that some students sometimes found the
software useful! I do wish that that part could have continued for a little
longer.)</p>
<p>Setting aside my
<a href="/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/#a-strange-thing-happened-this-weekend">DeVIDE-nostalgia</a>
(and a bit of sadness) for a moment, I would like to apply some of this
learning to my current (and perhaps your) situation.</p>
<p>My idea would be to define a new side-project that can act as the slightly
longer-lived container for some of the smaller side-projects and learnings I
sometimes manage to spend time on.</p>
<p>It would have to be a technology / thematic fit for many of my other
side-projects. It would of course constitute a double-whammy if this
side-project had commercial potential.</p>
<p>Well, SURPRISE!</p>
<p>I do have at least one side-project that ticks a number of these boxes, and
could <em>potentially</em> serve as such a vehicle.</p>
<h3 id="aikno">AIKNO</h3>
<p>The side-project in question is called AIKNO, which is pronounced &ldquo;I know&rdquo;, but
which somehow expands to <em>AI organizational knowledge base</em>. Magic!</p>
<p>It eats all of your organization&rsquo;s emails for breakfast, and then uses
different methods, both algorithmic and crowd/team-sourced, to sort and
organize those emails and all of their attachments, and then makes those easily
and attractively (hey, data visualization!) accessible by that organization.</p>
<p>Think of it as an almost zero-effort always-up-to-date organizational knowledge
base.</p>
<p>Besides having slots for various machine learning and visualization techniques,
it fits nicely into my overgrown knowledge management hobby.</p>
<p>The first commit in the AIKNO repo was in November of 2017. Oof. The prototype
is able to import emails and attachments into its structured database, and
already does funky stuff with similarity searches and whatnot.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, it has also suffered from my regular technology stack
changes, and it&rsquo;s currently languishing while I write blog posts.</p>
<p>My previous failed side-project was called <em>TableTops</em>, or <em>Paradigm Desktop</em> by
the same people who dubbed DeVIDE &ldquo;Not Responding&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It was a free-form canvas / whiteboard tool for the free-form storage and
linking of <em>anything</em>. For example, it had relational data structures for
linking specific coordinates or regions in photos to centralised concepts, and
other interesting things that will probably never see the light of day.</p>
<p>It went through seven tech-stack-change-induced rewrites before being obsoleted
by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">my growing Emacs Orgmode powers</a>. (first
commit October 2013, last commit August 2017, now on the backest back
burner. the one that&rsquo;s not burning.)</p>
<p>I did learn a <em>tremendous</em> amount.</p>
<p>Maybe <em>that</em> is the real reason for doing these things?</p>
<h2 id="always-be-learning">Always Be Learning.</h2>
<p>Thanks for joining me on that trip folks.</p>
<p>I hope to see you soon. Until then, make an amazing time!</p>
<figure>
<a href="coffee_company_belgian_brownie.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
100% amazing Belgian brownie and delectable flat white at the
Coffee Company on Lourensford this past weekend.
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #111: A swift hack.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/15/weekly-head-voices-111-a-swift-hack/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2016 20:04:30 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/15/weekly-head-voices-111-a-swift-hack/</guid><description> Well hello friends! In this here,the one hundred and eleventh edition of the Weekly Head Voices, I present a personal view of selected events that took place in the time between Monday, July 25 and Sunday, August 14 of 2016.
Post summary: HackerNews FastMail to Gmail retrospective (WARNING NERD CONTENT), Craft Beer tips, Swift Playgrounds (teach your kids to code!) and a tiny bit of backyard philosophy at the end.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well hello friends! In this here,the one hundred and eleventh edition of the Weekly Head Voices, I present a personal view of selected events that took place in the time between Monday, July 25 and Sunday, August 14 of 2016.</p>
<p>Post summary: HackerNews FastMail to Gmail retrospective (WARNING NERD CONTENT), Craft Beer tips, Swift Playgrounds (teach your kids to code!) and a tiny bit of backyard philosophy at the end.</p>
<h2 id="the-hackernews-effect">The HackerNews effect</h2>
<p>When I submitted my <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to Fastmail blog post</a> to HackerNews last Monday, it was after some consideration, and with considerable trepidation. The previous time a similar post of mine was picked up by the HN frontpage (and reddit) in 2013, it resulted in a great number of fairly harsh insults flung my way (the harsh ones seem to hit much harder than the many more constructive ones can compensate for). The problem is not having your work criticised, it’s rather being ad hominem’ed into the ground.</p>
<p>The internet can unfortunately get quite bad that way.</p>
<p>However, this time the internet was in a good mood!</p>
<p>As a Z-list (aka hobbyist) blogger, I already get quite excited when even two people find something entertaining or educational in my blog, so you can imagine my excitement when I saw my blog stats jump into the thousands during the first hour after hitting the HN front page.</p>
<p>646 upvotes, 365 comments (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12247401">in the HN discussion</a>) and more than 50 thousand blog post views later (!!), my asbestos suit is still in storage, and the box of kleenex (for drying up my tears) is still unopened. I am very happy with the healthy and mostly happy discussion both on HN and here on the blog.</p>
<h2 id="a-taste-of-my-secret-beer-notes">A taste of my secret beer notes</h2>
<p>In my travels around the world (ok, maybe just in a few hundred kilometre radius of where I live) I taste many exotic and strange drinks (okay, maybe just the local craft beers). Here’s an excerpt from my top secret beer notes for your reading and hopefully soon tasting pleasure:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/stellies_bosch_weiss.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/stellies_bosch_weiss-648x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Stellies Bosch Weiss"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Stellies Bosch Weiss</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The <strong>Stellies Bosch Weiss</strong> is is a refreshing white beer which I can imagine enjoying much more in 35 celsius. However, I find it way too gassy for my taste and thus give it 0.4 on the Celis White scale. As everyone knows, <a href="https://www.beeradvocate.com/beer/profile/565/5222/">Celis White</a> is the best white beer in the world. I’m also not the biggest fan of CBC’s Krystal Weiss because of its gassiness. This could also be a German vs Belgian thing.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://www.darlingbrew.co.za/beers.html#/bc">Darling Brew Bone Crusher</a> is probably a 0.8 on the Celis scale, and scores mega bonus points for choosing such a heavy metal name.







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/patriot_lager.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/patriot_lager-576x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Citizen Beer’s Patriot Lager"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Citizen Beer’s Patriot Lager</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Citizen Beer has a real knack for naming beers; so this weekend I was able to do my patriotic duty (ha ha) by enjoying their <strong>Patriot lager</strong>. Fortunately, they also have a great knack for making lovely beers. This lager is more than hoppy enough to remind you that it’s a craft, but at the same time it is refreshingly light.







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_lager.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_lager-576x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Devil’s Peak Lager"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Devil’s Peak Lager</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Not completely coincidentally, I also tasted the <strong>Devil’s Peak Lager</strong> this weekend. There are subtle differences between it and the Patriot which I will only be able to describe after more tasting. For now: Same lightness, but with enough hop. Highly enjoyable.







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_pale_ale.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_pale_ale-524x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Devil’s Peak Pale Ale"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Devil’s Peak Pale Ale</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>As I’ve mentioned before, it’s no coincidence that happiness and hoppiness look so similar. The <strong>Devil’s Peak Pale Ale</strong> was a superbly hoppy (about 239% more hoppy than the lager) and full flavoured conclusion to the weekend. In spite of its full body this Cape Town beer’s alcohol content is lower than I would have expected: Only 4%.</p>
<h2 id="first-impressions-of-swift-playgrounds">First impressions of Swift Playgrounds</h2>
<p>I might or might not have acquired a new iPad Air 2 with the primary motivation of being able to test the new <a href="https://www.apple.com/swift/playgrounds/">Swift Playgrounds</a> on Genetic Offspring Unit #1 (now 10 years old). This is a new and attractive iPad-only app that has been designed by Apple to teach kids how to program in Swift. Note that you’ll have to upgrade to <a href="https://beta.apple.com/sp/betaprogram/">iOS 10 Beta</a> to get the app, at least until <a href="https://www.apple.com/ios/ios10-preview/">iOS 10 is officially released</a>. One of the exercises looks like this (image taken from the website):</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-14-at-6.25.43-PM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-14-at-6.25.43-PM-1024x729.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Previous experiments with <a href="https://scratch.mit.edu/">scratch</a> and with <a href="https://processing.org/">processing</a> have met with limited success but no permanence. However, GOU#1 is an iPad fanatic, and the potential of getting her addicted to the programming bug is just too fantastic to let this opportunity go by.</p>
<p>On the first day, she was already writing functions and for loops in Swift in order to navigate a cute alien solving puzzles on a 3D landscape.  I was looking over her shoulder now and then: The educational content and execution of the app is impressive. Besides the built-in puzzle worlds such as the 3D one pictures above, you can create your own Swift projects from scratch. These projects can use iPad hardware such as bluetooth and the camera, but we’re not quite there yet. Apple has also promised to keep on expanding the educational content.</p>
<p>I’m really crossing my fingers that GOU#1 will keep at it. If Swift Playgrounds helps to get her programming, I might just have to go full fanboy.</p>
<h2 id="heading">∞♥</h2>
<p>This past Friday at the breakfast table, Genetic Offspring Unit #2 asked her mom how much she thought GOU#2 loved the baby GOU#3, upon which the mom asked “How much do you love GOU#3?”.</p>
<p>GOU#2 answered: Infinitely much!</p>
<p>My fragile parental unit heart almost exploded with happiness at this point. It’s what I tell GOU#1 and #2 when I put them to bed, and every morning when I drop them at school. (GOU#3 herself does not yet parse our language.)</p>
<p>Ok kids, it looks like there’s an infinite amount of the good stuff to go around. You know what to do!








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/bettys_bay_somewhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/bettys_bay_somewhere-1024x576.jpg"
        
            alt="I went jogging (or rather walking with a two-step now and then). Enjoyment of surroundings and physical activity was quite intense at this point in spacetime: 15:55 on August 7, 2016; GPS coordinates in EXIF data."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>I went jogging (or rather walking with a two-step now and then). Enjoyment of surroundings and physical activity was quite intense at this point in spacetime: 15:55 on August 7, 2016; GPS coordinates in EXIF data.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2016 20:22:04 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/</guid><description> In 2013, when it became clear, primarily through Edward Snowden&amp;rsquo;s heroic actions, that the level of snooping by the US and other governments was far greater than any of us would have thought, I moved all of my data out of the US and of course blogged about it (that blog post has been read almost 70000 times; I think for many people this is an important issue).
This included migrating 60000 emails away from my beloved GMail (I got my GMail invite from The Vogon Poet on August 24, 2004.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In 2013, when it became clear, primarily through Edward Snowden&rsquo;s heroic actions, that the level of snooping by the US and other governments was far greater than any of us would have thought, I moved all of my data out of the US and of course <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">blogged about it</a> (that blog post has been read almost 70000 times; I think for many people this is an important issue).</p>
<p>This included migrating 60000 emails away from my beloved GMail (I got my GMail invite from <a href="https://twitter.com/vogonpoet">The Vogon Poet</a> on August 24, 2004. At that time, you could only get GMail by invitation. It was pretty exciting! (I have emails from before 2004, back to &lsquo;93 or &lsquo;94, but those are in a backup archive somewhere.)) to the little <a href="https://www.engadget.com/products/synology/ds213j/">Synology DS213j</a> standing next to my desk at the time.  This was all well and good behind the stable Dutch 100 Mbit/s <em>down</em> / 10 Mbit/s <em>up</em> cable connection I had, but when we decided to move back to South Africa, where home internet is a few years behind The Netherlands, I ended up having to pay for a virtual private server in Cape Town (to keep latency between me and my mail server manageable) and having to admin my own dovecot IMAP and postfix SMTP server.</p>
<p>Initially this was workable, until the Nth time that I had to interrupt my real job (which has nothing to do with mail servers) to apply a security patch or get the VPS booting again after a botched kernel upgrade. Besides that, I had to deal with keeping my server out of over-enthusiastic spam blacklists and whatnot. Also, inspite of <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2014/06/06/configuring-emacs-mu4e-with-nullmailer-offlineimap-and-multiple-identities/">mu4e</a>, I did end up missing the fast graphical GMail web interface.</p>
<p>So, it was with a great deal of tail between my legs that on June 10, 2015 (<a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">I have a lab journal, remember</a>) I went right back back to GMail. My mail setup, although pleasingly decentralised, was costing me too much time and hence actual money.</p>
<p>Fast forward to July 15, 2016 (there&rsquo;s that lab journal again…) when, after receiving an email from Google asking me to indicate how exactly I would like them to use my data to customise adverts around the web, and after thinking for a bit about what kind of machine learning tricks I would be able to pull on you with 12 years of your email, I decided that I really had to make alternative plans for my little email empire.</p>
<p>Somehow FastMail came up and in one of those impulsive LET&rsquo;S WASTE SOME TIME manoeuvres, I pressed the big red MIGRATE button!</p>
<p>The rest of this post is my mini-review of the FastMail service after almost 3 weeks of intensive use.</p>
<h2 id="importing-mail-from-gmail">Importing mail from GMail</h2>
<p>







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-10.50.45-AM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-10.50.45-AM-1024x594.png"
        
            alt="The main import &amp;amp; export window"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The main import &amp; export window</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-11.01.46-AM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-11.01.46-AM.png"
        
            alt="IMAP migration configuration dialog"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>IMAP migration configuration dialog</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The <strong>Settings | Import &amp; Export</strong> option in FastMail was easy to setup. It knows how to authenticate with GMail, even when you make use of two-factor authentication, like I do and you probably should.</p>
<p>The import takes place via the GMail IMAP interface. It&rsquo;s important to remember that via the IMAP client, an email tagged in GMail with both <em>important</em> and <em>info</em> will appear in two different folders. Because of this, I did check the <strong>no duplicates</strong> checkbox, but still I noticed that my 15 GB FastMail evaluation mailbox was filling up more quickly than I would have expected.</p>
<p>After a support request which was responded to within minutes (bonus), I discovered the <strong>Quota Usage</strong> screen and could see that the duplicate detection did indeed not seem to work correctly during the import. Based on more tips from the support tech, I made use of the <strong>Mass delete or remove duplicates</strong> module (Settings | Folders | Scroll all the way to the bottom of the page) to delete thousands of duplicate emails during the import. This was indeed because of emails appearing in multiple IMAP folders due to their GMail tags. <em><strong>Note:</strong> Friend and reader <a href="https://twitter.com/stefanvdwalt">stefanvdwalt</a> reported the exact same mail duplication during import issue which in his case did go over quota, so do keep an eye on this!</em></p>
<p>After a day or so (during which I could email more or less normally) I received an import report from FastMail claiming that the import had been successful, except for this error:</p>
<pre>Log: Fri Jul 15 17:49:17 2016; cpbotha/imap.gmail.com; Migrating folder Inbox -&gt; Inbox
Log: Fri Jul 15 17:49:17 2016; cpbotha/imap.gmail.com; Creating local folder Inbox
Log: Fri Jul 15 17:49:17 2016; cpbotha/imap.gmail.com; Error migrating remote folder Inbox: Failed to create Inbox. IMAP Command : 'create' failed. Response was : no - Mailbox already exists</pre>
<p>The import had managed to figure out that GMail Sent should map to FastMail Sent for example, but Inbox was probably too special to map in the same way. I fixed this by firing up my trusty Thunderbird, and using IMAP to drag and drop emails from my GMail Inbox to my shiny new FastMail Inbox.</p>
<p>In retrospect, I should have selected <strong>Create under new sub-folder</strong> in the IMAP migration configuration instead of <strong>Merge into existing folders</strong>. I discovered later that <strong>moving thousands of emails to a different folder is near instantaneous</strong> in the FastMail web-app.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-like">What I like</h2>
<h3 id="webmail-speed">Webmail speed</h3>
<p>I live more or less at the southern tip of the African continent. My lowest latency connection with the rest of the internet is via undersea optic cable to Europe (about 140ms ping).</p>
<p>The FastMail web servers are in the USA, which is, as the ping flies, much further away. I was not expecting much from the webmail, but colour me surprised when I discovered that this felt subjectively <em>faster</em> than GMail (who have servers everywhere, even down here). Things remained snappy, even with all 50000 of my conversations imported.</p>
<p>As far as I can figure out, it seems that much of this is due to FastMail&rsquo;s self-designed but open source IMAP-replacement called <a href="http://jmap.io/">JMAP</a>. JMAP has been designed for low latency, and for improved battery life. What it does differently, is batch requests together, and it also has optimisations specifically for interactive webmail.</p>
<p>The web-app has full support for keyboard shortcuts, which increases the subjective perception of speed.</p>
<h3 id="webmail-search">Webmail search</h3>
<p>For my purposes, search in FastMail is on par with that of GMail. I can dig up any of my emails, back up to 2004, in seconds.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-11.18.06-AM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-11.18.06-AM.png"
        
            alt="FastMail advanced search interface"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>FastMail advanced search interface</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s also very useful, is that you can turn any search into a virtual folder.</p>
<h3 id="tech-support">Tech support</h3>
<p>This is one area where Google really can&rsquo;t hold a candle to FastMail. If something goes wrong with your gmail account (this hardly ever happens, but it&rsquo;s possible) it&rsquo;s almost impossible to get hold of any kind of official tech support. Here&rsquo;s <a href="https://medium.com/@xdvl/stop-using-gmail-com-for-things-you-care-about-14af40e43a88#.h5ljyewg7">a recent story</a> where a GMail user&rsquo;s account was summarily terminated. There <em>was</em> probably some kind of ToS infringment, but the user has no idea what or why, and has lost all access to their emails and contacts database.</p>
<p>So far I&rsquo;ve contacted FastMail tech support twice: Once during my email migration, and once to confirm the absence of the “quote selected text in reply” feature (discussed below). In both cases, I was helped by real humans who responded very quickly and courteously to my support requests.</p>
<h3 id="email-and-contacts-and-calendar-out-of-googles-view">Email and contacts (and calendar) out of Google&rsquo;s view</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m still of the opinion that Google makes fantastic and valuable products. However, with all of their data mining know-how and resources, one has to decide how much of one&rsquo;s personal information one is willing to trade in for the use of these fantastic products.</p>
<p>With FastMail, I have been able to extricate my significant email archive (2004 to 2016, 50000 conversations) as well as my contacts database. I&rsquo;m still making use of Google Calendar, because of bunches of sharing going on with family members, but I have the option of moving that out also.</p>
<p>By the way, the FastMail Calendar web interface is more than capable (and pretty enough) to replace Google&rsquo;s version.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-dont-like">What I don&rsquo;t like</h2>
<h3 id="missing-integrations-todoist">Missing integrations: Todoist</h3>
<p>GMail, being as popular as it is, has tonnes of integrations with other apps. In my case, I will really miss the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/todoist-for-gmail/clgenfnodoocmhnlnpknojdbjjnmecff">Todoist for Gmail extension</a>. With this, I had a mini-todoist window inside my GMail, and I could turn any email into a task at the click of a button (or the press of a shortcut).</p>
<p>Because FastMail email URLs seem to be persistent, I use the <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/todoist-to-do-list-and-ta/jldhpllghnbhlbpcmnajkpdmadaolakh">Todoist Chrome extension&rsquo;s</a> “Add to Todoist” context menu action to add the URL and email subject as a task. This not as nice as the gmail-specific extension (the task goes immediately into the todoist inbox, without the possibility to edit metadata such as due date and tags).</p>
<h3 id="missing-feature-quote-selection-in-reply">Missing feature: Quote selection in reply</h3>
<p>In Gmail and in Thunderbird, if you select text in an incoming email and then reply, that selected text is quoted in the reply email. Unfortunately, this feature is not available in the FastMail web-app, and they have no plans to implement it.</p>
<p>I use both the FastMail web-interface as well as Thunderbird, because of its great PGP email encryption and signature support (hey, <a href="https://keybase.io/cpbotha">find me on keybase</a>, send me encrypted email!), so this issue is somewhat ameliorated. Still, it would have been nice.</p>
<h3 id="android-app-lag">Android app lag</h3>
<p>I do have <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.fastmail.app">FastMail&rsquo;s Android app</a> on my telephone. The app is a Cordova / PhoneGap / CrossWalk style unit with real-time email push and notification via Google Cloud Messaging (this is a relatively energy-efficient way for android phones to get push notification and is natively supported by FastMail).</p>
<p>However, there is a few second lag when I open the inbox, so I prefer using the pro version of <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.kman.AquaMail">AquaMail, a great Android IMAP mail client</a>. I have this set to 15 minute polling for new email, as IMAP IDLE (push, in other words) is not as battery efficient as GCM or Apple&rsquo;s email push. Opening any folder or email in AquaMail is of course instantaneous, as the emails live on the phone.</p>
<p>That being said, I use the FastMail app for searching, which is just as fast and as effective as the web-app.</p>
<p>THAT being said, FastMail really needs to implement some sort of caching in the Android app for lightning <em>fast</em> folder and email access. (The FastMail app is quite attractive, I would prefer using it more.)







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fastmail_calendar_google_play.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/fastmail_calendar_google_play-1024x580.png"
        
            alt="FastMail Android app Calendar screen, from the Google Play page."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>FastMail Android app Calendar screen, from the Google Play page.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<h3 id="niggle-creating-an-email-alias--incoming-route-automatically-creates-a-new-sending-identity">Niggle: Creating an email alias / incoming route automatically creates a new sending identity</h3>
<p>FastMail can manage the DNS for any of the custom domains that you assign to it, which is super useful if you don&rsquo;t already have a DNS service.</p>
<p>I already make use of webfaction&rsquo;s DNS for all of my domains, so I chose to add DNS records to designate fastmail as the official MX for those domains. (All of this is explained clearly in the FastMail help.)</p>
<p>When you do this, you have to create an email alias for each incoming address you would like to receive mail for (you can also create a catchall, but this could result in more spam arriving in your inbox). For each and every alias, <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/help/receive/alias-catchall.html">FastMail automatically creates an outgoing (from address) identity</a>. While this is usually quite convenient, I have quite a number of incoming addresses, but I only ever send from a subset of these addresses, so the drop-down list with sending identities became quite unwieldy.</p>
<p>I deleted all of the unnecessary identities. What would help, would be if FastMail were to implement most-used-at-the-top sorting for that drop-down.</p>
<h2 id="other-noteworthy-points">Other noteworthy points</h2>
<h3 id="domain-setup">Domain setup</h3>
<p>For my most important domains, I have set FastMail to be the MX. I have also performed the necessary <a href="https://blog.fastmail.com/2014/12/09/email-authentication/">SPF and DKIM</a> setup: FastMail gives super useful feedback in its configuration screens to help you with this. For these domains, I send mail directly via the FastMail SMTP servers, and mail is delivered directly to FastMail servers. Nice and simple.







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-9.46.01-PM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-06-at-9.46.01-PM-1024x623.png"
        
            alt="Domain setup feedback screen."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Domain setup feedback screen.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>For some other email accounts I have with clients, FastMail supports POP fetch from and SMTP send via foreign servers.</p>
<h3 id="ios-push-support">iOS Push support</h3>
<p>If you use any Apple iOS devices to read your mail, you&rsquo;ll be pleased to know that FastMail, with help from the big A, <a href="https://blog.fastmail.com/2015/07/17/push-email-now-available-in-ios-mail/">fully supports iOS push</a>. This means battery efficient real-time incoming emails to make it even more difficult for you to focus on That One Really Important Thing.</p>
<h3 id="android-contact-syncing-with-carddav">Android contact syncing with CardDAV</h3>
<p>With google contacts, syncing on Android just works, and it works really well. To sync my contacts with FastMail&rsquo;s Address Book instead, I bought the pro version of the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.dmfs.carddav.Sync">CardDAV android app</a> for 24 South African Ront (that&rsquo;s about EUR 1.5). This works as a sync provider, so once setup, the process is also pretty much transparent.</p>
<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>So there you have it: A hopefully helpful story, with included mini-review, about my move from GMail to the FastMail service.</p>
<p>So far, my conclusion is that this is a service that is technically more than capable of replacing GMail, even for power users. Furthermore, FastMail&rsquo;s primary (and in fact only) business model is to charge you money for making sure that you can keep on emailing like a boss. Together, this makes for an offer that I could not refuse.</p>
<p><em>P.S. Let me know in the comments if you would like me to add anything else to this post.</em></p>
<p><em>P.P.S. You can also join the lively <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12247401">Hacker News discussion of this post</a>!</em></p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #109: GABA</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 11:17:09 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/</guid><description> From now on, I would like to limit WHVs to bullets (really) or to named sections, to ease reading. DOWN WITH WALLS OF TEXT! After a multi-year, completely coincidental, break from medical imaging, I am back to The Real Business since the start of July. I am super excited about the plans we’re cooking up and executing. I can obviously not say too much, unless beer is involved, or you hang around here for muuuuuch longer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>From now on, I would like to limit WHVs to bullets (really) or to named sections, to ease reading. DOWN WITH WALLS OF TEXT!</li>
<li>After a multi-year, completely coincidental, break from <strong>medical imaging</strong>, I am back to <em>The Real Business</em> since the start of July. I am super excited about the plans we’re cooking up and executing. I can obviously not say too much, unless beer is involved, or you hang around here for muuuuuch longer. I think I am allowed to mention <strong>digital pathology</strong> and <strong>machine learning</strong> and beer.</li>
<li>Last week we <strong>road-tripped up the East Coast to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Francis_Bay">St Francis Bay</a></strong>, via Oudtshoorn and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cango_Caves">Cango Caves</a>.
<ul>
<li>Pro tip: When road tripping with more than 0 (zero) children (babies count double; sick babies +5 hit points), and you have to stay overnight somewhere, invest extra in the biggest suite you (or your children’s college fund) can afford.</li>
<li>On the beach in St Francis Bay (right in the middle of winter, you still seem to get these lovely balmy beach days), it seemed that <em>everybody</em> was surfing. Whole families, with the mom, the dad, all the kids, and grandma and grandpa, were all on various sizes of surfboards in the sea catching some waves.</li>
<li>Here’s a photo from the furthest point on what I call “Not The Ugliest Jogging Route in The World” (in St Francis Bay):</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/20160714_170901.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/20160714_170901-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<ul>
<li>Last night I accidentally discovered that I can pinpoint the exact weekend and location when and where I first tasted my <strong>favourite <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trappist_beer">trappist beer</a> (EVER)</strong>, namely Rochefort #8. It’s all written up in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/">this 2003 post</a>.</li>
<li>When Google send me an email this weekend asking me exactly <em>how</em> I would like them to use my email (yes, a few months ago I migrated my mail empire back to Google because <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">my self-hosting experiment</a> had started to cost me time and money) to show me custom advertisements, I was reminded that I do actually find the machine learning models they’re building about me quite creepy, and that perhaps I would prefer not also handing them 12 years of emails to make their models more accurate. There and then <strong>I migrated said 12 years of emails from GMail to <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/">FastMail</a></strong>. So far I’m really impressed by the product, mostly due to the speed and the user experience of the web-app. There might be a more detailed post in the near future, let me know if you’re interested.</li>
<li><em>Most surprising and interesting (to me) new scientific discovery of the week:</em> A team of scientists at Northeastern University in Boston <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/2095769-gut-bacteria-spotted-eating-brain-chemicals-for-the-first-time/">have shown</a> that <strong>one of the many kinds of bacteria living in your stomach eats exclusively <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-Aminobutyric_acid">GABA</a></strong>, a really important brain chemical (neurotransmitter) that plays a role in keeping you calm. Based on this and other work, it looks like the bacteria in your tummy, also known as your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gut_flora">gastrointestinal microbiota</a>, besides being crucially important to your digestive system and your general survival, probably also play quite an important role in your psyche. I find this slightly mind-blowing.</li>
</ul>
<p>Have a great week kids, I hope to see you on the other side.</p>
<p>P.S. Those bullets made for quite an impressive wall of text, didn’t they?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>