<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>disconnecting on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/disconnecting/</link><description>Recent content in disconnecting on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 19:01:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/disconnecting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #219: Stilbaai Easter weekend 12/10</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 19:01:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/</guid><description> This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Monday March 29 to Sunday April 4, 2021.
However, its raison d&amp;rsquo;être is to act as a reminder of the epic weekend in Stilbaai that we have just returned from, and also to practise the borderline (un)justified use of a posh French expression or two.
Figure 1: If morning starts like this, day could turn out OK.
You might remember me mentioning this place for the first time almost exactly a year ago in WHV #191, when we went there for the first time and had to cut our visit short due to the first COVID lockdown.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Monday March 29
to Sunday April 4, 2021.</p>
<p>However, its <em>raison d&rsquo;être</em> is to act as a reminder of the epic weekend in
Stilbaai that we have just returned from, and also to practise the borderline
(un)justified use of a posh French expression or two.</p>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_morning_run.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: If morning starts like this, day could turn out OK."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: If morning starts like this, day could turn out OK.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You might remember me mentioning this place for the first time almost exactly a
year ago in <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">WHV #191</a>, when we went there for the first time and had to cut our
visit short due to the first COVID lockdown.</p>
<p>A few months later, in <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/">WHV #208</a> to be exact, we had the good fortune to return
there, and for me to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/disconnecting/">get disconnected</a> unexpectedly quickly.</p>
<p>This time, exactly 11 WHVs later, we executed a text-book
maximise-your-Easter-weekend <em>manoeuvre</em> as we (the whole clan) left town after
school on Thursday.</p>
<p>Although the roads were quite busy, we did not get caught in any jams, and were
rewarded after a few hours (including a pretty busy stop at Heidelberg (ZA,
haha, I don&rsquo;t drive <em>that</em> fast) for coffee) by finding ourselves safe and sound
somewhere in Stilbaai on the Thursday evening, ready for a LONG weekend of fun
and games.</p>
<p>Oh, and this time <a href="/tags/disconnecting/">the disconnect</a> took place almost immediately upon arrival!</p>
<p>The weekend was pretty much perfect, with all of the stars aligning: The
weather (for a large part thanks to our sun, WHICH IS ONE OF THE STARS ALIGNING
TUN TUN TUUUUUN. Stilbaai is balmy this time of the year!), beautiful
surroundings and, most importantly, all of my clan peeps committed to having
fun.</p>
<p>The specific experiences I will want to remember include but are not limited
to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Morning runs, large parts on the tranquil beach, with its
perfect-for-barefoot-running sand, once also accompanied by GOU#1, who found
it exhilarating in spite of not <em>wanting</em> to run on the beach, because
teenager.</li>
<li>Long days on the beach by the river mouth, with all of my peeps, some of the
time spent trying not to fall from an inflatable <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standup%5Fpaddleboarding">SUP</a>. The general mood on the
beach is truly Laid Back.</li>
<li>Evening walks with the whole clan on that same tranquil, golden beach.</li>
<li>A visit to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stilbaai%5FTidal%5FFish%5FTraps">the ancient intertidal stonewall fish traps in Stilbaai</a>. See below
for a photographic impression.</li>
<li>As it behooves the people from this part of the world, daily fire and braai,
with craft beer and wine. (Also my music playlists, which I&rsquo;m mentioning
here, not because they&rsquo;re loved (they&rsquo;re not), but because they transported
me back into yet older but equally fond memories of more experiences with
friends.)</li>
</ul>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: One of the Stilbaai Tidal Fish Traps. Fish swim into trap when high tide. Fish now trapped, ready for&amp;hellip; next stage."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: One of the Stilbaai Tidal Fish Traps. Fish swim into trap when high tide. Fish now trapped, ready for&hellip; next stage.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>On the return journey, a little bit of our luck ran out as we got caught in the
post-long-weekend jam.</p>
<p>You see, it seems that the whole of Cape Town decided to return home from
various spots on the warmer coast in such a way so as to meet in exactly the
same spot (on the pass between the Hermanus turn-off and Houwhoek) at exactly
the same time (around about lunch).</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure how they coordinated this so perfectly (WhatsApp? maybe Discord?),
but we were definitely part of the project.</p>
<p>Thousands of cars, bumper to bumper, fortunately moving, albeit slowly. We were
going to make it, it would just take a bit longer.</p>
<p>I told my kids &ldquo;This is like life. Sometimes you go really slow, but the trick
is to just keep on going, one foot in front of the other. You&rsquo;ll be surprised
how far you can get.&rdquo;</p>
<p>They were probably not listening. Maybe they&rsquo;ll read it here one day.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the weekend had been so sublime that even the Great
Easter Jam of &lsquo;21 came, and then simply unraveled, just like any other thought
always does during meditation practice.</p>
<p>With that observation similarly unraveling, we have almost reached the end of
the 219th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, with only one more thing to say:</p>
<p><em>À bientôt les amis!</em></p>
<p>(hehe)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #208: Stilbaai</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 10:59:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</guid><description> Welcome back folks!
Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.
It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.
Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.
Running and reading I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, GOU #1 (14) completed her first (virtual) 10km race.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks!</p>
<p>Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.</p>
<p>It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period
Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="skulpiesbaai_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="running-and-reading">Running and reading</h2>
<p>I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> (14) completed her
first (virtual) 10km race.</p>
<p>Her journey started when a friend from school invited her to join the race, at
which point GOU #1 suddenly became much more enthusiastic about running
regularly with her old dad. (that&rsquo;s me)</p>
<p>There is something pretty primal about running with your offspring, an
observation that I might have mentioned before on these pages.</p>
<p>Anyways, after her race she was visibly happy, and also relieved that, in her
words, &ldquo;she didn&rsquo;t die&rdquo;.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m perhaps even more happy about than the preparatory runs together, and
her completing the race, is that since the race we&rsquo;ve been out together for a
run or three.</p>
<p>(Running and reading are two of the most important low-level habits I would
like to try and get my offspring hooked on.)</p>
<h2 id="ieee-vis2020">IEEE VIS2020</h2>
<p>At the start of October, I had a great experience <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#vcbm-2020-virtually">virtually attending the VCBM
2020 conference</a>.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough grade A1 10/10 conferencing for one year, my other
favourite conference, IEEE VIS (for visualization) was also fully virtual this
year in the week of October 26, so again I dove into YouTube streams and
well-organised discord rooms, and again this experience was highly edifying and
enjoyable.</p>
<p>Somehow, it was even <em>more</em> fun than my already optimistic expectations to run
into friends at the conference.</p>
<p>I would like to transfer this one piece of sage advice given by the amazing
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%5Fvan%5FWijk">Prof. Jarke van Wijk</a> during the panel on &ldquo;Why should I stay in academia&rdquo; when
the discussion treated the issue of dealing with rejection, something that is
unfortunately a regular part of most academic careers.</p>
<p>At this point, he was referring specifically to accepted papers and proposals,
but the advice should really be applied to any victory, large or small, in all
walks of life:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Celebrate your victories.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="cycles">Cycles</h2>
<p>You will of course remember that we were fortunate enough to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">spend our last few
days of freedom in Stilbaai,</a> as autumn was arriving, and more acutely right
before the first lockdown started on March 26,</p>
<p>It was really great going back to the exact same house (thanks kind host!),
after months of various levels of lockdown, this time just as spring was really
getting off the ground.</p>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_0181.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I did take work with me for the long weekend, but this time, and quite
unexpectedly, the important <a href="/tags/disconnecting">disconnect</a> happened quite quickly without too much
conscious effort from my side.</p>
<p>If I had to put my finger on it, I would say that getting everyone to go
outside as often as possible on little adventures of various sizes was the
catalyst.</p>
<h2 id="back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">Back to reality: An 18-minute plan for managing your day</h2>
<p>I could not imagine a more sudden transition from the long weekend zen above
than this jump to Peter Bregman&rsquo;s 18 minute plan for planning your work day.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Sometimes, fortunately mostly later in the afternoon, I wonder why my systems
have failed in helping me to keep my eye on that ball for longer. (See <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">my
slippery eel</a> for more struggles.)</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s when I procrastinate quasi-productively by searching online for any new
self-optimisation tricks that I might have missed, and which might constitute
that Last Piece of The Puzzle that will fix this once and for all.</p>
<p>This time, to my great surprise, I did actually run into something 1. that was
written aaaaaall the way back in 2009 and 2. that contained something new that
I had not run into before, namely the &ldquo;refocus&rdquo; reminder.</p>
<p>The refocus reminder is literally an alarm that goes off every hour on the
hour, at which point you explicitly take a step back for a whole minute to
review the past hour, and, if required (most probably the case the later it is
in the day), to re-commit to the following hour.</p>
<p>This reminded me specifically about mindfulness&rsquo;s <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#therunning-and-the-mindful">&ldquo;Each breath a new beginning;
each out-breath a letting go&rdquo;</a>, and more generally about <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">life as eternal
practice</a>.</p>
<p>You can use any sort of timer to do this, but this seemed like a great feature
for the little Lazar Focus app, so I implemented it along with a nice
mindfulness bell sound to add some gravitas to the moment.</p>
<p>If you like, you can read the short summary I wrote about the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/10/24/peter-bregmans-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day-and-the-surprising-power-of-refocus-reminders/">18-minute plan
and refocus reminders over on the LazarFocused blog</a>. There are some other more
widely known but great tips for running your work days more efficiently.</p>
<h2 id="kind-regards">Kind regards</h2>
<p>Folks, thank you very much for joining me here.</p>
<p>The comments section below is ready for your thoughts, if you would like to
externalise them.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #187: Checklists everywhere.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 19:15:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/</guid><description> Welcome back ANYONE WHO IS READING THIS!
Fiery sky in Betty's Bay. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about the situation in the Northern hemisphere, but down here in the South it seems as if just about everyone has disconnected for the Christmas period.
I decided that I would prefer at least trying to end the year with a few more-or-less on time WHVs, even if they have to slim down a bit to do so.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back ANYONE WHO IS READING THIS!</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_sky_fire_hu184f60bcf431b94c2b4abae030e6edf5_556834_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Fiery sky in Betty's Bay.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure about the situation in the Northern hemisphere, but down here in
the South it seems as if just about everyone has disconnected for the Christmas
period.</p>
<p>I decided that I would prefer at least trying to end the year with a few
more-or-less on time WHVs, even if they have to slim down a bit to do so.</p>
<p>So here we are: Just you and me. Maybe just me.</p>
<p>This WHV looks back on the week from Monday December 16 to Sunday December 22, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="the-last-work-week-of-2019-partially-in-bullets">The last work-week of 2019, (partially) in bullets.</h2>
<p>For me this was the last <em>real</em> work week.</p>
<p>I did spend most of it working from places other than the office, which was
nice.</p>
<p>Other than that, I would like to mention the following noteworthy learnings and
events:</p>
<ul>
<li>Schlepping along my Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic Desktop keyboard (current
favourite) and mouse, as well as my collapsible laptop stand (to bring the
laptop screen up to eye height) made a huge positive difference to my
ergonomics. 12/10 would do again.</li>
<li>We had a gratifying 4 day turn-around from the report of a pretty
obscure and initially irreproducible bug, through analysis and debugging, to
a new Windows driver release.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/projectstorm/react-diagrams">react-diagrams</a> is an
amazing TypeScript library for putting together a boxes and lines frontends
to manipulate graph-based dataflow backends. However, the TypeScript class
hierarchies and lack of documentation complicate customisation, if that&rsquo;s
your goal. I had to throw out that work and start over, building everything
on React (<a href="https://reactjs.org/docs/hooks-intro.html">hooks</a> all the way
baby!) and little bits of d3 for the spliny bits.</li>
<li>In the same vein, <a href="https://github.com/tgdwyer/WebCola">Cola.js / WebCola</a> is
an impressive layout approach for graphs. The force-directed layout in d3 is
great for interactive demos, but sometimes you want something that, you know,
lays out the graph. See this <a href="https://js.cytoscape.org/demos/2ebdc40f1c2540de6cf0/">cytoscape
demo</a> for even more
fun.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="on-checklists">On checklists.</h2>
<p>During this last week, as I was fighting to maintain the last islands of focus
being relentlessly eroded by the persistent seas of vacation-temptation, I was
helped a great deal by micro-checklists.</p>
<p>I briefly debated calling them multi-scalar checklists, but they are really
just normal checklists, except applied to any duration of work or focus time.</p>
<p>In other words, given an hour in the evening to spend on research, I would
start the hour by quickly jotting down (in Emacs Orgmode of course) a checklist
of the 4 to 5 things I would like to get done in that hour.</p>
<p>It was surprising to me much that 5 minute time investment would return in the
subsequent 55.</p>
<p>The lesson that I am taking from this, is that <a href="http://localhost:1313/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">my daily planning
checklist</a>
is not enough.</p>
<p>The daily landscape itself, my energy levels and my interest change far too
much and too quickly for a single daily checklist.</p>
<p>When you only get a few hours here and there to work, this problem is even more acute.</p>
<p>I am still figuring out how exactly to cultivate this new habit of making a new
checklist before every block of work, multiple times per day.</p>
<p>(What exactly is a block of work? Practically, how can I delineate this during
the day?)</p>
<h2 id="on-disconnecting-for-recuperation">On disconnecting for recuperation.</h2>
<p>During this time of the year I&rsquo;m usually spending a number of mental cycles
debating how exactly to disconnect from The Network.</p>
<p>(See <a href="/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/#you-are-turning-into-a-cyborg">You are turning into a
cyborg</a>
from a 2014 Weekly Head Voices, for example.)</p>
<p>Even longer ago than that, I used to keep my work and personal email separate.</p>
<p>During vacations, I would temporarily remove the work account from all of my
devices so that I could only see the mostly social-related personal emails.</p>
<p>These days, work and personal networks seem to have become even more
intertwined all by themselves, complicating measures like the above.</p>
<p>When I re-joined the Exciting World of Business and Great Success in 2013, I
merged all of my email back into a single account, for better knowledge
management and especially retrieval.</p>
<p>Another more important and more current example of this is WhatsApp, which more
or less dominates all instant messaging and a great deal of general
communication down here.</p>
<p>Many people I know use WhatsApp for work.</p>
<p>However, most of them, probably like most of you, use a single phone with a
single SIM.</p>
<p>This means that they will probably see work-related messages and activities
during their vacation, traditionally, but now perhaps increasingly
anachronistically, a period of disconnection.</p>
<p>(By the way, see <a href="/2011/02/05/postmodern-creativity-weekly-head-voices-37/">me in 2011 recommending WhatsApp over
SMS</a> when WhatsApp
was still quite small, and see <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">me in 2016 recommending Signal over
WhatsApp</a>. Signal
is still the best choice by far if you value your privacy and security.)</p>
<p>Personally, it feels like my current adventure in the Exciting World of
Business and Great Success requires me to be available, just in
case. Therefore, I am planning only a very few days of &ldquo;offline&rdquo;, which is more
of a mental state than a technological setting.</p>
<p>Other than that, my colleagues are all really great about staying off the
emails and the WhatsApps, partly because they <em>are</em> really great (see above)
and partly because they are applying similar methods.</p>
<p>The only question that remains is, how much disconnection, and at which
intensity, does the disconnecting human require for optimal functioning?</p>
<p>Friends, whatever your level of disconnect, I wish you maximum rest.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/bettys_rocks_hufd20b379848dff4c50dee7269192e3d2_2299980_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Deep Work: A welcome kick in the butt.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 08:31:25 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Based on this tweet by Enrico Bertini:
Little project I developed during the break looking back at 2016: &quot;Quantifying and Visualizing “Deep Work”&quot; https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q
&mdash; Enrico Bertini (@FILWD) January 3, 2017  &hellip; after having been successfully primed by this one some weeks ago (because locals!):
I also recommend https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf. I was skeptical, but it’s surprisingly good.
&mdash; Rian van der Merwe (@RianVDM) December 22, 2016 &hellip; I bought and then devoured Deep Work by Cal Newport in two to three sessions.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Based on this tweet by <a href="http://enrico.bertini.io/">Enrico Bertini</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Little project I developed during the break looking back at 2016: &quot;Quantifying and Visualizing “Deep Work”&quot; <a href="https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q">https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q</a></p>&mdash; Enrico Bertini (@FILWD) <a href="https://twitter.com/FILWD/status/816374094212067328?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 3, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; after having been successfully primed by this one some weeks ago (because locals!):</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I also recommend <a href="https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf">https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf</a>. I was skeptical, but it’s surprisingly good.</p>&mdash; Rian van der Merwe (@RianVDM) <a href="https://twitter.com/RianVDM/status/811955081201319936?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 22, 2016</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script
<p>&hellip; I bought and then devoured <a href="http://calnewport.com/books/deep-work/">Deep Work by Cal Newport</a> in two to three sessions.</p>
<p>As I munched through the book, I could almost physically sense the impact it was making on my thought patterns. I have since spent another Deep Work Pomodoro scanning through its pages again to make sure I did not miss anything.</p>
<p>Deep Work is at its heart Cal Newport&rsquo;s passionate argument for Deep Work in this extremely fragmented and highly connected information age. He defines Deep Work as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Professional activities performed in a state of distraction-free concentration that push your cognitive capabilities to their limit. These efforts create new value, improve your skill, and are hard to replicate.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Armed with a whole book full of stories and examples, he makes the case for eschewing <em>network tools</em> such as email, twitter, facebook, reddit, slack, whatsapp and so forth, instead dedicating as much of your time as possible to specific valuable outcomes. Yes, even after work, he makes the case for structuring your leisure activities in a similar fashion.</p>
<p>Although the book cites a number of studies, storytelling is its main persuasive tool. Whatever the case may be, I am utterly convinced.</p>
<p>I have resolved to put in a massive effort to get my Deep Work muscles back in top form.</p>
<p>I <em>knew</em> all of this stuff before. Heck, I&rsquo;ve even written on this blog about <a href="/2010/09/28/slow-e-mail-weekly-head-voices-32/">deprioritising communication to make room for important things</a>, <a href="/2010/08/08/workin-9-to-5-weekly-head-voices-28/">minimising interruptions and maximising concentration</a> and more (use the search Luke).</p>
<p>Somehow, maybe because of my transition to business, I&rsquo;ve slipped back into the illusion that you have to be connected all the time. On an average workday, I have email, two instances of slack, one instance of mattermost and whatsapp all open on my desktop, just in case I need to be reached. (To be clear, there&rsquo;s a great deal of messages that go through them every day, so it&rsquo;s not just me sitting there waiting in vain for someone, anyone, to please send me a message.)</p>
<p>Contrary to what I&rsquo;ve convinced myself of, these tools all detract significantly from my value production, both in terms of quality and throughput.</p>
<h2 id="structure-and-summary-of-the-book">Structure and summary of the book</h2>
<p>In Part 1, Newport tries to convince you of the value and necessity of Deep Work. The take-home message is that in order to excel at learning and at doing especially in the current interruption and distraction filled information age, we need unfragmented periods of distraction-free concentration, during which we push our cognition to the limit.</p>
<p>When I say it like that, it seems pretty obvious, doesn&rsquo;t it?</p>
<p>Phrased differently, the great fallacy of current times is that one can perform at one&rsquo;s best whilst being hyper-connected.</p>
<p>One can&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>Even worse, if we continue doing it this way, we&rsquo;ll start losing our ability to focus.</p>
<p>In Part 2, Newport gives high-level advice towards implementing Deep Work, packaged as the four rules of Deep Work:</p>
<ol>
<li>Work deeply: More about this further down.</li>
<li>Embrace boredom: Avoid busywork. That is, when you have a few minutes waiting in line somewhere, use the time to think instead of reaching for your smartphone.</li>
<li>Quit social media: EEEKE! Don&rsquo;t worry, it&rsquo;s slightly more complicated, but “manage social media” would not have had the same impact.)</li>
<li>Drain the shallows: Squeeze out as much as possible shallow work from your schedule. Focus work should be the default, distractions (shallow work) the exception.</li>
</ol>
<p>In terms of scheduling, rule #1 can be implemented in at least four different ways: monastic (isolate yourself almost permanently), bimodal (isolate yourself some of the time, but for significant periods, e.g. a month sabbatical), rhythmic (integrate into your schedule at set times during the day every day), journalistic (cultivate the ability to work deeply whenever you get a moment).</p>
<p>Of these, the rhythmic philosophy is probably the most practical for me and for most of the readers of this blog.</p>
<p>More practically, rule #1 (“Work Deeply”, remember?!) can be implemented using the following four disciplines:</p>
<ol>
<li>Focus on the wildly important: Make sure that you always know what the absolute most valuable thing is to work on.</li>
<li>Act on lead measures: Track your deep work by metrics that can be calculated <em>before</em> the output realises and not after, for example track your daily number of hours during which you were able to work deeply.</li>
<li>Keep a compelling scoreboard: Create some modality with which you can see clearly your daily deep work performance.</li>
<li>Create a cadence of accountability: Your daily or weekly routine should ensure that you review your work, and your deep work performance via the scoreboard for example.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="how-im-planning-to-apply-deep-work">How I&rsquo;m planning to apply Deep Work</h2>
<p>In the book Newport reiterates an important observation: We humans have limited stores of will power. These can and will get depleted through the day if we&rsquo;re not careful.</p>
<p>If it takes too much conscious effort to avoid distractions and to stay focused on the mentally taxing task at hand, our will power is depleted at some point and then our defences crumble.</p>
<p>Before you know it, you&rsquo;re stuck in that super satisfying (not) email, twitter, facebook, reddit, email, twitter, whatsapp, slack loop again.</p>
<p>An effective remedy for this is ritualization.</p>
<p>This does not mean that you have to get out the old Ouija board. Rather, it means that you should develop “routines and rituals to your working life designed to minimize the amount of your limited willpower necessary to transition into and maintain a state of unbroken concentration”.</p>
<p>Fortunately, because of a choice I made in 2013, my work already involves spending longer periods reading, thinking and programming. Now I only need to ensure that these periods are as deep as possible, which means eliminating distractions and practising as intensively as possible focusing on that One Really Important Thing.</p>
<p>I will eliminate distractions by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Using the pomodoro method (as I&rsquo;ve been doing all this time, just badly).</li>
<li>Extending the length of the 25 minute pomodoro. If I&rsquo;m in the deep work flow, I&rsquo;ll continue past the 25 minute alarm. A longer break can be taken later.</li>
<li>Activating my phone&rsquo;s no distraction mode during pomodori. Only phone calls get through, nothing else.</li>
<li>Killing my email app and all browser tabs that have to do with real-time communication (slack, mattermost, whatsapp, and so on).</li>
<li>Just in case, pasting a list of time-wasting site hostnames into my uBlock Origin&rsquo;s “My Filters” list.</li>
</ul>
<p>Besides that, I am recording deep work by prepending one of D0, D1, … D5 to the mytomatoes.com pomodoro description, corresponding to the spectrum from shallow to most deep work.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="http://www.veronikach.com/">veronikach.com</a>, I am using <a href="https://www.focusatwill.com/">focus@will</a> which helps tremendously with my concentration in the sometimes busy office.</p>
<p>Newport explains that most people can manage a maximum of four hours per day of truly deep work. Furthermore, for many people, it is most effective to schedule creative and deep work for the morning, and shallow work (email, admin, meetings etc.) for the afternoon. For a longer time I have been following the guideline of scheduling meetings for the afternoon, so now I&rsquo;ll strengthen that by trying to get my deep work done in the morning, leaving shallow work for the afternoon as far as possible.</p>
<p>Finally, I think that probably the most important advice here is to practise, practise and then practise some more.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This could very well be due to my own bias, but if I had to describe Deep Work as compactly as possible, I would have to say that it comes down to “mindful action”.</p>
<p>It might sound like a contradiction in terms (mindfulness is the practice of being, amongst other things), but I am referring to the practice of being fully connected to and focused on the current moment.</p>
<p>With Deep Work, one practises connecting fully to and focusing on the current endeavour, thus greatly enriching that experience and the output that it generates.</p>
<p>Thank you, Cal Newport, for this very welcome kick in the butt.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #77: A South African state of Mindful.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2014 17:57:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/07/16/a-south-african-state-of-mindful/</guid><description> I deliberately skipped a week, because it was one of those extremely taxing pre-vacation weeks during which I had several near-foetal-position-thumb-in-mouth-moments. Instead I’ll be writing about my vacation, with pictures, and a little bit of backyard philosophy.
This post is being written in a speeding Toyota Quantum 10-seater minibus (yes, it looks exactly like a taxi, we are currently the king of the road). Don’t worry, my co-driver has taken over.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I deliberately skipped a week, because it was one of those extremely <em>taxing</em> pre-vacation weeks during which I had several near-foetal-position-thumb-in-mouth-moments. Instead I’ll be writing about my vacation, with pictures, and a little bit of backyard philosophy.</p>
<p>This post is being written in a speeding Toyota Quantum 10-seater minibus (yes, it looks exactly like a taxi, we are currently the king of the road). Don’t worry, my co-driver has taken over. I’m not yet ready to attempt blogging whilst driving. (I do aspire.)</p>
<p>In any case, the week started with us flying from Cape Town to Johannesburg, and then making our way in this same speeding minibus to the Skukuza gate of the <a href="http://www.sanparks.co.za/parks/kruger/">Kruger National Park</a>, henceforth KNP. (This park is about 19500 square kilometres, almost half the size of The Netherlands!)</p>
<p>Due to a wrong turn-off (we blame the GPS), we spent an hour or two navigating pothole-riddled roads in pitch dark conditions in perhaps not the safest regions of my beloved country. It was one of those stressful but life-affirming experiences for which one is thankful but would prefer never having to repeat.</p>
<p>We spent the rest of the week more or less in the wild, mostly at a game lodge directly adjacent to the KNP. It’s quite amazing what being surrounded by the bush and all kinds of wild animals does to one’s state of mind. One by one, all of the incoming streams of information and internal lines of busy-thought are put firmly in their place, in some cases switched off with resounding clicks, eventually turning really-really-busy-you into mindful you.</p>
<p>Mindful you has time to think, and to focus. Related to this phenomenon, and partly due to it, there are two thoughts I would like to mention.</p>
<p>However, first those promised pictures! I tried to make a representative selection from the few hundred photos that I took.</p>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-mjejane_elephant.jpg" title=""><img alt="" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-mjejane_elephant-300x225.jpg"/></a>
</p>
</div>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-1" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-mjejane_rhino.jpg" title=""><img alt="" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-mjejane_rhino-300x225.jpg"/></a>
</p>
</div>
<p>I guess there’s a reason they call it the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crocodile_River_(Mpumalanga)">Crocodile River</a>:</p>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-2" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-mjejane_crocodiles1.jpg" title=""><img alt="" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-mjejane_crocodiles1-300x225.jpg"/></a>
</p>
</div>
<p>After days of searching for them, we finally ran into five young male lions during an early morning drive. Much excitement between the rangers and in our car, with the lions just outside of touching distance. The ranger told us that they see the car as a non-threatening animal, and that somehow us pink and soft humans sitting inside are not interesting, in spite of the large (about lion-sized) open windows:</p>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<a data-rel="lightbox-image-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-mjejane_lion.jpg" title=""><img alt="" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/wpid-mjejane_lion-300x225.jpg"/></a>
</p>
</div>
<p>Finally, I was very lucky to catch this dramatic hippopotamus face-off. You knew they were huge, but did you know they could move this fast? Watch them chase each other and then face off, concurrently marking territory by, uhm, spraying faeces around with their little wagging tails. Fascinating!</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/snrHHa7vnfU?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Still with me?! Here are those two backyard philosophy(ish) thoughts I promised:</p>
<h2 id="you-are-turning-into-a-cyborg">You are turning into a cyborg.</h2>
<p>We are all slowly turning into cyborgs.</p>
<p>We have our always-connected smartphones, our tablets, our laptops, and soon we will have heads-up displays always in front of our eyes (<a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/">I called it in 2009</a>, I think Google read my blog post). Probably due to our foraging nature and the accompanying neuro-chemistry, we find it incredibly hard to resist the call of email, of facebook, of twitter. <i>What if something new and interesting appears?</i> There’s a lovely dopamine shot waiting right there.</p>
<p>On top of this empire of connected technology, we build intricate systems to keep track of our time, our responsibilities and all of the odd bits of information that we come across. Heaven forbid that we forget anything! We open up as many pathways to capture as much as possible of our environment.</p>
<p>What happens when we are able to switch all of this off temporarily? Well, initially nothing much. Internally, business continues as usual. There’s no more incoming information, but our brains keep on going.</p>
<p>However, after a while things start calming down. All of the little thoughts fall away, leaving the big and important ones. Life starts coalescing, becoming more integrated again. Because all of the little stones are temporarily out of the way, it seems that one is able to move the really big rocks. It’s a strange and exhilarating experience.</p>
<p>So, busy-you makes way for mindful-you. Loads of small thoughts and some big ones make way for a few big ones.</p>
<p>With this, I’m not saying that we should fight the cyborgs that we are becoming. I think we should embrace our future. We <i>need</i> to be more knowledgeable and more connected to our fellow humans. We <i>need</i> to integrate with our technology. I do wonder how we can unite all this with being more mindful.</p>
<p>Is it possible to learn how to switch digital you on and off on demand?</p>
<h2 id="south-africa-you-are-the-most-interesting-place-in-the-world">South Africa, you are the most interesting place in the world.</h2>
<p>(to me)</p>
<p>Before I left for Europe 14 years ago, I used to want South Africa to play more to its European influences, to <i>be</i> more European.</p>
<p>In the years since then, I’ve had the pleasure to live in one of the prettiest little cities in The Netherlands, and to spend vacation time in Italy, in the south of Spain, in the south of France, in Greece and in Sardinia (technically Italy, but I mention it separately because it was that awesome). I’ve also had the pleasure to spend work time in Germany, Norway and Sweden. Altogether, this is a not too shabby sampling of Western Europe.</p>
<p>What I’ve seen is beautiful, and it has been a superb growing experience making the connections between my European heritage and its various sources.</p>
<p>Exploring these connections has also helped me to better understand the African influences that have partially formed me, and are the foundations of South Africa. Added to this, I’ve had the distinct privilege of being a tourist in my own country together with Dutch friends. This was perhaps the most acute eye opener. I’ve come to appreciate that Africanness of which I once thought that it should be moved slightly more to the background.</p>
<p>So here I am now. SA is a fantastically interesting place. It’s a beautiful country, but, more relevantly, it’s currently in a huge state of flux. I’m happy to be able to play a small role in trying to redefine the strange little subculture that I belong to. I’m doing my best to connect more with fellow South Africans.</p>
<p>I am optimistic that the country will be able to define its own voice; that it will integrate everyone, even its seemingly out of place European children, in a uniquely <i>South</i> African cocktail.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Slow philosophy. [Weekly Head Voices #64]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2012 22:23:13 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/</guid><description> I’ve spent days writing this post in my head, and now it’s taken more than two weeks to get done. It’s not that I have something complicated or difficult to tell you, it’s just that I was privy to three absolutely awesome weeks of vacation in an undisclosed location to the very far south of my current coordinates, during which I attained ultimate levels of relaxation that caused my brain to shut-down large parts of itself.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I’ve spent days writing this post in my head, and now it’s taken more than two weeks to get done. It’s not that I have something complicated or difficult to tell you, it’s just that I was privy to three absolutely awesome weeks of vacation in an undisclosed location to the very far south of my current coordinates, during which I attained ultimate levels of relaxation that caused my brain to shut-down large parts of itself. The only parts that managed to remain online were those dedicated to slow living, appreciation of people and surroundings and, finally, deep thought. My brain is currently taking its sweet time to come fully online again.</p>
<p>Oh well.</p>
<p>I <em>did</em> bring you a photo of Disa Uniflora, a special little orchid that likes living close to little waterfalls, for example just like the one that can be found on your hike up Leopard’s Kloof. Look:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/disa_uniflora_leopards_kloof.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/disa_uniflora_leopards_kloof-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty Disa in Leopard&#39;s Kloof."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty Disa in Leopard's Kloof.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>As is usual for sunny vacations during which we transition into a new year, a number of realizations and resolutions slowly bubbled up to the surface from some usually submerged part of my consciousness. I’d like to share some of them with you:</p>
<p><em>Life goals are bad.</em> Let’s stop doing them. The problem is that humans are awesome at adaptation. Unfortunately this means that two days after having celebrated your latest epic life achievement, you’re bored with it. Some people even get bored with their lives in general, and then buy a leather jacket and a motorbike because they think that <em>that’ll</em> somehow solve the problem, only to get bored with their new image soon after. Fortunately, there is a way to sidestep the problem quite elegantly. Don’t set life goals, but rather set life directions. Instead of defining the point that you want to go towards, define your preferred direction. If you do it right, you’ll pass those points as you go along in any case, except you won’t land in the depressing goal vacuum right after reaching the point that you’ve been moving towards for so long, because you’re motoring along in a direction, and that’s what’s important. To those more mathematically inclined, ignore the life function, rather design its derivatives. This is a practical way of <em>applying</em> the well-known addage that life is about the journey, and not the destination.</p>
<p><em>Disconnecting is good.</em> I do love the internet. I also think it’s one of the most awesome achievements of the whole of humankind ever, and it really empowers humans everywhere. I’m more or less addicted to being constantly connected, having constant access to the sum total of human knowledge and in principle to a large percentage of my fellow humans. However, there is a fine line between having constant access and being constantly interrupted by too many not necessarily valuable packets of data. We’re very vulnerable to this latter situation, due to <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/health_and_science/science/2009/08/seeking.html" title="slate article dealing with brain chemistry and internet interruption">our brain chemistry being optimized by all of evolution for novelty</a>, and for foraging, so we keep on clicking on “refresh”, and our ears perk up whenever a phone goes “ping”. However, when not being interrupted, human thought gets the room it needs to grow and deepen, into importance and into impact.</p>
<p>I’ve also been thinking about consumption. I’d like to do much less of that, and when I do, I’d prefer to consume quality. In my thoughts, it was primarily about information, but it applies to many other things. It’s an ongoing process.</p>
<p>I’m adding all of these to my growing list of little life tips. As regular readers of this blog, you know some of these by now: Keep on  <a href="/2011/08/28/the-lowlands-tooth-fairy-37-weekly-head-voices-55/" title="balance and harmony mentioned, has to bemore">striving for balance and harmony</a>, <a href="/2011/03/19/drown-in-the-now-weekly-head-voices-42/" title="drown in the now">focus on the now</a>, <a href="/2011/11/05/happiness-slingshot-weekly-head-voices-61/" title="create value">create value</a>, <a href="/2010/08/01/the-human-animal-post/" title="the human animal post">study your manual</a>, and, most importantly, <a href="/tag/coffee/" title="posts tagged with coffee">drink lots of coffee</a>. One day I’m going to combine them all nicely into the Unified Dogma of  Me (UDM) and then I’ll start a sect. Seriously though, it’s quite challenging keeping these and the other ones in the front of my mind all the time. The UDM would definitely help. And I could start a sect.</p>
<p>One more thing before you go: I came across <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2012/01/10/1115323109" title="Ratcliff 2012 in PNAS">this recent PNAS article</a> via the science pages of my newspaper. William Ratcliff and colleagues at the Michigan State University showed with a terribly simple experiment that single-celled yeast cells can evolve into multi-cellularity quite quickly. Pouring yeast from one test tube into another about 60 times, an action that favours, or selects, yeast cells that clump together, resulted into a multi-celled organism: The clumped together yeast cells started showing internal specialization. Pretty awesome results, especially considering the fact that you could probably reproduce this experiment in your kitchen.</p>
<p>That’s all for this week kids. Have fun evolving!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>