<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>twitter on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/twitter/</link><description>Recent content in twitter on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 15:04:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/twitter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #211: Table Mountain Run(ish)</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 15:04:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/</guid><description> Welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices friends!
These ones, the two hundred and eleventh (haha, remember at school you always wondered if anyone would ever really need to be able to write out numbers&amp;hellip; IT WAS ALL FOR ME) edition, will hopefully be talking more or less coherently about events that took place during the two weeks from Monday November 23 to Sunday December 6 of the year 2020.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices friends!</p>
<p>These ones, the two hundred and eleventh (haha, remember at school you always
wondered if anyone would ever really need to be able to write out numbers&hellip; IT
WAS ALL FOR ME) edition, will hopefully be talking more or less coherently
about events that took place during the two weeks from Monday November 23 to
Sunday December 6 of the year 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="table-mountain-20201204-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Not the worst spot to eat one&amp;rsquo;s peanut butter sandwiches"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Not the worst spot to eat one&rsquo;s peanut butter sandwiches</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">Wetware checklist to bootstrap your software checklist</h2>
<p>My <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">daily review</a> routine has been taking quite a beating.</p>
<p>The busier it gets, the more easily I somehow skip my whole daily review in the
morning thinking that I can better invest that time into just jumping on the
most urgent things first.</p>
<p>This is of course one of the stupidest things I can do at that point.</p>
<p>It doesn&rsquo;t help that the daily review contains quite a number of points I have
to take care of every morning.</p>
<p>So, what does one do to help sticking to your morning daily review habit?</p>
<p>Logically, one creates yet another, but this time smaller and hopefully more
robust, habit that triggers the larger habit!</p>
<p>(In the end, it&rsquo;s turtles all the way down in any case.)</p>
<p>The one redeeming factor in my morning routine has been the increasing
regularity of meditation exercise. (Thanks PK for putting me back on that
horse, or should I say <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/#shorter-focus-blocks-work-better">elephant</a>, and thanks to Sam Harris and his Waking Up
app.)</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;ve now added to my system is a smaller checklist with three items on it:</p>
<ol>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> meditation</li>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> deep reading</li>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> planning: review + task setting</li>
</ol>
<p>The difference is that this checkpoint now lives in my brain, and is much
harder to side-step. Also, because of the firmly embedded meditation kernel,
there&rsquo;s a bit of momentum to help me move on to items 2 and 3.</p>
<p>I sneaked in item 2, because reading is basically cheap but really powerful
cybernetic upgrades for normal humans, and I found that it nicely completes
this 30 minutes (or so) of quite time in the morning before I start with work.</p>
<p>So far, this small addition to my firmware has made quite a positive impact,
although I have to admit that AoC (see further down) is temporarily interfering
with items 2 and/or 3.</p>
<p>Oh well, one just has to keep on keeping on.</p>
<h2 id="someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet-part-972387">Someone is wrong on the internet, part 972387</h2>
<p>Some of you (does 2 out of my total of 5 readers qualify as &ldquo;some of you&rdquo;,
relatively speaking?) will remember that I sometimes have a fraught
relationship with people being wrong on the internet, or you could just look up
<a href="/2014/07/01/weekly-head-voices-76-someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet/">WHV #76 to read about a previous episode</a>.</p>
<p>Most recently, I was again trying spectacularly unsuccessfully to avoid
twitter, when I ran into a thread where people were arguing about wearing
facemasks or not in these times.</p>
<p>My plan was to pull myself away from my phone, then throw the phone into the
fire, and then start the BBQ, but unfortunately one of the persons who was
arguing on the wrong side carries the same name as I do.</p>
<p>Although I am the <strong>one true Charl Botha</strong>, as is confirmed by the world&rsquo;s
premier reference on everything Charl Botha, namely the website <a href="https://charlbotha.com/">charlbotha.com</a>,
I was still worried that someone somewhere might confuse me with the third-rate
Charl Botha who was putting his lack of humanity on display.</p>
<p>My initial reaction was to go in there with all of my verbal guns blazing in
order to correct the poor sod, and to ensure that people would see there were
more Charls, some of which were not <em>as</em> bad, but fortunately some of the
psychology I have been absorbing from the literature kicked in on time and I
managed to limit my reply tweet to the fact that 1) I was in fact the real
Charl Botha (the one with a brain), and 2) that I thought one should wear a
mask because it&rsquo;s kind to other humans.</p>
<p>This made me think about the observation that mask deniers would always believe
that there were holes in the science of mask-wearing, when the most important
consideration comes down to the fact that even if mask-wearing helped your
fellow humans possibly only a little bit, it&rsquo;s already the kind thing to do.</p>
<p>After that, I made the following tweet to summarise my thinking on this topic:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Folks, remember that
of the 14 mask types tested in <a
href="https://t.co/BrQ6cpCnkk">https://t.co/BrQ6cpCnkk</a> (sensitive to
droplet size all the way down to 0.5um), 13 of them reduced droplet
transmission relative to no mask. SO: Be kind. Wear a multi-layer mask, reduce
droplets, help your fellow humans. <a
href="https://t.co/COyrdksV9K">pic.twitter.com/COyrdksV9K</a></p>&mdash; Charl
Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a
href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1332014932481732608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November
26, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>What I learned from this would-be altercation, is that it&rsquo;s better for me to
focus my someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet rage into something that&rsquo;s more
constructive:</p>
<p>Strip the issue down as far as you can. Inject information. Combine that with
the desire that many humans share for a society where we can all just get
along.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s probably still not going to work, but just maybe, it&rsquo;ll cause less trouble
and result in a little bit more goodwill, and who knows where that may lead?</p>
<p>P.S. On the topic of mask-wearing: Even if there were no COVID-19, don&rsquo;t you
think we&rsquo;d all be a little better of if the wearing of good masks became the
norm?</p>
<p>There are indications that <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/flu-season-never-came-to-the-southern-hemisphere1/">mask-wearing and physical distancing basically
stopped flu season in the Southern Hemisphere</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Never in my 40-year career have we ever seen rates &hellip; so low</p>
<p>&ndash; Greg Poland, influenza expert at the Mayo Clinic</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="advent-of-code-2020">Advent of Code 2020</h2>
<p>Thanks to this tweet by <a href="https://twitter.com/RameezKhanSA">@RameezKhanSA</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My pledge this year is
to do the <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/AdventOfCode?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#AdventOfCode</a>
in <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Clojure?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Clojure</a>. Looking
forward to it. Already started doing some of last years challenges. Want to
keep it simple. No Leiningen just a plain deps.edn.</p>&mdash; Rameez
(@RameezKhanSA) <a
href="https://twitter.com/RameezKhanSA/status/1332692669190074370?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November
28, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; I am taking part, for the first time, in <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">the Advent of Code</a>!</p>
<p>Nerds from the world over get a new two-part programming puzzle every day at 5
AM UTC, from December 1 to December 25, for a total of 50 puzzles.</p>
<p>The idea is that said nerds use any programming language, or combination of
programming languages, to solve the puzzles and enter the answers on the AoC
website.</p>
<p>The quickest nerds, the ones who manage to solve these puzzles in an amazing
minute or three, earn a highly-coveted place on the <a href="https://adventofcode.com/2020/leaderboard">leaderboard</a>.</p>
<p>Just like Rameez, I wanted to use the AoC to get to know a programming language
better, although in my case that language is Nim.</p>
<p>So far, this has been a great deal of fun!</p>
<p>To my non-programmer friends: Solving puzzles is like concentrated cat nip to
programmers. In the case of AoC, you get unadulterated puzzle solving, and none
of the other complications of writing production software.</p>
<p>Besides the fun, Nim <em>really</em> shines at this. As I mentioned in <a href="/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/#save-image-from-clipboard">the previous
WHV</a>, Nim somehow manages to combine the expressivity and development velocity
of Python, with a great dollop of Python&rsquo;s famed batteries-included, with close
to the metal performance.</p>
<p>(My brain is currently spending background cycles figuring out if I could
somehow use this in a product.)</p>
<p>I am sort of expecting to drop out eventually, because, based on past years,
it&rsquo;s going to take up an increasing amount of time.</p>
<p>However, although I&rsquo;m already happy with what I have (day 6&rsquo;s puzzles completed
on Sunday December 6, ostensibly the end of this WHV&rsquo;s window of reality), I
would be really chuffed reaching the double digits!</p>
<p><em>Narrator: He ended up reaching the double digits.</em></p>
<h2 id="table-mountain-run--ish--2020">Table Mountain Run(ish) 2020</h2>
<p>We thought we were going to do a trail run up Skeleton Gorge.</p>
<p>Well, if one is us, one does not simply run up Skeleton Gorge. Instead, one
huffs and one puffs, for about a kilometre of ascent. It is a substantial
amount of huffing and puffing.</p>
<p>We did get to run on top of the mountain, from the beach at the top of Skeleton
Gorge (yes, there&rsquo;s a beach), to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maclear%27s%5FBeacon">Maclear&rsquo;s Beacon</a>, which I&rsquo;ve now learned was
used in the calculation of the curvature of he Earth, to the old cable station,
past the reservoirs to end up walking really slowly back down Nursery Gorge.</p>
<p>It was an interesting observation that although I found parts of the route hard
and sometimes maybe even a little unpleasant (coming down Nursery Gorge&hellip;)
whilst in the thick of things, the whole memory of the experience started
transmogrifying into <em>wonderful</em> verging on <em>magical</em> extremely soon after we
had reached the finish.</p>
<p>12/10 would do again, but next time a more gradual descent please!</p>
<h2 id="hi-mom">Hi mom</h2>
<p>My mom has now seen three quarters of a century.</p>
<p>I am happy to report that she is as fit as a fiddle. Genetics and some really
great habits are a really solid combination.</p>
<p>Importantly, we are truly fortunate to count her as an integral part of our
household.</p>
<p>(Them is some big words for: We have so much fun together! Our GOUs, who are
also her GOUs, will probably never forget these stories with their Oma.)</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s to the next quarter century!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve convinced her of the great business opportunity of publishing a book at
100 with tips and tricks for other (aspirant) centenarians, so she really needs
to remain as sharp and as fit as she is today!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #202: I don't even have to miss Dr Topol!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 22:16:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/</guid><description> Welcome everyone to this, the two hundred and second edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 27 to Sunday August 9 of the year of our simulation-running overlords 2020.
Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1.
Shape Up: Stop Running in Circles and Ship Work that Matters After it having spent a few quality months in my to-do list, I finally got around to reading the Shape Up book by Ryan Singer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome everyone to this, the two hundred and second edition of the Weekly Head
Voices, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 27 to Sunday August 9 of
the year of our simulation-running overlords 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="closeup_prot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/closeup_prot_hu1c6e2bb0e824a6f072e5b23d6b6aa3d0_796243_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Photo of multiple instances of an important local flower, taken by GOU #1.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="shape-up-stop-running-in-circles-and-ship-work-that-matters">Shape Up: Stop Running in Circles and Ship Work that Matters</h2>
<p>After it having spent a few quality months in my to-do list, I finally got
around to reading <a href="https://basecamp.com/shapeup">the Shape Up book by Ryan Singer</a>.</p>
<p>(You can too, by clicking on that link, it&rsquo;s free!)</p>
<p>This book documents the development methodology that the folks over at
37signals, also the original makers of <a href="https://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a>, <a href="https://basecamp.com/">Basecamp</a>, and most
recently the new email re-imagining <a href="https://hey.com/">HEY</a>, have evolved over the years.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not currently using any of those artifacts, but RoR has made (and is
probably still making) a significant impact on the technology landscape, and
the other products are truly impressive in their own right.</p>
<p>My point is, the 37signals company ships high-impact products like it&rsquo;s
nobody&rsquo;s business, so one should probably pay attention if they are willing to
explain to the rest of us how they are able to perform this feat so
consistently.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re involved in software development, or are interested, then this
compact book is worth your time.</p>
<p>However, until you can get around to it, I present to you the book&rsquo;s own
bullet-list summary (you&rsquo;ll find it in the conclusions chapter), where I&rsquo;ve
embellished each bullet with my from-memory explanation.</p>
<dl>
<dt>Shaped versus unshaped work</dt>
<dd>In Shape Up, each project is a user-visible
feature that can be done in 6 weeks or less. Senior devs in the company
<em>shape</em> the work, which means that they derisk and write down enough to
delineate the work, to specify the parameters, but not so much that it has
been pinned down. The team that gets the project assigned is given free reign
as to <em>how</em> exactly they fill in the space delineated by the shaping.</dd>
<dt>Setting appetites instead of estimates</dt>
<dd>Instead of specifying a feature,
and then estimating how much time it will take (feature first, number
second), Shape Up suggests rather determining at management level how much
appetite / motivation there is for a feature, up to a maximum of 6 weeks,
knowing that the feature will be <em>hammered</em> down to fit into the appetite for
it (number first, feature second).</dd>
<dt>Designing at the right level of abstraction</dt>
<dd>As mentioned above, the
shaping process has to reach the Goldilocks level somewhere between abstract
and concrete. Enough detail so there are no surprises that could risk the
success of the project, but little enough so that the team has the freedom to
construct a solution independently and in a more data-driven fashion.</dd>
<dt>Concepting with breadboards and fat marker sketches</dt>
<dd>These are practical
tricks to keep the detail level under control. For example, during shaping, a
<strong>fat marker</strong> is used to draw UI ideas to prevent the shapers from inking in
too much detail.</dd>
<dt>Making bets with a capped downside (the circuit breaker) and honoring uninterrupted time</dt>
<dd>This
is pretty hardcore. If a project runs over its time (e.g. 6 weeks), it is
cancelled, that is, moth-balled. End of story. As a corollary, teams are not
to be interrupted during their project cycle.</dd>
<dt>Choosing the right cycle length (six weeks)</dt>
<dd>Six weeks is the maximum time
a team will get to finish a feature. This seems to be the sweet spot for
features that are significant enough to be interesting, but don&rsquo;t get too big
to manage.</dd>
<dt>A cool-down period between cycles</dt>
<dd>After every six week cycle, all teams
get two weeks of cool-down time. This is to be used for fixing bugs, writing
tests, doing spikes, and just generally recovering from the feature
development cycle.</dd>
<dt>Breaking projects apart into scopes</dt>
<dd>As a team works on a certain feature,
the sub-tasks that they formulate as they work, can be naturally grouped into
thematic scopes. It&rsquo;s important that these emergent groupings are closely
monitored and updated. They are useful for understanding the feature, and for
reporting on progress.</dd>
<dt>Downhill versus uphill work and communicating about unknowns</dt>
<dd>The team
gives <em>asynchronous</em> feedback on project progress by plotting each scope on a
<a href="https://basecamp.com/features/hill-charts">hill chart</a>. To me this is yet another interesting and useful concept from the
book. If a scope is somewhere on the uphill part, there are still unknowns
that have to be investigated. Once the team thinks there are no more
unknowns, a scope can be moved past the top and somewhere onto the downhill
section.</dd>
<dt>Scope hammering to separate must-haves from nice-to-haves</dt>
<dd>In this case,
scope is used in the more traditional software development sense, and scope
hammering refers to the action of whittling down features until a project
fits into the time allotted to it.</dd>
</dl>
<p>At work, we are currently experimenting with elements of this methodology for a
new product we&rsquo;re working on. I&rsquo;m curious to see how much of this will work in
our setup. It sure looks good on paper!</p>
<p>(The book impressed me further with its chapter containing practical advice on
how to implement various levels of Shape Up in organizations of various types
and sizes. Super pragmatic!)</p>
<h2 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion Effect</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently reading the organizational psychologist Adam Grant&rsquo;s book <a href="https://www.adamgrant.net/give-and-take">Give
and Take</a>.</p>
<p>In this book he describes the classic study led by Harvard psychologist Robert
Rosenthal, where he told the teachers of 18 different classrooms that 20
percent of their children had scored high on a Harvard aptitude test, when in
fact they had been randomly chosen.</p>
<p>In spite of being <em>randomly chosen</em>, those children showed consistently higher
performance than their peers, even when they were measured years later.</p>
<p>From Grant&rsquo;s book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Harvard test was discerning: when the students took the cognitive ability
test a year later, the bloomers [the randomly selected kids, ed.] improved more
than the rest of the students. The bloomers gained an average of twelve IQ
points, compared with average gains of only eight points for their
classmates. The bloomers outgained their peers by roughly fifteen IQ points in
first grade and ten IQ points in second grade. Two years later, the bloomers
were still outgaining their classmates. The intelligence test was successful in
identifying high-potential students: the bloomers got smarter &ndash; and at a faster
rate than their classmates</p>
</blockquote>
<p>and then a paragraph or two later:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Teachers' beliefs created self-fulfilling prophecies. When teachers believed
their students were bloomers, they set high expectations for their success. As
a result, the teachers engaged in more supportive behaviors that boosted the
students' confidence and enhanced their learning and development. Teachers
communicated more warmly to the bloomers, gave them more challenging
assignments, called on them more often, and provided them with more
feedback. Many experiments have replicated these effects, showing that teacher
expectations are especially important for improving the grades and intelligence
test scores of low-achieving students and members of stigmatized minority
groups.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just to reiterate: These kids were randomly selected, but just because their
teachers <em>thought</em> that they had scored higher on an aptitude test and hence
treated them differently, they started and then kept out-performing their peers
for years.</p>
<p>Grant writes that similar experiments have been successfully performed in different
learning contexts, and the results were always the same.</p>
<p>This really blows my mind folks. I hope I can keep this knowledge close.</p>
<h2 id="yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">Yet another social media fast because you have to keep on doing them</h2>
<p><a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">The Great Social Media Fast of 2019</a> really was great when it started, but it
unfortunately fizzled out a few months later, probably when the end-of-the-year
vacation started.</p>
<p>When COVID-19 hit, I had such a need for up-to-the-minute news that my phone
soon had twitter almost permanently on position #1 of the app suggestions you
get when you swipe down.</p>
<p>Fast-forward another few months, and I was again stuck in TwiFRaF-Yo like it
was nobody&rsquo;s business.</p>
<p>Anyways, this weekend I had some serious discussions with myself, during which
I <em>again</em> had to convince myself that the select few jewels of Twitter (Dr
Topol, I salute you) and the rest of TwiFRaF-Yo did not even come close to
justifying the amount of mental cycles I was spending.</p>
<p>Fortunately I won that debate, and so now I&rsquo;m again officially on a social
media fast, during which I have resolved to read more books, blogs and other
long-form content, and to write more notes and blogs.</p>
<p>My brain already feels substantially more roomy and relaxed than it did a mere
day ago.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I didn&rsquo;t mention one of my favourite College Humor skits
in this context:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315"
src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/md4kM9AKjHs" frameborder="0"
allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
allowfullscreen></iframe>
<h3 id="a-not-quite-satisfactory-solution-for-not-having-to-miss-dr-topol">A not quite satisfactory solution for not having to miss Dr Topol</h3>
<p>Dr Topol did briefly complicate my temporary exit.</p>
<p>How was I going to keep up to date with his twitter stream without using the
twitter app and getting sucked in?</p>
<p>Unfortunately, my inoreader &ldquo;supporter&rdquo; subscription does not include its
social media subscription function that does exactly what I need, and the
upgrade is $50 per year instead of my current $20.</p>
<p>While I think about this, I&rsquo;ve activated <a href="https://ifttt.com/applets/xcHFiVvR-get-an-email-when-there-s-a-new-tweet-from-a-specific-username">the IFTTT twitter to email thingy</a>.</p>
<p>This sends me an email for <em>each</em> tweet, which constitutes a whole new problem
in itself.</p>
<h3 id="inoreader-satisfaction-with-a-side-of-retail-therapy">Inoreader satisfaction with a side of retail therapy</h3>
<p><em>&hellip; 8 hours pass after this post was published &hellip;</em></p>
<p>Narrator: <em>It became a whole new problem in itself.</em></p>
<p>Dr Topol can&rsquo;t stop tweeting admittedly truly interesting health- and
covid-related research, but the format of one email per tweet is indeed not
going to cut it.</p>
<p>I have deactivated that IFTTT thingy, and upgraded my inoreader subscription to
pro.</p>
<p>This is where I read all my blog subscriptions when I make time for that, so
having Dr Topol&rsquo;s feed there as well makes a great deal more sense.</p>
<h2 id="an-ai-to-fall-in-love--with">An AI to fall in love (with)</h2>
<p><a href="https://lexfridman.com/">Lex Fridman</a> is another of the internet&rsquo;s jewels, who is fortunately accessible
via long-form podcast.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://lexfridman.com/matt-botvinick/">episode #106</a>, he talks with <a href="https://hai.stanford.edu/people/matthew-botvinick">Prof. Matt Botvinick</a>, a brilliant
neuro-scientist who also employs AI in his research, and clearly likes to think
deeply about deep questions.</p>
<p>One of the things I (and apparently many of his interviewees) love about Dr
Fridman, is the left-field questions he often poses.</p>
<p>He does this with Botvinick:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But let me ask the over-romanticized question: Do you think we&rsquo;ll ever engineer
an AGI system that we humans would be able to love and that would love us back?
So have that level and depth of connection?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Goodness, so many layers.</p>
<p>What do you think?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #198: A short update for future me</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 11:51:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/</guid><description> Figure 1: Evening walk with the fam-jam up a familiar mountain route after a failed attempt at finding the start of a far more spectacular but unfamiliar route.
I was planning to skip a week, because a whole blog post about the work that has been filling my days is really no fun at all.
However, after a good night&amp;rsquo;s sleep, my mind changed itself, as it is wont to do, and in the morning gave the advice that future me would in fact be quite interested to look back into these times.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="sunset_walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/sunset_walk_huda656488f3ba1a055da1deb07ab09d51_604659_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Evening walk with the fam-jam up a familiar mountain route after a failed attempt at finding the start of a far more spectacular but unfamiliar route."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Evening walk with the fam-jam up a familiar mountain route after a failed attempt at finding the start of a far more spectacular but unfamiliar route.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I was planning to skip a week, because a whole blog post about the work that
has been filling my days is really no fun at all.</p>
<p>However, after a good night&rsquo;s sleep, my mind changed itself, as it is wont to
do, and in the morning gave the advice that future me would in fact be quite
interested to look back into these times.</p>
<p>So here we are, in the probably shorter-than-average 198th edition of the
Weekly Head Voices, ostensibly covering the week from Monday June 8 to Sunday
June 14. 2020.</p>
<h2 id="how-will-2020-go-down-in-history">How will 2020 go down in history?</h2>
<p>I wonder if in the future we will have some interesting name for 2020, or for
the era that 2020 ushered in?</p>
<p>The following tweet by Peter Kolchinsky, virologist and biotech investor,
struck a chord with me:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I think 2020 will be
remembered as the year politics tried to bend science &amp; nature yet they
just wouldn’t bend. Whether it’s how the virus spreads or which vaccines and
drugs work, the truth is waiting to be discovered with proper scientific
method, not punditry.</p>&mdash; Peter Kolchinsky
(@PeterKolchinsky) <a href="https://twitter.com/PeterKolchinsky/status/1272337332402884608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">June
15, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>I really hope that he&rsquo;s right.</p>
<p>In this, COVID-19 is a lot like science, except that it&rsquo;s a whole lot less
forgiving:</p>








<figure>
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/science_and_your_beliefs.jpg"
            

        /> 
</figure>

<p>I am scientifically extremely curious to see how all of this plays out, as the
heads of denialists (of any kind) are known to consist of some of the densest
materials in the universe.</p>
<p>Let us wait and see!</p>
<h3 id="aside-longevity-of-twitter-citations-in-this-blog">Aside: Longevity of Twitter citations in this blog</h3>
<p>Just to allay your fears, fictitious reader, and mine, I have just
double-checked: If twitter were ever to disappear completely from the internet,
the text of the above tweet is embedded in this blog and will remain readable.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know what the chances of twitter disappearing are, but one has to
remember that it&rsquo;s only been around since 2006, although it feels like it&rsquo;s
been part of the universe forever.</p>
<p>For those of you who find such things interesting, my late joining in 2009 is
of course <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">documented in a post on this blog</a>.</p>
<h3 id="how-we-are-personally-doing">How we are personally doing</h3>
<p>It was the main motivation for deciding to write this post, but I&rsquo;m hiding this
short piece away here in a subsection.</p>
<p>With us as a family it&rsquo;s going as well as it possibly could, under the
circumstances.</p>
<p>We have each other, and we appreciate each other. We have made our home as
comfortable as possible, because we are serious about physical distancing as
much as possible.</p>
<p>We are super grateful for what we have, and we are acutely aware of the fact
that most people don&rsquo;t have it this good.</p>
<p>GOU#1 sometimes struggles a bit with the fact that some of her friends are out
socializing, when we, the science-based parents, are sticking more closely to
the guidelines.</p>
<p>South Africa is currently at 73533 confirmed cases with 1568 deaths (2.1% <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/covid-mortality-risk">CFR,
or Case Fatality Rate</a>).</p>
<p>The whole province of the Western Cape (where we live) is responsible for a
disproportionately large part of those figures: 42892 cases and 1111 deaths.</p>
<p>In addition, we are fortunate enough to have grandma living with us, so we are
playing it as safe as we can. (Grandma is one of the healthiest, fittest 74
year olds that you could ever run into.)</p>
<p>Dear GOU#1 in the future: You were already so graceful and understanding
in 2020. Hopefully when future you reads this, you&rsquo;ll be reminded that we
mostly have good reasons for what we do.</p>
<h2 id="on-engineers-being-right-and-being-nice">On engineers, being right and being nice</h2>
<p>If you have an engineer in your life, this should ring bells, quite loudly:</p>








<figure>
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/arguing_with_an_engineer_hu88272c4f7339ec6f85b7ef50bd009825_28467_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/arguing_with_an_engineer.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Arguing with an Engineer is a lot like wrestling in the mud with a pig, after a couple of hours you realize the pig likes it."/> 
</figure>

<p>Yes, we love arguing.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the goal is usually not to win, but to reach the best answer.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;ve had a good argument with your team about some issue, and the winning
configuration was implemented, that engineering decision has a pretty good
motivation behind it.</p>
<p>More importantly, it usually has the buy-in of the team.</p>
<p>All of that being said, during the recent months a mis-remembered yet more
appropriate version of a quote has been slowly but surely integrating with the
latest version of my wetware.</p>
<p>(That&rsquo;s nerd-speak for: &ldquo;I&rsquo;m really trying to apply this life guideline more
consistently my fellow humans&rdquo;.)</p>
<p>The original quote is the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>They may forget what you said — but they will never forget how you made them
feel. &ndash; Carl W. Buehner</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(It has often been mis-attributed, most notably to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maya%5FAngelou">Maya Angelou</a>, but <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2014/04/06/they-feel/">Quote
Investigator</a> says it&rsquo;s most probably due to Buehner.)</p>
<p>My mis-remembered version is as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>People will quickly forget whether you were <em>right</em> or <em>wrong</em>, but they will
never forget how you made them feel.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m just going to leave that there.</p>
<h2 id="post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">Post Scriptum: The WHV approach to life, the universe and everything</h2>
<p>It <em>just</em> occurred to me that the core philosophy I teach my GOUs rests on
two main pillars: Love and Science.</p>
<p>That ordering is deliberate, as love sometimes has to override science, just
like being kind sometimes has to override being right.</p>
<p>As a reminder, <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/"><em>The WHV&rsquo;s Two no Three Rules for Achieving Great Success in
Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em></a> rests on top of those
pillars. The rules are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be useful.</li>
<li>Be likable.</li>
<li>Evolve.</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #137: Let me mine your metadata.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/03/25/weekly-head-voices-137/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Mar 2018 20:42:29 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/03/25/weekly-head-voices-137/</guid><description> Winter is coming, somewhere on the R44 between Betty’s Bay and Gordon’s Bay.
Wisdom from the Twitters Let me start this week’s edition with something that a friend forwarded, quite ironically, from the dark underbelly of the internet, also known as “twitter”:
Daily activities to avoid:
- Consuming endless (news) feeds
- Discussion w/ anyone with a big ego
- Thinking without pen &amp;amp; paper
- Arguing on Twitter</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/IMG_3443.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/IMG_3443-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Winter is coming, somewhere on the R44 between Betty’s Bay and Gordon’s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Winter is coming, somewhere on the R44 between Betty’s Bay and Gordon’s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h1 id="wisdom-from-the-twitters">Wisdom from the Twitters</h1>
<p>Let me start this week’s edition with something that <a href="https://twitter.com/francoistweet">a friend</a> forwarded, quite ironically, from the dark underbelly of the internet, also known as “twitter”:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Daily activities to avoid:<br><br>- Consuming endless (news) feeds<br>- Discussion w/ anyone with a big ego<br>- Thinking without pen &amp; paper<br>- Arguing on Twitter<br>- Mindlessly saying yes to meetings</p>&mdash; muneeb.btc (@muneeb) <a href="https://twitter.com/muneeb/status/975432822973399042?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">March 18, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>Most of these resonate with me, except for arguing on twitter.</p>
<p>This is not because I disagree, but rather because I sort of went cold-twitter-turkey about a year ago, a departure which has had only positive effects on my humanity, as well as on my trust in the goodness of humans.</p>
<p>I still sometimes slip and fall into arguments on other platforms,  where the same advice unfortunately holds.</p>
<h1 id="deletefacebook">#DeleteFacebook?</h1>
<p>On the topic of online arguments, I would like to bring the next interesting conundrum to your astute attention.</p>
<p>There is at this moment quite some internet rage due to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/news/series/cambridge-analytica-files">the details that have been revealed about the extent to which the company Cambridge Analytica managed to exfiltrate social network data from facebook</a>, in order to perform extremely targeted advertising and hence psychological manipulation to get vulnerable users to vote for Trump, and to vote for Brexit leave.</p>
<p>Readers of this blog might remember that I <a href="/2017/03/25/fake-news-is-just-the-beginning/">already talked about this exact issue <em><strong>one year ago</strong></em> to the day</a>. I even cited <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2017/feb/26/robert-mercer-breitbart-war-on-media-steve-bannon-donald-trump-nigel-farage">this early article in The Guardian mentioning Robert Mercer, Bannon, and Cambridge Analytica</a> and their role in geo-political interference.</p>
<p>At this point, I hope you will allow me a quick two-pronged educational intermezzo:</p>
<ol>
<li>Do read my posts carefully, and you too can be all like “I knew that a year ago you silly muggles”.</li>
<li>Probably more importantly, read <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/">The Guardian</a>. (I would like to thank the brilliant <a href="https://www.keele.ac.uk/istm/staff/edchadwick/">Dr Ed Chadwick</a> for introducing me to The Guardian so many years ago in Delft and/or Amsterdam, over either a pint of Irish stout (which he also introduced me to) and/or a Trappist.</li>
</ol>
<p>Anyways, back to my rant.</p>
<p>So the internet is angry (<em>years</em> too late), and everyone and their mom is telling each other to #DeleteFacebook.</p>
<p>I too disapprove in the strongest terms of what Cambridge Analytica and its backers did (besides the immorality of the approach, conservative thinking is really primitive), and Facebook facilitated.</p>
<p>However, I also think that we find ourselves in a tricky baby-with-bathwater situation.</p>
<p>Let me ironically summarise the two main points from a comment I posted on Facebook:</p>
<ol>
<li>What happens when the clever / privacy-conscious people leave facebook? It becomes an even bigger echo chamber for the uneducated. Is it not our duty to come and fight with a vaccine denialist, or a conservative or someone who is in some other way unenlightened now and then? (instead of arguing, you could also choose a more socratic approach, or just be that persistently cool perfectly rational actor in any discussion)</li>
<li>What replaces facebook as the admittedly flawed but largest virtual human gathering ever? Related to this: Facebook is the most <em>accessible</em> publication platform we have ever had. More people have a voice and can be heard than ever before. Do we really want to take that away?</li>
</ol>
<p>Let me know in the comments what you think. I promise I’ll only mine a little bit of your metadata.</p>
<h1 id="new-arduino-blog-posts-at-vxlabs">New arduino blog posts at vxlabs</h1>
<p>My arduino – artwork journey continues. Over on vxlabs I have published a <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/03/23/which-jumper-to-set-on-the-itead-xbee-shield-v1-1-for-use-with-a-3-3v-arduino/">short post on the itead shield 3.3V jumper</a>, and a much more interesting <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/03/24/developing-arduino-sketches-with-jetbrains-clion-a-minimal-example/">post showing a barebones solution (i.e. no additional software) to using the JetBrains CLion IDE for Arduino sketch programming</a>.</p>
<p>I hope that these help future travellers on their quest.</p>
<h1 id="whv-film-club-blade-runner-2049">WHV Film Club: Blade Runner 2049</h1>
<p>The original Blade Runner was an important part of my upbringing.</p>
<p>This weekend I, up to this point 100% unspoilered, finally got around to watching all but the last 30 minutes of Blade Runner 2049, and I was utterly blown away.</p>
<p>It’s true what they say: You can take just about any scene from the movie, and look at it like you look at a painting. The scenes are thought- and emotion-provoking.</p>
<p>Without giving anything away, the story is an amazing example of how great science fiction is the perfect mechanism for making us think deeply about strange but extremely relevant human situations.</p>
<h1 id="tot-gauw">Tot gauw</h1>
<p>Over the past few weeks, these blog posts have played a small but necessary role in more than one high quality human connection.</p>
<p>Each time this happens, the time I spend here feels like it has been rewarded 100 times over.</p>
<p>I thank you, and I look forward to the next time that we may meet.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Look mom, Hacker News front page!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/20/look-mom-hacker-news-front-page/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 20:11:57 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/20/look-mom-hacker-news-front-page/</guid><description> (In my previous post, I promised I was going to micro-blog from here. That post is now on the HN frontpage, which makes for a perfect first micro-blog!)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=13000445">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/2016-11-20-220721_729x319_scrot.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>(In <a href="/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/">my previous post</a>, I promised I was going to micro-blog from here. That post is now on the HN frontpage, which makes for a perfect first micro-blog!)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Let’s replace Twitter with something much better.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 10:05:10 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/</guid><description> (There is also a Russian language version of this post available, translated and published by SoftDroid on 2017-04-12.)
I love Twitter. I love that by following certain people, my timeline has become a stream of interesting and entertaining information. I love that sometimes I am able to fit my little publication just so into the 140 characters given to me. I found The Trumpocalypse truly depressing, but the joke tweets were golden:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(There is also a <a href="http://softdroid.net/chem-zamenit-twitter-alternativa">Russian language version of this post available</a>, translated and published by <a href="http://softdroid.net/">SoftDroid</a> on 2017-04-12.)</em></p>
<h1 id="i-love-twitter">I love Twitter.</h1>
<p>I love that by following certain people, my timeline has become a stream of interesting and entertaining information. I love that sometimes I am able to fit my little publication just <em>so</em> into the 140 characters given to me. I found The Trumpocalypse truly depressing, but the joke tweets were golden:</p>








<figure><a href="https://twitter.com/AFLNow/status/796210777241710592">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/2016-11-19-112633_665x359_scrot.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I love that Twitter is so widely accessible and utilised. For example here in South Africa, if you make a small effort, you can get great, grassroots-level inputs from all corners of our political spectrum. This has helped me tremendously to try and understand our complicated environment a little better.</p>
<h1 id="however">However…</h1>
<p>I really don’t like that we are all putting our content, including those golden joke tweets, into someone else’s silo. You’re giving Twitter full control over all of your content. That’s a huge price to pay for the exposure, especially in the light of the fact that there are user-controlled alternatives.</p>
<p>Also, with Twitter’s commercial survival <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/david-giannetto/the-future-of-twitter-sta_b_9232280.html">often being debated</a>, can we really trust this budding public service (it has become that central) with our public history?</p>
<p>Far more importantly, Twitter is doing a really <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2016/10/19/13328380/twitter-abuse-disney-salesforce-bids-pulled">bad job at keeping abusive users and abuse out of the system</a>. Users have very little power against abusive groups. There have been a great number of cases when users were forced to leave Twitter, in effect being muzzled, due to direct and concerted abuse.</p>
<p>This can’t be right.</p>
<h1 id="couldwe-replace-twitter-with-something-better">Could we replace Twitter with something better?</h1>
<p>Yes, I think we can.</p>
<p>Blogs and RSS, the latter a system for subscribing to a collection of blogs, and being able to read their posts in a single chronological stream, almost exactly like Twitter, have been around forever.</p>
<p>Setting up a blog at for example <a href="https://wordpress.com/">WordPress.com</a> is not much more complicated than creating a new Twitter account. Readers can subscribe to your blog using any number of apps, for example the <a href="https://en.blog.wordpress.com/2013/05/29/wordpress-reader/">WordPress.com Reader</a> or any other so-called aggregator, such as <a href="http://www.inoreader.com/">Inoreader</a> or <a href="https://feedly.com/i/welcome">Feedly</a>. Your list of subscriptions can be freely exported from one aggregator and imported into another.</p>
<p>Instead of posting your 140 character masterpiece via the Twitter app, you would do so via the <a href="https://apps.wordpress.com/mobile/">WordPress app</a>. You can write short tweets, or long essays, with as much embedded media and with as much typesetting as you like.</p>
<p>By default, you have to moderate (approve or deny) comments on any of your posts. Bye-bye abusive users. In fact, you’re able to muzzle <em>them</em>, which is how it should be. This is <em>your</em> content and <em>your</em> voice after all. However, they are also free to start their own blogs of course. Everyone else is free never to go there.</p>
<p>Furthermore, your content can be easily exported into a self-hosted blog (using the open source wordpress.org software), such as this one, where you truly control the whole system. In all cases, the content is yours to do with as you please.</p>
<h1 id="what-needs-to-happen">What needs to happen?</h1>
<p>It looks like all the components of the solution have been right here all along.</p>
<p>However, to become as accessible as Twitter, they definitely require some polish (this used to be “a little polish”, but commenter AJ made valid points) .</p>
<p>If for example the WordPress app became as straight-forward as the Twitter app, for setting up a new blog, for posting and for reading all of your followed blogs, that would be great.</p>
<p>If the WordPress app, or any alternative, could come up with a streamlined user story for the posting of short (approximately 140 characters maybe?! :) snippets, that would be even better. (If you did not know about post formats yet, <a href="https://en.support.wordpress.com/posts/post-formats/">check them out</a>. For exmample, the “aside” post format is a way to post a short title-less snippet to your blog.)</p>
<p>Furthermore, we definitely need a good discovery platform. This is the thing where Twitter will recommend new accounts to follow based on your existing subscriptions. WordPress does something similar, but it has to be much more discoverable.</p>
<p>In the coming weeks, I will be running a little experiment by trying to post even my short, previously twitter-only blurbs to this blog. I will have to cross-tweet these, but at least the primary source will be right here in my own database.</p>
<p>What do you think? Is this possible? Is it something you would like?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Facebook Like, Share and Retweet buttons in your WordPress</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/02/facebook-like-share-and-retweet-buttons-in-your-wordpress/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2010 21:09:36 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/02/facebook-like-share-and-retweet-buttons-in-your-wordpress/</guid><description> Hey man, I’m really busy at the moment, but it took me unnecessarily long to get those really hip facebook like, facebook share and retweet buttons everywhere on my blog, so I thought I’d try and save you some time by dropping a quick note on how I did it.
Adding the Facebook Like button functionality wasted the most time, because there are far too many plugins and howtos that claim to work and don’t quite.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hey man, I’m really busy at the moment, but it took me unnecessarily long to get those really hip facebook like, facebook share and retweet buttons everywhere on my blog, so I thought I’d try and save you some time by dropping a quick note on how I did it.</p>
<p>Adding the Facebook Like button functionality wasted the most time, because there are far too many plugins and howtos that claim to work and don’t quite. I ended up using the Like plugin (<a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/like/" title="Wordpress page for like plugin">official wordpress page</a> and <a href="http://blog.bottomlessinc.com/2010/04/creating-a-wordpress-plugin-add-the-new-facebook-like-button-to-your-posts/" title="Like plugin website">plugin website</a>), because it has the best documentation that includes details on <a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/like/faq/" title="Like plugin FAQ">all the ways in which things can go wrong</a>, and there are many.  I’m using the IFRAME option, also because that seems to work most of the time.  I had a hard time finding this plugin in the built-in directory, so I downloaded and installed it manually.</p>
<p>For the facebook share button, I use the <a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/facebook-share-new/" title="facebook share (new) button plugin homepage"><em>Facebook Share (New) Button</em> plugin</a>, and for the retweet button, I’m using the <a href="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/topsy/" title="Topsy Retweet Button plugin homepage"><em>Topsy Retweet Button</em> plugin</a>.  I installed both of them from the built-in “Plugins | Add New” directory.</p>
<p>In all three cases, I made use of the plugin options to have the buttons placed all over my blog, instead of manually editing the theme.</p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy your shiny buttons, and I look forward to seeing you for the next <a href="http://cpbotha.net/category/weekly-head-voices/" title="Weekly Head Voices category">Weekly Head Voices</a>!</p>
<p><em>P.S. feel free to click on my buttons, right below this post.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>When the going gets tough…</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2009 10:44:13 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/</guid><description> The past months have been hectic. Since the start of 2009 I have initiated, developed and run the brand new TU Delft Medical Visualisation M.Sc. course (cutting-edge learning methods with integrated lectures and hands-on exercises, more on this in a future post), released DeVIDE 9.1, worked on bunches of research proposals, co-authored articles and setup new research projects. This happened in parallel with my normal work duties. The lecture/workshop part of the course is now done, proposals and articles were all submitted last week and newly setup projects are coming along nicely.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The past months have been hectic. Since the start of 2009 I have initiated, developed and run the brand new <a href="http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4307" title="IN4307 website">TU Delft Medical Visualisation M.Sc. course</a> (cutting-edge learning methods with integrated lectures and hands-on exercises, more on this in a future post), released <a href="http://devidenews.wordpress.com/2009/02/04/devide-91-released/" title="DeVIDE 9.1 release blog posting">DeVIDE 9.1</a>, worked on bunches of research proposals, co-authored articles and setup new research projects. This happened in parallel with my normal work duties.   The lecture/workshop part of the course is now done, proposals and articles were all submitted last week and newly setup projects are coming along nicely.  It’s a strange feeling sitting here on a Saturday morning <em>not</em> having to work towards some deadline:  I’d sort of gotten used to working 7-day weeks.</p>
<p>In the darkest periods of the past months, when that help-the-world-is-crashing-in-on-me feeling tends to rear its ugly head, I realised how much I enjoy what I’m doing.  It’s tough at times chasing a deadline when you’d prefer relaxing for a bit, but the work is fantastically stimulating.  It’s brilliant when you manage to formulate that one paragraph in the proposal just so that your research idea gives you goose bumps.  It’s tremendously gratifying when a bright student goes completely over the top solving an almost impossibly hard problem.  It’s beautiful when the value of your (that’s plural!) work gets confirmed by an independent source.  It’s truly addictive working with like-minded and creative colleagues.  It’s mildly entertaining thinking up new superlatives and qualifying adverbs when describing your work!</p>








<figure><a href="http://www.uibk.ac.at/exphys/museum/html/details/mech/guericke.html.en">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/magdeburg.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>In about a week I’ll leave for a month-long micro-sabbatical at the <a href="http://wwwisg.cs.uni-magdeburg.de/cvcms/en" title="University of Magdeburg Visualisation Group">research group of Prof. Bernhard Preim</a> at the University of Magdeburg.  Purpose: <em>Do something new and interesting.</em></p>
<p>I know, it’s a tough life.</p>
<p>P.S. Just so you won’t think that I have the perfect job, I do have one serious complaint:  They don’t buy me new laptops even nearly often enough.</p>
<p>P.P.S. On that rather negative note, I’d like to conclude (If your pedantic sensibilities are urging you to comment on me concluding in a post-postscriptum, don’t.) with a list of odds and ends:</p>
<ul>
<li>GTD was a life-saver especially during these past few months.  I did let tasks slip every so often, but it was all in a controlled fashion.  Remember kids: Searching for the perfect GTD implementation can also ruin your life, so just choose a system and work with it.</li>
<li>Another lesson that was confirmed: Expectation management is important.  If you won’t be able to get around to a  mail or project within a reasonable time, mail and say so!  This is much better than keeping quiet and letting the other party come to all the wrong conclusions.  I’m not 100%  on this yet, but definitely getting there.</li>
<li>Google Docs is brilliant for collaborative proposal writing.  You have to put some effort in initially to make it look like a real proposal, but the rewards in terms of saved time (your most valuable asset) are great.  Sending around Word (blech!  urgh!  hate hate hate!) documents with track changes gets really old really fast.  Google Docs does everything you need for real-time collaborative proposal writing and does it <em>really well</em>.</li>
<li>I’m on Twitter now, in spite of often having said that it’s stupid and I’d never do it.  I am sort of enjoying it, although it does seem to have an effect on my blogging as it offers an alternative outlet for small gripes and rants.  Follow me on <a href="http://twitter.com/cpbotha" title="My twitter profile">http://twitter.com/cpbotha</a></li>
</ul>
<p>P.P.P.S. I would have liked to end with some profound quote, but I’m fresh out.  I humbly suggest spending the one minute you’ve just saved thinking really deep thoughts.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>