<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>stellenbosch on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/stellenbosch/</link><description>Recent content in stellenbosch on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:43:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/stellenbosch/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #168: Postcards from the edge.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:43:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek, Stellenbosch. My friend showed me a photo and said &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s a picture of me when I was younger&rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger. &ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)
In this edition of the WHV, I cast my now older eyes back on the week starting on Monday, April 1 and ending on Sunday, April 7, 2019.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="postcard_cafe_view.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



</a>
<figcaption> 
Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes
you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek,
Stellenbosch.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<blockquote>
<p>My friend showed me a photo and said &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s a picture of me when I was
younger&rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger.
&ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this edition of the WHV, I cast my now older eyes back on the week starting
on Monday, April 1 and ending on Sunday, April 7, 2019.</p>
<p>I have to apologise for the extremely high nerd content. There will be wine at
the end to make up for it!</p>
<h2 id="working-late-like-its-1998">Working late like it&rsquo;s 1998.</h2>
<p>At the start of the week, I had resolved to get more sleep.</p>
<p>It seems that when I have a good night&rsquo;s sleep, really working that
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glymphatic_system">glymphatic system</a> (I&rsquo;m
currently fascinated by the glymphatic system, I hope you like it too),
amongst other nightly repair activities, there is a greater probability that I
am able to hold my focus the next day.</p>
<p>This was going swimmingly.</p>
<p>At least that was the case until Wednesday, when I decided that the time had
come to port <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs</a>, the far more nerdy sister of this
blog, from <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">wordpress to hugo as
well</a>.</p>
<p>One thing led to another, and by 1:00AM (on a school night no less!) I was
busy wrapping up the isso commenting system configuration.</p>
<p>(We&rsquo;re able to use free and ad-free disqus over here because this is a
personal blog. vxlabs on the other hand is strictly speaking a commercial
site, even although it&rsquo;s filled with non-commercial blog posts.)</p>
<p>One of the many funny things about being a nerd, is that it&rsquo;s almost
impossible to go to bed before a technical thing like this has been
convincingly put to bed.</p>
<p>Fortunately this late night indiscretion yielded a working self-hosted
commenting system, and, far more importantly, a <a href="/2019/04/06/isso-on-webfaction/">rather attractively styled
post, thanks to the Hugo-port, detailing the whole
installation</a>.</p>
<p>In entirely predictable fashion, the next day was not the best focus-wise.</p>
<p>P.S. 1998 - first postgrad year in the DSP lab. All-nighters all the way down&hellip;</p>
<figure>
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu9ee58e4bdba0ae214d7d56f78a627136_96292_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu9ee58e4bdba0ae214d7d56f78a627136_96292_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu9ee58e4bdba0ae214d7d56f78a627136_96292_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



<figcaption>DSP lab, somewhen between 97 - 99.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="nim-surprise">nim-surprise.</h2>
<p>I chose Isso because it&rsquo;s Python.</p>
<p>DayJob(tm) is all about Python, so this was a great choice in terms of time
savings.</p>
<p>With all of the time I had saved, I decided that I would experiment with
re-implementing parts of Isso in <a href="https://fsharp.org/">f#</a>, my current hobby
functional language.</p>
<p>Setting aside the irony here, I learned after some time that getting f#, the
impressive looking <a href="https://fsprojects.github.io/SQLProvider/">SQLProvider</a> and
sqlite (isso&rsquo;s database) all working together on Linux was <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/fsharp/comments/8ufvzz/how_can_i_add_sqlprovider_to_my_existing_project/e1idy1o/">&ldquo;probably the
single most complicated thing that you can do with a F# project, when it comes
to
tooling&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>In this case, I was thankfully able to switch gears and did a brief review of
possible candidates for a functional(ish), memory efficient, fast(ish)
compilation languages that could be used to implement an Isso web-service
replacement.</p>
<p>Somehow I ended up with <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a>.</p>
<p>This has been on my radar for a while now, but there were always shinier
things to try.</p>
<p>I think what might have put me off was the similarity to Python.</p>
<p>So, with the rest of the time I had saved choosing Isso, I got up to
speed(ish) with nim by starting to implement a replacement for parts of the
isso commenting system.</p>
<p>I was quite positively surprised by the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Compilation speed: The nim compiler transforms my webservice code into C and
then compiles that in about 1.2 seconds.</li>
<li>Performance and memory size of resultant binary: This is not a fair
comparison to Python, but the multi-threaded nim service consumes a few
megabytes in total.</li>
<li>Availability of packages especially for building a web service like this:
Using the nimble package manager, I could install
<a href="https://github.com/dom96/jester">jester</a> and had my first running
web-service in a few minutes.</li>
<li>Built-in sqlite support.</li>
<li>Real macros: I used the list comprehension one in the <code>sugar</code> module.</li>
</ul>
<p>This was really just an exercise (for now), but I have a new tool for whenever
I need to write a fast and compact compiled web-service again!</p>
<p>P.S. Learning new programming languages is one of my favourite things.</p>
<p>P.P.S. Thanks to the internet and open source, and especially tools like
github, we are currently going through a sort of programming language Cambrian
explosion. See this <a href="http://fll.presidentbeef.com/">Fledgling Languages List</a>
for example. Pony!</p>
<h2 id="decompression">Decompression.</h2>
<p>On Sunday, we made the drive out to Jonkershoek in Stellenbosch.</p>
<p>Even although it&rsquo;s only 40 minutes away, I haven&rsquo;t been there in far too
long. It&rsquo;s a truly beautiful corner of the planet.</p>
<p>At the Postcard Café, after some internal deliberation, I made the decision
that the moment was special enough to interrupt LAZ
(lifestyle-alcohol-zero(tm)) with an all the more special glass of the
<a href="https://winemag.co.za/stark-conde-the-field-blend-2014/">Stark-Condé Field Blend white
wine</a>.</p>
<p>This is a hyper-local blend of Chenin Blanc, Rousanne, Verdelho and Viognier,
all four varietals which grow on the mountain-side right across from the
Café&rsquo;s veranda.</p>
<p>It really was divine.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Teaching InfoVis in Stellenbosch</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 11:42:36 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/</guid><description> In week 40 (that’s Monday October 4 to Friday October 8 for those of you not so much into week numbers) I had the privilege of giving a week-long Information Visualisation course to a group of post-graduate students (a mix of B.A. Honours in either Socio-informatics or in Decision-making and Values Studies) at the Centre for KDD of the University of Stellenbosch in the building previously-known-as “The BJ”.
With this post, I want to summarise, extremely compactly, my impressions:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In week 40 (that’s Monday October 4 to Friday October 8 for those of you not so much into week numbers) I had the privilege of giving a week-long Information Visualisation course to a group of post-graduate students (a mix of B.A. Honours in either Socio-informatics or in Decision-making and Values Studies) at the <a href="http://www.informatics.sun.ac.za/" title="Centre for KDD website">Centre for KDD</a> of the University of Stellenbosch in the building previously-known-as “The BJ”.</p>
<p>With this post, I want to summarise, extremely compactly, my impressions:</p>
<ul>
<li>In spite of the odd publication at an InfoVis venue, and in spite of putting significant effort into broadening my horizons also into InfoVis, I’m strictly speaking still a Scientific Visualisation (SciVis) guy. In this context, developing and giving an InfoVis course was a fantastically educational experience. I aspire to be equally fluent in SciVis and InfoVis when I grow up.</li>
<li>I designed a course based on a mix of lecturing, paper reading and discussion and hands-on exercises. I can now highly recommend this combination. Next time I will put more effort into involving everyone more actively in the discussion. What also seemed to work well was the course website that students could add their work to during class.</li>
<li>I sourced almost all of my material from generous InfoVis colleagues, primarily Dr. Tamara Munzner, but also Dr. John Stasko, Prof.dr. Jarke van Wijk and Dr. Maneesh Agrawala. Thank you!</li>
<li>Having spent 7 years at the Stellenbosch Engineering Faculty (1500 guys all wearing t-shirts in jeans; furthermore, social skills are frowned upon) and the past 10 years at the TU Delft, a kind of Ultra-Engineering-Faculty, spending the week at The BJ interacting with socially adept and skilled communicators was a truly interesting experience.</li>
<li>I was otherwise also impressed with the level of cooperation between the students and their willingness to work hard (and long).</li>
<li>Laptop-use during lectures in a relatively small class: It’s an interesting phenomenon, having to deal with your own little <a href="http://mariandoerk.de/visualbackchannel/" title="visual backchannel paper at infovis 2010">communication backchannel</a>. Banning laptop use is obviously not an option as there are too many possible advantages, but I’m not sure yet what a good solution would be towards making sure that the laptops are being used to augment learning.</li>
<li>Most students chose <a href="http://vis.stanford.edu/protovis/" title="ProtoVis website">ProtoVis</a> (from <a href="http://stbvis2010.medvis.org/syllabus/p-infovis-design" title="list of software toolkits stbvis2010 students could use">a list of 8 possibilities</a>, and they were free to use anything else too) to implement their final mini-projects with. This was probably due to their previous web-programming experience, and also that ProtoVis requires more or less zero setup.</li>
</ul>
<p>Conclusion: Much learned, hopefully the students did too. :) All in all a positive and energising experience!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>