<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>easter on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/easter/</link><description>Recent content in easter on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 19:01:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/easter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #219: Stilbaai Easter weekend 12/10</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Apr 2021 19:01:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/</guid><description> This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Monday March 29 to Sunday April 4, 2021.
However, its raison d&amp;rsquo;être is to act as a reminder of the epic weekend in Stilbaai that we have just returned from, and also to practise the borderline (un)justified use of a posh French expression or two.
Figure 1: If morning starts like this, day could turn out OK.
You might remember me mentioning this place for the first time almost exactly a year ago in WHV #191, when we went there for the first time and had to cut our visit short due to the first COVID lockdown.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Monday March 29
to Sunday April 4, 2021.</p>
<p>However, its <em>raison d&rsquo;être</em> is to act as a reminder of the epic weekend in
Stilbaai that we have just returned from, and also to practise the borderline
(un)justified use of a posh French expression or two.</p>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_morning_run.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_morning_run_hu92b0ff6511bd4df5e80be3a00894882a_2483189_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: If morning starts like this, day could turn out OK."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: If morning starts like this, day could turn out OK.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You might remember me mentioning this place for the first time almost exactly a
year ago in <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">WHV #191</a>, when we went there for the first time and had to cut our
visit short due to the first COVID lockdown.</p>
<p>A few months later, in <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/">WHV #208</a> to be exact, we had the good fortune to return
there, and for me to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/disconnecting/">get disconnected</a> unexpectedly quickly.</p>
<p>This time, exactly 11 WHVs later, we executed a text-book
maximise-your-Easter-weekend <em>manoeuvre</em> as we (the whole clan) left town after
school on Thursday.</p>
<p>Although the roads were quite busy, we did not get caught in any jams, and were
rewarded after a few hours (including a pretty busy stop at Heidelberg (ZA,
haha, I don&rsquo;t drive <em>that</em> fast) for coffee) by finding ourselves safe and sound
somewhere in Stilbaai on the Thursday evening, ready for a LONG weekend of fun
and games.</p>
<p>Oh, and this time <a href="/tags/disconnecting/">the disconnect</a> took place almost immediately upon arrival!</p>
<p>The weekend was pretty much perfect, with all of the stars aligning: The
weather (for a large part thanks to our sun, WHICH IS ONE OF THE STARS ALIGNING
TUN TUN TUUUUUN. Stilbaai is balmy this time of the year!), beautiful
surroundings and, most importantly, all of my clan peeps committed to having
fun.</p>
<p>The specific experiences I will want to remember include but are not limited
to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Morning runs, large parts on the tranquil beach, with its
perfect-for-barefoot-running sand, once also accompanied by GOU#1, who found
it exhilarating in spite of not <em>wanting</em> to run on the beach, because
teenager.</li>
<li>Long days on the beach by the river mouth, with all of my peeps, some of the
time spent trying not to fall from an inflatable <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standup%5Fpaddleboarding">SUP</a>. The general mood on the
beach is truly Laid Back.</li>
<li>Evening walks with the whole clan on that same tranquil, golden beach.</li>
<li>A visit to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stilbaai%5FTidal%5FFish%5FTraps">the ancient intertidal stonewall fish traps in Stilbaai</a>. See below
for a photographic impression.</li>
<li>As it behooves the people from this part of the world, daily fire and braai,
with craft beer and wine. (Also my music playlists, which I&rsquo;m mentioning
here, not because they&rsquo;re loved (they&rsquo;re not), but because they transported
me back into yet older but equally fond memories of more experiences with
friends.)</li>
</ul>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/04/05/weekly-head-voices-219-stilbaai-easter-weekend/stilbaai_tidal_fish_traps_hud57c88035e47d57a820378ff75f7043b_1970148_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: One of the Stilbaai Tidal Fish Traps. Fish swim into trap when high tide. Fish now trapped, ready for&amp;hellip; next stage."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: One of the Stilbaai Tidal Fish Traps. Fish swim into trap when high tide. Fish now trapped, ready for&hellip; next stage.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>On the return journey, a little bit of our luck ran out as we got caught in the
post-long-weekend jam.</p>
<p>You see, it seems that the whole of Cape Town decided to return home from
various spots on the warmer coast in such a way so as to meet in exactly the
same spot (on the pass between the Hermanus turn-off and Houwhoek) at exactly
the same time (around about lunch).</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not sure how they coordinated this so perfectly (WhatsApp? maybe Discord?),
but we were definitely part of the project.</p>
<p>Thousands of cars, bumper to bumper, fortunately moving, albeit slowly. We were
going to make it, it would just take a bit longer.</p>
<p>I told my kids &ldquo;This is like life. Sometimes you go really slow, but the trick
is to just keep on going, one foot in front of the other. You&rsquo;ll be surprised
how far you can get.&rdquo;</p>
<p>They were probably not listening. Maybe they&rsquo;ll read it here one day.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the weekend had been so sublime that even the Great
Easter Jam of &lsquo;21 came, and then simply unraveled, just like any other thought
always does during meditation practice.</p>
<p>With that observation similarly unraveling, we have almost reached the end of
the 219th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, with only one more thing to say:</p>
<p><em>À bientôt les amis!</em></p>
<p>(hehe)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>