<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>dopamine on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/dopamine/</link><description>Recent content in dopamine on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 22:26:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/dopamine/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #177: Streakers.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 22:26:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/</guid><description> A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly challenging post-Sunday-lunch run. This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to Sunday September 8, 2019.
On friendship, 25 years later. The birthday mentioned previously, along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends for more than 25 years now.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="lourensriver_at_vergelegen.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/lourensriver_at_vergelegen_hud2cab3a366684cc9909e698ad19a55fb_4685321_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>A piece of the Lourensriver, captured for you during a particularly
challenging post-Sunday-lunch run.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 26 to
Sunday September 8, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="on-friendship-25-years-later">On friendship, 25 years later.</h2>
<p>The birthday <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/#celebration">mentioned
previously</a>,
along with the portentous visit of a good friend from afar, led to at least two
small celebrations (that I know of) with a bunch of us that have been friends
for more than 25 years now.</p>
<p>In the bigger scheme of things, it&rsquo;s not <em>that</em> long, but what I would like to
mention here is how much such friendships can grow into the most honest of
human connections.</p>
<p>It is as if with the passing years, one is able to shed all of the unnecessary
baggage one tends to carry around as a beginner human.</p>
<p>What is left, is pure human warmth, unconditional support and, perhaps most
significantly, the effortless loss of self.</p>
<p><em>You</em> fade away, quite happily so, when one of your friends gets up in the
light to tell a story.</p>
<p>For a while at least, one&rsquo;s only representative in the conversation is one&rsquo;s
undivided recognition of and attention to the other.</p>
<p>This is certainly not reserved for 25+ year friendships, although this
pre-requisite seems to facilitate the process to the point of effortlessness.</p>
<h2 id="nested-headings-of-miscellany-nhom-nhom">Nested Headings of Miscellany (NHoM-NHoM).</h2>
<h3 id="org-pdf-tools-for-constructing-unifying-notes">org-pdf-tools for constructing unifying notes.</h3>
<p>Recently, I had to work through a stack of regulatory documents in PDF format.</p>
<p>The challenge was that the documents described different aspects of a single,
complicated procedure, but were severely lacking in overview-engendering
outlines or, even better, diagrams.</p>
<p>I did what I mostly do when faced with any research-related complexity: BUST
OUT SOME MORE OF THAT EMACS!</p>
<p>I found the Emacs package
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/">org-pdftools</a>, which I then
<a href="https://github.com/fuxialexander/org-pdftools/pull/4">PRd to work on my newer
Orgmode</a> (github makes
this sort of collaboration so easy!) and then integrated into my workflow.</p>
<p>org-pdftools enables one to link to specific annotated extracts, created
on-demand inside Emacs, from one&rsquo;s orgmode notes.</p>
<p>I used this to synthesise an overview document explaining the whole process,
linking to different parts of multiple PDFs explaining each aspect in more
detail.</p>
<p>Being able to jump effortlessly from a central overview document to specific
positions in reference PDFs is a huge boon to the research process.</p>
<h3 id="escalante">Escalante!</h3>
<p>One friend of work pointed me at an online source of affordable Altras.</p>
<p>I have secretly been pining for a pair of these shoes.</p>
<p>I was planning to use them for the longer runs when I can feel that my feet
need a little more support than my sandals are able to provide.</p>
<p>However, my feet have really gotten used to the wide open spaces of sandals, or
even better, of going barefoot.</p>
<p>Altras are zero-drop shoes, with <em>ginormous</em> toe boxes. Their motto is &ldquo;Embrace
the Space&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It seems like I have found some shoes with the right motto&hellip;</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://altrarunning.com/">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/altra-foot-space.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>Friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation had shoes that were semi-affordable, contrary to my
expectation.</p>
<p>When I pointed friend #2 from work at friend #1&rsquo;s recommendation, he pointed me
at an even <em>more</em> affordable source.</p>
<p>I <em>could</em> have continued with this iterative process, but I was unable to delay
this purchase any longer.</p>
<p>My new pair of Altra Escalante 1.0s arrived the next day.</p>
<p>(Yes, I know, 1.5 and 2.0 are available. However, <a href="https://runrepeat.com/altra-escalante">the stellar reviews of
1.0</a> have not changed, and did I say
&ldquo;affordable&rdquo;?!)</p>
<p>On Friday I broke them in, and on Sunday I made a slightly longer than normal
run (see in-progress photo above) to see how they did.</p>
<p>Anyways, in spite of the rest of me taking quite a beating on the second run, I
can happily report that the shoes did a marvellous job of balancing support
on the one hand and foot-freedom on the other.</p>
<h2 id="life-optimisation-tip-73-streak-more">Life optimisation tip #73: Streak more.</h2>
<p>As I was scrolling aimlessly through my facebook feed during my last session
before the Great Social Media Fast of September 2019 (see next section), I
quite ironically ran into a truly interesting post by a Swedish visualization
colleague (SVC).</p>
<p>In this post, he talked about his hobby and progress as a <em>run streaker</em>.</p>
<p>It turns out that there are runners with the <em>excellent</em> additional hobby of
<em>streaking</em>, which in <em>this</em> context refers to the act of running every single
day of their lives, and trying to do these daily runs for the longest
continuous streak possible.</p>
<p>The streakers know of each other, almost like Highlander, and are in a friendly
competition, very much unlike Highlander.</p>
<p>SVC now has a single uninterrupted streak, spanning multiple years, of daily
running behind him. He has friends in his city who have also been streaking for
multiple years now.</p>
<p>I find this fantastic, both specifically as a running and fitness feat, and
more generally as a brilliant human optimisation trick.</p>
<p>The longer your streak, the harder it&rsquo;s going to become to break that
streak. Add in the friendly competition element, and you have become an
accomplishment machine.</p>
<p>I see great potential here in the context of
<a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">compounding</a>
more consistently, and for longer.</p>
<p>What else could we streak folks?</p>
<h2 id="the-great-social-media-fast-of-2019">The Great Social Media Fast of 2019.</h2>
<p>Twitter, Facebook, Reddit and friends&hellip; hot durnit.</p>
<p>Because I recently re-acquired the habit of checking reddit and twitter
multiple times during the day, I again examined the mechanisms driving this
undesirable behaviour.</p>
<p>The insidiousness, at least for me, lies in the fact that TwiFRaF (twitter,
facebook, reddit and friends) always has something looking like new information
on tap, where with tap, I mean firehose.</p>
<p>At any given moment during the day, when brain desires new input, or is just
tired and would like to take a break, TwiFRaF firehoses are ready to spew
something that appears to be new information but is only a very convincing
analogue.</p>
<p>Brain thinks it&rsquo;s getting what it wanted, plus a tiny and uninspired spurt of
discovery-dopamine here and there, which helps to keep up the illusion.</p>
<p>Any chance of real curiousity taking its natural course is cancelled.</p>
<p>Instead of pondering a question, and then going out on a slow and deliberate
search for information and later enlightenment, the firehose is opened, because
it&rsquo;s easier.</p>
<p>Furthermore, brain is unnecessarily exhausted trawling through a mix of mostly
generic rubbish with, granted, an interesting nugget every blue moon.</p>
<p>Hot durnit.</p>
<p>Fortunately, I like experiments, and Cold Turkey is my middle name!</p>
<p>So, on Saturday I decided to cut out TwiFRaF completely.</p>
<p>Initially I thought it would be an experiment until the end of September, but
now I&rsquo;m thinking that streaking might be an even better option.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;ll see.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #130-2: Direct experience dopamine.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/02/04/weekly-head-voices-130-2-direct-experience-dopamine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2018 18:43:17 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/02/04/weekly-head-voices-130-2-direct-experience-dopamine/</guid><description> Photogenic and non-camera-shy dragonfly I met in Paarl over the weekend.
As I went through my notes to extract material for this week’s post, I noticed a small discrepancy between the task description for the previous post and the published version: #129 in my notes versus #130 in the published post!
It’s too late now to rename #130, so in this reality I’m just going to have to deal with the fact that WHV #129 will never exist.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/IMG_3174-1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/IMG_3174-1-1024x576.jpg"
        
            alt="Photogenic and non-camera-shy dragonfly I met in Paarl over the weekend."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Photogenic and non-camera-shy dragonfly I met in Paarl over the weekend.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I went through my notes to extract material for this week’s post, I noticed a small discrepancy between the task description for the previous post and the published version: #129 in my notes versus <a href="/2018/01/28/weekly-head-voices-130-ttaggg/">#130 in the published post</a>!</p>
<p>It’s too late now to rename #130, so in this reality I’m just going to have to deal with the fact that WHV #129 will never exist. I have decided to name this edition #130-2 so that eventually (well, in about a week), we will be back to uninflated post numbers. Nobody likes inflation. Except perhaps tyres. And balloons.</p>
<h1 id="your-brain-at-work-part-2-dopamine-and-more-mindfulness">Your brain at work part 2: Dopamine and more mindfulness</h1>
<p>Ironically, the incorrectly numbered post #130 dealt with <a href="/2018/01/28/weekly-head-voices-130-ttaggg/#your-brain-not-at-work">the many ways in which our brains fail us every day</a>. (Now that I’ve finally gotten around to installing the <a href="https://wordpress.org/plugins/wp-anchor-header/">WP Anchor Header plugin</a>, we can link directly down to any heading in any post, as demonstrated in the previous sentence.)</p>
<p>At least some clouds do seem to have a silver lining.</p>
<p>Your Brain at Work, <a href="/2018/01/28/weekly-head-voices-130-ttaggg/#your-brain-not-at-work">the book I mentioned last week</a>, has turned out to be a veritable treasure trove of practical human neuroscience, and I still have about 30% to go. My attempt at meteorological humour above was inspired by part of the book’s treatment of the important role of dopamine in your daily life.</p>
<p>For optimal results, one is supposed to remain mildly optimistic about expected future rewards, but not too much, which will result in a sharp dopamine drop when those rewards don’t crystallise, and a greater increase when they do. For optimal results, one should try to remain in a perpetual state of mildly optimistic expectations, but also in a state of being continually pleasantly surprised when those expectations are slightly exceeded.</p>
<p>More generally, the book deals really well with the intricacies of trying to keep one’s various neural subsystems happy and in balance. Too much stress, and the <a href="http://www.brainbasics.org/home/limbic-system">limbic system</a> starts taking over (you want to run away, more or less), blocking your ability to think and make new connections, which in this modern life could very well be your only ticket out of Stress Town.</p>
<p>To my pleasant surprise (argh, I’ll stop), <a href="/tag/mindfulness/">mindfulness</a> made its appearance at about 40% into the book, shortly after I had published last week’s WHV.  In my favourite mindfulness book, <a href="https://books.google.co.za/books?id=rxddAgAAQBAJ&amp;source=gbs_similarbooks">Mindfulness: A Practical Guide to Peace in a Frantic World</a> by <a href="https://www.neuroscience.ox.ac.uk/research-directory/mark-williams">Mark Williams</a> and Danny Penman, two of the major brain states are called <em>doing,</em> the planning and execution mode we find ourselves in most of the time, also in the middle of the night when we’re worrying about things we can do nothing about at that point, and <em>being</em>, the mode of pure, unjudgemental observation the activation and cultivation of which is practised in mindfulness.</p>
<p>In David Rock’s book, these two states are described as being actual brain networks, and they have different but complementary names: The <em>narrative network</em> corresponds to the doing mode, and the <em>direct experience network</em> corresponds to the being mode.</p>
<p>The narrative network processes all incoming sensory information through various filters, moulding it to fit into one’s existing mental model of the world. David Rock describes it in the book and in <a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.com/david-rock/the-neuroscience-of-mindf_b_2908665.html">this HuffPost piece</a> as follows:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When you experience the world using this narrative network, you take in information from the outside world, process it through a filter of what everything means, and add your interpretations. Sitting on the dock with your narrative circuit active, a cool breeze isn’t a cool breeze, it’s a sign than summer will be over soon, which starts you thinking about where to go skiing, and whether your ski suit needs a dry clean.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is certainly useful most of the time, but it can get tiring and increase stress when you least need it.</p>
<p>The much-more attractively named <em>direct experience network</em> is active when you feel all of your senses opening up to the outside world to give you that full HD IMAX(tm) surround sound VR experience. No judging, no mental modelling, just sensory bliss and inner calm. <a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.com/david-rock/the-neuroscience-of-mindf_b_2908665.html">Rock sez</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When this direct experience network is activated, you are not thinking intently about the past or future, other people, or yourself, or considering much at all. Rather, you are experiencing information coming into your senses in real time. Sitting on the jetty, your attention is on the warmth of the sun on your skin, the cool breeze in your hair, and the cold beer in your hand.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Again, these two systems are on opposite sides of a neurophysiological see-saw. When you are worrying and planning, no zen for you! On the other hand, when you’re feeling the breeze flowing and and through each individual hair on your arms and the sun rays seemingly feeding energy directly into your cells, your stress is soon forgotten.</p>
<p>Fortunately, mindfulness gives us practical tools to distinguish more easily when we’re on which path, and, more importantly, to switch mental modes at will.</p>
<p>I hope you don’t mind me concluding this piece by recursively quoting David Rock quoting John Teasdale, one of the three academic founders of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindfulness-based_cognitive_therapy">Mindfulness Based Cognitive Therapy (MBCT)</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Mindfulness is a habit, it’s something the more one does, the more likely one is to be in that mode with less and less effort… it’s a skill that can be learned. It’s accessing something we already have. Mindfulness isn’t difficult. What’s difficult is to remember to be mindful.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(If the book has any more interesting surprises, I’ll be sure to report on them in future WHV editions.)</p>
<h1 id="miscellany-at-the-end-of-week-5-of-2018">Miscellany at the end of week 5 of 2018</h1>
<ul>
<li>The rather dire water situation has not changed much, except that due to more citizens putting their backs into the water saving efforts, day zero (when municipal water is to be cut off) has been postponed by 4 days to April 16. We are now officially limited to 50 litres per person per day, for everything. Practically, this means even more buckets of grey water are being carried around in my house every day in order to be re-used.</li>
<li>I ran 95km in January, which is nicely on target for my modest 2018 goal. Although January was a long month, and Winter Is Coming (And Then We Run Much Less Often), I am mildly optimistic that I might be able to keep it up.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0484/">Python type hinting</a> is brilliant. I have started using it much more often, but I only recently discovered how to specify a type which can have a value or None, an often-occurring pattern:</li>
</ul>
<pre class="src src-python"><span style="color: #0000ff;">from</span> typing <span style="color: #0000ff;">import</span> Optional, Tuple
<span style="color: #0000ff;">def</span> <span style="color: #006699;">get_preview_filename</span><span style="color: #707183;">(</span>attachment: Attachment<span style="color: #707183;">)</span> -&gt; Tuple<span style="color: #707183;">[</span>Optional<span style="color: #7388d6;">[</span><span style="color: #006fe0;">str</span><span style="color: #7388d6;">]</span>, Optional<span style="color: #7388d6;">[</span><span style="color: #006fe0;">str</span><span style="color: #7388d6;">]</span><span style="color: #707183;">]</span>:
    <span style="color: #0000ff;">pass</span>
</pre>
<ul>
<li>On Wednesday, January 31, GOU #3 had her first real (play) school day, that is, without any of us present at least for a while. We’re taking it as gradually as possible, but it must be pretty intense when you’re that young (but old enough to talk, more or less) and all of a sudden you notice that you’re all alone with all those other little human beings, none of which are the family members you’re usually surrounded with.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="the-end">The End</h1>
<p>Thank you dear reader for coming to visit me over here, I really do enjoy it when you do!</p>
<p>I hope to see you next again next week, same time, same place.</p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>