<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>oliver burkeman on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/oliver-burkeman/</link><description>Recent content in oliver burkeman on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2022 17:08:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/oliver-burkeman/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #246: Call up your friends</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2022 17:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/</guid><description> This, the 246th edition of the WHV, looks back at the longer-than-expected stretch of time between Monday August 8 and Sunday September 25 of the year 2022.
Figure 1: A slightly alternative view from somewhere up along Platties.
Disclaimer The later I get, the more difficult it becomes to put these things out.
Although not that many people read them, it feels like expectations increase over time, and thus the barrier continues getting higher and higher.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 246th edition of the WHV, looks back at the longer-than-expected
stretch of time between Monday August 8 and Sunday September 25 of the
year 2022.</p>








<figure><a href="2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu7c0f6730321986d4bd27d25914ccb09c_1559862_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu7c0f6730321986d4bd27d25914ccb09c_1559862_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu7c0f6730321986d4bd27d25914ccb09c_1559862_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu7c0f6730321986d4bd27d25914ccb09c_1559862_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu7c0f6730321986d4bd27d25914ccb09c_1559862_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A slightly alternative view from somewhere up along Platties."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>A slightly alternative view from somewhere up along Platties.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2>
<p>The later I get, the more difficult it becomes to put these things out.</p>
<p>Although not that many people read them, it feels like expectations increase
over time, and thus the barrier continues getting higher and higher.</p>
<p>Contrary to what it might sound like, I love doing what I&rsquo;m doing right now.</p>
<p>However, sometimes I wish to return to less complicated times, when writing a
post was a relaxed Sunday morning affair.</p>
<p>Changing space and time is not going to happen, and so, as is often the case, <em>I</em>
am the one who will have to change.</p>
<p>On the immediate term, it means that this post is even more all over the place
than normal. I would tell you to skip it, but then you might miss the bits at
the end.</p>
<p>On the slightly longer term, I would like to try to write a few WHV sentences
every day, apart from my normal daily notes, to see if that could mitigate the
writing gradient build-up.</p>
<p><em>On y va!</em></p>
<h2 id="birthday-messages">Birthday messages</h2>
<p>During the past weeks, I completed another orbit around the sun, of course only
as a (hopefully sufficiently erudite) planetary hitchhiker.</p>
<p>On the day, many friends sent me so many lovely messages over various
communication channels.</p>
<p>In some cases, people had clearly made use of the opportunity to include
additional and quite specific warm wishes.</p>
<p>Every year, I am again surprised by how <em>much</em> I appreciate these gifts.</p>
<p>This is my reminder to me, and to anyone else who might need to hear it: Write
sweet birthday wishes. In fact, make use of any such excuse to connect with
people.</p>
<p>P.S. Back in 2015, <a href="/2015/06/28/weekly-head-voices-93-a-thank-you-note/">I mentioned the sage advice of David Sedaris</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Write thank you notes.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="coffee-machine-reincarnation">Coffee machine reincarnation</h2>
<p>Some of you might remember when it arrived, and some of you have even tasted of
its dark and delicious produce over the years.</p>
<p>I am of course referring the beautiful mechanical beast that is our Saeco
Incanto Cappuccino, the Italian bean-to-cup machine <a href="/2007/04/08/infinite-espressos/">that came into our lives
fifteen years ago</a> and since then has only brought us pleasure, and structure,
and so much focus.</p>
<p>Sadly, it recently started tripping the RCD, aka residual current device, aka
the ECB, aka the earth leakage breaker, aka the GFCI if you&rsquo;re in the US.</p>
<p>This generally happens after the first cup, at the second solenoid tap (of
three), between the grinding and the pouring of the coffee.</p>
<p>This means that somewhere in the machine a live wire  has come into contact with
the chassis. The RCD measures this as a (small) current difference (the earth
leakage) between live and neutral and isolates that circuit to prevent any
humans from being electrocuted.</p>
<p>I took it in for repairs, and although it came back all nice and shiny with new
o-rings everywhere, the earth leakage was not remedied.</p>
<p>We took this as a sign that it was finally time to invest in a new bean-to-cup
machine, and so we did&hellip;</p>
<p>&hellip; into a brand new Saeco, this time the <a href="https://www.philips.co.za/c-p/HD8927_01/picobaristo-super-automatic-espresso-machine">Saeco PicoBaristo</a>.</p>
<p>While the old machine was the epitome of purpose-built simplicity, the new one
does have <em>significantly</em> more buttons and lights.</p>
<p>One improvement that I can really appreciate, is the fact that the new machine
is able to complete a coffee that is interrupted by the water reservoir
empyting mid-process.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, it is <em>quite</em> capable of converting beans into tasty
coffee at sufficient speed with just the right amount of ritual, and that was
the point.</p>
<h2 id="the-world-in-their-eyes">The world in their eyes</h2>
<p>Thanks to friends visiting us from NL (for the first time), we had the
privilege of spending some time with them (re-)exploring our surroundings.</p>
<p>Thanks to their abundance of vacation energy (keeping up even for the while
that we did was challenging) we squeezed in a number of activities (themes:
hikes, restaurants and fine wine), two of which I would like to mention here:</p>
<p>We had an absolutely fabulous Sunday lunch adventure at <a href="https://www.creationwines.com/">Creation Wines</a> on the
Hemel-en-Aarde ridge.</p>
<p>This lunch adventure consisted of various small and large dishes combined with
the tasting of various Creation wines, all of this coordinated by Jack, our amazing
sommelier and story-teller for the afternoon.</p>
<p>Combined with the frankly brilliant view of the vineyard-covered mountain, this
was definitely one of those <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">perfect present moment <em>things</em> deserving all of
one&rsquo;s attention</a>.</p>
<p>In order to compensate for our sins on the Sunday, on Monday we hiked up to the
top of Table Mountain via Platteklip Gorge. It was quite a bit slower than <a href="/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/#getting-high">my
previous Platties adventure in 2017</a>, but it was good fun nonetheless.</p>
<p>However, now I do feel obliged to go up again in the not too distant future,
but this time in speed mode in order to calibrate my memory of my 2017
performance.</p>
<p>More generally speaking, spending time with friends in tourist mode is a great
way to maintain one&rsquo;s gratitude for this amazing place.</p>
<h2 id="blom-bullet-list-of-miscellany">BLoM: Bullet List of Miscellany</h2>
<h3 id="never-ending-search-for-mobile-notes-is-never-ending">Never-ending search for mobile notes is never-ending</h3>
<p>From the niche-within-a-niche-within-a-niche department: If you&rsquo;re using
Org-roam in Emacs, and you&rsquo;d like to have random markdown files act like
they&rsquo;re org-roam nodes, you too could <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">modify md-roam for frontmatter-less
operation</a>!</p>
<h3 id="beautiful-alder-lake-aka-meep12700">Beautiful Alder Lake aka meep12700</h3>
<p>I have a new work machine and it&rsquo;s an old-fashioned desktop PC!</p>
<p>Due to various constraints, some of them budgetary, I ended up with an:</p>
<ul>
<li>Intel 12700 (12th gen baby!)</li>
<li>Corsair H100x AiO water cooling (so the 12700 power limits can be lifted if
needed)</li>
<li>64GB of DDR4-3200 RAM</li>
<li>2 TB of PCIe 4.0 SSD: The Mushkin Vortex with Innogrit IG5236 controller</li>
<li>Asus TUF GAMING B660M-PLUS WIFI D4 motherboard</li>
<li>Super Flower Leadex III Gold 850W PSU</li>
<li>all of the above contained in the roomy and airflowy Phanteks Eclipse P400A
case.</li>
</ul>
<p>See <a href="https://pcpartpicker.com/list/tCfRwc">this PCPartPicker</a> for the full details.</p>
<p>Laptops definitely have their perks, but there&rsquo;s something magical about the
raw performance of a new PC, and especially about its longevity.</p>
<p>Completely subjectively, <a href="/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/#new-machine-zen">meepzen3, home PC acquired slightly more than a year
ago</a>, feels ever so slightly quicker.</p>
<h3 id="meet-your-heroes">Meet your heroes</h3>
<p>Lex Fridman made a 5 hour+ long <a href="https://lexfridman.com/john-carmack/">podcast with John Carmack</a>.</p>
<p>As is the case for many programming nerds, Carmack has been a hero of mine
since the day I learned of his existence. Also like many nerds of my era, I
spent many hours first with Commander , and later with Wolfenstein, Doom and
Quake.</p>
<p>Although John Romero certainly deserves much of the credit for these culture
changing projects, Carmack was and probably still is one of the best
programmers on the planet.</p>
<p>Anyways, it was great to hear that he sounds like a very decent human as well.</p>
<p>You should probably listen to the podcast (haha), but I would like to single
out here how Carmack explained that they were uniquely positioned when starting
on Commander Keen, in terms of the hundreds (thousands?) of hours of practice
they had had building multiple games per year for Softdisk.</p>
<p>In other words, while they were brilliant, Carmack attributes a great deal of
their break-through success to plain old hard work.</p>
<p>(See <a href="/2018/03/11/weekly-head-voices-135-its-all-rainbows-and-unicorns-no-really/#the-carmack-productivity-method-cpm">WHV #135</a> for a previous bit about Carmack&rsquo;s productivity.)</p>
<h3 id="call-up-your-friends">Call up your friends</h3>
<p>In an interview between Sam Harris and Oscar Burkeman (he of <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#reading">the 4000 weeks
book, winner of the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em></a> , and of <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">the power of
being able to put down your work</a>), Sam remarks so astutely that we have become
so caught up in the importance of the illusion of control of one&rsquo;s time, that
we have stopped calling up our friends.</p>
<p>Instead, you send a message with something like &ldquo;hey, let me know when you have
a few minutes for a phone call&rdquo;&hellip;</p>
<p>Now your friend either sees this much later, or sees it when you send it, and
then has to cogitate about if and when they could maybe fit you in somewhere
later in the day.</p>
<p>Not so long ago, you could just call up your friend, all serendipitous, and all
present-momenty, because what could be truly more important than spending a few
minutes connecting with your friend and/or loved one, and maybe having the
opportunity to just let them know that you&rsquo;re there for them?</p>
<p>If they are really unable to take your call, they won&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>However, the subtle improvement here is that everyone sometimes needs a tiny
bit of a nudge to do the right thing and connect with a brother or sister.</p>
<p>Be the nudge. Accept the nudge. Call up your friends!</p>








<figure><a href="2022-08-28-west-coast-whv.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hud4ddaea33b30dfc681d707b0fcf8820a_911091_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hud4ddaea33b30dfc681d707b0fcf8820a_911091_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hud4ddaea33b30dfc681d707b0fcf8820a_911091_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hud4ddaea33b30dfc681d707b0fcf8820a_911091_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hud4ddaea33b30dfc681d707b0fcf8820a_911091_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Impression from a sneaky slightly early trip to the West Coast to see the flowers."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Impression from a sneaky slightly early trip to the West Coast to see the flowers.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2021 to 2022 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</guid><description> Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.
I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to 2014 (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and 2015 (no real excuse).
Much later, on Sunday January 23: It could very well still win the Most Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&amp;rsquo;s done.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition
post</a>!</p>








<figure><a href="20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to
<a href="/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/">2014</a> (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and <a href="/2015/01/21/weekly-head-voices-88-just-be-yourself-they-said/">2015</a> (no real
excuse).</p>
<p><em>Much later, on Sunday January 23:</em> It could very well still win the Most
Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Emacs and <code>M-x count-words</code> (on a temporary buffer copied over from <a href="/archive/#2021">the 2021
blog post archive</a>) tells me that I published 28 posts on this blog, and 8
technical posts over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>Just like with the running below, but for different reasons, I lost a lot of
steam during the last few months of the year.</p>
<p>In a truly surprise twist, in 2022 I will again attempt to write regularly, and
to write more, and to keep it up until the end.</p>
<h3 id="stats-addendum">Stats addendum</h3>
<p>Applying the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess log analyzer</a> to this blog&rsquo;s log files with the following
invocation:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#859900">for</span> i in {2..13..1}; <span style="color:#859900">do</span> <span style="color:#cb4b16">echo</span> cpbotha.net.access.log.<span style="color:#268bd2">$i</span>.gz; <span style="color:#859900">done</span>) | xargs zcat -f -- | goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; tells me that in 2021 cpbotha.net welcomed over 115000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>The same tool reports that <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a> clocked in at just under 165000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>Even if the real number of actual human visits is a quarter of what the tool is
reporting, I am ecstatic!</p>
<p>The three most popular cpbotha.net posts based on hits during 2021 were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">Dear USA, my data has left your building</a></li>
<li><a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">Note-taking strategy 2019</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>Thanks to Strava&rsquo;s handy training calendar shown below, we can see that I spent
125 hours last year (mostly, about 4 hours was spent on hiking just over 20km)
running a bit over 1300km.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can also see quite clearly that I lost steam in November and especially in
December.</p>
<p>This was initially due to work getting quite busy, and then later in December a
bout with Omicron (highly probably) and also less than run-friendly weather in
St. Francis.</p>
<p>I am always happy when I manage to average 100km or more per month, and I&rsquo;ll
probably try to do that again in 2022.</p>
<h3 id="possibly-tmi-read-on-at-your-own-risk">Possibly TMI, read on at your own risk</h3>
<p>Those of you who know me, will also know about my giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunion">bunion</a>, or hallux
valgus as it prefers to be called.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&amp;rsquo;s complicated." width="240px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyways, Mr Valgus is unfortunately playing an increasingly frequent role in my
attempts at running, often starting to complain at N kilometres where N is
fortunately still higher than most of my attempts, but still affecting a
worrying number of them.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to push on, until Mr Valgus overstays its welcome, at which point
it will be time to explore invasive corrective procedures.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Probably my most redeeming habit of them all, is reading books every night in
bed until I fall asleep.</p>
<p>Even if the day has been less than satisfactory, ending it with an entirely
deliberate and focused reading session tends to make up for quite a lot.</p>
<p>Although I was planning to do more book summaries in 2021, I managed to
complete only one. At least it was a good one, namely <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Seven
and a Half Lessons About the Brain&rdquo; by Lisa Feldman Barrett</a>, which I can
strongly recommend if you have not checked it out yet.</p>
<p>Thanks to strong contenders like the one above, the competition was fierce, but
in the end the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em> could go to nothing other
than Oliver Burkeman&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08FGV64B1/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</em></a>.</p>
<p>Burkeman, he of the <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">importance of being able to put <em>down</em> your work</a> and of <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">more
appearances on this blog</a>, has created a beautifully written ode to our terribly
limited lifespans (4000 weeks if you&rsquo;re lucky, you can almost hear them ticking
away&hellip;), and to our terribly limited capacity to make the most of the time
that we do get, and to really just giving up the fight to <em>get everything done</em>,
because we will never ever win the battle against the law of perpetually
filling inboxes of various kinds, and because it&rsquo;s so much better to simply
<em>disconnect</em> from the firehose (which we can&rsquo;t get rid of completely) in order to
spend time on no-excuses leisure, and especially on our loved ones.</p>
<p>My favourite fiction book by far was <em>The Anomaly</em> by Hervé le Tellier, as
translated by Adriana Hunter.</p>
<p>After having just grudgingly finished Elizabeth Bear&rsquo;s Ancestral Night (first
novel in the White Space series; some interesting ideas, but just too pulpy,
clumsy and exposition-rich for my taste, in spite of space opera being a guilty
pleasure&hellip;), the light literariness and French cynicism of The Anomaly was a
<em>delightful</em> and refreshing breeze that I was unable to put down until it was
done.</p>
<p>In 2022, I&rsquo;m planning to read more than in 2021, and publish more of those
summaries.</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#mindfulness">daily meditation streak that started in 2020</a> continued for most of 2021,
until the end-of-year school vacation started. I am not yet sure how I&rsquo;ll be
able to fit this into my new 2022 work-routine.</p>
<h2 id="worst-habit-of-2021">Worst habit of 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV Award for Worst Habit of 2021 By Far goes, without a doubt, to my old
friend TwiFRaF-Yo, although this time around the main culprits were Twitter,
Reddit and YouTube.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know exactly when I fell out of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">the previous social media fast</a>, but I
fell out with a vengeance.</p>
<p>Although I subscribe almost entirely to technical communities on reddit (Emacs,
Orgmode, Org-roam, keyboards, etc.), there are enough of them to keep a person
busy.</p>
<p>If you add to that my twitter feed, where I&rsquo;ve also taken care to remove the
noise, subscribing largerly to high-signal science-, technology- , and
engineering-related feeds, there&rsquo;s a great deal of valuable-seeming information
that one feels compelled to get through every day&hellip;</p>
<p>(It feels like I&rsquo;ve told this story before&hellip;)</p>
<p>Anyways, every time I manage to disconnect (it&rsquo;s been a few weeks now, I think
Monday January 3 was the official start date of the current fast), only then am
I able to recognise (where by &ldquo;recognise&rdquo;, I mean that friends say this to me,
and this is when I&rsquo;m able to admit that they&rsquo;re right) that the net value for
me is highly probably negative.</p>
<p>While there is certainly valuable information that enters via those streams, it
costs so much attention and emotional energy that it&rsquo;s not really worth it.</p>
<p>So.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m back on the no-social-media cart until next time.</p>
<p>Just like the previous time, I&rsquo;m limiting myself to the brilliant Inoreader RSS
subscription service (which I pay for) to keep up to date with 99% long-form
blogs, and two Twitter accounts that are worth too much to me to disconnect
from (<a href="https://twitter.com/erictopol">Eric Topol</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/alper">Alper Çuğun-Gscheidel</a>).</p>
<p>Although I sometimes think this makes me slower, because I don&rsquo;t have all of
the current happenings at my fingertips all the time, I&rsquo;m hoping this gives me
more space and time for reading, thinking and writing.</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">Systems and tools for running this human (PKM baby)</h2>
<p>In the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">2018 to 2019 transition post</a> I mentioned the &ldquo;The System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This time, for this section, I would like to limit it to tools for knowledge
management and task management (this is not my favourite term, but I&rsquo;m erring
on the side of familiarity here) .</p>
<p>All of Emacs and Orgmode and Org-roam is still going strong, although I waver
quite a bit sometimes when I see some of the shiny new things, like <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>,
which I would probably be using if it wasn&rsquo;t for Emacs.</p>
<p>However, when I sometimes dive into my notes, I can see the difference it makes
when you stick to a single tool for longer than a few years. The amount of
knowledge keeps on growing, and I am slowly getting better at linking it all
together and&hellip;  sometimes even using it.</p>
<p>The picture below shows the graph created, by the <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> package, of a
sub-section of my notes network:</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Before I got side-tracked by the pretty picture, I was planning to dedicate
this section to a new WHV award, namely the Award for the Most Unexpectedly
Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021.</p>
<p>This year the award goes to&hellip; <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper/guide">Dropbox Paper</a>!</p>
<p>Back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">WHV #233</a> I listed many of the reasons why. In the few months since then
it has become only more useful to me as the go-to mobile tool for checklists
(especially useful when we go on trips), lists of books, movies and music
recommended by people in person, and so on.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualifier features, such as its markdown DNA and its
usability on mobile for idea capturing, the fact that Paper documents show up
in Dropbox searches, which is how I usually search when I <span class="underline">really</span> need to find a
specific file (versus ripgrep searches in Orgmode), is the deal maker.</p>
<p>(My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">strange scheme for continuously converting all org files to docx</a> for
searching and reading on the iPhone is also still going strong.)</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I had a piece written here with more details about what exactly was happening
at work, but I decided to nuke that and instead keep it more personal by
mentioning that thanks to great big dollops of serendipity and people, I find
myself, with a number of levers at my disposal, right in the middle of an
organization which, after a few months of reconfiguration and preparation, has
embarked on a genuinely exciting, and importantly more unified, course.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not mention the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">discomfort and stress</a> I was
experiencing at the start of the current personal phase, most probably due to
trying to adapt quickly to my new circumstances and responsibilities.</p>
<p>In the time since then, my stress levels have returned to more acceptable
levels, but expectations remain high.</p>
<h2 id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<p>One of the most positive changes I made in the past year, was to put more
effort into making regular and active (virtual) contact with friends whom I
don&rsquo;t see in person regularly enough.</p>
<p>THANKS INTERNET YOU DA BEST.</p>
<p>This year, I want to try harder to do more of that.</p>
<p>More generally, I made a note (yes, again, one has to keep doing this until the
end) to celebrate any of my peeps and our relationships whenever there&rsquo;s a
chance.</p>
<p>Secret message for my innner INNER circle: You are my energy and my joy, I am
here to be yours.</p>
<p>Whatever else happens, these precious relationships are all we have.</p>
<h2 id="even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">Even more plans for 2022: Continue trying</h2>
<p>First off, I would really like to get this blog post here done and
published. (it wants to be too much, or rather I want it to be too much, and so
we sit here staring at each other instead of just getting on with it so I can
try again to write a good post for once)</p>
<p>Second, EAZ is back on, since Monday January 10. EAZ means no alcohol until at
least February 10. As has been the case previously, my sleep quality is
subjectively better, and it seems like my energy levels are more consistent
throughout the week.</p>
<p>I just looked back at last year&rsquo;s transition post, and especially at the <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">final
sections, including the neatly documented Life Systems 2021</a>. That guy
(<a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">apparently we share only about 2% of our atoms</a>) really seemed to have his
stuff together, on paper at the very least.</p>
<p>As I write this (22:38 on Saturday, January 22), I have just realised that <em>this</em>
&ldquo;I&rdquo; definitely needs to spend some more time thinking about &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo; (The WHV
approach to life, the universe and everything, the one with the pillars (love
and science, that&rsquo;s the easy and reliable bit) and the rules) and specifically
if and how to revise the daily life direction clusters.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll have it on your desk by Monday.</p>
<p>Until then, the one thing I&rsquo;m sure about, is that I wish you and your loved
ones the best 2022 possible.</p>








<figure><a href="stormsriver-mouth.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #233: Atomic party sections</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.
Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.
(Don&rsquo;t) Stress for success (aka 4000 weeks at 60%) It&rsquo;s really quite busy at work, perhaps even verging on the slightly too busy territory.
I&rsquo;m consistently putting in stretches of focused, high intensity work to help push us into calmer waters.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/bettys_bay_spectacular_colours_pano_hue1fbfac4e9ab5bc6c3eb81c97a752dce_10617605_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: GOU#1 living her best life at in the Betty&rsquo;s Bay water at dusk, accompanied by spectaculour colours.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome friends to this, the 233d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering
the two weeks from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 26, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="don-t--stress-for-success--aka-4000-weeks-at-60">(Don&rsquo;t) Stress for success (aka 4000 weeks at 60%)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s really quite busy at work, perhaps even verging on the slightly too busy
territory.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m consistently putting in stretches of focused, high intensity work to help
push us into calmer waters.</p>
<p>However, in spite of all of this, my stress levels seem to have have subsided
to quite an extent over the last few weeks.</p>
<p>This could be ascribed to me slowly moving out of <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">new challenge discomfort
territory</a>, because I&rsquo;m either getting better at what I&rsquo;m supposed to be doing,
or, if you want to be cynical, I just care a little less.</p>
<p>Maybe these two are the same.</p>
<p>I like to think that it could also be the growing effect of <em>Four Thousand
Weeks: Time and How to Use It</em>, <a href="/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/#how-i-m-putting-down-my-work">the book I mentioned in WHV-231</a> that so
eloquently and quite urgently makes the case that because life is so stupidly
short, and you&rsquo;re not even going to get close to Getting your Things Done, and
that working hard so that you can relax at some future point in time is a
terribly imprudent approach forced upon us by our instrumentalist society, you
should instead do your best extracting every bit of enjoyment from every moment
that you get, when you get it.</p>
<p>Every morning is an opportunity for a mini coffee and breakfast party, and
every evening is an opportunity for a mini dinner party, both of these with the
people, big and small, I hold the most dear.</p>
<p>Every day I do need to work, but there is ample opportunity for curiosity, for
learning, and for offering a helping hand.</p>
<p>There is generally also time to go out for a wide-open-perception run in the
sun.</p>
<p>All of this is available to you if you can just learn how to keep your own set
of instrumentalising demons safely locked up in their cages. (these are the
gremlins who keep on bugging you to try to finish one more thing.)</p>
<p>As Burkeman writes on page 144:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To the philosophers of the ancient world, leisure wasn&rsquo;t the means to some
other end; on the contrary, it was the end to which everything else worth doing
was a means.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Back in <a href="/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/#flip-it">WHV #222, I tried to say something similar, just far less eloquently</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve completed only a pinch over 60% of the book. I might have more to say when
it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">Dropbox Paper (aka mobile note-taking evolving)</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s no secret around these parts that <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#mobile">the mobile aspects of my otherwise
pretty respectable note-taking game are weak</a>. (In short: Emacs Org mode is
amazing and can do <em>anything</em>, <strong>except</strong> when on my iPhone. Moar shorter: iPhone =
Org mode Kryptonite)</p>
<p>Somehow, in spite of being so deep in with Dropbox, and in spite of using
<a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper">Dropbox Paper</a> for other things, I overlooked it when evaluating solutions for
mobile note capture all the way back in 2019.</p>
<p>This weekend, because I had to scrounge around for an important bit of
information I <em>knew</em> I had stored somewhere (it turned out to be in my Apple
Notes doh), I spent some time trying to find a tool that would give me
mobile-editable notes that would turn up more readily in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Well, it turns out that Dropbox Paper documents turn up in Dropbox searches.</p>
<p>Who would have guessed?!</p>
<p>In addition to that, Paper has:</p>
<ul>
<li>markdown support</li>
<li>syntax highlighting of triple-backtick source code blocks</li>
<li>LaTeX math!</li>
<li>embedding of arbitrary media which gets automatically uploaded to dropbox on
drag and drop</li>
<li>easy linking to other Paper docs</li>
<li>checklists</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Cue sound of another personal knowledge management puzzle piece snapping into place&hellip;</em></p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m not allowed to talk about it here, because the blog post in question
happened <em>after</em> this blog post&rsquo;s legally allowed observed timespan, but shortly
in the future, I will also solve the issue of being able to search through and
preview all of my Org mode notes on the iPhone.</p>
<p>Post is on vxlabs if you&rsquo;re from the (near) future.</p>
<h2 id="a-truly-spectacular-long-weekend-in-betty-s">A truly spectacular long weekend in Betty&rsquo;s</h2>
<p>The second week ended with a weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay that was so spectacular
that it deserves its own section in this blog post.</p>
<p>Well this is it. The section dedicated to the weekend. I hope you like it.</p>
<h2 id="the-section-at-the-end">The section at the end</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this.</p>
<p>I wish you continuous and consistent atomic party moments.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #231: Two thousand four hundred fourty-four</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/</guid><description> Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW
This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to Sunday August 29, 2021.
Orbital mechanics that are important to me Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.
That&amp;rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.
Let me try again:
Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="pano_from_watsonia.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/pano_from_watsonia_huf09b3b830678fba98c344ef52bf8224e_3459144_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; with bestie DW"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>View from Watsonia (Helderberg) &ldquo;run&rdquo; with bestie DW</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday August 16 to
Sunday August 29, 2021.</p>
<h2 id="orbital-mechanics-that-are-important-to-me">Orbital mechanics that are important to me</h2>
<p>Sowehere during this period, I completed yet another full orbit around the sun.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s quite a bit more egocentric than I intended.</p>
<p>Let me try again:</p>
<p>Thanks to family and friends and good fortune, my existence continued for
another complete revolution of the planet Earth around the star Sol.</p>
<p>As is our custom here, I get to increase the mathematical encoding (this is a
fantastically consistent and useful approach to the structured modelling of
reality) of my time as an alive unit by one.</p>
<p>When I was younger, it was possible to use this number to impress one&rsquo;s
friends. Sometimes, the number of an older sibling or even a parent could also
be used to increase social standing, if one&rsquo;s own number was still quite small.</p>
<p>Ironically, as the number gets bigger, we prefer not to talk or even think
about it too much.</p>
<p>Thanks to math, the number could in theory be transformed into &ldquo;number of
revolutions remaining&rdquo;, but fortunately our complex physiologies and
environments greatly complicate the estimation of the required term for that
transformation, in this case greatly comforting us with uncertainty.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS&hellip;</p>
<p>I had an amazing birthday.</p>
<p>From morning video chats with homies, to working lunches that turned into
superbly relaxed lunches with old friends, surprise visits by far-off friends
the day before, birthday mountain runs with a bestie, and so many (voice)
messages on various platforms from friends everywhere, my birthday was a
friendship-and-life-affirming business.</p>
<p>Friends, thank you for working together like that. You are all breath-taking!</p>
<p>P.S. Experiencing this acted as a beautiful reminder to send that message,
write that email or make that call whenever you can find an excuse!</p>
<h2 id="how-i-m-putting-down-my-work"><em>How</em> I&rsquo;m putting down my work</h2>
<p>In the previous edition of the WHV, I talked about <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">the important skill of being
able to put down one&rsquo;s work</a>.</p>
<p>Here I would just like to mention how I&rsquo;ve been trying to practise this in my
life, especially because it really seems to have helped me since we last spoke.</p>
<p>Ok, get ready!</p>
<p>You Won&rsquo;t Believe This One Trick&hellip;</p>
<p>At 17:00, 17:30 at the latest, I explicitly switch off any tools that I use for
work, and disconnect from all dayjob-related systems.</p>
<p>Work email closed, development enviroments exited, docker containers all stopped.</p>
<p>For good measure, I roll a tumbleweed or two across my office floor, blowing
air out through my pursed lips.</p>
<p>The thing is, my brain has the tendency to continue cogitating on the last
thing I kept it busy with.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I used to have the tendency to still try and solve that problem
before bed, only resulting in me later lying in said bed, unable to get my
brain to stop cogitating, leading to bad sleep, contributing to subpar
performance the next day.</p>
<p>I have to qualify here that putting down work tools does not exclude me from
picking up hobby programming projects later in the evening, after &ldquo;The Making
of The Dinner, With Wine&rdquo; and &ldquo;The Chilling With The Family&rdquo; stages.</p>
<p>Although programming plays a substantial part of dayjob, I have never stopped
enjoying and being relaxed by this activity in the recreational setting.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, making a point of putting down work on time, starting
the gradual wind-down, has drastically reduced the number and severity of
<em>Trying Unsuccessfully to Solve All Work Problems In The Dark, From One&rsquo;s Bed</em> for
me.</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/">Oliver Burkeman</a>, author of <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">the putting-down-your-work post</a>, also wrote a
book titled <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2021/aug/16/four-thousand-weeks-time-and-how-to-use-it-by-oliver-burkeman-review">Four Thousand Weeks: Time and How to Use It</a>, which my mom got me
for my birthday (THANKS MOM!).</p>
<p>As soon as I&rsquo;m done with <a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">Seligman&rsquo;s book flourish</a>, I&rsquo;ll start with this book,
which will hopefully filter through to this blog.</p>
<p>In the meantime, here&rsquo;s the blurb which is already food  for thought:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The average human lifespan is absurdly, insultingly brief.</p>
<p>If you live to be 80, you’ll have had about 4,000 weeks. But that’s no reason for despair.</p>
<p>Confronting our radical finitude  and how little control we really have  is the key to a fulfilling and meaningfully productive life.</p>
</blockquote>








<figure><a href="helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/02/weekly-head-voices-231-two-thousand-four-hundred-fourty-four/helderberg_reserve_snowy_mountain_view_huc5bc7a7c2fc28634f19327d8e354e5c8_5562117_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&amp;rsquo;ve been treated with."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>View from a family walk in the Helderberg reserve, where you can hopefully see some of the snowy peaks we&rsquo;ve been treated with.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #230: Follow your blisters</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="van_breda_cottage_angles.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_huedb1ad4f1cb6a20b2d7c644468e8c088_1711153_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&amp;rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &amp;ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&amp;rdquo; (I didn&amp;rsquo;t and I don&amp;rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV covers the three weeks from Monday July 26 to Sunday August 15.</p>
<h2 id="why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">Why I don&rsquo;t like dark mode anymore</h2>
<p>As you might know, I spent most of my working (and sometimes hobby, we&rsquo;ll get
back to that further down) hours in front of this screen or some other screen.</p>
<p>Up to now, I was really convinced that I preferred dark mode everywhere, until
recently two events transpired:</p>
<p>I started noticing more eye-strain than usual, even on my 27&quot; screen, something
which had a perceptible effect on my productivity. This I resignedly ascribed
to my advancing age, although I did find the suddenness quite surprising,
especially since I recently had my glasses updated.</p>
<p>Then, after years with only the admittedly brilliant <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">zenburn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/fniessen/emacs-leuven-theme">Leuven (dark)</a>
Emacs themes checking all of the boxes for me, I finally ran into a really
interesting and usable theme called <a href="https://github.com/kunalb/poet">Poet</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s interesting, because it uses variable pitched fonts for everything but
code, tables and elements of the fixed width domain, where most Emacs fonts
stick to the traditional all-fixed-width approach.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="20210822-poet-theme-screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hucdb166019581fdceafde52e837ca82ff_214350_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can probably understand that for someone who uses Emacs almost primarily
for technical notes and other writing, this book-like appearance could work
really well.</p>
<p>The theme was even more interesting for me personally, as it suddenly became
clear as day that I experienced almost no eye-strain when using Emacs with this
lighter theme than when I used any of my other usually dark-themed tools!</p>
<p>It became obvious that poet-theme&rsquo;s lighter background was much easier on my
eyes than dark mode in vscode. (No, this specific advantage can&rsquo;t be ascribed
to Emacs itself I&rsquo;m afraid.)</p>
<p>Reading pages such as <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/digital-eye-strain/is-dark-mode-better-for-eyes/">this</a> explains that dark mode leads to pupils having to
dilate more to let in more light, which there is less of with dark themes.</p>
<p>This leads to, just like with cameras and any other optics with lenses and
apertures, a shortened depth of field, and hence more difficulty focusing on
the screen!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/dark-mode/">This article by the well-known Nielsen Norman Group</a> nicely summarises research
on this topic. In short:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In people with normal vision (or corrected-to-normal vision), visual
performance tends to be better with light mode, whereas some people with
cataract and related disorders may perform better with dark mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Up until recently, I did not experience a qualitative difference in vision
between dark and light, but I sit here relieved that my eye-strain issue has
been resolved by an Emacs theme!</p>
<h2 id="know-how-to-put-down-your-work">Know how to put down your work</h2>
<p>The following take from <a href="https://twitter.com/brandsrock/status/1426163442256330753">a recent tweet by mike joubert</a> struck me
(tweet-take-strike! words are funny&hellip;):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly valuable skill isn&rsquo;t the capacity to push yourself harder, but to
stop and recuperate despite the discomfort of knowing that work remains
unfinished, emails unanswered, other people&rsquo;s demands unfulfilled.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">article, titled <em>The three-or-four-hours rule for getting creative work
done</em></a>, is itself a good read about the observation that creative types (amongst
which I count engineers) have at their best three to four hours of focus time
per day &mdash; so it is crucially important that their days are structured such
that there is an <strong>uninterrupted</strong> block of three to four hours inside of which
that lovely focus has the possibility of appearing.</p>
<p>The tweet-extract focuses on the similarly important but more subtle art of
being able to put one&rsquo;s work down, completely, when that block of time is over,
even when it feels like the work is far from complete.</p>
<p>I especially like that it also explicitly mentions the illusions created by
one&rsquo;s perception of &ldquo;other people&rsquo;s demands&rdquo;, something that ironically becomes
even harder to walk away from when one is more tired at the end of the work
day.</p>
<p>For me, becoming better at putting work down has pleasant echoes of running
slower to run faster, of emptiness in art and more broadly, <a href="https://zenhabits.net/work-less/">choosing fewer f*cks
to give</a>.</p>
<h2 id="follow-your-blisters">Follow your blisters</h2>
<p>On the topic of choosing your ducks&hellip;</p>
<p>I initially did not like <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/what-you-should-follow-instead-of-your-passion">this HBR</a> post when it first crossed my stream, because
it smacks a bit too much of the current social media style of &ldquo;wisdom&rdquo;, namely
&ldquo;everything you need to know in 280 characters&rdquo;, or &ldquo;this 1 minute tiktok video
will change your life&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the title is pretty clickbaity: <em>What You Should
Follow Instead of Your Passion</em>.</p>
<p>However, the core message of the post, which I could not help reading, did
stick with me, and after a few days I realised that I would have to go find the
article again in order to talk about it here.</p>
<p>The core message is to replace <em>find your passion</em> with <strong><em>Find your blisters.</em></strong></p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s point is that folks often get the wrong idea with <em>passion</em> as
something that is simply always delightful, whilst the thing you should
actually be looking for, is that activity that you simply are unable to stop
doing, even when you try, and especially even when you don&rsquo;t directly derive
pleasure from it, for example because you feel that you&rsquo;re not that good at it.</p>
<p>They give the personal example of writing.</p>
<p>Although they&rsquo;ve been at it for years, it&rsquo;s still a difficult and laborious
process, and they are often not happy with the results.</p>
<p>However, they have been unable to stop from returning to writing projects again
and again over the years.</p>
<p>Ironically, even although they find that they are still bad at it, they have in
fact become really good, simply because they have been pushing through and
practising more than almost anyone else over the years.</p>
<p>I really like this down-to-earth view.</p>
<p>One can indeed source almost unlimited amounts of energy from one&rsquo;s &ldquo;blisters&rdquo;,
but true benefits will for a large part be brought about by a <a href="/tags/practice/">lifetime of often
challenging practice</a>.</p>








<figure><a href="flowers_everywhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu56b127f7a133dce7ca4454aabdb42870_4234731_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &amp;ldquo;blommetjieskyk&amp;rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>