<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>bat on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/bat/</link><description>Recent content in bat on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 17:18:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/bat/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #244: Biyamiti Bat-Fan</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 17:18:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/</guid><description> Welcome to Weekly Head Voices number 244, stretching from Monday June 20 to Sunday July 24, 2022.
Winter, don&amp;rsquo;t call us, we&amp;rsquo;ll call you Shortly after the start of this period, June 21 to be exact, I was frankly and quite pleasantly surprised by the Southern Hemisphere winter solstice.
This handy Time and Date website has more details, including but not limited to:
The June solstice (winter solstice) in Cape Town is at 11:13 on Tuesday, 21 June 2022.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to Weekly Head Voices number 244, stretching from Monday June 20 to
Sunday July 24,  2022.</p>








<figure><a href="giraffe.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/giraffe_hu0c5b1ac7828618d845e256b9a3c7840a_3503992_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="winter-don-t-call-us-we-ll-call-you">Winter, don&rsquo;t call us, we&rsquo;ll call you</h2>
<p>Shortly after the start of this period, June 21 to be exact, I was frankly and
quite pleasantly surprised by the Southern Hemisphere winter solstice.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-AFRICA/cape-town">This handy Time and Date website</a> has more details, including but not limited
to:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The June solstice (winter solstice) in Cape Town is at 11:13 on Tuesday, 21
June 2022. In terms of daylight, this day is 4 hours, 32 minutes shorter than
the December solstice. In locations south of the equator, the shortest day of
the year is around this date.</p>
<p>The earliest sunset is on 12 June. The latest sunrise is on 29 June or 30 June.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some of you <a href="/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">might remember</a> that this is an important point in the year for me,
the moment when I can see the big light, namely summer, at the end of the
tunnel.</p>
<h2 id="projections">Projections</h2>
<p>I recently finished reading the book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/55411738-projections"><em>Projections: A Story of Human Emotions</em>
by Karl Deisseroth</a>.</p>
<p>As a layperson, I found this psychiatrist and world-changing scientist&rsquo;s view
of the world, and especially of the psyches of his patients, absolutely
fascinating.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Deisseroth">Deisseroth</a> writes about several different types of psychiatric disorders, but
does so via specific but (probably) fictional patients who embody the important
aspects of the disorder in question.</p>
<p>He also writes about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optogenetics">Optogenetics</a>.</p>
<p>Optogenetics is a technique, invented by Deisseroth, for controlling neurons
with lasers, <em>in vivo</em>.</p>
<p>More specifically, by inserting specific genes from algae, neurons can be
modified to activate when struck by light.</p>
<p>Using this technique, researchers are able to activate very specific subsets of
neurons in mice brains, making the mice feel anxious for example, or
comfortable, or any of the different neural components making up these mental
states.</p>
<p>From the Wikpedia artictle:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In systems neuroscience, the ability to control the activity of a genetically
defined set of neurons has been used to understand their contribution to
decision making, learning, fear memory, mating, addiction, feeding, and
locomotion.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The use of this technique has already contributed significantly to our
fundamental understanding of the brain, and the first steps have been taken
towards using it in therapy.</p>
<p>Judging by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Optogenetics#Awards">the list of awards</a>, the scientific world has really noticed the
value of this work.</p>
<p>Personally, I am optimistic that there&rsquo;s much more to come.</p>
<p>P.S. Close to the end of <a href="https://lexfridman.com/karl-deisseroth/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Deisseroth</a>, Deisseroth
mentioned that he really doubts whether he has done enough&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="batting-for-biyamiti">Batting for Biyamiti</h2>
<p>I am Bat-Fan.</p>
<p>No really, I appreciate bats. (and puns)</p>
<p>They&rsquo;re little flying mammals who see and navigate the world <em>expertly</em> using
echolocation (just imagine what that <em>feels</em> like?!) . They eat large numbers of
insects, including a <a href="https://news.wisc.edu/study-bolsters-bats-reputation-as-mosquito-devourers/">debatable</a> number of mosquitoes (I did not know about the
debate until right now).</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s not to like?</p>
<p>However, during our recent freshly reinstated yearly <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/">KNP break</a>, we enjoyed
fantastic summer weather (it&rsquo;s winter down here, but that&rsquo;s Mpumalanga for
you), we spent one night in Biyamiti with a pretty active bat in the room.</p>
<p>As we went to sleep, we thought that it would probably be ok.</p>
<p>It was not.</p>
<p>In addition to the bat expertly dropping something wet in my eye (your guess is
as good as mine), during parts of the night it started doing fly-bys so close
to our faces that we could feel the discrete wind gusts caused by the flapping
of its little wings.</p>
<p>On the one hand I was quite impressed by its sheer <em>mammalian</em> skill, but on
the other we just really wanted to sleep.</p>
<p>We decided that the price of a few extra insects in the room was worth it, and
so we opened the mesh.</p>
<p>Our bat friend, in spite of apparently having built a little nest in the nook
right up in the apex of the roof, fortunately obliged by exiting to perform the
rest of its manouevres outside in the night.</p>








<figure><a href="sunset-crocodile-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/sunset-crocodile-pano_hu596e58aa070eb1e8b2ace66dd4d17d05_1856712_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: The sun sets over the Crocodile. Nothing else matters."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>The sun sets over the Crocodile. Nothing else matters.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>