<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Pkm on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/pkm/</link><description>Recent content in Pkm on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 12:58:37 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/pkm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Note-taking strategy 2023</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2023 13:48:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/</guid><description> I wrote about my note-taking approach for the first time in 2016 (read for fun), and then pretty expansively about its evolved version in 2019.
In spite of the title of these posts, already in 2019 it had become more a system for personal knowledge management than just for note-taking.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure class="flush-left"><a href="emacs-user-dalle.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/emacs-user-dalle_hu_e56ee92c05542946.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/emacs-user-dalle_hu_fedc46e03857ec89.jpg 800w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/emacs-user-dalle_hu_fedc46e03857ec89.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Painting of an Emacs user making notes using Emacs with Org mode (dall-e via chatgpt.el)" width="320px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>I wrote about my note-taking approach for <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">the first time in 2016</a> (read for
fun), and <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">then pretty expansively about its evolved version  in 2019</a>.</p>
<p>In spite of the title of these posts, already in 2019 it had become more a
system for <em>personal knowledge management</em> than just for note-taking.</p>
<p>It is now again three years later (3.5 to be slightly more accurate), and the
system has continued on its path of steady evolution.</p>
<p>It currently contains thousands of interlinked notes, as well as hundreds of
saved articles and web-pages. It also tracks of all of my projects and tasks,
both work and personal.</p>
<p>The purpose of this post is to document the <em>current</em> state of the system. You
don&rsquo;t need any prior knowledge from the other posts; this post should be
self-contained.</p>
<h2 id="high-level-overview">High level overview</h2>
<p>The system has to satisfy the following functional requirements:</p>
<ol>
<li>Fast capture of any information on desktop and mobile, including free-form
notes, web-pages and other media.</li>
<li>Tracking of projects, tasks and metadata such as due dates and schedules.</li>
<li>Fast and accurate retrieval of any information relevant to the current
situation.</li>
<li>Potentially serendipitous surfacing of assets that might be relevant to the
main search focus, for example through linking or through search.</li>
</ol>
<p>The system should have the following two characteristics:</p>
<ol>
<li>There should be a single search interface that can in theory find everything
that was ever stored in the system. This is to prevent the situation where
you urgently need some document and can&rsquo;t remember into <em>which</em> notes app you
stored it so many years ago. (True story)</li>
<li>As far as possible, the canonical source of everything should be plain old
files on local drives, and be synchronized with a tool like Dropbox or
OneDrive. In this way, the system is robust to the whims of a note-taking
SaaS. The litmus test for this is that you are able to change out sync
services and still remain with a working system. (True story)</li>
</ol>
<p>At the highest level, my system, which satisfies the requirements and
characteristics above, consists of the following components:</p>
<dl>
<dt>Emacs with Org-mode and Org-roam</dt>
<dd>This is the nexus of the whole thing. It
tracks projects, tasks and notes, spread out over just over a thousand
org-files, each of them containing one or more (org-roam) notes, all linked
together.</dd>
<dt>Mobile device for capturing and access</dt>
<dd>In my case that&rsquo;s an iPhone with a
number of additional apps for the capturing into and accessing of my notes
database. See figure below, and explanation further down.</dd>
<dt>Reproducible digital filing system</dt>
<dd>This just refers to the fact that over
the years I&rsquo;ve evolved a recipe for &ldquo;where to put that file&rdquo; which is
reproducible in the sense that if I receive the same file a year later, my
brain will automatically follow the same logic and end up in the same
spot. Over the past year or two, I have started applying aspects of the <a href="https://fortelabs.com/blog/para/">PARA
method</a> to a subset of my files, and a heavily modified <a href="https://johnnydecimal.com/">Johnny•Decimal</a> to
the &ldquo;areas&rdquo; in PARA. I am happy with the results so far.</dd>
<dt>PDF&rsquo;d web-pages and articles (JBOP)</dt>
<dd>Locally stored PDF versions of
reference-worthy web-pages and articles can be annotated, linked and shared,
and they remain usable long after the source website has disappeared.</dd>
<dt>Academic articles managed with Zotero</dt>
<dd>Zotero is one of the best ways to
manage all of your academic literature and metadata. As if that&rsquo;s not enough,
it&rsquo;s fully open source. Since I&rsquo;m doing less academia these days, this is
seeing minimal use.</dd>
<dt>OneDrive (previously Dropbox) for cloud synchronization and searching</dt>
<dd>This
infrastructural component is critical. It ensures that all of the files are
synced and available on all devices that I use, and, quite importantly, it
indexes everything so that I can interactively search through the contents of
hundreds of thousands of files. There are some work-arounds and caveats which
I will get into further down.</dd>
<dt>SyncThing</dt>
<dd>Having a local version of my whole notes database, both in its
native Org format as well as an automatically updated Obsidian Vault version,
gives the best experience on mobile.</dd>
</dl>
<p>The following figure is a different view of the Rube Goldberg machine described
above:</p>










<figure><a href="cpbotha-pkm-2023.excalidraw.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/cpbotha-pkm-2023.excalidraw_hu_befb16bc9676e148.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/cpbotha-pkm-2023.excalidraw_hu_c5b4472c7e72470.png 800w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/cpbotha-pkm-2023.excalidraw_hu_c5b4472c7e72470.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Selected apps forming my note-taking approach on desktop and mobile."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Selected apps forming my note-taking approach on desktop and mobile.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="some-of-the-components-in-more-detail">Some of the components in more detail</h2>
<h3 id="emacs-with-org-mode-and-org-roam">Emacs with Org-mode and Org-roam</h3>
<p>At the <strong>heart of my knowledge management system</strong>, let&rsquo;s call it <code>pkb4000</code>, is
<a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/">Emacs</a>, together with the venerable <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Org mode</a> package, its more recent
augmentation <a href="https://www.orgroam.com/">Org-roam</a>, and a whole zoo of finely tuned packages.</p>
<p>Org mode, or &ldquo;Your life in plaintext&rdquo;, is a powerful text-file-based system for
managing notes, task lists, projects and even authoring documents.</p>
<p>Once you get used to the programmable flexibility that it and especially Emacs
itself are able to offer, you will find it hard to go back to any conventional
system.</p>
<p>After some years of trial and error, I have settled on using the following main
Org-mode sub-components:</p>
<dl>
<dt>monthly journal files</dt>
<dd>a diary-like setup where I try to document every
single day, and where I keep track of personal tasks and projects.</dd>
<dt>notes database</dt>
<dd>consisting of hundreds of interlinked notes about people,
things and tricks. Thanks to the magic of org roam, notes can live as files
or as headings in a month or project file.</dd>
<dt>project / area of responsibility files</dt>
<dd>where each org-file contains or
links all information related to a specific project, product or area of
responsibility.</dd>
<dt>org-agenda</dt>
<dd>This Org mode feature dynamically creates a view of all of my
projects and tasks, extracted from a subset of the files mentioned above.</dd>
</dl>
<h4 id="monthly-journal-files">Monthly journal files</h4>
<p>In my main Org mode directory, I have a subdirectory named <code>journals</code>, which
contains a directory for each year.</p>
<p>Each of these year directories contains an <code>.org</code> file for each month, so we
would have for example <code>journals/2022/2022-06-Jun.org</code>.</p>
<p>Each month file follows the structure showed in the following redacted version
of my current journal file:</p>










<figure><a href="2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot_hu_33a64c0e5a682456.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot_hu_3725d935171f0730.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot_hu_e610321c99d9886.png 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-09_19-28-05_screenshot_hu_3725d935171f0730.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A simplified example of a month journal file"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A simplified example of a month journal file</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Aside from the Hugo properties which mean I&rsquo;m ready to publish any heading as a
blog post (this is usually how <a href="/categories/weekly-head-voices/">WHVs</a> are done), my Life Systems 2022 aka
personal philosophy reminder, and the clock table where I get a complete
break-down of all work-time spent, I would like to mention the following two
aspects of the month journal.</p>
<!--list-separator-->
<ul>
<li>
<p>Day planning</p>
<p>When I start the day, I instantiate a new org-capture &ldquo;day planning&rdquo; template
by pressing <code>C-c c p</code>.</p>
<p>This creates the <em>Day planning</em> subsection with all of its subsections and
checklists. As you will see, this guides me through the morning review, which
in turn has me check each of those additional sources of incoming information
and tasks.</p>
<p>New bits of information are filed into their correct place, whilst the
org-agenda-powered task review shows me a list of tasks, extracted from the
month file and the list of current project files, so that I can decide which
ones should be taken on.</p>
<p>I list tasks which should preferably be taken care of today under <em>Tasks for
today</em>, whilst any really high-value high-satisfaction tasks go under <em>One Main
Thing and Task(s) that will satisfy end-of-day Charl</em>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<!--list-separator-->
<ul>
<li>
<p>Kill your darlings (during the monthly review).</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned this before, but it&rsquo;s just an important aspect of my &ldquo;system&rdquo;
that I would like to mention it again.</p>
<p>When I still used primitive task management systems such as <strong>everything else</strong>
that&rsquo;s not Org mode, the collection of more mature tasks would soon grow out of
control.</p>
<p>However, because I create a new Org mode file for every month, I have to copy
across manually any tasks that have not been completed yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WHY IS THAT NOT AUTOMATED YET?!&rdquo; you are probably thinking.</p>
<p>Well, the advantage of having to copy each task over manually is that it is the
ideal opportunity to evaluate the task and ask some hard questions as to its
continued relevance&hellip;</p>
<p>When a task gets too old, I will often make the decision to change its status
to <code>CANC</code> (for cancelled), sometimes with the reason for the cancellation
explained in the task body, and then just leave it there in the old month file.</p>
<p>With most of these task systems, regular reviews are of crucial importance. The
monthly start-over is a great, almost enforced, opportunity for review, as is
the morning routine when I instantiate the day planner template.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="org-agenda">Org-agenda</h4>
<p>Org-agenda is a standard Org mode feature which extracts, filters and then
shows a dynamic summary of projects and tasks from an arbitrary subset of org
files that you specify.</p>
<p>In my case, there are currently 15 org files that are consulted. This
collection evolves over time as projects and areas of responsibility come and
go.</p>
<p>I use <a href="https://github.com/alphapapa/org-super-agenda">org-super-agenda</a> for additional filtering and grouping, so that on an
average weekend day my agenda looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_21c3c5c773b616f5.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_a1ad2b977f25ead1.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_bcc9819fd36978b5.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_3ebda4b9a037d53e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2023-04-08_17-22-50_screenshot_hu_a1ad2b977f25ead1.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Semi-anonymised screenshot of my org-agenda on 2023-04-09"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Semi-anonymised screenshot of my org-agenda on 2023-04-09</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>One noteworthy extra here is that I have two lists of respectively my highest
level work and personal projects or areas of responsibility.</p>
<p>Sometimes when I get lost in the weeds, it helps to pull back to that level to
get a summary of <em>everything</em>.</p>
<p>Also, it really helped me to distinguish between projects (something with a
clear end and expected end date) vs areas of responsibility, something that
could continue indefinitely.</p>
<p>This distinction was inspired by the <a href="https://fortelabs.com/blog/para/">PARA method</a>, which has also influenced how
I organise a large subset of my filesystem.</p>
<p>On my better days, I manage to start work with a few minutes of active task and
project review (see <a href="#day-planning">Day planning</a>), and then Org agenda is incredibly useful.</p>
<h4 id="core-notes-database">Core notes database</h4>
<p>With &ldquo;database&rdquo; I of course refer to just over a thousand org (and a few
markdown, which form part of my org-roam database via <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">my md-roam changes</a>)
files, most of which find themselves in the top-level <code>pkb4000/pages</code> directory
(for logseq compatibility, story for a different time), adjacent to the
<code>journals</code> directory containing all of the monthly journal files.</p>
<p>There are files on various <code>rsync</code> and <code>ffmpeg</code> invocations, files on programming
languages, software tools, note-taking strategies, personal information on each
of my kids, and much more.</p>
<p>Org mode enables me to combine document structure, math, vector and bitmap
images and executable source code in many different languages.</p>
<p>I have configured my Emacs (where by &ldquo;configured&rdquo; I mean &ldquo;coded up the emacs
lisp for&rdquo;) to invoke ripgrep on different subsets of my notes database, and to
proffer up the results in different ways.</p>
<p>I can usually find anything that went in to this database at any point.</p>
<p>What I really like, is also being able to tell you on which day, and during
which hour, I learned this or that, or experimented with something or the
other.</p>
<p>On <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#isso-2654">February 26, 2020, a commenter on the 2019 post asked if I&rsquo;d taken a look at
org-roam</a>, a question to which my answer at that point was that I had looked
but not really gotten into it yet.</p>
<p>I just checked my notes (an <code>org-roam</code> buffer with backlinks, which sort of gives
away the story), and it turns out that a week later on March 3 of 2020 I indeed
got <code>org-roam</code> configured and running.</p>
<p>From that point on, it pretty much took over the <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#core-notes-database">core notes database</a> function
of my PKM.</p>
<p>Fortunately <code>org-roam</code> relies as much as possible on standard Org-mode
functionality while adding all of the instantaneous note searching, creation
and linking that has succeeded in drastically upgrading my Org-mode
implementation to a increasingly densely linked, tagged and far more useful
exocortex.</p>
<p>Although I <em>can</em> use <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> to visualize graphically the linkage in my
notes database, as shown below, I don&rsquo;t often do it. However, I <em>do</em> really often
follow internal links around, so I do my best to create them when and where I
can.</p>










<figure><a href="2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_40728afff6cb72c1.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_e5f7f59d0dd72b3f.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_731f5640e231f1ed.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_7c90998ffb6d57fd.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/2022-02-26_22-16-07_screenshot_hu_e5f7f59d0dd72b3f.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 4: A screenshot of org-roam-ui showing a part of my knowledge base in February of 2022."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 4: </span>A screenshot of org-roam-ui showing a part of my knowledge base in February of 2022.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I really appreciate and use the flexibility that org-roam offers in having
notes either be complete files, or headings within larger files.</p>
<h4 id="project-files">Project files</h4>
<p>Work and personal projects, and areas of responsibility, each get their own Org
file. Some projects even get a whole directory to themselves, in cases where
the project will have many more files than just the main Org file.</p>
<p>Each project / area org file has its own <code>Tasks</code> and datetree sections, similar
to the month journal.</p>
<h4 id="email-linking">Email linking</h4>
<p>An important part of knowledge and task management is one&rsquo;s emails.</p>
<p>Although I currently prefer processing my email using <a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email"><code>mu4e</code></a>, an email client
which lives inside of Emacs, I have used other tools in the past, and will
probably use new tools in the future.</p>
<p>Even at this moment I alternate between <code>mu4e</code> and the <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">FastMail</a> web-interface.</p>
<p>Long story short, I have it setup so that I can easily convert any email in
<code>mu4e</code> into a universal <code>message://message-id</code> link to be integrated with a new
task or note entry.</p>
<p>When I later open that link using a shortcut, I have programmed it so that <code>mu4e</code>
will open the relevant email if it is active, or the <code>FastMail</code> webmail when it
is not. From here I can either review the email to see what the associated task
requires, or respond to it, if the task has been completed.</p>
<p>Some of these <code>message://</code> links were created using macOS mail and they still
work. In future, if I add a new mail client to the mix, I will still be able to
jump to specific old emails, no matter where they find themselves inside of my
FastMail mailboxes.</p>
<h3 id="mobile">Mobile</h3>
<p>My workflow  on mobile can be summarised as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Rapidly find info that I need from my notes using the converted Obsidian
Vault (see below).</li>
<li>Very occasionally I edit org files using <a href="https://plainorg.com/">PlainOrg</a>. Once this app gets the
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/plainorg/comments/rfivtn/feature_request_search_directory/">often-requested directory search function</a>, I hope to use it more for
retrieval as well.</li>
<li>Keep up to date with online material via paid-for <a href="https://www.inoreader.com/">InoReader</a> (RSS), <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha">Mastodon</a>,
and reddit (tiny &ldquo;argh&rdquo; there).</li>
<li>Either save interesting articles as PDF into <code>03-Resources/refs/YEAR</code> via the OneDrive
Files integration, or send the link into
<code>pkb4000/journals/YEAR/inbox-mobile.org</code> via <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/2020/04/30/voice-capture-org-mode-notes-and-more-using-siri-shortcuts-on-ios/">my Siri shortcut</a> automation,
slightly modified to write to the local org file which will be synced via
SyncThing.
<ul>
<li>On mobile, I strongly recommend the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/extensions/safari">Print Friendly &amp; PDF bookmarklet</a> to
strip out all of the cruft, yielding PDFs that focus on the content.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Scan and OCR any invoices and other physical documents to PDF using
<a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/microsoft-lens-for-ios-fbdca5f4-1b1b-4391-a931-dc1c2582397b">Microsoft Lens</a>. Previously I used the Dropbox scan app for this.</li>
<li>There are a small number of markdown files which I mostly need to edit on
mobile. <a href="https://1writerapp.com/">1writer</a> is great for this, thanks to preview, directory search,
favourited directories and files.</li>
<li>I keep a small subset of ephemeral notes (think loyalty cards, shopping
lists) in Apple Notes because it&rsquo;s still the quickest to open up to the note
that I need, almost in one action.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="syncthing">SyncThing</h4>
<p>An important improvement here over my 2019 setup is the addition of the
paid-for <a href="https://www.mobiussync.com/">Möbius Sync</a> iPhone app in order to keep full copies of my read/write
org database and its read-only Obsidian Vault version (see below) on the phone.</p>
<p>Apps like <a href="https://plainorg.com/">PlainOrg</a> and <a href="https://1writerapp.com/">1writer</a> work really well, even rendering image
attachments (which I use often), when you have a fully local copy of the files.</p>
<h4 id="obsidian-for-efficient-notes-access-on-mobile">Obsidian for efficient notes access on mobile</h4>
<p>Recently, inspired by Jethro Kuan&rsquo;s braindump scripts, I created <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/braindump4000">braindump4000</a>,
which I have hooked up to a cronjob to convert (incrementally of course) my
whole org mode database into an Obsidian Vault.</p>
<p>This vault is synced to the correct location on my phone using the Möbius Sync
SyncThing app so that I can use the Obsidian mobile app to access my whole
database.</p>
<p>Due to much better UX, this has (fortunately) almost completely replaced the
use of <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">my slightly strange system for converting my org database into docx
files</a>, although said strange system is still useful to ensure that OneDrive&rsquo;s
lacklustre search is able to find notes when I do a global search.</p>
<h2 id="noteworthy-changes-since-the-2019-version">Noteworthy changes since the 2019 version</h2>
<h3 id="replacing-dropbox-with-onedrive">Replacing Dropbox with OneDrive</h3>
<p>After more than a decade, I switched out Dropbox for OneDrive. You can <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#byeeeeee-dropbox">read
more about the switch in this post</a>, but in short:</p>
<ul>
<li>I <strong>really</strong> enjoyed using Dropbox Paper, but it meant I had a bunch of info
stuck in the Dropbox cloud (not synced file on disk).</li>
<li>Dropbox were really dragging their feet migrating us loyal customers to the
2020 Paper version, and they were being <em>frustratingly</em> opaque about it. This
was a reminder to take and maintain control of one&rsquo;s own files.</li>
<li>For the record, Dropbox&rsquo;s syncing is substantially faster (lower latency)
than OneDrive, and, although I have not yet had any issues with OneDrive,
Dropbox has been extremely solid for me for over a decade, in spite of my
over half a million files, <a href="/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/#yes-you-can-keep-your-checked-out-source-code-in-dropbox-or-onedrive">including many active git repos</a>.</li>
<li>However, I was already paying $80 / year for Microsoft 365 Family, which
includes Office software licenses for the whole family (initially the main
reason to get it) and 6 x 1 TB OneDrive accounts vs. a minimum of $120 / year
for Dropbox for me only&hellip; Currently, the difference in practical functioning
does not justify that extra money, plus that I felt I had to vote with my
wallet re the frustrating Dropbox Paper situation.</li>
<li>On the bright side, being able to switch out the main cloud sync layer of my
system ensures that it&rsquo;s just a sync layer, and not sync-layer plus services
which subtly lock you in.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="org-roam-for-interlinked-atomic-notes">org-roam for interlinked atomic notes</h3>
<p>I have already written about this, but org-roam more than deserves a place on
this list for the drastic way in which it improved how I take and use notes.</p>
<h3 id="braindump4000-obsidian-to-access-notes-on-the-go">braindump4000: Obsidian to access notes on the go</h3>
<p>Over the years I have attempted to compensate for the lack of a worthy Emacs
representative on the iPhone first by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">importing my database to Apple Notes</a>
(updates are very tricky), then through <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">a bulk docx conversion</a> (klunky and
ugly, but updates work, and I <em>can</em> find stuff in a pinch) and now finally using
<a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/braindump4000">braindump4000</a>, in obsidian mode, to convert to and update an Obsidian Vault
which is synced to my phone via SyncThing.</p>
<p>Note that you can also use braindump4000 to generate a Hugo website with all of
your notes, which was initially the main motivation to build it!</p>
<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</h2>
<p>One of the aspects which has convincingly remained the same in my whole
personal knowledge management setup is&hellip;</p>
<p>Emacs.</p>
<p>Over the years I have seen, and sometimes been thoroughly tempted, by all of
the brilliant new tools that have gone by: Roam, Notion, Dendron, LogSeq,
Obsidian and many more.</p>
<p>However, the power of a tool which can be so thoroughly shaped as Emacs should
not be under-estimated.</p>
<p>The more I use it, the more I learn how to make it sing in new and interesting
ways.</p>
<p>The other advantage of this constant in particular, is that the utility of a
knowledge base can grow tremendously when you can consistently work on that
same system, accruing knowledge whilst all the while evolving the system itself
to remain useful in an ever-changing environment.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2021 to 2022 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.
I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to 2014 (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and 2015 (no real excuse).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition
post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_43b7cf87c31b21c0.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_fc6e5e937f90c6a9.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_12a18d122cde4000.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_5b0c7558e9575.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu_fc6e5e937f90c6a9.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to
<a href="/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/">2014</a> (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and <a href="/2015/01/21/weekly-head-voices-88-just-be-yourself-they-said/">2015</a> (no real
excuse).</p>
<p><em>Much later, on Sunday January 23:</em> It could very well still win the Most
Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Emacs and <code>M-x count-words</code> (on a temporary buffer copied over from <a href="/archive/#2021">the 2021
blog post archive</a>) tells me that I published 28 posts on this blog, and 8
technical posts over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>Just like with the running below, but for different reasons, I lost a lot of
steam during the last few months of the year.</p>
<p>In a truly surprise twist, in 2022 I will again attempt to write regularly, and
to write more, and to keep it up until the end.</p>
<h3 id="stats-addendum">Stats addendum</h3>
<p>Applying the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess log analyzer</a> to this blog&rsquo;s log files with the following
invocation:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0550ae">(</span><span style="color:#cf222e">for</span> i in <span style="color:#0550ae">{</span>2..13..1<span style="color:#0550ae">}</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">do</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> cpbotha.net.access.log.<span style="color:#953800">$i</span>.gz<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">done</span><span style="color:#0550ae">)</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> xargs zcat -f -- <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format<span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; tells me that in 2021 cpbotha.net welcomed over 115000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>The same tool reports that <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a> clocked in at just under 165000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>Even if the real number of actual human visits is a quarter of what the tool is
reporting, I am ecstatic!</p>
<p>The three most popular cpbotha.net posts based on hits during 2021 were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">Dear USA, my data has left your building</a></li>
<li><a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">Note-taking strategy 2019</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>Thanks to Strava&rsquo;s handy training calendar shown below, we can see that I spent
125 hours last year (mostly, about 4 hours was spent on hiking just over 20km)
running a bit over 1300km.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_d8797d3ae69f2074.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_bcb23928a764c751.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_71b26fe22f2669f7.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_fd426be487962b7e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu_bcb23928a764c751.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can also see quite clearly that I lost steam in November and especially in
December.</p>
<p>This was initially due to work getting quite busy, and then later in December a
bout with Omicron (highly probably) and also less than run-friendly weather in
St. Francis.</p>
<p>I am always happy when I manage to average 100km or more per month, and I&rsquo;ll
probably try to do that again in 2022.</p>
<h3 id="possibly-tmi-read-on-at-your-own-risk">Possibly TMI, read on at your own risk</h3>
<p>Those of you who know me, will also know about my giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunion">bunion</a>, or hallux
valgus as it prefers to be called.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated." width="240px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyways, Mr Valgus is unfortunately playing an increasingly frequent role in my
attempts at running, often starting to complain at N kilometres where N is
fortunately still higher than most of my attempts, but still affecting a
worrying number of them.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to push on, until Mr Valgus overstays its welcome, at which point
it will be time to explore invasive corrective procedures.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Probably my most redeeming habit of them all, is reading books every night in
bed until I fall asleep.</p>
<p>Even if the day has been less than satisfactory, ending it with an entirely
deliberate and focused reading session tends to make up for quite a lot.</p>
<p>Although I was planning to do more book summaries in 2021, I managed to
complete only one. At least it was a good one, namely <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Seven
and a Half Lessons About the Brain&rdquo; by Lisa Feldman Barrett</a>, which I can
strongly recommend if you have not checked it out yet.</p>
<p>Thanks to strong contenders like the one above, the competition was fierce, but
in the end the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em> could go to nothing other
than Oliver Burkeman&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08FGV64B1/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</em></a>.</p>
<p>Burkeman, he of the <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">importance of being able to put <em>down</em> your work</a> and of <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">more
appearances on this blog</a>, has created a beautifully written ode to our terribly
limited lifespans (4000 weeks if you&rsquo;re lucky, you can almost hear them ticking
away&hellip;), and to our terribly limited capacity to make the most of the time
that we do get, and to really just giving up the fight to <em>get everything done</em>,
because we will never ever win the battle against the law of perpetually
filling inboxes of various kinds, and because it&rsquo;s so much better to simply
<em>disconnect</em> from the firehose (which we can&rsquo;t get rid of completely) in order to
spend time on no-excuses leisure, and especially on our loved ones.</p>
<p>My favourite fiction book by far was <em>The Anomaly</em> by Hervé le Tellier, as
translated by Adriana Hunter.</p>
<p>After having just grudgingly finished Elizabeth Bear&rsquo;s Ancestral Night (first
novel in the White Space series; some interesting ideas, but just too pulpy,
clumsy and exposition-rich for my taste, in spite of space opera being a guilty
pleasure&hellip;), the light literariness and French cynicism of The Anomaly was a
<em>delightful</em> and refreshing breeze that I was unable to put down until it was
done.</p>
<p>In 2022, I&rsquo;m planning to read more than in 2021, and publish more of those
summaries.</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#mindfulness">daily meditation streak that started in 2020</a> continued for most of 2021,
until the end-of-year school vacation started. I am not yet sure how I&rsquo;ll be
able to fit this into my new 2022 work-routine.</p>
<h2 id="worst-habit-of-2021">Worst habit of 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV Award for Worst Habit of 2021 By Far goes, without a doubt, to my old
friend TwiFRaF-Yo, although this time around the main culprits were Twitter,
Reddit and YouTube.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know exactly when I fell out of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">the previous social media fast</a>, but I
fell out with a vengeance.</p>
<p>Although I subscribe almost entirely to technical communities on reddit (Emacs,
Orgmode, Org-roam, keyboards, etc.), there are enough of them to keep a person
busy.</p>
<p>If you add to that my twitter feed, where I&rsquo;ve also taken care to remove the
noise, subscribing largerly to high-signal science-, technology- , and
engineering-related feeds, there&rsquo;s a great deal of valuable-seeming information
that one feels compelled to get through every day&hellip;</p>
<p>(It feels like I&rsquo;ve told this story before&hellip;)</p>
<p>Anyways, every time I manage to disconnect (it&rsquo;s been a few weeks now, I think
Monday January 3 was the official start date of the current fast), only then am
I able to recognise (where by &ldquo;recognise&rdquo;, I mean that friends say this to me,
and this is when I&rsquo;m able to admit that they&rsquo;re right) that the net value for
me is highly probably negative.</p>
<p>While there is certainly valuable information that enters via those streams, it
costs so much attention and emotional energy that it&rsquo;s not really worth it.</p>
<p>So.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m back on the no-social-media cart until next time.</p>
<p>Just like the previous time, I&rsquo;m limiting myself to the brilliant Inoreader RSS
subscription service (which I pay for) to keep up to date with 99% long-form
blogs, and two Twitter accounts that are worth too much to me to disconnect
from (<a href="https://twitter.com/erictopol">Eric Topol</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/alper">Alper Çuğun-Gscheidel</a>).</p>
<p>Although I sometimes think this makes me slower, because I don&rsquo;t have all of
the current happenings at my fingertips all the time, I&rsquo;m hoping this gives me
more space and time for reading, thinking and writing.</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">Systems and tools for running this human (PKM baby)</h2>
<p>In the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">2018 to 2019 transition post</a> I mentioned the &ldquo;The System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This time, for this section, I would like to limit it to tools for knowledge
management and task management (this is not my favourite term, but I&rsquo;m erring
on the side of familiarity here) .</p>
<p>All of Emacs and Orgmode and Org-roam is still going strong, although I waver
quite a bit sometimes when I see some of the shiny new things, like <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>,
which I would probably be using if it wasn&rsquo;t for Emacs.</p>
<p>However, when I sometimes dive into my notes, I can see the difference it makes
when you stick to a single tool for longer than a few years. The amount of
knowledge keeps on growing, and I am slowly getting better at linking it all
together and&hellip;  sometimes even using it.</p>
<p>The picture below shows the graph created, by the <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> package, of a
sub-section of my notes network:</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_d1209fe41888514f.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_31ce23bcfd961e9f.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_950ec103a8bb11b5.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_df618e90e2d265e3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu_31ce23bcfd961e9f.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Before I got side-tracked by the pretty picture, I was planning to dedicate
this section to a new WHV award, namely the Award for the Most Unexpectedly
Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021.</p>
<p>This year the award goes to&hellip; <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper/guide">Dropbox Paper</a>!</p>
<p>Back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">WHV #233</a> I listed many of the reasons why. In the few months since then
it has become only more useful to me as the go-to mobile tool for checklists
(especially useful when we go on trips), lists of books, movies and music
recommended by people in person, and so on.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualifier features, such as its markdown DNA and its
usability on mobile for idea capturing, the fact that Paper documents show up
in Dropbox searches, which is how I usually search when I <span class="underline">really</span> need to find a
specific file (versus ripgrep searches in Orgmode), is the deal maker.</p>
<p>(My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">strange scheme for continuously converting all org files to docx</a> for
searching and reading on the iPhone is also still going strong.)</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I had a piece written here with more details about what exactly was happening
at work, but I decided to nuke that and instead keep it more personal by
mentioning that thanks to great big dollops of serendipity and people, I find
myself, with a number of levers at my disposal, right in the middle of an
organization which, after a few months of reconfiguration and preparation, has
embarked on a genuinely exciting, and importantly more unified, course.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not mention the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">discomfort and stress</a> I was
experiencing at the start of the current personal phase, most probably due to
trying to adapt quickly to my new circumstances and responsibilities.</p>
<p>In the time since then, my stress levels have returned to more acceptable
levels, but expectations remain high.</p>
<h2 id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<p>One of the most positive changes I made in the past year, was to put more
effort into making regular and active (virtual) contact with friends whom I
don&rsquo;t see in person regularly enough.</p>
<p>THANKS INTERNET YOU DA BEST.</p>
<p>This year, I want to try harder to do more of that.</p>
<p>More generally, I made a note (yes, again, one has to keep doing this until the
end) to celebrate any of my peeps and our relationships whenever there&rsquo;s a
chance.</p>
<p>Secret message for my innner INNER circle: You are my energy and my joy, I am
here to be yours.</p>
<p>Whatever else happens, these precious relationships are all we have.</p>
<h2 id="even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">Even more plans for 2022: Continue trying</h2>
<p>First off, I would really like to get this blog post here done and
published. (it wants to be too much, or rather I want it to be too much, and so
we sit here staring at each other instead of just getting on with it so I can
try again to write a good post for once)</p>
<p>Second, EAZ is back on, since Monday January 10. EAZ means no alcohol until at
least February 10. As has been the case previously, my sleep quality is
subjectively better, and it seems like my energy levels are more consistent
throughout the week.</p>
<p>I just looked back at last year&rsquo;s transition post, and especially at the <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">final
sections, including the neatly documented Life Systems 2021</a>. That guy
(<a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">apparently we share only about 2% of our atoms</a>) really seemed to have his
stuff together, on paper at the very least.</p>
<p>As I write this (22:38 on Saturday, January 22), I have just realised that <em>this</em>
&ldquo;I&rdquo; definitely needs to spend some more time thinking about &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo; (The WHV
approach to life, the universe and everything, the one with the pillars (love
and science, that&rsquo;s the easy and reliable bit) and the rules) and specifically
if and how to revise the daily life direction clusters.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll have it on your desk by Monday.</p>
<p>Until then, the one thing I&rsquo;m sure about, is that I wish you and your loved
ones the best 2022 possible.</p>










<figure><a href="stormsriver-mouth.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_9489d85cd70e5f2e.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_ebadf81992f9fe5e.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_f4dbd9f895343922.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_cfb4aaba0c7a1dbd.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu_ebadf81992f9fe5e.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Note-taking strategy 2019.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 16:19:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/</guid><description>At the start of 2016, I published an overview of my note-taking strategy then.
In the intervening three and a half years, my note-taking has further evolved to adapt to my changing environment, and the underlying &amp;ldquo;system&amp;rdquo; has co-evolved to support this.
Although note-taking is at the core of the system, a more accurate description of its current purpose would be personal knowledge management.
What you&amp;rsquo;ll also find in this post, is the culmination of many years of lessons learned trying to &amp;ldquo;keep a lab journal&amp;rdquo;.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>At the start of 2016, I published an <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">overview of my note-taking strategy
then</a>.</p>
<p>In the intervening three and a half years, my note-taking has further evolved
to adapt to my changing environment, and the underlying &ldquo;system&rdquo; has co-evolved
to support this.</p>
<p>Although note-taking is at the core of the system, a more accurate description
of its current purpose would be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_knowledge_management"><em>personal knowledge
management</em></a>.</p>
<p>What you&rsquo;ll also find in this post, is the culmination of many years of lessons
learned trying to <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#three">&ldquo;keep a lab
journal&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p><em>Note: You can now also read my more recent post <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/">Note-taking strategy
2023</a>.</em></p>
<h2 id="highest-level-overview-of-note-taking-system">Highest level overview of note-taking system.</h2>
<p>My approach consists of four main components:</p>
<p>At the core of everything is <a href="https://orgmode.org/"><strong>1. Emacs Org mode</strong></a>.</p>
<p>As you might know, Org mode is infinitely flexible. This is where all of my
projects and tasks are tracked. This is also where I keep my daily personal and
work journals.</p>
<p>I describe the specific directory structure and orgfile setup in the sections
below.</p>
<p>I continually and actively search for and find interesting <strong>2. Web-pages and
Articles</strong>, both academic and less so, which I convert to PDF and store in a
year-stamped directory inside of my
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">JBOP</a>.</p>
<p><strong>3. Academic articles</strong> that I plan to refer to in my own writings graduate into my
Zotero bibliographic database, which is synced together with everything else.</p>
<p>On <strong>4. Mobile</strong> (phone and watch, oh my!), I use the Dropbox app for capturing
and for limited access to my notes database via a small subset of markdown
files, PDFs and exported HTML, and I use the new WatchOS 6 voice notes if I&rsquo;m
not able to use my phone.</p>
<h3 id="other-noteworthy-characteristics">Other noteworthy characteristics.</h3>
<p>Everything mentioned above lives on local drives, synced with Dropbox and also
automatically and continuously backed-up to a removable disk at my office.</p>
<p>The Org mode part of the system has been in use since 2014. I have also
imported a few years of Simplenote text notes into Org mode, so its memory
stretches a bit further back still.</p>
<p>The longer the system lasts, the more valuable it gets.</p>
<p>It has now happened more than once that I could help someone with the same
advice I helped someone else with 4 years ago, simply because the real-time
text search found the relevant snippet of code or attachment in my Org mode
database.</p>
<p>Even if I were ever to change tools, the current single source of truth is a
collection of plaintext org files and PDF files which can easily be further
processed and imported into some new system.</p>
<h2 id="the-components-in-slightly-more-detail">The components in slightly more detail.</h2>
<p>In the following sections, I explain each of the four components in more detail
than in the overview above.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-org-mode">Emacs Org mode.</h3>
<p>The heart of my knowledge management system, let&rsquo;s call it <code>pkb4000</code>, is <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Emacs
Org mode</a>. Org mode, or &ldquo;Your life in plaintext&rdquo;, is a
powerful text-file-based system for managing notes, task lists, projects and
even authoring documents.</p>
<p>Once you get used to the programmable flexibility it offers, you will find it
hard to go back to any conventional system.</p>
<h4 id="monthly-journal-files">Monthly journal files.</h4>
<p>In my main Org mode directory, I have a subdirectory named <code>journals</code>, which
contains a directory for each year.</p>
<p>Each of these year directories contains an <code>.org</code> file for each month, so we would have for example
<code>journals/2019/2019-09-Sep.org</code>.</p>
<p>Each month file follows the structure showed in the following redacted version
of my current journal file:</p>
<!-- I used M-x htmlize-region-save-screenshot to get this HTML representation of a real org file onto the clipboard. -->
<pre style="color: #DCDCCC; background-color: #3F3F3F;">
<span style="color: #b3b3b3;">#+TITLE:</span> <span style="color: #8CD0D3; background-color: #3F3F3F; font-weight: bold;">2019-09 September month journal
</span>
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Vitals</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Focus items</span>
Topics and reminders I would like to spend a few minutes on during every
morning review: High value time, always be compounding, always be in a focus
block, etc.
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tired list</span>
A general list of valuable activities for when I have some time, but brain too
tired to come up with anything.
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Planning / overview / major done list</span>
Check lists with books, courses, etc.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Projects</span>
A list of current major projects, with links to each project's dedicated org
file.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks</span>
A list of Org mode tasks that are not associated with specific projects. This
list is reviewed at the start of every month, as I have to manually copy across
those tasks that are still relevant and important.
<span style="color: #DFAF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">*</span><span style="color: #BFEBBF; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019-09 September</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">**</span><span style="color: #7CB8BB; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* 2019-09-19 Thursday (example day)</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">***</span><span style="color: #D0BF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Day planning </span><span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">[2019-09-19 Thu 09:17]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Done list / thoughts / diary</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks for today </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[/]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[/]</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Focus blocks</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Sleep</span>
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Review </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[3/8]</span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> <span style="color: #D0BF8F; text-decoration: underline;"><a href="*Vitals">Month vitals</a></span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> Calendar
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> Org tasks
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> <span style="color: #D0BF8F; text-decoration: underline;"><a href="file:~/Dropbox/notes/mobile/inbox/">dropbox mobile inbox</a></span>
      - ...

<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">****</span><span style="color: #93E0E3; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* Habits / important </span><span style="color: #CC9393; font-weight: bold;">[7/12]</span>
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> 7.5 hrs sleep last night
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[ ]</span> are you satisfied with number of pomodori? = 0 (v R)
      - <span style="color: #FFFFEF; background-color: #5F5F5F;">[X]</span> did you write stuff down?
      - ...
<span style="color: #3F3F3F;">***</span><span style="color: #D0BF8F; background-color: #3F3F3F;">* is dropbox better than evernote for mobile capturing? </span><span style="color: #8CD0D3; text-decoration: underline;">&lt;2019-09-19 Thu 22:16&gt;</span>

     in ios, with any page in safari, I can do "save to dropbox" and get a PDF
     version of the page for the <span style="color: #b3b3b3;">=notes/mobile/inbox=</span>.
</pre>
<p>As you can see from the example above, the monthly journal file is the main
index to my current high-level goals and focus items, my currently running work
and personal projects, miscellaneous tasks, and my detailed daily journalling
and habit tracking.</p>
<h5 id="daily-review">Daily review.</h5>
<p>When I start the day, I instantiate a new org-capture &ldquo;day planning&rdquo; template
by pressing <code>C-c c p</code>.</p>
<p>This creates the <code>Day planning</code> subsection with all of its subsections and
checklists. As you will see, this guides me through the morning review, which
in turn has me check each of those additional sources of incoming information
and tasks.</p>
<p>New bits of information are filed into their correct place, whilst the task
review shows me a list of tasks, extracted from the month file and the list of
current project files, so that I can decide which ones should be taken on.</p>
<p>I list tasks which should preferably be taken care of today under <code>Tasks for today</code>, whilst any really high-value high-satisfaction tasks go under <code>Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl</code>.</p>
<h5 id="during-the-day">During the day.</h5>
<p>During the rest of the day, I&rsquo;ll write short diary-like notes under <code>Done list / thoughts / diary</code> and log pomodori (focus blocks) under, you guessed it,
<code>Focus blocks</code>, either using the <code>org-pomodoro</code> package, or plain Org mode
clocking in and out functions.</p>
<p>I use additional custom org-capture templates, via keyboard shortcuts, to
create more extensive timestamped journal entries (see the <code>is dropbox better ...</code> example) and to create new timestamped and logged Org mode <code>TODO</code> entries.</p>
<h5 id="kill-your-darlings-during-the-monthly-review">Kill your darlings (during the monthly review).</h5>
<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned this before, but it&rsquo;s just an important aspect of my &ldquo;system&rdquo;
that I would like to mention it again.</p>
<p>When I still used primitive task management systems such as <em>everything else</em>
that&rsquo;s not Org mode, the collection of more mature tasks would soon grow out of
control.</p>
<p>However, because I create a new Org mode file for every month, I have to copy
across manually any tasks that have not been completed yet.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WHY IS THAT NOT AUTOMATED YET?!&rdquo; you are probably thinking.</p>
<p>Well, the advantage of having to copy each task over manually is that it is the
ideal opportunity to evaluate the task and ask some hard questions as to its
continued relevance&hellip;</p>
<p>When a task gets too old, I will often make the decision to change its status
to <code>CANC</code> (for cancelled), sometimes with the reason for the cancellation
explained in the task body, and then just leave it there in the old month file.</p>
<p>With most of these task systems, regular reviews are of crucial importance. The
monthly start-over is a great, almost enforced, opportunity for review, as is
the morning routine when I instantiate the day planner template.</p>
<h5 id="what-about-email">What about email?!</h5>
<p>An important part of knowledge and task management is one&rsquo;s emails.</p>
<p>Although I currently prefer processing my email using
<a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email"><code>mu4e</code></a>,
an email client which lives inside of Emacs, I have used other tools in the
past, and will probably use new tools in the future.</p>
<p>Also, even at this moment I alternate between <code>mu4e</code> and the
<a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">FastMail</a>
web-interface.</p>
<p>Long story short, I have it setup so that I can easily convert any email in
<code>mu4e</code> into a universal <code>message://message-id</code> link to be integrated with a
new task or note entry.</p>
<p>When I later open that link using a shortcut, I have programmed it so that
<code>mu4e</code> will open the relevant email if it is active, or the <code>FastMail</code> webmail
when it is not. From here I can either review the email to see what the
associated task requires, or respond to it, if the task has been completed.</p>
<p>Some of these <code>message://</code> links were created using macOS mail and they still
work. In future, if I add a new mail client to the mix, I will still be able to
jump to specific old emails, no matter where they find themselves inside of my
FastMail mailboxes.</p>
<h4 id="core-notes-database">Core notes database.</h4>
<p>With <code>database</code> I of course refer to hundreds of org and markdown files, most
of which find themselves in the top-level <code>pkb4000</code> directory, one level up
from the <code>journals</code> directory containing all of the monthly journal files.</p>
<p>There are files on various <code>rsync</code> or <code>ffmpeg</code> invocations, files on
programming languages, software tools, note-taking strategies, personal
information on each of my kids, and much more.</p>
<p>Org mode enables me to combine document structure, math, vector and bitmap
images and executable source code in many different languages.</p>
<p>I have configured my Emacs (where by &ldquo;configured&rdquo; I mean &ldquo;coded up the emacs
lisp for&rdquo;) to invoke ripgrep on different subsets of my notes database, and to
proffer up the results in different ways.</p>
<p>I can usually find anything that went in to this database at any point.</p>
<p>What I really like, is also being able to tell you on which day, and during
which hour, I learned this or that, or experimented with something or the
other.</p>
<h4 id="project-files">Project files.</h4>
<p>Work and personal projects each get their own Org file. Some projects even get
a whole directory to themselves, in cases where the project will have many more
files than just the main Org file.</p>
<p>In all cases, the project org file will live somewhere below a year-stamped
directory, e.g. <code>work/projects/2019/project-name/</code>.</p>
<p>Some projects go over year boundaries, but their files and directories remain
in the year that they started in. The project org also has <code>Tasks</code> and a
datetree section, similar to the month journal.</p>
<p>All current project files, along with my the current month file, are configured
to be part of the <code>org-agenda-files</code> variable.</p>
<p>This means that when I activate the <code>org-agenda</code> view, I see a unified list of
all tasks as extracted from all current project files and the current monthly
journal file.</p>
<p>When a project is completed, it is of course removed from <code>org-agenda-files</code>.</p>
<h3 id="web-pages-and-articles">Web-pages and articles.</h3>
<p>As mentioned in the short system overview, I store all web-pages and articles I
come across as date-stamped PDF files in a set of year-stamped directories.</p>
<p>For more detail, please refer to the
<a href="/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">JBOP</a>
section of WHV#165 on this blog.</p>
<p>In short, I use good ad-blocking and <em>mostly</em> the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/">printfriendly browser
extension</a> in Brave or Chromium to convert any
interesting web-pages to PDF. PDF articles from journals and other reputable
sources obviously don&rsquo;t have to be converted.</p>
<p>I name and save these PDFs into my <code>refs</code> hierarchy, for example
<code>Dropbox/refs/2019/20190518 Measles and Immune Amnesia - asm.pdf</code>.</p>
<p>Usually, to win any argument, I can find the pertinent reference on my phone or
my laptop in 30 seconds or less.</p>
<p>(I used to be a paying Pocket subscriber. However, as you will read in WHV#165
cited above, I was disappointed by the super important search function. The
advantages of having Just a Bunch of PDFs on your (synced) disc are many.)</p>
<h3 id="zotero">Zotero.</h3>
<p>The <code>refs</code> directory hierarchy described above is great for quickly storing an
article in the right place with a suitable name, ready for search-based
retrieval later.</p>
<p>However, in cases where one needs to cite any academics works, having these
articles in a good reference manager is important.</p>
<p>Zotero is in my view one of the best reference managers out there, and it&rsquo;s open
source!</p>
<p>The reasons I prefer zotero are:</p>
<ul>
<li>You can make use of their synchronisation service, or you can do it
yourself. I have about 2.3GB of additional articles in zotero, so this is
great.</li>
<li>Zotero uses your browser to retrieve fulltexts automatically when you import
any web-page with bibliographic information using the browser extension. This
is great when you have access via your institution. Competing cloud services
would historically use <em>their</em> servers to retrieve the fulltext, which would
often not work.</li>
<li>Zotero is open source. To me this is important, <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/zotero/">because on more than one
occasion</a> I have been able to make small
modifications to make it perform peculiar tricks I needed at that point.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="mobile">Mobile.</h3>
<p>This has always been the weakest part of my whole knowledge management system.</p>
<p>Ideally, I would have easy access to my complete org database and any related
files. Ideally, it would be possible to store any interesting tidbits I come
across whilst browsing using my phone.</p>
<p>So far I have invested time in the following apps and ecosystems:</p>
<ul>
<li>iCloud Notes: This was great, until <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/#so-tell-me-why-did-your-somewhat-stylish-macbook-phase-have-to-come-to-an-end">I sold my
MacBook</a>. iCloud
Notes web-access is terribly slow and more or less unusable. Whatever I have
on mobile, needs to interoperate smoothly with desktop.</li>
<li>Google Keep: This worked pretty well on mobile and via the web, but it&rsquo;s a
closed off ecosystem. You can
<a href="https://takeout.google.com/settings/takeout">&ldquo;takeout&rdquo;</a> your data, but you
end up with ginormous HTML files (images are base64-encoded and included)
that are not straight-forward to work with.</li>
<li>OneNote: This has SO MUCH potential (free-form note-taking, drawing with
Apple Pencil, apps for so many platforms, great organization, etc. etc.) but
is just so frustratingly unusable due to syncing issues everywhere, even on
my true-blue Windows 10 laptop with the true-blue official gold star
Microsoft OneNote application. Microsoft is doing fantastic work in some
domains (Visual Studio Code, .net core, WSL, etc. etc.) but in some others
not so much it seems.</li>
<li>Evernote: I recently just gave up and bought a premium subscription for the
year, because Evernote is the industry standard and it had Apple Watch voice
notes even before WatchOS 6 was released. In any case, although initially
promising, Evernote is unfortunately quite slow at unpredictable moments
(sharing web-page with evernote mobile app for storage can sometimes take 20
second or more&hellip;) so I&rsquo;ve had to ditch it. Again.</li>
</ul>
<p>During all of this experimentation, I started storing mobile discoveries in a
new section called &ldquo;inbox&rdquo; in the relevant note-taking app&rsquo;s organizational
structure. During morning review, I go through the relevant inbox, and
re-convert the relevant page into PDF for my more permanent archive.</p>
<p>It dawned on me that this approach could also be applied with just the Dropbox
app! It would be klunky, but at least not disappointing.</p>
<p>So, when I want to store something from the phone, I either print to PDF or
make use of the &ldquo;Save to Dropbox&rdquo; app extension, and then store the resultant
PDF in <code>Dropbox/notes/inbox</code>. During morning review, PDFs in this directory are
re-converted if required, and then stored in their more permanent home.</p>
<p>Using the Dropbox app, I can also create markdown text files in the <code>inbox</code>
directory.</p>
<p>If I have something a little more extensive, I have the option of using the
&ldquo;Voice Memos&rdquo; app, either on the phone, or even via the Apple Watch.</p>
<p>In <code>Dropbox/notes/mobile</code> I keep items I often need to access from the phone:
Think loyalty cards, markdown files with IP numbers and configuration of my
home network, and so on. This directory is marked as &ldquo;available offline&rdquo;, so I
can access its contents even when there&rsquo;s no data connection.</p>
<p>Other than that, I do an export of my whole org database to HTML now and then,
following a procedure similar to the one I used <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">to use for exporting Org mode
to iCloud
Notes</a>. The
HTML versions are searchable on the phone.</p>
<p>What would be better, is if the Dropbox iOS app would start recognising .org
files as plaintext files, much like what it already does for markdown .md
files. As it stands, I keep a small subset of my notes as markdown, instead of
the superior org, for mobile editing.</p>
<h4 id="drawing-with-apple-pencil-on-the-ipad-using-notability">Drawing with Apple Pencil on the iPad using Notability.</h4>
<p>Sometimes one does need to sketch.</p>
<p>This could be a rough UI, an architecture diagram, a data flow chart, or just
doodling.</p>
<p>Since about the end of 2018, I&rsquo;ve been using the <a href="https://apps.apple.com/za/app/notability/id360593530">Notability
app</a> along with an iPad
6th gen (2018 entry-level, the first non-Pro to support the Pencil) to doodle
electronically.</p>
<p>Notability automatically syncs all of these drawings as fully vectorised PDFs
to my Dropbox. All handwritten text is quite smartly OCRd, and the OCRd version
is stored as correctly positioned metadata behind my ugly scribbles.</p>
<p>I would have liked Notability even more if it supported arbitrary canvas sizes
(as it stands, only standard paper size in protrait mode), and had an always
visible overview minimap.</p>
<h4 id="signal-messaging-apps-brilliant-note-to-self-contact">Signal messaging app&rsquo;s brilliant &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo; contact.</h4>
<p>The <a href="https://signal.org/">Signal messaging app</a>, which you should all be using,
has a built-in contact called &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As of late (since about December 2019) this has become my main <em>capturing tool</em>
when I&rsquo;m on the phone.</p>
<p>You can share links, media, photos, voice notes or a plain old text message,
all of which will be securely stored, neatly timestampted to boot, in your
conversation with this silent but very useful &ldquo;Note to Self&rdquo; character.</p>
<p>During the morning review, I go through each of the shared items, processing
them, and then add the message &ldquo;DONE =====&gt;&rdquo; to indicate that they have been
completed.</p>
<h2 id="limitations-and-points-for-improvement">Limitations and points for improvement.</h2>
<p>The current system is great for capturing and search-based retrieval of
personal knowledge.</p>
<p>However, I miss functionality for making some of the higher-level patterns and
networks more <em>discoverable</em>.</p>
<p>For example, as I create a new orgmode entry, the system could show me related,
older nodes (that is something I could implement&hellip;).</p>
<p>Furthermore, it would have been great to see some form of visual representation
of the associations between nodes, and of how they fit into higher-level
concepts. This bit is slightly far-fetched.</p>
<p>Interestingly, I just ran into the following paragraph at the end of <a href="/2016/01/05/note-taking-strategy-early-2016/">my 2016
note-taking post</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>However, I think that there might be room for a fourth type of tool that is
more visual, supports rich and graphical linking between data items and even
between sub-components of such items and, perhaps most importantly, enables
us to build note landscapes that are natively as non-linear as our thoughts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let&rsquo;s see what happens over the next few years!</p>
<h2 id="appendix">Appendix</h2>
<h3 id="redacted-emacs-orgmode-capture-template">Redacted Emacs Orgmode capture template</h3>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; normally I construct current-journal-filename using mix of expand-file-name and concat</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">setq</span> <span style="color:#953800">current-journal-filename</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;/full/path/to/current/month-journal/&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; %i = selected text, %a org-store-link, %U created timestamp, %? place cursor here</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">setq</span> <span style="color:#953800">org-capture-templates</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#0550ae">&#39;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">((</span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;t&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;Todo&#34;</span> <span style="color:#953800">entry</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">file+headline</span> <span style="color:#953800">current-journal-filename</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;Tasks&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;* TODO %?\n:LOGBOOK:\n- Created \&#34;TODO\&#34; %U\n:END:\n%i\n%a\n\n&#34;</span> 
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#6639ba">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">1</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;j&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;Journal&#34;</span> <span style="color:#953800">entry</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">file+olp+datetree</span> <span style="color:#953800">current-journal-filename</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;* %? %T\n&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#6639ba">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">1</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;p&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;Day planning&#34;</span> <span style="color:#953800">entry</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">file+olp+datetree</span> <span style="color:#953800">current-journal-filename</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;* Day planning %U
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Done list / thoughts / diary
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- %?
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Tasks for today [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Experiment: Articulate your directions / systems.
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Tasks that will satisfy end-of-the-day Charl [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Focus blocks
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Review [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] [[*Vitals][Month vitals]]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] Org sub-projects
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] Calendar
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] ...
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">** Habits / important [/]
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] 7.5 hrs sleep last night
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] are you satisfied with number of pomodori? = 0 (v R)
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] did you write stuff down?
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">- [ ] ...
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#6639ba">:empty-lines</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">1</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)))</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>
<h3 id="sunday-2020-01-12">Sunday 2020-01-12</h3>
<ul>
<li>Add <a href="#redacted-emacs-orgmode-capture-template">example of orgmode capture template
configuration</a> in appendix.</li>
<li>Add <a href="#drawing-with-apple-pencil-on-the-ipad-using-notability">section about iPad, Notability and Apple
Pencil</a>.</li>
<li>Add <a href="#signal-messaging-apps-brilliant-note-to-self-contact">section about Signal&rsquo;s Note to Self
contact</a>.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>