<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Zen on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/zen/</link><description>Recent content in Zen on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2019 08:33:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/zen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #174: Row row row your boat.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2019 08:33:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/</guid><description> The view through one of the old windows of Cucina di Giovanni in Paarl on a brilliant winter afternoon. The symbolism of this will hopefully shine through soon. Hello friends.
Although these Weekly Head Voices look back at the week from Monday July 15 to Sunday July 21, it is already Wednesday, July 24, as I write this.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="view_from_giovannis_paarl.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu_855476995ed8d2c7.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu_ebfccb0aa132d2b8.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu_d06957caa756c851.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu_73ddd65fa6af7858.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/view_from_giovannis_paarl_hu_ebfccb0aa132d2b8.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
The view through one of the old windows of Cucina di Giovanni in Paarl on a brilliant winter afternoon. The symbolism of this will hopefully shine through soon.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Hello friends.</p>
<p>Although these Weekly Head Voices look back at the week from Monday July 15 to
Sunday July 21, it is already Wednesday, July 24, as I write this.</p>
<p>As is usually the case this time of the year, I access the below visualization
perhaps a tad too often:</p>
<a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-africa/cape-town?month=7&year=2019">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu_f07f49ffcbf327d2.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu_9d4dfa04067688b3.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu_8dd95c5d143ba3f6.png 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/sunrise_sunset_july_24_2019_hu_9d4dfa04067688b3.png"
  

   />



</a>
<p>Although it&rsquo;s grey and cold and rainy down here at the moment, I console myself
with the fact that the days are slowly but surely getting longer again, minute
by minute.</p>
<p>Starting from the depths of the Winter Solstice on June 21, when there were 9
hours and 53 minutes of daylight, today that had already stretched to a period
of 10 hours and 16 minutes.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re slowly making our way to 14 hours and 25 minutes of daylight on December
22, the Summer Solstice.</p>
<p>Although I do try to savour every moment, I can&rsquo;t help but look forward to the
warmth.</p>
<p>Anyways, the rest of this post exploded into a solid dollop of backyard
philosophy, which I hope you enjoy.</p>
<h2 id="bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Bullet List of Miscellany (BLoM).</h2>
<p>Before we dig in to the promised solid dollop, let&rsquo;s warm up with a BLoM.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Last week I
reported</a>
that we had half-bricked the solar inverter with a firmware upgrade. Shortly
after that, with some help from local support, we reflashed everything from
scratch (note: Although the manual says NOT to use EzFlash for GW5048-ES
inverters shipped after March, you in fact have to use EzFlash in this case)
and, lo and behold, the inverter was resurrected!
<ul>
<li>With BMS (battery management system) communication online, the system works
like a charm. Record solar consumption so far is 24.1 kWh, which is great for
winter!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>My favourite (and only) TPN (Tall Philosophical Neighbour) alerted me to the
fact that images were positively ginormous in the email version of this
blog. I&rsquo;ve fine-tuned the Hugo image-resizing shortcode to do a better job.</li>
<li>After a discussion with a friend from work about kindness, I came across this
post I wrote five (5) years ago: <a href="/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/">Weekly Head Voices #81 - Middle-aged
zen</a>. For me it was worth
reading again. (Also, the person who wrote that seems to be more advanced
than I currently am. Life is circles.)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="life-is-but-a-dream">Life is but a dream.</h2>
<p>I would like to take you on a little trip.</p>
<p>Please imagine an extremely dark room.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;re stuck in this room.</p>
<p>Fortunately there are two really small holes in the thick black walls through
which light shines in. If you get up and peak out through the holes, you can
make out what&rsquo;s going on outside of the room.</p>
<p>There are two more holes through which you can hear sounds from the outside
world, if you put your ears up to them.</p>
<p>Every day, someone shoves food in through yet another small hole.</p>
<p>At least you won&rsquo;t go hungry.</p>
<p>However, if you have to be honest, this room, your jail, is still really
dark and really lonely.</p>
<p>After some time, you discover, behind a really heavy floor tile, a number of
levers.</p>
<p>Using these levers, you are able to make the room rock to and fro.</p>
<p>After some months of practice, you learn how to rock the room more
consistently, and move it in a certain direction.</p>
<p>When you do this, the rays of light coming in through the two pinprick holes
change in interesting ways.</p>
<p>Very slowly, over a period of years, you start figuring out that the rays of
light coming in through the two holes, and the sounds coming in through the
other holes, are often caused by other prisoners, all trapped in cells similar
to yours.</p>
<p>You start making <em>contact</em>.</p>
<h3 id="real-time-reality-synthesis">Real-time reality synthesis.</h3>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to tell this story without giving it away of course.</p>
<p>Your brain is in fact trapped in a bony cage.</p>
<p>It has two slimy nerve bundles slithering out through two holes in your
skull. The ends of those nerve bundles are sensitive to photons falling on them
(light), and send electrical signals back along their bodies when this happens.</p>
<p>Your brain has more slimy nerve bundles connected to your ears.</p>
<p>Sound waves hitting your eardrums via a chain of contact end up as vibrations
in the fluid inside your cochleae, where another set of nerve endings are
stimulated and send more electrical signals back along their bodies.</p>
<p>Your whole body is criss-crossed by more of these bundles of super long
neurons.</p>
<p>Trapped in its terribly dark bony cage, your brain is a slimy mass that absorbs
all of the electrical signals coming back from your eyes, your ears, and the
rest of your nervous system.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s really not that much coming in folks.</p>
<p>However, somehow, somewhere inside of that slimy mass, &ldquo;you&rdquo; experience all of
this as a multi-coloured, high definition, surround-sound, smell-&lsquo;o-vision,
multi-million dollar 3D Hollywood movie.</p>
<p>When I look at the imbalance between the real-time sensory data coming in on
the one hand, and the incredible richness of the experience on the other, and
bolstered slightly by what I know about the human sensory system, I come to the
conclusion that the multi-million dollar experience is a result of an almost
perpetual hallucination.</p>
<p>In other words, the reality that we experience while awake is <em>seeded</em> by our
senses, but a large part of its verdant richness is synthesised, in real-time,
by our amazing brains.</p>
<p>Thinking about it this way, it is not so surprising that we are apparently able
to synthesise whole realities while we dream, including people, environments,
conversations, relationships and experiences, all in apparent real-time.</p>
<h3 id="ps-its-the-music">P.S. It&rsquo;s the music.</h3>
<p>This whole story came up in a conversation I recently had with my partner.</p>
<p>I was trying to explain that I easily get lost in thought with the right
music.</p>
<p>Heck, when I go running (for realz), I sometimes get utterly lost in my
imagination, and it&rsquo;s quite a visual, even multi-sensory affair.</p>
<p>During that conversation, I had the insight that when this happens (i.e. I get
lost in thought), it&rsquo;s only some of the lower bandwidth sensory feeds that are
suppressed and/or slightly disrupted, for example by the right music, enabling
the super deluxe reality synthesis equipment in my brain to do what it normally
does, only slightly less constrained by outside stimuli.</p>
<p>Taking this one step further, although one might be permanently hallucinating,
one does have some control over the balance between incoming feeds and internal
simulation.</p>
<p>In <a href="/2018/02/04/weekly-head-voices-130-2-direct-experience-dopamine/#your-brain-at-work-part-2-dopamine-and-more-mindfulness">direct experience
mode</a>,
one shifts more bandwidth to the incoming feeds.</p>
<p>(Internal simulation still has to fill in the multitude of blanks.)</p>
<p>Then, when one&rsquo;s imagination takes flight, incoming feeds are turned down
somewhat, enabling internal simulation to take over.</p>
<h2 id="row-row-row-your-boat">Row, row, row your boat.</h2>
<p>I wish you an amazing week, and I look forward to when we meet again.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #147: The yearly post-Mpumalanga post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 20:50:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/</guid><description> The Lilac-Breasted Roller. I met this enchanting and almost surrealistically pretty creature for the first time two weeks ago.
Time period covered by this post: Monday June 18 to Sunday July 8.
Reason for extended absence: Holiday-based recharge.
Holiday rating: 13/10. Math is irrelevant.
It’s relatively quiet from the European side of my family. I trust (partly confirmed by the grapevine) that my peeps over there are having themselves a wonderful rest.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/lilac_breasted_roller.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/lilac_breasted_roller-1024x377.jpg"
        
            alt="The Lilac-Breasted Roller. I met this enchanting and almost surrealistically pretty creature for the first time two weeks ago."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Lilac-Breasted Roller. I met this enchanting and almost surrealistically pretty creature for the first time two weeks ago.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>Time period covered by this post:</strong> Monday June 18 to Sunday July 8.</p>
<p><strong>Reason for extended absence:</strong> Holiday-based recharge.</p>
<p><strong>Holiday rating:</strong> 13/10. Math is irrelevant.</p>
<p>It’s relatively quiet from the European side of my family. I trust (partly confirmed by the grapevine) that my peeps over there are having themselves a wonderful rest.</p>
<p>Over here on the tip of the African continent, we migrated temporarily about 1800km to the North-East, to Mpumalanga, where winter is a rather theoretical concept.</p>
<p>The week was amazing.</p>
<p>It’s hard to explain the emotions evoked by the rugged beauty of the surroundings, and by the African sun, albeit slightly gentler than usual, beating down on one’s back.</p>
<div class="gallery galleryid-3205 gallery-columns-2 gallery-size-medium" data-carousel-extra='{"blog_id":1,"permalink":"https:\/\/cpbotha.net\/2018\/07\/10\/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post\/"}' id="gallery-9">
<figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon landscape">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-9" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843.jpg" title=""><img alt="" class="attachment-medium size-medium" data-attachment-id="3206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"5.6","credit":"","camera":"Canon PowerShot SX260 HS","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1530003714","copyright":"","focal_length":"43.736","iso":"100","shutter_speed":"0.0025","title":"","orientation":"1"}' data-image-title="IMG_5843" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-1024x768.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-300x225.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843.jpg" data-orig-size="4000,3000" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/img_5843/" height="225" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-300x225.jpg 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-768x576.jpg 768w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5843-1200x900.jpg 1200w" width="300"/></a>
</div></figure><figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon landscape">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-9" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919.jpg" title=""><img alt="" class="attachment-medium size-medium" data-attachment-id="3207" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"5.6","credit":"","camera":"Canon PowerShot SX260 HS","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1530092144","copyright":"","focal_length":"40.31","iso":"100","shutter_speed":"0.004","title":"","orientation":"1"}' data-image-title="IMG_5919" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-1024x768.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-300x225.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919.jpg" data-orig-size="4000,3000" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/10/weekly-head-voices-147-the-yearly-post-mpumalanga-post/img_5919/" height="225" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-300x225.jpg 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-768x576.jpg 768w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_5919-1200x900.jpg 1200w" width="300"/></a>
</div></figure>
</div>
<p>Added to that, every evening we were embroiled in a non-competitive competition to outcook the previous evening’s culinary adventure.</p>
<p>All of this made for a rather primal holiday experience filled with wild animals, eating, old-fashioned human contact (including a serendipitous meeting with friends I had last seen 20 years ago), thinking and running.</p>
<p>This weekend we’ll hopefully return to the usual WHV programming, with more, you know, content.</p>
<p>Until then, I would like to leave you with the following sunset.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/zen_potjie.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/zen_potjie-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Potjie, overflowing with Zen."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Potjie, overflowing with Zen.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #81: Middle-aged zen.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 20:21:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/</guid><description>(Warning: This post has an extremely high backyard philosophy content. Will probably greatly offend any real philosophers, and a bunch of other people I probably have not even thought about.)
I recently became middle-aged. As part of the thank you I wrote for the many kind words people posted to my facebook wall, I made a short summary of the things I had learned over the past N years. I hope you don’t mind that I post them here as well:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(Warning: This post has an extremely high backyard philosophy content. Will probably greatly offend any real philosophers, and a bunch of other people I probably have not even thought about.)</em></p>
<p>I recently became middle-aged. As part of the thank you I wrote for the many kind words people posted to my facebook wall, I made a short summary of the things I had learned over the past N years. I hope you don’t mind that I post them here as well:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>… here’s what I’ve picked up over the past decades (only two things, I’m a slow learner):</p>
<ol>
<li>Relationships – the most important thing (and maybe even the only thing) in the world.</li>
<li>Kindness – it really looks like we have unlimited quantities of this to give, but somehow there’s not as much of it going around as there could be. Let’s fix this!</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Since that note (I’ve skipped a number of weekly posts here as you might have noticed; really really busy) I have also been thinking about the relationship between one’s happiness, one’s circumstances, and the plasticity of one’s self.</p>
<p>I’ll start this little story with me during a coffee-induced zen moment:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/wpid-cpbotha_at_coffee_roasting_co.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/wpid-cpbotha_at_coffee_roasting_co.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Zen is a real thing that you can read about on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen">wikipedia</a>, in a billion blogs and also in <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://youtu.be/MOXQo7nURs0">BookBooks</a>. I don’t think that I’m deviating <strong>too</strong> far from the real deal when I use zen to describe any form of personal enlightenment, or that elevated state of self I should be striving for every moment of every day, but mostly forget to do because I get caught up in life as, ironically, I am not yet zen enough.</p>
<p>Sometimes, I find myself in a perfect little moment of warmth and humanity with close friends or family (and/or with a perfect coffee) and I am somehow able to observe and appreciate the moment in real-time from a spot somewhere outside of the conversation, for example while I’m walking to school with my daughter on a spring morning and realise that life in these simple moments is even greater than I thought. Sometimes I am briefly able to distance myself from some perceived life complexity, a distance from which everything actually looks pretty fine and then turns out to be exactly that. Was it that way to start with, did it change, or did I change?</p>
<p>I think being able to take a few (or a thousand) steps back in order to better see yourself and your situation is related to one of the few fundamental zen principles: Enlightenment through growing self-knowledge. I also somehow had in my mind that there was some connection between zen and the principle of mind like water, or <em>mizo no kokoro</em> if you prefer its prettier ring. In searching for this link, I stumbled onto <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/quotes/163198-you-must-be-shapeless-formless-like-water-when-you-pour">this Bruce Lee quote</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You must be shapeless, formless, like water. When you pour water in a cup, it becomes the cup. When you pour water in a bottle, it becomes the bottle. When you pour water in a teapot, it becomes the teapot. Water can drip and it can crash. Become like water my friend.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>During those occasional and coincidental flashes of increased perception I mentioned above the quote, when I was both in the experience and outside, at a good distance, I was able to look inwards and see how I could best change <em>me</em> to suit the situation better. The better I suit the situation, the more it agrees with me. Harmony.</p>
<p>Let me restate that: Most often I am not able to change my environment. However, I am apparently able to train my ability to change <em>me</em>, which in many cases can lead to the same desired harmonious outcome.</p>
<p>So, sort of in addition to the things I’ve learned over the past years, here are the things I strive to have cultivated when I grow up:</p>
<ul>
<li>Mindfulness, of me, the human beings I am fortunate to be surrounded with and all of the interactions between us. This includes the ability to take a thousand steps back, and to see clearly.</li>
<li>A mind like water, not to do kung fu fighting, but to be able to change and flow continuously to contribute more to harmony and happiness.</li>
</ul>
<p>Because I’m not sure how else to do this, I’m ending this story with a photo of a beer that I took during a really sunny zen moment:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-radison_jack_black.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-radison_jack_black.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Have a beautiful and harmonious week fellow humans!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Drown in the now. [Weekly Head Voices #42]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/03/19/drown-in-the-now-weekly-head-voices-42/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2011 13:39:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/03/19/drown-in-the-now-weekly-head-voices-42/</guid><description> Carrying the portentous number 42, this edition of the Weekly Head Voices owes it to the sometimes nerdy expectations of its readers to offer at least a small part of the answer to life, the universe and everything. In other words, #42 is 100% backyard philosophy. Water, and bridges, and paths, taken this morning especially for you. You should start feeling all pensive now.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <div>
<p>
    Carrying the portentous number 42, this edition of the Weekly Head Voices owes it to the sometimes nerdy expectations of its readers to offer at least a small part of the answer to life, the universe and everything. In other words, #42 is 100% backyard philosophy.
  </p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/paths_and_water_of_intrigue.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/paths_and_water_of_intrigue.jpg"
        
            alt="Water, and bridges, and paths, taken this morning especially for you. You should start feeling all pensive now."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Water, and bridges, and paths, taken this morning especially for you. You should start feeling all pensive now.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
    I’ve had a really brilliant week. When it started, one of the slightly more zen voices in my head proposed a little experiment: What would happen if, at the start of <em>every</em> episode or moment that I found myself in, I would consciously and explicitly remind myself to be fully and exclusively in that moment, to focus on the now. I could only agree that this was an intriguing question, and one worth attempting to answer.
  </p>
<p>
    The hardest part was remembering to do this every time. However, once I managed to get past that hurdle, the seemingly simple and low-level act of sub-vocally reminding myself to dedicate my undivided attention to the moment currently at hand resulted in more and more sustained periods of focus, which gave each situation, even the seemingly straightforward ones and especially those involving social contact, significantly more depth. It was almost like flipping a big bass boost button on my daily experiences, with all primary and secondary senses arriving in glorious multi-dimensional technicolour.
  </p>
<p>
    If your brain is like mine, constantly shooting off in five different tangents at the smallest instigation, I can only recommend this self-reminder trick. There are other times when such tangents are useful and should be stimulated, for example during planning or creative sessions, but more often being fully in the now is what you should go for. This goes diametrically against the grain of our evolved <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Information_foraging" title="wikipedia on information foraging">information foraging</a> compulsion and the associated multi-tasking (that we turn out to be really bad at), but is worth the mental effort many times over.
  </p>
<p>
    I’ll end this short post with a musical conclusion:
  </p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1GLIoUtWHcY?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>
<em>Drown in the now…</em> A beautiful and apt title for a song with some of the most spacy lyrics you’ll come across, at least until the next time you do some Crystal Method.
  </p>
<p>
    Kids, have an awesome week, filled with pure Now.
  </p>
<p>
    p.s. Jorik, in an uncontrollable attack of the WABs, just pointed out a spelling mistake in this post. It’s <em>portentous,</em> and <strong>not</strong> <em>portentious.</em> :)
  </p>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>I like nano-sabbaticals. [Weekly Head Voices #39]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/26/i-like-nano-sabbaticals-weekly-head-voices-39/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Feb 2011 17:27:08 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/26/i-like-nano-sabbaticals-weekly-head-voices-39/</guid><description>This past week I was away from work, doing a nano-sabbatical in my secret lair. Example of some random evil lair. Mine is exactly the same, except that it's not in a hollowed-out volcano, doesn't have my face on the outside and is not near the sea.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This past week I was away from work, doing a nano-sabbatical in my secret lair.









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_lair_landscape.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_lair_landscape.png"
        
            alt="Example of some random evil lair. Mine is exactly the same, except that it&#39;s not in a hollowed-out volcano, doesn&#39;t have my face on the outside and is not near the sea."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Example of some random evil lair. Mine is exactly the same, except that it's not in a hollowed-out volcano, doesn't have my face on the outside and is not near the sea.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I thought I was being original by dubbing my week-long self-imposed working isolation a nano-sabbatical, but [google knows better][1]. It turns out other people call their week-long sabbaticals <em>nano</em> too.  Durn. In any case, as you will recall I also went away on a [month-long micro-sabbatical in 2009][2], but this time I wanted to experiment with spending almost a whole work-week focusing on a single task, trying to finish a [survey article][3] I’ve been working on for almost two years. The week is now over and the article is not ready for submission yet, but it <em>has</em> become a completely different and much improved animal during the past week. I’m a happier person too!</p>
<p>I would like to share with you some of the high-level conclusions I’ve drawn from this experiment:</p>
<ul>
<li>Over the past years, I’ve had to get used to multi-tasking. Switching to focus mode was quite a challenge, as my reflex is to switch, switch and switch. Judicious application of [pomodori][4], killing of browser windows and general self talkings-to mostly helped. I have it mostly under control, but I’m sure I could push up my effectivity further with more practice.</li>
<li>I did manage to work quite efficiently from day one, but only by the end of the second day did I find myself in the right <em>frame of mind</em> for writing this kind of paper. It’s one of those cases where you can work really hard, but if you’re not in the right frame of mind, you’re not being effective.</li>
<li>At the beginning of the week, I had configured a vacation email auto-reply, keeping the exact reason for my absence vague. The idea is that I would act as if I were on vacation, that is not responding to email and not taking care of any other work-related issues. Still, I couldn’t help taking care of the bare minimum of important matters, which acted as an extra distraction. I think for any sabbatical, nano to mega, it’s important where exactly you draw the line. During my 2009 sabbatical, I had the strict rule that I could only do normal work-related things during the evenings, which worked quite well.</li>
<li>By the end of the week I was completely embroiled in interesting article-related issues, with very little else interrupting my concentration. It was refreshing having almost all thought-processes dealing with one topic, instead of bouncing between too many concurrent projects.</li>
<li>I truly love the process of writing, even if it is scientific writing, which requires a different attitude regarding the structuring of one’s text and the willingness to rewrite a piece of text as many times as it’s required to get it <em>exactly</em> right. There’s nothing like looking at a single short sentence that concisely communicates the thought <em>just so</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>On the nerd front (skip to the next paragraph if you’re feeling non-nerdy): eclipse, texlipse, mercurial, jabref and dropbox make for a beautiful LaTeX editing workflow, on Linux and Windows machines. There’s nothing like continuous LaTeX builds for the gainful utilisation of the idle and overpowered CPUs in your workstation or laptop.</em></p>
<p>There will definitely be more weeks like this one just past, and perhaps even a real sabbatical in the not-too-distant future. It is unfortunate that multi-tasking has become so <em>de rigueur</em> in modern life. There is a whole lot to be said for the zen of pouring oneself into just that one important thing.</p>
<p>[1]: <a href="http://www.google.nl/search?sourceid=chrome&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=nano-sabbatical#sclient=psy&amp;hl=en&amp;source=hp&amp;q=%22nano-sabbatical%22&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=&amp;aql=&amp;oq=&amp;pbx=1&amp;fp=368f0808b1fe00fa">http://www.google.nl/search?sourceid=chrome&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=nano-sabbatical#sclient=psy&amp;hl=en&amp;source=hp&amp;q=%22nano-sabbatical%22&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=&amp;aql=&amp;oq=&amp;pbx=1&amp;fp=368f0808b1fe00fa</a> &ldquo;link to google search for &ldquo;nano-sabbatical&rdquo;&rdquo;
[2]: /2009/04/25/my-first-sabbatical/ &ldquo;My First Sabbatical&rdquo;
[3]: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survey_article">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Survey_article</a> &ldquo;wikipedia definition of survey article&rdquo;
[4]: /2010/09/20/an-indecent-proposal-weekly-head-voices-31/ &ldquo;one of my pomodori posts&rdquo;</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>