<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>helderberg on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/helderberg/</link><description>Recent content in helderberg on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 10:06:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/helderberg/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #203: Spiritual</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 10:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</guid><description> Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&amp;rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&amp;rsquo;s magic.
Dear friends,
It brings me joy to meet you here again.
Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10 to Sunday September 6, 2020.
If I were in your shoes, I would hop skip and jump selectively over the hopefully not too unhelpfully titled headings.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="jonkershoek_magic_20200901.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&amp;rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&amp;rsquo;s magic."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&rsquo;s magic.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>It brings me joy to meet you here again.</p>
<p>Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will
attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10
to Sunday September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>If I were in your shoes, I would hop skip and jump selectively over the
hopefully not too unhelpfully titled headings.</p>
<p>In order to reduce this wall of text somewhat, I have pre-emptively moved a
sub-section or two to the next edition of the WHV.</p>
<p><em>Dear Charl of the Future,</em></p>
<p><em>You have no choice. (also no free will haha) I am writing this for you, so you
better read every last bit.</em></p>
<p><em>I am watching you.</em> 👀</p>
<h2 id="i-m-sorry-but-it-really-is-just-quite-complicated">I&rsquo;m sorry, but it really is just quite complicated</h2>
<p>I would like to kick this off with the following cartoon by Wiley Miller, which
entered my information field of view via dr topol&rsquo;s tweet stream. (don&rsquo;t worry,
this came in via my rss reader. i have not returned to twitter.)</p>








<figure><a href="science_vs_everything_else.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It is ironic that the people who get it, already got it, but that the people who
really should get it, won&rsquo;t get it.</p>
<p>As is the case with many of these efforts, i guess that the best we can hope
for is that some of those on the borders between the aforementioned two groups
might be gently encouraged to gravitate towards the light.</p>
<h3 id="the-giant-band-aid-phenomenon">the giant band-aid phenomenon</h3>
<p>Related to the cartoon above, it is quite interesting to me how often
well-meaning people desire to come up with a giant band-aid for any current
problem.</p>
<p>Climate change? Inequality? Surely if we just find a band-aid big
enough we can make the problem go away!</p>
<p>There really is no band-aid.</p>
<h2 id="on-the-minimum-unit-of-focus">On the minimum unit of focus</h2>
<p>Somewhere in week 34 i was struggling to wrap up a piece of programming work
that i had been struggling with for a few days, in-between meetings and a whole
smorgasbord of other modern interruptions.</p>
<p>Finally i decided to bust out the little focus tool that i shall not name here,
because that&rsquo;s not the point.</p>
<p>The point is rather that i created an interruption-free block of time and then
wrapped up the stupid programming problem decisively, there and then.</p>
<p>Relieved that it was finally done, I did feel stupid that it had taken me that
long to just shut off those damn interruptions.</p>
<p>The experience did remind me of the following cartoon by <a href="https://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/">the slightly
disgruntled scientist</a>. It describes <strong>extremely</strong> well how a single little
interruption can derail a whole constellation of mental models in an instant.</p>
<p>Click or tap to zoom in, or skip past if you know this:</p>








<figure><a href="ProgrammerInterrupted.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted_hu3267a53534c5d7f823d13c1b76e71025_414884_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted.png"
            

         width="30%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>I have found that the absolute minimum block of distraction-free time i need to
do reliably something worthwhile is about an hour.</p>
<p>A large part of my job is indeed handling the information that arrives via all
of the those pesky interruptions, but sometimes i wonder if there&rsquo;s not a
better way to reconcile these two facets.</p>
<p>Very much related to this phenomenon, is falling into the morning distraction
trap, something which is probably familiar to a number of you. (future charl,
you don&rsquo;t count.)</p>
<p>It goes like this: i arrive at work (or these days, i walk a few metres on from
the kitchen into the guest bedroom / home office), and then i start the day
with meetings, microsoft teams chats, and emails.</p>
<p>If I&rsquo;m not careful, I get stuck in this reactive mode, forgetting until far too
late in the day to eject from the reactive-jet for some of them juicy focus
hours.</p>
<p>#feelsbadman</p>
<p>Just this past week, I decided on Thursday and Friday to start work directly on
my main project, ignoring emails and chats and any other distractions until the
first stand-up meeting at 9:00.</p>
<p>Just priming my mind like this for slightly more than an hour was enough to
give the whole day a flavour of focus and intentionality.</p>
<p>It feels like I forget this lesson every other day.</p>
<p>How do you manage this?</p>
<h2 id="on-the-opposite-of-focus">On the opposite of focus</h2>
<p>Sort of inspired by <a href="https://youtu.be/0m3hGZvD-0s">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s deliberate scheduling of a shallow work
session</a> after the day&rsquo;s deep work, I was pleasantly surprised during a past few
evening sessions where I combined an entertaining DJ Set on the second screen
with some actual programming work on the main.</p>
<p>Somehow the fully intentional addition of distracting entertainment, and
importantly the <em>acceptance</em> that the work would necessarily be approached with
a leisurely attitude, I got a surprising amount of extra work done, and
experienced the whole session as relaxing.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to file this under &ldquo;101 stupid but effective tricks to fool your mind
into being more useful&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Let me know if you try this, or if you knew this all along and <em>that&rsquo;s</em> how you
manage everything so well!</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://lexfridman.com/podcast/">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s podcasts</a> are edifying and humanity-affirming. Try them if
you haven&rsquo;t yet.</p>
<h2 id="on-divide-and-conquer-for-the-email">On divide and conquer for the email</h2>
<p>Spontaneously in the night somewhere during the past weeks, I had the idea that
it was time to split my <a href="https://www.stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> work email account from the rest of my
email empire (which is partially also work, because vxlabs, but not my main
job).</p>
<p>I did this because the account I use to manage everything, the <a href="/tags/fastmail/">fastmail one</a>,
was becoming far too chaotic.</p>
<p>(Back in the TU Delft days, an adventure that ended now almost 7 years ago, I
also used to sport an e-mail split.)</p>
<p>My perception now is that I&rsquo;m working against the idea of the whole being
greater than the sum of the parts, i.e. the whole chaos is perhaps worse than
the two smaller chaos explosions by themselves.</p>
<p>(That&rsquo;s a pretty convoluted way to think about &ldquo;divide and conquer&rdquo;, isn&rsquo;t it?)</p>
<p>Also, the dream of being able to search through all of my email and actually
finding stuff is not being realised.</p>
<p>Email searching these days is usually a last resort, because I have a pretty
good <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">personal knowledge management system</a>. It could also be that fastmail
search is not as clever as gmail search.</p>
<p>In the weeks since I did this split (my notes tell me this happened on Friday,
August 21, 2020 at around 8:30 in the morning), I have noticed that my Stone
Three email is now under control, while my personal email is slightly out of
control, which is an improvement.</p>
<p>I have noticed that I do in fact apply a whole different mode of cognition and
context to the handling of work email than I do to personal/work-ish email.</p>
<p>A further advantage is that I can now focus on mastering the way of life that
is called Outlook. The first artifact I have to show for this is a pretty
complicated blog post in the drafts folder that shows how you can link to
arbitrary outlook items (in the latest outlook) from anywhere, in my case of
course Emacs.</p>
<h2 id="life-progress-update">Life progress update</h2>
<p>During the past several weeks, I passed a birthday.</p>
<p>As one bestie remarked, I am now just past the halfway mark, at least by one
pretty optimistic estimate of the total duration of me.</p>
<p>Anyways, moving on&hellip;</p>
<p>I took the largest part of the day off to go run the in the mountains here in my
backyard.</p>
<p>The route that I took for the first time, and which caused a considerable
amount of enjoyment, could be described by Watsonia, Baboon traverse, Leopard
Loop, Caracal, Protea, Sugarbird.</p>
<p>Making time for outdoorsy activities on your birthday: Two WHV thumbs up, would
do again.</p>
<p>Thanks to the <a href="http://www.workoutdoors.net/">WorkOutDoors Apple Watch app</a>, which I bought two years ago but
have never used, I did not get lost like I usually do when attempting trail
runs.</p>
<p>The app displays brilliant vector maps on your watch, optionally overlaid with
GPX routes supplied by generous friends.</p>
<p>After the birthday run, I use it again on more trails (see photo at start of
post) to run almost like someone who actually possesses a sense of
direction.</p>
<p>Technological augmentation FTW!</p>
<h2 id="here-s-to-a-more-regular-return">Here&rsquo;s to a more regular return</h2>
<p>Thank you for working through this mishmash with me!</p>
<p>We are now caught up until Sunday, September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>At this stage, I would have preferred to post more coherent little posts more
often, but I seem to find myself in a loop of slightly too much busyness (and
other issues), which ironically is contributing to my need to write more, but
which is taking up so much time and so many mental cycles that blog-writing
opportunities are hard to create and make use of.</p>
<p>Anyways&hellip; at least the overfull post-pipeline fence has now been cleared.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you equanimity, kindness and health.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next connection.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #186: Helderberg 20.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 16:08:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/</guid><description> Friends, it is with great pleasure that I welcome you back here to the Weekly Head Voices!
The passing of time usually seems to be quite a theoretical affair, but at this moment I can really feel the year taking its last few breaths.
(People even seem to think of this as the last year of the decade, which makes it all the more dramatic, but not everyone is convinced. If the first day of the first year was January 1, year 1, the end of the first year was December 31, year 1, and the end of that first decade was on December 31, year 10.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Friends, it is with great pleasure that I welcome you back here to the Weekly
Head Voices!</p>
<p>The passing of time usually seems to be quite a theoretical affair, but at this
moment I can really feel the year taking its last few breaths.</p>
<p>(People even seem to think of this as the last year of the decade, which makes
it all the more dramatic, but <a href="https://www.withum.com/resources/end-of-the-decade/">not everyone is
convinced</a>. If the first
day of the first year was January 1, year 1, the end of the first year was
December 31, year 1, and the end of that first decade was on December 31,
year 10. By this reasoning, the end of the current decade is still more than a
year away, on December 31, 2020. Yes, the calendar has changed drastically over the years, but the principle of when decades start and end is the same.)</p>
<p>Anyways, one thing I am only slightly more sure about is that this edition of
the WHV Monday looks back on the days from Monday December 9 to Sunday December
15, 2019!</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/im_on_a_goat_hu980e3d28ebd8f0404c770613f1ce21d8_2899568_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
<p>There&rsquo;s a buck (a sort of goat), probably of the duiker variety, really showing
off its camouflage on one of the ledges in this photo taken along the West Peak
/ Woody&rsquo;s Walk route on Helderberg mountain. See if you can find it!</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="we-are-load-shedding-again">We are load shedding again.</h2>
<p>So yeah, there&rsquo;s that.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re load shedding again.</p>
<p>Everything I wrote &ldquo;<a href="/2019/03/24/weekly-head-voices-166-morgan-bay/#on-being-powerless">on being
powerless</a>&rdquo;
in March of this year is again happening, down to me spending more time on
Twitter again (DANG IT) searching for voices that might indicate justice
eventually being served.</p>
<p>In spite of the fact that our home is now more or less load-shedding-proof due
to it being for the largest part <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">solar
powered</a> this time
around, the rotating power outages (we had a week or two of stage 4, i.e. 3 x
2.5 hour outages per day, and one evening of escalation to stage 6) are an
upsetting reminder of the decades-long and now continuing incompetence and
corruption of the country&rsquo;s leadership.</p>
<p>Apart from the numerous mental cycles this phenomenon has been <em>stealing</em> (see
what I did there) from my work focus, it is hard not to notice how businesses,
colleagues and friends are being hit by this.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s perhaps new this time, is that <a href="https://www.timeslive.co.za/politics/2019-10-29-eskom-board-member-slams-interference-says-there-should-be-load-shedding/">it has been confirmed by an Eskom board
member</a>
that the same politicians who have caused this mess, are <em>still</em> meddling in
technical affairs they have no idea about, for all of the wrong reasons.</p>
<p>To put it quite bluntly, instead of trying to address the almost insurmountable
technical problems at the electricity supplier, it seems that the ruling party
(the ANC of course) for example insisted that the electricity be kept on at all
costs during the elections.</p>
<p>Numerous incidences of this sort of interference helped them to save face over
the years, at the cost of further debilitating the already fragile South
African economy.</p>
<p>At this moment, as large parts of industry are shutting down for the Christmas
period, we are enjoying a respite from load shedding.</p>
<p>We will see what happens in the new year.</p>
<p>The board member quoted above stated that if meddling had not been such a
concern, and they could face the technical problems head-on, we were looking at
at least 8 months of load shedding.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m sure that the people would be able to deal with it if those cards were
simply laid on the table, without all of the political meddling and backroom
dealings.</p>
<p>As was the case the previous time, I do remain hopeful that the number of
spines in power grows, and that the electricity provider is able to focus all
of its energy on addressing the significant problems that it faces.</p>
<h2 id="time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">Time-restricted Eating (TRE) with Black Coffee please.</h2>
<p>I think it was Reader K who introduced me to the idea of time-restricted
eating, or TRE, a year or two ago.</p>
<p>(Together we tried to figure out on which medium this happened, because under
normal circumstances I would have wanted to look up the exact time and contents
of the messages.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, we discovered that it must have been via Facebook Messenger, and
somewhere between then and now Reader K had expunged their whole Facebook
history.</p>
<p>I think there&rsquo;s a lesson in here somewhere, but we have to forge ahead, so
we&rsquo;re going to have to side-step it.)</p>
<p>Time-restricted eating, or TRE, is a sort of intermittent fasting where the
eating window is deliberately limited to an as short as possible duration
during the daytime.</p>
<p>The theory behind it is that our metabolism is in fact also ruled by the
all-powerful circadian clock.</p>
<p>During our long evolution, we would have been foraging and feeding during
daylight, and resting during the night.</p>
<p>With artificial light and the ubiquitousness of food of modern times, we easily
fall into the habit of starting to eat when we wake up, and having the last
snack shortly before going to sleep, hours after sunset.</p>
<p>In short, we really do eat too much, and to make it even worse, we eat at all
the wrong times.</p>
<p>With research around TRE, science, as is its wont, is showing us the way back
to redemption.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s starting to look like limiting one&rsquo;s feeding window to a few hours during
daylight could have a number of health advantages.</p>
<p>See for example:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4255155/">Time-restricted feeding is a preventative and therapeutic intervention
against diverse nutritional
challenges</a> - a 2014
Cell Biology study with mice.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2019/12/191205141731.htm">Clinical study finds eating within 10-hour window may help stave off
diabetes, heart
disease</a> - a 2019 Science Daily summary.</li>
<li><a href="https://m2performancenutrition.com/blog/can-time-restricted-feeding-make-you-fitter">Can time restricted feeding make you
fitter</a> -
a reasonable overview.</li>
</ul>
<p>After a debate with friend LM about whether black sugarless coffee constituted
a break of the TRE fast (I thought that it did due to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m6KClPkotxM">this conversation
between Rhonda Patrick and Joe
Rogan</a>, friend LM did not, so I
initially did not even try TRE because I am unable to operate without black
coffee in the mornings), I have been dipping my toes in the TRE pool.</p>
<p>I have never been a breakfast person (&ldquo;Breakfast is the most important meal of
the day&rdquo; ??! TRUST NO ONE.), so sticking to black coffee in the mornings until
as late as possible, which is in many cases lunch, and not eating anything
after dark, has subjectively worked out pretty well so far.</p>
<p>Sometimes, shortly before lunch, there seems to be a slight delusional quality
to my seemingly enhanced mental clarity, but let&rsquo;s keep that between you and
me.</p>
<h2 id="anniversary-walk-up-the-mountain">Anniversary walk up the mountain.</h2>
<p>Recently, my life partner and I celebrated two decades of official
togetherness by walking up the Helderberg mountain.</p>
<p>We did not quite make West Peak, and we were pretty bushed by the end, but
that&rsquo;s ok. The scenery was epic, and getting back home was brilliant.</p>
<p>We will try again in 2029.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/helderberg_pano_huc4bb1951375ad5886434a63b8e273f0b_2731244_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
<p>All by itself, Google&rsquo;s AI stitched together a bunch of my photos of the
Helderberg hike to make this lovely panorama. It&rsquo;s better than the panorama I
made by myself, so I&rsquo;m giving you this one. Click for higher resolution.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #102: High on life.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/20/weekly-head-voices-102-high-on-life/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 07:21:17 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/20/weekly-head-voices-102-high-on-life/</guid><description> The week of Monday January 11 to Sunday January 17, 2016 got off to a brilliant start with a business lunch at Bodega, a restaurant that finds itself on the Dornier Wine Estate. The view looked something like this:
… and the company was suitably awesome. (This is not the first time that Bodega makes its appearance on this blog, or in the blog-free suburbs of my social calendar. The company might be different every time, but so far its level of awesomeness has been quite consistent.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The week of Monday January 11 to Sunday January 17, 2016 got off to a brilliant start with a <em>business</em> lunch at <a href="http://www.dornier.co.za/restaurant">Bodega</a>, a restaurant that finds itself on the Dornier Wine Estate. The view looked something like this:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/view_from_bodega.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/view_from_bodega-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>… and the company was suitably awesome. (This is not the first time that Bodega makes its appearance on this blog, or in the blog-free suburbs of my social calendar. The company might be different every time, but so far its level of awesomeness has been <em>quite</em> consistent.)</p>
<p>The rest of the (work) week was consumed by extreme nerdery, which is of course the way I love it. Besides more GPU shader fine-tuning (at least once I exclaimed on the <a href="http://www.stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> HipChat, hopefully soon the Stone Three <a href="http://www.mattermost.org/">Mattermost</a>,  <em>WITNESS THE POWER OF MATH!</em>, before showing a rendering that was marginally better than the one where the POWER OF MATH had not yet been invoked a sufficient number of times), there was Javascript, <a href="http://d3js.org/">d3.js</a> (d3 is another fantastic example of what you can do with vectorised thinking and computation) and Python.</p>
<p>In break time I finally took a closer look at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C%2B%2B14">C++14</a> and beyond and came away super impressed. There’s a blog post in the pipeline on generic lambda expressions, because I think they’re brilliant. I don’t know why I love different programming languages so much, but I do.</p>
<p>On Saturday,  I got really high with one of my besties, a superb gentleman who also goes by the name of A Very Flat Cat. We reached this altered state by the old-fashioned but extremely reliable (and cheap!) method of physically increasing our altitude via ambulation up the west peak of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helderberg">Helderberg</a>. The walk (a few hours in 35 degrees Celsius…) was exhilarating, and the view from the top awe-inspiring. Check it (click for high-res):</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/20160116_100314-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/20160116_100314-PANO-1024x137.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I’ve often wondered about the effect of one’s surroundings on one’s mindfulness. This was one of those cases where mother nature, without asking for permission or anything like that, simply brute-forced the <em>being</em> switch with her astonishing beauty. Very grateful I was.</p>
<p>Have a great week friends, see you on the other side!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Back in South Africa</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 10:29:50 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/</guid><description> (I was supposed to publish this around the start of February, but then life happened, and I didn’t get to quite finish it.)
For the first time in the three weeks after having arrived back on South African soil, we find ourselves in something that we’re going to call home for the coming months. Until now we have been living out of our suitcases, spending time with various grandpas and grandmas somewhere in the Boerewors Gordyn (the Northern ‘burbs of Cape Town, to those of you not in the know), The Oven (I just made that up.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(I was supposed to publish this around the start of February, but then life happened, and I didn’t get to quite finish it.)</em></p>
<p>For the first time in the three weeks after having arrived back on South African soil, we find ourselves in something that we’re going to call home for the coming months. Until now we have been living out of our suitcases, spending time with various grandpas and grandmas somewhere in the Boerewors Gordyn (the Northern ‘burbs of Cape Town, to those of you not in the know), The Oven (I just made that up. It’s Paarl, the town where I grew up thinking that 40 Celsius was a normal temperature to be wearing a blazer and a tie. 40 Celsius is now my preferred outside temperature.) and in Betty’s Bay (that’s its real name. It’s really cute that way. Look at me walking the thin line of apostrophe (ab)use.) We’ve been doing our fair share of early-to-bed-early-to-rise makes John cranky and not very wise, because Genetic Offspring Unit #1 had to be taken to school in our current town of residence, from our at that point temporary residence.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/taking_a_walk_bbay.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/taking_a_walk_bbay-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="So you’re really planning to publish that blog post, but then you take a walk instead. TISA."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>So you’re really planning to publish that blog post, but then you take a walk instead. TISA.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>At the moment I’m sitting in our new home behind an extremely shaky cellular data connection (the house is like the Bermuda triangle of mobile reception. Even in this carefully chosen spot the signal dances a really silly tap dance between H, 3G and EDGE. EDGE is NOT nice, trust me. I think EDGE is actually a synonym for “no connection at all, but we just like to make you think that there has to be something”. At some vague point in the future, ADSL will hopefully be installed. Africa does not care about the timeliness of your internet connection, deal with it.).</p>
<p>So we have our suitcases, and a whole bunch of borrowed items until Our Ship Comes In. No really, we have a ship that’s coming in with all of our old stuff on it. Until that moment, we have a special place where meat can be scorched, also in a social context. This is quite grand.</p>
<p>There is also a mountain in my backyard which I can’t help gawking at whenever I return home. The mountain is majestic, and that is even more grand than the place where you can scorch your meat. I have promised myself to retain and cultivate my awe at this mountain, and at all the mind-blowing natural majesty surrounding me wherever I go in this place, for as long as I can.</p>
<p>See you later everyone!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>