<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Utrecht on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/utrecht/</link><description>Recent content in Utrecht on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 09:11:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/utrecht/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #175: Plaintext me.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 09:11:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/</guid><description>Good evening fellow humans.
This is Head Voice #37 reporting for duty. I have been instructed to perform retrospection on the period of time from Monday July 22 to Sunday July 28.
Due to the ongoing hibernation and consequent lack of interesting events to talk about, this should be short.
This delectable Fred &amp; Max Flat White was one of a quite few more enjoyed during life-affirming breakfast with a Very Flat Cat. (By the way, why didn't any of you tell me that fried egg yolk slowly drenching the quinoa bed it lies on is so amazing?!) I&amp;rsquo;m stubbornly doubling down on plaintext email. I spent a precious hour or two (or perhaps three, in which case I am ashamed) performing experiments to try and understand how GMail, fastmail web, thunderbird and the iOS mail.app encode quoting in HTML email replies.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Good evening fellow humans.</p>
<p>This is Head Voice #37 reporting for duty. I have been instructed to perform
retrospection on the period of time from Monday July 22 to Sunday July 28.</p>
<p>Due to the ongoing hibernation and consequent lack of interesting events to
talk about, this should be short.</p>
<figure>
<a href="fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hu_2e802987491c2189.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hu_3111ad2b659804b5.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hu_2f6fa6a9eb12ae78.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hu_f75fe072bdd3618a.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hu_3111ad2b659804b5.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
This delectable Fred & Max Flat White was one of a quite few more enjoyed
during life-affirming breakfast with a Very Flat Cat. (By the way, why didn't
any of you tell me that fried egg yolk slowly drenching the quinoa bed it lies
on is so amazing?!)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="im-stubbornly-doubling-down-on-plaintext-email">I&rsquo;m stubbornly doubling down on plaintext email.</h2>
<p>I spent a precious hour or two (or perhaps three, in which case I am ashamed)
performing experiments to try and understand how GMail, fastmail web,
thunderbird and the iOS mail.app encode quoting in HTML email replies.</p>
<p>The answer is that they all do it in subtly different ways&hellip;</p>
<p>The even more shocking answer is that since HTML email took over, people have
really just been winging it, and quite badly so.</p>
<p>To give you an idea, gmail adds explicit inline CSS <em>styling</em> to display the
vertical reply bar on the left, like some kind of <em>barbarian</em>.</p>
<p>WAT?!</p>
<p>Back when plaintext email was the only game in town, there were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Posting_style">fairly strict
but effective guidelines</a> that
determined exactly how one could quote previous emails, up to any depth, when
crafting that thoughtful reply.</p>
<p>However, it seems that, thanks to Outlook and perhaps far more insidiously
Google&rsquo;s GMail, <em>many</em> people currently have no idea that a thing such as email
quoting with inline replies used to be a solved problem.</p>
<p>That is, until users mistakenly thought that badly chosen fonts with even more
badly chosen colours were more important than, you know, effective and
efficient written communication.</p>
<p>Although this battle is lost, this has only encouraged me to stick it to the
(HTML email) man, and double-down on my old-school plaintext emails.</p>
<p>If you receive a simple-looking email from me which sometimes wraps strangely,
you&rsquo;ll know why.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;d like join me, the new
<a href="https://useplaintext.email/">useplaintext.email</a> site is a good start!</p>
<h2 id="linux-on-the-thinkpad">Linux on the ThinkPad.</h2>
<p>I <em>thought</em> that the NVIDIA GPU being hard-wired to the external display
outputs on this <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad</a> meant that I would
never be able to run Linux with <em>dynamic</em> display connection.</p>
<p>Well it turns out I was wrong.</p>
<p>I slipped this weekend, and now the Linux partition is configured with Manjaro
Linux (a surprise to me too).</p>
<p>In short, ThinkPad consumes just over 5W at idle, because NVIDIA is only
switched on when necessary. I can switch it on for CUDA (for example to work
with neural networks that fit into the 4GB of VRAM), and I can switch it on
when I need to connect an external display.</p>
<p>All of this without having to reboot or even logout and back in again.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested, see the <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/28/manjaro-bumblebee-thinkpad-x1-extreme-2019/">vxlabs blog
post</a>
for all of the details.</p>
<h2 id="we-live-in-the-future">We live in the future.</h2>
<p>At the UMC Utrecht, two patients have received entirely patient-specific
3D-printed titanium spinal implants.</p>
<p>Thanks to this, the patients, one of whose spine had previously collapsed, are
still able to walk.</p>
<p>Read more in <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/news/2019/07/teenager-can-walk-again-thanks-to-dutch-3d-printed-spinal-implant/">this DutchNews
summary</a>,
or preferably <a href="https://www.volkskrant.nl/wetenschap/implantaten-uit-de-3d-printer-laten-utrechtse-patient-weer-lopen~bab3372e/">this Volkskrant
article</a>
if you can follow Dutch.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve embedded the Lancet video abstract for your convenience:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315"
src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3gxiDo3ac0k" frameborder="0"
allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>This used to be the stuff of science fiction folks!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>