<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Practice on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/practice/</link><description>Recent content in Practice on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 19:38:35 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/practice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #245: This too shall pass</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 20:18:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/</guid><description>WELL HELLO EVERYONE and welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices, edition #245 to be specific, looking back at the period of time from Monday July 25 to Sunday Aug 7, 2022.
Figure 1: Scene from a walk after a delicious family Sunday lunch.
In the spirit of full disclosure, I do seem to be going through a patch of mostly pretty &amp;ldquo;meh&amp;rdquo; WHV attempts.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>WELL HELLO EVERYONE and welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices, edition #245 to
be specific, looking back at the period of time from Monday July 25 to Sunday
Aug 7, 2022.</p>










<figure><a href="vergelegen-peekaboo.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_6485fe595a71baa1.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_1b86f2c5acf415fc.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_f00fcd5217c38b3e.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_a041747863e6b183.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/vergelegen-peekaboo_hu_1b86f2c5acf415fc.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a walk after a delicious family Sunday lunch."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Scene from a walk after a delicious family Sunday lunch.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In the spirit of full disclosure, I do seem to be going through a patch of
mostly pretty &ldquo;meh&rdquo; WHV attempts.</p>
<p>However, as they say, a badly written but <em>published</em> blog post is miles better
than an unpublished blog post of <em>any</em> quality.</p>
<p>Also, one day when I finally reach <a href="/2017/06/11/weekly-head-voices-122/">the A-list</a> you&rsquo;ll be able to say that you
were already reading my stuff before it was cool.</p>
<p>More seriously though, the whole of <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">life is continuous practice</a>, which can
include long stretches of rolling hills of meh.</p>
<p>(see also <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">WHV #144&rsquo;s section on Mastery</a>)</p>
<h2 id="nerdy-bits">Nerdy bits</h2>
<h3 id="postel-s-law-and-iso-8601-date-and-time-formatting">Postel&rsquo;s law and ISO 8601 date and time formatting</h3>
<p>This movie is based on a true story that happened at work.</p>
<p>I published a short org-roam note to my nerd blog. You can read it here:
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/08/05/conservative-rendering-and-liberal-parsing-of-iso-8601-timestamps-in-python/">Conservative rendering and liberal parsing of ISO 8601 timestamps in Python</a></p>
<h3 id="replacing-ddw-with-rd-on-windows-for--wsl--devcontainers">Replacing DDW with RD on Windows for (WSL) devcontainers</h3>
<p>I have replaced Docker Desktop for Windows with <a href="https://rancherdesktop.io/">Rancher Desktop</a>, with the
dockerd runtime, on two of my Windows development machines.</p>
<p>Although you have to create some WSL symlinks manually, configure RD&rsquo;s
<code>docker-credential-wincred.exe</code> (if you&rsquo;re using private container registries)
and manually install zsh completions, the end-result is a great and
fully-functional replacement for my use-case of <a href="https://containers.dev/">devcontainers</a> everywhere.</p>
<p>Please let me know if you need more detail about the RD config.</p>
<p>P.S. It might come as a shock to some readers, not to mention me of 10 years
ago, that I have not only one, but two Windows workstations. My excuse is:
&ldquo;adaptation&rdquo;.</p>
<p>P.P.S. There will soon be three of them.</p>
<h3 id="notes-on-locally-upgrading-the-firmware-of-the-gw5048d-es-inverter">Notes on locally upgrading the firmware of the GW5048D-ES inverter</h3>
<p>There is a Goodwe GW5048D-ES 4.6 kVA inverter at the heart of the solar system powering my house.</p>
<p>I love it, because it&rsquo;s reliable, and just does the work 99.7% of the time.</p>
<p>However, because that 0.3% manifested recently (settings were partially
scrambled, resulting in a few minutes of darkness during a load shedding
session; could have been the Home Assistant Goodwe integration; more acutely,
its wifi access point, needed for configuration, recently disappeared) and the
OTA firmware I requested via Goodwe support failed, probably due to firmware
being a bit old already, I had to attempt a local firmware upgrade, with a USB
cable, like <a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">I last did three years ago</a> (rocky road then).</p>
<p>Well, although my inverter is now sporting firmware version 2424G, the upgrade
definitety went on roads of the more rocky variety.</p>
<p>Here are some tips to help you if you&rsquo;re in the same boat:</p>
<ul>
<li>Follow the instructions to the letter:
<ul>
<li>Remove all power sources except for a single DC source. I disconnected grid
and solar panels, keeping only the batteries connected which were close to
full.</li>
<li>Remove the wifi module: 4 screws, and then carefully remove the plastic
connector.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Get a straight USB-A male to USB-A male cable. None of my USB-C to USB-A
cables, or my various Frankensteined extensions, could connect (as reported
by EzFlash.</li>
</ul>
<p>In my case, the EzFlash upgrade worked (two bin files), but then right after
that the DataSend failed.</p>
<p>I retried DataSend multiple times, but finally lost connection to the
inverter&rsquo;s USB port.</p>
<p>After I put everything back together (having resolved to contact support to
help troubleshoot), the inverter&rsquo;s access point magically appeared, at which
point I could connect to see that everything was functioning, and inverter
reported firmware version as 2424G.</p>
<p>I did contact Goodwe to ask about the implications of DataSend
failing. Although I&rsquo;m happy with their service, I would have appreciated a bit
more detail.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve summarised our email thread below:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I asked: &ldquo;When I did the upgrade, the DataSend file did not go through at
all. Could you help me understand how the upgrade is OK if I only did the
EzFlash stage, and NOT the DataSend phase?&rdquo;</p>
<p>They answered: &ldquo;Do note that the datasend file is only for use when updating
the Armware. When updating firmware its only the EZflash and master bin file
that is use.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Then I asked: &ldquo;What is the Armware for then? Why is it not necessary to upgrade
it, although the upgrade manual gives instructions to upgrade it?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Upon which they replied: &ldquo;You ARM is already updated that is why i advised not
to worry about it. There isn&rsquo;t anything technical that i can share on this. The
arm as we know normally works with communication with the batteries.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="school-s-anti-wikipedia-stance-leads-to-lessons-and-pi-hole">School&rsquo;s anti-wikipedia stance leads to lessons and Pi-hole</h2>
<p>Last week, GOU #2 tried to print a pretty nasty, infinite-scroll, ad-infested
site with stolen wikipedia content because her school has a far too simplistic
and strict rule <em>against</em> using wikipedia for school work.</p>
<p>I then proceeded to:</p>
<ol>
<li>have a long talk with her about computers not doing what you intend, but
rather exactly what you tell them to,</li>
<li>Do some research and realise to my shock that this anti-wikipedia stance
seems to be a world-wide teacher thing;</li>
<li>Write a long but friendly email to the teacher explaining that it&rsquo;s a lot
more nuanced, and could I please help them to understand the nuances so that
our kids get better at filtering information rather than just blindly
avoiding wikipedia and</li>
<li>At long last get around to installing <a href="https://pi-hole.net/">Pi-hole</a> on this old linux laptop (via
docker-compose) and sending all DNS requests its way (via my main router&rsquo;s
DHCP service), all-in-all quite a painless process!</li>
</ol>
<p>What this means is that all devices in my household (and there&rsquo;s quite a number
of them) get all of their ads blocked automatically.</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_9f33616edd076712.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_2fe147269d2279a1.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_76a38c9e9321d821.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_1b46d164299f7434.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/08/09/weekly-head-voices-245-this-too-shall-pass/images/2022/2022-08-09_14-53-44_screenshot_hu_2fe147269d2279a1.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: The Pi-hole dashboard a few moments ago. The percentage of blocked queries remains around 10%." width="480"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>The Pi-hole dashboard a few moments ago. The percentage of blocked queries remains around 10%.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I should have done this much earlier. There&rsquo;s really no chance I can install
ublock origin or equivalent on each of the growing cloud of devices and
accounts at home. Pi-hole makes 10x more sense.</p>
<h2 id="this-too-shall-pass">This too shall pass</h2>
<p>On Saturday July 30, the date of the final interschools clash between Paarl
Boys&rsquo; High School (my alma mater) and its arch-opponent Paarl Gimnasium, I had
the privilege of attending the 30th (!!) anniversary of my matriculation year,
along with about 50 class mates.</p>
<p>As a bit of context, back then I operated probably at the lowest end of the
popularity scale, mostly because of my personality. Not that it&rsquo;s that
important anymore, but I think that I would probably have irritated myself (in
both ways) to quite an extent.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, I had even <em>less</em> ball sense then than I do now.</p>
<p>In spite of all that, the reunion was a sublime and deeply enjoyable affair.</p>
<p>It was so great connecting again with the human journeyers I had in many cases
last seen right before we would all set off on the start of adulthood.</p>
<p>Back then, we were all bright-eyed, hot-headed, full of plans and with heads
full of luscious hair.</p>
<p>Now there was substantially less hair, many hard lessons learned, but wisdom,
and sometimes peace, in the eyes.</p>
<p>To me it really felt as if everyone there had this collective, positive
realisation of:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You know what?</p>
<p>Everything&rsquo;s OK.</p>
<p>We know better what&rsquo;s truly important, and it&rsquo;s not what we believed back then.</p>
<p>All of this? Let us enjoy it without complication.</p>
<p>Like everything before it, this too shall pass.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps I am over-projecting.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the enjoyment was as real as could be.</p>
<p>Thank you Boys High&rsquo; Class of &lsquo;92!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #230: Follow your blisters</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Aug 2021 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/</guid><description> Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&amp;rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &amp;ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&amp;rdquo; (I didn&amp;rsquo;t and I don&amp;rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="van_breda_cottage_angles.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_b81e281e98679d6a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_1e9bab3660c89449.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_cecd63736e6ae3a2.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_f936d96a4cce0835.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/van_breda_cottage_angles_hu_1e9bab3660c89449.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much)."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>During the West Coast sunset worshipping ritual I turned around and entirely coincidentally saw this picture waiting there for me. (We&rsquo;re sitting off to the left on the stoep.) I love the photo, but then started to wonder if it had a bit too much of &ldquo;I just did a photography course and now I have to make photos like this&rdquo; (I didn&rsquo;t and I don&rsquo;t). My friends have assured me that it does not look like that (too much).</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV covers the three weeks from Monday July 26 to Sunday August 15.</p>
<h2 id="why-i-don-t-like-dark-mode-anymore">Why I don&rsquo;t like dark mode anymore</h2>
<p>As you might know, I spent most of my working (and sometimes hobby, we&rsquo;ll get
back to that further down) hours in front of this screen or some other screen.</p>
<p>Up to now, I was really convinced that I preferred dark mode everywhere, until
recently two events transpired:</p>
<p>I started noticing more eye-strain than usual, even on my 27&quot; screen, something
which had a perceptible effect on my productivity. This I resignedly ascribed
to my advancing age, although I did find the suddenness quite surprising,
especially since I recently had my glasses updated.</p>
<p>Then, after years with only the admittedly brilliant <a href="https://github.com/bbatsov/zenburn-emacs">zenburn</a> and <a href="https://github.com/fniessen/emacs-leuven-theme">Leuven (dark)</a>
Emacs themes checking all of the boxes for me, I finally ran into a really
interesting and usable theme called <a href="https://github.com/kunalb/poet">Poet</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s interesting, because it uses variable pitched fonts for everything but
code, tables and elements of the fixed width domain, where most Emacs fonts
stick to the traditional all-fixed-width approach.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="20210822-poet-theme-screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_61bc38e25939896c.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_741ea773817f7739.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_19248625c7c1a3e8.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_4cb0af8349c12ee4.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/20210822-poet-theme-screenshot_hu_741ea773817f7739.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can probably understand that for someone who uses Emacs almost primarily
for technical notes and other writing, this book-like appearance could work
really well.</p>
<p>The theme was even more interesting for me personally, as it suddenly became
clear as day that I experienced almost no eye-strain when using Emacs with this
lighter theme than when I used any of my other usually dark-themed tools!</p>
<p>It became obvious that poet-theme&rsquo;s lighter background was much easier on my
eyes than dark mode in vscode. (No, this specific advantage can&rsquo;t be ascribed
to Emacs itself I&rsquo;m afraid.)</p>
<p>Reading pages such as <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/digital-eye-strain/is-dark-mode-better-for-eyes/">this</a> explains that dark mode leads to pupils having to
dilate more to let in more light, which there is less of with dark themes.</p>
<p>This leads to, just like with cameras and any other optics with lenses and
apertures, a shortened depth of field, and hence more difficulty focusing on
the screen!</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/dark-mode/">This article by the well-known Nielsen Norman Group</a> nicely summarises research
on this topic. In short:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In people with normal vision (or corrected-to-normal vision), visual
performance tends to be better with light mode, whereas some people with
cataract and related disorders may perform better with dark mode.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Up until recently, I did not experience a qualitative difference in vision
between dark and light, but I sit here relieved that my eye-strain issue has
been resolved by an Emacs theme!</p>
<h2 id="know-how-to-put-down-your-work">Know how to put down your work</h2>
<p>The following take from <a href="https://twitter.com/brandsrock/status/1426163442256330753">a recent tweet by mike joubert</a> struck me
(tweet-take-strike! words are funny&hellip;):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The truly valuable skill isn&rsquo;t the capacity to push yourself harder, but to
stop and recuperate despite the discomfort of knowing that work remains
unfinished, emails unanswered, other people&rsquo;s demands unfulfilled.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">article, titled <em>The three-or-four-hours rule for getting creative work
done</em></a>, is itself a good read about the observation that creative types (amongst
which I count engineers) have at their best three to four hours of focus time
per day &mdash; so it is crucially important that their days are structured such
that there is an <strong>uninterrupted</strong> block of three to four hours inside of which
that lovely focus has the possibility of appearing.</p>
<p>The tweet-extract focuses on the similarly important but more subtle art of
being able to put one&rsquo;s work down, completely, when that block of time is over,
even when it feels like the work is far from complete.</p>
<p>I especially like that it also explicitly mentions the illusions created by
one&rsquo;s perception of &ldquo;other people&rsquo;s demands&rdquo;, something that ironically becomes
even harder to walk away from when one is more tired at the end of the work
day.</p>
<p>For me, becoming better at putting work down has pleasant echoes of running
slower to run faster, of emptiness in art and more broadly, <a href="https://zenhabits.net/work-less/">choosing fewer f*cks
to give</a>.</p>
<h2 id="follow-your-blisters">Follow your blisters</h2>
<p>On the topic of choosing your ducks&hellip;</p>
<p>I initially did not like <a href="https://hbr.org/2020/11/what-you-should-follow-instead-of-your-passion">this HBR</a> post when it first crossed my stream, because
it smacks a bit too much of the current social media style of &ldquo;wisdom&rdquo;, namely
&ldquo;everything you need to know in 280 characters&rdquo;, or &ldquo;this 1 minute tiktok video
will change your life&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the title is pretty clickbaity: <em>What You Should
Follow Instead of Your Passion</em>.</p>
<p>However, the core message of the post, which I could not help reading, did
stick with me, and after a few days I realised that I would have to go find the
article again in order to talk about it here.</p>
<p>The core message is to replace <em>find your passion</em> with <strong><em>Find your blisters.</em></strong></p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s point is that folks often get the wrong idea with <em>passion</em> as
something that is simply always delightful, whilst the thing you should
actually be looking for, is that activity that you simply are unable to stop
doing, even when you try, and especially even when you don&rsquo;t directly derive
pleasure from it, for example because you feel that you&rsquo;re not that good at it.</p>
<p>They give the personal example of writing.</p>
<p>Although they&rsquo;ve been at it for years, it&rsquo;s still a difficult and laborious
process, and they are often not happy with the results.</p>
<p>However, they have been unable to stop from returning to writing projects again
and again over the years.</p>
<p>Ironically, even although they find that they are still bad at it, they have in
fact become really good, simply because they have been pushing through and
practising more than almost anyone else over the years.</p>
<p>I really like this down-to-earth view.</p>
<p>One can indeed source almost unlimited amounts of energy from one&rsquo;s &ldquo;blisters&rdquo;,
but true benefits will for a large part be brought about by a <a href="/tags/practice/">lifetime of often
challenging practice</a>.</p>










<figure><a href="flowers_everywhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_77f0491ce2bb652a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_c88a425b4a6e1547.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_26051671c6ea88b0.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_c1d1549ff9af473f.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/flowers_everywhere_hu_c88a425b4a6e1547.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A scene from our incredibly fortunately timed (thanks partner!) &ldquo;blommetjieskyk&rdquo; trip to the West Coast national Park. This was taken somewhere between Postberg and Tsaarsbank, GPS coords in photo.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #226: Stress practice</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 16:07:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/</guid><description>Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.
Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the 226th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, this one covering the
week from Monday June 7 to Sunday June 13, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="bettys_run_pano_20210612.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu_9294ce5ff34fe3c0.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu_4392b58b4b1a01d9.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu_76a32b2bef8a8fdd.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu_989300adce5310c8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/bettys_run_pano_20210612_hu_4392b58b4b1a01d9.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Panoramic view from a winter run in Betty&rsquo;s Bay. I was hoping Google Photos would stitch the pretty clouds together, and it did.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I put these finishing touches on the post, it&rsquo;s Wednesday, June 16 (<a href="https://www.gov.za/youth-day">Youth
Day</a>), 16:09. I have just spent about an hour debugging my usually super smooth
Emacs Org-mode / <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo">ox-hugo</a> blogging machine (read <a href="https://github.com/kaushalmodi/ox-hugo/issues/447">this github issue</a> for more
details), which is a small price when you consider all the hours this
combination has saved me in the past.</p>
<h2 id="solstice-tipping-point-is-coming">Solstice tipping point is coming!</h2>
<p>The last thing we&rsquo;re supposed to do is to wish even just a little bit for time
to pass more quickly, for fairly obvious reasons.</p>
<p>However, when you&rsquo;re a few days from the darkest point in the year, it&rsquo;s hard
not to.</p>
<p>We currently have 9 hours and 56 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s just two minutes, and a few days, from the winter solstice on June 21,
when we&rsquo;ll have to make do with 9 hours and 54 minutes of daylight.</p>
<p>I mention this here, because those 6 AM wake-ups feel more and more like the
middle of the night.</p>
<p>After the solstice, I&rsquo;ll start imagining the sun coming up a few moments
earlier every morning, and it will.</p>
<p>(Well, it will, eventually. Reader WIMM just pointed out via email that
although the days start getting longer, the sunrise will initially become even
a minute later, before finally becoming earlier starting from July 11. Read
more <a href="https://theconversation.com/why-the-sunrise-is-still-later-after-the-winter-solstice-shortest-day-77628">here</a> (thanks WIMM) or check the tables <a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/south-africa/stellenbosch?month=6&amp;year=2021">here</a>.)</p>
<p>It has been &hellip; <code>1 year and 11 months</code> &hellip; since <a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/">the previous mention of winter
solstice on this blog</a>.</p>
<h2 id="avoid-the-jbl-endurance-run-bt-earphones-at-all-costs">Avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones at all costs</h2>
<p>A month ago <a href="/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/#world-in-my-eyes">I wrote about the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a> that I was
initially so happy with, which then spontaneously broke after a few hours of
running, and which I then returned for a replacement.</p>
<p>Well, the replacement set of <a href="https://eu.jbl.com/JBL+ENDURANCE+RUNBT.html?dwvar%5FJBL%20ENDURANCE%20RUNBT%5Fcolor=Black-GLOBAL-Current">proudly sweat-proof JBL Endurance Run BT earphones</a>
lasted for about 9 hours of running, at which point they spontaneously broke in
exactly the same way.</p>
<p>Out of nowhere, the loud crackling sound started in the earpiece opposite to
the site with the control unit.</p>
<p>This crackling sound (similar to the disturbance you hear when speaker wires
have a connection issue) did not stop, even after un-pairing and even after
switching off the unit.</p>
<p>Connecting the charger after this would result in the charge light flickering
and fading in-and-out in a decidedly analogue fashion.</p>
<p>After experiencing the exact same problem with two different units, I am wary
wasting more time on a third set.</p>
<p>This was quite a disappointment, because mechanically this design was perfect
for me.</p>
<p>I will continue on my search for the perfect (1. secure in my large and
sometimes perspiring ears, so needs something in addition to just ear canal fit
and 2. durable, i.e. continues working <em>long</em> after the first 9 hours of
running) set of running earphones, and I&rsquo;ll keep you up to date on my findings.</p>
<p>In the meantime, please avoid the JBL Endurance Run BT earphones.</p>
<h2 id="remote-work-culture-is-hard-work">Remote work culture is hard work</h2>
<p>During our Tuesday evening meetup, Theunis de Klerk of <a href="https://www.noldor.co.za/">Noldor</a> (the now fully
remote tech company, not <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noldor">the race of elves from Middle Earth</a>, although there is
a link here) gave an interesting and inspiring talk on how they have built and
cultivate great remote work culture.</p>
<p>This was an insightful look into an organization where the top leadership
continuously pours a great deal of thought and energy into maintaining healthy
culture, even in a fully remote environment with parts in different timezones.</p>
<p>On the one hand, it&rsquo;s great seeing working examples like this, on the other, it
can be quite a daunting prospect when you start thinking about how to apply
this in your own environment.</p>
<p>I believe that the future of knowledge work will <em>not</em> involve highly qualified
folks having to spend 8 hours per day at their desk because we still have not
learned that work is all about contributing value, and not about the number of
hours spent in captivity at one&rsquo;s desk.</p>
<p>That being said, during the current global remote working experiment, although
we are learning how to roll with value-generation, I do miss some of the almost
effortlessly and socially generated collaboration glue that at its best gets
folks almost instinctively chasing the same worthy goals.</p>
<p>(On the other hand, at its worst, it causes conflicts, grudges and ulcers, so
there&rsquo;s that&hellip;)</p>
<p>I would like to wrap this ramble up with one conclusion, and one interesting
tweet storm by Steven Sinofsky of Andreesen Horowitz:</p>
<ul>
<li>Conclusion: 1. Am I overestimating how &ldquo;easy&rdquo; social cohesion was when we
were in the office? 2. How do we go about getting back that real or imagined
social cohesion in this fully remote setting?</li>
<li><a href="https://a16z.com/2021/06/12/disruption-at-work-its-more-than-just-wfh/">Highly interesting tweet storm about the issue being larger and more
intricate than just WFH vs hybrid vs HQ</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="eternal-practice-vs-stress">Eternal practice vs stress</h2>
<p>I do need to note here (for future me) that I was consistently far grumpier
than usual for the last few days of the week under examination here.</p>
<p>When I say grumpy, I do mean quite detectably so.</p>
<p>This is definitely not my preferred state, so I&rsquo;m even meta-grumpy about that.</p>
<p>My retro- and introspection during the weekend came up with &ldquo;more stress than
usual&rdquo;, which is indeed probably a main contributor (wow, thanks work).</p>
<p>However, being grumpy or not is still fully my responsibility.</p>
<p>Increased stress at work is currently primarily due to new responsibilities and
the (often amplified by one&rsquo;s own imagination) expectations of colleagues, and
the unsurprising feeling of discomfort that is associated with finding oneself
faced with new kinds of challenges that you are not accustomed to (<em>cf.</em>
&ldquo;comfort zone&rdquo; and <a href="/2013/11/11/creative-process-stage-5-whv-67/">stages 2 to 4 of the creative process</a>).</p>
<p>During the weekend I first resolved simply to be less grumpy (yes, you can do
that).</p>
<p>Fortunately, I also had a spot of insight as to how the root cause, i.e. the
work-related stress, could be better addressed in my specific case.</p>
<p>You see, I have chosen to be in this situation. I would have preferred the new
challenges without the concomitant stress, but that&rsquo;s unfortunately not how
<em>this</em> human normally works.</p>
<p>The realisation that I had was that this too is simply part of my lifelong
practice session.</p>
<p>I first talked about the idea of life being continuous pracrtice back in <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">WHV
#133</a>, and again later in <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">WHV #144</a> when I got around to reading a
reader-recommended book on the topic, titled &ldquo;Mastery&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Something I did not mention back then, probably because I only experience the
stress aspect as acutely at this moment, is that this particular framing helps
me to approach my current problems with curiosity, with an appetite for
learning and experimentation, and with the acceptance that my performance could
be far from perfect, perhaps even to the point of failure.</p>
<p>Some days will be good and some days will be bad.</p>
<p>(Even outside of the practice framing, one just has to accept that <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning"><em>some days
gonna be crap</em></a>.)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, every day is a brand new opportunity to practice the
difficult new stuff, and to become gradually better at it, until one day, just
maybe, comfort slowly starts overtaking discomfort.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #133: Onder in my Whiskeyglas.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 21:15:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/</guid><description> The legendary Koos Kombuis (aka André Letoit) performing with Schalk Joubert on bass and Vernon Swart on percussion in the Helderberg Nature reserve, eponymous mountain visible through the trees on the right. This was a surprisingly amazing end to the week.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/IMG_3288.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/IMG_3288.jpg"
        
            alt="The legendary Koos Kombuis (aka André Letoit) performing with Schalk Joubert on bass and Vernon Swart on percussion in the Helderberg Nature reserve, eponymous mountain visible through the trees on the right. This was a surprisingly amazing end to the week."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The legendary Koos Kombuis (aka André Letoit) performing with Schalk Joubert on bass and Vernon Swart on percussion in the Helderberg Nature reserve, eponymous mountain visible through the trees on the right. This was a surprisingly amazing end to the week.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>What a week.</p>
<p>It was beautiful to see the whole team step up to the plate and <em>engineer</em> at about 110% throughput (software gets complicated quickly, and there&rsquo;s always one more thing you need to get done before the deliverable is ready), all the while remaining calm and, most importantly, kind.</p>
<h2 id="pro-tip-special">Pro-tip Special</h2>
<p>I was of course the lucky winner of the manual-writing sub-project. I love writing code, but there&rsquo;s also something quite satisfying about writing documentation for a technical product. Anyways, there are five tiny but hopefully useful lessons I extracted from this exercise which I would like to present here:</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2011/08/28/a-windows-console-that-does-not-suck/">I&rsquo;ve lamented the sorry state of the Windows console before</a> (in 2011 to be exact). In a surprise twist, the Windows console still sucks almost 7 years later. At least it&rsquo;s reliable. Anyways, <a href="http://cmder.net/">cmder is a great console replacement</a> which makes some of the stupid go away, somewhat.</li>
<li>The Windows 10 built-in screenshot facility … wait for it… sucks. When you&rsquo;re writing documentation you need a tool that fits into your workflow. Keyboard shortcut – window or region – image ends up in a directory of your choice. <a href="http://getgreenshot.org/">Greenshot is an open source screenshotting tool</a> that does this with aplomb.</li>
<li>You need to show a CHM (Windows Help) file to the user of your wxPython application when they hit F1. How hard could it be? Well, you could spend a number of hours trying to come up with a wx-y cross-platform solution, or you could use that time for something else worth your while and just use the <a href="http://docs.activestate.com/activepython/3.3/pywin32/win32help__HtmlHelp_meth.html">Python win32 package to call into the official Windows help API</a>. (cross-platform does work, it&rsquo;s just really ugly)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/master/">Sphinx</a> is a much better tool to write technical manuals than is Markdown and related tools. I briefly considered Markdown because I always have to look up reStructuredText syntax, but fortunately ran into enough other places <a href="http://ericholscher.com/blog/2016/mar/15/dont-use-markdown-for-technical-docs/">warning against using Markdown for documentation</a>. For the record, I prefer orgmode over all of these puny formats in most other cases, but the documentation story of Sphinx with reStructuredText is admittedly much better.</li>
<li>Start writing the manual as early as possible. It was amazing to see how this helped me to see the software we are designing at a more integrated (user) level. This knowledge was useful in driving more valuable improvements. If you can&rsquo;t explain the flow of some procedure in a manual, that&rsquo;s a good sign the procedure might need some refinement.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="humble-book-bundle-and-rust">Humble Book Bundle and Rust</h2>
<p>I bought the <a href="https://www.humblebundle.com/books/functional-programming-books">Humble Bundle of (O&rsquo;Reilly) Functional Programming Books</a> for a super affordable $15. I was primarily interested in the <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920040385.do">Programming Rust book by Blandy and Orendorff</a>, but the other titles on Scala, Clojure, Erlang, Elixir, Haskell, Javascript and general functional programming are welcome additions to my library. Speaking of which, I emailed O&rsquo;Reilly to ask if the books in the bundle could be added to my member library, which they promptly did!</p>
<p>I have avoided Rust up to now due to natural hype suppression circuitry, and because I grew up with C++, but its zero-overhead memory safety and trustworthy concurrency story makes it hard to ignore any longer. Even although <a href="https://www.quora.com/Which-language-has-the-brightest-future-in-replacement-of-C-between-D-Go-and-Rust-And-Why/answer/Andrei-Alexandrescu">Andrei Alexandrescu once called Rust the language that skips leg day</a>, it&rsquo;s certainly interesting seeing the constructs the language designers have come up to build a really fast compiled language with the lowest number of foot-guns per line of code.</p>
<p>Anyways, when this blog gets published, you should still have about 22 hours to make use of the <a href="https://www.humblebundle.com/books/functional-programming-books">Humble Bundle deal</a> if you too see something that you like.</p>
<h2 id="life-is-continuous-practice">Life is continuous practice</h2>
<p>I wanted to conclude with something that I&rsquo;ve been thinking about recently. It has to do with explicitly treating one&rsquo;s life as <em>continuous practice</em>. As I&rsquo;ve mentioned before on this blog and people much smarter than me have been pointing out since forever, <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">goals are no good</a> and (lasting) <a href="/Weekly-Head-Voices-125/#Happy-Not-Happy">happiness is probably not attainable</a>.</p>
<p>Discarding as many as possible of these sorts of fetters is liberating (you Buddhist), but can seem to leave holes in one&rsquo;s  life narrative. However, treating your life as a super long practice session is an interesting perspective.</p>
<p>There is also no end point, and no real life goal.</p>
<p>The only point of the whole exercise (yes, I see what I did there) is to try to improve continuously. Every day, we try to become a little better at our jobs, or at running, or at being a good human, or a partner, or a parent.</p>
<p>Practice means that you have good days and bad days. It means that you sometimes look back and think that you were a better person then than you are now. Practice means that when you pick one activity, another will temporarily languish until you can make time for it again.</p>
<p>All of this is ok, because tomorrow you have a whole new day to try again.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>