<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>book on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/book/</link><description>Recent content in book on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 23:16:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/book/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Notes on the book "Seven and a Half Lessons About the Brain" by Lisa Feldman Barrett</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 23:16:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/</guid><description> Professor Lisa Feldman Barrett is a neuro-scientist and psychologist who studies the brain and especially how emotion works in the brain.
In addition to her 240 peer reviewed scientific publications, she is the author of the popular books How Emotions are Made: The Secret Life of the Brain and Seven and a Half Lessons About the Brain, the book notes on which you are reading here.
The book consists of seven and a half beautifully written and amazing stories about the human brain.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><a href="https://lisafeldmanbarrett.com/about/">Professor Lisa Feldman Barrett</a> is a neuro-scientist and psychologist who
studies the brain and especially how emotion works in the brain.</p>
<p>In addition to her 240 peer reviewed scientific publications, she is the author
of the popular books <a href="https://lisafeldmanbarrett.com/books/how-emotions-are-made/">How Emotions are Made: The Secret Life of the Brain</a> and
<a href="https://lisafeldmanbarrett.com/books/seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Seven and a Half Lessons About the Brain</a>, the book notes on which you are
reading here.</p>








<figure><a href="seven_and_a_half_lessons_about_the_brain_cover_mandelbrot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/_hu0e733d53da9064585e8561457e0952a5_972424_b583c02291db35a571419c5d94af1703.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/_hu0e733d53da9064585e8561457e0952a5_972424_a82b6f62d3f7c3938ff3083ef3571a02.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/_hu0e733d53da9064585e8561457e0952a5_972424_f138c01568f3908421d20a28713618d2.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/_hu0e733d53da9064585e8561457e0952a5_972424_3f7a062f831e4a62f34491da1543c778.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/_hu0e733d53da9064585e8561457e0952a5_972424_a82b6f62d3f7c3938ff3083ef3571a02.jpg"
            

         width="320px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>The book consists of seven and a half beautifully written and amazing stories
about the human brain.</p>
<p>If you have any interest in how humans work, or in brains (and who doesn&rsquo;t?!),
and you like good stories, please purchase and read this book.</p>
<p>In the meantime, you can apply that amazing, ever-evolving, never-sleeping
chunk of information processing tissue in your skull to ingest the concepts
encoded by the words below!</p>
<h2 id="your-brain-is-not-for-thinking">Your Brain Is Not for Thinking</h2>
<p>The main reason or motivation for the evolution of the brain was not such much
the ability to think, which is admittedly an entertaining side-effect, but
rather the efficient running of the <em>body budget</em>.</p>
<p>Feldman Barrett writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A budget for your body similarly tracks resources like water, salt, and glucose
as you gain and lose them. Each action that spends resources, such as swimming
or running, is like a withdrawal from your account. Actions that replenish your
resources, such as eating and sleeping, are like deposits</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Body budgeting</em>, or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allostasis">allostatis</a>, refers to the idea that organisms continuously
and automatically <em>predict</em> the body&rsquo;s needs <em>before</em> they arise.</p>
<p>For the human body with all of its complexity, it&rsquo;s clear to see that
accurately predicting needs and expenditures before they arise can become
tricky, and might just require that big brain after all.</p>
<p>It becomes especially interesting when you remember that our complex social
embedding and interactions form a crucial part of our survival.</p>
<p>In other words, we&rsquo;re not just predicting the direct physical needs of our own
bodies, but a whole network of interwoven social interactions and
relationships, the effects of our actions and those of others on everyone in
that network, and the possible future implications for our requirements and
expenditures.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re going to need that supercomputer.</p>
<h2 id="you-have-one-brain">You Have One Brain (Not Three)</h2>
<p>Just like it is to me, I&rsquo;m sure that the idea of the triune brain, that is the
idea that the humain brain consists of three &ldquo;layers&rdquo;, namely the most
primitive &ldquo;lizard&rdquo; brain, focused on survival, the slightly more modern limbic
system for emotion on top of that and finally the neocortex, the rational part
that differentiates humans from other animals and that includes the prefrontal
cortex, is quite familiar to you.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s clear that Feldman Barrett experiences considerable mirth when she gets to
shatter that familiar mental model for everyone reading her book.</p>
<p>After some unravelling of assumptions, she writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The triune brain idea is one of the most successful and widespread errors in
all of science. It&rsquo;s certainly a compelling story, and at times, it captures
how we feel in daily life.</p>
<p>[some text omitted]</p>
<p>But human brains don&rsquo;t work that way. Bad behavior doesn&rsquo;t come from ancient
and unbridled inner beasts. Good behavior is not the result of rationality. And
rationality and emotion are not at war . . . they do not even live in separate
parts of the brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A bit further on, we learn that the brains of all mammals, and possibly the
brains of reptiles and other vertebrates, are &ldquo;built from a single
manufacturing plan&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In other words, in typical lazy (or efficient) Mother Nature fashion, maximal
reuse is at play here, and we&rsquo;re not special. (phew)</p>
<p>The brains follow the same manufacturing process, with the same stages in the
same order, but the stages do run for different durations depending on the
species.</p>
<p>To further ram that point home:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>So the human brain has no new parts. The neurons in your brain can be found in
the brains of other mammals and, likely, other vertebrates. This discovery
undermines the evolutionary foundations of the triune brain story.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As an&hellip; erstwhile fan of pre-frontal cortex (PFC) explanations, I felt quite
directly addressed by her final assertion that it was really time to let the
triune brain go now:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Anything you read or hear that proclaims the human neocortex, cerebral cortex,
or prefrontal cortex to be the root of rationality, or says that the frontal
lobe regulates so-called emotional brain areas to keep irrational behavior in
check, is simply outdated or woefully incomplete. The triune brain idea and its
epic battle between emotion, instinct, and rationality is a modern myth.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The 1.5th lesson is concluded with some great advice for the future:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You have one brain, not three. To move past Plato&rsquo;s ancient battle, we might
need to fundamentally rethink what it means to be rational, what it means to be
responsible for our actions, and perhaps even what it means to be human.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="your-brain-is-a-network">Your Brain Is a Network</h2>
<p>(I already had some knowledge of the brain network, but this lesson surprised
me with new knowledge on every page!)</p>
<p>Your brain is a network of 128 billion (that&rsquo;s 128 thousand million, or 128 x
10<sup>9</sup>) interconnected neurons.</p>
<p>There are very many connections&hellip;</p>
<p>How many?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Each neuron directly passes information to just a few thousand other neurons
and receives information from a few thousand others, give or take, yielding
over five hundred trillion neuron-to-neuron connections.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Five hundred trillion means five hundred million million, or 500 x 10<sup>12</sup>.</p>
<p>If you went and connected each neuron with every other neuron, there would be
many more connections than this, but that would be far too expensive,
energy-wise.</p>
<p>Instead, the brain is connected just well enough to do its amazing job, in a
superbly energy-efficient way.</p>
<p>The next lesson that struck me was this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Your brain network is always on. Your neurons never just sit around waiting for
something in the outside world to make them fire. Instead, all of your neurons
chat constantly with one another through their wiring. Their communications may
become stronger or weaker depending on what&rsquo;s happening in the world and in
your body, but the conversation never stops until you die.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It&rsquo;s pretty crazy to think (haha) that all of those connections are firing, all
the damn time.</p>
<p>It never stops, until you die.</p>
<h3 id="a-network-of-clustered-neurons-some-clusters-acting-as-long-distance-hubs">A network of clustered neurons, some clusters acting as long-distance hubs</h3>
<p>Getting back to the observation that the brain is not fully connected, but
rather sparsely so, a good next question would be &ldquo;but how exactly is it
sparsely connected?&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Unsurprisingly, Feldman Barrett has a crystal clear explanation of the modular
structure of the brain:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Your brain network is organized in much the same way [as the network of
airports]. Its neurons are grouped into clusters that are like airports. Most
of the connections in and out of a cluster are local, so, like an airport, the
cluster serves mostly local traffic. In addition, some clusters serve as hubs
for communication. They are densely connected to many other clusters, and some
of their axons reach far across the brain and act as long-distance
connections. Brain hubs, like airport hubs, make a complicated system
efficient. They allow most neurons to participate globally even as they focus
more locally. Hubs form the backbone of communication throughout the brain</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To the best of our (where with &ldquo;our&rdquo;, I mean &ldquo;science&rsquo;s&rdquo;) knowledge, this kind
of network gives the most bang for your energy buck. It&rsquo;s extremely powerful,
yet efficient and as an added bonus actually fits into your skull.</p>
<p>I also found it interesting to read that damage to the hub clusters
specifically was associated with a number of neurological disorders, such as
depression, schizophrenia, dyslexia, chronic pain, dementia and Parkinson&rsquo;s.</p>
<p>Just as would be the case with an airport network, if the airport hubs were
damaged, that would have far-reacing effects on the whole system.</p>
<h3 id="the-network-is-bathed-in-chemicals-called-neurotransmitters">The network is bathed in chemicals called neurotransmitters</h3>
<p>Each tiny neuron continuously fires its electrical signal out through its axon
into possibly thousands of downstream neurons.</p>
<p>The gap between the firing axon and the receiving neuron&rsquo;s dendrite is called a
synapse.</p>
<p>To add some more variability and flexibility to the already complex network,
the whole thing is bathed in neurotransmitters which either help or hinder that
firing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Your brain wiring is bathed in chemicals that complete the local connections
between neurons. These chemicals, such as glutamate, serotonin, and dopamine,
are called neurotransmitters, and they make it easier or harder for signals to
pass across synapses.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perhaps because that wasn&rsquo;t already interesting enough, a subset of these
chemicals, notably serotonin and dopamine, can boost or diminish the effect of
other neurotransmitters, and can therefore be called <em>neuromodulators</em>.</p>
<h3 id="neurons-can-do-different-tasks-the-same-task-can-be-done-by-different-neurons">Neurons can do different tasks, the same task can be done by different neurons</h3>
<p>The common perception that each brain region is responsible for a specific task
is incorrect. Groups of neurons are indeed more likely to perform a specific
task, but there are many examples of such groups participating in various other
tasks.</p>
<p>Similarly, the same task can easily be performed by different sets of neurons,
a phenomenon called <em>degeneracy</em>.</p>
<p>Feldman Barrett notes that even reaching for the exact same thing twice in a
row will engage different sets of neurons.</p>
<h3 id="slow-to-fast-changes-complexity-is-key-in-dealing-with-our-reality">Slow to fast changes, complexity is key in dealing with our reality</h3>
<p>I really liked the explanation of how the brain adapts to the world at
different speeds:</p>
<ul>
<li>Slow changes by learning / rewiring connections / plasticity.</li>
<li>Faster changes by neurotransmitters and neuromodulators.</li>
<li>Neurons performing multiple jobs.</li>
</ul>
<p>The network needs to be this complex because:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; your brain can create massive numbers of different patterns by combining
bits and pieces of old patterns it has made before. The result is a brain that
runs its body efficiently in a world full of constantly changing situations by
recalling patterns that helped in the past and generating new ones to try.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&hellip; and then further down, this intriguing observation on memories not being
stored, but being reconstructed on demand:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Brains of higher complexity can remember more. A brain doesn&rsquo;t store memories
like files in a computer—it reconstructs them on demand with electricity and
swirling chemicals. We call this process remembering but it&rsquo;s really
assembling. A complex brain can assemble many more memories than either
Meatloaf Brain or Pocketknife Brain could. And each time you have the same
memory, your brain may have assembled it with a different collection of
neurons.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This lesson is wrapped up with the mind-expanding (haha) realization that the
brain encompasses more than just the neurons in your head:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Your brain is more than just neurons. It includes blood vessels and various
fluids that I haven&rsquo;t talked about. It also includes other kinds of brain
cells, called glial cells, that function in ways that scientists don&rsquo;t fully
understand yet. Your brain network may even extend, surprisingly, into your gut
and intestines, where scientists have found microbes that communicate with your
brain via neuro-transmitters.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="little-brains-wire-themselves-to-their-world">Little Brains Wire Themselves to Their World</h2>
<p>Please note, teenagers and other young adults, your brain is only fully formed
when you reach the ripe old age of 25!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; little human brains are born under construction. They don&rsquo;t take on their
full adult structure and function until they finish their principal wiring, a
process that takes about twenty-five years.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This has interesting and far-reaching consequences for the best approach to
work with younger humans. They might walk like adults and talk like adults,
when in fact they still need a few years of brain maturation before being fully
responsible.</p>
<p>On the other hand, the record for humans older than 25 is also not that
impressive.</p>
<p>Half-jokes aside, it is fascinating and quite terrifying to read how much a
human child is, often irrevocably, formed by its environment:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To a remarkable extent, a baby&rsquo;s genes are guided and regulated by the
surrounding environment. The brain areas that are most centrally involved in
vision, for example, develop normally after birth only if a baby&rsquo;s retinas are
regularly exposed to light. An infant&rsquo;s brain also learns to locate sounds in
the world based on the specific shape of the baby&rsquo;s ear. To make matters even
stranger, a baby&rsquo;s body requires some additional genes that sneak in from the
outside world. These tiny visitors travel inside of bacteria and other critters
and affect the brain in ways that scientists are only beginning to understand</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There&rsquo;s a lot more later, but this is a good introduction of the idea that our
brains, our very identities, are so intertwined with the external world, and
especially so when we are small and quite helpless.</p>
<p>Parents <em>really</em> need to do their utmost best.</p>
<p>The child&rsquo;s brain develops into its adult complexity via two processes called
<em>tuning</em> and <em>pruning</em>.</p>
<p><em>Tuning</em> means that neural connections that are used often become stronger. At
a cellular level this happens through the myelin sheaths around axons (the
neurons output) becoming thicker, facilitating signal transmission, and also
through the dendrites (the inputs) becoming bushier.</p>
<p><em>Pruning</em> means that neural connections that are not really used weaken and
disappear. Here Feldman Barrett invokes one of my favourite principles when
trying to understand the ruthless efficiency in human physiology: <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/#use-it-or-lose-it">Use it or
lose it</a>.</p>
<p>In the case of the developing child, it starts with far more neurons than an
adult brain needs. This is great for a brain that will need to adapt to a range
of new situations. However, once the situation is known, the unused neurons and
connections are ruthlessly pruned away to result eventually in a more efficient
brain.</p>
<p>Feldman Barrett proceeds to give a number of compelling examples how the baby&rsquo;s
caretakers and the environment that they create play an absolutely crucial role
in the <em>physical</em> development of the new neural network.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Little brains require a social world in order to develop typically. You&rsquo;ve
already learned that babies need certain physical inputs, such as photons of
light bombarding their retinas, or their brains will never develop normal
vision. It turns out that they also need social inputs from other humans who
guide their attention, speak or sing to them, and cuddle them at key
moments. If these needs aren&rsquo;t met, things can go terribly wrong.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>She then discusses a horrible example where thousands of Romanian babies found
themselves in orphanages in the 1960s due to terrible leadership decisions.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In some orphanages, babies were warehoused in rows of cribs, with little
stimulation or social interaction. Nurses or caregivers would come in and feed
them, change them, and put them back in the cribs. That was about it.</p>
<p>[text ommitted]</p>
<p>As a consequence of this social neglect, the Romanian orphans grew up
intellectually impaired. They had problems learning language. They had
difficulty concentrating and resisting distractions, probably because nobody
had shared attention with them, so their brains never developed the wiring for
an effective spotlight. They also had trouble controlling themselves. Alongside
the children&rsquo;s mental and behavioral issues, their bodies were stunted, most
likely because they grew up without caregivers to keep their body budgets
solvent. This meant their brains never learned to budget effectively. A little
brain wires itself to its environment, and when that environment is missing key
elements for healthy body budgeting, critical brain wiring can be pruned away.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Based on this and far too many other observations, it is clear that children
absolutely need to be well cared for, both physically and socially, in order to
have a chance to develop into healthy adults.</p>
<p>This is a fundamental mechanism that can&rsquo;t be easily remedied later.</p>
<p>She continues with this line of discussion into the now even more relevant
poverty cycle phenomenon:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Research shows that early and long exposure to poverty is bad for the
developing brain. Inadequate nutrition, interrupted sleep due to street noise,
poor temperature regulation due to lack of heat or ventilation, and other
circumstances of poverty may alter the development of the front of the cerebral
cortex, namely the prefrontal cortex. This brain area is involved in a range of
critical functions, including attention, language, and body
budgeting. Scientists are still studying the ways that poverty affects brain
development, but we do know that it&rsquo;s linked to poorer performance in school
and fewer years of education. These burdens ultimately increase a child&rsquo;s risk
of living in poverty when he grows up and has children of his own</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finally, this lesson is wrapped up with the observation that nature and nurture
are deeply and intricately intertwined:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When it comes to the brain, simple distinctions like nature versus nurture are
alluring but not realistic. We have the kind of nature that <em>requires</em>
nurture. Your genes require a physical and social environment &ndash; a niche filled
with other humans who shared your infant gaze, spoke to you with intent, set
your sleep schedule, and controlled your body temperature &ndash; in order to
produce a finished brain</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="your-brain-predicts--almost--everything-you-do">Your Brain Predicts (Almost) Everything You Do</h2>
<p>Readers of my personal blog might remember <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/#life-is-but-a-dream">my story in 2019 about the brain
being stuck in the dark bony cage we call &ldquo;skull&rdquo;</a>, taking fairly limited
sensory inputs, and in actual fact dreaming up all of one&rsquo;s reality on demand,
a story <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#the-describers">I later found out was also called transcendental idealism</a>.</p>
<p>At the start of lesson 4, Feldman Barrett writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Scientists used to believe that the brain’s visual system operated sort of like
a camera, detecting the visual information “out there” in the world and
constructing a photograph-like image in the mind. Today we know better. Your
view of the world is no photograph. It’s a construction of your brain that is
so fluid and so convincing that it appears to be accurate.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&hellip; and then comes the brain stuck in a box story again!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>From the moment you’re born to the moment you draw your last breath, your brain
is stuck in a dark, silent box called your skull. Day in and day out, it
continually receives sense data from the outside world via your eyes, ears,
nose, and other sensory organs. This data does not arrive in the form of the
meaningful sights, smells, sounds, and other sensations that most of us
experience. It’s just a barrage of light waves, chemicals, and changes in air
pressure with no inherent significance.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Most probably I picked this up somewhere on the echoing internet waves. Lex
Fridman podcast would be my bet, but not <a href="https://lexfridman.com/lisa-feldman-barrett/">the Feldman Barrett episode</a> because
that only came out in October of 2020.</p>
<p>However, this lesson is not only about your brain being stuck in a box, but the
observation that your brain is constantly predicting what&rsquo;s going to happen
next.</p>
<p>This is perhaps even more extreme than you might guess.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What happens next still astounds me, even as a neuroscientist. If your brain
has predicted well, then your neurons are already firing in a pattern that
matches the incoming sense data. That means this sense data itself has no
further use beyond confirming your brain’s predictions. What you see, hear,
smell, and taste in the world and feel in your body in that moment are
completely constructed in your head. By prediction, your brain has efficiently
prepared you to act.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So yes, it seems we are mostly all in fact dreaming together in a highly
synchronized fashion.</p>
<h2 id="your-brain-secretly-works-with-other-brains">Your Brain Secretly Works with Other Brains</h2>
<p>This aspect fascinated me during the podcast with Lex Fridman:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Part of being a social species, it turns out, is that we regulate one another&rsquo;s
body budgets &ndash; the ways in which our brains manage the bodily resources we use
every day.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As if it wasn&rsquo;t already trick enough that we regulate our own body budgets, we
also have a profound effect on each other&rsquo;s body budgets, an effect that we
ideally put to good use for positive regulation.</p>
<p>The stress that we often experience due to interaction with our fellow humans
plays a prominent role in this lesson.</p>
<p>In the workplace, having great colleagues that you can trust will leave more
energy to do your work better:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When people work in an environment where they can learn to trust one another,
they&rsquo;ll have less burden on their body budgets, saving resources that can be
invested in new ideas.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Profoundly, but probably not surprisingly, our prediction machines have a much
easier time modelling humans that are similar to us, and conversely a much more
difficult time working with fellow humans that are different from us:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When you have empathy for other people, your brain predicts what they&rsquo;ll think
and feel and do. The more familiar the other people are to you, the more
efficiently your brain predicts their inner struggles. The whole process feels
obvious and natural, as if you were reading another person&rsquo;s mind. But there&rsquo;s
a catch—when people are less familiar to you, it can be harder to
empathize. You might have to learn more about the person, an extra effort that
translates into more withdrawals from your body budget, which can feel
unpleasant. This may be one reason why people sometimes fail to empathize with
those who look different or believe different things than they do and why it
can feel uncomfortable to try. It&rsquo;s metabolically costly for a brain to deal
with things that are hard to predict.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This only underlines the fact that we really have no choice but to put in the
best effort that we can to support and cultivate more diversity.</p>
<p>Like in many other situations, mother nature can&rsquo;t be trusted here either, so
we have to apply our humanity to make up for her failings.</p>
<p>Next Feldman Barrett discusses the central role of speech also in how we
regulate each other&rsquo;s stress levels:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Primates like monkeys and chimpanzees also use vision to regulate each other&rsquo;s
nervous systems. Humans are unique in the animal kingdom, however, because we
also regulate each other with words. A kind word may calm you, as when a friend
gives you a compliment at the end of a hard day. A hateful word from a bully
may cause your brain to predict threat and flood your bloodstream with
hormones, squandering precious resources from your body budget.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is of course accurate and makes complete sense to me, but I have never
thought about it in these explicit co-regulation terms.</p>
<p>What follows is an important warning that it really does not matter what the
source of the stress is, if it continues, it will all pile up over time and it
will harm you.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It&rsquo;s important to understand that the human brain doesn&rsquo;t seem to distinguish
between different sources of chronic stress. If your body budget is already
depleted by the circumstances of life—like physical illness, financial
hardship, hormone surges, or simply not sleeping or exercising enough—your
brain becomes more vulnerable to stress of all kinds. This includes the
biological effects of words designed to threaten, bully, or torment you or
people you care about. When your body budget is continually burdened, momentary
stressors pile up, even the kind that you&rsquo;d normally bounce back from
quickly. It&rsquo;s like children jumping on a bed. The bed might withstand ten kids
bouncing at the same time, but the eleventh one snaps the bed frame.  Simply
put, a long period of chronic stress can harm a human brain.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Furthermore, contrary to the popular idiom, the wrong sorts of words <em>can</em> and
<em>will</em> cause bodily harm:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But if you&rsquo;re exposed to verbal nastiness continually for months and months or
if you live in an environment that persistently and relentlessly taxes your
body budget, words can indeed physically injure your brain. Not because you&rsquo;re
weak or a so-called snowflake, but because you&rsquo;re a human. Your nervous system
is bound up with the behavior of other humans, for better or for worse. You can
argue what the data means or if it&rsquo;s important, but it is what it is.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>She explains that when you&rsquo;re exposed to social stress within two hours from a
meal, you even metabolize the foods from that meal much worse than you normally
would.</p>
<p>She summarises the whole idea with the following observation, and perhaps this
is that one thing we should take home with us:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The best thing for your nervous system is another human. The worst thing for
your nervous system is also another human</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="our-interconnectedness-and-our-personal-freedom">Our interconnectedness and our personal freedom</h3>
<p>Feldman Barrett has an extremeley timely piece at the end of this chapter
about how our inescapable (and fantastic) interconnectedness has significant
implications for our personal freedoms.</p>
<p>First, she makes clear how deeply we have always affected each other, and how
inescapable this is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>After all, history is filled with examples of overcoming our biology so we can
live our values. Other people carry germs, for example, that can make us sick
or even kill us, but only in the most nightmarish cases do we legislate a
solution that restricts our personal freedoms. More commonly, we cooperate and
innovate. We invent soap, we bump elbows instead of shaking hands, we search
for new medicines and vaccines, and so on. If this is insufficient, experts
tell us we&rsquo;re supposed to voluntarily isolate ourselves and practice social
distancing. Even in a free society, our actions affect one another in ways that
are, like viruses, often invisible to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&hellip; and then she completes this train of reasoning with the observation that
personal freedom does have a great associated cost which is often exacted from
others:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Scientists are often asked to make their research useful to everyday
life. These scientific findings about words, chronic stress, and disease are a
perfect example. There is a real biological benefit when people treat one
another with basic human dignity. And if we don&rsquo;t, there is also a real
biological consequence, and it eventually trickles down to a financial and
social cost for everyone. The price of personal freedom is personal
responsibility for your impact on others. The wiring of all of our brains
guarantees it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is clear that personal freedom has to be balanced carefully with cost to
others, where the latter does have precedence.</p>
<h2 id="brains-make-more-than-one-kind-of-mind">Brains Make More than One Kind of Mind</h2>
<p>She starts this chapter about the sometimes large differences differences
between humans with the great example that people from Bali in Indonesia <em>fall
asleep when they are very afraid</em>, while most Western folks are more likely to
freeze on the spot, eyes wide, and gasp.</p>
<p>Perhaps even more fundamental than that, those same folks who grep up in Bali,
or in the Illongot culture in the Philippines, don&rsquo;t experience <em>thinking</em> and
<em>feeling</em> as two separate concepts, like most Westerners do, but rather as a
single thing.</p>
<p>She has more examples like this, but her overarching statement is that the same
physical brain can produce and house quite different <em>minds</em>.</p>
<p>Importantly, variation is the norm.</p>
<p>Physical brains do have many common features, but minds by definition less so,
because of the great adaptability of the underlying physical brains.</p>
<p>She gives another example pointing out that the Western idea of the body and
mind as separate interacting constructs is also not the norm:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Brains have a lot of common features; minds, less so, because minds depend in
part on micro-wiring that is tuned and pruned by culture. For example, many
Western cultures draw strong dividing lines between the mental and the
physical. If your stomach hurts, you&rsquo;re likely to visit your primary care
physician or a gastroenterologist; if you’re feeling anxiety, you&rsquo;re more
likely to see a psychologist, even if the symptoms and the underlying causes
are identical. But in some Eastern cultures, such as those that practice
Buddhism, mind and body are much more integrated.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As an aside, with all the work that is currently happening on the microbiome,
showing how bacteria in your gut can and do affect your mood and personality,
it is starting to look like the body-and-mind-in-one perspective could be
closer to reality.</p>
<p>I highlighted the following paragraph, because (as an engineer and a data
person) I found it an intriguing idea that your brain is summarising in
real-time, down to a single metric called &ldquo;affect&rdquo;, the storm of external and
internal data that it has to deal with.</p>
<p>In other words, <em>affect</em> is a single metric, or rather feeling, that summarises
the complete state of your whole system.</p>
<p>Feldman Barrett writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Where does affect come from? In every moment &ndash; like right now, as you read
these words &ndash; your hormones, organs, and immune system are producing a storm
of sense data, and you&rsquo;re barely aware of it. You notice your heartbeat and
breathing only when they&rsquo;re intense or you focus on them. You almost never
notice your body temperature unless it&rsquo;s too high or too low. Your brain,
however, makes meaning from this data storm continuously to predict your body’s
next action and meet its metabolic needs before they arise. In the midst of all
this activity inside you, something miraculous happens. Your brain summarizes
what&rsquo;s going on with your body in the moment, and you feel that summary as
affect.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finally, for better or for worse, it is possible to modify your mind with
chemicals or with experiences:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You can modify your mind. People do this all the time. College students use
caffeine or amphetamines to create minds that can pull an all-nighter before a
final exam. Partygoers drink alcohol to create minds that are more relaxed and
less inhibited in social situations (and miraculously, other people around them
suddenly become much more attractive). These chemical modifications last for
only a short time. For longer-lasting modifications, you can try new
experiences or learn new things to rewire your brain, as we discussed in
earlier lessons.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>She mentions that one of the most challenging experiences in terms of changing
your mind is moving to another culture.</p>
<p>The lesson is concluded with the following re-iteration of its central point,
the malleability of the mind:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When it comes to human minds, variation is the norm, and what we call &ldquo;human
nature&rdquo; is really many human natures. We don&rsquo;t need one universal mind in order
to claim that we are all one species. All we need is an exceptionally complex
brain that wires itself to its physical and social surroundings.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="our-brains-can-create-reality">Our Brains Can Create Reality</h2>
<p>This is such an amazing chapter, which I really hope that you are able to read
in its full form.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, here I&rsquo;ll try to summarise the main gist.</p>
<p>Humans have the unique ability to create <em>social reality</em>.</p>
<p>The country that you live in, its name, the exact border surrounding it, the
customs and the laws that you share with your fellow citizens, the right way to
act at a party, and so on&hellip;</p>
<p>All of that was <em>synthesized</em>, created out of nothing, by a bunch of human
minds.</p>
<p>Furthermore, we have demonstrated in many cases that we are able to keep these
social realities operational for thousands of years.</p>
<p>Scientists do not know for sure how our brains developed this capability, but
they suspect it is based on what Feldman Barrett calls the Five Cs:</p>
<dl>
<dt>Creativity</dt>
<dd>We are able to draw a border and then invent a country with a
national identity and a bunch of rules.</dd>
<dt>Communication</dt>
<dd>Millions of brains are subsequently able to communicate our
new country and its rules to each other, and to keep each other up to date.</dd>
<dt>Copying</dt>
<dd>Our children learn how to operate by copying us. Similarly, we
learn form each other by copying behaviour.</dd>
<dt>Cooperation</dt>
<dd>We cooperate on a geographical scale. The book quite casually
mentions the example of food distribution, all the way from farms anywhere on
the globe onto your plate for dinner.</dd>
<dt>Compression</dt>
<dd>This concept definitely needs a bit more space, so I&rsquo;ll
continue in the text below.</dd>
</dl>
<p>You&rsquo;ll recall from a previous lesson that <a href="#your-brain-is-a-network">your brain is a (giant) network</a>.</p>
<p>What was not emphasised in that lesson (or my notes), is the massive
abstraction capability inherent in our brain architectures.</p>
<p>There are millions of neurons bringing in signals from the photosensitive
receptors in your retina. After a few centimetres, those neural pathways
connect <em>in groups</em> to summarising neurons, which combine each group&rsquo;s
information into a single signal.</p>
<p>All of those summarising neurons output into yet another layer of
well-connected summarising neurons.</p>
<p>This process of successive summarisation continues all the way into the front
of your brain, which contains the highest level of summarisation, that is, the
fewest number of mega-neurons that aggregate effectively massive amounts of
information from all of the lower levels indirectly feeding into them.</p>
<p>I hope that it is obvious now why this successive summarisation is also
referred to as <em>compression</em>.</p>
<p>So what does this <em>compression</em> buy us humans?</p>
<p>This extreme level of compression enables us to <em>think
abstractly</em>. Abstraction, together with the rest of the Five Cs enables us to
create and maintain social reality.</p>
<p>Feldman Barrett wraps it up like this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The wiring of your cerebral cortex makes compression possible. Compression
enables sensory integration. Sensory integration enables
abstraction. Abstraction permits your highly complex brain to issue flexible
predictions based on the functions of things rather than on their physical
form. That is creativity. And you can share these predictions by way of
communication, cooperation, and copying. That is how the Five Cs empower a
human brain to create and share social reality</p>
</blockquote>
<p>No other animal brain can achieve the extreme levels of compression and
abstraction required to create social reality.</p>
<p>As if this chapter in the book was not amazing enough, Feldman Barrett
discusses the benefits and disadvantages of our reality creation superpower.</p>
<p>As an example of the disadvantages, I strongly agree with her view on our often
stupid fascination with boxes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For example, humans vary tremendously, like every animal species does. But
unlike the rest of the animal kingdom, we organize some of this variation into
little boxes with labels such as race, gender, and nationality. We treat the
labeled boxes as if they&rsquo;re part of nature when in fact we build them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I would like to conclude this section with a part of the book&rsquo;s conclusion to
this inspiring chapter:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Social reality is a superpower that emerges from an ensemble of human
brains. It gives us the possibility to chart our own destiny and even influence
the evolution of our species. We can make up abstract concepts, share them,
weave them into a reality, and conquer just about any environment &ndash; natural,
political, or social &ndash; as long as we work together. We have more control over
reality than we might think. We also have more responsibility for reality than
we might realize.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="a-summary-of-the-summary">A summary of the summary</h2>
<p>For those of you that have no time to read the book or even these book notes,
Feldman Barrett has a super compact summary of her seven and a half lessons in
the epilogue.</p>
<p>The human brain is:</p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>A brain that constructs such rich mental experiences that we feel like
emotion and reason wrestle inside us</li>
<li>A brain that&rsquo;s so complex that we describe it by metaphors and mistake them
for knowledge</li>
<li>A brain that&rsquo;s so skilled at rewiring itself that we think we&rsquo;re born with
all sorts of things that we actually learn</li>
<li>A brain that&rsquo;s so effective at hallucinating that we believe we see the world
objectively, and so fast at predicting that we mistake our movements for
reactions</li>
<li>A brain that regulates other brains so invisibly that we presume we&rsquo;re
independent of each other</li>
<li>A brain that creates so many kinds of minds that we assume there&rsquo;s a single
human nature to explain them all</li>
<li>A brain that&rsquo;s so good at believing its own inventions that we mistake social
reality for the natural world</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Notes on the book "Creativity, Inc." by Ed Catmull with Amy Wallace</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 14:57:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/</guid><description> You are reading the consolidated and refined version of the notes and excerpts I made while reading the book Creativity Inc..
This is by no means a complete summary of the book, but rather a collection of lessons that I found note-worthy.
Overview The book deals with the building and maintenance of sustainable creative organizations, painted on the rich background of Ed Catmull&amp;rsquo;s role in the construction and running of Pixar and later also of Disney Animation.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>You are reading the consolidated and refined version of the notes and excerpts
I made while reading the book <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18077903-creativity-inc"><em>Creativity Inc.</em></a>.</p>
<p>This is by no means a complete summary of the book, but rather a collection of
lessons that I found note-worthy.</p>
<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>
<p>The book deals with the building and maintenance of sustainable creative
organizations, painted on the rich background of Ed Catmull&rsquo;s role in the
construction and running of Pixar and later also of Disney Animation.</p>
<p>The first and most substantial part of the book is the entertaining and
edifying story of Ed Catmull and of the birth and evolution of the company
called Pixar.</p>
<p>The second part contains a number of extended guidelines for the building and
running of creative organizations such as Pixar and Disney Animation.</p>
<p>In the following, each section (except for the Catmull introduction) deals with
a specific learning or episode. In theory, each should make sense when read by
itself.</p>
<h2 id="who-is-ed-catmull">Who is Ed Catmull?</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edwin%5FCatmull">Dr Edward Catmull</a> is one of the most important pioneers of making films with
computer graphics.</li>
<li>He was one of the three founders of Pixar, together with Steve Jobs and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John%5FLasseter">John
Lasseter</a>.</li>
<li>You might recall that Pixar released the movie Toy Story in 1995, a
fantastically successful movie that revolutionised film-making with computer
graphics.</li>
<li>Later when Pixar and Disney Animation merged, Dr Catmull also became the
president of Disney Animation.</li>
<li>Under his guidance, both Pixar and later Disney Animation released a slew of
award-winning and, more importantly, culture defining films. Besides the Toy
Story series, think about Monsters, Inc., Finding Nemo and The Incredibles.</li>
</ul>
<p>He made the first digitally rendered 3D movie, called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A%5FComputer%5FAnimated%5FHand">A Computer Animated Hand</a>,
in the spring of 1972, by laboriously and manually recording the surface of his
hand as 3D triangles, and then using computers to animate and render this
surface.</p>
<p>He also invented the Z-buffer, independently from Wolfgang Straßer who
described the same technique 8 months previously, a technique for quickly
rendering opaque shapes that correctly occlude each other, and a technique that
every single computer graphics student learns about as one of their first
orders of business.</p>
<h2 id="core-presumption-your-people-are-good-your-organization-needs-to-support-them">Core presumption: Your people are good, your organization needs to support them</h2>
<p>Early in the book a core presumption is stated:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We start from the presumption that our people are talented and want to
contribute. We accept that, without meaning to, our company is stifling that
talent in myriad unseen ways. Finally, we try to identify those impediments and
fix them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This might be surprising to some, but in an organization that has its core the
pursuit of creativity, this approach is the most logical.</p>
<p>The creativity can&rsquo;t come from anywhere <em>but</em> the people, so such an
organization will reasonably do the best they can to hire the best people that
they can.</p>
<p>Therefore, if the output is not as good as the people the organization has
hired, the organization is somehow not sufficiently supporting the people.</p>
<p>Similar reasoning should apply for engineering companies.</p>
<h2 id="the-story-is-more-important-than-the-technology">The story is more important than the technology</h2>
<p>While Ed Catmull was the computer graphics guy initially, and later graduated
to transcendent leadership status, and Steve Jobs was the business brain, John
Lasseter was the story guy.</p>
<p>Catmull makes it clear early in the book that without Lasseter&rsquo;s story-telling
genius, Pixar would not have succeeded.</p>
<p>The first of many examples, he illustrates this wonderfully with the success of
the first Toy Story movie.</p>
<p>This was a ground-breaking technical achievement at the time: A full-length
fully computer-generated animation movie that became an international
blockbuster.</p>
<p>However, when Catmull tells the story of its release, he mentions quite
specifically the fact that viewers and critics were raving far more about the
story than about the amazing technical achievements that made the movie
possible.</p>
<p>Even for those of us who are not in the business of computer animation, this
holds true: People always find the story much more important than anything else
that might have been involved in any endeavour.</p>
<h2 id="reaching-a-life-goal-can-set-you-adrift">Reaching a life goal can set you adrift</h2>
<p>In the introduction, Catmull tells the story of how they (Pixar) had fulfilled
his life goal of making the first computer animated film with the fantastic
success that was the Toy Story.</p>
<p>He writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Now, the goal that had been a driving force in my life had been reached, and
there was an enormous sense of relief and exhilaration &ndash;at least at first. In
the wake of Toy Story&rsquo;s release, we took the company public, raising the kind
of money that would ensure our future as an independent production house, and
began work on two new feature-length projects, A Bug&rsquo;s Life and Toy
Story 2. Everything was going our way, and yet I felt adrift. In fulfilling a
goal, I had lost some essential framework. &ldquo;Is this really what I want to do?&rdquo;
I began asking myself.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">written before about the phenomenon of fulfilled life goals leading to
tricky vacuums</a>, but my advice then was to favour <em>life directions</em> rather than
goals.</p>
<p>In that same chapter, Catmull writes that it took him another year to find his
new goal, after having seen so many great companies with smart leaders (he
mentions Silicon Graphics, Cray Computer, Sun Microsystems) start failing after
a brilliant and creative start.</p>
<p>His new mission would be:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I would devote myself to learning how to build not just a successful company
but a sustainable creative culture. As I turned my attention from solving
technical problems to engaging with the philosophy of sound management, I was
excited once again &ndash;and sure that our second act could be as exhilarating as our
first.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is great seeing this evolution from solving mostly technical problems to
solving mostly human problems.</p>
<p>Interestingly, in chapter 10 &ldquo;Broadening our view&rdquo; he explains that the future
is not a destination, but a direction!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The future is not a destination &ndash; it is a direction. It is our job, then, to
work each day to chart the right course and make corrections when, inevitably,
we stray.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="ed-catmull-struck-the-academic-lottery-at-university">Ed Catmull struck the academic lottery at University</h2>
<p>He graduated from the University of Utah in 1969 with a degree in physics and
one in computer science. He was planning to continue his graduate studies in
programming language design, but then he met Ivan Sutherland, one of the
pioneers of interactive computer graphics.</p>
<p>Catmull joined the lab of Sutherland and Evans, a place which attracted the
brightest students, and then gave them freedom and resources to experiment.</p>
<p>This collaborative and inspiring place would form part of the inspiration for
the later creation of Pixar.</p>
<p>Catmull&rsquo;s lab mates were themselves pretty legendary:</p>
<ul>
<li>Jim Clark, who later founded Silicon Graphics and Netscape</li>
<li>John Warnock, who later co-found Adobe</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan%5FKay">Alan Kay</a>, a pioneer in object-oriented programming and windowing GUIs</li>
</ul>
<p>He also writes about the culture and the group dynamics in the lab:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This tension between the individual&rsquo;s personal creative contribution and the
leverage of the group is a dynamic that exists in all creative environments,
but this would be my first taste of it. On one end of the spectrum, I noticed,
we had the genius who seemed to do amazing work on his or her own; on the other
end, we had the group that excelled precisely because of its multiplicity of
views. How, then, should we balance these two extremes, I wondered.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="two-steve-jobs-moments-from-the-book">Two Steve Jobs moments from the book</h2>
<h3 id="steve-jobs-and-bill-joy-two-great-egos-at-the-1985-siggraph-conference">Steve Jobs and Bill Joy: Two great egos at the 1985 SIGGRAPH conference</h3>
<p>Steve had previously offered to buy the commercially struggling graphics group
(what would later become Pixar) from Lucasfilm, but that deal had not gone
through. At that point, he wanted the group to build him a new computer, and
not to pursue its computer animation ambitions.</p>
<p>Since then, Steve had started NeXT, and at the conference was chatting again
with Ed Catmull to see what could be worked out.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As we talked, we came upon Bill Joy, one of the founders of Sun Computer. Bill,
like Steve, was an extraordinarily bright, competitive, articulate, and
opinionated person. I don&rsquo;t remember what they talked about as we stood there,
but I&rsquo;ll never forget the way they talked: standing nose to nose, their arms
behind their backs, swaying from side to side &ndash;in perfect sync &ndash;completely
oblivious to anything going on around them. This went on for quite a while,
until Steve had to break off to go meet someone.</p>
<p>After Steve left, Bill turned to me and said, &ldquo;Boy, is he arrogant.&rdquo;</p>
<p>When Steve came by our booth again later, he walked up to me and said of Bill:
&ldquo;Boy, is he arrogant.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I remember being struck by this clash-of-the-titans moment. I was amused by the
fact that each man could see ego in the other but not in himself.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="the-steve-jobs-method-of-resolving-disagreements">The Steve Jobs method of resolving disagreements</h3>
<p>Shortly after the SIGGRAPH conference, Steve made another offer to buy the
graphics group (the company that would later be known as Pixar), but this time
it was clear that he would let the company be itself and govern itself.</p>
<p>In preparation for the possible collaboration, Catmull asked Jobs &ldquo;how things
got resolved when people disagree with him&rdquo;.</p>
<p>His answer was:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When I don&rsquo;t see eye to eye with somebody, I just take the time to explain it
better, so they understand the way it should be.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I found that humorous, and in-line with the <em>public</em> image of Jobs.</p>
<p>However, please note that Catmull wrote a truly heartfelt and filled with
respect portrait of Jobs in the afterword titled &ldquo;The Steve We Knew&rdquo;.</p>
<p>This gives a relatively scarce glimpse into the pivotal role Steve Jobs played
in building Pixar (all the while in parallel with leading Apple into its
trillion dollar future!), but more importantly into the great friendship
between Ed Catmull, John Lasseter and himself.</p>
<h2 id="anybody-can-stop-the-assembly-line-an-american-in-japan">Anybody can stop the assembly line: An American in Japan</h2>
<p>In Chapter 3, A Defining Goal, I read the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The responsibility for finding and fixing problems should be assigned to every
employee, from the most senior manager to the lowliest person on the production
line. If anyone at any level spotted a problem in the manufacturing process,
Deming believed, they should be encouraged (and expected) to stop the assembly
line.</p>
<p>Japanese companies that implemented Deming&rsquo;s ideas made it easy for workers to
do so: They installed a cord that anyone could pull in order to bring
production to a halt.</p>
<p>Before long, Japanese companies were enjoying unheard-of levels of quality,
productivity, and market share.</p>
<p>Deming&rsquo;s approach &ndash; and Toyota&rsquo;s, too &ndash; gave ownership of and responsibility
for a product&rsquo;s quality to the people who were most involved in its
creation. Instead of merely repeating an action, workers could suggest changes,
call out problems, and &ndash;this next element seemed particularly important to
me &ndash;feel the pride that came when they helped fix what was broken. This resulted
in continuous improvement, driving out flaws and improving quality</p>
</blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: It is important to ensure that all of the people in an organization can
take ownership of and responsibility for that organization&rsquo;s output. This
necessarily includes giving everyone a certain degree of agency in how that
output comes into being.</p>
<h2 id="focus-on-the-people-then-the-ideas-will-come">Focus on the people, then the ideas will come</h2>
<p>In Chapter 3, we (re-)learn that people are more important than ideas. Focus on
the people, and then the ideas will come. In more detail:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To reiterate, it is the focus on people &ndash; their work habits, their talents,
their values &ndash; that is absolutely central to any creative venture. And in the
wake of Toy Story 2, I saw that more clearly than I ever had. That clarity, in
turn, led me to make some changes.</p>
<p>Looking around, I realized we had a few traditions that didn&rsquo;t put people
first. For example, we had a development department, as do all movie studios,
that was charged with seeking out and developing ideas to make into films. Now
I saw that this made no sense.</p>
<p>Going forward, the development department&rsquo;s charter would be not to develop
scripts but to hire good people, figure out what they needed, assign them to
projects that matched their skills, and make sure they functioned well
together.</p>
<p>To this day, we keep adjusting and fiddling with this model, but the underlying
goals remain the same: Find, develop, and support good people, and they in turn
will find, develop, and own good ideas.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="the-braintrust">The Braintrust</h2>
<p>In Chapter 5, Honesty and Candor, Catmull writes the following about the Pixar
Braintrust:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Braintrust, which meets every few months or so to assess each movie we&rsquo;re
making, is our primary delivery system for straight talk. Its premise is
simple: Put smart, passionate people in a room together, charge them with
identifying and solving problems, and encourage them to be candid with one
another. People who would feel obligated to be honest somehow feel freer when
asked for their candor; they have a choice about whether to give it, and thus,
when they do give it, it tends to be genuine. The Braintrust is one of the most
important traditions at Pixar. It&rsquo;s not foolproof &ndash; sometimes its interactions
only serve to highlight the difficulties of achieving candor &ndash; but when we get
it right, the results are phenomenal. The Braintrust sets the tone for
everything we do.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To paraphrase:</p>
<p>The Braintrust at Pixar is a group of the most senior and knowledgeable folks
who regularly get together to give <em>non-binding</em> feedback about in-progress
projects to the responsible teams.</p>
<p>Pixar works continuously on the culture to ensure that criticism can be openly
given, and received as easily as possible. See also <a href="#postmortems">Postmortems</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-power-of-rework-rework-rework">The power of rework, rework, rework</h2>
<p>It came as a great surprise to me that &ldquo;early on, all Pixar movies suck&rdquo;.</p>
<p>They recognize this, and accept it, and then use it to their advantage by
pushing that sucky movie through many cycles of criticism and improvement.</p>
<p>Gradually through this sometimes uncomfortable evolution the project turns into
a masterpiece!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This idea &ndash; that all the movies we now think of as brilliant were, at one time,
terrible &ndash; is a hard concept for many to grasp. But think about how easy it would
be for a movie about talking toys to feel derivative, sappy, or overtly
merchandise-driven. Think about how off-putting a movie about rats preparing
food could be, or how risky it must&rsquo;ve seemed to start WALL-E with 39
dialogue-free minutes. We dare to attempt these stories, but we don&rsquo;t get them
right on the first pass. And this is as it should be. Creativity has to start
somewhere, and we are true believers in the power of bracing, candid feedback
and the iterative process &ndash; reworking, reworking, and reworking again, until a
flawed story finds its throughline or a hollow character finds its soul.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This story really resonated with me: Creativity (and perhaps even brilliance in
some cases) just means keeping at something for long enough.</p>
<h2 id="protect-the-new--ideas">Protect the new (ideas)</h2>
<p>At the start of Chapter 7, The Hungry Beast and the Ugly Baby, Catmull writes
the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When I advocate for protecting the new, then, I am using the word somewhat
differently. I am saying that when someone hatches an original idea, it may be
ungainly and poorly defined, but it is also the opposite of established and
entrenched &ndash; and that is precisely what is most exciting about it. If, while
in this vulnerable state, it is exposed to naysayers who fail to see its
potential or lack the patience to let it evolve, it could be destroyed. Part of
our job is to protect the new from people who don&rsquo;t understand that in order
for greatness to emerge, there must be phases of not-so-greatness.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This sounds like it can be quite tricky, balancing criticism that is sometimes
very much required with &ldquo;protecting the new&rdquo;.</p>
<h2 id="a-continuous-balancing-act-between-groups-in-the-organization">A continuous balancing act between groups in the organization</h2>
<p>In Chapter 7, The Hungry Beast, Catmull talks about the phenomenon where
sub-groups in an organisation have conflicting goals, and instinctively, each
group will try to have their goals satisfied at the cost of other groups.</p>
<p>The concrete and simple example that he gives is that if the director &ldquo;wins&rdquo;,
the film will probably be too long, whereas if the marketing people &ldquo;win&rdquo;, the
film will mimic other films that have succeeded in the past, and so on.</p>
<p>However, if any of these competing groups win, the organisation will lose.</p>
<p>He writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In an unhealthy culture, each group believes that if their objectives trump the
goals of the other groups, the company will be better off. In a healthy
culture, all constituencies recognize the importance of balancing competing
desires &ndash; they want to be heard, but they don&rsquo;t have to win. Their interaction
with one another &ndash; the push and pull that occurs naturally when talented
people are given clear goals &ndash; yields the balance we seek. But that only happens
if they understand that achieving balance is a central goal of the company.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To me this was quite an insightful realisation. The goal is to maintain the
healthy tension between groups on opposite sides of the table, to reach that
balance that will result in the best possible outcome for the whole
organisation.</p>
<p>However, he goes on to explain that this balance is not a static state, but
rather a continuous interplay of often opposing forces, as reality, and all the
people involved, also continually change.</p>
<p>In short, it&rsquo;s a 1. balancing 2. act. :)</p>
<h2 id="how-to-deal-with-constant-change-and-people-s-desire-for-its-opposite">How to deal with constant change and people&rsquo;s desire for its opposite</h2>
<p>At the start of Chapter 8, Change and Randomness, Catmull tells the funny and
endearing story of the speech he gave to the Pixar employees when they decided
to sell Pixar to Disney in an immensely favourable deal.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We knew that the prospect of our little studio being absorbed into a much
larger entity would worry many people. While we&rsquo;d worked hard to put safeguards
in place that would ensure our independence, we still expected our employees to
be fearful that the merger would negatively impact our culture.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll say more about the specific steps we took to protect Pixar in a later
chapter, but here I want to discuss what happened when, in my eagerness to ease
my colleagues' fears, I stood up and assured them that Pixar would not change.</p>
<p>It was one of the dumbest things I&rsquo;ve ever said.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Catmull understandably wanted to assuage the fears of his people by promising
that nothing would change, when he actually meant that they would do their best
to maintain what made Pixar special, within the much more dynamic context of
new possibilities and opportunities afforded by the new combined companies.</p>
<p>What then happened, quite obvious in retrospect, is that every time Pixar
wanted to embrace some new opportunity, employees would line up at Catmull&rsquo;s
office to complain that he had promised that nothing would change.</p>
<p>This illustrates how important it is to invest more energy and perhaps suffer
pain upfront in order to analyse people&rsquo;s fears and address them as
specifically as possible, whilst leaving room for the inevitable evolution and
adaptation of a healthy organization.</p>
<p>A few pages later, Catmull writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>WHAT IS IT, exactly, that people are really afraid of when they say they don&rsquo;t
like change? There is the discomfort of being confused or the extra work or
stress the change may require. For many people, changing course is also a sign
of weakness, tantamount to admitting that you don&rsquo;t know what you are
doing. This strikes me as particularly bizarre &ndash; personally, I think the
person who can&rsquo;t change his or her mind is dangerous. Steve Jobs was known for
changing his mind instantly in the light of new facts, and I don&rsquo;t know anyone
who thought he was weak.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>People are naturally afraid of the additional energy expenditure required by
change, which is understandable. It&rsquo;s less understandable that people believe
that leadership can predict the complete course of the future, and hence should
not need to change direction. Direction changes can happen daily!</p>
<p>I found the example of Steve Jobs, known for his stubbornness, changing his
mind instantly when faced with new evidence, inspiring.</p>
<h2 id="profit-from-your-mistakes-by-eliminating-the-blame-game">Profit from your mistakes by eliminating the blame game</h2>
<p>In chapter 8, one can read about that time when <em>someone</em> at Pixar did an <code>rm -rf *</code> on all of the Toy Story 2 media files.</p>
<p>Those of you who know, might just have broken out in a sympathetic cold sweat&hellip;</p>
<p>Those of you who don&rsquo;t: <code>rm -rf *</code> is a destructive deletion of
<em>everything</em>. The whole movie during development at that point, equal to 30
person years.</p>
<p>Ok, now you are probably thinking: Of course Pixar had backups.</p>
<p>Well, yes they did, but as the more experienced under you will probably guess
by now, they discovered right at this point that there had been a fundamental
issue with the backup system, whereby there were no usable backups.</p>
<p>Using this exceptional story as an example, Catmull makes two really great
points.</p>
<p>First, treat all setbacks, gigantic (like this one) down to really tiny,
exactly the same.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes a big event happens that changes everything. When it does, it tends
to affirm the human tendency to treat big events as fundamentally different
from smaller ones. That&rsquo;s a problem, inside companies. When we put setbacks
into two buckets &ndash; the &ldquo;business as usual&rdquo; bucket and the &ldquo;holy cow&rdquo; bucket &ndash;
and use a different mindset for each, we are signing up for trouble. We become
so caught up in our big problems that we ignore the little ones, failing to
realize that some of our small problems will have long-term consequences &ndash; and
are, therefore, big problems in the making.</p>
<p>What&rsquo;s needed, in my view, is to approach big and small problems with the same
set of values and emotions, because they are, in fact, self-similar. In other
words, it is important that we don&rsquo;t freak out or start blaming people when
some threshold &ndash; the &ldquo;holy cow&rdquo; bucket I referred to earlier &ndash; is reached. We
need to be humble enough to recognize that unforeseen things can and do happen
that are nobody&rsquo;s fault.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Second, instead of getting out your giant set of The Blame Game, deal with the
results of the setback, learn from it, and put measures in place to make your
systems robust to these sorts of issues in the future:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The real lesson of the event, though, was in how we dealt with its
aftermath. In short, we didn&rsquo;t waste time playing the blame game. After the
loss of the film, our list of priorities, in order, were: (1) Restore the film;
(2) Fix our backup systems; (3) Install precautionary restrictions to make it
much more difficult to access the deletion command directly.  Notably, one item
was not on our list: Find the person responsible who typed the wrong command
and punish him or her.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You&rsquo;ll be happy to hear that thanks to a crew member who had previously worked
at home due to the arrival of a second baby, they discovered that there was
still a scheduled automatic task which copied all the movie assets to a special
computer setup at her home.</p>
<p>Toy Story 2: Rescued!</p>
<p>Taking a step back, this looks, like so many other of these lessons from Pixar,
like an organization that follows the scientific approach: Instead of blaming
people, rather analyse and learn from the problems themselves.</p>
<h2 id="on-the-pitfalls-of-hierarchy-in-organizations">On the pitfalls of hierarchy in organizations</h2>
<p>In Chapter 9, <em>The Hidden</em>, Catmull writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;ve worked in some highly structured, &ldquo;hierarchical&rdquo; environments that
inspired top-notch work and a healthy interchange between colleagues.  At the
same time, there are some hierarchal environments that are a nightmare.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s what turns a successful hierarchy into one that impedes progress: when
too many people begin, subconsciously, to equate their own value and that of
others with where they fall in the pecking order.</p>
<p>Thus, they focus their energies on managing upward while treating people
beneath them on the organizational chart poorly.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In short: Beware when the pecking order becomes important.</p>
<h2 id="attain-clarity-by-learning-how-to-combine-different-viewpoints">Attain clarity by learning how to combine different viewpoints</h2>
<p>From Chapter 9, <em>The Hidden</em>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>So my colleagues know more than I do about what&rsquo;s going on in any given
department at any given moment. On the other hand, I know more about issues
that people working in production do not: schedule requirements, resource
conflicts, market problems, or personnel issues that may be difficult or
inappropriate to share with everyone. Each of us, then, draws conclusions based
on incomplete pictures. It would be wrong for me to assume that my limited view
is necessarily better.</p>
<p>[text omitted]</p>
<p>When faced with complexity, it is reassuring to tell ourselves that we can
uncover and understand every facet of every problem if we just try hard
enough. But that&rsquo;s a fallacy. The better approach, I believe, is to accept that
we can&rsquo;t understand every facet of a complex environment and to focus, instead,
on techniques to deal with combining different viewpoints. If we start with the
attitude that different viewpoints are additive rather than competitive, we
become more effective because our ideas or decisions are honed and tempered by
that discourse. In a healthy, creative culture, the people in the trenches feel
free to speak up and bring to light differing views that can help give us
clarity.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In short: Accept that usually everyone will have an extremely limited
understanding of any issue. Become great at and foster a culture of combining
the different viewpoints of different folks in order to gain clarity.</p>
<h2 id="beware-mental-models-based-on-limited-evidence-and-beliefs">Beware mental models based on limited evidence and beliefs</h2>
<p>Closer to the end of chapter 9, The Hidden:</p>
<p>Related to the previous observation, where viewpoints are limited simply
because they are housed in single individuals who can only see what&rsquo;s visible
to them in the organization, limited evidence decision-making can also happen
due to people&rsquo;s &ldquo;beliefs&rdquo;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Somehow, though, this episode led Pixar&rsquo;s directors to decide that, going
forward, they should write the first drafts of their movies and thus be
credited as writers. This belief shaped our model of how we should work as a
studio, and this, in turn, affected how several of the directors defined what
it meant to be a director. The problem was that these were all wrong
conclusions, based on a single bad experience. And that led to more problems.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What I take from this is that one should be really careful about the emotions
that can be caused by a single event, and even more so when one tries to draw
conclusions that feel logical although they are primarily fueled by one&rsquo;s
beliefs.</p>
<h2 id="the-hidden-and-how-to-deal-with-the-hidden">The Hidden and how to deal with The Hidden</h2>
<p>At the end of chapter 9, The Hidden, which is also the last chapter of part 2
of the book, Catmull has the following to say about how to deal with The
Hidden, that is, everything in your organization that is normally hidden from
sight, because of the fundamental limitations in human communication and
understanding:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Hidden &ndash; and our acknowledgement of it &ndash; is an absolutely essential part of
rooting out what impedes our progress: clinging to what works, fearing change,
and deluding ourselves about our roles in our own success.</p>
<p>Candor, safety, research, self-assessment, and protecting the new are all
mechanisms we can use to confront the unknown and to keep the chaos and fear to
a minimum. These concepts don&rsquo;t necessarily make anything easier, but they can
help us uncover hidden problems and, thus, enable us to address them.</p>
</blockquote>
<dl>
<dt>Candor</dt>
<dd>Accept the sort of honesty by our fellows that can help us to
understand our limitations and improve. It makes a huge difference on both
sides of the transaction when the candor&rsquo;s sole intention is improvement, and
not placing blame.</dd>
<dt>Safety</dt>
<dd>This refers either to the implied feeling of safety of the bearer
of criticism, and/or to the safety of an organization which by nature has to
change, but does keep its people and its core values safe.</dd>
<dt>Research</dt>
<dd>Gather knowledge and measurements from everywhere. Process what
is learned, integrate it and act on it.</dd>
<dt>Self-assessment</dt>
<dd>The organization, or more accurately the people in it,
have to dedicated themselves to continuous and true self-assessment in order
to bring any hidden issues to light.</dd>
<dt>Protecting the new</dt>
<dd>Give new ideas that are still forming, but could have
great potential, the room and the resources to grow. (see chapter 7)</dd>
</dl>
<p>Looking at this list, one would be forgiven for stating that what Catmull is
proposing is running an organization like a scientist with a heart.</p>
<h2 id="eight-practical-methods-towards-a-sustainable-creative-organization">Eight practical methods towards a sustainable creative organization</h2>
<p>Chapter 10</p>
<h3 id="dailies-or-solving-problems-together">Dailies, or Solving Problems Together</h3>
<p>Pixar has worked really hard to integrate deeply into their culture on openness
to criticism, both on the giving and the receiving end of the transaction.</p>
<p>This is even more difficult than it sounds: One needs strong leadership, and
the consistent and trustworthy message that people should be free to say what
they think, and people should be open to all of that feedback, because the
single most important goal is to help people and their creative output improve.</p>
<p>Catmull writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Dailies are a key part of Pixar culture, not just because of what they
accomplish &ndash; constructive midstream feedback &ndash; but because of how they
accomplish it. Participants have learned to check their egos at the door &ndash;
they are about to show incomplete work to their director and colleagues</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He continues further down:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The whole activity becomes socially rewarding and productive. To participate
fully each morning requires empathy, clarity, generosity, and the ability to
listen. Dailies are designed to promote everyone&rsquo;s ability to be open to
others, in the recognition that individual creativity is magnified by the
people around you. The result: We see more clearly</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This sounds like a super difficult but amazing achievement in any company that
is serious about its people and about the quality that it wants to produce.</p>
<p>Even from my short experience, I know that this can only succeed with
unrelenting hard-work and dedication of those who are tasked with maintaining
this unique environment that is under continuous strain from the humans that
are part of it, and who stand to gain the most by its continuation.</p>
<h3 id="research-trips">Research trips</h3>
<p>This section talks about the interesting phenomenon that for creative people it
often feels like the safer choice to mash-up the great bits of previous
successes from one&rsquo;s field. However, this work is by definition derivative and
probably mediocre, when the creative person ideally produces a work of art that
is new and unique. This latter choice carries risk.</p>
<p>When Pixar was working on the movie <em>Ratatouille</em>, members of the team went to
France for two weeks to dine in Michelin-starred restaurants, to visit their
kitches and to talk with the chefs.</p>
<p>That sounds like a tough life. ;)</p>
<p>Catmull mentions a number of Pixar movies where team members would travel the
globe to understand better the subject of their art, and to have a real shot at
authenticity.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know how many other organizations have this sort of clear motivation or
funding for these kinds of far-flung research trips, but what I extract from
this method that it makes sense for creative organizations to prioritize
research activities that have a high probability of taking team members out of
their comfort zones.</p>
<p>Catmull writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In any business, it&rsquo;s important to do your homework, but the point I&rsquo;m making
goes beyond merely getting the facts straight. Research trips challenge our
preconceived notions and keep clichés at bay. They fuel inspiration. They are,
I believe, what keeps us creating rather than copying</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="the-power-of-limits">The Power of Limits</h3>
<p>This technique comes down to imposing limits on the way people work, or rather
making the existing limits clear to them, so that they come up with new and
interesting solutions:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; the limits we impose internally, if deployed correctly, can be a tool
to force people to amend the way they are working and, sometimes, to invent
another way. The very concept of a limit implies that you can&rsquo;t do everything
you want &ndash; so we must think of smarter ways to work</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Catmull tells the entertaining story that every single one of the 90 compact
discs in the pile that was collapsed by the character Boo in the movie
<em>Monsters, Inc.</em> was in fact perfectly shaded.</p>
<p>This means that the animators hand spent a number of person weeks carefully
specifying the full lighting equations for each of those 90 CDs, when the scene
was only 3 seconds long, and it was physically not possible for any viewer of
the movie to apprecate the detail in the CDs.</p>
<p>While everyone loves attention to detail, those person weeks could have been
used to work on something that had more actual impact. (<em>Monsters, Inc.</em> was
already a huge success already, so this point is somewhat academic.)</p>
<p>Catmull says that in this case &ldquo;the desire for quality had gone well beyond
rationality&rdquo;.</p>
<p>They later went on to develop a physical system of popsicle sticks, where each
stick represented a person week of effort. During the making of <em>The
Incredibles</em>, they would have next to each character the number of popsicle
weeks dedicated to the animation of that character. If someone, for example the
director, came with a request for some additional work, they would have to
decide from which other character or aspect a popsicle stick could be removed
to create time for that new request.</p>
<p>This helped greatly in creating visibility of how much time and effort was
dedicated to which aspect of the project, and hence helped with the making of
good decisions.</p>
<h3 id="integrating-technology-and-art">Integrating Technology and Art</h3>
<p>Pixar is quite uniquely positioned for the almost equal-parts integration of
technology and art. Their product, computer animated movies, by definition have
to combine these two streams.</p>
<p>Catmull writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When everything is functioning as it should be, art and technology play off
each other and spur each other to new heights. Given how different the two
mindsets can be, it can be tough to keep them aligned and engaged with each
other. But in my view, the effort is always worth it. Our specialized skills
and mental models are challenged when we integrate with people who are
different. If we can constantly change and improve our models by using
technology in the pursuit of art, we keep ourselves fresh</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For companies that are not pixar, the advice is still very much
noteworthy. Engineering-focused organizations can do with more creativity, and
creative organizations can do with more engineering.</p>
<p>More generally, the observation that &ldquo;Our specialized skills and mental models
are challenged when we integrate with people who are different&rdquo; &ndash; is relevant
and truly important.</p>
<h3 id="short-experiments">Short Experiments</h3>
<p>Pixar has a long tradition of making amazing short films, many of which you&rsquo;ll
probably recognize if you see them again.</p>
<p>They intended to use these short films to experiment with new techniques and
with new stories, and even to give less experienced colleagues the chance to
gain some experience.</p>
<p>However, although the short films ended up reaching neither goal (the
full-length movies drove innovation the most; the short films were so different
from full-lengths that the experience did not carry over that much), it helped
greatly by getting Pixar employees to work together in smaller teams, and most
importantly, it enabled Pixar to fail at small scale.</p>
<p>In short, they were able to make mistakes on these relatively small projects,
&ldquo;miniature trains&rdquo; as Catmull calls them, that helped them avoid &ldquo;train wrecks
with real trains&rdquo;</p>
<p>In software development, there is a related concept called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spike%5F(software%5Fdevelopment)">a spike</a>.</p>
<h3 id="learning-to-see">Learning to see</h3>
<p>Here he uses the example of the 1979 book <em>Drawing on the Right Side of the
Brain</em> by Betty Edwards, elements of which were taught in drawing workshops
given by Elyse Klaidman at Pixar.</p>
<p>In this, people are instructed for example to turn the picture or photo of a
face upside-down before trying to draw the face.</p>
<p>When you don&rsquo;t do this, strong mental models of the human face override what
you&rsquo;re actually seeing, ironically complicating the drawing of a good looking
face!</p>
<p>The lesson here is that one should apply similar efforts to enable the elective
suppression of one&rsquo;s mental models, so that it becomes possible on occasion to
look past preconceptions and biases in order to see more than one usually would.</p>
<p>Catmull wrote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The real point is that you can learn to set aside preconceptions. It isn&rsquo;t that
you don&rsquo;t have biases, more that there are ways of learning to ignore them
while considering a problem.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="postmortems">Postmortems</h3>
<p>Judging by the amount of text here, and more importantly the amount of energy
Pixar puts into their postmortems, this is an important element of their
machinery.</p>
<p>They have these postmortems after every movie project. The idea is to
retrospectively explore and gather data from the whole project, with the
following five goals:</p>
<dl>
<dt>Consolidate What&rsquo;s Been Learned</dt>
<dd>It&rsquo;s usually not possible to integrate
lessons as they are being learned during the project. During the postmortem,
there is time to put everything together into a larger and coherent body of
knowledge.</dd>
<dt>Teach Others Who Weren&rsquo;t There</dt>
<dd>This is obvious.</dd>
<dt>Don&rsquo;t Let Resentments Fester</dt>
<dd>People express their frustrations in a
respectful manner. This helps with closure, and moving on.</dd>
<dt>Use the Schedule to Force Reflection</dt>
<dd>This is about the <em>preparation</em> for
the postmortem being even more important than the postmortem itself.</dd>
<dt>Pay It Forward</dt>
<dd>All of the lessons consolidated during the postmortem will
be used to safeguard and optimize future projects.</dd>
</dl>
<p>It was surprising to me to learn that these posed quite a challenge at Pixar,
as humans would naturally game the <em>format</em> of the postmortem every time. In
short, the risk associated with being honest often results in people pulling
punches when they should actually be giving criticism.</p>
<p>What they did was to change the format of every new postmortem, in order to
maximise the probability of honest feedback and no pulling of punches.</p>
<p>Catmull proposes an additional trick to enable people to give complete and
honest feedback:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One technique I&rsquo;ve used to soften the process is to ask everyone in the room to
make two lists: the top five things that they would do again and the top five
things that they wouldn&rsquo;t do again. People find it easier to be candid if they
balance the negative with the positive, and a good facilitator can make it
easier for that balance to be struck.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="continuing-to-learn">Continuing to learn</h3>
<p>Catmull tells the story of Pixar University, a program inside Pixar where they
would arrange classes and workshops in worktime that all employees were free to
attend.</p>
<p>Listen:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>So what exactly was Pixar getting out of all of this? It wasn&rsquo;t that the class
material directly enhanced our employees' job performance. Instead, there was
something about an apprentice lighting technician sitting alongside an
experienced animator, who in turn was sitting next to someone who worked in
legal or accounting or security—that proved immensely valuable. In the
classroom setting, people interacted in a way they didn&rsquo;t in the
workplace. They felt free to be goofy, relaxed, open, vulnerable. Hierarchy did
not apply, and as a result, communication thrived.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here we can see the tremendous power of getting people together in a learning
environment. Learning is such a fundamental human activity. Putting people
together in learning mode breaks down barriers and brings them closer.</p>
<p>Furthermore:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; to send a signal about how important it is for every one of us to keep
learning new things. That, too, is a key part of remaining flexible: keeping
our brains nimble by pushing ourselves to try things we haven&rsquo;t tried before.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If I really had to take a single lesson of this book with me, this would be it.</p>
<p>ABL: Always be learning. You, and your organization.</p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>I truly enjoyed reading this book, for the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Just like other humans, I love stories, and this book is full of them.</li>
<li>The stories are about Pixar, whose movies, in addition the role they have
played in modern culture, I and my children have all tremendously enjoyed,
some of them a number of times.</li>
<li>The stories are about Steve Jobs, a fascinating and impactful human being.</li>
<li>The stories are about Ed Catmull, whose work and name played a role in the
computer graphics part of my postgraduate studies, not in the least due to
the stories of my fabulous advisor Frits Post.</li>
<li>The stories contain many lessons dealing with the immensely challenging work
of building and maintaining sustainable creative organizations.</li>
</ul>
<p>If I had to summarize the advice of the complete book, it would be the following:</p>
<p>Great leaders run great creative organizations with love, and with science.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #195: Pragmatic</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 23:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/</guid><description> Figure 1: Photo from a walk with the fam jam up the mountain a little while out from our backyard, all within the sanctioned exercise hours between 6 and 9 in the mornings.
This edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the week from Monday May 11 to Sunday May 17, 2020.
The rest of this post consists of a part about keyboards, a part chock full of ways to waste your time with WSL and f#, a part about why you might be wasting your time with aforementioned, and then finally a part about a really interesting book.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="nbh_mountain_walk_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/nbh_mountain_walk_pano_huf2970f51c94e01f85b4e747c8808a4c0_1666878_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo from a walk with the fam jam up the mountain a little while out from our backyard, all within the sanctioned exercise hours between 6 and 9 in the mornings."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Photo from a walk with the fam jam up the mountain a little while out from our backyard, all within the sanctioned exercise hours between 6 and 9 in the mornings.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the week from Monday May
11 to Sunday May 17, 2020.</p>
<p>The rest of this post consists of a part about keyboards, a part chock full of
ways to waste your time with WSL and f#, a part about why you might be wasting
your time with aforementioned, and then finally a part about a really
interesting book.</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t like keyboards, and you&rsquo;re wondering in a non-curious way what a
WSL is, I would strongly recommend that you jump to the part, at the end of the
post, about the really interesting book.</p>
<h2 id="ergonomic-keyboard-one-way-street">Ergonomic keyboard one-way street</h2>
<p>As you will recall from <a href="/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/#microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-desktop-at-4-years-rip">the thrilling events of episode #193</a>, one of my two
(home-office and office-office) Microsoft Sculpt Ergonomic keyboards gave up
the ghost.</p>
<p>After far too many keyboard reviews and a fruitless search for a worthy
alternative, I indeed gave up and tried to make peace with the fact that over
the coming years I&rsquo;ll be slowly buying up the rest of the world&rsquo;s Sculpt
supply.</p>
<p>My secret campaign got off to a pretty unspectacular start as I was able to
find exactly one (1) online retailer that was able to supply at this moment.</p>
<p>I mundanely ordered the thing, and it was pretty mundanely delivered to my
house a few days later.</p>
<p>After some breaking in, I am happy to report that a brand-new Sculpt indeed
feels a great deal more amazing than a 4-year-old Sculpt.</p>
<p>As backups for any additional future apocalyptic situations, I also bought two
much cheaper &ldquo;normal&rdquo; keyboards, namely <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/accessories/en-us/products/keyboards/wired-keyboard-600/anb-00001">the Microsoft Wired Keyboard 600</a>.</p>
<p>I tried typing on one just to see what it was like, but more specifically to
develop some sort of intuition for if I would ever be able to return to
straight boards.</p>
<p>To be quite frank, my first impressions were pretty horrible.</p>
<p>Wrists having to bend outwards like that is positively uncomfortable, while the
keys on that unit make for a solid 14 on the 10-point mushiness scale.</p>
<p>One could perhaps get used to the mushiness, or preferably just invest in a
more expensive (mechanical) keyboard, but that ulnar deviation is a total deal
breaker.</p>
<p>My dreams of joining the clickety-clackety cliques of the mechanical keyboard
digerati had been shattered, fortunately quite cheaply.</p>
<p>Instead, I shall be redoubling my Sculpt stockpiling efforts.</p>
<h2 id="interlude-of-even-more-nerdy-miscellany-dot">Interlude of even more nerdy miscellany.</h2>
<p>On Friday evening I was sucked into Windows and WSL2 again.</p>
<p>I stayed up a bit too late because I discovered that instead of displaying to
X410 on Windows, which is slightly painful with WSL2 due to port redirects
and/or firewalling and/or the connection dying every time the Windows host
suspends, one can also start xrdp on WSL2, and then connect to that with
Windows remote desktop.</p>
<p>For WSL2, this is much more robust than X11, and for some use-cases it offers a
better experience. (I&rsquo;m writing this on Tuesday, and <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/commandline/the-windows-subsystem-for-linux-build-2020-summary/">MSBuild has just made a
number of super relevant announcements with regard to native WSL2 Linux GUI
support</a>. For the demo of WSL2 Linux GUI apps, they were displaying to Wayland
on WSL2 and connecting to that using RDP.)</p>
<p>On Saturday, I wrestled with and was solidly trounced by .net core 5 preview 3
and the preview of F# 5.</p>
<p>My goal was to try out the <a href="https://devblogs.microsoft.com/dotnet/announcing-f-5-preview-1/">new <code>r# nuget</code> package references</a>, and specifically
to try this out with the PowerShell type provider in <a href="https://github.com/fsprojects/FSharp.Management">FSharp.Management</a>.</p>
<p>At this point, I also can&rsquo;t tell you exactly why.</p>
<p>I now believe that this was just an instance of the eternal and far broader
learn-something-completely-new vs. work-on-some-compounding-activity conundrum.</p>
<p>(I would later learn that Fsharp.Management has not been updated in a while,
and the packages are not compatible with netcore or netstandard.)</p>
<p>Probably more importantly, I learned that when you&rsquo;re an utter F# noob like me
you should probably just avoid the bleeding edge altogether.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s called the <em>bleeding</em> edge for good reason.</p>
<h3 id="the-story-behind-this-story-one-context-to-rule-them-all">The story behind this story: One context to rule them all!</h3>
<p>When I bought my ex-MacBook Pro 2017 in 2017 on my birthday, you might remember
<a href="/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/#new-laptop">how I justified it then</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Up to then, I had been working on all of three different machines:
Linux-running i7 desktop (acquired in Feb of 2015), early 2015 13″ retina
MacBook Pro (acquired in June of 2015) and my trusty old klunky i7 Acer
Linux-running laptop (acquired around March 2013).</p>
<p>Data is kept in sync, but context switching between different projects with
different development environments on different machines at home and at work
does seem to take up more time than I would care to admit.</p>
<p>Having everything on a single powerful-enough laptop would indeed make the most
sense from a time-efficiency perspective.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That part of the MacBook Pro experiment worked out quite well: The hardware and
software was good enough for <em>everything</em> that I needed to do, so I hardly ever
needed to context switch out of the laptop.</p>
<p>Although <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">the new ThinkPad</a> is more powerful, the fact that I reboot multiple
times per day in and out of Windows and two different Linux configurations on
the laptop is almost like having three different machines, which of course
kills the whole single context dream.</p>
<p>(spoiler alert: In the book-review section after this, context-switching is one
of the main villains!)</p>
<p>Anyways, the reason I keep on returning to WSL2 and then wasting time trying to
make it work more like native Linux and to integrate better with my workflow on
Windows is because I would really like to get rid of this specific context
switch.</p>
<h2 id="pragmatic-thinking-and-learning">Pragmatic Thinking and Learning</h2>
<p>This past weekend I finished reading <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3063393-pragmatic-thinking-and-learning">Pragmatic Thinking &amp; Learning - Refactor
Your Wetware (ed: ahem) by Andy Hunt</a>.</p>
<p>The book is chock full of valuable guidelines for trying to improve the way in
which I apply the limited mental energy I have at my disposal.</p>
<p>(Quite ironically, it felt like the weekend was pretty much me flying right in
the face of just about every piece of advice in the book.)</p>
<p>Here is a selection of the notes I made, slightly massaged for your
consumption. Bon appetit!</p>
<ul>
<li>Make room for the creative part of your brain to fly. First pour in some
reading and structured thinking, and then take a walk, stare out into space,
shower (again), take a nap, make a drawing upside-down. Do whatever&rsquo;s
required to shut logical Spock voice up for a while. When the ideas start
flying in, and they do, switch logical Spock voice back on to structure and
process them.</li>
<li>Build and start using an exocortex. (The reason I bought this book, is
because it was pointed out to me as a good reference for the context and term
<em>exocortex</em>. I&rsquo;m planning to write more about it <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/#the-amazing-niklas-luhmann-and-his-zettelkasten">here</a> and <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">elsewhere</a>.)</li>
<li>Science says that happiness enhances cognition. In other words, when you&rsquo;re
happier, you&rsquo;re really smarter.</li>
<li><strong>Write drunk, revise sober.</strong></li>
<li>Get in the habit of collecting snippets of your writing. That&rsquo;s what the
exocortex is for. You might be surprised at what you&rsquo;re able to construct
with all of the snippets you collect over time. In the book, this is called
the Fieldstone method, but it sounds suspiciously similar to slips of paper
in a slipbox, aka Zettelkasten.</li>
<li>Formulate SMART goals, that is Specific, Measurable, Achivable, Relevant and
Time-boxed. If you read this blog, you&rsquo;re probably &ldquo;smart&rdquo; enough (dad joke,
sorry) to figure out why this is good.</li>
<li>Manage your mind along three axes:
<ol>
<li>Increase focus and attention, e.g. by training focus and attention also
through practising meditation and by sometimes just doing nothing. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple%5Fdrafts%5Fmodel">Daniel
Dennett&rsquo;s <em>multiple drafts</em> model of consciousness</a> is discussed here,
super interesting stuff.
<ul>
<li>On that note, your whole brain and all of its high-level capabilities
are squarely in the use-it-or-lose-it camp.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Manage your knowledge. You guessed it: Exocortex.</li>
<li>Optimise your current context. Keep in your view only what is required to
work on the current thing. Minimise context switching. Avoid distractions
and manage interruptions.</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Well, that was basically my exocortex flexing for you.</p>
<p>ANYWAYS</p>
<p>After all of that, my favourite part of the book was this:</p>








<figure><a href="pragmatic_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="pragmatic_screenshot.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>For those of you viewing this blog in its 100% text-only form, the screenshot
above is of the part of the text explaining that not every day is going to be a
productive one.</p>
<p>I highlighted that, and added the comment:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Some days gonna be crap.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As life goes on, I have come to the realisation that no matter how hard you
work and how much you practise, the days when everything seems to go right
according to plan are truly scarce and should be celebrated.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s probably best to make peace with that fact, and simply to never stop
trying.</p>
<p>Also remember that it is quite possible to bend time just a little bit so as to
create a little more space around the small victories and pleasures that one
experiences even on <em>those</em> days.</p>
<p>See you around friends!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Deep Work: A welcome kick in the butt.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 08:31:25 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Based on this tweet by Enrico Bertini:
Little project I developed during the break looking back at 2016: &quot;Quantifying and Visualizing “Deep Work”&quot; https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q
&mdash; Enrico Bertini (@FILWD) January 3, 2017  &hellip; after having been successfully primed by this one some weeks ago (because locals!):
I also recommend https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf. I was skeptical, but it’s surprisingly good.
&mdash; Rian van der Merwe (@RianVDM) December 22, 2016 &hellip; I bought and then devoured Deep Work by Cal Newport in two to three sessions.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Based on this tweet by <a href="http://enrico.bertini.io/">Enrico Bertini</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Little project I developed during the break looking back at 2016: &quot;Quantifying and Visualizing “Deep Work”&quot; <a href="https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q">https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q</a></p>&mdash; Enrico Bertini (@FILWD) <a href="https://twitter.com/FILWD/status/816374094212067328?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 3, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; after having been successfully primed by this one some weeks ago (because locals!):</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I also recommend <a href="https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf">https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf</a>. I was skeptical, but it’s surprisingly good.</p>&mdash; Rian van der Merwe (@RianVDM) <a href="https://twitter.com/RianVDM/status/811955081201319936?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 22, 2016</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script
<p>&hellip; I bought and then devoured <a href="http://calnewport.com/books/deep-work/">Deep Work by Cal Newport</a> in two to three sessions.</p>
<p>As I munched through the book, I could almost physically sense the impact it was making on my thought patterns. I have since spent another Deep Work Pomodoro scanning through its pages again to make sure I did not miss anything.</p>
<p>Deep Work is at its heart Cal Newport&rsquo;s passionate argument for Deep Work in this extremely fragmented and highly connected information age. He defines Deep Work as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Professional activities performed in a state of distraction-free concentration that push your cognitive capabilities to their limit. These efforts create new value, improve your skill, and are hard to replicate.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Armed with a whole book full of stories and examples, he makes the case for eschewing <em>network tools</em> such as email, twitter, facebook, reddit, slack, whatsapp and so forth, instead dedicating as much of your time as possible to specific valuable outcomes. Yes, even after work, he makes the case for structuring your leisure activities in a similar fashion.</p>
<p>Although the book cites a number of studies, storytelling is its main persuasive tool. Whatever the case may be, I am utterly convinced.</p>
<p>I have resolved to put in a massive effort to get my Deep Work muscles back in top form.</p>
<p>I <em>knew</em> all of this stuff before. Heck, I&rsquo;ve even written on this blog about <a href="/2010/09/28/slow-e-mail-weekly-head-voices-32/">deprioritising communication to make room for important things</a>, <a href="/2010/08/08/workin-9-to-5-weekly-head-voices-28/">minimising interruptions and maximising concentration</a> and more (use the search Luke).</p>
<p>Somehow, maybe because of my transition to business, I&rsquo;ve slipped back into the illusion that you have to be connected all the time. On an average workday, I have email, two instances of slack, one instance of mattermost and whatsapp all open on my desktop, just in case I need to be reached. (To be clear, there&rsquo;s a great deal of messages that go through them every day, so it&rsquo;s not just me sitting there waiting in vain for someone, anyone, to please send me a message.)</p>
<p>Contrary to what I&rsquo;ve convinced myself of, these tools all detract significantly from my value production, both in terms of quality and throughput.</p>
<h2 id="structure-and-summary-of-the-book">Structure and summary of the book</h2>
<p>In Part 1, Newport tries to convince you of the value and necessity of Deep Work. The take-home message is that in order to excel at learning and at doing especially in the current interruption and distraction filled information age, we need unfragmented periods of distraction-free concentration, during which we push our cognition to the limit.</p>
<p>When I say it like that, it seems pretty obvious, doesn&rsquo;t it?</p>
<p>Phrased differently, the great fallacy of current times is that one can perform at one&rsquo;s best whilst being hyper-connected.</p>
<p>One can&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>Even worse, if we continue doing it this way, we&rsquo;ll start losing our ability to focus.</p>
<p>In Part 2, Newport gives high-level advice towards implementing Deep Work, packaged as the four rules of Deep Work:</p>
<ol>
<li>Work deeply: More about this further down.</li>
<li>Embrace boredom: Avoid busywork. That is, when you have a few minutes waiting in line somewhere, use the time to think instead of reaching for your smartphone.</li>
<li>Quit social media: EEEKE! Don&rsquo;t worry, it&rsquo;s slightly more complicated, but “manage social media” would not have had the same impact.)</li>
<li>Drain the shallows: Squeeze out as much as possible shallow work from your schedule. Focus work should be the default, distractions (shallow work) the exception.</li>
</ol>
<p>In terms of scheduling, rule #1 can be implemented in at least four different ways: monastic (isolate yourself almost permanently), bimodal (isolate yourself some of the time, but for significant periods, e.g. a month sabbatical), rhythmic (integrate into your schedule at set times during the day every day), journalistic (cultivate the ability to work deeply whenever you get a moment).</p>
<p>Of these, the rhythmic philosophy is probably the most practical for me and for most of the readers of this blog.</p>
<p>More practically, rule #1 (“Work Deeply”, remember?!) can be implemented using the following four disciplines:</p>
<ol>
<li>Focus on the wildly important: Make sure that you always know what the absolute most valuable thing is to work on.</li>
<li>Act on lead measures: Track your deep work by metrics that can be calculated <em>before</em> the output realises and not after, for example track your daily number of hours during which you were able to work deeply.</li>
<li>Keep a compelling scoreboard: Create some modality with which you can see clearly your daily deep work performance.</li>
<li>Create a cadence of accountability: Your daily or weekly routine should ensure that you review your work, and your deep work performance via the scoreboard for example.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="how-im-planning-to-apply-deep-work">How I&rsquo;m planning to apply Deep Work</h2>
<p>In the book Newport reiterates an important observation: We humans have limited stores of will power. These can and will get depleted through the day if we&rsquo;re not careful.</p>
<p>If it takes too much conscious effort to avoid distractions and to stay focused on the mentally taxing task at hand, our will power is depleted at some point and then our defences crumble.</p>
<p>Before you know it, you&rsquo;re stuck in that super satisfying (not) email, twitter, facebook, reddit, email, twitter, whatsapp, slack loop again.</p>
<p>An effective remedy for this is ritualization.</p>
<p>This does not mean that you have to get out the old Ouija board. Rather, it means that you should develop “routines and rituals to your working life designed to minimize the amount of your limited willpower necessary to transition into and maintain a state of unbroken concentration”.</p>
<p>Fortunately, because of a choice I made in 2013, my work already involves spending longer periods reading, thinking and programming. Now I only need to ensure that these periods are as deep as possible, which means eliminating distractions and practising as intensively as possible focusing on that One Really Important Thing.</p>
<p>I will eliminate distractions by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Using the pomodoro method (as I&rsquo;ve been doing all this time, just badly).</li>
<li>Extending the length of the 25 minute pomodoro. If I&rsquo;m in the deep work flow, I&rsquo;ll continue past the 25 minute alarm. A longer break can be taken later.</li>
<li>Activating my phone&rsquo;s no distraction mode during pomodori. Only phone calls get through, nothing else.</li>
<li>Killing my email app and all browser tabs that have to do with real-time communication (slack, mattermost, whatsapp, and so on).</li>
<li>Just in case, pasting a list of time-wasting site hostnames into my uBlock Origin&rsquo;s “My Filters” list.</li>
</ul>
<p>Besides that, I am recording deep work by prepending one of D0, D1, … D5 to the mytomatoes.com pomodoro description, corresponding to the spectrum from shallow to most deep work.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="http://www.veronikach.com/">veronikach.com</a>, I am using <a href="https://www.focusatwill.com/">focus@will</a> which helps tremendously with my concentration in the sometimes busy office.</p>
<p>Newport explains that most people can manage a maximum of four hours per day of truly deep work. Furthermore, for many people, it is most effective to schedule creative and deep work for the morning, and shallow work (email, admin, meetings etc.) for the afternoon. For a longer time I have been following the guideline of scheduling meetings for the afternoon, so now I&rsquo;ll strengthen that by trying to get my deep work done in the morning, leaving shallow work for the afternoon as far as possible.</p>
<p>Finally, I think that probably the most important advice here is to practise, practise and then practise some more.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This could very well be due to my own bias, but if I had to describe Deep Work as compactly as possible, I would have to say that it comes down to “mindful action”.</p>
<p>It might sound like a contradiction in terms (mindfulness is the practice of being, amongst other things), but I am referring to the practice of being fully connected to and focused on the current moment.</p>
<p>With Deep Work, one practises connecting fully to and focusing on the current endeavour, thus greatly enriching that experience and the output that it generates.</p>
<p>Thank you, Cal Newport, for this very welcome kick in the butt.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The new MedVis Book is out!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2013/12/24/the-new-medvis-book-is-out/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2013 12:28:16 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2013/12/24/the-new-medvis-book-is-out/</guid><description> For the past 2.5 years, I have been helping my friend Prof. Bernhard Preim to write the new Medical Visualization textbook. A crazy number of hours of studying scientific literature (a quick count in the bbl file yields 1880 cited references!!), trying to fit everything into a coherent conceptual framework and then trying to write all of it down as a more or less readable story has finally led to more than 1000 pages of Medical Visualization reading pleasure.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>For the past 2.5 years, I have been helping my friend <a href="http://isgwww.cs.uni-magdeburg.de/~bernhard/" title="bernhard's website">Prof. Bernhard Preim</a> to write the new Medical Visualization textbook. A crazy number of hours of studying scientific literature (a quick count in the bbl file yields 1880 cited references!!), trying to fit everything into a coherent conceptual framework and then trying to write all of it down as a more or less readable story has finally led to more than 1000 pages of Medical Visualization reading pleasure.</p>
<p>It looks like this:</p>
<p><a href="http://medvisbook.com/"><img alt="" class="alignnone" height="922" src="http://medvisbook.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/cover_full_20130729.jpg" width="1650"/></a></p>
<p>The title has been changed to <em>Visual Computing for Medicine</em> to reflect the significant rework, and also the broader treatment of the field. The book itself is 836 pages with hundreds of colour figures. Five chapters (190+ pages) are <a href="http://medvisbook.com/online-chapters/" title="medvisbook online chapters">available exclusively online</a>, free to download.</p>
<p>Go to <a href="http://medvisbook.com/" title="medvisbook website">the book website</a> (run by us) to read more <a href="http://medvisbook.com/about/" title="about the book">about the contents</a> of the book, and to find out <a href="http://medvisbook.com/where-to-buy/" title="where to buy">where you can get your very own copy</a>!</p>
<p>P.S. It was a huge pleasure working on the book together with Bernhard. (We’ve been collaborating quite intensively since the end of 2007 somewhere, when we started setting up the <a href="http://www.vcbm.org/" title="VCBM website">Eurographics Workshops on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine</a>, which have since then been held in 2008, 2010, 2012 and will be held again in 2014 in Vienna.) Just for the record, he definitely put a great deal more work into the book than I did. The exact ratio will remain our secret.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>