<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Beer on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/beer/</link><description>Recent content in Beer on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:48 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/beer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 4 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-22 As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&amp;rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS! At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&amp;hellip; Short but really nice streamlit demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually played with it. Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3. In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola. Tuesday 2024-01-23 At the office nice and early (7:30). Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at react-flow and comfyui react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY! streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &amp;ldquo;things I learned&amp;rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document. Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&amp;rsquo;s a zero day vulnerability in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites. Wednesday 2024-01-24 8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW! Remember kids: Our spine&amp;rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally. This is also the reason why I&amp;rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair. Lovely working lunch with friend S at No Way José Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work: idea: make github so that people can pipx install marimo-turbo to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on. idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS &amp;hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844 (post is also embedded below) idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&amp;gt; nginx -&amp;gt; supervisord -&amp;gt; tornado systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation I would prefer to use supervisord for this This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick? ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &amp;ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&amp;rdquo; googling blog post: https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/ the kubernetes thing: https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&amp;rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via iframe.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-22">Monday 2024-01-22</h2>
<ul>
<li>As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &ldquo;When you&rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS!</li>
<li>At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&hellip;</li>
<li>Short but really nice <a href="https://streamlit.io/">streamlit</a> demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&rsquo;ve never actually played with it.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3.
<ul>
<li>In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-23">Tuesday 2024-01-23</h2>
<ul>
<li>At the office nice and early (7:30).</li>
<li>Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at <a href="https://reactflow.dev/">react-flow</a> and comfyui
<ul>
<li>react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see <a href="https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary">https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary</a>
<ul>
<li>it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster</li>
<li>marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &ldquo;things I learned&rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document.</li>
<li>Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&rsquo;s a <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/news/apple-issues-urgent-security-updates-to-fix-zero-day-flaw-update-your-iphone-and-mac-right-now">zero day vulnerability</a> in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-24">Wednesday 2024-01-24</h2>
<ul>
<li>8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot</li>
<li>dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work</li>
<li>right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW!
<ul>
<li>Remember kids: Our spine&rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally.</li>
<li>This is also the reason why I&rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lovely working lunch with friend S at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/NoWayJoseSomerset">No Way José</a></li>
<li>Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work:
<ul>
<li>idea: make github so that people can <code>pipx install marimo-turbo</code> to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on.</li>
<li>idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap
<ul>
<li>sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets</li>
<li>in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS
<ul>
<li>&hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844</a> (post is also embedded below)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&gt; nginx -&gt; supervisord -&gt; tornado
<ul>
<li>systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: <a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation">https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation</a></li>
<li>I would prefer to use supervisord for this</li>
<li>This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&rdquo; googling
<ul>
<li>blog post: <a href="https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/">https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/</a></li>
<li>the kubernetes thing: <a href="https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s">https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0" width="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><script src="https://emacs.ch/embed.js" async="async"></script>
<h3 id="til-mastodon-embeds-are-not-as-durable-as-twitter-embeds">TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds</h3>
<p>As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via <code>iframe</code>.</p>
<p>With twitter, you get more self-contained HTML which will render even when twitter or just the original tweet don&rsquo;t exist anymore.</p>
<p>This is probably just another reason to figure out how I can get more low-friction microblogging going on my own websites so that the embedding implementations of other microblogging sites become irrelevant.</p>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-25">Thursday 2024-01-25</h2>
<ul>
<li>Took a look at <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/connections/connect-networks/get-started/">cloudflare tunnels</a> to expose marimo and other dashboards to the internet
<ul>
<li>great that I can use my existing domains for this, and I can route between multiple domains to multiple locally running services</li>
<li>some more steps to setup, but it did not take more than about 5 minutes, and gives me even more options than tailscale funnels. OPTIONS MAN!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At work, quickly got react-flow&hellip; flowing. SHINY!</li>
<li>In the evening, found <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/">https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/</a> which is the new Shortcuts based way, based on the old AppleScript way, of getting a <code>message://</code> link onto the clipboard.
<ul>
<li>You <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#email-linking">might recall from this blog</a> that <code>message://</code> are the most durable and cross-platform way to link to emails from your notes (or anywhere else)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-26">Friday 2024-01-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up to cool, overcast weather, a big change from a series of 30℃ + days. Really had to resist going out for a run (normal run day + that amazing coolness), because of Wednesday&rsquo;s partially pulled back muscle not being 100% yet.</li>
<li>Worked on mystery visualization project (react-flow)</li>
<li>Lovely and energising lunch with previous colleague and friend. Happy that I reached out on Thursday although they have a packed schedule because only in country for limited time. I guess this is quite related to <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">calling up your friends</a>, with a ping of serendipity salt.</li>
<li>I was shocked by how well and fast <a href="https://ollama.ai/">ollama</a> worked on my MacBook. See embedded tweet below.</li>
<li>Almost at the end of the afternoon, friend S and I went to some more friends for the first Weiss-off, that is, a Weiss beer tasting contest. It was huge fun blind-tasting 10 different Weiss beers, ranking them, trying to identify them (so much harder than I thought!), and then having them revealed at the end.
<ul>
<li>Between the experts there (read: us), Stangen Weiss Bier came out on top, followed by Weisbier No5 and Jack Black Atlantic Weiss. The fourth place was shared by Erdinger and CBC Amber Weiss.</li>
<li>My favourite, Stellenbrau Jonkersweiss, is glaringly absent from the top. I&rsquo;ll live, probably consoled by just such a Jonkersweiss. Super happy that Amber Weiss and Atlantic are both present!</li>
<li>There was a trophy (for the taster who could blind-identify the most beers in the Weiss-off), which we have christened the <em>David Weisselhoff wisseltrofee</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">With <a href="https://twitter.com/MistralAI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@MistralAI</a>&#39;s Mistral 7B at Q4_0 on this MacBook M1 Pro 10C / 16C, <a href="https://twitter.com/ollama?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ollama</a> looks like it&#39;s easily 3 times faster than the new MLX 0.0.11 (with GGUF support).<br><br>It&#39;s subjectively (visually) faster, and the tokens/s measurements confirm this. <a href="https://t.co/9vyluimLKK">pic.twitter.com/9vyluimLKK</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1750824125419942036?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 26, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-27">Saturday 2024-01-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yesterday&rsquo;s Wonderful Weiss-off also had some, thankfully quite minor, effect the next morning, but I went out for a careful weekday distance run, which fortunately went without a hitch. Just very hot thanks.</li>
<li>Went to Buco and then to <a href="https://appletoolandgas.com/">Apple Tool and Gas</a> to find the rest of the screws I needed to repair the shower door. Friendly gentleman at Apple even sawed some of my screws to size! Shower door back in operation.</li>
<li>Updated my &ldquo;old&rdquo; M1 MBA to macOS 14.3 and then reset to transfer to GOU#1&rsquo;s iCloud. Say what you want about Apple, but that part of their stuff works <em>really</em> well.</li>
<li>Left for Betty&rsquo;s Bay at about 16:00 with GOUs #1 and #2. The rest of the family already there.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-28">Sunday 2024-01-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up in Betty&rsquo;s Bay after a longer than normal night of sleep, but Garmin body battery was still not completely happy.</li>
<li>In spite of having run yesterday and still feeling a bit tired (see body battery above), I had the best run of the month so far in Betty&rsquo;s. Go figure.</li>
<li>Spent some time with Canva &ndash; what a great resource for doing nice designs, even flow charts &ndash; but not sure where I could use this.</li>
<li>Background thought through the past weeks, and mentioned on Tuesday: I would really like to do (and promite) more TIL-style writing at work and at home. See <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/">Simon Willison&rsquo;s amazing TIL collection</a> for inspiration.</li>
<li>Ran into <a href="https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines">https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines</a> a Python library that can guarantee structured text generation from many LLMs, e.g. 100% valid JSON according to a specified schema. What makes it different from similar libraries? &ldquo;Unlike other libraries, regex-guided generation in Outlines is almost as fast as non-guided generation.&rdquo;</li>
<li>I already had <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/autogen">AutoGen</a> on my list for experimenting with multi-agent LLM applications, but now it has been joined by <a href="https://github.com/joaomdmoura/crewAI">crewAI</a> which I have also just ran into (thanks reddit!) and which seems to have significant support online.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #251: Week one fun</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/08/weekly-head-voices-251-week-one-fun/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 22:23:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/08/weekly-head-voices-251-week-one-fun/</guid><description>Welcome to the first regular Weekly Head Voices of the year folks!
This, the 251st edition, looks back at the week from Monday, January 2 to Sunday, January 8 of the brand new year 2023.
Figure 1: Blue waters of Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay main beach. The weather was amazing.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the first regular Weekly Head Voices of the year folks!</p>
<p>This, the 251st edition, looks back at the week from Monday, January 2 to
Sunday, January 8 of the brand new year 2023.</p>










<figure><a href="bettys-main-beach.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/08/weekly-head-voices-251-week-one-fun/bettys-main-beach_hu_2001f4641f2248f6.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/08/weekly-head-voices-251-week-one-fun/bettys-main-beach_hu_6b5efddaf37b8a25.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/08/weekly-head-voices-251-week-one-fun/bettys-main-beach_hu_93e7039947b520c1.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/08/weekly-head-voices-251-week-one-fun/bettys-main-beach_hu_159f0e0ac8efaa4e.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/08/weekly-head-voices-251-week-one-fun/bettys-main-beach_hu_6b5efddaf37b8a25.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Blue waters of Betty&rsquo;s Bay main beach. The weather was amazing."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Blue waters of Betty&rsquo;s Bay main beach. The weather was amazing.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You might recall from the 2023 transition post that appeared a mere week ago,
that <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#quo-vadis-2023">I really wanted to try to post more regularly here</a>, even if it meant that
the posts might be less substantial.</p>
<p>Well here we are: A short post that is on time!</p>
<p>(The proposed blogging pipeline improvements that were also mentioned are still in progress (AKA I have
not yet started).)</p>
<h2 id="gou-1-is-back-from-dot-de">GOU #1 is back from .de!</h2>
<p>The biggest news of the week is that GOU #1 has returned from a month-long
<a href="https://fsa-youthexchange.co.za/">FSA exchange</a> visit to Essen, in Germany.</p>
<p>We really missed her, but she&rsquo;s back after an experience-packed four weeks with
an amazing host family, living her best life as she has this obvious talent to
do.</p>
<h2 id="a-tonne-of-fun-in-week-one">A tonne of fun in week one</h2>
<p>Due to possibly debatable life decisions, I returned to work on Monday,
January 3.</p>
<p>There are perks to starting up so early in the year, primarily that it&rsquo;s quite
peaceful, and there&rsquo;s a bit more headspace than normal to think about bigger
plans for the year ahead.</p>
<p>Sadly, I have not yet made any break-throughs in this regard.</p>
<p>Partially this is due to a substantial number of my mental cycles having to go
into a data-science project that requires my attention, and partially because I
have not yet taken that deep-thinking-walk.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll get on that walk tomorrow!</p>
<p>In spite of work, we did manage to fit in a whole bunch of fun in this first
week:</p>
<ul>
<li>We squeezed in a sneaky but sublime school night sunset dinner at Millhouse
Kitchen on Lourensford Farm to celebrate our anticipation of GOU #1&rsquo;s return
the next day.</li>
<li>We made a family outing of a trip to the V&amp;A Waterfront on Saturday to return
an Adoozy powerbank that they saved abovementioned GOU&rsquo;s phone with at OR
Tambo airport in Johannesburg. Their rental powerbank concept looks
interesting, and the people were really super helpful, but their network in
Cape Town is a bit anaemic with the main issue that you can&rsquo;t return your
powerbank at Cape Town airport!
<ul>
<li>During this outing, we had lunch at <a href="https://denanker.co.za/">Den Anker</a> where we always enjoy
culinary and cultural echoes of our other home. In my case, this includes
the taste of my favourite Trappist beer, namely <a href="/tags/rochefort/">the Rochefort</a>. On this
beautiful sunny day, I opted for and limited myself to the lighter #6. (I
and some of my friends have been known to enjoy all of those even numbers
in sequence.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>On Sunday, we (famjam) made use of the absolutely fabulous weather and spent
a glorious day in Betty&rsquo;s Bay, mostly on its main beach. I&rsquo;m currently
reading <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/43263225-supernova-era">Liu
Cixin&rsquo;s Supernova Era</a> and the story, with its pretty inventive premise, has
just switched up a few gears.
<ul>
<li>The ocean views from <a href="/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/">Clarence Drive</a> were truly breath-taking today. They
were so over-the-top beautiful that GOU #1 exclaimed at least once that
they &ldquo;look like a rendering&rdquo;, which struck me as a really remarkable
compliment. (This was followed by some joking in the car about all of <em>this</em>
<a href="https://www.simulation-argument.com/">being a simulation</a>.)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Have a great week friends, I hope to see you again on the other side!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #181: The Slow Ones.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 19:47:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/</guid><description>Welcome back everyone!
This edition of the WHV, #181, looks back at the period of time from Monday October 7 to Sunday October 13, 2019.
Compulsory running shot: Looking at Gordon's Bay from the Strand. This was on Thursday. I squeezed in another short run on Friday, which my legs definitely did not appreciate. Note to self: Laziness earlier in the week leads to skipped rest days and sore legs later. (cf. "A stitch in time saves nine." Also cf. Always Be Compounding.) Alternative WHV notification modalities. Shortly after publishing WHV #180, I decided (bolstered by the advice of my, err, advisor) to return to announcing new WHVs on Facebook and perhaps even on Twitter, in spite of TwiFRaF-YT.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>This edition of the WHV, #181, looks back at the period of time from Monday
October 7 to Sunday October 13, 2019.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_77e9f02865b47207.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_668df39896270fff.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_b72391f5381e5a66.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_2ae12fc41c639bc1.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/gbay_running_hu_668df39896270fff.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Compulsory running shot: Looking at Gordon's Bay from the Strand. This was on
Thursday. I squeezed in another short run on Friday, which my legs definitely
did not appreciate. Note to self: Laziness earlier in the week leads to skipped
rest days and sore legs later. (cf. "A stitch in time saves nine." Also
cf. Always Be Compounding.)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="alternative-whv-notification-modalities">Alternative WHV notification modalities.</h2>
<p>Shortly after publishing WHV #180, I decided (bolstered by the advice of my,
err, advisor) to return to announcing new WHVs on Facebook and perhaps even on
Twitter, in spite of
<a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#twifraf-progress-report">TwiFRaF-YT</a>.</p>
<p>For the past months, the only place where you could opt in to be notified of
new WHVs was on the mailing list. (Well, that and RSS, which seems to be
becoming more niche with every passing day.)</p>
<p>Although the mailing list works for a number of people, I am interested in
adding other options that would make sense for WHV readers.</p>
<p>Readers, where else would be a good place to keep you up to date about new WHV
posts, should you like to be kept up to date?</p>
<h2 id="what-i-did-in-week-41">What I did in week 41.</h2>
<p>This was a great week for social events.</p>
<p>It was not the best week for avoiding amazing craft beer and even more amazing
wine.</p>
<p>(I knew what I was getting into when the week started. I committed to it.)</p>
<p>On Tuesday evening, I really enjoyed our local Helderberg business and nerdery
meetup.</p>
<p>Two &ldquo;lightning&rdquo; talks were given: The first on getting your podcasting game on
(microphones, syndication, oh my!), and the second on personal knowledge
management, based on the recently published <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">note-taking post on this
blog</a>.</p>
<p>Craft beer was enjoyed.</p>
<p>The next day, at a regular(ish) Top Secret Business Meeting (at the Thirsty
Scarecrow), I made use of the opportunity to drink my favourite IPA of all time
(so far), a beer which goes by the name of WARLORD, and a beer that has been
<a href="/2018/03/18/weekly-head-voices-136-slightly-more-than-nothing-much/#new-beer-warlord">documented before on these
pages</a>.</p>
<p>As the tasting ceremony started, I was greeted by this portentous sign:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_9df3cb3833e72e2f.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_6fcb5215693ddb6e.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_9d9262709756aa9c.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_64c6f6f1a80190f0.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/warlord_bone_crusher_phear_me_rawr_hu_6fcb5215693ddb6e.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
The name is BONECRUSHER, WARLORD BONECRUSHER.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Coincidence? I think not.</p>
<p>On Friday, we had lunch with friends from the Netherlands at the newly
re-opened Long Table restaurant at Haskell Winery.</p>
<p>The view from one&rsquo;s lunch table looked something like this:</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_286fa91df2fcb999.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_36c973590ec6c78b.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_260eab87618f8b58.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_7f478114624e5f24.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/long_table_lunch_view_hu_36c973590ec6c78b.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
For a whole while before the guests arrived and before I took this photo I just
sat there drinking in the view with my own eyes, like a crazy person.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>As if that was not enough, we had the exquisite pleasure of making the
acquaintance of the Haskell Anvil 2018, probably the best Chardonnay I have
ever tasted.</p>
<h3 id="running-with-fluids-and-fuel-1210-going-to-do-again">Running with fluids and fuel. 12/10 going to do again.</h3>
<p>On Sunday, I went out on a long run, partly to atone for my sins but mostly just
because I really like going on long runs.</p>
<p>What was special about this run, is that I took along extra fluids for the
first time ever.</p>
<p>Weekend runs these days are mostly longer than an hour.</p>
<p>After an hour of running on a sunny day down here, one loses quite an amount of
moisture. If this moisture is not replenished, one&rsquo;s running equipment starts
to malfunction.</p>
<p>To prevent this situation, I recently acquired a <a href="https://runnerclick.com/camelbak-circuit-vest-review/">Camelbak Circuit 1.5l
Hydration vest</a>.</p>
<p>On Sunday, I took this vest out for its maiden voyage. It had about a litre of
Game (local cheap isotonic drink) in the bladder, and two bananas stuffed in
the front pockets.</p>
<p>Subjectively, the run went better than usual and I was able to increase my
distance by a little, but gratifying, bit.</p>
<p>However, next time I&rsquo;m filling that bladder to capacity.</p>
<p>The angst-inducing sound which that thing makes when you suck out the last few
drops of drink with some distance still left to go is not something I want to
hear again soon.</p>
<h2 id="solar">Solar</h2>
<p>For the first time since <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">our house was
solarized</a>, this
thing happened on Saturday morning at 7:18:</p>
<figure style="width: 400px;">














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24.png">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24_hu_3849a9dd8612a7a7.png 480w
  
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/solar24.png"
  

   />

</a>

</figure>
<p>The house&rsquo;s batteries were still at 24%, but the sun was already high enough to
meet our modest energy demands at that point.</p>
<p>In other words, for the first time, we had stored enough solar power the
previous day to get us 100% through the night and back into solar, without us
having to dip into the grid.</p>
<p>(The inverter is programmed not to let the lithium batteries discharge below
20%, in order to further increase their lifespan. When there&rsquo;s a real power
outage, it will go down to 10%.)</p>
<p>This should happen more often now that the days are getting longer.</p>
<p>I derive a <em>substantial</em> amount of pleasure from every single kilowatt-hour of
sunbeam-powered electricity that we generate and use.</p>
<h2 id="first-rule-of-blogging-you-dont-blog-about-blogging">First rule of blogging: You don&rsquo;t blog about blogging.</h2>
<p>According to <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/oct/12/blogging-twenty-five-years-old-all-grown-up">this Guardian
article</a>,
blogging turned 25 on Monday, October 7, 2019.</p>
<p>They define the start of blogging as the birth of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dave_Winer">Dave
Winer&rsquo;s</a> first blog post in 1994. It
turns out that Winer has posted to his blog on every single day since that very
first year.</p>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/QFKtHSlaMVI">RESTECP!</a></p>
<p>I like how the Guardian article juxtaposes blogging with modern social media.</p>
<p>Of course the truth is more complicated, but generally blogging is more about
the content, and the reasoning, albeit just as opinionated, behind it, whereas
social media is all about emotion-driven <em>engagement</em> and extremely short-term
gratification-analogues of some kind or another.</p>
<h2 id="the-slow-ones">The Slow Ones.</h2>
<p>Complementing <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">ABC</a>, I
feel another (old) theme brewing amongst the voices&hellip;</p>
<p>Deliberate, deep and slow thinking and doing, is an additional antidote to the
all-encompassing AI-optimised immediate gratification information environment
that we live in, and to humankind&rsquo;s concomitant addiction to all that is
instant.</p>
<p>In a science fiction world, we&rsquo;re going to end up with yet another
schism between humans.</p>
<p>There will be those who will hold conversations with ten others at the same
time, data streams coming in from twenty more sources in the background,
processing-processing-processing.</p>
<p>There will be a far smaller group of folks who still command the almost
forgotten art of focusing intently on a single thing for hours on end, without
swiping in any direction.</p>
<p>Communication between the two groups will become increasingly difficult.</p>
<p>Will this remain the stuff of fiction?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #179: Direct Experience Trigonometry.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2019 22:18:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/</guid><description>(WARNING: not your typical WHV post ahead. CONTINUE AT YOUR OWN RISK.)
In this, the 179th edition of the WHV, I look back at the week from Monday, September 24 to Sunday, September 29, 2019.
We spent slightly more than half of this time on vacation in the Cederberg mountains.
This Cederberg mountains frame and support a truly beautiful place, with as one of its many additional features the fact that mobile phone reception and other forms of modern digital communication have not managed to penetrate all that much.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>(WARNING: not your typical WHV post ahead. CONTINUE AT YOUR OWN RISK.)</p>
<p>In this, the 179th edition of the WHV, I look back at the week from Monday,
September 24 to Sunday, September 29, 2019.</p>
<p>We spent slightly more than half of this time on vacation in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cederberg">Cederberg
mountains</a>.</p>
<p>This Cederberg mountains frame and support a truly beautiful place, with as
one of its many additional features the fact that mobile phone reception and
other forms of modern digital communication have not managed to penetrate all
that much.</p>
<p>(Because this time was spent for the largest part, as it should be, in direct
experience mode, that is, &ldquo;humans see, humans taste, humans run, the end&rdquo;, the
rest of this post contains many images and has morphed into a sort of holiday
report.)</p>
<p>To be more specific about the how and the where, we hitched a super compact
version of one of those self-contained
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Command_%26_Conquer_(1995_video_game)">Command-&amp;-Conquer</a>-like
mobile bases, in the shape of a <a href="http://www.echo4x4.co.za/product/echo-4-off-road-trailer/">rugged-looking 4x4
trailer</a> (all of
this temporarily arranged), to our decidedly non-4x4 family carrier vehicle,
and set off on a high gradient drive to a tourist farm in the Cederberg called
Driehoek.</p>
<figure>
<a href="driehoek_back_entrance.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/driehoek_back_entrance_hu_eb682f3abf97d419.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/driehoek_back_entrance_hu_d48578fe00ac08fe.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/driehoek_back_entrance_hu_cfaf57d19f67df63.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/driehoek_back_entrance_hu_7ce0c125a80bd2c1.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/driehoek_back_entrance_hu_d48578fe00ac08fe.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>(Next time you see me, ask me about time when above-mentioned family carrier
vehicle was physically unable to pull the same trailer out of Beaverlac
camping. Oh wait, <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#gous-go-camping-for-their-first-time-ever">I did mention that in a previous blog
post</a>!
You should still ask me about it.)</p>
<h2 id="humans-see">Humans see.</h2>
<p>Close to the Stadsaal (&ldquo;Town Hall&rdquo;) caves, you too should be able to find this
wonderfully preserved San rock art:</p>
<figure>
<a href="stadsaal_rock_art.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/stadsaal_rock_art_hu_98b03c3ac78915af.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/stadsaal_rock_art_hu_ee188d93019cf89d.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/stadsaal_rock_art_hu_b68822ef78a81d8.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/stadsaal_rock_art_hu_86fb30a02c82f0d2.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/stadsaal_rock_art_hu_ee188d93019cf89d.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>We also went exploring the Stadsaal caves themselves. This specific scene
reminded me strongly of the composition of a Star Wars poster:</p>
<figure>
<a href="star_wars_stadsaal.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/star_wars_stadsaal_hu_838c1115afb648f8.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/star_wars_stadsaal_hu_e292033b9ebfe400.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/star_wars_stadsaal_hu_3a1424940c8b24cc.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/star_wars_stadsaal_hu_cb1e83cf08a72d5e.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/star_wars_stadsaal_hu_e292033b9ebfe400.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<h2 id="humans-taste">Humans taste.</h2>
<p>On our way back from the Stadsaal caves, we took a turn-off and went down the
mountain to visit <a href="https://cederbergpark.com/">Cederberg Park</a> on the
Kromrivier farm.</p>
<p>Ostensibly this was about lunch, but the deeper purpose was experiencing the
locally brewed <a href="http://www.nieuwbrew.co.za/">NieuwBrew</a> craft beer.</p>
<p>The hot day seemed to be perfect for a Weiss, and so I chose the Sandfish Weiss:</p>
<figure>
<a href="nieuw_brew_sandfish_weiss.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/nieuw_brew_sandfish_weiss_hu_41689a365f0252f7.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/nieuw_brew_sandfish_weiss_hu_5c0ac5e998db832.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/nieuw_brew_sandfish_weiss_hu_d747c46ffa869c54.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/nieuw_brew_sandfish_weiss_hu_d7c45648e2a3a8c9.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/nieuw_brew_sandfish_weiss_hu_5c0ac5e998db832.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>On this day, in that beautiful location, the Sandfish Weiss scored an 11/10 on
<a href="/2016/08/15/weekly-head-voices-111-a-swift-hack/">the famous WHV Celis White
scale</a>.</p>
<p>After lunch and NieuwBrew, we paid a visit to the <a href="https://www.cederbergwine.com">Cederberg
Wines</a> cellar for a grand old wine-tasting.</p>
<p>Again the visit was that much more special because it&rsquo;s simply not that easy to
reach, but here again the wines surprised with their quality. Our host Aubrey
did a sterling job guiding us on this journey of taste and flavour.</p>
<p>On the way out, I was again pleasantly surprised to run into more <a href="https://www.cederbergbrewery.com/the-team/">craft beer
constructed by the Cederberg Wines winemakers David Niewoudt and Alex
Nel</a>.</p>
<figure>
<a href="cederberg_voertsek_beer.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/cederberg_voertsek_beer_hu_6ccb610a7946b22f.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/cederberg_voertsek_beer_hu_a5855f4f3e96d03f.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/cederberg_voertsek_beer_hu_935f270173011f0.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/cederberg_voertsek_beer_hu_5de8030a7b22b9b4.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/cederberg_voertsek_beer_hu_a5855f4f3e96d03f.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>WHV score: 11/10, getting worried about how and when I&rsquo;ll be able to acquire
more of this.</p>
<h2 id="humans-run">Humans run.</h2>
<p>On the Friday morning, I did a short run(ish) up the mountain(ish).</p>
<p>The scenery was epic, but the mountain(ish) was steep, and the wine and beer
tasting of the previous days did my legs absolutely zero (0) favours.</p>
<p>Enjoyment 10/10, performance 4/10.</p>
<p>You would have thought that this would be a lesson, but no.</p>
<p>All of the endless gravel roads we took during the rest of the Friday on our
visits to the caves and to the cellar called to me during the night.</p>
<p>On the Saturday morning, I girded up my loins, donned my trusty sandals, and
off I went on my favourite running surface: gravel roads, surrounded by as
much nothingness as possible.</p>
<figure>
<a href="gravel_road_run.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/gravel_road_run_hu_a26d131c96189856.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/gravel_road_run_hu_5530517a2defd34b.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/gravel_road_run_hu_cd084f54059c5825.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/gravel_road_run_hu_59afeb4aa946b646.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/10/03/weekly-head-voices-179-direct-experience-trigonometry/gravel_road_run_hu_5530517a2defd34b.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>After the first few kilometres, I took a turn-off onto a gravel road that we
had not yet explored, with the idea to add a few more kilometres before turning
back.</p>
<p>However, my keen sense of direction, where with &ldquo;keen sense&rdquo; I mean &ldquo;<em>utter</em>
lack of&rdquo;, convinced me that the road I was on would eventually meet the
turn-off on the very other side of the farm.</p>
<p>So I kept on running.</p>
<p>I did have a cut-off point in mind, where if I did not yet see the expected
entrance, I would have to turn around.</p>
<p>After a few more kilometres of gravel road through beautiful nothing, and a few
more upward adjustments of my turn-around point into over-exertion territory, I
was experiencing an interesting bit of stress.</p>
<p>Based on only a hunch, substantially weakened by my sense of direction track
record, do I turn around, or do I double down for the great reward of an epic
run in the Cederberg?</p>
<p>DO I FEEL LUCKY, PUNK?!</p>
<p>Well, sneaky engineer chose door #3: Acquire More Data.</p>
<p>I flagged down a car.</p>
<p>The friendly driver knew nothing about Driehoek, at which point I started
sinking into the hard ground.</p>
<p>Suddenly he perked up and said that in fact he did remember passing it a few
kilometres back.</p>
<p>Whoohoo!</p>
<p>With the driver thanked and my stress greatly reduced, I switched back into
running mode, now truly committed to close this particular loop.</p>
<p>After a few kilometres more, I finally arrived at the revered entrance.</p>
<p>My legs were feeling quite empty (thanks more beer and wine the previous day!),
but there was still a little more enjoyment to be squeezed from the remaining
kilometre or four of winding gravel road back to our camp, and so I did my
best.</p>
<p>The run itself was a whole lot easier than writing a satisfying ending to this
piece of text, a task that has me convincingly stumped.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m keeping this post here. It&rsquo;ll be fun to read in a few years.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #112: Emergency Smörgåsbord.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 12:48:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/</guid><description>(This blog post documents snippets of time taken from the period starting on Monday August 15 and ending on Tuesday November 8, 2016.)
My longing simply became too great.
For an epic few days in August, I found myself in The Netherlands (my other home) mixing business and pleasure like a boss. Thank you besties, my cup has not stopped running over. Photo by Bestie DJ Fiasco.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This blog post documents snippets of time taken from the period starting on Monday August 15 and ending on Tuesday November 8, 2016.)</em></p>
<p>My longing simply became too great.</p>
<p>For an epic few days in August, I found myself in The Netherlands (my other home) mixing business and pleasure like a boss. Thank you besties, my cup has not stopped running over.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/IMG-20160827-WA0010.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/IMG-20160827-WA0010-1024x576.jpg"
        
            alt="Photo by Bestie DJ Fiasco."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Photo by Bestie DJ Fiasco.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Shortly after returning from NL, my year counter ticked over one more time.</p>
<p>I have become indeed <em>quite</em> middle-aged.</p>
<p>On the flip side, I am content with where I find myself in space-time, both physically and meta-physically. Although I seem to think more slowly, I do seem to have become slightly better at retrospection, introspection and at <a href="/2016/05/22/weekly-head-voices-107-balance/">seeing the bigger picture</a>.</p>
<p>As an additional consolation, it seems that I am in the best physical condition I have been for years due to a recent(ish) and surprising discovery of a latent jogging addiction. I am terrible at the action itself, but I really enjoy being repeatedly terrible at it.</p>
<p>On the topic of consolation, I tasted (at least) three new local craft beers, the experience of which I would like to share with you.</p>
<div class="gallery galleryid-2538 gallery-columns-3 gallery-size-thumbnail" data-carousel-extra='{"blog_id":1,"permalink":"https:\/\/cpbotha.net\/2016\/11\/12\/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord\/"}' id="gallery-3">
<figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon portrait">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651.jpg" title=""><img alt="" aria-describedby="gallery-3-2541" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" data-attachment-id="2541" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"2.4","credit":"","camera":"LG-D855","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1476385610","copyright":"","focal_length":"3.97","iso":"350","shutter_speed":"0.071428571428571","title":"","orientation":"1"}' data-image-title="20161013_190651" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651-576x1024.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651-169x300.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651.jpg" data-orig-size="1280,2276" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/20161013_190651/" height="150" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161013_190651-150x150.jpg" width="150"/></a>
</div><figcaption class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-3-2541"> Striped Horse Pils. Deserving of the awards it won in 2015 and 2016! </figcaption></figure><figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon portrait">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835.jpg" title=""><img alt="" aria-describedby="gallery-3-2543" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" data-attachment-id="2543" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":"","orientation":"0"}' data-image-title="20161029_121835" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835-452x1024.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835-132x300.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835.jpg" data-orig-size="934,2115" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/20161029_121835/" height="150" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161029_121835-150x150.jpg" width="150"/></a>
</div><figcaption class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-3-2543"> Jack Black Atlantic Weiss: a 9.8 on the Celis White scale! </figcaption></figure><figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon landscape">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-3" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings.jpg" title=""><img alt="" aria-describedby="gallery-3-2545" class="attachment-thumbnail size-thumbnail" data-attachment-id="2545" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"0","credit":"","camera":"","caption":"","created_timestamp":"0","copyright":"","focal_length":"0","iso":"0","shutter_speed":"0","title":"","orientation":"0"}' data-image-title="mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings-1024x921.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings-300x270.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings.jpg" data-orig-size="2601,2340" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/12/weekly-head-voices-112-emergency-smorgasbord/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings/" height="150" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/mountain_weiss_mixed_feelings-150x150.jpg" width="150"/></a>
</div><figcaption class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-3-2545"> Mountain Weiss is a lovely white beer that gives me very mixed feelings, because reasons. </figcaption></figure>
</div>
<p>The Striped Horse Pils won gold at the 2015 and <a href="http://brewmistress.co.za/winners-of-the-2016-south-african-national-beer-trophy/">2016 National Beer Trophy</a>. More importantly, it also won the WHV-two-voices-cheering-loudly award, because it’s a full-bodied hoppy beer.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.jackblackbeer.com/#atlantic-weiss">Jack Black Atlantic Weiss</a> gets a whopping 9.8 on <a href="/2016/08/15/weekly-head-voices-111-a-swift-hack/">my famous Celis White scale</a>. This is the lighter, fresher version of the Bone Crusher that we’ve all been waiting for. Now you just have to cross your fingers that more suppliers will get this. At this moment, it’s still quite tricky to track down.</p>
<p>On a subsequent failed mission to acquire more Atlantic Weiss, I ran into the Newlands Spring Brewing Company’s <em>Mountain Weiss</em>. As I was enjoying this light white beer (THE SUMMER IS COMING) something was tugging at the edge of my memory…</p>
<p>As I turned the bottle around, my worst suspicions were confirmed: Newlands Spring Brewing Company belongs to South African Breweries (SAB), the behemoth beer-brewing international mega-corp. They’ve been trying to get into the craft beer market, a sector traditionally belonging to often entrepreneurial and even family-run small enterprises, and this was their sneaky attempt.</p>
<p>In spite of its lovely taste, I do prefer spending my craft beer budget on mom-and-pop setups. Besides the truly tasty beer, I really like that craft beer has democratised a traditionally closed (by SAB!) area of commerce, and so would prefer putting my money there.</p>
<p>(That is not to say that I don’t buy SAB’s non-craft beers. A man gets thirsty!)</p>
<p>The following marvelous animation <a href="https://twitter.com/WorldAndScience/status/795747812424216576">popped up in my twitter timeline</a>:</p>
<div class="wp-video" style="width: 718px;">
<!--[if lt IE 9]><![endif]--><video class="wp-video-shortcode" controls="controls" height="522" id="video-2538-1" preload="metadata" width="718"><source src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/stable_milkyway_earth_rotation.mp4?_=1" type="video/mp4"/>
<a href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/stable_milkyway_earth_rotation.mp4">https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/stable_milkyway_earth_rotation.mp4</a></video>
</div>
<p>Someone configured their camera stabilisation to lock on to the milky way in this National Geographic timelapse video. The result of this simple experiment is that you can clearly see the rotation of the Earth.</p>
<p>It’s really amazing what you can achieve by simply changing your perspective.</p>
<p>In Other Much More Important News, one of my last academic children <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/defended-phd-thesis-virtual-surgical-pelvis-anatomy-visualization-education-surgical-planning/">got doctorified on October 31</a>. I left academia for entirely non-children-related reasons (the children were the best part of academia!) <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/my-phd-supervisor-left-me/">shortly after she started with her doctorate</a>, hence the significance of this.</p>
<p>Henceforth, everyone has to add an extra DOCTOR to her already impressive title, namely <a href="https://twitter.com/eagereyes/status/793107701400162305">Evil Empress of the SciVis Galaxy</a>. Doctor Evil Empress of the SciVis Galaxy will continue her reign from her new (iron?) throne in the Visualization Group at the University of Bergen, Norway.</p>
<p>Don’t worry puny subjects, you are in good hands!</p>
<p>I read somewhere that good stories tend to make circles (could anyone help me out with a good reference?), so let me end this thing with a brilliantly coloured but slightly more lonesome sunset:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161102_192034.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/20161102_192034-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Have fun peeps, I hope to see you soon!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #111: A swift hack.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/15/weekly-head-voices-111-a-swift-hack/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2016 20:04:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/15/weekly-head-voices-111-a-swift-hack/</guid><description>Well hello friends! In this here,the one hundred and eleventh edition of the Weekly Head Voices, I present a personal view of selected events that took place in the time between Monday, July 25 and Sunday, August 14 of 2016.
Post summary: HackerNews FastMail to Gmail retrospective (WARNING NERD CONTENT), Craft Beer tips, Swift Playgrounds (teach your kids to code!) and a tiny bit of backyard philosophy at the end.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well hello friends! In this here,the one hundred and eleventh edition of the Weekly Head Voices, I present a personal view of selected events that took place in the time between Monday, July 25 and Sunday, August 14 of 2016.</p>
<p>Post summary: HackerNews FastMail to Gmail retrospective (WARNING NERD CONTENT), Craft Beer tips, Swift Playgrounds (teach your kids to code!) and a tiny bit of backyard philosophy at the end.</p>
<h2 id="the-hackernews-effect">The HackerNews effect</h2>
<p>When I submitted my <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to Fastmail blog post</a> to HackerNews last Monday, it was after some consideration, and with considerable trepidation. The previous time a similar post of mine was picked up by the HN frontpage (and reddit) in 2013, it resulted in a great number of fairly harsh insults flung my way (the harsh ones seem to hit much harder than the many more constructive ones can compensate for). The problem is not having your work criticised, it’s rather being ad hominem’ed into the ground.</p>
<p>The internet can unfortunately get quite bad that way.</p>
<p>However, this time the internet was in a good mood!</p>
<p>As a Z-list (aka hobbyist) blogger, I already get quite excited when even two people find something entertaining or educational in my blog, so you can imagine my excitement when I saw my blog stats jump into the thousands during the first hour after hitting the HN front page.</p>
<p>646 upvotes, 365 comments (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12247401">in the HN discussion</a>) and more than 50 thousand blog post views later (!!), my asbestos suit is still in storage, and the box of kleenex (for drying up my tears) is still unopened. I am very happy with the healthy and mostly happy discussion both on HN and here on the blog.</p>
<h2 id="a-taste-of-my-secret-beer-notes">A taste of my secret beer notes</h2>
<p>In my travels around the world (ok, maybe just in a few hundred kilometre radius of where I live) I taste many exotic and strange drinks (okay, maybe just the local craft beers). Here’s an excerpt from my top secret beer notes for your reading and hopefully soon tasting pleasure:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/stellies_bosch_weiss.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/stellies_bosch_weiss-648x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Stellies Bosch Weiss"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Stellies Bosch Weiss</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The <strong>Stellies Bosch Weiss</strong> is is a refreshing white beer which I can imagine enjoying much more in 35 celsius. However, I find it way too gassy for my taste and thus give it 0.4 on the Celis White scale. As everyone knows, <a href="https://www.beeradvocate.com/beer/profile/565/5222/">Celis White</a> is the best white beer in the world. I’m also not the biggest fan of CBC’s Krystal Weiss because of its gassiness. This could also be a German vs Belgian thing.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://www.darlingbrew.co.za/beers.html#/bc">Darling Brew Bone Crusher</a> is probably a 0.8 on the Celis scale, and scores mega bonus points for choosing such a heavy metal name.









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/patriot_lager.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/patriot_lager-576x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Citizen Beer’s Patriot Lager"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Citizen Beer’s Patriot Lager</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Citizen Beer has a real knack for naming beers; so this weekend I was able to do my patriotic duty (ha ha) by enjoying their <strong>Patriot lager</strong>. Fortunately, they also have a great knack for making lovely beers. This lager is more than hoppy enough to remind you that it’s a craft, but at the same time it is refreshingly light.









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_lager.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_lager-576x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Devil’s Peak Lager"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Devil’s Peak Lager</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Not completely coincidentally, I also tasted the <strong>Devil’s Peak Lager</strong> this weekend. There are subtle differences between it and the Patriot which I will only be able to describe after more tasting. For now: Same lightness, but with enough hop. Highly enjoyable.









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_pale_ale.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_pale_ale-524x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Devil’s Peak Pale Ale"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Devil’s Peak Pale Ale</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>As I’ve mentioned before, it’s no coincidence that happiness and hoppiness look so similar. The <strong>Devil’s Peak Pale Ale</strong> was a superbly hoppy (about 239% more hoppy than the lager) and full flavoured conclusion to the weekend. In spite of its full body this Cape Town beer’s alcohol content is lower than I would have expected: Only 4%.</p>
<h2 id="first-impressions-of-swift-playgrounds">First impressions of Swift Playgrounds</h2>
<p>I might or might not have acquired a new iPad Air 2 with the primary motivation of being able to test the new <a href="https://www.apple.com/swift/playgrounds/">Swift Playgrounds</a> on Genetic Offspring Unit #1 (now 10 years old). This is a new and attractive iPad-only app that has been designed by Apple to teach kids how to program in Swift. Note that you’ll have to upgrade to <a href="https://beta.apple.com/sp/betaprogram/">iOS 10 Beta</a> to get the app, at least until <a href="https://www.apple.com/ios/ios10-preview/">iOS 10 is officially released</a>. One of the exercises looks like this (image taken from the website):</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-14-at-6.25.43-PM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-14-at-6.25.43-PM-1024x729.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Previous experiments with <a href="https://scratch.mit.edu/">scratch</a> and with <a href="https://processing.org/">processing</a> have met with limited success but no permanence. However, GOU#1 is an iPad fanatic, and the potential of getting her addicted to the programming bug is just too fantastic to let this opportunity go by.</p>
<p>On the first day, she was already writing functions and for loops in Swift in order to navigate a cute alien solving puzzles on a 3D landscape.  I was looking over her shoulder now and then: The educational content and execution of the app is impressive. Besides the built-in puzzle worlds such as the 3D one pictures above, you can create your own Swift projects from scratch. These projects can use iPad hardware such as bluetooth and the camera, but we’re not quite there yet. Apple has also promised to keep on expanding the educational content.</p>
<p>I’m really crossing my fingers that GOU#1 will keep at it. If Swift Playgrounds helps to get her programming, I might just have to go full fanboy.</p>
<h2 id="heading">∞♥</h2>
<p>This past Friday at the breakfast table, Genetic Offspring Unit #2 asked her mom how much she thought GOU#2 loved the baby GOU#3, upon which the mom asked “How much do you love GOU#3?”.</p>
<p>GOU#2 answered: Infinitely much!</p>
<p>My fragile parental unit heart almost exploded with happiness at this point. It’s what I tell GOU#1 and #2 when I put them to bed, and every morning when I drop them at school. (GOU#3 herself does not yet parse our language.)</p>
<p>Ok kids, it looks like there’s an infinite amount of the good stuff to go around. You know what to do!










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/bettys_bay_somewhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/bettys_bay_somewhere-1024x576.jpg"
        
            alt="I went jogging (or rather walking with a two-step now and then). Enjoyment of surroundings and physical activity was quite intense at this point in spacetime: 15:55 on August 7, 2016; GPS coordinates in EXIF data."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>I went jogging (or rather walking with a two-step now and then). Enjoyment of surroundings and physical activity was quite intense at this point in spacetime: 15:55 on August 7, 2016; GPS coordinates in EXIF data.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #105: There will be tears.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/15/weekly-head-voices-105/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 20:04:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/15/weekly-head-voices-105/</guid><description>Congratulations, you have successfully completed the week of Monday February 8 to Sunday February 14, 2016!
About 4 seconds after posting previous edition WHV #104 to Facebook with the “When you’re a vegan and haven’t told anyone in 10 minutes” meme image included, friend Ivo T. zinged me with this reply:
So much truth. I have been put back in my place. Sorry vegans. Sorry MBA students. Not sorry Ayn Randers.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Congratulations, you have successfully completed the week of Monday February 8 to Sunday February 14, 2016!</p>
<p>About 4 seconds after posting previous edition <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2016/02/08/weekly-head-voices-104-let-me-update-you/">WHV #104</a> to Facebook with the “When you’re a vegan and haven’t told anyone in 10 minutes” meme image included, friend Ivo T. zinged me with this reply:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/12651073_10153234132252035_804640390912092906_n.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/12651073_10153234132252035_804640390912092906_n.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>So much truth. I have been put back in my place. Sorry vegans. Sorry MBA students. Not sorry Ayn Randers.</p>
<p>This is currently my favourite lager ever (at least until next week):</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/jack_black_lager.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/jack_black_lager-576x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>It is indeed a craft beer. If we’ve ever chatted more than 10 minutes in the past (or in the future), you’ll know everything about my braai, and you probably also know that I find craft beer to be one of the greatest inventions ever, along with fire, and the internet.</p>
<p>Here’s a another beer which I recently had the pleasure of enjoying, at a secret networking meeting (yes, we have secret meetings where we in fact do manage a large number of aspects of your daily life, and where we also orchestrate it so you’ll never suspect that we are behind everything, subtly manipulating reality) where, when the beer arrived at the table, everyone who looked vaguely hipster-like claimed vocally not in fact to be even remotely hipster-like:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/tears_of_the_hipster.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/tears_of_the_hipster-576x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>META-HIPSTER CRAFT BEER! At first I was confused, but then I realised it was just another case of <strong>WHAT A TIME TO BE ALIVE!</strong></p>
<p>(By the way, I stripped the EXIF GPS data from the Jack Black photo, because privacy, but I left it hidden in the tears of the hipster. First one who tells me in the comments where the secret meeting was held gets a free craft beer!)</p>
<p><em>Nerd tip of the week</em>: It’s somehow not prominent enough on their site, but GitLab, the open source GitHub alternative, also <a href="https://about.gitlab.com/gitlab-com/">offer free hosting of an unlimited number of private repositories with an unlimited number of private collaborators</a>. In other words, if you’re on a budget, you can host your commercial and proprietary project git repositories (and bug tracking and wikis) there at <em>no cost</em>. This is cheaper than github ($7 for the smallest subscription for 5 private repos) and better than bitbucket (private repos for free, but if you have more than 5 team members you have to pay). I pay quite gladly for the online services I use, but in this particular case, such a level of free is hard not to like.</p>
<p><em>Nerd tip #2 of the week:</em> The <a href="http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/">Clang static C++ analyser</a> is brilliant. If you program in C++, and you need to up your game, integrating this into your workflow is a solid step in the right direction. I’ve been using this via the <a href="http://clang-analyzer.llvm.org/scan-build.html">scan-build method</a>. Let me know in the comments if you’d like to know more about this!</p>
<p>After some <a href="http://www.pcservices.co.za/">professional</a> ethernet cabling down to the sort-of basement of our new house, I have checked off another item from my non-existent bucket list: <em>We now have a lab at our house.</em> So far there are computers, all kinds of DIY supplies and art stuff for the genetic offspring units, and all of this to <em>create</em>. I spent some of the best times of my life in labs of some sort of another. It’s really great bringing some of that back home to my clan.</p>
<p>Have a great week kids, see you on the other side!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #97: Beerbow.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/10/weekly-head-voices-97-beerbow/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 19:59:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/10/weekly-head-voices-97-beerbow/</guid><description>This, the ninety seventh edition of the WHV, looks back at the week of Monday August 3 to Sunday August 9, 2015.
John Scalzi (famous and successful SciFi author) describes how he works in this post on lifehacker. What I found really interesting was that when he’s working on a book or other project, he switches off the internet between 8 and noon. I just discovered that Four Tet’s mom is South African-born. This week my work time was divided between having to analyse someone else’s quite complex application and bits of their domain in order to implement new features on the one hand, and designing a new relational data representation for workflow provenance on the other. I perceived both of these activities as challenging, and hence (I think) my work week as very satisfying. After the whole day programming at work, I often relax at home in the evenings by programming some more. I’ve noticed that the after-dinner beer (or two) make architectural and design-level work more challenging. On the topic of programming for relaxation, this weekend I had the feeling that my longest-running side-project was finally getting off the ground, at least technically. When it grows up, it really wants to be a non-linear graphical personal knowledge management tool – the crazy and colourful glue linking together all of your digital stuff. On the topic of beer, I made you a photo of my weekend craft beer (the Skeleton Coast IPA by Jack Black) with a rainbow in the background. I call it a beerbow: Have a great week everyone!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the ninety seventh edition of the WHV, looks back at the week of Monday August 3 to Sunday August 9, 2015.</p>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<img alt="Brainbow_(Lichtman_2008).jpg" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/58/Brainbow_(Lichtman_2008).jpg"/>
</p>
</div>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Scalzi">John Scalzi</a> (famous and successful SciFi author) describes how he works in <a href="http://lifehacker.com/im-john-scalzi-and-this-is-how-i-work-1720935145">this post on lifehacker</a>. What I found really interesting was that when he’s working on a book or other project, he switches off the internet between 8 and noon.
  </li>
<li>
    I just discovered that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Tet">Four Tet’s</a> mom is South African-born.
  </li>
<li>
    This week my work time was divided between having to analyse someone else’s quite complex application and bits of their domain in order to implement new features on the one hand, and designing a new relational data representation for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Provenance#Data_provenance">workflow provenance</a> on the other. I perceived both of these activities as challenging, and hence (I think) my work week as very satisfying.
  </li>
<li>
    After the whole day programming at work, I often relax at home in the evenings by programming some more. I’ve noticed that the after-dinner beer (or two) make architectural and design-level work more challenging.
  </li>
<li>
    On the topic of programming for relaxation, this weekend I had the feeling that my longest-running side-project was finally getting off the ground, at least technically. When it grows up, it really wants to be a non-linear graphical personal knowledge management tool – the crazy and colourful glue linking together all of your digital stuff.
  </li>
<li>
    On the topic of beer, I made you a photo of my weekend craft beer (the <a href="http://www.jackblackbeer.com/#skeleton-coast">Skeleton Coast IPA by Jack Black</a>) <i>with a rainbow in the background</i>. I call it a <b>beerbow</b>:
  </li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-skeleton_coast_ipa_rainbow.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/wpid-skeleton_coast_ipa_rainbow.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Have a great week everyone!</p>
<p>P.S. I could not help adding that <em>beerbow</em> was partly inspired by the <em>brainbow</em>, a technique for making individual neurons (brain cells!) fluoresce with different colours. This technique has played a major role in the study of neural connections in the brain (this study is also called <em>connectomics</em>). Read more about the technique in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brainbow">its wikipedia article</a>, and see the pretty examples I have now added to the top of this post!</p>
<p>P.P.S. I just saw that a book chapter called <em>Visualization in Connectomics</em> that we put <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1206.1428">on arxiv (FREE fulltext!!)</a> whilst waiting for the rest of the book to happen, did eventually get <a href="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-1-4471-6497-5_21">published by Springer</a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>A blacksmith and a lumberjack walk into a bar</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/18/a-blacksmith-and-a-lumberjack-walk-into-a-bar/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 17:21:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/18/a-blacksmith-and-a-lumberjack-walk-into-a-bar/</guid><description>Jack Black brewery’s Lumberjack is an amber ale craft brewed in Cape Town. As bottle designs go, this one is pretty metal:
Amongst a number of impressive-sounding statements, the back of the bottle concludes with:
Lumberjack has a sturdy malt driven backbone packed with loads of roasted malt. Huge hop additions intensify the piney-citrus aromas of this full flavoured ale. A beer for the brave.
After reading that, who does not want to drink this beer for the brave?! Based on extensive testing, I can report that this is indeed a full-bodied beer that deserves and rewards your full attention.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Jack Black brewery’s Lumberjack is an amber ale craft brewed in Cape Town. As bottle designs go, this one is pretty <em>metal</em>:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/lumberjack_front.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/lumberjack_front-576x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Amongst a number of impressive-sounding statements, the back of  the bottle concludes with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Lumberjack has a sturdy malt driven backbone packed with loads of roasted malt. Huge hop additions intensify the piney-citrus aromas of this full flavoured ale. A beer for the brave.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>After reading that, who does <em>not</em> want to drink this <strong>beer for the brave</strong>?! Based on extensive testing, I can report that this is indeed a full-bodied beer that deserves and rewards your full attention.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://blacksmithskitchen.co.za/">Blacksmith’s Kitchen</a> is a vineyard restaurant in Paarl. It looks like this:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/blacksmiths_kitchen.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/blacksmiths_kitchen-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The views from the outside tables are quite beautiful:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/blacksmiths_kitchen_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/blacksmiths_kitchen_view-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Weather permitting (which is very often in Paarl), this kitchen is absolutely worth a visit.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #89: Xanthohumol.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/02/01/weekly-head-voices-89-xanthohumol/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 17:01:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/02/01/weekly-head-voices-89-xanthohumol/</guid><description>I found myself in Stellenbosch this weekend, so I drove by my old student house. Fifteen odd years ago, the house used to go by the name The Far Side. It was usually inhabited by five fairly attractive yet dangerously intelligent male engineering students, who were, quite unexpectedly, also extremely modest. (In those days, prepending “male” to “engineering student” was mostly redundant.)
Well, it seems The Far Side has gone through a little transformation of its own:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I found myself in Stellenbosch this weekend, so I drove by my old student house. Fifteen odd years ago, the house used to go by the name <em>The Far Side</em>. It was usually inhabited by five fairly attractive yet <em>dangerously</em> intelligent male engineering students, who were, quite unexpectedly, also extremely modest. (In those days, prepending “male” to “engineering student” was mostly redundant.)</p>
<p>Well, it seems <em>The Far Side</em> has gone through a little transformation of its own:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/wpid-farside-now-venustia.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/wpid-farside-now-venustia.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Yes, there are little hearts hanging everywhere, and the little hearts have, probably in some kind of fractal frenzy, been arranged to form even larger hearts. In my mind, <em>The Far Side</em> was still exactly as we had left it, except with a new bunch of unexpectedly modest engineering students, thinking, saying and doing things almost like we used to, except for the occasional interjection of ideas that did not yet exist in our time, like “wifi”, “tablet” and “smartphone”.</p>
<p>Initial pattern-matching-driven expectations and consequent surprise aside, this was a physical reminder that even mundane matters can change quite significantly given sufficient time. This is a good thing, although the whole fractal cardiac decoration aspect was perhaps not completely called-for.</p>
<p>On the nerd front:</p>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
    I wrote a vxlabs blog post on <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2015/01/28/sending-emails-with-math-and-source-code/">sending pretty emails with math and syntax highlighted source code</a>, of course using emacs, org-mode and mu4e.
  </li>
<li>
    After some emacs-lisp tracing through mu4e and gnus, I finally discovered how to activate <code>format=flowed</code> in the default text/plain emails sent with mu4e, thus enabling reflowing of hard-wrapped emails on receiving (mobile) clients that support this. It occurred to me that the group of nerds affected by this particular behaviour in this particular software setup is <i>extremely</i> small. Read all about it in <a href="https://github.com/djcb/mu/issues/569">my github issue report</a> on the matter.
  </li>
<li>
    I wrote <a href="http://osssa.org.za/2015/01/27/cape-town-open-data-portal-now-live-unfortunately-with-microsoft-file-formats/">an osssa blog post</a> on the opening of the new Cape Town Open Data Portal (fantastic!) using non-open Microsoft file format standards (not so great).
  </li>
</ul>
<p>Blog reader MrK sent me <a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2015/01/150128113947.htm">this sciencedaily article</a> with the great news that there is a small but real chance that beer <em>might</em> protect us from neurodegenerative diseases. In lab tests it was found that xanthohumol, a compound found in hops, could <em>potentially</em> protect brain cells against neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer’s and Parkinson’s. Of course we should be very careful jumping to conclusions based on these types of experiments performed on isolated compounds under lab conditions.</p>
<p>That being said, I do think that careful optimism whilst enjoying beer might be justified. As we all know, the more beer one drinks, the more intelligent one becomes, at least up to a certain optimum:</p>
<div class="figure">
<p>
<img alt="ballmer_peak.png" src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/ballmer_peak.png"/>
</p>
</div>
<p>It seems there’s even a shadowy but very powerful organization built upon this exact principle. They are called <em>The Inebriati</em>:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-Zj50DmBFp0?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Thanks for reading this. I hope that you have a great week, and I hope to see you again soon.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>