<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Vxlabs on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/vxlabs/</link><description>Recent content in Vxlabs on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 22:34:38 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/vxlabs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #223: The potjie never left</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 22:34:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/</guid><description>Welcome friends to the two hundred and twenty third edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the period of time from Monday May 3 to Sunday May 16, 2021.
(Hah, by writing out the words like that, I&amp;rsquo;ll get paid even more for this article!)
Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome friends to the two hundred and twenty third edition of the Weekly Head
Voices, covering the period of time from Monday May 3 to Sunday May 16, 2021.</p>
<p>(Hah, by writing out the words like that, I&rsquo;ll get paid even more for this
article!)</p>










<figure><a href="verg_just_before_endurance_broke.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_7cbec36f66f46ce9.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_9c00e99c7ebe6317.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_5b4904a8b92c6eb0.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_2059833eebfe1bf7.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/verg_just_before_endurance_broke_hu_9c00e99c7ebe6317.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from the perfect first half of a run, right before that sublime experience was sunk by a catastrophic audio hardware fault.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="vxlabs-software-development-handbook-v1-is-out">vxlabs software development handbook v1 is out</h2>
<p>Well, it&rsquo;s not really a book, more of a blog post really, but it is chock full
of practical guidelines for developers.</p>
<p>It is also 100% free and open source, and can be accessed <a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/">over at the vxlabs</a>.</p>
<p>None of this will be surprising for any of you experienced developers, but it&rsquo;s
super handy having a single place that you can point folks at when you have
some specific advice in mind.</p>
<p>My personal favourite and most important guideline is <a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/#comment-your-code">&ldquo;Comment your code&rdquo;</a>. It
seems that this advice really can&rsquo;t be repeated often enough.</p>
<p>The first commit (i.e. words written) happened on December 14 of 2020, and
version 1 published on 2021-05-03. Most of this had to happen in between other
activities, but that&rsquo;s ok. This is one of the <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#interstitial-projects">interstitial projects</a> I implied
in January.</p>
<h2 id="world-in-my-eyes">World in my eyes</h2>
<p>The photo at the start of this post was taken at the entrance of Vergelegen, at
about 7km into an absolute epic Saturday late afternoon run.</p>
<p>It was epic, because the autumn weather was absolutely perfect, my running
mechanism was smooth and efficient, and there was great music piping into my
brain via the recently acquired JBL Endurance Run bluetooth earphones.</p>
<p>I mention the earphones specifically, because for the first time I had found
something that fit perfectly and even advertised being &ldquo;sweatproof&rdquo; on the box,
a characteristic that is quite important when you produce as much sweat as I
do. (TMI, but please bear with me here)</p>
<p>I was so satisfied after five or six runs that I had taken a few photos earlier
that day, as I was planning a short blog post extolling the virtues of said
gadget.</p>
<p>Probably about 60 seconds after I took the photo, running back out to the road,
thinking to myself how great these earphones were working and how far I was
still going to run and how amazing everything is, the right earphone starts
going &ldquo;GGGGGGGHHHHHRRRRRRRRGGGGGWWWWWGGGGHHHHHH&rdquo; (you have to read that with an
authentic, hard Dutch guttural) and it simply does not stop.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Have you tried switching them off and on again?&rdquo; you might say.</p>
<p>Well, the sound just kept on going, switched on, or off.</p>
<p>No amount of power cycling, shaking, re-pairing or swearing made any
difference.</p>
<p>Right earphone just kept on going &ldquo;GGGGGGGHHHRRRRRGGGGHHHHH&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I finally bundled up the JBL TripSpoiler BT into my hand, and ran home, like a
person who runs without music.</p>
<p>P.S. The section title is a Depeche Mode song (one of my teenage favourites) in
which the highest mountain is contrasted with the deepest sea, albeit in a
utterly different context.</p>
<p>P.P.S. As I write this, takealot is sending me a replacement set. I&rsquo;m hoping
the new unit is an anti-lemon.</p>
<h2 id="pretty-hip-birthday-party">Pretty hip birthday party</h2>
<p>GOU #2 held her 11th party here at our facility.</p>
<p>The plans started out as a VR party (or at least that&rsquo;s what I thought), but
great forces out of my control determined that There Would Also Need to Be
Karaoke.</p>
<p>This is one time where the more technically inclined dads can shine!</p>
<p>I purchased exactly one cheap but great value Karaoke microphone (the Samson
SCR10S Karaoke Dynamic Microphone with Switch, if you must know), and then
mixed everything together using an old Windows laptop, our old burglary-proof
(when flat screens were still thick) TV with HDMI input, and a bunch of cables.</p>
<p>Friends arrived, and an extremely fun-looking and partially sugar-fuelled
teenage chaos ensued.</p>
<p>Interestingly, the VR setup ended up getting a significant chunk of the
attention. Even amongst these ultra-connected digital natives, the tech is
still new enough to garner a substantial amount of the unobtainium aka
attention.</p>
<p>(Although I never ever sing, not even in the shower, that karaoke setup has a
surprisingly strong magnetic force, if you catch my drift. GOU #2 was quite
relieved when none of her parents decided to make a guest appearance at the
main event. In my case, it&rsquo;s really for the better.)</p>
<h2 id="boomer-party">Boomer party</h2>
<p>A few days later, after we had sufficiently recovered from the teenage party,
it was time to invite long time friends of ours over for an old people party.</p>
<p>As is our wont down here, when the friends are this dear, we take time to make
a potjie.</p>
<p>The autumn weather contributed fabulously, and so we enjoyed scenes like this:</p>










<figure><a href="chicken-curry-potjie-2021.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_851d8ef19cf3be22.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_a6e81b0fbea9949a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_c7468ed7bcf7e946.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_e029c5f2d370256.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/21/weekly-head-voices-223-the-potjie-never-left/chicken-curry-potjie-2021_hu_a6e81b0fbea9949a.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: From this photo, it&rsquo;s also quite clear that I have become much taller."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: From this photo, it&rsquo;s also quite clear that I have become much taller.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Readers of this blog might recognise the visual composition above, perhaps from
<a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/">a post back in January of 2016</a>, when I initiated the pot with coincidentally
the same recipe.</p>
<p>The potjie scene seems to repeat itself (these are not the only two examples),
acting as a sort of reliable cast iron backdrop (with enamel coating!) for our
family and friendship rituals.</p>
<p>On this day, the ritual was indeed sublime.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #216: Sup?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 09:08:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/</guid><description>Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.
Figure 1: Sup?
The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard with Lots of Focus.
I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily application of the One Main Thing idea, but experience has taught me that it&amp;rsquo;s probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&amp;rsquo;ll be solidly back in the arms of my old friend the really slippery eel.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello everyone, and welcome to WHV #216, the one looking back at the two weeks
from Monday February 1 to Sunday February 14, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="sup_bettys.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_fb2d17c10710e237.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_44250e253e07a2d6.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_f280c2aa6b5952a1.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_229a3bd50666e81d.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/02/19/weekly-head-voices-216-sup/sup_bettys_hu_44250e253e07a2d6.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sup?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Sup?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The two weeks in question can be characterised by Somehow Working Really Hard
with Lots of Focus.</p>
<p>I would like to say that it has something to do with the liberal daily
application of <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">the One Main Thing idea</a>, but experience has taught me that it&rsquo;s
probably some other unexpected and hidden interaction of a number of obscure
factors that I will never ever understand, and that next week I&rsquo;ll be solidly
back in the arms of my old friend the <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">really slippery eel</a>.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I have been making good use of the (temporarily?)
increased capacity.</p>
<h2 id="fresh-from-the-oven-vxlabs-software-development-handbook">Fresh from the oven: vxlabs software development handbook</h2>
<p><a href="https://vxlabs.com/software-development-handbook/">The vxlabs software development handbook</a>, at the time of this writing about 65%
complete (that&rsquo;s a random number that my brain gives me every time I publish a
new version), is now available over on my nerdy blog.</p>
<p>If you are working with a smaller development team, or you&rsquo;re starting with a
new dev team, the handbook is not the worst place to look for development
process tips. Furthermore, it&rsquo;s available under the Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International License, so you can copy and paste and rebrand to
your heart&rsquo;s content as long as you give due credit somewhere to the original
author (me and vxlabs).</p>
<p>In the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll be trying to complete more sections to get closer to
that mythical 100% completion grade.</p>
<h2 id="two-miscellaneous-tips-for-nerds">Two miscellaneous tips for nerds</h2>
<h3 id="printfriendly-on-your-phone">PrintFriendly on your phone</h3>
<p>You might remember from my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#web-pages-and-articles">2019 note-taking strategy post</a> that I convert all
interesting web pages I come across to PDF and dump them in my dropbox.</p>
<p>This has turned out to be the best way to store web-pages for later searching,
reference and winning of arguments.</p>
<p>However, the mobile part of that strategy was traditionally weak, as is also
discussed in that post.</p>
<p>The problem was that Safari on iPhone has a great reading mode that strips ads
and other unnecessary bits, but when you print from reading mode, the PDF is
formatted for mobile, and, more importantly, there&rsquo;s no way to get the source
URL embedded in the PDF.</p>
<p>Anyways, after years of using the <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/">PrintFriendly</a> browser extension on the
desktop (as is also explained in the note-taknig post), I finally got around to
installing their mobile bookmarklet on the iPhone. (this should work on any
mobile browser)</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.printfriendly.com/extensions/iOS">instructions are a bit finicky</a>, but one ends up with a bookmark that you
can activate on any page to have the printfriendly service pre-process that
page for reading, from which you can tap on the print icon to get a mostly
perfect PDF that is also stamped with the source URL!</p>
<h3 id="fish-shell">Fish shell</h3>
<p>After years of resisting all the zsh blog posts and especially the pretty
oh-my-zsh powerline prompts and sticking to my stock standard bash because
get-off-my-lawn, I finally broke down and installed&hellip;</p>
<p><a href="https://fishshell.com/">fish!</a></p>
<p>fish shell is a &ldquo;smart and user-friendly command line shell for Linux, macOS,
and the rest of the family&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I like it because one of its goals is to be more useful with hardly any extra
configuration, but you can also install <a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/oh-my-fish">oh-my-fish</a> with my new favourite theme
<a href="https://github.com/oh-my-fish/theme-bobthefish">bobthefish</a>.</p>
<p>I <em>was</em> planning to convince you of my choice with a number of technical
reasons, but it is now clear to me that technical arguments are irrelevant when
you can rock a theme called &ldquo;bobthefish&rdquo;.</p>
<p>P.S. Let me know in the comments if you would still prefer to talk about
technical reasons.</p>
<h2 id="a-brief-pause">A brief pause</h2>
<p>Since we <a href="/2021/02/02/weekly-head-voices-215-gateway-universe-taalmonument/#gou-1-s-growing-running-habit">last spoke about GOU#1&rsquo;s running habit</a>, it gives me great pleasure to
report that she has, quite routinely if I may add, done another two or three
10k runs, one of them even up to eleven by accident.</p>
<p>Folks I wish you all the best. I look forward to our next connection!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #122: Thanks Pythagoras.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/06/11/weekly-head-voices-122/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 13:14:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/06/11/weekly-head-voices-122/</guid><description> Pink sunset, as they do here in my backyard.
Welcome back everyone!
During a brilliant breakfast chat with friends who are visiting from afar, friend S (now 16.67% name-dropped) admitted that the WHV, strange unfocused mishmash of thoughts that it is, contributed positively to his information diet.
In spite of this admission adding to my already considerable posting anxiety, I am enormously grateful for the encouragement. I often worry about this mishmash, as I also aspire to enter the fabled halls of A-list bloggers one day.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/swest_pink_sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/swest_pink_sunset-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Pink sunset, as they do here in my backyard."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pink sunset, as they do here in my backyard.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>During a brilliant breakfast chat with friends who are visiting from afar, friend S (now 16.67% name-dropped) admitted that the WHV, strange unfocused mishmash of thoughts that it is, contributed positively to his information diet.</p>
<p>In spite of this admission adding to my already considerable posting anxiety, I am enormously grateful for the encouragement. I often worry about this mishmash, as I also aspire to enter the fabled halls of A-list bloggers one day.</p>
<p>Perhaps I should just embrace the mishmash. Again.</p>
<p>In this edition of the mishmash, I extremely sparsely review the weeks from Monday May 8 to Sunday June 11.</p>
<p>During our weekly extra math, science and philosophy lessons, GOU#1 (now 11 years old) and I arrived through serendipity at the topic of Pythagoras. Her mind almost visibly expanded when she discovered the relationship between the 9, 16 and 25 square adjacent squares I drew for her on the 3-4-5 example triangle. Her eyes went wide when I explained that this works for <em>any</em> right-angled triangle.</p>
<p>She was soon happily squaring, adding (long-form on paper of course) and square-rooting away on geometry problems.</p>
<p>Seeing your own child discover the beauty that is math is brilliant.</p>
<p>After complaining about <a href="/2016/11/27/android-security-in-2016-is-a-mess/">subpar android security</a> and <a href="/2017/02/12/android-vs-iphone-performance-a-quick-note/">dismal android performance</a> on this blog, I finally decided to bite the bullet and acquired a second-hand iPhone 6S 64GB on May 10, 2017. The phone is in mint condition, and the price was excellent.</p>
<p>So far, the performance is substantially better than any of my previous Androids. In fact, so far I’ve never had to wait for anything on this phone, which was my main issue with the Androids. (Google Maps anyone?!) Besides that, when Apple pushes a software update, all phones immediately get that update, without interference from any third parties, including carriers.</p>
<p>(A word to the wise: There is no official way to transfer your complete WhatsApp message history from Android to iPhone, which was a huge disappointment. There are unofficial, closed-sourced, solutions that require one to connect one’s Android phone in USB debugging mode to the PC. That risk is a bit too great for me.)</p>
<p>After a period of rest, <a href="http://visible-orbit.org/">the Visible Orbit website</a>, including the <a href="http://visible-orbit.org/the-collection/high-res-section-stacks/">high-resolution microscopic slice data and viewer</a>, is online again! It was quite satisfying getting all of the backed-up data back on the interwebs again.</p>
<p>Since the previous WHV (well actually mainly during the last week), I’ve published five posts on my nerd blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/03/bitcoin-and-the-blockchain-in-10-minutes/">Bitcoin and the blockchain in 10 minutes</a> – I extracted this from <a href="/2016/07/25/weekly-head-voices-110-satoshi/">WHV #110</a>, because I’ve been spending way too much time on various blockchains (read: cryptocurrencies) and was planning more nerdy blog posts over here.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/03/querying-restful-webservices-into-emacs-orgmode-tables/">Querying RESTful webservices into Emacs orgmode tables</a> – Here I combined two of my obsessions, one old (Emacs) and the other new (cryptocurrencies) to show how you could pull live ticker data (prices) into your Emacs.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/06/setting-up-fastcgi-apps-on-webfaction/">Setting up FastCGI apps on WebFaction</a> – I love it when work leads to spin-off blog posts! In this case, to get the visible-orbit high-res slice viewer working on WebFaction, I had to jump some hoops. This post shows you how to jump them too.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/07/adding-page-sidebar-to-wordpress-twenty-seventeen-theme/">Adding page sidebar to WordPress Twenty Seventeen theme</a> – Intellectually the least interesting, but still a visible-orbit spin-off that might help at least one other person. I’m crossing my fingers.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/06/10/extracting-the-jaxx-12-word-wallet-backup-phrase/">Extracting the Jaxx 12-word wallet backup phrase</a> – After a few hours of analysis on Saturday (yesterday), I discovered a serious vulnerability in a popular multi-cryptocurrency wallet. The post has been picked up by a number of other blogs, and has caused good discussion on the various social media outlets.</li>
</ul>
<p>Three of those five posts have to do with cryptocurrency, which is to a certain extent a reflection of my free-time mental cycles at the moment. Looking at how technology such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ethereum">Ethereum</a> and its Smart Contracts (a Smart Contract blog post is currently forming in the back of my head…) seem to be breaking through, I can’t help but be reminded of stories such as those by Charlie Stross in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Accelerando">Accelerando</a> (at least the first bits).</p>
<p>Do we find ourselves at the start of something truly significant, or is this just an extremely elegant and high-tech dead-end?</p>
<p>What a time to be alive!</p>
<p>P.S. Here, have another outdoorsy photo on the house!










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/IMG_0109.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/IMG_0109-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="I tricked GOU#1 and GOU#2 to join me on a sneakily long mountain walk. They did a sterling job."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>I tricked GOU#1 and GOU#2 to join me on a sneakily long mountain walk. They did a sterling job.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Nerd-alert: Ubuntu Linux 12.04 on my NVIDIA Optimus Samsung NP300V3A laptop</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/05/02/nerd-alert-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-my-nvidia-optimus-samsung-np300v3a-laptop/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 08:01:14 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/05/02/nerd-alert-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-my-nvidia-optimus-samsung-np300v3a-laptop/</guid><description>When I acquired my pre-ultrabook-era but still pretty Samsung NP300V3A laptop some nine months ago, I lamented that I’d probably never be able to put Linux on there due to the NVIDIA Optimus graphics switching thingamagoo.
Well, yesterday I ate my hat.
If you have nerdy tendencies, head on over to VXLabs, my nerd blog, to read all about it.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>When I acquired my pre-ultrabook-era but still pretty <a href="/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/" title="samsung np300v3a welcome post">Samsung NP300V3A laptop some nine months ago</a>, I lamented that I’d probably never be able to put Linux on there due to the NVIDIA Optimus graphics switching thingamagoo.</p>
<p>Well, yesterday I ate my hat.</p>
<p>If you have nerdy tendencies, head on over to VXLabs, my nerd blog, to <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2012/05/01/review-of-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-the-samsung-np300v3a-core-i5-nvidia-optimus-laptop/" title="ubuntu 12.04 on Samsung NP300V3A post on VXLabs">read all about it</a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Great Success! [weekly head voices #48]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/05/15/great-success-weekly-head-voices-48/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2011 17:24:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/05/15/great-success-weekly-head-voices-48/</guid><description>Seven years ago, a wise man gave the following advice on this blog:
There are two rules to success in life:
Rule 1: Don’t tell people everything you know.
At that stage, twitter did not exist yet (the first tweet would only be made on March 21, 2006), so the clearly visionary post author had the habit of writing short, tweet-like blog posts. Because times have changed (my posts are slightly longer than 140 characters these days), but the advice is still sound, I’m repeating it here.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Seven years ago, a wise man <a href="/2004/05/20/the-two-rules-to-success-in-life/">gave the following advice on this blog</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There are two rules to success in life:</p>
<p>Rule 1: Don’t tell people everything you know.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At that stage, twitter did not exist yet (the first tweet would only be made on March 21, 2006), so the clearly visionary post author had the habit of writing short, tweet-like blog posts. Because times have changed (my posts are slightly longer than 140 characters these days), but the advice is still sound, I’m repeating it here.</p>
<p>Also on the topic of success, he most significant event of the past week must be <a href="http://www.clinicalgraphics.com/" title="Clinical Graphics website">Clinical Graphics</a>, represented by its CEO Dr. Peter Krekel, winning the prestigious Philips Innovation Award (PHIA) 2011. See below for a video of the announcement, the real action starts at 3:50 (you can even hear me shouting):</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0TEkWyaWWc0?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>It was absolutely awesome being there to witness this grand event. Clinical Graphics won this for the largest part due to its innovative product, but the company was also evaluated, by a jury consisting of Extremely Experienced and Probably Very Rich Entrepreneurs and High-Powered Managers, based on its full business plan and potential. I am of course also fantastically proud of my good friend Dr. Krekel, having coincidentally had the privilege to act as his academic advisor throughout his master’s and his Ph.D., and now as scientific advisor to Clinical Graphics. Watch this company, do buy their stuff or get the people you know to buy more of their stuff!</p>
<p>By the way, I got to take a 20 minute ride on the AquaLiner (I WAS ON A BOAT!) from the Willemskade in Rotterdam (where I took the photo below) through the Rotterdam harbour (it’s frikking awesome) to the RDM campus where the PHIA finals were held:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/erasmus_bridge_20110513.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/05/erasmus_bridge_20110513-1024x612.jpg"
        
            alt="Erasmus Bridge and surroundings taken before boarding the AquaLiner to the PHIA 2011 finals at the RDM campus."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Erasmus Bridge and surroundings taken before boarding the AquaLiner to the PHIA 2011 finals at the RDM campus.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>In other less momentous news, I’ve actually written <strong>three</strong> blog posts today:</p>
<ol>
<li>This one.</li>
<li><a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/05/15/ubuntu-11-04-natty-narwhal-annoyances-dell-e6410-with-nvs-3100m-gpu/" title="ubuntu 11.04 annoyances post on VxLabs.">A post on my ultra-nerd blog VxLabs</a> dealing with a number of annoyances and their work-arounds in the latest Ubuntu release, version 11.04, aka The Natty Narwhal (eeuw).</li>
</ol>
<p>So that’s it for now kids! Let’s focus on GREAT SUCCESS this week, ok? Whilst you’re pondering how to get started doing this, you could do worse than watching this video of a dude lip-syncing the 50 worst video game voices, in quite entertaining and hence probably successful, fashion:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/R_bx_9QYt7k?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Future is Sick [Weekly Head Voices #36]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/23/the-future-is-sick-weekly-head-voices-36/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2011 21:12:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/23/the-future-is-sick-weekly-head-voices-36/</guid><description>Post summary: Conference, VXLabs, SIP, boots, backyard philosophy on you the consumer, dramatic reading. Read on for more!
Just before the weekend I spent two days at the Dutch Bio-Medical Engineering Conference in Egmond aan Zee, in a ginormous seaside hotel. Probably because I attempted to keep up with the young ones during their nightly escapades, I’m currently dealing quite badly with a serious cold, which is why this is the first sick blog post of 2011. Besides all those germs, I also brought you this photo of said seaside right after sunset: Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Conference, VXLabs, SIP, boots, backyard philosophy on you the consumer, dramatic reading. Read on for more!</em></p>
<p>Just before the weekend I spent two days at the Dutch Bio-Medical Engineering Conference in Egmond aan Zee, in a ginormous seaside hotel. Probably because I attempted to keep up with the young ones during their nightly escapades, I’m currently dealing quite badly with a serious cold, which is why this is the first sick blog post of 2011.  Besides all those germs, I also brought you this photo of said seaside right after sunset:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/egmond_aan_zee_bme2011.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/egmond_aan_zee_bme2011.jpg"
        
            alt="Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The conference was an energetic and motivating affair, at which yours truly even got to chair a session, during which I tried, in spite of not getting to bed all that early the night before, to Keep Things Extremely Punctual As Well As Mildly Entertaining. I succeeded in the former, you’ll have to ask the audience about the latter.</p>
<p>The absolute highlight, for me at least, was the capstone on Friday by <a href="https://depts.washington.edu/biointel/" title="Prof. Satava's website">Professor Richard Satava</a>, a surgeon with an amazing vision of the future. Bordering on science fiction but for a large part backed by his own and other groups’ research, his superbly delivered presentation touched on surgical operating rooms completely staffed by robots (some elements remotely controlled by a surgeon), cell engineering, surgery robots that heal troops at the scene of the crime (hehe), genetic engineering, cloning and a healthy dash of trans-humanism. By the end the whole room was collectively straining at the leash to go and genetically upgrade anything and anyone they could find. With a room full of BME researchers, that’s more dangerous than it sounds. :)</p>
<p>Other note-worthy items of the past two weeks can be summarised in the following neat bullet list:</p>
<ul>
<li>I’ve started a new blog, called VXLabs, for matters that are too nerdy even for this blog. If you’re interested, you can start by reading the <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/01/22/htc-desire-z-an-in-depth-and-nerdy-review/" title="in-depth and nerdy review of the HTC Desire Z at VXLabs">HTC Desire Z (my lovely new smartphone) review</a> I’ve recently gotten around to writing. If you’re nerdy enough, you might consider subscribing VXLabs as well!</li>
<li>There are far cheaper ways than Skype to call telephones around the world. With SIP software, such as SIPDroid on Android, you can use cheap SIP servers that even offer free calls to many destinations. See <a href="http://www.backsla.sh/betamax" title="table of betamax providers">this page</a> for a list of just the betamax (German VOIP company) providers and the free countries that they support.</li>
<li>I was approached by a company producing Ugg-like boots to review their boots, get a free pair in the process, and get a good deal for my readers. This is probably because I went on about those BEAUTIFUL Timberland boots in one of my previous posts. Although I was flattered that the gentleman in question thought my widely-read (haha) opinion would be good for his brand and he called this a <em>fashion blog</em> (!!), I declined, stating that my readership probably is more into Timberlands than Uggs. That’s true, readership? Right?!</li>
<li><strong>Micro Backyard Philosophy</strong>: After one of those late nights refreshing my Twitter, Facebook, Google Reader and GMail for the Nth time, I got to thinking about how the internet sometimes turns us into 100% consumers, leaving <strong>no room for creativity</strong>. It’s insidious, because we believe that the internet will give us exactly what we crave if we just know how to search for it, and that it should do so with that next press on the refresh button, when in fact this is hardly ever the case, especially when that which you crave is in fact to create. Remember this the next time it’s getting late and you think Just One More Refresh. Don’t push that button. <strong>Sit back and think about what you really want to do</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it boys and girls, thank you very much for reading this far! You go and have yourselves a fabulous and especially creative week. If you get lonely waiting for the next edition of the Weekly Head Voices, marvel at this dramatic reading of a bad user game review, creativity at its finest:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Z2Z23SAFVA?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>