<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>mr robot on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/mr-robot/</link><description>Recent content in mr robot on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2015 20:17:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/mr-robot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #96: Never gonna give you up.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/03/weekly-head-voices-96-never-gonna-give-you-up/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2015 20:17:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/03/weekly-head-voices-96-never-gonna-give-you-up/</guid><description> The week has resulted in a terribly nerdy list of bullets. READ AT YOUR OWN RISK! (there’s a beer recommendation or three at the end to compensate)
It turns out that the terrible Samsung trim bug which would eat all of your data, as discovered by Algolia, was a Linux kernel bug after all (now patched by Samsung) and that it would only affect RAID setups. Let’s hope there are no surprising new turning outs.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The week has resulted in a terribly nerdy list of bullets. READ AT YOUR OWN RISK! (there’s a beer recommendation or three at the end to compensate)</p>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
    It turns out that the terrible Samsung trim bug which would eat all of your data, <a href="https://blog.algolia.com/when-solid-state-drives-are-not-that-solid/">as discovered by Algolia</a>, was <a href="http://www.spinics.net/lists/raid/msg49468.html">a Linux kernel bug after all</a> (now patched by Samsung) and that it would only affect RAID setups. Let’s hope there are no surprising new turning outs.
  </li>
<li>
    Found out that the fastest ADSL lines available at my new place are a whole 2 Mbit/s. We’ve called off the transaction and we’re now searching for a new house.
  </li>
<li>
    I’m joking. It <b>was</b> really shocking however to consider the world as seen through a 2 Mbit/s connection. Now it seems that I will soon be entering the wonderful world of 5 GHz wireless connectivity, which should give me a fast enough connection, at least until fibre is rolled out in the year 3047.
  </li>
<li>
    Started watching <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4158110/">Mr Robot</a>. I don’t normally do series, but the pilot was just <i>that</i> good. I like the story, I really like the socially very strangely adjusted hacker protagonist and I love the cinematography. Up to episode 3, I give it 4 out of 5 Linux Distributions!
  </li>
<li>
    Continued fighting with OSX to get it completely working with my Dvorak and Emacs keybindings, also in Java apps such as IntelliJ IDEA. <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2015/07/19/weekly-head-voices-94-into-the-wild/">Two weeks ago I mentioned karabiner</a> as a solution to most of these problems. The final piece of the puzzle was unbinding keys like <code>Alt+W</code> (or <code>Mod+W</code> as Apple calls it) in <code>~/Library/KeyBindings/DefaultKeyBinding.dict</code> to prevent OSX from turning it into a \(\Sigma\) (sigma); as everyone knows, <code>M-w</code> is the Emacs shortcut for copying the selected region! You can use this trick to prevent OSX from turning any of the other <code>Mod</code> combos into completely unwanted special characters. (My base dict file is <a href="http://www.hcs.harvard.edu/~jrus/Site/cocoa-text.html">that of Jacob Rus</a>.)
  </li>
<li>
    I guess OSX only Just Works(tm) if your time is worth nothing. Err…
  </li>
<li>
    My <a href="https://github.com/kivy/kivy/pull/3506">first Kivy pull request</a>, a fix for a Mac-bug (go figure), was recently merged into <a href="http://kivy.org/">master</a>. I’ve been using Kivy in the third or fourth generation of my current and probably longest running side project.
  </li>
<li>
    I’ve also been screencasting some of my night-time coding sessions using one of the more prominent livecoding sites (bonus points if you can find these sleep-inducing performances). It has been an interesting and strange experience programming with people watching over one’s shoulder as it were.
  </li>
<li>
    On Sunday, I ended up at the <a href="http://www.root44.co.za/index.php">Root44 Market</a> in Stellenbosch for another of those really terrible balmy winter days. I had so much fun in the sun, tasting <a href="http://www.devilspeakbrewing.co.za/first-light-golden-ale/">Devil’s Peak First Light Golden Ale</a> and their <a href="http://www.devilspeakbrewing.co.za/kings-blockhouse-ipa/">King’s Blockhouse IPA</a>, and <a href="http://stellenbrau.co.za/beers/">Stellenbrau’s Craven Lager</a>, all from the tap, that I forgot to take a photo of the beautiful surroundings.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>Have a beautiful week dear readers! Just remember, <em>I’m never gonna give you up.</em></p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/v4_M5PcJQmU?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;start=45&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>