<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Devide on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/devide/</link><description>Recent content in Devide on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 21:53:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/devide/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #173: I know.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</guid><description> Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm still quite bad. Let&amp;rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:
Well hello there folks!
A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not have much to report on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="helderberg_protea.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu_66c419594fe907b8.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu_1f4206b92344cf93.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu_c50f4b5f50802767.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu_1d16e531377b9b0d.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu_1f4206b92344cf93.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By
the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm
still quite bad.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:</p>
<p>Well hello there folks!</p>
<p>A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not
have much to report on.</p>
<p>However, it&rsquo;s funny how these things go. One week nothing&hellip; Then it&rsquo;s just a
single week later and there&rsquo;s almost a bit too much that I would like to talk
about.</p>
<p>It seems to have been a mix of more writing, but also just more doing.</p>
<p>So, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 1 to Sunday July 14, 2019, I
would like to present the following notes.</p>
<h2 id="bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Bullet List of Miscellany (BLoM).</h2>
<ul>
<li>GOU#1, age 13, is on a week-long school trip in a different time zone
(GMT+8). I am super happy that she can have this experience, but durnit, one
misses one&rsquo;s genetic offspring units dearly!</li>
<li>Remember that I told you about our <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">solar inverter not talking to the
battery&rsquo;s BMS</a>?
Well, one small recommended firmware upgrade later, from 151507 to 151508,
and the whole system is completely down. Please cross your fingers, because
we&rsquo;ve tried <strong>everything</strong> else.</li>
<li>I regularly get accosted by off-leash dogs whilst running. There are
incredibly clear by-laws down here which absolutely forbid any dog ever being
off-leash in any public space which is not a designated off-leash zone. I
recently made the mistake (twice) of trying to explain this to the relevant
dog-owners. Well, dog-owners seem to be quite sadly under-endowed in the area
of introspective capability, but at least I&rsquo;m getting a lot better at
unprepared debates in public spaces. (Psychologists in the audience, help me
out here with any tips please!)</li>
<li>I really enjoyed <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/162-medical-intelligence/">this Sam Harris podcast with Eric
Topol</a>. <a href="https://www.scripps.edu/faculty/topol/">Eric
Topol</a> is a cardiologist and the
founder and director of the Scripps Research Translational Institute in the
US. Apart from the main topic of the discussion, namely Topol&rsquo;s
well-developed and articulated view of AI in medicine (well, his books on
this topic are quite influential, so there&rsquo;s that), I was struck and inspired
by the humble gentleness of this impressive intellect. Furthermore, although
we are not supposed to use twitter anymore (in some circles, it has been
dubbed &ldquo;road rage of the internet&rdquo;), <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Prof Topol&rsquo;s tweet
stream</a> is a shining example of how twitter
could be used more constructively.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email">Would you like some more Emacs with that Email?</h2>
<p>During the past two weeks I published two blog posts on my nerd blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/03/send-queued-mails-in-background-with-mu4e/">Sending queued mails in the background with
mu4e.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/05/mbsync-vs-offlineimap-speed/">Is mbsync really faster than offlineimap? A
measurement.</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Based on these, you might come to the conclusion that I&rsquo;m processing email
inside of Emacs
<a href="/2014/05/24/weekly-head-voices-71-vote-for-the-future/">again</a>.</p>
<p>I can confirm that this is indeed the case.</p>
<p>Probably for a large part due to the popularity of google&rsquo;s gmail, the growth
of the rest of the email ecosystem seems to have been stunted to a significant
degree.</p>
<p>In this specific case, I am referring to the dearth of really good email
clients for Windows.</p>
<p>(By the way, Thunderbird, still my fallback, usually makes the top of any
Windows email client lists. However, if it weren&rsquo;t for GMail, Thunderbird
would probably also be miles better than it is today.)</p>
<p>After losing more hours than I could afford trying to find that perfect email
client (I would have settled for &ldquo;still has all of its own teeth&rdquo;), I realised
that I would just have to buckle down and get <a href="/tags/mu4e/">mu4e</a>, my favourite
Emacs email client, working well enough on Windows, which I currently <em>prefer</em>
(DID I JUST SAY THAT?!) due to my <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1E
baby</a>.</p>
<p>That was of course a whole different wormhole to get sucked into.</p>
<p>Well, more of those precious hours later, I have a Frankensteined concoction
consisting of Emacs running on the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL),
displaying to the Windows desktop via <a href="https://token2shell.com/x410/">X410</a>,
and opening email and orgmode attachments, and dired files, using the native
Windows handlers via an
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Xdg-utils#xdg-open">xdg-open</a> work-alike
I coded up in Python.</p>
<p>(I am planning to release my xdg-open clone along with a more detailed howto
blog post. Let me know if you would like advanced access.)</p>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. after all of that effort I am now back more or less to where I
started in 2014.</p>
<p>(To be honest, Emacs is near the top of my list of compounding activities. The
fact that it&rsquo;s back in my email workflow, combined with five years of
compounded Emacs skills, has resulted in further increased efficiency.)</p>
<h3 id="sticking-it-to-the-man-gmail-with-fastmail">Sticking it to the Man (GMail) with FastMail.</h3>
<p>Wrapping up that email workflow reconfiguration frenzy, I did spend some
minutes doing a quick survey of fastmail alternatives which might have email
servers somewhat closer to the Southern tip of Africa and hence shave off a few
seconds of latency.</p>
<p>I found nothing that came close in terms of features and price. Except for one
outage, <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">I&rsquo;ve been a really happy fastmail camper for the last three
years</a>.</p>
<p>All of that, together with the fact that gmail&rsquo;s continued dominance is
unhealthy for the world of email, convinced me to stick with fastmail for the
conceivable future.</p>
<h2 id="stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">Stone Three Healthcare is now a thing.</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.stonethree.com/healthcare/">Stone Three Healthcare</a>, until recently
a business unit within Stone Three Venture Technology, has now been officially
spun out.</p>
<p>In other words, S3HC is now a more-or-less independent company that will
henceforth have to create its own success.</p>
<p>As some of you know, this project has been cooking for a few years now.</p>
<p>We have a really great team, products with customers and a market, and a
respectable patch of runway.</p>
<p>There are worse ways for a startup to start up.</p>
<p>P.S. if you have any golden tips for startup dummies, I (and probably others)
would be super grateful if you could let &rsquo;em loose in the comments!</p>
<h2 id="always-be-compounding-the-side-project-edition">Always Be Compounding: The side-project edition.</h2>
<p>In the previous WHV, I <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">started going on about the principle of ABC, or Always Be
Compounding</a>.</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been spending a great deal of mental cycles on finding more
ways to ABC.</p>
<p>Besides the more general examples I mentioned there, another method is to
design some long-running project that can function as a container for all of
the work that you&rsquo;ll have to do in any case.</p>
<p>A perhaps slightly flawed personal example is DeVIDE, an open source
visualization and image processing tool that started life somewhere in 2001,
<a href="/2003/12/19/the-visualisation-and-image-processing-platform-formerly-known-as-dscas3/">was renamed to DeVIDE at the end of
2003</a>,
open-sourced in 2007 and had its last release in 2012.</p>
<p>Although it did see some use after that, the project went into hibernation
(weeeelll&hellip;.) when I left academia.</p>
<p>My point is that, for about 10 years, I had a single technical <em>artifact</em> with
a name that became slowly better known (even if it was often by its alias &ldquo;Not
Responding&rdquo;), into which I could integrate all the other new work I was doing.</p>
<p>This enabled me to enjoy some of the advantages of compounding effort, in the
shape of DeVIDE, even although the work I was doing over the years necessarily
had to change.</p>
<p>(A really nice additional benefit was that some students sometimes found the
software useful! I do wish that that part could have continued for a little
longer.)</p>
<p>Setting aside my
<a href="/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/#a-strange-thing-happened-this-weekend">DeVIDE-nostalgia</a>
(and a bit of sadness) for a moment, I would like to apply some of this
learning to my current (and perhaps your) situation.</p>
<p>My idea would be to define a new side-project that can act as the slightly
longer-lived container for some of the smaller side-projects and learnings I
sometimes manage to spend time on.</p>
<p>It would have to be a technology / thematic fit for many of my other
side-projects. It would of course constitute a double-whammy if this
side-project had commercial potential.</p>
<p>Well, SURPRISE!</p>
<p>I do have at least one side-project that ticks a number of these boxes, and
could <em>potentially</em> serve as such a vehicle.</p>
<h3 id="aikno">AIKNO</h3>
<p>The side-project in question is called AIKNO, which is pronounced &ldquo;I know&rdquo;, but
which somehow expands to <em>AI organizational knowledge base</em>. Magic!</p>
<p>It eats all of your organization&rsquo;s emails for breakfast, and then uses
different methods, both algorithmic and crowd/team-sourced, to sort and
organize those emails and all of their attachments, and then makes those easily
and attractively (hey, data visualization!) accessible by that organization.</p>
<p>Think of it as an almost zero-effort always-up-to-date organizational knowledge
base.</p>
<p>Besides having slots for various machine learning and visualization techniques,
it fits nicely into my overgrown knowledge management hobby.</p>
<p>The first commit in the AIKNO repo was in November of 2017. Oof. The prototype
is able to import emails and attachments into its structured database, and
already does funky stuff with similarity searches and whatnot.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, it has also suffered from my regular technology stack
changes, and it&rsquo;s currently languishing while I write blog posts.</p>
<p>My previous failed side-project was called <em>TableTops</em>, or <em>Paradigm Desktop</em> by
the same people who dubbed DeVIDE &ldquo;Not Responding&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It was a free-form canvas / whiteboard tool for the free-form storage and
linking of <em>anything</em>. For example, it had relational data structures for
linking specific coordinates or regions in photos to centralised concepts, and
other interesting things that will probably never see the light of day.</p>
<p>It went through seven tech-stack-change-induced rewrites before being obsoleted
by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">my growing Emacs Orgmode powers</a>. (first
commit October 2013, last commit August 2017, now on the backest back
burner. the one that&rsquo;s not burning.)</p>
<p>I did learn a <em>tremendous</em> amount.</p>
<p>Maybe <em>that</em> is the real reason for doing these things?</p>
<h2 id="always-be-learning">Always Be Learning.</h2>
<p>Thanks for joining me on that trip folks.</p>
<p>I hope to see you soon. Until then, make an amazing time!</p>
<figure>
<a href="coffee_company_belgian_brownie.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu_629d5970772d1350.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu_ae2fca1166c8723b.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu_718d28a1a141e54f.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu_b4ce8d12a992e4c.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu_ae2fca1166c8723b.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
100% amazing Belgian brownie and delectable flat white at the
Coffee Company on Lourensford this past weekend.
</figcaption>
</figure>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #170: Yeet.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2019 22:02:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/</guid><description>Hello there friends!
This edition of the WHV, number 170, is how I choose look back at the three weeks from Monday April 15 to Sunday May 5, 2019.
This period was host to whooshing-by-deadline-induced stress, one amazing and thought-provoking wedding, the birthdays of two of my GOUs, and, a bit strangely part of this list, the acquisition of a new computing device.
At least we were able to pause everything for a sublime afternoon at a favourite vineyard close to my backyard:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello there friends!</p>
<p>This edition of the WHV, number 170, is how I choose look back at the three
weeks from Monday April 15 to Sunday May 5, 2019.</p>
<p>This period was host to whooshing-by-deadline-induced stress, one amazing and
thought-provoking wedding, the birthdays of two of my GOUs, and, a bit
strangely part of this list, the acquisition of a new computing device.</p>
<p>At least we were able to pause everything for a sublime afternoon at a
favourite vineyard close to my backyard:</p>
<figure>
<a href="lourensford_cellar_skies.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_20b2c5ad8d092c5e.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_d6f7ceb2c7fd7b01.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_6e561138cc326ce3.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_6e7ba6ca8a4e13aa.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_hu_d6f7ceb2c7fd7b01.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
I ended the three week WHV-hiatus in this place, together with my
fam jam<sup>*</sup>. It was lit.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h1 id="a-brief-but-educational-interlude-how-to-speak-gen-z">A brief but educational interlude: HOW TO SPEAK GEN Z.</h1>
<p>I too did not know what &ldquo;fam jam&rdquo; meant until I viewed the educational video
below.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YtrxVWf91Jo" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>I feel like I understand my budding teenager (GOU#1) a little better now.</p>
<p>On a related note: GOU#1 and I went to watch End Game together, on her 13th
birthday.</p>
<p>This is the first time I&rsquo;ve been in a cinema since forever, as I usually find
it hard to justify the time expense.</p>
<p>In this case however, the film, but far more importantly my company and the
special occasion, made it doubly worth it.</p>
<p>P.S. Dumbledore doesn&rsquo;t make it. 😢</p>
<p>P.P.S. That emoji comes straight from my Emacs! (It comes as a bit of a
surprise to me that I am quite excited by how our systems of written
communication are evolving.)</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. If you too want your Emacs to do this, add the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; 💪💪💪</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">use-package</span> <span style="color:#953800">emojify</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#6639ba">:ensure</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">t</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#6639ba">:config</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">emojify-set-emoji-styles</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">&#39;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">unicode</span><span style="color:#1f2328">))</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">global-emojify-mode</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">global-set-key</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">kbd</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;C-x 8 e&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;emojify-insert-emoji</span><span style="color:#1f2328">))</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><h1 id="the-other-blog-posts-i-did-get-around-to-writing">The other blog posts I did get around to writing.</h1>
<p>Perhaps unbeknownst to you, I was not completely quiet on the blogging front.</p>
<p>I produced the following four posts, the latter three of which will have to
live on the nerdy sister blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">meepx1e: I haz new laptop!</a> - The traditional
welcome-new-computer-to-my-household post on this blog.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/16/dotnet-fsi-in-vscode/">Using the new dotnet fsi from .NET Core 3 Preview 3 in Visual Studio
Code</a> - A modest trick
for an improved F# repl.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/19/django-typescript-docker-compose-windows/">PyCharm and Docker Compose for Django and TypeScript development on Windows
10</a> -
You can run your Linux inside of Microsoft-supported Docker containers on
your Windows laptop. How times have changed&hellip;</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/20/link-thunderbird-emails-from-emacs-orgmode/">Link directly to emails from Emacs Orgmode using Thunderbird and
Thunderlink</a> -
This is a core part of my task management workflows. On macOS it worked more
or less out of the box, on Windows and Linux you have to get your hands
dirty.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="the-easiest-but-most-high-impact-measure-you-can-take-to-not-die-too-soon-go-to-bed-on-time">The easiest but most high impact measure you can take to not die too soon: Go to bed on time.</h1>
<p><a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">I&rsquo;ve mentioned Matthew Walker, the increasingly world-renowned Professor of
Sleep Science, on this blog
before</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently working through a three-part podcast between <a href="https://peterattiamd.com">Dr Peter Attia
MD</a>, life optimisation expert with the
hyper-analytical accent(tm), and Prof. Walker, and it is absolutely
<em>fascinating</em>.</p>
<p>Several times now, points discussed by the two gentleman have made me go
&ldquo;OH. MY. GOODNESS.&rdquo; in the car between home, the daily school-run and work.</p>
<p>The long and the short of it is that although we so easily trade away sleep for
an extra hour of work, or even worse to assuage pangs of guilt at not working
enough during the day, that sleep is one of the most crucial components of
one&rsquo;s health.</p>
<p>Looking at it from a different angle, and one which Walker is not scared to
take, probably because it is so critical, lack of sleep has terrifyingly
deleterious effects on human health.</p>
<p>Anyways, if you&rsquo;re looking for a thought-provoking conversation, you could
easily do worse than this.</p>
<ul>
<li>Part 1: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker1/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker1/</a></li>
<li>Part 2: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker2/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker2/</a></li>
<li>Part 3: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker3/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker3/</a></li>
</ul>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have the opportunity to listen to the podcast, perhaps because you
need to catch up on your sleep, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/sep/24/why-lack-of-sleep-health-worst-enemy-matthew-walker-why-we-sleep">this 2017 article in The
Guardian</a>
is a great summary.</p>
<h1 id="the-edge-of-humanity">The Edge of Humanity.</h1>
<p>(Not interested in hearing about sleep? How about existential risks that
threaten the continued existence of our species? Here at the WHV we like to
keep the issues light and light-hearted!)</p>
<p><em>Homo Deus</em> by Yuval Harari is one of those books I really think <em>everyone</em>
should read. This is such a fantastic and broad treatise on where we came from,
and where we might be going.</p>
<p>I am happy that we have the privilege of Harari as the superbly articulate
thinker that he is.</p>
<p>This discussion between Yuval Harari and Sam Harris, available as <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/138-edge-humanity/">podcast #138
on Sam Harris&rsquo;s website</a>, is
both valuable and highly entertaining.</p>
<p>Besides the moment at about 32 minutes in when Harari made the case that all of
the large scale media manipulation and user data mining demonstrate that the
human mind is now indeed hackable (!!), I wanted to mention the
thought-provoking topic of how comically out of their depth our political
leaders are.</p>
<p>They don&rsquo;t seem to be able to do much more than <em>react</em> to short-term fears and
impulses (which they also play to), and as if that was not bad enough, they do
so with an horizon of not much more than about four years.</p>
<p>How many of our leaders would be able to field convincingly the question of
what their plans were, what their <em>vision</em> is for humanity, for the coming 40
years?</p>
<p>What <em>is</em> our 40 year grand plan for energy, for the environment, for poverty,
and for preventing another world war?</p>
<p>Please give your answers in the comments.</p>
<h1 id="a-strange-thing-happened-this-weekend">A strange thing happened this weekend.</h1>
<p>During my time at the TU Delft, I made and maintained a software tool called
DeVIDE, or the <em>Delft Visualisation and Image Processing Development
Environment</em>, or <em>Not Responding</em> as it was called by <em>some</em> of its users.</p>
<p>Development started in 2002, the first open source release was in 2007 and the
last release was in 2012.</p>
<p>(You can still download working binaries of the 2012 release from the
<a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/devide/wiki/Downloads">downloads page</a>. It was
pretty strong on loading chaotic collections of DICOM images, and it was pretty
strong on enabling users to talk to almost any part of it in Python, at
runtime. Frits Post and I published a <a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Hybrid-Scheduling-in-the-DeVIDE-Dataflow-Botha-Post/a96cc2530609d46d9a39f5884d8a9f8192991114">paper in 2008 which nicely summarised
the interesting parts of the
software</a>.)</p>
<p>When <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">I left the TU and
academia</a>, my work
positively careened off in a different direction and it became more or less
impossible for me to justify continuing to maintain DeVIDE.</p>
<p>Fast forward a few years, and due to Project Z I&rsquo;m again all up in the
<a href="https://www.dicomlibrary.com/dicom/">DICOMs</a>.</p>
<p>More acutely however, I feel the need for creatively implemented projective
geometry.</p>
<p>Well, my weekend brain got behind the steering wheel, and before I knew it I
was staring at the DeVIDE UI, all prettied up with Python 3 and VTK 8.2:</p>
<figure>
<a href="devide2019-screenshot-20190505.png">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hu_e2661da33963fa84.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hu_9a4ca26d37fe4833.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hu_2d6809a082ccbefd.png 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hu_9a4ca26d37fe4833.png"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>At this moment it&rsquo;s only a limping shadow of its previous self, but it still
managed to bring back so many warm memories.</p>
<p>With a few hours more of work, it could start becoming useful again.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not entirely sure where weekend-brain wanted to go with this. We&rsquo;ll have to
wait until he gets back to see.</p>
<h1 id="heading">🙏🙏🙏</h1>
<p>Friends, thank you for connecting with me here in these words and symbols.</p>
<p>I am already looking forward to the next time that we meet!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>What is love? [Weekly Head Voices #64 no #65]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/02/14/what-is-love-weekly-head-voices-64/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2012 22:05:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/02/14/what-is-love-weekly-head-voices-64/</guid><description> I’ve been dealing with a spot of blog writer’s block, hence the lateness of this post. I’d forgotten that these monthly instalments were initially intended to be extended status updates, with a spot of backyard philosophy every so often. Trying to come up with worthwhile backyard philosophy every week is just plain hard. This week I’m going for half a status update along with a list of possibly interesting sciencey tidbits.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/dont_herd_me.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2012/02/dont_herd_me-1024x681.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I’ve been dealing with a spot of blog writer’s block, hence the lateness of this post. I’d forgotten that these monthly instalments were initially intended to be extended status updates, with a spot of backyard philosophy every so often. Trying to come up with worthwhile backyard philosophy every week is just plain hard. This week I’m going for half a status update along with a list of possibly interesting sciencey tidbits.</p>
<ul>
<li>I’ve managed to <a href="http://devidenews.wordpress.com/2012/02/11/devide-12-2-7-sees-the-light-of-day/" title="devide 12.2.7 release post">release a stable version of DeVIDE</a>, my Frankenstein-Borg software system for visualization and image processing, only about 2.5 years after the previous stable release. Go get yours <a href="http://code.google.com/p/devide/wiki/Downloads?tm=2" title="devide downloads">fresh from the oven</a>, it’s completely open source!</li>
<li>It <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/" title="right after first MedVis course">seems like yesterday</a> when I got to design and teach the first MedVis Ninja course at the TU Delft. The fourth generation of students have just started with the course (partly the reason for pushing out a new DeVIDE release). The previous generations are kicking ass as we speak, and I’m proud of ’em all.</li>
<li>I had the privilege of giving another invited talk, in Dutch, at the yearly conference of the Dutch Anatomical Society. In my talk, titled <em>Data Visualization: Driving the human visual system for fun and profit</em>, I introduced data and medical visualization, and then discussed three illustrative examples in more depth: high quality volume rendering (work by Thomas Kroes), diffusion tensor imaging (work by Jorik Blaas) and fMRI connectivity visualization (work by André van Dixhoorn).</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it for the status update. The sciencey bits I thought were worth mentioning are:</p>
<ul>
<li>There’s been some press lately about the letter to the Wall Street Journal, signed by 16 scientists, in which they try to make the case that climate change is really not such an issue. Climate change denialists everywhere rejoiced, I cringed. I really don’t like denialism. Fortunately, it turns out that I’m not the only one, and that there’s a story behind the story: The WSJ editorial board is severely biased against climate science.  Another letter, signed by 255 real scientists (all members of the US National Academy of Science), dealing with the realities of climate change, was flat-out rejected by the WSJ. It’s a shame that the first factually dubious letter got so much of the press. Read more about the whole debacle in <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/petergleick/2012/01/27/remarkable-editorial-bias-on-climate-science-at-the-wall-street-journal/" title="forbes article concerning WSJ climate bias">this Forbes article</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://pss.sagepub.com/content/23/2/187" title="Lower Cognitive Ability Predicts Greater Prejudice ">A recent Psychological Science article</a> contains the results of a study  on more than 15000 UK inhabitants, as well as on a group in the US, that shows that lower cognitive ability predicts greater prejudice, manifesting in for example right-wing ideologies or homophobia. Ha ha.</li>
<li>In another not-so-surprising turn of events, it turns out that alcohol does indeed make you more creative.  <a href="http://francoismalan.com/">FrancoisMalan.com</a> sent me, albeit indirectly, this <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1053810012000037" title="Uncorking the muse: Alcohol intoxication facilitates creative problem solving">Consciousness and Cognition article</a>, titled <em>Uncorking the muse: Alcohol intoxication facilitates creative problem solving</em>. Note the creative title, draw your own conclusions about the state of intoxication required for authoring a successful scientific article. Ahem.</li>
</ul>
<p>Good science should be reproducible. Judging by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blood_alcohol_content">the blood alcohol content and weight tables</a> on Wikipedia, I should be more creative between 3 and 4 beers, a result I will certainly try to confirm during my next WHV writing session. It is left as an exercise to the reader to calculate my body weight based on this information.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #17: The Eternal Foreigner.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/14/weekly-head-voices-17-the-eternal-foreigner/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2010 22:18:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/14/weekly-head-voices-17-the-eternal-foreigner/</guid><description>In this edition, looking back on the 10th week of 2010, I report briefly on the lack of blog-worthy events in my life, noting that my life is undoubtedly extremely exciting, just not always in that special blog-worthy way, before concluding with some backyard psycho-philosophy on my perception of the greenness of grass as a function of its distance from the observer. Skip to just after the YouTube clip if you want to get right to the backyard part of this blog.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this edition, looking back on the 10th week of 2010, I report briefly on the lack of blog-worthy events in my life, noting that my life is undoubtedly extremely exciting, just not always in that special blog-worthy way, before concluding with some backyard psycho-philosophy on my perception of the greenness of grass as a function of its distance from the observer.  Skip to just after the YouTube clip if you want to get right to the backyard part of this blog.</p>
<p>Work-wise, last week was good for 2 hours of lecture preparation, 3 hours of lecturing, 12 hours of meetings, including an inspiring visit to Real Scientists at the EMC, and finally some quality time catching a monday night paper deadline in the nick of time with one of our MedVis Ninjas, whom I’m coincidentally extremely proud of at the moment.  I completed only 16 GTD tasks, down 6 from last week.</p>
<p>Besides not having hot water for two days due to my boiler’s operating system (yes, it has a frikking operating system) refusing to switch on the heat exchanger, forcing me to take a bath in 15 litres of hot water boiled, cowboy style, on the stove, and also experiencing first-hand the surprisingly high actual efficiency of my house’s Super Environmentally Friendly heat-retention system (everything is insulated, air is mechanically circulated at about 100 cubic metres per hour, extra heat exchanger transfers warmth from expelled air to fresh injected air) which managed to keep the internal temperature at a comfortable 18 C (outside between 1 and 8 C) without any hot water in the radiators, and also managing to write one of the longest sentences in a blog post since last Tuesday, the only other blog-worthy artifact I have to offer you is this YouTube screencast I made the other day, demonstrating how to perform a rudimentary segmentation on DICOM CT data and extract STL surface meshes using DeVIDE:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_PtTpRz3aU8?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>You can add this to your growing list of natural non-ingestible sleep medicine.</p>
<p>Last week I heard that I’d passed my <a href="http://www.inburgeren.nl/inburgeraar/korte_vrijstellingstoets/korte_vrijstellingstoets.asp" title="link to KVT info">Korte Vrijstellingstoets</a>. This is a test that you, foreigner in The Netherlands, can take to demonstrate that you have sufficient knowledge of Dutch language and culture and thus don’t have to take bunches of other compulsory courses and/or exams that are far more time-consuming. This is not such a significant happening, were it not for the fact that it’s another very concrete symbol of my growing affinity with and attachment to this little patch of the planet. I can hardly avoid thinking seriously about the future of this relationship.</p>
<p>Further, this weekend I missed the wedding of one my best friends due to the niggling matter of 10000 kilometres conspiring with sundry but unavoidable work-related constraints. I would <em>really</em> have loved to be there… There will always be drawbacks, no matter where you choose to live. Especially if you choose for the excitement of a country-skipping adventure and do so for any significant length of time, you will always long for That Other Place, that special coordinate that you currently can’t occupy, and the people associated with it.  Even if you go back to where you started, irrevocably tainted with a strange culture, you don’t quite fit in and long for your acquired home. The grass is and will remain greener on the other side.</p>
<p>I had the good fortune of meeting a wise and well-spoken French man shortly after starting my European adventure. This man, who had done quite some country skipping, finally ending up in Lugano (one can end up in worse places than Lugano), introduced me to the concept of the Eternal Foreigner. This is what one becomes when one simply <em>embraces</em> the idea that, once having moved country and culture, one can never ever be at Home again. Instead of struggling to blend in, struggling to be more like one’s neighbour, or struggling to retain and manifest some warped version of one’s own culture in an environment where it’s doomed to wilt, simply accept Being From Elsewhere.</p>
<p>The Eternal Foreigner misses Home, but smiles, and is at peace.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #14: My Week Was A Wormhole.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/21/weekly-head-voices-14-my-week-was-a-wormhole/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2010 18:25:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/21/weekly-head-voices-14-my-week-was-a-wormhole/</guid><description>In this week’s post, documenting the 7th week of 2010, I wonder about perceived business, mention two of our most recent open source releases and give to you, my readers, two screencasts about the DRE, in addition probably highly effective in the treatment of insomnia. Screenshot of the FoBVis system. This is just one of our many attempts to take over the world, subtly.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this week’s post, documenting the 7th week of 2010, I wonder about perceived business, mention two of our most recent open source releases and give to you, my readers, two screencasts about the DRE, in addition probably highly effective in the treatment of insomnia.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/fobvis1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/fobvis1.jpg"
        
            alt="Screenshot of the FoBVis system. This is just one of our many attempts to take over the world, subtly."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Screenshot of the FoBVis system. This is just one of our many attempts to take over the world, subtly.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Just before bedtime on Monday, I had still managed to make a note in my special top-secret Weekly Head Voices journal.  I usually do this every day to make sure I don’t forget anything by the weekend, when I usually have some time to write these posts.  Thursday night’s entry simply says “WTF, where did my week go?!” — There had been no other entries since Monday. I’m still not quite sure why it felt that way, as my breakdown of activities is similar to that of the previous week: 2 hours of lecture preparation, 3 hours of lecturing, 15 hours of scheduled meetings and 20 tasks completed (one more than last week!!) across 10 projects. Perhaps those four extra hours of meetings don’t scale linearly in the amount of business they cause, due to the number of extra context switches that they bring. I have to add that a number of truly exciting projects are brewing, but I can’t say more about them until I can say more about them, if you know what I mean.</p>
<p>We (The Group, of course) recently released two new open source software projects:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://fobvis.googlecode.com/" title="FoBVis project site">FoBVis</a> is a tool for the real-time acquisition and visualisation of human motion: Currently it supports the Flock-of-Birds electromagnetic acquisition system, we are currently working to integrate Optotrak optical tracking system. We should also shortly have a version of the <a href="http://code.google.com/p/devide/wiki/HelpDRE" title="You can use the DRE to run stuff, including the FoBVis.">DRE</a> that can run the FoBVis on YOUR computer as well.</li>
<li><a href="http://histovis.googlecode.com/" title="HistoVis project site">HistoVis</a> is a client-server system for the visualisation of large collections of (registered) histological sections.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s all very exciting that more products of our research are entering the big bad outside world!  The FoBVis is already being actively used by the LUMC Laboratory for Motion Analysis (we hope that more labs will start using this soon), and HistoVis will soon go live from the <a href="http://visible-orbit.nl/" title="Visible Orbit website">visible-orbit.nl server</a>. Of course these have both been released under the new BSD license, as the GPL sucks.</p>
<p>Screencasts: Video Performance Art of the Nerdily Inclined. That’s where one makes a recording of one’s computer screen whilst demonstrating some or other procedure, optionally narrated by oneself, and then proceeds to upload said recording (called a screencast) to YouTube or similar. See <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/05/10/recording-screencasts-on-windows-with-free-software/" title="Instructions on creating screencasts in Windows.">a previous post of mine</a> for one possible (and free) way of doing this on Windows. This weekend I produced and uploaded two such pieces, both demonstrating aspects of the DeVIDE Runtime Environment, or <a href="http://code.google.com/p/devide/wiki/HelpDRE" title="DRE help page">DRE</a>, that paradoxically do NOT involve DeVIDE itself. Especially the second is really soothing, one could even say mildly sleep-inducing.  I just say: <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xEbYw73y3pM" title="First sleep-inducing DRE screencast.">(1) Try</a> <a data-rel="lightbox-video-1" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7FwPw9qlsms" title="Second sleep-inducing DRE screencast.">(2) it</a>.</p>
<p>To conclude, I give you a track from the new Massive Attack album Heligoland, called Paradise Circus. It should make your brain sit and scratch its chin stubble, not unlike the usual dose of backyard philosophy:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jEgX64n3T7g?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Recording screencasts on Windows with free software</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2008/05/10/recording-screencasts-on-windows-with-free-software/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2008 20:23:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2008/05/10/recording-screencasts-on-windows-with-free-software/</guid><description>(This post was first written in May of 2008, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been updating it periodically. See also the updates right at the end.)
What are screencasts? Screencasts refer to video recordings of screen activity, often with narration. These can be used to demonstrate software or to serve as a kind of visual HOWTO. We often make screencasts of software we design in the Medical Visualisation group at the TU Delft to use in presentations at conferences or to distribute online.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This post was first written in May of 2008, but I&rsquo;ve been updating it
periodically. See also the updates right at the end.)</em></p>
<h2 id="what-are-screencasts">What are screencasts?</h2>
<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Screencast" title="Screencast entry on Wikipedia">Screencasts</a> refer to video recordings of screen activity, often with
narration. These can be used to demonstrate software or to serve as a kind of
visual HOWTO. We often make screencasts of software we design in the <a href="http://visualisation.tudelft.nl/MedVis" title="MedVis at the TU Delft">Medical
Visualisation group</a> at the TU Delft to use in presentations at conferences
or to distribute online.</p>
<h2 id="windows-software-for-making-screen-recodings">Windows software for making screen recodings</h2>
<p>On Windows, Camtasia Studio ($300) or Camtasia SnagIt ($40) are probably the
best options your money can buy. Most of the free alternatives suck quite
badly: This includes the Windows Media Encoder, thank you very much. In fact,
the Windows Media 9 Screen Capture Codec has been fine-tuned to create the
worst possible quality movies you can imagine. Another problem with the free
options is that they often can&rsquo;t sustain writing the video stream to disk,
hence resulting in dropped frames and unusable screencasts. When they are able
to sustain writing, it probably means that the compression is completely
killing video quality.</p>
<h3 id="camstudio-free-and-open-source-just-be-careful-from-where-you-download">CamStudio: Free and open source, just be careful from where you download</h3>
<p>Fortunately, it turns out that there is a free option which offers comparable
performance to the Camtasia products, and for good reason. It&rsquo;s called
<a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/camstudio/files/stable/" title="Link to CamStudio sourceforge">CamStudio</a>, and it&rsquo;s even open source! It&rsquo;s terribly important that you
also install the <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/camstudio/files/legacy/CamStudioCodec_1.5_Setup.exe/download" title="CamStudio screen capture codec link">lossless CamStudio Screen Capture codec</a>, it&rsquo;s this that
makes all the difference.</p>
<p>This codec compresses all frames with the fast LZO lossless compression
algorithm, so you get the highest possible quality without dropping frames due
relatively slow disc writing.</p>
<p>It is important that you stick to the sourceforge links I&rsquo;ve posted above. It is
quite unfortunate that some of the CamStudio installers have a sordid history
with adware and malware, but these SourceForge versions seem to be fine.</p>
<p>Using CamStudio, I made a 3.5 minute screencast, with live audio recording,
show-casing some of the new DICOM browsing functionality in the next DeVIDE
release. After capture, I transcoded the CamStudio screen capture codec AVI to
XVID using <a href="http://www.mediacoderhq.com/" title="MediaCoder website">MediaCoder</a>, and then uploaded to YouTube (play at your own
risk!):</p>
<iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/iLfu6JXkWP4" width="560"></iframe>
<h2 id="update-on-2010-02-21">Update on 2010-02-21</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve made <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xEbYw73y3pM" title="Link to DRE screencast #1">two</a> <a data-rel="lightbox-video-1" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7FwPw9qlsms" title="Link to DRE screencast #2">more</a> screencasts and learnt some time-expensive
lessons:</p>
<ul>
<li>DON&rsquo;T encode with H.264, in spite of YouTube&rsquo;s recommendation. This screws up
captured text elements extremely badly. I had much more success with XVID at
1500 kbit/s and MP3 audio using MediaCoder, and <strong>THE MOST SUCCESS OF ALL
just directly uploading the lossless codec screencast to YouTube, without any
transcoding</strong>.</li>
<li>DO capture at 640x480 or at 1280x720 (HD).  For example 800x600 is NOT worth
it, it gets downscaled by YouTube. By capturing at 640x480 or 1280x720 you
have much more control over what finally appears on YouTube.</li>
<li>If you get audio / video sync problems (I experienced them with a 10 minute
screencast), try activating &ldquo;Use MCI Recording&rdquo; in the CamStudio &ldquo;Audio
Option for Microphone&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="update-on-2011-10-22">Update on 2011-10-22</h2>
<p>With CamStudio 2.6 r294 getting the codec working on Windows 7 64bit is not straight-forward. You first install the codec in the normal way (with the exe installer), then you have to do TWO things. First copy camcodec.dll from Windows\System32 to Windows\SysWOW64. Second, create a reg file with the following contents:</p>
<pre class="brush: plain; title: ; notranslate" title="">
Windows Registry Editor Version 5.00
[HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Wow6432Node\Microsoft\Windows NT\CurrentVersion\drivers.desc]
"camcodec.dll"="CamStudio lossless codec [CSCD]"
[HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Wow6432Node\Microsoft\Windows NT\CurrentVersion\Drivers32]
"VIDC.CSCD"="camcodec.dll"
</pre>
<p>Install it by double-clicking the reg file, or doing right-click and then selecting Merge. After this, you should be able to select the camstudio codec from Options | Video Options | Compressor.</p>
<p>Furthermore, you can upload camstudio-encoded movies directly to Google Picasa, it Just Works(tm)!</p>
<h2 id="update-on-2013-02-13">Update on 2013-02-13</h2>
<p>If CamStudio 2.7 complains about MSVCR100.dll being missing, you should install
the <a href="http://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=5555" title="MS Visual C++ redistributable 32bit">MS Visual
C++ redistributable</a> (32bit, because CamStudio is 32bit).</p>
<h2 id="update-on-2020-06-25">Update on 2020-06-25</h2>
<p>It is the year 2020.</p>
<p>We have flying cars and sentient androids &hellip; and camstudio is still working
fine on the latest Windows 10 2004 release.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve just installed <code>CamStudio_Setup_2-7_r316</code> and <code>CamStudioCodec_1.5_Setup</code>
from the sourceforge links in the third paragraph of this post, and everything
still works like a charm: Lossless recording using the camstudio codec, and
then transcoding to mp4 using <a href="https://handbrake.fr/">HandBrake</a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Visualisation and Image Processing Platform Formerly Known as DSCAS3</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2003/12/19/the-visualisation-and-image-processing-platform-formerly-known-as-dscas3/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Dec 2003 17:53:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2003/12/19/the-visualisation-and-image-processing-platform-formerly-known-as-dscas3/</guid><description>The current marketing conditions and long-term strategy dictate a name change. The new name should contain at least the words “Delft”, “Visualisation”, “Image [Processing]”, and then one of “platform”, “framework”, “[software environment]”.
I’m currently looking at “devise” (Delft Visualisation and Image processing Software Environment), “devious” (“ou” not used, the rest you can easily guess) and perhaps “divine” (or “devine”, which I like more, because of the infamous Devine Brown and the fact that I would be able to use acronyms like “PIMP” for Parallel IMage Processing”) which would stand for Delft Visualisation and Image processing Network Environment, which is not an entirely correct description (the network environment is just one aspect) but acceptable nonetheless.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The current marketing conditions and long-term strategy dictate a name
change. The new name should contain at least the words “Delft”,
“Visualisation”, “Image [Processing]”, and then one of
“platform”, “framework”, “[software
environment]”.</p>
<p>I’m currently looking at “devise” (Delft Visualisation and
Image processing Software Environment), “devious”
(“ou” not used, the rest you can easily guess) and perhaps
“divine” (or “devine”, which I like more, because of
the infamous Devine Brown and the fact that I would be able to use acronyms
like “PIMP” for Parallel IMage Processing”) which would
stand for Delft Visualisation and Image processing Network Environment, which
is not an entirely correct description (the network environment is just one
aspect) but acceptable nonetheless.</p>
<p>So, what do you think? Do you have any other suggestions?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>