<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Lifelog on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/categories/lifelog/</link><description>Recent content in Lifelog on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:52:34 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/categories/lifelog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 9 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/10/daily-head-voices-2024-week-9/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/10/daily-head-voices-2024-week-9/</guid><description>Monday 2024-02-26 started the morning (and the work week!) with stupid indecision: Had all my work gear in the car, but chose to drive back home after dropping of GOU#3 for a logistical task which one of my other clan members would gladly have taken care of. Indecision irrelevant against the backdrop: We had such a good time in the car first being on time (GOU#3 loves that), then listening to Skrillex together, then talking, and then performing our morning ritual of verbally attesting our super-infinite love for each other as I drop her off at school. During highly technical demo outside of my domains, used perplexity in real-time to lookup various details as the demo was going on, and thus could focus on the really interesting questions for the presenter. Between meetings, struggled a bit to focus in the focusy bits, but managed to do quite a bit of work eventually (with focusapp and some deep house) and even got milestones done. Tuesday 2024-02-27 Super frustrated during the morning rush, because could not find running shoes at the critical moment when we had to leave for school Reverted to backup shoes (old ones, with too many kilometres on them) Good run in L&amp;amp;Z, but it took so long to disconnect from my shoe moment, in spite of really putting my mind to it. Succeeded a little bit at the end, shocked at the mental cost of something this trivial. BTW, it was almost a textbook &amp;ldquo;not inside it&amp;rsquo;s on top!&amp;rdquo; situation. Wednesday 2024-02-28 For once some Waking Up in the morning! (I once had a streak of more than a year. Currently happy if I do just one!) Started the day in pensive mood (before and after the meditation) thinking about what I would like from the future Naturally I wanted to write a note, so then I tapped out a topic in the daily list so that I could use org-roam-node-find-similar to surface similar notes from the past. I did find the correct historic note which I would not have otherwise, but then I got sucked into emacs config&amp;hellip; why has my org-roam-node-find-* never done live preview like other consult commands? &amp;ndash; solved by installing https://github.com/jgru/consult-org-roam/tree/main and then tooting about it: https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/112008312753264000 During the day I was surprised at the amount of traction that toot got. It seems there are more people who missed this. It seems it can sometimes really help to share the minutiae. realised that org-roam-node-find-similar did not sort the similar nodes by similarity, so fixed that: https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity/commit/d940c12e70468adfbc1e41ef997c5f797540ebf7 After extricating myself back out of Emacs config yak shaving, I did spend some quality time writing up my thoughts, helping to clarify them. I don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer yet, but the direction I&amp;rsquo;m moving in feels good. Lunch with inner circle friend and mentor DMW at No Way Jose was great thank you! Thursday 2024-02-29 Run at shortly after 7. Legs did not really want to cooperate. Got distracted by meetings day at work, so almost no writing in the daily. Now, [2024-03-10 Sun 18:35], I&amp;rsquo;m really sorry. Friday 2024-03-01 Pool repair at my house. They are able to pump out all water, repair floor of pool, then pump all water back all in a few hours. I have two ideas for the weekend Build and publish a QRCode contact card generator using marimo and wasm build a telegram bot to manipulate my org-mode database, e.g. adding tasks, searching for existing tasks and notes. I don&amp;rsquo;t like this second idea, but it keeps on coming back to me. Saturday 2024-03-02 12km run with tired legs, so tired that I decided to stop the fast and get Powerade for the last 5km, which felt like it really helped. Super happy that I could get the promised marimo-wasm-qrcode generator online: https://vxlabs.com/2024/03/02/contact-qrcode-generator-with-marimo-and-wasm/ Sunday 2024-03-03 After sunday morning coffee and scrolling, dug into marimo to see if there&amp;rsquo;s some way to create the WASM locally. There does not seem to be. Scanned through https://core.telegram.org/bots to see (again&amp;hellip;) what might be possible. Actually, now I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about the idea of making a telegram bot that sends me random tasks from my org-mode every day. I already have a proof of concept in Python that uses emacsclient to expose org-roam nodes via API (see https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas ) so I would probably follow a similar path, probably with something like org-ql. Does anyone know if something like this exists somewhere? Apple&amp;rsquo;s Journal app, that suggests a new journalling possibility now and then, made me think that this could help. In iTerm2, press the Option-Cmd keys together to make a rectangular selection. Sublime lunch at Millhouse Kitchen with inner circle family Back home, tried to get MobileOrg going again; looked promising, but then after successful sync ran into this bug with empty outlines in the app when synced via iCloud. 😥 Configured perplexity via gptel in my Emacs; I am especially interested in using perplexity&amp;rsquo;s sonar-online internet-capable models.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-02-26">Monday 2024-02-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>started the morning (and the work week!) with stupid indecision: Had all my work gear in the car, but chose to drive back home after dropping of GOU#3 for a logistical task which one of my other clan members would gladly have taken care of.
<ul>
<li>Indecision irrelevant against the backdrop: We had such a good time in the car first being on time (GOU#3 loves that), then listening to Skrillex together, then talking, and then performing our morning ritual of verbally attesting our super-infinite love for each other as I drop her off at school.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>During highly technical demo outside of my domains, used perplexity in real-time to lookup various details as the demo was going on, and thus could focus on the really interesting questions for the presenter.</li>
<li>Between meetings, struggled a bit to focus in the focusy bits, but managed to do quite a bit of work eventually (with focusapp and some deep house) and even got milestones done.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-02-27">Tuesday 2024-02-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super frustrated during the morning rush, because could not find running shoes at the critical moment when we had to leave for school
<ul>
<li>Reverted to backup shoes (old ones, with too many kilometres on them)</li>
<li>Good run in L&amp;Z, but it took so  long to disconnect from my shoe moment, in spite of really putting my mind to it. Succeeded a little bit at the end, shocked at the mental cost of something this trivial.</li>
<li>BTW, it was almost a textbook &ldquo;not inside it&rsquo;s on top!&rdquo; situation.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-02-28">Wednesday 2024-02-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>For once some <a href="https://www.wakingup.com/">Waking Up</a> in the morning! (I once had a streak of more than a year. Currently happy if I do just one!)</li>
<li>Started the day in pensive mood (before and after the meditation) thinking about what I would like from the future
<ul>
<li>Naturally I wanted to write a note, so then I tapped out a topic in the daily list so that I could use <code>org-roam-node-find-similar</code> to surface similar notes from the past. I did find the correct historic note which I would not have otherwise, but then I got sucked into emacs config&hellip;
<ul>
<li>why has my <code>org-roam-node-find-*</code> never done live preview like other consult commands? &ndash; solved by installing <a href="https://github.com/jgru/consult-org-roam/tree/main">https://github.com/jgru/consult-org-roam/tree/main</a> and then tooting about it: <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/112008312753264000">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/112008312753264000</a>
<ul>
<li>During the day I was surprised at the amount of traction that toot got. It seems there are more people who missed this. It seems it can sometimes really help to share the minutiae.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>realised that <code>org-roam-node-find-similar</code> did not sort the similar nodes by similarity, so fixed that: <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity/commit/d940c12e70468adfbc1e41ef997c5f797540ebf7">https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity/commit/d940c12e70468adfbc1e41ef997c5f797540ebf7</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>After extricating myself back out of Emacs config yak shaving, I did spend some quality time writing up my thoughts, helping to clarify them.
<ul>
<li>I don&rsquo;t know the answer yet, but the direction I&rsquo;m moving in feels good.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lunch with inner circle friend and mentor DMW at No Way Jose was great thank you!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-02-29">Thursday 2024-02-29</h2>
<ul>
<li>Run at shortly after 7. Legs did not really want to cooperate.</li>
<li>Got distracted by meetings day at work, so almost no writing in the daily. Now, <span class="timestamp-wrapper"><span class="timestamp">[2024-03-10 Sun 18:35]</span></span>, I&rsquo;m really sorry.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-03-01">Friday 2024-03-01</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pool repair at my house. They are able to pump out all water, repair floor of pool, then pump all water back all in a few hours.</li>
<li>I have two ideas for the weekend
<ul>
<li>Build and publish a QRCode contact card generator using marimo and wasm</li>
<li>build a telegram bot to manipulate my org-mode database, e.g. adding tasks, searching for existing tasks and notes.
<ul>
<li>I don&rsquo;t like this second idea, but it keeps on coming back to me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-03-02">Saturday 2024-03-02</h2>
<ul>
<li>12km run with tired legs, so tired that I decided to stop the fast and get Powerade for the last 5km, which felt like it really helped.</li>
<li>Super happy that I could get the promised marimo-wasm-qrcode generator online: <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/03/02/contact-qrcode-generator-with-marimo-and-wasm/">https://vxlabs.com/2024/03/02/contact-qrcode-generator-with-marimo-and-wasm/</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-03-03">Sunday 2024-03-03</h2>
<ul>
<li>After sunday morning coffee and scrolling, dug into marimo to see if there&rsquo;s some way to create the WASM locally. There does not seem to be.</li>
<li>Scanned through <a href="https://core.telegram.org/bots">https://core.telegram.org/bots</a> to see (again&hellip;) what might be possible.</li>
<li>Actually, now I&rsquo;m thinking about the idea of making a telegram bot that sends me random tasks from my org-mode every day. I already have a proof of concept in Python that uses emacsclient to expose org-roam nodes via API (see <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas</a> ) so I would probably follow a similar path, probably with something like org-ql. Does anyone know if something like this exists somewhere?
<ul>
<li>Apple&rsquo;s Journal app, that suggests a new journalling possibility now and then, made me think that this could help.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In iTerm2, press the Option-Cmd keys together to make a rectangular selection.</li>
<li>Sublime lunch at Millhouse Kitchen with inner circle family</li>
<li>Back home, tried to get MobileOrg going again; looked promising, but then after successful sync ran into <a href="https://github.com/MobileOrg/mobileorg/issues/292">this bug with empty outlines in the app when synced via iCloud</a>. 😥</li>
<li>Configured perplexity via gptel in my Emacs; I am especially interested in using perplexity&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/hub/blog/introducing-pplx-online-llms"><code>sonar-online</code> internet-capable models</a>.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 8 of 2024: India Venster</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/02/daily-head-voices-2024-02-19_25/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2024 18:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/02/daily-head-voices-2024-02-19_25/</guid><description> Monday 2024-02-19 to Wednesday 2024-02-21 Prepared for and did business trip to Johannesburg with longest time friend FS. Highlight was tripping with FS, and trip was successful to boot. Only one night away, really missed the famjam. Dealing with stomach issues this week, relatively mild but distracting nonetheless. Thursday 2024-02-22 Short run this morning in school district. Not feeling 100%, but good enough for run and conditions perfect. Did run into G-J on Reservoir road and had quick chat, serendipity! Lunch will follow. Stomach getting better, but not yet in a good place. Friday 2024-02-23 Ran into the Kagi sidekick proposal, which made me think about frontend-only search functions for my static websites SemanticFinder: Frontend-only live semantic search with transformers.js victoria.dev: Adding lunr.js to Hugo for frontend-only search Spent some cycles today exploring ways to save a tweet so that it can be archived and searched offline If I could just traverse the DOM tree, starting from the &amp;lt;article&amp;gt; or the parent &amp;lt;section&amp;gt;, and also gathering all of the applicable styles, I would be golden Discovered three different paid-for chrome extensions that do exactly this. Small side-hustle idea right there. MarkDownload extension for saving any page as markdown came quite close Dev tools &amp;ldquo;capture node screenshot&amp;rdquo; saves to PNG. Would have been great if it could have done the same to PDF. Had a lovely lunch with great colleague from 1999/2000 at Mont Marie in Stellenbosch. Randomly reached out when I heard that he was back in this valley, super grateful for this enjoyable reconnection. Remember, call up your friends! Saturday 2024-02-24 Spent too many hours building a Tampermonkey script with which I can get tweet threads reasonably clean in order to print them First time using Tampermonkey, good tool to have on the belt! Twitter makes this a lot more tricky than it needs to be. Ideally, people would stop using twitter altogether, but for the ML crowd, I still need to go there Perfect dinner at Decameron in Stellenbosch with the family, because we had to take GOU#1 to a party in the region Karpathy proclaims his love for Obsidian, very cool! https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/1761467904737067456 Sunday 2024-02-25 Thanks to serendipitous serendipity the previous day, took part in an unexpected and epic hike up India Venster with a lifetime friend (first hike together in the 90s!) and a fantastic new friend. Experienced maximal presence. Glorious.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="img_0138.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/02/daily-head-voices-2024-02-19_25/img_0138_hu_8f9f3d427861d972.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/02/daily-head-voices-2024-02-19_25/img_0138_hu_5c39aef4dde4c6b7.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/02/daily-head-voices-2024-02-19_25/img_0138_hu_f182457ee5291df1.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/02/daily-head-voices-2024-02-19_25/img_0138_hu_6e1ea265cbec06c2.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/02/daily-head-voices-2024-02-19_25/img_0138_hu_5c39aef4dde4c6b7.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="monday-2024-02-19-to-wednesday-2024-02-21">Monday 2024-02-19 to Wednesday 2024-02-21</h2>
<ul>
<li>Prepared for and did business trip to Johannesburg with longest time friend FS.
<ul>
<li>Highlight was tripping with FS, and trip was successful to boot.</li>
<li>Only one night away, really missed the famjam.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Dealing with stomach issues this week, relatively mild but distracting nonetheless.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-02-22">Thursday 2024-02-22</h2>
<ul>
<li>Short run this morning in school district. Not feeling 100%, but good enough for run and conditions perfect.
<ul>
<li>Did run into G-J on Reservoir road and had quick chat, serendipity! Lunch will follow.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Stomach getting better, but not yet in a good place.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-02-23">Friday 2024-02-23</h2>
<ul>
<li>Ran into the <a href="https://sidekick.kagi.com/">Kagi sidekick</a> proposal, which made me think about frontend-only search functions for my static websites
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/do-me/SemanticFinder">SemanticFinder</a>: Frontend-only live semantic search with transformers.js</li>
<li><a href="https://victoria.dev/blog/add-search-to-hugo-static-sites-with-lunr/">victoria.dev: Adding lunr.js to Hugo for frontend-only search</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent some cycles today exploring ways to save a tweet so that it can be archived and searched offline
<ul>
<li>If I could just traverse the DOM tree, starting from the <code>&lt;article&gt;</code> or the parent <code>&lt;section&gt;</code>, and also gathering all of the applicable styles, I would be golden
<ul>
<li>Discovered three different paid-for chrome extensions that do exactly this. Small side-hustle idea right there.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/deathau/markdownload">MarkDownload extension</a> for saving any page as markdown came quite close</li>
<li>Dev tools &ldquo;capture node screenshot&rdquo; saves to PNG. Would have been great if it could have done the same to PDF.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Had a lovely lunch with great colleague from 1999/2000 at Mont Marie in Stellenbosch.
<ul>
<li>Randomly reached out when I heard that he was back in this valley, super grateful for this enjoyable reconnection.</li>
<li>Remember, <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">call up your friends!</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-02-24">Saturday 2024-02-24</h2>
<ul>
<li>Spent too many hours building a Tampermonkey script with which I can get tweet threads reasonably clean in order to print  them
<ul>
<li>First time using Tampermonkey, good tool to have on the belt!</li>
<li>Twitter makes this a lot more tricky than it needs to be.</li>
<li>Ideally, people would stop using twitter altogether, but for the ML crowd, I still need to go there</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Perfect dinner at Decameron in Stellenbosch with the family, because we had to take GOU#1 to a party in the region</li>
<li>Karpathy proclaims his love for Obsidian, very cool! <a href="https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/1761467904737067456">https://twitter.com/karpathy/status/1761467904737067456</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-02-25">Sunday 2024-02-25</h2>
<ul>
<li>Thanks to serendipitous serendipity the previous day, took part in an unexpected and epic hike up India Venster with a lifetime friend (first hike together in the 90s!) and a fantastic new friend. Experienced maximal presence. Glorious.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 7 of 2024: Rest For Success</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/18/daily-head-voices-week-7-2024/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 17:42:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/18/daily-head-voices-week-7-2024/</guid><description> Most people in high-stress, decision-making industries are always operating at this kind of simmering six, as opposed to the undulation between just deep relaxation and being at a 10. Being at a 10 is millions of times better than being at a 6. It’s just in a different universe. &amp;ndash; Josh Waitzkin (see Sunday below)
Monday 2024-02-12 I really enjoyed this Rolling Stone article about Nine Inch Nails&amp;rsquo; Head Like a Hole Yes, that&amp;rsquo;s also a subtle jab at those of you who read last week&amp;rsquo;s title and did not get the reference. :P Extreme almost asymptotic anger moment at Outlook PWA: Spent time crafting a detailed meeting description. Unrelated meeting notification came in, meeting edit dialog disappears, all of those beautiful words gone. Forever. Accidentally upgraded Emacs to 29.2 (brew upgrade if you must now, and there it went building emacs along with installing all the other smaller dependencies, the ones I actually had in mind) Added ad-hoc similar node search for org-roam-similarity (that links to the new function&amp;rsquo;s documentation) This means you can also select any text, or just use the whole current buffer as your input, and then get a completing read list of similar nodes to open The area of my forehead around the scar feels like it has substantial nerve drop-out. I can&amp;rsquo;t feel much there, and I also can&amp;rsquo;t actuate much. The reconstructive surgeon warned before the time that this might be the case. Thanks again cancer. I&amp;rsquo;m crossing my fingers that there&amp;rsquo;s still some recovery that needs to happen and this is not my forehead&amp;rsquo;s final form. bitbar is now xbar. It looks like xbar can eat RAM https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725 I looked this up, because during my previous macOS phase I contributed code to bitbar to support Lua plugins. That work is now gone. Oh well. What a craptastically unproductive day. I had all of the time, and in that time I utterly failed at my selected task. I did some other interesting and possibly valuable stuff, but the majority of the time was wasted. Old lesson on this blog: some days gonna be crap However, responded to this by reviving my old FocusApp licence (see pro-tip #2 in WHV #126) and installed on my machine Tuesday 2024-02-13 First day back at the office. Lots of conversations due to the giant scar criss-crossing over half my forehead. Implemented the new (but very very old) &amp;ldquo;avoid all social media during work hours except a little bit on your phone during real breaks&amp;rdquo; rule. Using terminal Emacs for some remote work, because reasons Bothersome delay when pressing escape to get out of insert mode into normal mode. IT WAS TMUX. https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868 Noticed how much I rely on the cursor shape to know in what mode (insert, normal, emacs) I am. Fortunately found https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer and it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;hellip; game changer. Today was much fun at the office. Also much higher productivity due to above-mentioned no-social-media-goofing-off-rule. Wednesday 2024-02-14 Happy Valentine&amp;rsquo;s day everyone! Utterly crazy this morning because load-shedding, but due to GOU#3 being so very on time we left at 7:05 and could avoid most of that chaos. 6.5km short run just to get back into it, after 1.5 weeks out thanks to surgery and recovery. Garmin not happy with my fitness, but man it felt good. Went to doctor&amp;rsquo;s rooms to have stitches removed. Kind and professional nurse left the stitches in the middle, because skin there still needed some time to relax into the new situation. Feels really good to have the others out. Will go back on Friday for the rest. Pro-tip: it was a bit of a change management challenge, but I&amp;rsquo;ve converted my household to the new shopping list support in Apple Reminders. If you&amp;rsquo;re an Apple family, this woks much better than a WhatsApp group named &amp;ldquo;Shopping&amp;rdquo;. True story. Thanks to said app, remembered to get flowers. FocusApp really did its work today. I&amp;rsquo;m a tiny little bit bummed that no-one picked up on the Head like a Hole reference from last week&amp;rsquo;s Daily Head Voices. Or maybe someone did, but they just have not contacted me about it. Hopefully this week&amp;rsquo;s title does better. SUCH A GOOD DAY today thank you! Thursday 2024-02-15 Pretty busy day with meetings (Thursday is secondary meeting day at work after all), good conversations with colleagues, and an internal product playbook workshop. Friday 2024-02-16 Sublime run in Land &amp;amp; Zeezicht (school district) right after dropping off GOU#3, which also helped to avoid most of the traffic back home, again utterly crazy due to the 6 - 8:30 AM load-shedding slot disabling some critical (for us) traffic lights. Best afternoon ever: Father and daughter picnic with GOU#1 (school event, so many other fathers and daughters) at Zorgvliet Wine Estate In the evening, got my work inbox unread email count to just under 4000. Thank you for coming to my TED talk. Spent a bit more time reading about the new and open source Observable Framework I&amp;rsquo;ve always liked the ObservableJS notebooks, but this new development which supports working locally and self-hosting is really exciting! marimo is very nice for experimentation, but big advantage of OF is that it builds a static site as output. marimo needs Python to be running on the server. Again that idea: How automatically could I push a completely new OF built dashboard to a newly allocated CloudFlare pages site? Tried it out on Sunday evening (IN THE FUTURE): Was really quick to get the intro dashboard going in my case with pnpm, but a big challenge at this moment is the developer experience: There is very little coding assistance of any kind as you work on the javascript code blocks in the markdown pages. Hopefully they will be able to improve this with a vscode extension and/or a web-based editing experience, like marimo. Tried out Thunderbird 115.7 on the macbook. Much better than the TB 115 experience I had just after its release on Windows, where its currently selected mail logic handled it very badly when I archived a mail. I am trying out TB, because I miss the today, yesterday, last week date grouping. Saturday 2024-02-17 Woke up with low body battery (Garmin). Somewhat surprised, because only two beers last night. Perhaps the stress of the arguments, and probably still the alcohol because I&amp;rsquo;m old now. Wrote some Mojo to see if I could create a Pandas DataFrame and write to disc as Parquet. I love parquet. Although Mojo is still missing some data structures, it was not too involved to use the imported numpy and pandas libraries to do this job. Smoked snoek braai (so good! 🤤) at friend LM&amp;rsquo;s place with more friends. Sunday 2024-02-18 Super enjoyable 13km run. Not too hot, just a little bit of wind, and enough energy to finish strong. George Mack makes the statement: &amp;ldquo;There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.&amp;rdquo; This might indeed be a controversial statement, but I really like that his advice is to focus on the quality and purity of one&amp;rsquo;s rest (a very mindful idea), leading to much more energy for intensity 10 work. See his tweet (also embedded below, but please do click on &amp;ldquo;show more&amp;rdquo;) for a bunch of interesting examples. Figured out that it&amp;rsquo;s pretty easy to setup &amp;ldquo;Smart Mailboxes&amp;rdquo; on Apple Mail for today, yesterday, last week and so on. Truly sublime lunch with family at Stables on Vergelegen wine estate. Semi-controversial opinion: There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.
1. Winston Churchill used to work 16 hours per day in his old age during the war — but he also worked in bed every day until 11am. He had a nap after lunch, and a 2 hour nap… pic.twitter.com/kyiAuTEwjA</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Most people in high-stress, decision-making industries are always operating at this kind of simmering six, as opposed to the undulation between just deep relaxation and being at a 10. Being at a 10 is millions of times better than being at a 6. It’s just in a different universe. &ndash; Josh Waitzkin (see Sunday below)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="monday-2024-02-12">Monday 2024-02-12</h2>
<ul>
<li>I really enjoyed this <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-features/nine-inch-nails-head-like-a-hole-anthem-900750/">Rolling Stone article about Nine Inch Nails&rsquo; Head Like a Hole</a>
<ul>
<li>Yes, that&rsquo;s also a subtle jab at those of you who read last week&rsquo;s title and did not get the reference. :P</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Extreme almost asymptotic anger moment at Outlook PWA: Spent time crafting a detailed meeting description. Unrelated meeting notification came in, meeting edit dialog disappears, all of those beautiful words gone. Forever.</li>
<li>Accidentally upgraded Emacs to 29.2 (<code>brew upgrade</code> if you must now, and there it went building emacs along with installing all the other smaller dependencies, the ones I actually had in mind)</li>
<li>Added ad-hoc similar node search for <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity?tab=readme-ov-file#key-bind-the-ad-hoc-similarity-search">org-roam-similarity</a> (that links to the new function&rsquo;s documentation)
<ul>
<li>This means you can also select any text, or just use the whole current buffer as your input, and then get a completing read list of similar nodes to open</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The area of my forehead around the scar feels like it has substantial nerve drop-out. I can&rsquo;t feel much there, and I also can&rsquo;t actuate much. The reconstructive surgeon warned before the time that this might be the case. Thanks again cancer. I&rsquo;m crossing my fingers that there&rsquo;s still some recovery that needs to happen and this is not my forehead&rsquo;s final form.</li>
<li>bitbar is now xbar. It looks like xbar can eat RAM <a href="https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725">https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725</a>
<ul>
<li>I looked this up, because during <a href="/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/#new-laptop">my previous macOS phase</a> I contributed code to bitbar to support Lua plugins. That work is now gone. Oh well.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What a craptastically unproductive day. I had all of the time, and in that time I utterly failed at my selected task. I did some other interesting and possibly valuable stuff, but the majority of the time was wasted.
<ul>
<li>Old lesson on this blog: <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning">some days gonna be crap</a></li>
<li>However, responded to this by reviving my old FocusApp licence (see pro-tip #2 in <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">WHV #126</a>) and installed on my machine</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-02-13">Tuesday 2024-02-13</h2>
<ul>
<li>First day back at the office. Lots of conversations due to the giant scar criss-crossing over half my forehead.</li>
<li>Implemented the new (but very very old) &ldquo;avoid all social media during work hours except a little bit on your phone during real breaks&rdquo; rule.</li>
<li>Using terminal Emacs for some remote work, because reasons
<ul>
<li>Bothersome delay when pressing escape to get out of insert mode into normal mode. IT WAS TMUX. <a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868">https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868</a></li>
<li>Noticed how much I rely on the cursor shape to know in what mode (insert, normal, emacs) I am. Fortunately found <a href="https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer">https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer</a> and it&rsquo;s a &hellip; game changer.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Today was much fun at the office. Also much higher productivity due to above-mentioned no-social-media-goofing-off-rule.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-02-14">Wednesday 2024-02-14</h2>
<ul>
<li>Happy Valentine&rsquo;s day everyone!</li>
<li>Utterly crazy this morning because load-shedding, but due to GOU#3 being so very on time we left at 7:05 and could avoid most of that chaos.</li>
<li>6.5km short run just to get back into it, after 1.5 weeks out thanks to surgery and recovery. Garmin not happy with my fitness, but man it felt good.</li>
<li>Went to doctor&rsquo;s rooms to have stitches removed. Kind and professional nurse left the stitches in the middle, because skin there still needed some time to relax into the new situation. Feels really good to have the others out. Will go back on Friday for the rest.</li>
<li>Pro-tip: it was a bit of a change management challenge, but I&rsquo;ve converted my household to the new shopping list support in Apple Reminders. If you&rsquo;re an Apple family, this woks much better than a WhatsApp group named &ldquo;Shopping&rdquo;. True story.
<ul>
<li>Thanks to said app, remembered to get flowers.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>FocusApp really did its work today.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m a tiny little bit bummed that no-one picked up on the Head like a Hole reference from last week&rsquo;s Daily Head Voices. Or maybe someone did, but they just have not contacted me about it.
<ul>
<li>Hopefully this week&rsquo;s title does better.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>SUCH A GOOD DAY today thank you!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-02-15">Thursday 2024-02-15</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pretty busy day with meetings (Thursday is secondary meeting day at work after all), good conversations with colleagues, and an internal product playbook workshop.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-02-16">Friday 2024-02-16</h2>
<ul>
<li>Sublime run in Land &amp; Zeezicht (school district) right after dropping off GOU#3, which also helped to avoid most of the traffic back home, again utterly crazy due to the 6 - 8:30 AM load-shedding slot disabling some critical (for us) traffic lights.</li>
<li>Best afternoon ever: Father and daughter picnic with GOU#1 (school event, so many other fathers and daughters) at Zorgvliet Wine Estate</li>
<li>In the evening, got my work inbox unread email count to just under 4000. Thank you for coming to my TED talk.</li>
<li>Spent a bit more time reading about the new and open source <a href="https://observablehq.com/framework/">Observable Framework</a>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve always liked the ObservableJS notebooks, but this new development which supports working locally and self-hosting is really exciting!</li>
<li>marimo is very nice for experimentation, but big advantage of OF is that it builds a static site as output. marimo needs Python to be running on the server.</li>
<li>Again that idea: How automatically could I push a completely new OF built dashboard to a newly allocated CloudFlare pages site?</li>
<li>Tried it out on Sunday evening (IN THE FUTURE): Was really quick to get the intro dashboard going in my case with <code>pnpm</code>, but a big challenge at this moment is the developer experience: There is very little coding assistance of any kind as you work on the javascript code blocks in the markdown pages. Hopefully they will be able to improve this with a vscode extension and/or a web-based editing experience, like marimo.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Tried out Thunderbird 115.7 on the macbook.
<ul>
<li>Much better than the TB 115 experience I had just after its release on Windows, where its currently selected mail logic handled it very badly when I archived a mail.</li>
<li>I am trying out TB, because I miss the today, yesterday, last week date grouping.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-02-17">Saturday 2024-02-17</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up with low body battery (Garmin). Somewhat surprised, because only two beers last night. Perhaps the stress of the arguments, and probably still the alcohol because I&rsquo;m old now.</li>
<li>Wrote some Mojo to see if I could create a Pandas DataFrame and write to disc as Parquet.
<ul>
<li>I love parquet.</li>
<li>Although Mojo is still missing some data structures, it was not too involved to use the imported numpy and pandas libraries to do this job.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Smoked snoek braai (so good! 🤤) at friend LM&rsquo;s place with more friends.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-02-18">Sunday 2024-02-18</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super enjoyable 13km run. Not too hot, just a little bit of wind, and enough energy to finish strong.</li>
<li>George Mack makes the statement: &ldquo;There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.&rdquo;
<ul>
<li>This might indeed be a controversial statement, but  I really like that his advice is to focus on the quality and purity of one&rsquo;s rest (a very mindful idea), leading to much more energy for intensity 10 work.</li>
<li>See <a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1759122352036577546">his tweet</a> (also embedded below, but please do click on &ldquo;show more&rdquo;) for a bunch of interesting examples.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Figured out that it&rsquo;s pretty easy to setup &ldquo;Smart Mailboxes&rdquo; on Apple Mail for today, yesterday, last week and so on.</li>
<li>Truly sublime lunch with family at <a href="https://vergelegen.co.za/restaurants/stables-at-vergelegen/">Stables on Vergelegen wine estate</a>.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-dnt="true"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Semi-controversial opinion: There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.<br><br>1. Winston Churchill used to work 16 hours per day in his old age during the war — but he also worked in bed every day until 11am. He had a nap after lunch, and a 2 hour nap… <a href="https://t.co/kyiAuTEwjA">pic.twitter.com/kyiAuTEwjA</a></p>&mdash; George Mack (@george__mack) <a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1759122352036577546?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 18, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 6 of 2024: Head Like a Hole</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</guid><description>Why do I lifelog? One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&amp;rsquo;s not form their own mind.
Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="why-do-i-lifelog">Why do  I lifelog?</h2>
<p>One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&rsquo;s not form their own mind.</p>
<p>Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</p>
<h3 id="journalling-vs-lifelogging">Journalling vs lifelogging</h3>
<p>In my view, <em>journalling</em> is a more developed form of <em>lifelogging</em>. While the latter is just the direct jotting down of happenings and noteworthy items, the former, at least to me, entails more thinking and more processing, i.e. there is more retro- and introspection going on. I would prefer to be <em>journalling</em>, because that has even more benefits, but I&rsquo;ll take <em>lifelogging</em> when I can&rsquo;t make the prerequisite time to think, and really craft my words.</p>
<p>On to the lifelog:</p>
<h2 id="monday-2024-02-05">Monday 2024-02-05</h2>
<ul>
<li>Friend LM told me about wikitree.org, which is a collaborative online family tree thingy. I tried to import the myheritage.com exported GEDCOM, but wikitree.org wants me to reject or accept each and everyone of the hundreds of people in my database. This is understandable, but it&rsquo;s also a  blocker, exacerbated by the fact that wikitree&rsquo;s matching algorithm is quite bad.</li>
<li>Casey Neistat&rsquo;s Apple Vision Pro review is insightful. See the bit from 7:20 onwards: <a href="https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440">https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440</a> &ndash; &ldquo;&hellip; This is it. This is the future of computing&hellip;&rdquo;
<ul>
<li>also see my tweet embedded below</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>NVIDIA&rsquo;s GenAI competition <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/">https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/</a>
<ul>
<li>Use TensorRT or TensorRT-LLM on Windows to build something cool, submit by Feb 23, win RTX 4090 and GTC conf attendance. EZ PZ!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Remember that life is <em>supposed</em> to be just a long sequence of problems that you need to solve.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is such a fun &quot;review&quot; of the Apple Vision Pro by Casey Neistat, but his discussion at 7:20 on the significance of the product is so spot on.<br><br>I had similar ideas about ubiquitous face-computing back in 2009: <a href="https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc">https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc</a> <a href="https://t.co/au9RBh7as0">https://t.co/au9RBh7as0</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1754421449719193753?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 5, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>










<figure><a href="avp-angry-gf.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b5f62d2dc15edfd3.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b31467e1ec255b77.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_c35fee7f6f8120f9.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-06">Tuesday 2024-01-06</h2>
<ul>
<li>Using inkscape to draw SVG glyphs which can be converted with <a href="https://react-svgr.com/">svgr</a> into React components, for my visualization project. This works so well!</li>
<li>Definitely a bit stressed about tomorrow&rsquo;s surgery. Also little throat niggle, and as if that was not enough, stomach issues due to droëwors I ate in the afternoon to preload a bit for tomorrow&rsquo;s required fasting.
<ul>
<li>Narrator: This would be followed by one of <em>the</em> worst nights in a long time, including fever chills, nausea, and so on.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>My brain keeps on jumping on ideas for 3D / VR / AR / AI friendly / native ideas for managing personal knowledge / notes
<ul>
<li>on the one hand, it feels like the atomic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten">Zettelkasten</a> approach could work well here</li>
<li>on the other, we have chunking techniques to break up documents, so that we can extract the nuggets we want in order to embed them
<ul>
<li>this chunking can be dynamic and adaptive, perhaps even going down to sentences and individual diagrams, or dynamically constructed chunks consisting of sub-chunks merged from different sources</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>in the end, will it help  or even just be interesting to be able to walk / move through / manipulate different projections of your (or someone else&rsquo;s) thoughts, possibly even connected in different ways?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-07">Wednesday 2024-01-07</h2>
<ul>
<li>Microsoft Lens makes me login every single time, and is quite temperamental
<ul>
<li>alternatives are OneDrive app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo; or Files app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At Summerhill day clinic for the excision of the morpheaform basal cell carcinoma (BCC) on my forehead
<ul>
<li>Fortunately, the doctor decided the excision on my back (with clean borders pronounced by pathology lab) does not need to be re-excised.</li>
<li>Excision of 2cm x 1.5cm patch from my forehead via <a href="https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/conditions-and-diseases/mohs-surgery">Mohs surgery</a> is successful after first attempt, happiness!</li>
<li>Reconstructive surgeon however now has a challenge: How to close up hole with no loose skin in sight? (I am a tightly wrapped person)
<ul>
<li>problem is solved with step-wise incision from the top middle of my forehead all the way down to my right temple, about 20cm in total.</li>
<li>I look like I could be the son of Frankenstein and Harry Potter</li>
<li>The care at Summerhill is beyond excellent. Now I just have to follow instructions, drink many pills, and my new friend-for-life Scar should heal up nicely.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-08">Thursday 2024-01-08</h2>
<ul>
<li>Working from home because reasons</li>
<li>I have to work hard to focus, the medication seems to affect my concentration. I will grit my teeth harder.</li>
<li>In break time, tried out <a href="https://www.modular.com/blog/mojo-sdk-v0-7-now-available-for-download">Mojo v0.7.0 (released 2024-01-25)</a> through its REPL and also just a simple <code>hello.mojo</code>, which compiled into a nice 300kB binary on this MacBook! Cautiously excited for the future of this. (also&hellip;. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Lattner">Chris Lattner</a>! 😍)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-09">Friday 2024-01-09</h2>
<ul>
<li>In the morning, got mu4e setup and working on the new MacBook, although I thought I was not going to need this mail client
<ul>
<li>What is your favourite mail client?</li>
<li>I use the Fastmail web client, mu4e for Emacs and macOS Mail, but none of them is perfect. mu4e comes close. ;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Really struggled during the day with drowsiness, although I&rsquo;m sleeping extra well every night.</li>
<li>By the end, at least was able to make demo video of my in-progress visualization project.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-10">Saturday 2024-01-10</h2>
<ul>
<li>head still feeling quite woozy</li>
<li>happy to have kids at home, and have a pretty relaxed morning</li>
<li>I would really like to write / create something today. What?</li>
<li>family tree updates
<ul>
<li>tried out ancestris, which is unusably slow on my m1pro. just getting a context menu on a person in the tree, or scrolling around, has too much lag. Tried on my Windows desktop where it&rsquo;s better but still really slow.</li>
<li>Went back to wikitree (recommended by LM) where I updated some more records (extremely laboriously).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.familysearch.org/en/">https://www.familysearch.org/en/</a> has been really useful for scans of church registers and so on, confirming more of my earlier findings.
<ul>
<li>See for example <a href="https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910">https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910</a> which just came in as I was typing this. That&rsquo;s the death notice of my paternal great grandmother in 1919, very shortly after the birth of my grandfather.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I think I might have spent too much time on this today. There&rsquo;s a bit of a dopamine rush every time you solve a mini riddle. Here also I would like to have something shareable and reusable for other members of my family. For that, wikitree, although painful, seems like a good bet.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>mind wandered at 13:30ish, of course it ended up in infinite canvases and pkm
<ul>
<li>wanted to keep on letting it wander, but also wanted to use laptop to read about freeform
<ul>
<li>Apple Freeform looks like the pretty-ok-like-notes canvas solution: <a href="https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue">https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Instead of going to bed early, experimented with round-tripping markdown to docx and back with pandoc. See tomorrow for results.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-11">Sunday 2024-01-11</h2>
<ul>
<li>Briefly tried out the new(ish) built-in <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-za/guide/iphone/iph0e5ca7dd3/ios">iOS Journal app</a>
<ul>
<li>Super nice that it taps into your activities (photos, music, workouts, etc.) and makes recommendations for packets of media you could add to a journal, all of this entirely on-device.</li>
<li>Private, encourages folks to lock the app and so on.</li>
<li>No export capability, so your journals remain utterly locked in for now.</li>
<li>Makes it easy to configure reminders that will prompt you to write  a journal at specific moments during the week.</li>
<li>Minimalistic and well-executed app, will probably get quite a few iPhone users to start journalling, but not for me. I already have too many Apple apps in my personal system that I need to use (e.g. Apple Notes) but that don&rsquo;t interoperate particularly well with other systems.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent some more time on familysearch.org creating and attaching person records (from my family) to scans of old archive documents. Also uploaded a PDF of hand-written notes made by one of my family members from the headstones on a farm on which a number of my ancestors were buried.
<ul>
<li>Two-world problem. Bringing the physical into the digital.</li>
<li><strong>familysearch really does work better than wikitree&hellip;</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>About that Two World Problem. Had some thoughts about it in the context of my personal knowledge management, but it was slightly too much for the bullets I had allocated to it, and so it become a short post titled <a href="/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/">On the two world problem and personal knowledge management</a>.
<ul>
<li>In an ideal world, I am able to publish mini posts like that on a weekly basis.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Oh wait, I also made a short post on vxlabs with the results of last night&rsquo;s pandoc experiments, titled <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/02/11/pandoc-roundtrip-from-markdown-to-docx-and-back/">Pandoc roundtrip from markdown to docx and back</a>
<ul>
<li>In this case, I went direct to Hugo markdown instead of starting in Emacs Orgmode first, in order to further reduce activation energy. This makes sense for posts I want to get published where I don&rsquo;t necessarily need the benefit of having the content integrated with my main notes database.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 5 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/07/daily-head-voices-2024-02-29_04/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 09:42:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/07/daily-head-voices-2024-02-29_04/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-29 Took a bit of a deep dive today figuring out if and how we could implement our homegrown SciPy-heavy data ecosystem on Azure and Power BI. Ignoring the daunting (but predictable) costs, was quite impressed by MS Fabric. Read the following two blog posts for a good introduction, cast as a comparison between Fabric and the &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; Azure Synapse. https://medium.com/version-1/does-fabric-offer-anything-more-than-synapse-workspace-d5240e4a30fe https://endjin.com/blog/2023/05/azure-synapse-analytics-versus-microsoft-fabric-a-side-by-side-comparison Because I wanted to store and sometimes highlight bunches of web pages on above-mentioned topic, decided to use the OneNote webclipper to push to work&amp;rsquo;s cloud article extraction works quite well, and you can highlight, but there&amp;rsquo;s no nice way to attach a note / comment to that highlight omnivore sometimes struggles with extracting the article from a busy webpage, but attaching comments to highlights is a first class feature Tuesday 2024-01-30 Started with trying to write up Fabric notes in word doc, but did not get far. I do miss Dropbox Paper for things like this. Still, I should be able to get somewhere with just a DOCX and all of the screenshots I&amp;rsquo;ve been making. Defining high-level sprint goals worked much more nicely than I expected! Managed to get some sqlite3 data imported via Fabric Notebook into OneLake. Great feeling that it just works! Wednesday 2024-01-31 Started run at about 7:30 in Land en Zeezicht after dropping off GOU#3 Coffee with ex-colleague J at Deluxe Coffeeworks in Dorp Street Stellenboch. Grateful for the catch-up, and also the exceptional coffee. llava 1.6 (VLM) release post: https://llava-vl.github.io/blog/2024-01-30-llava-1-6/ Through reactflow, discovered ELK and elkjs for the layout of graphs! Play around with it here: https://rtsys.informatik.uni-kiel.de/elklive/ Renewed vehicle license via https://online.natis.gov.za/ and not via City of Cape Town eServices as we usually do, because heard from colleague Z that natis delivers via courier and not via the South African Postal Service, which does not really function anymore thanks to the current government, and either takes months to deliver the licence or sometimes just loses track of it. Thursday 2024-02-01 Breakfast with almost lifetime friend CFS Did some work before he arrived, but got SUPER frustrated with DSTV because I was checking in on all my TODOs as I transferred them to the new month file and thus discovered that they had still not changed my subscription (this is after months of them confirming the change and not following through), and so after 10 years of their most expensive subscription I have now terminated our relationship. Did you know: DSTV can be found in the dictionary under &amp;ldquo;galaxy-level grudge purchase&amp;rdquo;? I have been trying to downgrade @DStv premium to compact plus since April 2023. Numerous times website confirmed my downgrade, but then returns to premium and bills me. In January, consultant confirmed my downgrade in January. Guess what? website says Premium! Cancelling @DStv</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-29">Monday 2024-01-29</h2>
<ul>
<li>Took a bit of a deep dive today figuring out if and how we could implement our homegrown SciPy-heavy data ecosystem on Azure and Power BI. Ignoring the daunting (but predictable) costs, was quite impressed by <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/fabric/get-started/microsoft-fabric-overview">MS Fabric</a>. Read the following two blog posts for a good introduction, cast as a comparison between Fabric and the &ldquo;old&rdquo; Azure Synapse.
<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/version-1/does-fabric-offer-anything-more-than-synapse-workspace-d5240e4a30fe">https://medium.com/version-1/does-fabric-offer-anything-more-than-synapse-workspace-d5240e4a30fe</a></li>
<li><a href="https://endjin.com/blog/2023/05/azure-synapse-analytics-versus-microsoft-fabric-a-side-by-side-comparison">https://endjin.com/blog/2023/05/azure-synapse-analytics-versus-microsoft-fabric-a-side-by-side-comparison</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Because I wanted to store and sometimes highlight bunches of web pages on above-mentioned topic, decided to use the OneNote webclipper to push to work&rsquo;s cloud
<ul>
<li>article extraction works quite well, and you can highlight, but there&rsquo;s no nice way to attach a note / comment to that highlight</li>
<li>omnivore sometimes struggles with extracting the article from a busy webpage, but attaching comments to highlights is a first class feature</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-30">Tuesday 2024-01-30</h2>
<ul>
<li>Started with trying to write up Fabric notes in word doc, but did not get far. I do <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#byeeeeee-dropbox">miss Dropbox Paper</a> for things like this. Still, I should be able to get somewhere with just a DOCX and all of the screenshots I&rsquo;ve been making.</li>
<li>Defining high-level sprint goals worked much more nicely than I expected!</li>
<li>Managed to get some sqlite3 data imported via Fabric Notebook into OneLake. Great feeling that it just works!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-31">Wednesday 2024-01-31</h2>
<ul>
<li>Started run at about 7:30 in Land en Zeezicht after dropping off GOU#3</li>
<li>Coffee with ex-colleague J at Deluxe Coffeeworks in Dorp Street Stellenboch. Grateful for the catch-up, and also the exceptional coffee.</li>
<li>llava 1.6 (VLM) release post: <a href="https://llava-vl.github.io/blog/2024-01-30-llava-1-6/">https://llava-vl.github.io/blog/2024-01-30-llava-1-6/</a></li>
<li>Through reactflow, discovered ELK and elkjs for the layout of graphs! Play around with it here: <a href="https://rtsys.informatik.uni-kiel.de/elklive/">https://rtsys.informatik.uni-kiel.de/elklive/</a></li>
<li>Renewed vehicle license via <a href="https://online.natis.gov.za/">https://online.natis.gov.za/</a> and not via City of Cape Town eServices as we usually do, because heard from colleague Z that natis delivers via courier and not via the South African Postal Service, which does not really function anymore thanks to the current government, and either takes months to deliver the licence or sometimes just loses track of it.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-02-01">Thursday 2024-02-01</h2>
<ul>
<li>Breakfast with almost lifetime friend CFS</li>
<li>Did some work before he arrived, but got SUPER frustrated with DSTV because I was checking in on all my TODOs as I transferred them to the new month file and thus discovered that they had still not changed my subscription (this is after months of them confirming the change and not following through), and so after 10 years of their most expensive subscription I have now terminated our relationship.
<ul>
<li>Did you know: DSTV can be found in the dictionary under &ldquo;galaxy-level grudge purchase&rdquo;?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I have been trying to downgrade <a href="https://twitter.com/DStv?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@DStv</a> premium to compact plus since April 2023. Numerous times website confirmed my downgrade, but then returns to premium and bills me. In January, consultant confirmed my downgrade in January. Guess what? website says Premium! Cancelling <a href="https://twitter.com/DStv?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@DStv</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1752972827609694543?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 1, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="friday-2024-02-02">Friday 2024-02-02</h2>
<ul>
<li>Unexpectedly enjoyable little run at 7:27 in Land en Zeezicht (Beaumont school district), just after dropping off GOU#3, and just before the dailry heatwave hit. On Reservoir Road, close to the end of my route, I looked up at the beautiful clouds and experienced a feeling of what I can only describe as <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#multiplicity-of-you">inside-is-outside connected bliss</a>.</li>
<li>Made 40 seconds recording of my talking head in English, translated it to Spanish using <a href="https://www.heygen.com/">HeyGen</a>. I used the resultant video for a short GenAI update at work. Really funny but also a bit scary to see my mouth (in my face) talking Spanish in such convincing fashion.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-02-03">Saturday 2024-02-03</h2>
<ul>
<li>New licence, requested on Wednesday, delivered into my hands!</li>
<li>Against all the odds, and also in an utterly surprising (to me) move, four of us (3 NL, 1 ZA) have <a href="https://lowlands.nl/">Lowlands 2024</a> tickets. I was not planning to go this year, but friend MG got me back in the programme with a few well-placed Signal messages, casually mentioning that Skrillex was on the line-up (noooooo), and as if that was not enough, Fred Again and Soulwax too (unable&hellip;to&hellip;.resist). The crew will not be as complete as last year, which was why I was planning to sit on the bench this year, but life is short and I miss my friends.
<ul>
<li>I say against all the odds, because <a href="https://festileaks.com/2024/02/lowlands-2024-in-rap-tempo-uitverkocht/">all 60000+ tickets were sold out in 20 minutes</a>. We were in the digital queue together with 130000 other customers (each customer can buy up to 8 tickets!), but we eventually got the message that all tickets had been sold out, indeed after about 20 minutes. We did what many folks apparently do not: We just kept on trying! Looks like the odd ticket, probably from a failed payment, made its way back to the queue, and we managed to buy 1+2+1 by just not giving up.</li>
<li>Now I am equal parts ecstatic and daunted.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-02-04">Sunday 2024-02-04</h2>
<ul>
<li>13km run in the heat. Was planning for shorter, but run was much more fun than I expected, just super hot man.</li>
<li>Through an email from familysearch.org, saw that someone had uploaded scans of the &ldquo;Doop register NG Kerk Worcester&rdquo; all the way outta 1881, through which I could confirm some of my earlier findings (after a long search) re my <a href="https://www.familysearch.org/ark:/61903/1:1:6K5Q-5KJ8">great-grandfather Pieter Barend Francois, born in 1881</a>, namely that his dad was Daniël Stephanus Botha born born 1848. Thanks familysearch and thanks Church!
<ul>
<li>You might remember that myheritage was an important part of how I learned that I&rsquo;m actually an Appel straight outta Dutchieland (my home away from home) and not a real Botha. See <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#the-apple-doesn-t-fall-far-from-the-tree">WHV #237</a>.</li>
<li>However, I don&rsquo;t want to renew my myheritage.com sub in February. In spite of their 20% discount offer, it&rsquo;s really quite expensive if it&rsquo;s just hosting my data. It was definitely worth it when I was still actively trying to track down various ancestors.</li>
<li>Now I have to start looking for alternative tools to maintain our family tree. I know about gramps, but tonight I discovered ancestris, which works natively with GEDCOM (not just import and export).</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Absolutely sublime dinner outside with my whole family. Infinitely grateful.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 4 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-22 As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&amp;rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS! At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&amp;hellip; Short but really nice streamlit demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually played with it. Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3. In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola. Tuesday 2024-01-23 At the office nice and early (7:30). Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at react-flow and comfyui react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY! streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &amp;ldquo;things I learned&amp;rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document. Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&amp;rsquo;s a zero day vulnerability in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites. Wednesday 2024-01-24 8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW! Remember kids: Our spine&amp;rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally. This is also the reason why I&amp;rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair. Lovely working lunch with friend S at No Way José Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work: idea: make github so that people can pipx install marimo-turbo to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on. idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS &amp;hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844 (post is also embedded below) idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&amp;gt; nginx -&amp;gt; supervisord -&amp;gt; tornado systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation I would prefer to use supervisord for this This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick? ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &amp;ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&amp;rdquo; googling blog post: https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/ the kubernetes thing: https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&amp;rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via iframe.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-22">Monday 2024-01-22</h2>
<ul>
<li>As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &ldquo;When you&rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS!</li>
<li>At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&hellip;</li>
<li>Short but really nice <a href="https://streamlit.io/">streamlit</a> demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&rsquo;ve never actually played with it.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3.
<ul>
<li>In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-23">Tuesday 2024-01-23</h2>
<ul>
<li>At the office nice and early (7:30).</li>
<li>Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at <a href="https://reactflow.dev/">react-flow</a> and comfyui
<ul>
<li>react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see <a href="https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary">https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary</a>
<ul>
<li>it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster</li>
<li>marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &ldquo;things I learned&rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document.</li>
<li>Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&rsquo;s a <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/news/apple-issues-urgent-security-updates-to-fix-zero-day-flaw-update-your-iphone-and-mac-right-now">zero day vulnerability</a> in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-24">Wednesday 2024-01-24</h2>
<ul>
<li>8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot</li>
<li>dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work</li>
<li>right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW!
<ul>
<li>Remember kids: Our spine&rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally.</li>
<li>This is also the reason why I&rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lovely working lunch with friend S at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/NoWayJoseSomerset">No Way José</a></li>
<li>Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work:
<ul>
<li>idea: make github so that people can <code>pipx install marimo-turbo</code> to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on.</li>
<li>idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap
<ul>
<li>sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets</li>
<li>in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS
<ul>
<li>&hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844</a> (post is also embedded below)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&gt; nginx -&gt; supervisord -&gt; tornado
<ul>
<li>systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: <a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation">https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation</a></li>
<li>I would prefer to use supervisord for this</li>
<li>This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&rdquo; googling
<ul>
<li>blog post: <a href="https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/">https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/</a></li>
<li>the kubernetes thing: <a href="https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s">https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0" width="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><script src="https://emacs.ch/embed.js" async="async"></script>
<h3 id="til-mastodon-embeds-are-not-as-durable-as-twitter-embeds">TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds</h3>
<p>As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via <code>iframe</code>.</p>
<p>With twitter, you get more self-contained HTML which will render even when twitter or just the original tweet don&rsquo;t exist anymore.</p>
<p>This is probably just another reason to figure out how I can get more low-friction microblogging going on my own websites so that the embedding implementations of other microblogging sites become irrelevant.</p>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-25">Thursday 2024-01-25</h2>
<ul>
<li>Took a look at <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/connections/connect-networks/get-started/">cloudflare tunnels</a> to expose marimo and other dashboards to the internet
<ul>
<li>great that I can use my existing domains for this, and I can route between multiple domains to multiple locally running services</li>
<li>some more steps to setup, but it did not take more than about 5 minutes, and gives me even more options than tailscale funnels. OPTIONS MAN!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At work, quickly got react-flow&hellip; flowing. SHINY!</li>
<li>In the evening, found <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/">https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/</a> which is the new Shortcuts based way, based on the old AppleScript way, of getting a <code>message://</code> link onto the clipboard.
<ul>
<li>You <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#email-linking">might recall from this blog</a> that <code>message://</code> are the most durable and cross-platform way to link to emails from your notes (or anywhere else)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-26">Friday 2024-01-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up to cool, overcast weather, a big change from a series of 30℃ + days. Really had to resist going out for a run (normal run day + that amazing coolness), because of Wednesday&rsquo;s partially pulled back muscle not being 100% yet.</li>
<li>Worked on mystery visualization project (react-flow)</li>
<li>Lovely and energising lunch with previous colleague and friend. Happy that I reached out on Thursday although they have a packed schedule because only in country for limited time. I guess this is quite related to <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">calling up your friends</a>, with a ping of serendipity salt.</li>
<li>I was shocked by how well and fast <a href="https://ollama.ai/">ollama</a> worked on my MacBook. See embedded tweet below.</li>
<li>Almost at the end of the afternoon, friend S and I went to some more friends for the first Weiss-off, that is, a Weiss beer tasting contest. It was huge fun blind-tasting 10 different Weiss beers, ranking them, trying to identify them (so much harder than I thought!), and then having them revealed at the end.
<ul>
<li>Between the experts there (read: us), Stangen Weiss Bier came out on top, followed by Weisbier No5 and Jack Black Atlantic Weiss. The fourth place was shared by Erdinger and CBC Amber Weiss.</li>
<li>My favourite, Stellenbrau Jonkersweiss, is glaringly absent from the top. I&rsquo;ll live, probably consoled by just such a Jonkersweiss. Super happy that Amber Weiss and Atlantic are both present!</li>
<li>There was a trophy (for the taster who could blind-identify the most beers in the Weiss-off), which we have christened the <em>David Weisselhoff wisseltrofee</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">With <a href="https://twitter.com/MistralAI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@MistralAI</a>&#39;s Mistral 7B at Q4_0 on this MacBook M1 Pro 10C / 16C, <a href="https://twitter.com/ollama?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ollama</a> looks like it&#39;s easily 3 times faster than the new MLX 0.0.11 (with GGUF support).<br><br>It&#39;s subjectively (visually) faster, and the tokens/s measurements confirm this. <a href="https://t.co/9vyluimLKK">pic.twitter.com/9vyluimLKK</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1750824125419942036?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 26, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-27">Saturday 2024-01-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yesterday&rsquo;s Wonderful Weiss-off also had some, thankfully quite minor, effect the next morning, but I went out for a careful weekday distance run, which fortunately went without a hitch. Just very hot thanks.</li>
<li>Went to Buco and then to <a href="https://appletoolandgas.com/">Apple Tool and Gas</a> to find the rest of the screws I needed to repair the shower door. Friendly gentleman at Apple even sawed some of my screws to size! Shower door back in operation.</li>
<li>Updated my &ldquo;old&rdquo; M1 MBA to macOS 14.3 and then reset to transfer to GOU#1&rsquo;s iCloud. Say what you want about Apple, but that part of their stuff works <em>really</em> well.</li>
<li>Left for Betty&rsquo;s Bay at about 16:00 with GOUs #1 and #2. The rest of the family already there.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-28">Sunday 2024-01-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up in Betty&rsquo;s Bay after a longer than normal night of sleep, but Garmin body battery was still not completely happy.</li>
<li>In spite of having run yesterday and still feeling a bit tired (see body battery above), I had the best run of the month so far in Betty&rsquo;s. Go figure.</li>
<li>Spent some time with Canva &ndash; what a great resource for doing nice designs, even flow charts &ndash; but not sure where I could use this.</li>
<li>Background thought through the past weeks, and mentioned on Tuesday: I would really like to do (and promite) more TIL-style writing at work and at home. See <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/">Simon Willison&rsquo;s amazing TIL collection</a> for inspiration.</li>
<li>Ran into <a href="https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines">https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines</a> a Python library that can guarantee structured text generation from many LLMs, e.g. 100% valid JSON according to a specified schema. What makes it different from similar libraries? &ldquo;Unlike other libraries, regex-guided generation in Outlines is almost as fast as non-guided generation.&rdquo;</li>
<li>I already had <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/autogen">AutoGen</a> on my list for experimenting with multi-agent LLM applications, but now it has been joined by <a href="https://github.com/joaomdmoura/crewAI">crewAI</a> which I have also just ran into (thanks reddit!) and which seems to have significant support online.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 3 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 20:21:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-15 Discovered that we (at work) now have access to GPT-4 Turbo via Azure OpenAI: 128K context and much cheaper than the old GPT-4. Will have to upgrade our private internal assistant, code name StoneGPT. Inspired by stefanv, carefully trying out weekly planning, but in a slight deviation I&amp;rsquo;m doing this in addition to my daily planning, which I only get around to a fraction of the time in any case. I think that this sort of multi-scalar examination and planning will help. Went to Bloemhof for the welcoming of the new grade 8 learners. Was really great to see GOU#1 and GOU#2 there, on two very opposite ends of the spectrum. Tuesday 2024-01-16 MS Copilot Pro ($20) has been announced, and also Copilot 365 is now available for businesses of all sizes (not just enterprises who can commit to 300 seats): https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/ Copilot Pro not yet available in South Africa 😥 $20 per month for integration with some Office apps (which could be useful, will have to see), priority access to latest models such as GPT-4 Turbo, and custom Copilots. I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced, will stick to my perplexity.ai for now. Copilot for 365 can be purchased per seat, but minimum 1 year commitment which is $360 per person per year. Ouch. In addition to many meetings (Tuesday = meetings day), did manage to spend some quality time with a new visualization project. Slowly starting to use webcola again, but this time with d3@latest &amp;ndash; sorta works, but no dragging. Have found work-around, still need to test. Went to bed really early, because must be up at 5:30 to help GOU#2 get ready for school and get to the bus stop on time. (Slept super badly thanks.) Wednesday 2024-01-17 Up at 5:30 after a pretty restless night. GOU#2 on the bus at 6 after some serious morning prep multi-tasking, GOU#3 (age 7) so organized and independent, ready to leave for school at 7! Nice and early(ish) slightly longer weekday run before work. My hip sent me a Teams message &amp;ldquo;Hi&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; at about 80% of the route somewhere, but fortunately no follow-up. Colleagues on chat, haha. Got caught up in GEKKO Optimization Suite due to meetings with colleagues about various simulations. My initial enthusiasm was somewhat dampened upon learning that behind the Python API lies an admittedly useful but quite black-box compiled binary called apm.exe. TIL: John Lasseter drew the BSD daemon! See https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html &amp;ndash; I remember that daemon from the time when I had FreeBSD on my machine at home instead of Linux (somewhere in the 90s). You might remember that name from the Creativity Inc. book (the one about Pixar!) notes post on this blog Thursday 2024-01-18 AlphaGeometry from Google DeepMind is great work combining a symbolic math engine with a language model to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. See below for my breathless tweet. (twitter is still the uncontested ML firehose) News on our in-house GPT-wrapper front: Discovered that I now have to upgrade to the new tool_call api as the old functions one has been deprecated. Made use of the opportunity to improve our implementation of the supplied OpenAI type annotations Note to self, and to you: The *Params types are TypedDict declarations which you can use to work directly with JSON requests and responses, while the non-*Params types are pydantic models which you can use to (de)serialize JSON. Went to see a really good Mohs surgery dermatologist who will soon be removing my basal cell carcinomas. As always, AMA in the comments or via email. This is such fantastic work! Symbolic engine + language model working together to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. Also, beautiful illustrations in the paper and posts. https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-15">Monday 2024-01-15</h2>
<ul>
<li>Discovered that we (at work) now have access to GPT-4 Turbo via Azure OpenAI: 128K context and much cheaper than the old GPT-4. Will have to upgrade our private internal assistant, code name StoneGPT.</li>
<li>Inspired by stefanv, carefully trying out weekly planning, but in a slight deviation I&rsquo;m doing this <em>in addition</em> to my daily planning, which I only get around to a fraction of the time in any case. I think that this sort of multi-scalar examination and planning will help.</li>
<li>Went to Bloemhof for the welcoming of the new grade 8 learners. Was really great to see GOU#1 <em>and</em> GOU#2 there, on two very opposite ends of the spectrum.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-16">Tuesday 2024-01-16</h2>
<ul>
<li>MS Copilot Pro ($20) has been announced, and also Copilot 365 is now available for businesses of all sizes (not just enterprises who can commit to 300 seats): <a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/">https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/</a>
<ul>
<li>Copilot Pro not yet available in South Africa 😥
<ul>
<li>$20 per month for integration with some Office apps (which could be useful, will have to see), priority access to latest models such as GPT-4 Turbo, and custom Copilots. I&rsquo;m not convinced, will stick to my <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/">perplexity.ai</a> for now.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Copilot for 365 can be purchased per seat, but minimum 1 year commitment which is $360 per person per year. Ouch.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In addition to many meetings (Tuesday = meetings day), did manage to spend some quality time with a new visualization project. Slowly starting to use <a href="https://ialab.it.monash.edu/webcola/">webcola</a> again, but this time with d3@latest &ndash; sorta works, but no dragging. Have found work-around, still need to test.</li>
<li>Went to bed really early, because must be up at 5:30 to help GOU#2 get ready for school and get to the bus stop on time. (Slept super badly thanks.)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-17">Wednesday 2024-01-17</h2>
<ul>
<li>Up at 5:30 after a pretty restless night. GOU#2 on the bus at 6 after some serious morning prep multi-tasking, GOU#3 (age 7) so organized and independent, ready to leave for school at 7!</li>
<li>Nice and early(ish) slightly longer weekday run before work. My hip sent me a Teams message &ldquo;Hi&hellip;&rdquo; at about 80% of the route somewhere, but fortunately no follow-up. Colleagues on chat, haha.</li>
<li>Got caught up in <a href="#d41d8c">GEKKO Optimization Suite</a> due to meetings with colleagues about various simulations. My initial enthusiasm was somewhat dampened upon learning that behind the Python API lies an admittedly useful but quite black-box compiled binary called apm.exe.</li>
<li>TIL: John Lasseter drew the BSD daemon! See <a href="https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html">https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html</a> &ndash; I remember that daemon from the time when I had FreeBSD on my machine at home instead of Linux (somewhere in the 90s). You might remember that name from the <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/#the-story-is-more-important-than-the-technology">Creativity Inc.</a> book (the one about Pixar!) notes post on this blog</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-18">Thursday 2024-01-18</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>AlphaGeometry from Google DeepMind is great work</strong> combining a symbolic math engine with a language model to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. See below for my breathless tweet. (twitter is still the uncontested ML firehose)</li>
<li>News on our in-house GPT-wrapper front:
<ul>
<li>Discovered that I now have to upgrade to the new <code>tool_call</code> api as the old <code>functions</code> one has been deprecated. Made use of the opportunity to improve our implementation of the supplied OpenAI type annotations</li>
<li>Note to self, and to you: The <code>*Params</code> types are <code>TypedDict</code> declarations which you can use to work directly with JSON requests and responses, while the non-<code>*Params</code> types are pydantic models which you can use to (de)serialize JSON.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Went to see a really good <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mohs-surgery/about/pac-20385222">Mohs surgery</a> dermatologist who will soon be removing my basal cell carcinomas. As always, AMA in the comments or via email.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is such fantastic work! Symbolic engine + language model working together to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. Also, beautiful illustrations in the paper and posts. <a href="https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7">https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1747857845356298739?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 18, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-19">Friday 2024-01-19</h2>
<ul>
<li>Spent most of my working hours wrappng up and deploying the brand new version of our internal GPT. I read somewhere that you should <em>always</em> deploy on a Friday, as late as possible.</li>
<li>I was stressing quite a bit, as I had a great task before me:</li>
<li>Braaiing 200 boeries in the 39 degrees Celsius heat at the school in Stellenbosch, in order to feed the new grade 8 learners on the evening of their initiation.
<ul>
<li>All thanks to the fellow dad who joined me, the stress transformed completely into an enjoyable few hours taking care of this important duty, and I made a new friend!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The kids, including our very own GOU#2, were facing the challenging night before them&hellip;</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-20">Saturday 2024-01-20</h2>
<ul>
<li>woke up at 5:40 because was planning to fetch GOU#1 and GOU#2 after their eventful and successful night, but thankfully partner was willing to go!</li>
<li>me very tired the whole day, just hanging (literally) around with family, and spending too much time on twitter / threads / reddit / inoreader! (brain was not willing to do much else, at least learned new things, some of which are mentioned below)</li>
<li>Based on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39055139">this HN discussion</a> about <a href="https://delta.io/blog/delta-lake-vs-parquet-comparison/">this blog post comparing Delta Lake and Parquet</a>, learned that Delta Parquet aka Delta Tables (which I&rsquo;ve read about in the context of Azure) is just a bunch of parquet files with some json metadata!
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve been enjoying <a href="https://parquet.apache.org/">parquet</a> for years now, in the context of scipy and specifically pandas.</li>
<li>Indeed, OneLake, also part of Microsoft Fabric, has Delta Parquet at its core.</li>
<li>Apache Iceberg is a similar but more open source implemenation: <a href="https://iceberg.apache.org/">https://iceberg.apache.org/</a></li>
<li>Based on <a href="https://www.dremio.com/blog/exploring-the-architecture-of-apache-iceberg-delta-lake-and-apache-hudi/">this comparison between Iceberg, Delta Lake and Hudi</a> it looks like all of these data lake storage layers are just parquet files with metadata, and then some logic, to give database like semantics over distributed object stores. Neat!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In bed last night, falling asleep, I had the following idea:
<ul>
<li><em>My Current Life Canvas</em> is a 3D bubble (off to my right for some reason&hellip; and moving with me as I walk) the interior of which I can view using my phone via AR (have to move phone in space to view inside of bubble, with current topics arranged in familiar spots; I thought having a world map would help, because well-known and memorable locations for your topics / priorities / ideas) or any of these amazing new VR headsets, BUT you can also interact with it via computer because inside of bubble can just be projected to surface using any of the well-known <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Map_projection">map projection techniques</a>.</li>
<li>CLC does not have a regular cadence like the daily or weekly plan, but is revised or redone a few times per year. It focuses on your major life priorities at any one point in time.</li>
<li>Although this was just a dreamy idea, I do like that it offers multi-modal interaction on the spectrum from AR/VR to more conventional desktop paradigms</li>
<li>&hellip; of course there should be some kind of friendly AI floating in the bubble with you :P (Microsoft Bob?)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-21">Sunday 2024-01-21</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super enjoyable weekend long(ish) run.</li>
<li>Tried out Omnivore&rsquo;s PDF annotation support, see screenshot below. Pretty impressive, and very cool that the highlights sync into my Emacs-based notes setup via markdown. Have slightly mixed feelings, because now will have to come up with new rule for when a paper goes into Zotero (fully local, full citations, but no automatic highlights sync) and when it goes into Omnivore (good sort of cloud but not local, no full citations, automatic sync into my notes)</li>
<li>Extended family Sunday lunch at our place was great, but me not at normal energy levels yet.</li>
<li>One of my goals for this week was &ldquo;Get through the week, especially Friday braai&rdquo;. Mission successful!</li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_8552fa2e79f0c31.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_d562277b8133fec1.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_70c21750f4c22771.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_3fd7290a1dd605.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_d562277b8133fec1.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 2 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/15/daily-head-voices-2024-01-08_14/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 22:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/15/daily-head-voices-2024-01-08_14/</guid><description>Inspired by the impressive power (and philosophy) of One Punch Man&amp;rsquo;s Consecutive Normal Punches, I present: A Series of Consecutive Normal Daily Head Voices!
Monday 2024-01-08 First day back at work 😱 &amp;hellip; but the most lovely lunch run (not literally) and chat with colleague E. Single cable life at work is there, but it&amp;rsquo;s complicated: Thunderbolt3 cable from macbook to Thinkpad dock, dock thunderbolt3 to displayport-mini (adapter), displayport-mini to displayport to monitor. Had blood drawn for my quarterly PSA test. (prostate-specific antigen; regular test to check that prostate cancer stays gone) Double Commander (currently at 1.1.8) on macOS is even better than I remember it, and is only a brew install --cask double-commander away. Tuesday 2024-01-09 marimo looks really good! From the github: a reactive notebook for Python. It allows you to rapidly experiment with data and models, code with confidence in your notebook&amp;rsquo;s correctness, and productionize notebooks as pipelines or interactive web apps. I still have to play with it, but it sounds like an Observable for Python. Wednesday 2024-01-10 Shorter weekday run because hip and because sun. Hip only started complaining by the end, a little later than my last short run. 🎉 Tried to find reclining high-back office chairs with footrest in South Africa, starting from: https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/ Spectacular failure! Google Bard, Bing Chat, Perplexity come up with plausible looking links that go to different sites, but nowhere any chairs to be found perplexity is probably the least bad because it more often admits to just not finding any links in SA See e.g. https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c and https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5 Because of work, started to spend some quality time with d3.js again. I hope to be doing some nice interactive visualization soon! Thursday 2024-01-11 PSA is 0.006! 🥳 if you&amp;rsquo;ve ever worked with d3.js, you will have used bl.ocks.org quite often. To my surprise, none of these links work anymore, and instead redirect you to the source gist, where they used to show you the live visualization. I could not find much official news about this sunsetting, but was consoled by the discovery of the open source bl.ocks.org clone at https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/ via https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513 Tune of the evening: RÜFÜS DU SOL - On My Knees (Adriatique Remix) Friday 2024-01-12 Short week-day run, no hip issues! Very nice focused day at home: First half wrapping up a code review. Second half diving back into d3.js. So much old memories I have to unearth. In between hacked in an idle mode for org-roam-similarity, in the process discovered that on this M1 Pro, CPU is much faster (2x) and uses much less RAM than the hardware accelerated PyTorch MPS version Lovely weekend-starter braai with family. Ran into the final sections (and private comments the source org file) of WHV #208 &amp;ndash; besides the nostalgic music bits, really enjoyed reading some of the older journals. Publish or not, strong motivation to keep on writing journals. (now-you is often a very different person than then-you. interesting to keep in touch!) Saturday 2024-01-13 one of the highlights of the day was phone-call by and substantial conversation with bestie PK rest of day quite laid-back with the whole family, which was great thinking a lot about stefanv&amp;rsquo;s week planner instead of day planner, and the implications of this seemingly reduced planning effort (my daily planning is mostly only theoretical) greater family braai (GFB) Sunday 2024-01-14 Overslept a bit, woke up at 9 AM. This has not happened in ages. Slightly longer weekend run at 10 with new running hat and SPF50 on me face and neck. Hip issue did not manifest, am touching wood! Because I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about more visual ways to plan my week, worked on org-roam-canvas, making it a whole lot faster.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Inspired by the impressive power (and philosophy) of One Punch Man&rsquo;s <em>Consecutive Normal Punches</em>, I present: A Series of Consecutive Normal Daily Head Voices!</p>
<h2 id="monday-2024-01-08">Monday 2024-01-08</h2>
<ul>
<li>First day back at work 😱</li>
<li>&hellip; but the most lovely lunch run (not literally) and chat with colleague E.</li>
<li>Single cable life at work is there, but it&rsquo;s complicated: Thunderbolt3 cable from macbook to Thinkpad dock, dock thunderbolt3 to displayport-mini (adapter), displayport-mini to displayport to monitor.</li>
<li>Had blood drawn for my quarterly PSA test. (prostate-specific antigen; regular test to check that prostate cancer stays gone)</li>
<li>Double Commander (currently at 1.1.8) on macOS is even better than I remember it, and is only a <code>brew install --cask double-commander</code> away.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-09">Tuesday 2024-01-09</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/marimo-team/marimo">marimo</a> looks really good! From the github: <em>a reactive notebook for Python. It allows you to rapidly experiment with data and models, code with confidence in your notebook&rsquo;s correctness, and productionize notebooks as pipelines or interactive web apps</em>. I still have to play with it, but it sounds like an <a href="https://observablehq.com/">Observable</a> for Python.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-10">Wednesday 2024-01-10</h2>
<ul>
<li>Shorter weekday run because hip and because sun. Hip only started complaining by the end, a little later than my last short run. 🎉</li>
<li>Tried to find reclining high-back office chairs with footrest in South Africa, starting from: <a href="https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/">https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/</a>
<ul>
<li>Spectacular failure! Google Bard, Bing Chat, Perplexity come up with plausible looking links that go to different sites, but nowhere any chairs to be found</li>
<li>perplexity is probably the least bad because it more often admits to just not finding any links in SA</li>
<li>See e.g. <a href="https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c">https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c</a> and <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5">https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Because of work, started to spend some quality time with <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a> again. I hope to be doing some nice interactive visualization soon!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-11">Thursday 2024-01-11</h2>
<ul>
<li>PSA is 0.006! 🥳</li>
<li>if you&rsquo;ve ever worked with d3.js, you will have used bl.ocks.org quite often. To my surprise, none of these links work anymore, and instead redirect you to the source gist, where they used to show you the live visualization. I could not find much official news about this sunsetting, but was consoled by the discovery of the open source bl.ocks.org clone at <a href="https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/">https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/</a> via <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513">https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513</a></li>
<li>Tune of the evening: <a href="https://youtu.be/IAmmkJZ55vM?si=WjEjD8MLge7sCo0E">RÜFÜS DU SOL - On My Knees (Adriatique Remix)</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-12">Friday 2024-01-12</h2>
<ul>
<li>Short week-day run, no hip issues!</li>
<li>Very nice focused day at home: First half wrapping up a code review. Second half diving back into d3.js. So much old memories I have to unearth.</li>
<li>In between hacked in an idle mode for <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity">org-roam-similarity</a>, in the process discovered that on this M1 Pro, CPU is much faster (2x) and uses much less RAM than the hardware accelerated PyTorch MPS version</li>
<li>Lovely weekend-starter braai with family.</li>
<li>Ran into the final sections (and private comments the source org file) of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/#thank-you-joris">WHV #208</a> &ndash; besides the nostalgic music bits, really enjoyed reading some of the older journals. Publish or not, strong motivation to keep on writing journals. (now-you is often a very different person than then-you. interesting to keep in touch!)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-13">Saturday 2024-01-13</h2>
<ul>
<li>one of the highlights of the day was phone-call by and substantial conversation with bestie PK</li>
<li>rest of day quite laid-back with the whole family, which was great</li>
<li>thinking a lot about stefanv&rsquo;s week planner instead of day planner, and the implications of this <em>seemingly</em> reduced planning effort (my daily planning is mostly only theoretical)</li>
<li>greater family braai (GFB)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-14">Sunday 2024-01-14</h2>
<ul>
<li>Overslept a bit, woke up at 9 AM. This has not happened in ages.</li>
<li>Slightly longer weekend run at 10 with new running hat and SPF50 on me face and neck. Hip issue did not manifest, am touching wood!</li>
<li>Because I&rsquo;ve been thinking about more visual ways to plan my week, worked on <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">org-roam-canvas</a>, making it a <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas/commit/a67ad1ee59c93a2998a0c2975ed7d567e7f02c8d">whole lot faster</a>.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Sunday 2024-01-07</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:48:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-07/</guid><description> Last day of my vacation. 🥹 Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder than rest in the &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; periods instead. The assault bike saddles are garbarge. Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me. Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me. &amp;hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so. After getting wlziipsrv built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&amp;hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (bug in macOS 17.2) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS! Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 and GOU#2 ❤️</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Last day of my vacation. 🥹</li>
<li>Accompanied GOU#1 to the gym so that I could test out their assault bikes
<ul>
<li>Did a 42 minute interval-ish workout on the thing. Can get heart-rate up and keep it there quite easily. Intervals do feel quite harsh, and so I spent more time just pedalling harder  than rest in the &ldquo;rest&rdquo; periods instead.
<ul>
<li>The assault bike saddles are garbarge.</li>
<li>Will probably go back for another airbike session or two to see if / how much it grows on me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent the last 30 minutes quite enjoyably running on a &ldquo;normal&rdquo; treadmill after failing to get the motorless (self-powered) treadmill under control. It was either going to fast or too slow for me.
<ul>
<li>&hellip; hip niggle started to make an appearance by the end, but only subtly so.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>After getting <code>wlziipsrv</code> built as part of an arm64 docker image, decided to cancel the project (for now&hellip;) of porting all of my websites (static, wordpress, more stuff) from the Hetzner CX21 (2 Intel vCores, 4GB RAM, 40GB + 50GB extra) to the CAX21 (4 ARM64 cores, 8GB RAM, 80GB disk) as a neatly dockerized configuration. I pushed my image to dockerhub in case someone else finds its useful: <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv">https://hub.docker.com/r/cpbotha/supervisor-wlziipsrv</a></li>
<li>Discovered that karabiner, a tool I used in the past to work around JetBrains shortcuts getting confused with Dvorak, fixes both of my current § vs ` (and ~) button swapping (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MacOS/comments/18g4vxn/cannot_remap_keys_on_macbook_pro_with_hidutils_in/">bug in macOS 17.2</a>) and non-working-ctrl-in-rdp-to-windows issues on macOS!</li>
<li>Sublime post-dinner sunset walk with GOU#1 <em>and</em> GOU#2 ❤️</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Saturday 2024-01-06</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-06/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 22:47:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/07/daily-head-voices-2024-01-06/</guid><description> Researching assault-style airbikes as an alternative cardio modality, for when I would like a workout that&amp;rsquo;s not running (for when my joints need some rest) and that&amp;rsquo;s not in the sun so much An assault-style airbike uses a big fan as the front wheel, and engages your arms and upper body as well. Seems to be an important staple in the crossfit world. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if I&amp;rsquo;m the right person for it, but it sure looks convincing! Here&amp;rsquo;s a not-too-crazy beginner cardio workout example on youtube: https://youtu.be/6OMfabFyVFI?si=SId44AGsPX9U2YZJ Really special braai with a group of besties, hosted by SnR. According to the highly scientific DHV-scale, the evening has been classified as &amp;ldquo;life-affirming&amp;rdquo; and also &amp;ldquo;the absolute best possible way to spend those hours&amp;rdquo;. So much thank you!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Researching assault-style airbikes as an alternative cardio modality, for when I would like a workout that&rsquo;s not running (for when my joints need some rest) and that&rsquo;s not in the sun so much
<ul>
<li>An assault-style airbike uses a big fan as the front wheel, and engages your arms and upper body as well. Seems to be an important staple in the crossfit world. I&rsquo;m not sure if I&rsquo;m the right person for it, but it sure looks convincing!</li>
<li>Here&rsquo;s a not-too-crazy beginner cardio workout example on youtube: <a href="https://youtu.be/6OMfabFyVFI?si=SId44AGsPX9U2YZJ">https://youtu.be/6OMfabFyVFI?si=SId44AGsPX9U2YZJ</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Really special braai with a group of besties, hosted by SnR. According to the highly scientific DHV-scale, the evening has been classified as &ldquo;life-affirming&rdquo; and also &ldquo;the absolute best possible way to spend those hours&rdquo;. So much thank you!</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>