<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Mindfulness on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/mindfulness/</link><description>Recent content in Mindfulness on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/mindfulness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2024 to 2025 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 20:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to the year 2025!
We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&amp;rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this traditional yearly transition blog post here to keep you busy in the meantime.
The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2025!</p>
<p>We are all still waiting for our flying cars, but if you don&rsquo;t like the indistinguishable-from-human talking AIs you got instead, you can have this <a href="/tags/transition">traditional yearly transition blog post</a> here to keep you busy in the meantime.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20241228-st-francis-light-house.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a7c8fad0a4fb3336.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_c471bba5b301f4e3.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_7e36ecc6dd88d868.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20241228-st-francis-light-house_hu_a8fd52cf169879c1.webp"
            

        
            alt="The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Seal Point Lighthouse in Cape St. Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For those of you who are new here, 1) welcome! and 2) the traditional yearly transition post is where I both ramble semi-coherently on about the year that is closest to its conclusion and also speculate a bit about the year that is closest to its inception.</p>
<p>The main audience for this post is me &ndash; writing this up and the concomitant thinking and formulating bits form an important part of my maintenance process &ndash; but to anyone else who is reading this, there is hopefully something of value (or just a bit of entertainment) for you in these words. In any case, I am super happy that you&rsquo;re here!</p>
<h2 id="life-events">Life events</h2>
<p>In 2024, <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#i-turned-50">I turned 50</a> while <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#gou-1-turned-18">GOU#1 turned 18</a>, finished high school and is now on her way to university.</p>
<p>I mention these two in the same breath, because looking back it feels like the 5 years of her high school, a substantial chunk of time in terms of her development, went by in a flash.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s almost like we blinked <a href="/2019/12/08/weekly-head-voices-185-starship-gou-1/#starship-gou-1-taxiing-on-the-runway">when she was still our little girl going to high school</a> and now suddenly she is an adult, and we finally feel like actual adults (aka old people) ourselves.</p>
<p>Although these have been amazing years for us, this experience of a whole period of life flashing by, through the lense of our children&rsquo;s development into adults, is a stark reminder to strive even harder to experience the living daylights out of every single moment that we are blessed with.</p>
<p>If all goes according to plan, we will have two more blink-blink-another-high-school-journey-is-complete experiences (GOU#2 is now in her second year of that journey, GOU#3 has a few years to go before she can start) so we should probably try to blink far less often.</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>After the dip both this blog and I went through in 2023 (total of 3 WHV posts&hellip;) and a very slow blogging start in 2024, it does feel like I might slowly be getting my WHV groove back, which seems to be evidenced by 66% more WHV posting in 2024, i.e. a whole 5 WHV posts! (Contrast this with the historic average of one post every two weeks.)</p>
<p>In the introduction to <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/">WHV #255 You lift me up</a> I speculate a bit about the reasons for my hiatus (I didn&rsquo;t mention there that maybe 2023 was actually just a real downer for me) and the current potential revival.</p>
<p>In addition to the posts here, I published <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">12 technical posts over on at the vxlabs</a> and a whole bunch of short howtos / recipes in the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">brand new TiL section of my other-OTHER website</a>. WHV #255 <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">explains the motivation behind the TiL section</a>.</p>
<p>I am also quite happy about the fact that I wrote a daily entry in my private diary for a large part of 2024, and this is something that I would like to continue, hopefully for an even larger part of 2025.</p>
<p>Spending some time every day to review that day, where the review is enriched by the deliberate activitity of trying to formulate everything into a story that I can write down, helps me to make sense of everything.</p>
<p>Writing in general seems to modulate positively my experience of reality.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a lot about this idea in various posts on this blog, but allow me to surface <a href="/2019/10/07/weekly-head-voices-180-ensembleyou-and-the-describers/#the-describers">two relevant sections from WHV 180</a>, and especially the quote below (but you should go read those two sections):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Writing is the multi-purpose thread that runs backwards and forwards through time to connect the various different versions of me into a slightly less faulty entity.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>My secret running goal for 2024 was to do 25km of running every week. In my head this was auto-simplified to 1200km for the year (you know, the way one often calculates a month as 4 weeks), but of course we&rsquo;re talking 1300km.</p>
<p>Well, I failed at all of these goals!</p>
<p>However, I did manage to run a total of 1149.7km over the year, which comes to an average of 22.1km per week, which I am pretty OK with. I had over 100 hours of fun (I truly enjoy running) and no injuries that I can remember.</p>
<p>The training calendar below shows that August was my laziest month, but that&rsquo;s because August has the worst weather, and because I was away for a week visiting my Dutch family and getting many tens of thousands of dancing steps instead. The calendar also shows how I made a last ditch effort in December to close the gap with my goal as much as possible.</p>










<figure><a href="20250101-strava-training-calendar.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_e13adc1c4101c63a.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_2caa5fcc1a219359.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_57229ed99a10234e.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/20250101-strava-training-calendar_hu_9e69575ede352940.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You might remember <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">my three metrics-focused goals from last year&rsquo;s post</a>, namely 50 consecutive push-ups, VO<sub>2</sub> Max of at least 50 and a resting state heart rate of 50 or under&hellip;</p>
<p>Well, 50 consecutive push-ups was not that hard, Apple Health reports my average resting state heart rate for 2024 as 48 BPM (this would be mostly via my Garmin Forerunner 245 and more recently 265) but my VO<sub>2</sub> briefly peaked at 49 (some time after I turned 50) before settling back on 48. I  would have loved that 50, but <a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/blog/fitness/whats-a-good-vo2-max-for-me/">48 is not the worst for a man of my age</a>.</p>
<p>My real goal for the coming year is the same as last year: I want to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>The older I get and the more I learn, the more I understand that with exercise, the more hours I can spend every week doing it, of course maintaining balance with the rest of my life (see life systems further down), the better my meat-coated skeleton will work, and the happier the ghost driving it will be.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’re a ghost driving a meat-coated skeleton made from stardust; what do you have to be scared of?</p>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2022/10/13/ghost-stardust/">@rat_sandwich on twitter, January 31, 2013</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>P.S. of course I will again go for 25km of running per week. I think logging substantially more than 120 hours of activities in Strava will be good. I might even give that VO<sub>2</sub> Max goal another shot.</p>
<p>P.P.S. I read <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/outlive/">Peter Attia&rsquo;s book Outlive</a> a few months ago. This is a detailed and practical manual for healthy living. There&rsquo;s a lot in there, but at the core he wants you, while you still have any say in the matter, to become as fit (measured by our friend VO<sub>2</sub> Max) and as strong (measured by grip strength) as you possibly can. You see, from middle age we&rsquo;re all on a downward curve, and there&rsquo;s not much we can do about it, except ensuring that we start as high as possible.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. It&rsquo;s funny; back in school, I thought little of athleticism, because it was a jock thing, and the jocks were generally not very kind to nerd-kind (my people). Now that I&rsquo;m older and quite ironically due to my nerdy lifelong learning habits, I strive for us much athleticism as I can &ldquo;fit&rdquo; in (jock joke harr harr).</p>
<h3 id="diet">Diet</h3>
<p>During this post&rsquo;s generously long incubation, I thought it worth adding here my approach to eating.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been practising 16-8 time-restricted eating (intermittent fasting in some circles) about 95% of the time since somewhere in 2019. I first <a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">wrote about it in WHV 186</a>, and then in <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#i-really-don-t-like-breakfast">WHV 221 I came out and stated the beef I have with breakfast</a> (that pun might be too heavy for this post).</p>
<p>Anyways, while I still believe that breakfast is bad for most people, I know that the scientific world has not yet reached consensus on time-restricted eating for healthy folks.</p>
<p>However, there is considerably more consensus that lowering daily caloric intake is good for most people.</p>
<p>For me, 16-8 TRE, where I simply don&rsquo;t ingest anything besides water and black coffee from about 7 in the evening until about noon the next day, is an extremely practical and especially low-effort way to reduce caloric intake.</p>
<p>When I do eat, the portions are modest, I try to stick to natural and unprocessed where I can and I keep an eye on protein.</p>
<p>When I do break these rules, I do so with deliberation. Great food, great wine, great beer and the company of friends and family, especially when combined, constitute a perfect reason to break all of these rules.</p>
<p>In short, reduce caloric intake, increase per-calorie value and/or enjoyment!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and Tools</h2>
<p>This is the place where I summarise (read: ramble on about) the current state of my digital tools and systems. If you&rsquo;re going to skip a (nerdy) section, this is the one! You can dive back in at <a href="#life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</a>.</p>
<p>I am one of those people who <em>regularly</em> finds and uses information from notes that I made.</p>
<p>If I have the note, and I often do because I make an effort to write stuff down with the lowest possible friction but the highest possible chance of being found again, this is generally miles faster than finding the information online, even with tools like the <a href="https://kagi.com/">premium search engine Kagi</a> which I have been using regularly for a few weeks now.</p>
<h3 id="emacs-and-obsidian">Emacs and Obsidian</h3>
<p>A year ago I <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#systems-and-tools">experienced a bit of a crisis of (Emacs) faith</a>.</p>
<p>Whilst that was more of a clash between the either-or poles of Emacs and Obsidian, I am now at a place where I&rsquo;m finding increasing uses for Obisidian as an <em>additional</em> note-taking tool, working on the same collection of hundreds of org-mode and a growing number of markdown files.</p>
<p>Emacs and org-roam treat <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">markdown files as if they are native org-roam nodes</a>. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/BBazard/obsidian-orgmode-cm6">Benoit Bazard&rsquo;s fantastic new CodeMirror 6 org-mode plugin for Obsidian</a> and my <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Monitor-rclone-cron-job-with-Home-Assistant">rclone + syncthing syncing setup for iPhone</a>, I have semi-usable org database support on my phone.</p>
<p><a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> and since recently <a href="https://orgro.org/">Orgro</a> are great for editing org files in the iPhone, but they are missing the searching and discovery, let&rsquo;s call it <em>note management</em>, aspects of a tool like Obsidian.</p>
<p>Long but quite important-to-me story short, it looks like for the time being I&rsquo;ll continue to use both Emacs and Obsidian for note-taking. Because interoperability is not perfect, there will be some natural gravitational pull towards the one or the other which I have decided to explore.</p>
<p>At the moment, it looks like I might be writing more of my atomic notes as markdown files, whilst using org for the lab journal / logbook and project management type of notes.</p>
<p>On a deeper note, the Obsidian team is doing fantastic work.</p>
<p>Apart from their <a href="https://stephango.com/file-over-app"><em>file over app</em> philosophy</a>, Obsidian is <em>programmable</em> as can be witnessed by the thriving extension ecosystem.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve also <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins?id=ai-chat-as-md">written a modest extension</a> to test this out from the inside. The programmability is not as extensive as that of Emacs, but it runs everywhere, even on mobile devices, and it might be extensive enough for the note-taking platform that Obsidian has become.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been using Emacs on and off since the late 90s, but for the past 10 years it has become an always-running and integral part of my life. It feels really strange, disconcerting if I&rsquo;m being honest, that it seems to be losing its core spot.</p>
<p>I console myself in these moments with the observation that science must trump dogma, always.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;m writing this post in Emacs.</p>
<h4 id="til">TiL</h4>
<p>Thanks to Obsidian, my other, OTHER website <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#there-is-a-til-section-on-my-other-website">now has a &ldquo;today I learned&rdquo; (TIL) section</a> at <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/">charlbotha.com/til</a>, published directly from a sub-directory of my main notes directory.</p>
<p>The benefit is that there is even less friction than usual and, perhaps more importantly, the psychological friction has also been reduced because I have convinced myself that the posts there are just notes and not true blog posts.</p>
<h3 id="honorable-tool-mentions-zotero-and-quarto">Honorable tool mentions: Zotero and Quarto</h3>
<p>After <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#omnivore-is-no-more">my distastrous recommendation of Omnivore turned into a disaster</a>, it is with some emotional trepidation but intellectual confidence (thanks to file over app and its staunchly open source nature) that I can re-recommend Zotero as a reference (of all kinds!) management tool for the long term.</p>
<p>After I last mentioned it on my blog, I have been using it quite intensively, and <a href="https://bsky.app/hashtag/zotero?author=charlbotha.com">I keep on running into delightful features</a>, like the built-in PDF reader&rsquo;s pop-up visualization of citations and image references.</p>
<p>A more recent but high power entry into my toolbelt is <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, which I will contend strikes a fantastic usability-power balance in the world of technical document and presentation authoring. I&rsquo;ve now used it, in anger, to write a fairly extensive technical document, along with the afore-mentioned Zotero and <a href="https://retorque.re/zotero-better-bibtex/">Better BibTeX</a> for reference management, and the experience was magically smooth. To seal the deal, by the end I used Quarto to generate an attractive-looking docx for interoperability with the other stakeholders, but my contact time with Word was mercifully minimised.</p>
<h3 id="my-micro-blogging-history-2008---2025">My micro-blogging history 2008 - 2025</h3>
<p>Twitter says I created my account there in December of 2008. However, <a href="/2009/04/04/when-the-going-gets-tough/">this blog here says I only started using it in April of 2009</a>. (Twitter first launched in July of 2006.)</p>
<p>Some years later in 2016, coincidentally right before the previous Trumpocalypse, I wrote a post naively suggesting that we should <a href="/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/">replace twitter with something better (blogs&hellip;)</a> due to the risk of Twitter possibly going bad (ahem) and to the observation then that it was (then already) doing a crappy job keeping out abusive users (AHEM).</p>
<p>That post <a href="/2016/11/20/look-mom-hacker-news-front-page/">reached the front page of Hacker News</a>, and was thus read and discussed over there (and probably in the comments here) by tens of thousands of nerds, and a surprisingly small share of the usual &ldquo;Ackchyually&rdquo;-Bros.</p>
<p>(Please allow me this little tangent: A mental model that will really ease your time on sites like HN and reddit, is that the person on the other side, especially when they come across as super confident and assertive, is probably <strong>not</strong> an expert, not even by a long shot, on the topic that they are so confidently mansplaining. In fact, they are probably the least qualified to say anything. ChatGPT avant le lettre one might say. Ok back to your regular programming&hellip;)</p>
<p>Needless to say, my specific idea of replacing twitter with&hellip; blogs and rss was not implemented by the internet, at least not at that point&hellip;</p>
<p>When Musk acquired Twitter in October of 2022, the writing started appearing on the wall, at first vaguely, but with more and more definition as the months went on. I started looking for micro-blogging alternatives that were not twitter.</p>
<p>At first Mastodon looked too complicated, but then someone setup a <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#emacs-mastodon-server-was-irresistible">mastodon server dedicated to Emacs and I was immediately sold</a>.</p>
<p>However, Mastodon indeed turned out to be too complex and fundamentally quite fragile (all but the larger instances have a just a volunteer human or two behind them), leading to the owner of my favourite instance bascially being harassed to such an extent that it was better for him to get out of this business and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@cpbotha/113340325817581254">shut the Emacs mastodon server down</a>.</p>
<p>When I saw this announcement, I was disheartened.</p>
<p>When I read that Mastodon supports message export, but not message import, meaning that my posts would languish in a sad archive file somewhere, I was convinced that I had to try something out that was not Mastodon.</p>
<p>In parallel to my Mastodon efforts, I did also try Threads and was quite enthusiastic about its scale, and the speed with which Meta managed to build it, but I didn&rsquo;t manage to get any sort of interaction there. I think that it might be more geared for the Instagram model of influencers broadcasting to large groups of followers, in contrast to a more collaborative setup. (Urgh, the recent news about Meta&rsquo;s new &ldquo;free speech&rdquo; overhaul is additional motivation for me to spend even less energy there.)</p>
<p>ANYWAYS, it turns out that the newer and shinier microblogging service Bluesky was conceived in 2019 with the goal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluesky">&ldquo;to find or develop an open and decentralized standard for social media that would give users more control over their data and experience&rdquo;</a>, precisely the sort of thing that has suddenly become even more painfully relevant with the advent of the Trumpocalypse part deux, now with more Musk-power.</p>
<p>Long story short, in a very short time, Bluesky has proven to be almost exactly the microblogging platform that I enjoy participating in. Lots of human interaction, no ads, many different user-contributed algorithms to choose from, including just seeing the stuff your people post, in the order that they post it &ndash; it really feels like the thing was put together with semi-normal human interaction as the central concern.</p>
<p>Up to now, it also feels like <a href="/2024/11/17/weekly-head-voices-255-you-lift-me-up/#bluesky-is-my-new-micro-blogging-thing-of-choice">many folks on there prefer being decent to each other</a>, something I militantly (haha) support.</p>
<p>Some mastodon folks are downright unhappy with bluesky, because they feel that it&rsquo;s not truly decentralized like mastodon.</p>
<p>Thing is, Bluesky has chosen a different spot on the usability - decentralization spectrum, and and my opinion is exactly usable and decentralised enough for what it needs to be and do at this moment in time.</p>
<p>Looking slightly further into the future, there are well-funded initiatives like <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/13/24342799/free-our-feeds-social-media-ecosystem-at-protocol-bluesky">Free our feeds</a>, ideologically and technologically supported by the Bluesky company but otherwise unconnected, which has amongst its <a href="https://freeourfeeds.com/">goals to &ldquo;build independently hosted infrastructure (a second &lsquo;relay&rsquo;) so that Bluesky users, developers and researchers always have full access to the stream of content and data no matter what the company decides to do in future&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>If you would like to know more, Faine Greenwood has written <a href="https://little-flying-robots.ghost.io/the-great-bluesky-migration-i-answer-some-of-your-questions/">this great Bluesky explainer</a>.</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2025">Life Systems 2025</h2>
<p>My Life Systems are the guiding principles, rules, personal values and bags of tips that I have explicitly defined and refined over the years to help me be the best human that I can be.</p>
<p>Note: I write these up primarily as a reminder to myself. If it comes across as prescriptive, please remember that I&rsquo;m telling <em>me</em> how to live my life. I can do this, because I <em>am</em> the boss of me.</p>
<h3 id="core">Core</h3>
<p>You&rsquo;ll be happy to hear that the core of my Life Systems 2025 is exactly the same as the previous edition <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">Life Systems 2024</a>, except for the version number increase, and the concomitant price increase. (taking a leaf here from the Intel playbook!)</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t want to read <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#life-systems-2024">the 2024 write-up</a>, here is the compressed version:</p>
<p><em>Guiding principles:</em> 1. Love 2. Science. <em>Two no three rules for achieving great success in life, or just surviving, whichever comes first:</em> 1. Be useful. 2. be likable and 3. evolve. <em>Personal values:</em> 1. Be kind. 2. Be grateful. 3. Attend fully to the now. 4. Enjoy life with family and with my friends. 5. Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers. 6. Be there for my family. 7. Add value through work. 8. Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise. 9. Build and/or fix something. 10. Learn new things. 11. Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</p>
<h3 id="balance">Balance</h3>
<p>What I have been thinking about this year, especially when things get quite busy, is the sometimes tricky practice of applying balance to one&rsquo;s personal values.</p>
<p>A straight-forward example is when important work obligations start impacting my sleep or exercise schedule, in which case I have to apply balance and tone down slightly the ambition to fulfil personal value no 7.</p>
<p>It can easily get more tricky however; when something on that list of personal values, which is important to you, starts taking up more than its fair share of energy, that will come at the cost of all of the other endeavours that you value.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have a hard and fast rule for this, only the measure of remembering to <em>pay attention</em> also at that meta-level so that one can make suitable balancing adjustments when required.</p>
<h3 id="work-hard-party-hard-rest-hard">Work hard. Party hard. Rest hard.</h3>
<p>A lesson that has only become clearer for me over the years is that we humans function best when we are able to focus on one thing at a time, and when we have as few things as possible on the list that we select from.</p>
<p>This works at all scales of life, from what task do I work on during this half-hour all the way up to my main priority for today, or my three main priorities for this year.</p>
<p>The challenge in applying this lesson is three-fold:</p>
<ol>
<li>Know which thing to focus on at any time,</li>
<li>reduce switching between things and yet</li>
<li>get to all of the things that you should get to.</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you have all three of these covered, then comes the truly difficult part: <strong>Attend fully to the now.</strong></p>
<p>Those of us who are lucky get about 4000 weeks of life.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not truly present in the thing that you&rsquo;ve chosen at this moment, you are not using that allotted time to its fullest extent.</p>
<p>You can never ever get that time back.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s like you&rsquo;re in a Michelin-starred restaurant, and instead of going power level 9000 with all of your senses and your thoughts and your whole being into <em>experiencing</em> that food with your favourite human(s), you&rsquo;re scrolling on your phone, absent-mindedly shovelling forkfuls into your mouth.</p>
<p>Do the opposite.</p>
<p>Pick your battles, but sometimes also choose a party if you can and don&rsquo;t forget to rest like your life depends on it. Whatever you do, be the most maximally present in the thing you&rsquo;ve chosen. Presence and attention improve with regular practice.</p>
<p>In short: Work hard, party hard, rest hard.</p>
<!-- be maximally present to use that time right; do everything HARD -- came during my 2025-01-11 morning run -->
<h2 id="my-2024-to-2025-transition-wishes">My 2024 to 2025 transition wishes</h2>
<p>Humans<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> <em>at their peak</em> are a thing of beauty.</p>
<p>Above all they are truly kind.  They live and breathe the knowledge that we <em>homo sapiens</em> are at our absolute best when we connect with each other.</p>
<p>Peak humans are graceful, and they are elegant, and they are in harmony &ndash; the best sort of balance &ndash; with their surroundings, with those around them and with themselves.</p>
<p>Attaining this peak is hard. Maintaining it is nigh impossible. Best we can go for is <a href="/2018/06/03/weekly-head-voices-144-eternal-learner/#mastery">the never-ending practice</a> of these characteristics, and an eternal striving for moments to <em>become them</em>.</p>
<p>Friends, I wish you and your connected ones the willpower to strive for grace and elegance and harmony, and the presence of mind to attend fully to those perfect moments when they occur.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>If you&rsquo;re reading this, you might be one of these&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 9 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/10/daily-head-voices-2024-week-9/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/10/daily-head-voices-2024-week-9/</guid><description>Monday 2024-02-26 started the morning (and the work week!) with stupid indecision: Had all my work gear in the car, but chose to drive back home after dropping of GOU#3 for a logistical task which one of my other clan members would gladly have taken care of. Indecision irrelevant against the backdrop: We had such a good time in the car first being on time (GOU#3 loves that), then listening to Skrillex together, then talking, and then performing our morning ritual of verbally attesting our super-infinite love for each other as I drop her off at school. During highly technical demo outside of my domains, used perplexity in real-time to lookup various details as the demo was going on, and thus could focus on the really interesting questions for the presenter. Between meetings, struggled a bit to focus in the focusy bits, but managed to do quite a bit of work eventually (with focusapp and some deep house) and even got milestones done. Tuesday 2024-02-27 Super frustrated during the morning rush, because could not find running shoes at the critical moment when we had to leave for school Reverted to backup shoes (old ones, with too many kilometres on them) Good run in L&amp;amp;Z, but it took so long to disconnect from my shoe moment, in spite of really putting my mind to it. Succeeded a little bit at the end, shocked at the mental cost of something this trivial. BTW, it was almost a textbook &amp;ldquo;not inside it&amp;rsquo;s on top!&amp;rdquo; situation. Wednesday 2024-02-28 For once some Waking Up in the morning! (I once had a streak of more than a year. Currently happy if I do just one!) Started the day in pensive mood (before and after the meditation) thinking about what I would like from the future Naturally I wanted to write a note, so then I tapped out a topic in the daily list so that I could use org-roam-node-find-similar to surface similar notes from the past. I did find the correct historic note which I would not have otherwise, but then I got sucked into emacs config&amp;hellip; why has my org-roam-node-find-* never done live preview like other consult commands? &amp;ndash; solved by installing https://github.com/jgru/consult-org-roam/tree/main and then tooting about it: https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/112008312753264000 During the day I was surprised at the amount of traction that toot got. It seems there are more people who missed this. It seems it can sometimes really help to share the minutiae. realised that org-roam-node-find-similar did not sort the similar nodes by similarity, so fixed that: https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity/commit/d940c12e70468adfbc1e41ef997c5f797540ebf7 After extricating myself back out of Emacs config yak shaving, I did spend some quality time writing up my thoughts, helping to clarify them. I don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer yet, but the direction I&amp;rsquo;m moving in feels good. Lunch with inner circle friend and mentor DMW at No Way Jose was great thank you! Thursday 2024-02-29 Run at shortly after 7. Legs did not really want to cooperate. Got distracted by meetings day at work, so almost no writing in the daily. Now, [2024-03-10 Sun 18:35], I&amp;rsquo;m really sorry. Friday 2024-03-01 Pool repair at my house. They are able to pump out all water, repair floor of pool, then pump all water back all in a few hours. I have two ideas for the weekend Build and publish a QRCode contact card generator using marimo and wasm build a telegram bot to manipulate my org-mode database, e.g. adding tasks, searching for existing tasks and notes. I don&amp;rsquo;t like this second idea, but it keeps on coming back to me. Saturday 2024-03-02 12km run with tired legs, so tired that I decided to stop the fast and get Powerade for the last 5km, which felt like it really helped. Super happy that I could get the promised marimo-wasm-qrcode generator online: https://vxlabs.com/2024/03/02/contact-qrcode-generator-with-marimo-and-wasm/ Sunday 2024-03-03 After sunday morning coffee and scrolling, dug into marimo to see if there&amp;rsquo;s some way to create the WASM locally. There does not seem to be. Scanned through https://core.telegram.org/bots to see (again&amp;hellip;) what might be possible. Actually, now I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about the idea of making a telegram bot that sends me random tasks from my org-mode every day. I already have a proof of concept in Python that uses emacsclient to expose org-roam nodes via API (see https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas ) so I would probably follow a similar path, probably with something like org-ql. Does anyone know if something like this exists somewhere? Apple&amp;rsquo;s Journal app, that suggests a new journalling possibility now and then, made me think that this could help. In iTerm2, press the Option-Cmd keys together to make a rectangular selection. Sublime lunch at Millhouse Kitchen with inner circle family Back home, tried to get MobileOrg going again; looked promising, but then after successful sync ran into this bug with empty outlines in the app when synced via iCloud. 😥 Configured perplexity via gptel in my Emacs; I am especially interested in using perplexity&amp;rsquo;s sonar-online internet-capable models.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-02-26">Monday 2024-02-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>started the morning (and the work week!) with stupid indecision: Had all my work gear in the car, but chose to drive back home after dropping of GOU#3 for a logistical task which one of my other clan members would gladly have taken care of.
<ul>
<li>Indecision irrelevant against the backdrop: We had such a good time in the car first being on time (GOU#3 loves that), then listening to Skrillex together, then talking, and then performing our morning ritual of verbally attesting our super-infinite love for each other as I drop her off at school.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>During highly technical demo outside of my domains, used perplexity in real-time to lookup various details as the demo was going on, and thus could focus on the really interesting questions for the presenter.</li>
<li>Between meetings, struggled a bit to focus in the focusy bits, but managed to do quite a bit of work eventually (with focusapp and some deep house) and even got milestones done.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-02-27">Tuesday 2024-02-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super frustrated during the morning rush, because could not find running shoes at the critical moment when we had to leave for school
<ul>
<li>Reverted to backup shoes (old ones, with too many kilometres on them)</li>
<li>Good run in L&amp;Z, but it took so  long to disconnect from my shoe moment, in spite of really putting my mind to it. Succeeded a little bit at the end, shocked at the mental cost of something this trivial.</li>
<li>BTW, it was almost a textbook &ldquo;not inside it&rsquo;s on top!&rdquo; situation.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-02-28">Wednesday 2024-02-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>For once some <a href="https://www.wakingup.com/">Waking Up</a> in the morning! (I once had a streak of more than a year. Currently happy if I do just one!)</li>
<li>Started the day in pensive mood (before and after the meditation) thinking about what I would like from the future
<ul>
<li>Naturally I wanted to write a note, so then I tapped out a topic in the daily list so that I could use <code>org-roam-node-find-similar</code> to surface similar notes from the past. I did find the correct historic note which I would not have otherwise, but then I got sucked into emacs config&hellip;
<ul>
<li>why has my <code>org-roam-node-find-*</code> never done live preview like other consult commands? &ndash; solved by installing <a href="https://github.com/jgru/consult-org-roam/tree/main">https://github.com/jgru/consult-org-roam/tree/main</a> and then tooting about it: <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/112008312753264000">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/112008312753264000</a>
<ul>
<li>During the day I was surprised at the amount of traction that toot got. It seems there are more people who missed this. It seems it can sometimes really help to share the minutiae.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>realised that <code>org-roam-node-find-similar</code> did not sort the similar nodes by similarity, so fixed that: <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity/commit/d940c12e70468adfbc1e41ef997c5f797540ebf7">https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity/commit/d940c12e70468adfbc1e41ef997c5f797540ebf7</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>After extricating myself back out of Emacs config yak shaving, I did spend some quality time writing up my thoughts, helping to clarify them.
<ul>
<li>I don&rsquo;t know the answer yet, but the direction I&rsquo;m moving in feels good.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lunch with inner circle friend and mentor DMW at No Way Jose was great thank you!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-02-29">Thursday 2024-02-29</h2>
<ul>
<li>Run at shortly after 7. Legs did not really want to cooperate.</li>
<li>Got distracted by meetings day at work, so almost no writing in the daily. Now, <span class="timestamp-wrapper"><span class="timestamp">[2024-03-10 Sun 18:35]</span></span>, I&rsquo;m really sorry.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-03-01">Friday 2024-03-01</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pool repair at my house. They are able to pump out all water, repair floor of pool, then pump all water back all in a few hours.</li>
<li>I have two ideas for the weekend
<ul>
<li>Build and publish a QRCode contact card generator using marimo and wasm</li>
<li>build a telegram bot to manipulate my org-mode database, e.g. adding tasks, searching for existing tasks and notes.
<ul>
<li>I don&rsquo;t like this second idea, but it keeps on coming back to me.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-03-02">Saturday 2024-03-02</h2>
<ul>
<li>12km run with tired legs, so tired that I decided to stop the fast and get Powerade for the last 5km, which felt like it really helped.</li>
<li>Super happy that I could get the promised marimo-wasm-qrcode generator online: <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/03/02/contact-qrcode-generator-with-marimo-and-wasm/">https://vxlabs.com/2024/03/02/contact-qrcode-generator-with-marimo-and-wasm/</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-03-03">Sunday 2024-03-03</h2>
<ul>
<li>After sunday morning coffee and scrolling, dug into marimo to see if there&rsquo;s some way to create the WASM locally. There does not seem to be.</li>
<li>Scanned through <a href="https://core.telegram.org/bots">https://core.telegram.org/bots</a> to see (again&hellip;) what might be possible.</li>
<li>Actually, now I&rsquo;m thinking about the idea of making a telegram bot that sends me random tasks from my org-mode every day. I already have a proof of concept in Python that uses emacsclient to expose org-roam nodes via API (see <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas</a> ) so I would probably follow a similar path, probably with something like org-ql. Does anyone know if something like this exists somewhere?
<ul>
<li>Apple&rsquo;s Journal app, that suggests a new journalling possibility now and then, made me think that this could help.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In iTerm2, press the Option-Cmd keys together to make a rectangular selection.</li>
<li>Sublime lunch at Millhouse Kitchen with inner circle family</li>
<li>Back home, tried to get MobileOrg going again; looked promising, but then after successful sync ran into <a href="https://github.com/MobileOrg/mobileorg/issues/292">this bug with empty outlines in the app when synced via iCloud</a>. 😥</li>
<li>Configured perplexity via gptel in my Emacs; I am especially interested in using perplexity&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/hub/blog/introducing-pplx-online-llms"><code>sonar-online</code> internet-capable models</a>.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 4 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-22 As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&amp;rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS! At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&amp;hellip; Short but really nice streamlit demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually played with it. Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3. In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola. Tuesday 2024-01-23 At the office nice and early (7:30). Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at react-flow and comfyui react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY! streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &amp;ldquo;things I learned&amp;rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document. Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&amp;rsquo;s a zero day vulnerability in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites. Wednesday 2024-01-24 8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW! Remember kids: Our spine&amp;rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally. This is also the reason why I&amp;rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair. Lovely working lunch with friend S at No Way José Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work: idea: make github so that people can pipx install marimo-turbo to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on. idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS &amp;hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844 (post is also embedded below) idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&amp;gt; nginx -&amp;gt; supervisord -&amp;gt; tornado systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation I would prefer to use supervisord for this This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick? ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &amp;ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&amp;rdquo; googling blog post: https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/ the kubernetes thing: https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&amp;rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via iframe.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-22">Monday 2024-01-22</h2>
<ul>
<li>As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &ldquo;When you&rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS!</li>
<li>At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&hellip;</li>
<li>Short but really nice <a href="https://streamlit.io/">streamlit</a> demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&rsquo;ve never actually played with it.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3.
<ul>
<li>In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-23">Tuesday 2024-01-23</h2>
<ul>
<li>At the office nice and early (7:30).</li>
<li>Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at <a href="https://reactflow.dev/">react-flow</a> and comfyui
<ul>
<li>react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see <a href="https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary">https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary</a>
<ul>
<li>it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster</li>
<li>marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &ldquo;things I learned&rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document.</li>
<li>Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&rsquo;s a <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/news/apple-issues-urgent-security-updates-to-fix-zero-day-flaw-update-your-iphone-and-mac-right-now">zero day vulnerability</a> in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-24">Wednesday 2024-01-24</h2>
<ul>
<li>8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot</li>
<li>dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work</li>
<li>right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW!
<ul>
<li>Remember kids: Our spine&rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally.</li>
<li>This is also the reason why I&rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lovely working lunch with friend S at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/NoWayJoseSomerset">No Way José</a></li>
<li>Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work:
<ul>
<li>idea: make github so that people can <code>pipx install marimo-turbo</code> to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on.</li>
<li>idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap
<ul>
<li>sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets</li>
<li>in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS
<ul>
<li>&hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844</a> (post is also embedded below)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&gt; nginx -&gt; supervisord -&gt; tornado
<ul>
<li>systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: <a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation">https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation</a></li>
<li>I would prefer to use supervisord for this</li>
<li>This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&rdquo; googling
<ul>
<li>blog post: <a href="https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/">https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/</a></li>
<li>the kubernetes thing: <a href="https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s">https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0" width="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><script src="https://emacs.ch/embed.js" async="async"></script>
<h3 id="til-mastodon-embeds-are-not-as-durable-as-twitter-embeds">TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds</h3>
<p>As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via <code>iframe</code>.</p>
<p>With twitter, you get more self-contained HTML which will render even when twitter or just the original tweet don&rsquo;t exist anymore.</p>
<p>This is probably just another reason to figure out how I can get more low-friction microblogging going on my own websites so that the embedding implementations of other microblogging sites become irrelevant.</p>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-25">Thursday 2024-01-25</h2>
<ul>
<li>Took a look at <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/connections/connect-networks/get-started/">cloudflare tunnels</a> to expose marimo and other dashboards to the internet
<ul>
<li>great that I can use my existing domains for this, and I can route between multiple domains to multiple locally running services</li>
<li>some more steps to setup, but it did not take more than about 5 minutes, and gives me even more options than tailscale funnels. OPTIONS MAN!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At work, quickly got react-flow&hellip; flowing. SHINY!</li>
<li>In the evening, found <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/">https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/</a> which is the new Shortcuts based way, based on the old AppleScript way, of getting a <code>message://</code> link onto the clipboard.
<ul>
<li>You <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#email-linking">might recall from this blog</a> that <code>message://</code> are the most durable and cross-platform way to link to emails from your notes (or anywhere else)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-26">Friday 2024-01-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up to cool, overcast weather, a big change from a series of 30℃ + days. Really had to resist going out for a run (normal run day + that amazing coolness), because of Wednesday&rsquo;s partially pulled back muscle not being 100% yet.</li>
<li>Worked on mystery visualization project (react-flow)</li>
<li>Lovely and energising lunch with previous colleague and friend. Happy that I reached out on Thursday although they have a packed schedule because only in country for limited time. I guess this is quite related to <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">calling up your friends</a>, with a ping of serendipity salt.</li>
<li>I was shocked by how well and fast <a href="https://ollama.ai/">ollama</a> worked on my MacBook. See embedded tweet below.</li>
<li>Almost at the end of the afternoon, friend S and I went to some more friends for the first Weiss-off, that is, a Weiss beer tasting contest. It was huge fun blind-tasting 10 different Weiss beers, ranking them, trying to identify them (so much harder than I thought!), and then having them revealed at the end.
<ul>
<li>Between the experts there (read: us), Stangen Weiss Bier came out on top, followed by Weisbier No5 and Jack Black Atlantic Weiss. The fourth place was shared by Erdinger and CBC Amber Weiss.</li>
<li>My favourite, Stellenbrau Jonkersweiss, is glaringly absent from the top. I&rsquo;ll live, probably consoled by just such a Jonkersweiss. Super happy that Amber Weiss and Atlantic are both present!</li>
<li>There was a trophy (for the taster who could blind-identify the most beers in the Weiss-off), which we have christened the <em>David Weisselhoff wisseltrofee</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">With <a href="https://twitter.com/MistralAI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@MistralAI</a>&#39;s Mistral 7B at Q4_0 on this MacBook M1 Pro 10C / 16C, <a href="https://twitter.com/ollama?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ollama</a> looks like it&#39;s easily 3 times faster than the new MLX 0.0.11 (with GGUF support).<br><br>It&#39;s subjectively (visually) faster, and the tokens/s measurements confirm this. <a href="https://t.co/9vyluimLKK">pic.twitter.com/9vyluimLKK</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1750824125419942036?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 26, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-27">Saturday 2024-01-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yesterday&rsquo;s Wonderful Weiss-off also had some, thankfully quite minor, effect the next morning, but I went out for a careful weekday distance run, which fortunately went without a hitch. Just very hot thanks.</li>
<li>Went to Buco and then to <a href="https://appletoolandgas.com/">Apple Tool and Gas</a> to find the rest of the screws I needed to repair the shower door. Friendly gentleman at Apple even sawed some of my screws to size! Shower door back in operation.</li>
<li>Updated my &ldquo;old&rdquo; M1 MBA to macOS 14.3 and then reset to transfer to GOU#1&rsquo;s iCloud. Say what you want about Apple, but that part of their stuff works <em>really</em> well.</li>
<li>Left for Betty&rsquo;s Bay at about 16:00 with GOUs #1 and #2. The rest of the family already there.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-28">Sunday 2024-01-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up in Betty&rsquo;s Bay after a longer than normal night of sleep, but Garmin body battery was still not completely happy.</li>
<li>In spite of having run yesterday and still feeling a bit tired (see body battery above), I had the best run of the month so far in Betty&rsquo;s. Go figure.</li>
<li>Spent some time with Canva &ndash; what a great resource for doing nice designs, even flow charts &ndash; but not sure where I could use this.</li>
<li>Background thought through the past weeks, and mentioned on Tuesday: I would really like to do (and promite) more TIL-style writing at work and at home. See <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/">Simon Willison&rsquo;s amazing TIL collection</a> for inspiration.</li>
<li>Ran into <a href="https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines">https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines</a> a Python library that can guarantee structured text generation from many LLMs, e.g. 100% valid JSON according to a specified schema. What makes it different from similar libraries? &ldquo;Unlike other libraries, regex-guided generation in Outlines is almost as fast as non-guided generation.&rdquo;</li>
<li>I already had <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/autogen">AutoGen</a> on my list for experimenting with multi-agent LLM applications, but now it has been joined by <a href="https://github.com/joaomdmoura/crewAI">crewAI</a> which I have also just ran into (thanks reddit!) and which seems to have significant support online.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2022 to 2023 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 16:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2023 everyone, and to the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis
I wish all of you all of the best for this shiny new year twenty-twenty-three!
(By the way, this, the first day of the year, is the earliest that the yearly transition post has ever appeared!)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2023 everyone, and to the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="20221220-cape-st-francis-walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_9aeb90d9d01a11e9.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_8678af152961e9a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_d62854548d79e21e.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_4e0ce1b965a24760.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/20221220-cape-st-francis-walk_hu_8678af152961e9a.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Scene from a recent windy family walk in Cape St Francis</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I wish all of you all of the best for this shiny new year twenty-twenty-three!</p>
<p>(By the way, this, the first day of the year, is the earliest that the
yearly transition post has ever appeared!)</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Over the past year, I published fifteen posts on this blog, 14 of which were
&ldquo;weekly&rdquo; head voices posts (#237 to #250), and one <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/">the 2022 transition post</a>.</p>
<p>In an ideal world where I get to divide up my time between family and friends,
blogging, running and Emacs, I might be able to get close to the mythical 52
WHVs per year.</p>
<p>However, for me 2022 was definitely The Year of a Whole Lot of Work.</p>
<p>You might remember <a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">WHV #239 Embarrassing finitude</a>, in which I observed that you
only get to choose a really small number (probably only two: family and
friends, and one additional project) of significant priorities that you can
effectively contribute to over any given stretch of time.</p>
<p>I mostly remember that I&rsquo;ve made peace with this limitation, and I am realising
that (good) Work might be a crucial and substantial component of a long and
good life.</p>
<h3 id="some-stats">Some stats</h3>
<p>Invoking the goaccess log analysis tool using the incantation below reports that
this site was visited by just over 126 thousand unique visitor IP numbers in
the year up to December 27.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#6639ba">export</span> <span style="color:#953800">DOMAIN</span><span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>cpbotha.net
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#0550ae">(</span><span style="color:#cf222e">for</span> i in <span style="color:#0550ae">{</span>1..11<span style="color:#0550ae">}</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">do</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> <span style="color:#953800">$DOMAIN</span>.access.log.<span style="color:#953800">$i</span>.gz<span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#cf222e">done</span><span style="color:#1f2328">;</span> <span style="color:#6639ba">echo</span> <span style="color:#953800">$DOMAIN</span>.access.log<span style="color:#0550ae">)</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> xargs zcat -f -- <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span> goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format<span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The most popular posts also over 2022 were the very old <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">2013 usa my data has
left your building</a>, the still quite relevant <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">2016 migrating from gmail to
fastmail</a> and my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">2019 note-taking strategy post</a>.</p>
<p>From this it&rsquo;s clear that I really have to get around to completing that
started-month-ago-but-languishing 202x note-taking strategy update, as my
system has evolved quite substantially.</p>
<p>I did also publish five posts on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>, this site&rsquo;s nerdy sibling, which
in its turn attracted just over 147 thousand unique visitor IPs over the year.</p>
<p>The most popular posts from vxlabs were the following, in descending order:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2022/06/12/typescript-development-with-emacs-tree-sitter-and-lsp-in-2022/">TypeScript development with Emacs, tree-sitter and LSP in 2022</a> - with
tree-sitter having been merged with Emacs core in the meantime, this post
also needs a substantial update. Emacs is developing faster than ever!</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/12/06/wsl2-io-measurements/">Comparing WSL1 and WSL2 filesystem I/O performance on local and host files</a> &ndash;
still reasonably accurate, still relevant.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/11/21/using-kubernetes-for-development-containers/">Using Kubernetes for development containers</a> - I&rsquo;m surprised that this is
relatively popular. I thought that it would be super niche.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="selected-learnings-from-2022">Selected learnings from 2022</h3>
<p>I went through all of 2022&rsquo;s WHVs to make an <em>extremely critical</em> (haha)
selection of learnings that bear mention in this yearly overview.</p>
<p>Because I think all of them are worthy of a retrospection, they are
chronologically ordered.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237 Don&rsquo;t step over the thing</a> &ndash; <em>We’re constantly stepping over the thing that
we think we’re seeking in the act of seeking it.</em> &hellip; <em>You can’t actually
become happy. You can only be happy.</em>
<ul>
<li>Related: <a href="/2022/11/01/weekly-head-voices-247-precious-moments/#take-a-picture-with-your-mind">WHV #247 Take a picture with your mind</a> &ndash; Your narrating self, the
one that needs to take all of those photos, can also take you out of the
thing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/#the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">WHV #239 Embarrassing finitude</a> &ndash; I&rsquo;m going to summarise that post section
here with &ldquo;pick your battles&rdquo;, or for the more poetically inclined readers
&ldquo;choose your f*cks&rdquo;. Our time is extremely limited - it is best to make
extremely deliberate and economical choices about the things that we spend
our time and energy on at any point.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/">WHV #242 Multiplicity of me</a> &ndash; If you skip everything else, read this
one. It&rsquo;s like &ldquo;happiness for dummies, in 24 hours&rdquo;.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/06/23/weekly-head-voices-243-part-time-role-model/#part-time--role--model">WHV #243 Part-time role model</a> &ndash; Some motivation to never stop trying to be the
best you, also when, inevitably, you&rsquo;ll only have occasional success.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">WHV #246 Call up your friends</a> &ndash; Do call up that friend you&rsquo;re thinking
up. Write thank-you notes. Send birthday messages. Make the connection!</li>
<li><a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#self-discipline">WHV #249 Self-discipline</a> &ndash; Take care of this personal engine and it will
take you places.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/12/06/weekly-head-voices-250-durable-blissful-contentment/#happiness-is-a-joke">WHV #250 Durable, blissful contentment</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="quo-vadis-2023">Quo vadis 2023</h3>
<p>Writing on this here blog, and specifically the WHVs, is important to me for
the following reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>They enable learning, through retro- and introspection.</li>
<li>Each successful post is an exercise in applied and externalised self-discipline.</li>
<li>I enjoy practising the dying art of writing.</li>
<li>They help to form a connection with other humans, both friends and strangers.</li>
</ul>
<p>The reason for this retro-retrospection here, is that I am evaluating the
(smouldering) results and implications of the tension between post regularity
on the one hand, and self-perceived post substance on the other, over the past
year.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve erred on the side of post substance, when regularity might have been the
better option.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s not that I was able to control it that deftly; what we have here is merely
the result of trying to publish posts of a reasonable quality at a reasonable
cadence.</p>
<p>My current feeling is that I would like to increase regularity, in spite of
past performance.</p>
<p>To make this happen, I have to learn to be satisfied with somewhat less, and
more importantly, I have to come up with improvements to my blogging workflow
that enable a more predictable flow of material.</p>
<p>A new year won&rsquo;t be a true new year without overly ambitious resolutions, now
will it?</p>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>This year, I averaged 20km of running per week for a total of 1044km (118 runs,
just under 99 hours) over the whole year.</p>
<p>Last year I did 25km per week, which is what I would have liked for this year
as well, but this is fine. <em>Any</em> kilometres are better than no kilometres!</p>










<figure>
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_51b4310156cb6775.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_9b2d56329fea834b.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_44ff53ded7296414.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_b6f0d925e5348190.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/images/Tasks/2022-12-31_16-17-19_screenshot_hu_9b2d56329fea834b.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Random drop-outs in graph below. At least finished strong in last week of year."/> <figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Random drop-outs in graph below. At least finished strong in last week of year.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I did three quick spot checks in my daily journals to see if I could determine
any specific reasons for the low / no-exercise weeks, but nothing jumped out.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to have to blame work for this one too.</p>
<p>Anyways, what I <em>can</em> say, without any hesitation, is that running made a massive
positive contribution to my physical and mental well-being this year.</p>
<p>The effects can generally be immediately felt (that beautiful bit when it feels
like all one&rsquo;s limbs are finally working together, rhythmically even, is
exhilarating), and usually signal another start of a cascade of positive
physiological and life-style factors.</p>
<p>Running resolutions for 2023: 0) Much enjoy. 1) Don&rsquo;t get injured. 2) Try <em>again</em> for the 25km/w average.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>I really enjoyed the following books:</p>
<h3 id="fiction">Fiction</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/54906250-project-hail-mary">Project Hail Mary by Andy Weir</a> - feel good edge of seat stranded in space but
have to save the earth human-alien-buddy movie -book. Great for engineers who
know how to suspend disbelief.
<ul>
<li>I could not remember that I had ever bought this book, but enjoyed the
living daylights out of it. Only later discovered that it was GOU #1 (who
shares my Kindle account)! 🥰 we enjoyed the same book!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57357418-termination-shock">Termination Shock by Neal Stephenson</a> - this is such a disciplined, detailed,
diligent piece of science fiction by someone who clearly has <em>practised</em> this
art and honed their craft to perfection. I enjoyed the story (it does require
some reader stamina) and appreciated the massive skills of the artist.</li>
<li><a href="/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/#permutation-city">Permutation City by Greg Egan</a> - click on the link to the left to go to my
mini-review in WHV #240.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="non-fiction">Non-fiction</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2022/07/24/weekly-head-voices-244-biyamiti-bat-fan/#projections">Projections: A Story of Human Emotions by Karl Deisseroth</a> - click on the link
to the left to go to my mini-review in WHV #244.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/59516276-the-unseen-body">The Unseen
Body: A Doctor&rsquo;s Journey Through the Hidden Wonders of Human Anatomy by
Jonathan Reisman</a> - Join the doctor on a fascinating journey through each
and every organ in the human body, robustly spiced by his stories of travels
to some of the most remote corners of the globe, and of his experience
various medical emergencies.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="resolutions">Resolutions</h3>
<p>Somewhere in the second half of 2022, I somehow lost my <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#reading">reading-before-sleep
habit</a>.</p>
<p>I plan to reinstate this habit, and to install the new habit of reading more
books on my phone (vs being limited to my Kindle, which is not always with me).</p>
<p>Armed with these two life-hacks, I hope to finish reading 20 books in 2023.</p>
<p>Please send me your recommendations in the comments below!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human">Systems and tools for running this human</h2>
<p>As per tradition, I quote from previous transition posts my explanation of &ldquo;The
System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Similar to <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">last year</a>, Emacs, Orgmode and Org-roam are still going very strong,
and constitute the lion&rsquo;s share of my personal knowledge management system.</p>
<p>In fact, with the imminent Emacs 29 release, a recent build of which I&rsquo;m typing
this draft into (English is hard folks&hellip;), Emacs has only become <em>more</em>
compelling.</p>
<p>Amongst <a href="https://blog.phundrak.com/emacs-29-what-can-we-expect">many other improvements</a>, tree-sitter, eglot and use-package are now all
part of core.</p>
<h3 id="byeeeeee-dropbox">Byeeeeee Dropbox!</h3>
<p>However&hellip;</p>
<p>The time has finally come for me to drop (again) Dropbox.</p>
<p>Although I have been a paying customer for many years (see <a href="/2010/02/28/weekly-head-voices-15-auto-tune-my-cloud/">WHV #15</a> from
February of 2010 for a report close to the start of our commercial
relationship), in the end it was their intransigence and inscrutability around
the Dropbox Paper 2020 migration that broke the camel&rsquo;s back.</p>
<p>They have been promising since before 2020 that they would migrate all existing
users to the new 2020 edition of Dropbox Paper.</p>
<p>However, now all you can find about this are frustrated forum posts from
long-time customers. My direct support request to be migrated was promptly
answered, and then closed with the following message:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As much as I would like to help, currently, the latest version of Paper release
is available to new users only.</p>
<p>Our team is currently in the process of working on this new feature in order to
build the best Paper experience for all our users.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I still really love that tool (winner of the WHV Award for the Most
Unexpectedly Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021!), but the interaction above
only served as a reminder of the pitfalls of a relationship like this.</p>
<p>During the writing of my yet-to-appear 202x note-taking approach blog post, it
bugged me that I had to come up with a good explanation for why I allowed
Dropbox Paper to break my rule of everything-needs-to-be-a-file-I-could-sync.</p>
<p>Although my yearly Dropbox Paper subscription is only up for renewal in June of
&lsquo;23, I decided to bite the bullet and <a href="/2022/11/11/weekly-head-voices-248-oh-snap/#hell-freezes-over--again">migrate everything out to an extremely
frightening mix of OneDrive, syncthing and unison</a>.</p>
<p>As I write this, it&rsquo;s been just over two months with nary a hiccup.</p>
<p>In June, I&rsquo;ll let that Dropbox subscription lapse.</p>
<p>Dropbox Paper, RIP.</p>
<p>(With <a href="https://1writerapp.com/">1writer</a> and also <a href="https://plainorg.com/">Plain Org</a> on the iPhone, and <a href="https://syncthing.net/">syncthing</a> on my main desktop
at home, plus Apple Notes for the truly ephemeral stuff, I have a pretty
capable mobile response to Paper.)</p>
<h3 id="resolutions">Resolutions</h3>
<ol>
<li>I would really like to publish a blog post titled <em>Note-taking approach
2023</em>. Ideally, it should be full of information about my current PKM system.</li>
<li>Write more notes, including both journals and <a href="/tags/zettelkasten/">Zettelkasten-style</a> notes.</li>
<li>Stretch goal: Maybe get another useful patch into Emacs.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>2022 was my first year back in employment, after <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">eight years of freelancing</a>.</p>
<p>In this year, I have only become more deeply involved and invested in the
current <a href="https://stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> adventure.</p>
<p>As I mentioned previously, I have the privilege of working closely together
with extremely capable folks, in a high-trust setting.</p>
<p>Many of my colleagues are smarter than I am in their respective fields. Due to
that, and the fact that we are both growing and innovating, I am constantly
learning.</p>
<p>My personal responsibilities span the spectrum from programming, through
mentor- and leadership to management and org-level technical decisions. On the
other dimension, I am exposed to everything from software plumbing to data
science, engineering and visualization. (This is what&rsquo;s known as a
PiM-situation. PiM = pig in mud)</p>
<p>The work is hard, but it&rsquo;s varied, it&rsquo;s challenging, it&rsquo;s together with a group
of humans I like, and it feels meaningful.</p>
<p>I have written all these words to try and explain that although it&rsquo;s clear from
this post that Work(tm) took up significantly more time and space this year, it
has contributed substantially to my well-being.</p>
<p>Freelancing was less stressful &ndash; I could focus on the engineering tasks at
hand and usually deliver. Now I have more responsibility, which brings
substantially more stress but also more satisfaction.</p>
<p>Furthermore, in terms of maintaining the plasticity of my neural network,
something I do have to pay more and more attention to thanks to the advancing
years, the variation and challenges of my current work setting are great.</p>
<p>That being said, I definitely have to get better at controlling stress.</p>
<h2 id="things-i-would-like-to-work-on-in-2023">Things I would like to work on in 2023</h2>
<p>In addition to the blogging, running, reading and systems resolutions mentioned
above, I would like to work on the following bigger themes in 2023:</p>
<ol>
<li>Work(tm).</li>
<li>Self-discipline, <a href="/2022/11/20/weekly-head-voices-249-self-discipline/#self-discipline">as featured in WHV #249</a>. I will implement this by writing
really stern messages to me in my diary.</li>
<li>Creating, restoring and maintaining good habits that <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a>: Reading,
writing, running, mindfulness practice.</li>
</ol>
<p>&hellip; and then finally, my central theme for 2023 will be:</p>
<h3 id="4-dot-expansiveness">4. Expansiveness</h3>
<p>Sometimes, most probably when you&rsquo;re out in nature, you experience your senses
really opening up.</p>
<p>It is as if the usually clearly defined borders between you and your
surroundings start to fade away.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve talked about this phenomenon before, in <a href="/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/#the-strange-continuum-of-consciousness">WHV #217&rsquo;s The Strange Continuum
of Consciousness</a> and in other places.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a great feeling, and it usually happens when you are fully present in that
moment.</p>
<p>For a while, you can get pleasantly lost in the infinite and fractal detail in
the moment and its participants.</p>
<p>For a while, you can truly appreciate the beauty of your surroundings, of the food
and drink you might be enjoying, and of the humans in your company.</p>
<p>In 2023, let us be expansive!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #242: Multiplicity of me</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 20:51:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/</guid><description>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.
If you like backyard philosophy, you&amp;rsquo;re in the right place.
Even if you only like bullet lists, you&amp;rsquo;re going to be ok.
Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 242nd edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the weeks from
Monday April 18 to Sunday May 22 of the year 2022.</p>
<p>If you like backyard philosophy, you&rsquo;re in the right place.</p>
<p>Even if you only like bullet lists, you&rsquo;re going to be ok.</p>










<figure><a href="afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_41bd9f5429550d06.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_cd29c721e76c2270.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_968c3008cb01b577.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_454f8c3e3a4ec58f.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/afrikaburn-2022-dmv-wvdl_hu_cd29c721e76c2270.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo by friend WvdL."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo by friend WvdL.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="learning-at-the-burning">Learning at the Burning</h2>
<p>There&rsquo;s an unwritten rule that you should not make any life decisions for at
least three weeks after the (Afrika)Burn.</p>
<p>Apparently people have, inspired by the sometimes weird experiences of the
event, made some major but unfortunately quite regrettable decisions in its
afterglow.</p>
<p>Anyways, I did not come back with anything like that.</p>
<p>Without sounding (too much) like Zaphod eating the fairy cake powering the
Total Perspective Vortex and walking away pretty much unscathed, through the
week&rsquo;s ups (mostly) and downs I learned a bunch, and I did come back with some
internal changes, but they were at their most extreme a strong reminder (kick
in the butt might even be appropriate) of a partially buried perspective or
two.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it is now exactly three weeks after the thing, and although that
dusty afterglow has definitely waned, it feels like I&rsquo;ve just merged back into
reality without any major incidents, just a slight tweak (or gentle kick in the
butt) here and there, for the better.</p>
<p>(Because inquiring minds might want to know, yes, we again brought the
BURNIVERSITY. We&rsquo;re probably one of the smallest theme camps, but we were
intense, and it feels like our interactions were too.)</p>
<p>Anyways, here are some completely random words, some of them loosely based (or
not at all, or something in between) on a recent conversation with friend PK,
and some of them from friend DW:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/#perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA</a> is a good framework for your well-being, and that of your loved ones:
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion</li>
<li>Engagement</li>
<li>Relationships</li>
<li>Meaning</li>
<li>Accomplishment</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>That thing you&rsquo;re stressing about is most probably not worth such a high
personal cost, and health-risk.</li>
<li>Just do the work.</li>
<li><a href="https://typesense.org/blog/the-unreasonable-effectiveness-of-just-showing-up-everyday/">Just showing up every day is a super power</a>. Pick your thing(s), show up to
them every single day, profit.</li>
<li>Chopping onions is the physical manifestation of your love for the people for
whom you are cooking. Give it (chopping onions, making food, loving) your
<em>whole</em> attention, and see what happens. Thank you DW, for this wisdom, and
for the food.
<ul>
<li>(Dear reader, between you and me, man that guy was burning so bright&hellip;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Practice will boost your powers of attention. This will deeply improve you,
and how you interact with others.</li>
<li>Kindness is still the most important super power.</li>
<li>Check up on yourself every day, about all of these completely random words.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="multiplicity-of-you">Multiplicity of you</h2>
<p><a href="/2018/06/10/weekly-head-voices-145-the-narrating-self/#homo-deus">In 2018, I talked about <em>Homo Deus</em></a>, a book by Yuval Harari in which he
discusses several thought-provoking ideas, one of which I highlighted then and
would like to discuss again now:</p>
<p>Your experience of being a single identity, a single <em>I</em>, is most probably an
illusion, as your brain most probably houses more &ldquo;me&quot;s than you would think.</p>
<p>Research by the Nobel prize-winner Daniel Kahneman and his various
collaborators showed that we house at the very least two major selves, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thinking,_Fast_and_Slow#Two_selves">namely
the remembering / narrating self and the experiencing self</a>.</p>
<p>The experiencing self is the one who actually does the living and the
<em>experiencing</em> of each moment, while the narrating self is the one who
continuously stitches together your whole story, often bending the truth to fit
its (your) opinions of yourself and those around you.</p>
<p>The narrating self is the one who dominates, for better or for worse.</p>
<p>Kahnemann himself pointed out the irony of this the best:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Odd as it may seem, I am my remembering self, and the experiencing self, who
does my living, is like a stranger to me.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(You might have heard of <a href="https://positivepsychology.com/what-is-peak-end-theory/">Peak-End Theory</a>, or the phenomenon that humans tend to
judge an experience based largley on the single peak moment, and on how they
felt at the end. You can thank your remembering self for this, and you can
imagine how this could really complicate your decision making.)</p>
<p>Harari discusses Kahneman&rsquo;s selves, but continues into more research with
people who for various reasons have separated brain hemispheres.</p>
<p>When you show one brain hemisphere one version of reality, and the other
another, it is as if there are multiple narrating selves in the same person who
come up with stories that they are convinced are the truth, although in this
case these stories conflict diametrically with other thanks to the design of
the experiment.</p>
<p>From this and other data, Harari concludes that humans generally house multiple
identities.</p>
<p>What I want to to get at, is that it helps to remember (always) that &ldquo;you&rdquo; are
in fact a collection of sometimes competing &ldquo;you&quot;s.</p>
<p>As if that were not challenging enough, your narrating self takes
responsibility for all of these feelings, and tries to weave it all into a
consistent story, although that is often extremely difficult or even
impossible.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.samharris.org/blog/the-illusion-of-the-self2">an 2012 interview with Sam Harris</a>, Bruce Hood had the following to say about
this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>By rejecting the notion of a core self and considering how we are a multitude
of competing urges and impulses, I think it is easier to understand why we
suddenly go off the rails. It explains why we act, often unconsciously, in a
way that is inconsistent with our self image &ndash; or the image of our self as we
believe others see us.</p>
<p>That said, the self illusion is probably an inescapable experience we need for
interacting with others and the world, and indeed we cannot readily abandon or
ignore its influence, but we should be skeptical that each of us is the
coherent, integrated entity we assume we are.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because this thought has become much more prominent for me in quite a positive
way, I would like to take it even further, by reminding you to practise
reminding yourself of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Although your perception is generally tied to your narrating self (the one
that&rsquo;s going to remember this blog post), the complete &ldquo;you&rdquo; in fact
constitutes the whole playing field, the consciousness and its physical
medium, in which <em>all</em> of these selves live and move around. In the words of
Harris, &ldquo;you can drop back into that&rdquo; and just <em>be</em> the consciousness, <em>be</em> that
which contains it all.</li>
<li>While your own selves truly live in this conciousness, high definition
versions of your surroundings and everyone you interact with are also
running in this same (your) neural network.
<ul>
<li>This means that you have a surprising amount of control of how you
experience life.</li>
<li>When you hear a dog barking, this is really nothing more than clusters of
neurons firing in your brain, but you visualize the dog <em>over there</em>. When
you feel the wind blowing over your skin, there&rsquo;s just another set of
neurons firing not far away from the barking dog. It&rsquo;s all inside your
head, and the borders between &ldquo;inside&rdquo; and &ldquo;outside&rdquo; are far more blurry
than you might think.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>All of your selves are <em>you</em>. Treat them like you would a group of your closest
friends. You can hold them up to the group&rsquo;s standards, but you have to
forgive, and you have to be kind.</li>
</ul>
<p>Folks, I wish you all (and all the yous), and all of your people, peace and
love.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #225: Just a perfect weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 09:03:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/</guid><description>Dear reader,
Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.
Keyboard update: K1 You&amp;rsquo;ll remember from WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the Womier K87 with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown switches.
That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear reader,</p>
<p>Welcome (back) to the Weekly Head Voices, and specifically to the 225th
installment, covering the period from Monday May 24 to Sunday June 6, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="la_autumn_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_efacf2278401042b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_395a276d16bd5112.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_9b888013a0ce8df0.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_f05d46bcd41cf24a.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/10/weekly-head-voices-225-just-a-perfect-weekend/la_autumn_tree_hu_395a276d16bd5112.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="keyboard-update-k1">Keyboard update: K1</h2>
<p>You&rsquo;ll remember from <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">WHV #204 that my previous keyboard acquisition was the
Womier K87</a> with its all-encompassing RGB and hot-swappable Gateron brown
switches.</p>
<p>That keyboard is so much fun to type on.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s hard to describe what leads to all that fun, relative to say the MS Sculpt
Ergonomic (which makes a lot more sense as a typing device).</p>
<p>Perhaps it is the case that fingers also like the exercise, just like their
human owners.</p>
<p>I was not planning to buy any keyboards again soon, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was quite curious whether low profile key switches (that is, slightly less
finger travel) would be a good compromise between the fun of the Womier and the
efficiency of the Sculpt.</li>
<li>The K1 was on my list of candidates of keyboards with low-profile mechanical
switches.</li>
<li>I find it difficult to resist a good deal.</li>
</ul>
<p>You see, a friendly little bird (who also hangs out on the keyboards channel of
the zatech slack) told me about the extra-special Takealot birthday special
discount on <a href="https://www.imore.com/keychron-k1-v4-review">the Keychron K1 V4 87-key keyboard</a>.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a credit card transaction, a week of waiting for delivery and
another week of getting accustomed to the new board, and here we are, with at
least me typing these words on the new K1.</p>
<p>It took a while to get used to the keycaps, which can be a slippery sometimes
(or rather, my finger tip traction is variable), but my typing speed and
accuracy on this thing are in the neighbourhood of where they should be.</p>
<p>The thing is a great deal more <em>stylish</em> than my Womier; the Womier is that
guilty pleasure 80s disco that you really love, the K1 could work in a serious
coffee shop.</p>
<p>Also, having a keyboard which can switch this easily between wired operation
(the default for my desktop) and three different bluetooth connections is
pretty convenient. On trips where I usually only take the MacBook, I could
consider taking the K1 along when I have to do A Great Deal of Serious Typing.</p>
<p>All of that being said, I can&rsquo;t yet say if the low profile switches are indeed
the compromise that I wondered about. My subjective impression now is indeed
that my fingers don&rsquo;t get so physically tired as sometimes happens with the
Womier, but I&rsquo;ll have to switch between them a few times to get a better idea.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am certainly enjoying the experience of typing on
this thing, and I am certainly wondering about the interesting role that
different types of mechanical keyboards have begun to play in my computing
life.</p>
<h2 id="lessons-about-a-new-book-notes-post-about-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain">Lessons about a new book notes post about Seven and a Half Lessons about the Brain</h2>
<p>After two months of early(ish) morning typing on various keyboards, I finally
managed to wrap up <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">my book notes about Seven and a Half Lessons about the
Brain</a>, a fantastic book by neuro-scientist and psychologist Lisa Feldman
Barrett.</p>
<p>I had plans, in retrospect clearly too ambitious, to have at least two (2) book
notes posts out in Q1 of this year (after it took me months to complete <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">my book
notes on Creativity, Inc.</a> by the end of last year).</p>
<p>That goal was necessarily postponed to Q2, and as we can all see now, there is
not enough time for a second post like this.</p>
<p>Either I have to change the format of the book notes to something more compact,
like a bunch of bullet lists, or I should make peace with the fact that I write
these like I write them, a little prose with quotes interspersed that can
generally be read like a mini story itself, and with the fact that they&rsquo;re
going to take as much time as they do.</p>
<p>Sometimes I have mixed feelings about the practice itself.</p>
<p>It takes fragments of hobby time spread out over weeks, fragments of time that
I could probably use for more reading, other interesting tidbits and, uhm,
extra work.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it feels like a sort of a mini-rebellion doing exactly this,
assembling so many little pieces into something slightly more coherent and
significant, something that stands apart from work.</p>
<p>It seems I do know what to do.</p>
<p>Thanks for the chat!</p>
<h2 id="perfect-weekends-and-the-necessary-reminders-that-precede-them">Perfect weekends and the necessary reminders that precede them</h2>
<p>The weekend of June 4, 2021, was unexpectedly perfect, and I would like to make
note of that here for future me.</p>
<p>This is the recipe that we followed, utterly by happy accident:</p>
<ul>
<li>1x reminder during the week to really focus on the now.</li>
<li>1x absolutely perfect autumn weather package: balmy 20ish degrees Celsius,
lots of sun, very little wind.</li>
<li>3x braais, one per day, with various subsets of family.</li>
<li>2x runs: one a long weekend morning run, and the other an unplanned one
with GOU#1.</li>
<li>1x polishing and publishing of the blog post mentioned above.</li>
<li>1x unexpected Sunday evening star watching with GOU#2.</li>
</ul>
<p>One would think that daily practice would help, but it turns out that sometimes
a serendipitous reminder by a friend can help to switch one&rsquo;s brain into
exactly the right gear, right before the weekend.</p>
<p>During our Friday evening start-the-weekend ritual (it&rsquo;s a braai. surprise!), I
had my first quite visceral &ldquo;THIS, this is it, this is everything&rdquo;
experience. (so lovely)</p>
<p>From then on, brain remained in the right mode right through most of the
weekend.</p>
<p>If you ever run into me before the weekend (it&rsquo;s always before the weekend!), I
would be grateful if you could remind me that it is in fact now.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you much nowness.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #217: Continuum of Consciousness</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2021 13:44:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/</guid><description>Hey, welcome to the Monthly Weekly Head Voices!
This one covers the extensive period from Monday Feb 15 to Sunday March 21, 2021.
Since we last connected here, much has transpired, a strangely selected subset of which is mentioned below:
New computer An M1 MacBook Air became part of my computing zoo. See the new computer post if you&amp;rsquo;re into that sort of thing. Short version if you&amp;rsquo;re not: It&amp;rsquo;s the best Emacs-capable device I&amp;rsquo;ve ever used.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hey, welcome to the Monthly Weekly Head Voices!</p>
<p>This one covers the extensive period from Monday Feb 15 to Sunday March
21, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="bettys_bay_somewhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_8f9c87f732124c86.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_b0df16242502fa52.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_dc5a53dcce727ffb.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_147a9746ca3986c1.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/bettys_bay_somewhere_hu_b0df16242502fa52.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Since we last connected here, much has transpired, a strangely selected subset
of which is mentioned below:</p>
<h2 id="new-computer">New computer</h2>
<p>An M1 MacBook Air became part of my computing zoo. See <a href="/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/">the new computer post</a> if
you&rsquo;re into that sort of thing. Short version if you&rsquo;re not: It&rsquo;s the best
Emacs-capable device I&rsquo;ve ever used.</p>
<h2 id="pgp-i-m-not-dead-yet">PGP: I&rsquo;m not dead yet!</h2>
<p>In a pleasantly surprising turn of events, I found myself counter-signing PGP
encryption keys with different sets of friends.</p>
<p>In spite of my <a href="/2016/12/11/pgp-never-gonna-give-you-up/">PGP never gonna give you up post</a> of 2016, the thought that
old-fashioned PGP might soon disappear even from my archaic view, to be
replaced by more user-friendly and modern solutions such as <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">Signal</a>, has been on
my mind more often recently.</p>
<p>This would not be the worst turn of events. The more people are using secure
and private communication, the better.</p>
<p>However, it <strong>was</strong> fun doing our modest part to bolster the tiny and dwindling
group of humans who know how to use PGP and think that they still should.</p>
<p>All of that being said, we did also make use of the opportunity to perform
defensible <a href="https://support.signal.org/hc/en-us/articles/360007060632-What-is-a-safety-number-and-why-do-I-see-that-it-changed-">Signal safety number verification</a>.</p>
<h2 id="stone-three-healthcare-has-joined-back-up-with-the-rest-of-voltron">Stone Three Healthcare has joined back up with the rest of Voltron</h2>
<p>Back in July of 2019, I <a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">announced that Stone Three Healthcare had been
officially spun out from Stone Three Venture Technology</a>.</p>
<p>More recently, our corporate mothership embarked on a newly engineered (and
funded) scaling-up journey, bringing with it a host of opportunities for
positive impact on the world.</p>
<p>In the Healthcare company we had to make a choice between sticking it out as a
smaller startup on the one hand, or re-integrating into a newly-designed merged
organization and making use of the extended new capabilities to further our
vision.</p>
<p>(I&rsquo;m really trying to keep it real here, but the line between that and
corp-speak is like mono-filament!)</p>
<p>So, since this past week or so, I&rsquo;m working together with the new merged
entity.</p>
<p>My mandate is now broader in two ways:</p>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ll be focusing on technological solutions for precision Health <strong>and</strong>
Safety, where it was previously healthcare only.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;ll be assisting all parts of the company by optimizing technological
processes of all sorts.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is all very exciting to me, and they&rsquo;re even letting me keep some of the
science in my new official title!</p>
<h2 id="the-strange-continuum-of-consciousness">The strange continuum of consciousness</h2>
<p>This is a tricky one to mention, because it probably needs much more space than
I have here, and much more skill than I have to explain.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to try in any case, because just maybe it sparks something for
someone.</p>
<p>A large part of the <a href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up meditation</a> daily practice is exploring the exact
nature of one&rsquo;s experienced consciousness.</p>
<p>Specifically, there is the realisation that the whole of your consciousness,
including your thoughts, your interactions with real, live people, and
everything else, takes place in <strong>your</strong> mind.</p>
<p>Furthermore, <em>internal</em> sensations, like an itch, or pain, or a tingling on
your skin, and <em>external</em> sensations, like hearing or sight, although they seem
to be localised <em>inside</em> and <em>outside</em>, take place in the exact same
consciousness.</p>
<p>Everything that you experience, whether &ldquo;real&rdquo;, like looking at the sea, or
imaginary, like thinking about (and hence &ldquo;seeing&rdquo;) something that you need to
take care of tomorrow, or something that you experienced yesterday, are all
simulations that are running as part of your consciousness.</p>
<p>There is a continuum from internal to external, and a continuum from direct
sensory experience to remembered or predicted experience, along with all of its
thoughts and emotions.</p>
<p>These are all the same sort of signals coursing through the same neural
pathways.</p>
<p>Another core idea here is that although your brain is housed in your skull,
your feeling that your consciousness is somehow also localised behind your eyes
is not entirely apt.</p>
<p>Your consciousness is the <em>whole</em> space, with all of your observed reality in
it, <em>including</em> the illusion (or rather simulation) of your localisation.</p>
<p>You (the observer) are not at a single point, but rather everywhere where
consciousness is.</p>
<p>Everything that you perceive to happen, by definition &ldquo;happens&rdquo; in the space
that you call consciousness.</p>
<p>These are tricky lessons to learn, and it seems that at least in my case we are
destined to spend only fleeting moments together, but they have profound and
positive implications for how we go through life.</p>










<figure><a href="machineray2-668-16.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/machineray2-668-16_hu_f99d79eecee7f0e1.png 480w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/22/weekly-head-voices-217-consciousness-continuum/machineray2-668-16.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: I used the neural network-based artwork generator, called MachineRay 2, by artist Robert A. Gonsalves to generate this piece. Read more in his blog post."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: I used the neural network-based artwork generator, called MachineRay 2, by artist Robert A. Gonsalves to generate this piece. Read more in <a href="https://towardsdatascience.com/creating-abstract-art-with-stylegan2-ada-ea3676396ffb">his blog post</a>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2020 to 2021 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 15:19:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to the year 2021 friends.
Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.
You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to the &amp;ldquo;transition&amp;rdquo; tag page.
If you don&amp;rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through last year&amp;rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition.
This transition tradition started at the end of 2009, which coincidentally is also the year that the Weekly Head Voices was born.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2021 friends.</p>
<p>Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.</p>
<p>You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to <a href="/tags/transition/">the &ldquo;transition&rdquo;
tag page</a>.</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/">last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition</a>.</p>
<p>This transition tradition <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">started at the end of 2009</a>, which coincidentally is
also the year that <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">the Weekly Head Voices was born</a>.</p>
<p>The goal of the transition post is to do a really spotty year review, and then
to gaze unsuccessfully into the future.</p>










<figure><a href="leopards_kloof.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_a5029f88e36e0460.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_335ac2d3414debe5.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_2a0689e34a9c502a.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_dd9b132d68990a15.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu_335ac2d3414debe5.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>More seriously, the ever-evolving network of posts on this website (there are
now literally hundreds of them), along with the ever-evolving but also fading
network of neurons in my head (probably at least a few hundred of them too!),
benefit from an occasional higher-level connecting of some of the dots.</p>
<p>In the introduction of the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/">2018 to 2019 transition post</a>, I ramble on slightly
more about the multiscalar nature of my subjective experience, and how that is
reflected in my notes database, of which this blog is one aspect.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s get on with it!</p>
<h2 id="noteworthy-snippets-through-the-lens-of-this-blog">Noteworthy snippets through the lens of this blog</h2>
<h3 id="covid-19">COVID-19</h3>
<p>One of the biggest issues for most people last year and still at this moment is
COVID-19.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested, you could take a look at the Weekly Head Voices posts
that had something to say about <a href="/tags/covid19/">COVID-19</a>, but you don&rsquo;t really have to.</p>
<p>Fortunately, world-wide vaccination has commenced. However, we have to keep our
fingers crossed that:</p>
<ol>
<li>The world succeeds in getting the vaccine to a sufficient number of humans
on time.</li>
<li>A vaccine-resistant strain does not happen. It could, because math, and
because evolution (selection pressure due to the vaccine, doh),</li>
</ol>
<p>Whether the above outcomes realise or not, I do also hope that we retain as
many as possible of the lessons we have been learning thanks to the pandemic.</p>
<ul>
<li>Mask-wearing and generally improved hygeine with the major goal of protecting
our fellow humans are great habits.</li>
<li>We have made great strides towards the future of work, where many workers (by
far not all, but it&rsquo;s a good meaningful chunk) are able to commute less,
pollute less, better organize the interaction of their work and family lives
and, importantly, their work is measured by its value and not by the number
of hours it takes place in.</li>
<li>We humans are in this (today pandemic, tomorrow something else!) together.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="lazar-focus-the-side-project-that-got-released">Lazar Focus: The side-project that got released</h3>
<p>Around these parts we have a rich tradition of starting but then never
finishing side-projects, and the concomitant giant side-project graveyard to
show for it.</p>
<p>This year, I did manage to ship the little distraction blocker tool I wrote,
called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a>. The <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">first WHV mentioning was #196</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the fact that this little tool has ended up helping me to rescue
many aspirant unproductive days, it has sold more than 10 copies, which was my
life goal for this project.</p>
<h3 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion effect</h3>
<p>From Adam Grant&rsquo;s book Give and Take, I learned about the <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#the-pygmalion-effect">Pygmalion effect</a>,
where a teacher&rsquo;s <em>belief</em> in the intrinsic capabilities of a student, whether
those were justified or not at the time, had a significant and enduring
positive, one could say potentially life-changing, effect on that student&rsquo;s
performance.</p>
<p>Besides the bit about the Pygmalion effect, <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/">that post (WHV #201)</a> contains a
micro-summary of the Shape Up book by Basecamp, which is also worth a look.</p>
<h3 id="take-the-day-off-to-go-run-in-the-mountain">Take the day off to go run in the mountain</h3>
<p>During the year, for example in <a href="/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/#life-progress-update">WHV #203</a> when I took my birthday off to go
running in the mountains, I learned that taking days off on the birthdays of you
and your loved ones to go do stuff outdoors is a Great Idea(tm).</p>
<p>(I also learned that sometimes you don&rsquo;t even need an excuse. Just take the day
off and go run in the mountains.)</p>
<h3 id="use-it-or-lose-it">Use it or lose it</h3>
<p>The human system is amazingly adaptable.</p>
<p>The price that we pay for that flexibility is that each and every one of our
learned capabilities requires continuous practice in order to be maintained.</p>
<p>In short humans, <a href="/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/#use-it-or-lose-it">use it, or lose it</a>.</p>
<h3 id="fool-your-mind">Fool your mind</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m making peace with the fact that I apparently need to apply, continuously,
various silly tricks to keep <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">the slippery eel that is my mind</a> on the
straight-and-narrow.</p>
<p>As a shining example, <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">the refocus reminder</a>, a bell that reminds you at hourly
intervals to focus, indeed sounds a bit silly but adds a great deal of value.</p>
<p>My favourite example from last year however is creating yet more (but smaller!)
habits to kickstart my bigger habits, in this case a <a href="/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/#wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">3-item morning checklist
to kickstart the more daunting full day checklist</a>.</p>
<p>The morning bootstrap checklist is, at the risk of sounding like a startup-bro:</p>
<ol>
<li>meditation,</li>
<li>deep reading and</li>
<li>planning.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="blogging-stats">Blogging stats</h2>
<p>Since February 17 of 2020 when I <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">migrated everything to a small Hetzner VPS</a>,
the server log files tell me that cpbotha.net saw just over 157000 unique
visitors, which is 492 per day on average.</p>
<p>I wrote 30 posts on cpbotha.net during 2020, of which 25 were editions of the
Weekly Head Voices.</p>
<p>Thanks to the shiny new archive page I put together today, you can now finally
<a href="/archive/#2020">see all of 2020&rsquo;s posts in one place</a>, or of any other year, should you be more
into the older stuff.</p>
<p>In addition to the cpbotha.net posts, I also published 11 posts over on
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the regular WHV posts, I&rsquo;m happy to have published what will
hopefully be only the first in a whole collection of book notes posts, namely
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Creativity, Inc.&rdquo; by Ed Catmull with Amy Wallace</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s chunky at just over 7000 words, but it will give you a pretty good idea of
the contents of the much more substantial book it is based on!</p>
<h3 id="details-for-nerds">Details for nerds</h3>
<p>This is the invocation I used to generate reports from the nginx log files
using the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess</a> tool:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>zcat -f -- /var/log/nginx/cpbotha.net.access.log.*.gz <span style="color:#1f2328">|</span><span style="color:#0a3069">\
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format<span style="color:#0550ae">=</span>COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>In 2020 I seem to have run just 100 metres shy of 1100km. (Typical&hellip;)</p>
<p>More would have been good, but I&rsquo;m happy with this.</p>
<p>Exercise did take a bit of a hit due to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/#exercise">lockdown</a>, although I could definitely
have squeezed more in.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the aggregated amount of enjoyment and satisfaction
was astronomical.</p>
<p>A personal highlight was <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#random-notes-on-the-kogelberg-trail-adventure">running the 24km(ish) Kogelberg trail with a tiny
crew that included two of my Dutch family members</a>.</p>
<p>(These blog retrospectives are strange, because they are also life
retrospectives, but they shouldn&rsquo;t get too personal. I would be remiss however
if I did not mention that having these specific Dutch peeps here in 2020 was
magical. I am going to miss them terribly.)</p>
<p>Also thanks to said peeps, I did more trail running this year than ever before.</p>
<p>It turns out that I am surrounded by beautiful trails. WHO KNEW?!</p>
<p>The other highlight I want to mention was <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations">GOU#1</a> running her first race, the
distributed <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#running-and-reading">CTM 10km in Jonkershoek</a>. Here&rsquo;s to many more GOU kilometres!</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>Thanks to some strict words by friend PK during the year, I got solidly back on
the daily meditation train, which ended up being the start of a streak of
(workday) morning meditation longer than anything I&rsquo;ve been able to maintain up
to now.</p>
<p>(The bootstrap checklist in <a href="#fool-your-mind">Fool Your Mind</a> above might also have contributed to
this.)</p>
<p>The Waking Up course by Sam Harris has been amazing for more than two years
now, and even more so when trying to build and keep up a daily meditation
habit.</p>
<p>What I especially like about Waking Up is its focus on the explicit practice of
the experience of consciousness and the role (or non-role) of the self within
that. (for a tiny example, see <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#find-a-place-in-the-universe-that-is-your-consciousness">WHV #207</a>)</p>
<p>Practising this daily has been an experience that I can only recommend in the
strongest terms.</p>
<p>(Please let me know if you&rsquo;d like to try a month for free. As a subscriber, I
get to give these out to as many peeps as I want to.)</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV approach to life, the universe and everything (also known as &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo;,
but you have to over-emphasize the terribly soft &ldquo;W&rdquo;) has been evolving for a
few years now, but it was most recently summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.</p>
<p>At the basis of this approach we find the two formidable pillars of</p>
<ol>
<li><em>love</em> and</li>
<li><em>science</em>,</li>
</ol>
<p>and in that order. On top of these pillars rest <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">The WHV&rsquo;s Two no Three Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</a>.</p>
<p>The two no three rules are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be useful.</li>
<li>Be likable.</li>
<li>Evolve.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the previous transition post, I talked about <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">six personal daily life
directions</a>, the continuous reformulation of which I had integrated into my
morning routine.</p>
<p>It was a good start, but the life directions were a bit too specific, and six
separate things is too many to keep at the core of your thoughts.</p>
<p>Motivated by this, and also by <a href="https://lexfridman.com/chris-lattner-2/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Chris Lattner</a>
wherein Lattner, an amazing engineer, but more importantly such a kind human
being, underlined the importance to him of always continuing to grow and learn,
I mashed together everything I had to come up with two clusters of daily life
directions:</p>
<ol>
<li>Grow, learn, build, enjoy. (motion)</li>
<li>Be useful. Be likeable. Be kind. (self-checks)</li>
</ol>
<p>In the stupid-dimensional universe that is my mind, I know that these
directions are obviously in the spirit of WALUE, but I can&rsquo;t yet articulate
clearly how they relate to the pillars and the rules of WALUE.</p>
<p>Maybe they&rsquo;re just a neat little pile on top, or a little bit to the side,
leaning against the WALUE building?</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, they have been part of my daily checklist for a few
months now, and they seem to work in the sense of being practical, checkable
and tiny enough to keep in mind always.</p>
<h2 id="plans--for-tomorrow-at-least">Plans (for tomorrow, at least)</h2>
<p>This bit is quite scary.</p>
<p>I hardly know what&rsquo;s going to happen tomorrow, and here I wanted to talk about
plans for the whole year!</p>
<p>So, to be clear, what I&rsquo;ve listed below is limited to the concrete items that I
can see before me right now.</p>
<h3 id="the-absolute-basics">The absolute basics</h3>
<ul>
<li>Attempt to apply <a href="#life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</a> all of the time.</li>
<li>Practise mindfulness every day.</li>
<li>If I&rsquo;m wondering whether I should go run, the answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="comms-upgrade">Comms upgrade</h3>
<p>I would like to level up my communication game.</p>
<p>Work from home is here to stay, and that&rsquo;s a good thing, but it has muffled my
face-to-face communication modality, something that has had a profound impact
on my full communication suite.</p>
<p>Most of the clever folks now agree that <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">the correct answer is asynchronous
communication</a>. Future-facing companies like Basecamp and <a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/">Doist have been
preaching this long before COVID-19</a>.</p>
<p>To be more specific, I need to figure out first how to do asynchronous
communication in my daily work, and then to become really good at it.</p>
<h3 id="write-more-about-good-books">Write more about good books</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to publish more focused book notes like the recently appeared
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Creativity, Inc. post</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s great reading these books, but I&rsquo;ve noticed that if I&rsquo;m planning to
publish book notes, I read more intently, I take better notes, and the extra
processing stage before starting to put together a blog post really helps me to
integrate the knowledge contained in the book.</p>
<p>Every good book one is able to integrate is in fact a cheap, but possibly
game-changing firmware upgrade&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2021-for-you">Wishes for 2021, for you</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this. I am grateful that you&rsquo;re here.</p>
<p>I wish you and everyone you hold dear the best 2021 possible.</p>
<p>Quite concretely, we can all help to make this happen by being as kind as we
possibly can to as many fellow humans as we possibly can.</p>
<p>In the words of a fellow traveller: SMÉAGOL OUT!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #207: Kogelberg</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 15:58:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/</guid><description>The 207th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, which in theory should cover the week from Monday October 5 to Sunday October 11, 2020, is in fact only here to remind future me of that time when I took the Thursday October 8 off from work to go run the Kogelberg Trail with friends PK, TvD and EW.
(Ok, well maybe there is also a backyard philosophy thing hidden at the end of the post&amp;hellip;)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The 207th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, which in theory should cover the
week from Monday October 5 to Sunday October 11, 2020, is in fact only here to
remind future me of that time when I took the Thursday October 8 off from work
to go run the <a href="https://www.hikingsouthafrica.co.za/kogelberg-trail/">Kogelberg Trail</a> with friends PK, TvD and EW.</p>
<p>(Ok, well maybe there is also a backyard philosophy thing hidden at the end
of the post&hellip;)</p>










<figure><a href="kogelberg_5005.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hu_d691f21faf1d442.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hu_edd818a9a6434f03.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hu_c0f0b031baa67f1b.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hu_4bbc3dad17b08ca3.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/kogelberg_5005_hu_edd818a9a6434f03.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: About halfway through the first climb"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: About halfway through the first climb</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="random-notes-on-the-kogelberg-trail-adventure">Random notes on the Kogelberg Trail adventure</h2>
<ul>
<li>Taking the day off to go run in the mountains: These two separately pleasant
actions are even greater when applied together.</li>
<li>Based on the predictions a week or so before the time, we were going to run
in a bit of rain. As the date came closer, the predicted start time of the
rain kept on creeping later and later. The day itself was mostly gorgeous
sunshine with very little wind.</li>
<li>According to the Cape Nature peeps at the starting point, we were the first
people to run the route since before the lockdown when they, err, locked down
the nature reserve. This was noticeable by the overgrown vegetation we had to
fight through for a kilometre or two, just after the first climb. Other than
that, it felt pretty special!</li>
<li>I like running with a GPX of the route on my Apple Watch (<a href="http://www.workoutdoors.net/">WorkOutDoors</a> is
amazing for following a route with maps while you&rsquo;re running, especially if
you&rsquo;re directionless like me), but I could not find one available online
before the time.
<ul>
<li>So I started a Strava Pro trial so I could use their amazing <a href="https://www.strava.com/heatmap">global heatmap</a>
to draw the crowd-sourced GPX in about 6 clicks. I&rsquo;m probably going to keep
the Strava Pro: Being able to make routes like this of any place that you
might find yourself in is amazing.</li>
<li>You can download a GPX of the route we actually ran, as logged by my
iPhone, by clicking on the following link: <a href="./kogelberg_trail_cpbotha_20201008.zip">Kogelberg Trail GPX</a>. The whole
thing is just under 24km.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Below is a video impression somewhere just past halfway. Don&rsquo;t miss the waterfall!</p>
<video controls>
<source src="kogelberg_trail_impression_20201008.mp4" type="video/mp4">
Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
<h2 id="find-a-place-in-the-universe-that-is-your-consciousness">Find a place in the universe that is your consciousness</h2>
<p>On the morning of October 7, about halfway through a 10 minute mindfulness
practice with <a href="https://wakingup.com/">the Waking Up app</a>, Sam Harris says something like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Take a negative emotion, and examine it. Remember, you can find a place in
consciousness that is not implicated, to stand on and be able to do this.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>His words really struck home at that moment.</p>
<p>By the end of the session, analysing a particular negative thought, I
experienced quite viscerally (haha, sorry) the phenomenon of relatively easily
finding a non-implicated mental space to stand, from where I could take apart
that negative emotion piece by piece, without being drawn into it at all.</p>
<p>Now it feels like all of those practice sessions exploring the <em>experience</em> of
consciousness, as the whole of the reality simulation being run over the
trillions of neural connections in the human brain, were not in vain.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #206: Mount Ceder</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 13:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/</guid><description> Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder.
Welcome, dear readers, to the 206th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the two weeks from Monday September 21 to Sunday October 4, 2020.
Mount Ceder beauty The weather prediction for the September 25 long weekend did not look good at all.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="mount_ceder_4873_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu_db84bf0aa50e7187.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu_6f227f23e4613f53.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu_545f13115175fe2f.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu_7b0637a043d059d7.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4873_pano_hu_6f227f23e4613f53.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A view from a run with GOU#1 in Mount Ceder.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome, dear readers, to the 206th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering
the two weeks from Monday September 21 to Sunday October 4, 2020.</p>
<h2 id="mount-ceder-beauty">Mount Ceder beauty</h2>
<p>The weather prediction for the September 25 long weekend did not look good at
all.</p>
<p>Temperatures in the low single digits, and rain.</p>
<p>We were unable to reschedule our reservation, and so, with significant
trepidation, we packed our things for the weekend and made the drive to Mount
Ceder.</p>
<p>As we entered the valley right before arriving at our destination, the rugged
and wonderful beauty of the surroundings quickly started dispelling our puny
expectations.</p>
<p>The weather did turn out almost exactly as was predicted, but our time there
ended up being the brilliant opposite of what we had feared.</p>
<p>In between spells of rain, there was plenty of fresh sunshine outside, with a
super effective little closed combustion fireplace inside the house to keep it
toasty.</p>










<figure><a href="mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu_20f25df9b494b4d2.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu_15cb891e12a5695c.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu_99ede7465903e58d.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu_55eafea2a50a3421.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/mount_ceder_4883_pano_from_hike_hu_15cb891e12a5695c.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: View from a hike up the mountain with the whole fam-jam."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: View from a hike up the mountain with the whole fam-jam.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The outside jacuzzi which we discovered late on the Saturday afternoon might
also have played a role in the amount of fun that was had.</p>
<p>It does also need to be said that the fact that there&rsquo;s no telephone reception
is a massive perk for us visitors.</p>
<p>The older I get, the more I enjoy disconnecting.</p>
<h2 id="vcbm-2020-virtually">VCBM 2020, virtually</h2>
<p>Thanks to the modern miracle that is virtual conferences, I was able to attend
a large part of the <a href="https://www.gcpr-vmv-vcbm-2020.uni-tuebingen.de/">Visual Computing in Biology and Medicine (VCBM) 2020
conference</a>.</p>
<p>Although I am super interested in the themes and people of this conference, it
is <em>usually</em> not possible for me to fly around the globe to take part in this
or any other relevant academic gathering.</p>
<p>However, the current pandemic has brought with it a whole host of changes, not
least of which is the concept of being able to participate, as a first class
citizen, in an international conference.</p>
<p>It was really great, although slightly nostalgic, connecting with friends and
colleagues from years ago.</p>
<p>Just being able to join in on the post-talk question sessions, and in the
surreal social rooms on discord where you find yourself in a grid of talking
heads, was super enjoyable.</p>
<p>(It has to be noted here that the technical aspects of VCBM 2020 were also
top-class. Everything, from the interactive block-based conference programme
with downloadable papers, to the youtube streams for each session, to the
discord channels for real-time discussion and the discord channels for social
video conferencing, was simply top notch!)</p>
<h3 id="multi-tasking-virtual-meetings-quo-vadis">Multi-tasking virtual meetings: Quo vadis?</h3>
<p>What was also interesting to hear, was a possibly less positive aspect of
virtual conferencing, specifically that academic peeps were now in the
situation where they often had to multi-task whilst taking part in the
conference.</p>
<p>In the old days, pre-COVID, it could definitely happen that folks had to take
care of a few emails or perhaps even a video meeting, but the majority of the
day would be spent conferencing.</p>
<p>That is, people from potentially right around the globe would be chatting
face-to-face about anything and everything, an activity which is truly
important for collaboration, and friendship.</p>
<p>Now it seems that this ratio has changed, where most of the time folks are
expected to be available online for additional tasks and interactions, while
conferencing in parallel.</p>
<p>In my day job I&rsquo;ve noticed a similar phenomenon, where one can often notice
that people taking part in a meeting are only partially present.</p>
<p>Whilst this is perhaps a good thing for a number of meetings that are by their
nature not that efficient, I think that it&rsquo;s a dangerous habit to
cultivate.</p>
<p>Imagine that by default, every meeting means your poor cognition trying to keep
up with multiple streams of information at the same time. Looking at it from a
different perspective, now you have even less confidence that your
collaborators are paying attention to what is being discussed.</p>
<p>This might be yet another reason to <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">favour asynchronous offline communication</a>,
that is, writing long-form messages on message boards, with synchronous
face-time being reserved more and more for purely social reasons.</p>
<h2 id="on-thursday-october-1-too-much-distraction-was-too-much">On Thursday October 1, too much distraction was too much</h2>
<p>Seguing right on from the synchronous communication point above, On October 1 I
unfortunately needed to be jacked-in to Teams, WhatsApp <em>and</em> Discord for the
whole day, for various good reasons.</p>
<p>It was only around 16:20 that I was able to snap out of all of this and jack
out again, with <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a> helping to bring a bit of welcome rest and,
surprise(!), focus.</p>
<p>Before that, anxiety about possibly missing something kept me from plugging out
for even short bursts to be able to do work.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s funny how the expectations, real or perhaps more often just perceived, of
one&rsquo;s surroundings make it extremely difficult to disconnect, which leads to
more time lost to these various forms of distraction, which leads to further
anxiety, which further complicates just taking those few steps back and pulling
the plug.</p>
<p>I wish I had a trick to manage all of this better.</p>
<h2 id="that-time-i-nuked-all-of-my-computers-with-a-partition-resize-and-move-that-should-have-taken-no-more-than-5-minutes">That time I nuked all of my computers with a partition resize and move that should have taken no more than 5 minutes</h2>
<p><em>Massive nerd warning: If you don&rsquo;t want to know about filesystems, feel free</em>
<em>to skip this section. Before you do however, take this advice from me: Avoid</em>
<em>AOMEI.</em></p>
<p>My goal was simple: Move the newly appeared recovery partition (in addition to
the one at the start of the disk) to its end, so that I can grow my main system
partition to fill the available space on the drive.</p>
<p>Some years ago I had used EaseUs for something similar, but they wanted payment
for this task, and current reviews were pointing quite convincingly in the
direction of AOMEI.</p>
<p>Narrator: <em>The reviews were all tragically wrong.</em></p>
<p>My specific use case is even documented exactly on the AOMEI website, see <a href="https://www.diskpart.com/windows-10/windows-10-move-recovery-partition-4348.html">this
page</a>.</p>
<p>I followed those steps exactly.</p>
<p>My computer rebooted twice in order to perform the two actions:</p>
<ol>
<li>move recovery partition, and</li>
<li>resize system partition&hellip;</li>
</ol>
<p>&hellip; to conclude finally by leaving my laptop in a 100% unusable state.</p>
<p>No boot, no nothing.</p>
<p>I tried various combinations of booting into safe mode, which worked at first
but showed me the full drive&rsquo;s space available, meaning that the filesystem had
probably been damaged.</p>
<p>Hard.</p>
<p>I later booted with Windows installation media, from where I launched various
rescue attempts, including the stalwart <code>bootrec /rebuildbcd</code> and all of its
friends.</p>
<p>Nothing.</p>
<p>AOMEI had done a pretty great job in completely destroying my partition table
and filesystem.</p>
<p>Narrator: <em>He got what he paid for!</em></p>
<p>I ended up installing Windows 10 twice, the second time with the
soon-to-be-released 20H2 install media, because installing the old 1909 and
then upgrading was taking far too long.</p>
<p>The whole exercise, or should I say &ldquo;lesson&rdquo;, cost me about a day.</p>
<p>Stoic narrator: <em>Fortunately, the situation afterwards was better than it was before.</em></p>
<ul>
<li>My main WSL2 ubuntu 20.04 image, where most of my development work happens,
remained untouched on the second SSD and was up and running pretty quickly
after the Windows re-install.</li>
<li>My backups demonstrably work, although Windows File History is truly klunky
compared to Apple&rsquo;s Time Machine.</li>
<li>In the chaos of trying to get my work environment back up and running, I also
had to upgrade my deep learning Linux desktop machine to Ubuntu 20.04. (It
started as a Murphy&rsquo;s law situation, where both my laptop <em>and</em> the desktop
were unusable, the latter due to a stupid Ubuntu bug manifesting as a
non-working keyboard)</li>
<li>A fresh install of Windows feels really fresh.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">My mind is a slippery eel</h2>
<p>Recently I had to work on a chunk of software system design.</p>
<p>It starts with nothing laid down, just a general idea of what this pretty
significant feature should be able to do.</p>
<p>Pulling yourself up by your bootstraps, you have to start laying down the
bottom-most levels of the design that will eventually be able to make those
high-level desired features a reality.</p>
<p>This whole growing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rube%5FGoldberg%5Fmachine">Rube Goldberg machine</a> has to stay in your mind for a large
part of the day, as you&rsquo;re mentally twisting, turning and replacing bits here
and there.</p>
<p>Most of these days, getting my brain to stay focused felt a lot like trying to
hold on to a really slippery eel, and, if that wasn&rsquo;t tricky enough, trying to
aim the sporadically working laser, badly mounted on its slippery head, to try
and carve something recognisable from a block of slowly melting ice.</p>
<p>By the end of most days, it would mostly not feel like it had been very
productive.</p>
<p>I tried to make peace with the fact that some sorts of work, coupled with all
of the usual emotional interactions, would often result in this sort of
feeling.</p>
<p>In that moment, this did also help me to get back into the habit of daily
meditation practice. Fortunately there&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.wakingup.com/">the Waking Up app by Sam Harris</a> which
is perfect for this. Using this, I am usually able to squeeze in a 10 minute
practice before work starts, which subjectively seems to bring a little more
equanimity into each day.</p>
<p>Looking back at this experience now, it also seems like a strong vote for
paying more attention to the daily &ldquo;done&rdquo; list.</p>
<p>Although I mostly remember to journal every day, I often forget to look at it
also from the perspective of compactly listing the little tasks that have been
completed.</p>
<p>This could be tricky when working on an amorphous project like &ldquo;design this
vague thing&rdquo;, but I think that it&rsquo;s more about the ritual of formulating and
then reviewing a small but plausible thing that is now apparently done.</p>
<p>This seems to fool the anxious parts of one&rsquo;s brain into a semblance of
temporary calm, enabling some of the other parts to get back to work.</p>
<p>This too I shall file this under <a href="/tags/101-mind-tricks">&ldquo;101 stupid but effective tricks to fool your
mind into being more useful&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. I just discovered that some part of <a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/#do-you-write-stuff-down">January-2019-Charl already did</a>.</p>
<p>P.P.S. &ldquo;Fool your mind&rdquo;, although it sounds much less awesome than &ldquo;free your
mind&rdquo;, seems to be a recurring aspect of effectively operating the human
machine.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>