<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>T-Mobile on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/t-mobile/</link><description>Recent content in T-Mobile on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2011 19:31:55 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/t-mobile/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Barbarossa Town [Weekly Head Voices #51]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/07/11/barbarossa-town-weekly-head-voices-51/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2011 19:31:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/07/11/barbarossa-town-weekly-head-voices-51/</guid><description>Here’s a photo: Some train at the Rotterdam Station. I spent lots of time in these the past week.
… and here are four things, most of which happened last week:
I was honoured to be invited by the International Research Training Group (IRTG) of the University of Kaiserslautern to visit their institute and give a presentation on medical visualisation (my field of research, for those of you joining very late). Unfortunately, I was only able to stay an evening and a morning, flanked by two 7 hour train rides. In spite of my short stay, the exceptionally friendly Kaiserslautern peeps managed to put together an enjoyable and especially very efficient program with dinner, a morning of research discussion and of course my talk, which was only 45 minutes over time, and a delectable lunch outside. It was interspersed with questions and discussions, which I do like, and most of the audience managed to stay awake (!), but I still do have to take a more serious look into accurately timing interactive talks like this. Thank you very much IRTG, it was a perfect visit! The Delft – Kaiserslautern trip is just so that taking the train seems to make more sense than flying. The total trip time is greater, but the difference is small enough to be justified by the great deal of work one can do on these long train rides. I tried out T-Mobile’s new pre-paid Internet “abroad” option, called Travel &amp;amp; Surf. One pays EUR 4.95 for 50 MB over 24 hours, or EUR 14.95 for 100 MB (which they call “unlimited”, HAHA) over 7 days. Without this active, my mobile internet works abroad, but in the zone 1 countries (Germany, Norway, etc.) costs me EUR 2 / MB up to a maximum of EUR 60 per month, so it’s definitely nice being able to pre-pay and control the possibly nasty surprises. However, an Android telephone sucks down 50 MB of data without even thinking, unless you remember to deactivate syncing and background data, which does help to quite an extent. This is certainly a good development, but T-Mobile and all other mobile providers are probably still making an absolute killing by acting like it’s really complicated providing internet just over the Dutch border. On the really good news front, Francois Malan’s paper on measuring femoral lesions despite CT metal artifacts has been accepted for publication in Skeletal Radiology! The full citation (so far, it’s online first) is: Malan DF, Botha CP, Kraaij G, Joemai RM, van der Heide HJ, Nelissen RG, Valstar ER., Measuring femoral lesions despite CT metal artefacts: a cadaveric study, Skeletal Radiology, 2011. Cite it sesame! Here’s my final thing, a youtube clip that, to my surprise, I don’t think I’ve shown on this blog before. Pay attention, it’s full of braai-related culture and wisdom:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Here’s a photo:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/train_rotterdam.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/train_rotterdam-1024x608.jpg"
        
            alt="Some train at the Rotterdam Station. I spent lots of time in these the past week."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Some train at the Rotterdam Station. I spent lots of time in these the past week.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>… and here are four things, most of which happened last week:</p>
<ul>
<li>I was honoured to be invited by the <a href="http://www.irtg.uni-kl.de/" title="IRTG website">International Research Training Group (IRTG)</a> of the University of Kaiserslautern to visit their institute and give a presentation on medical visualisation (my field of research, for those of you joining <em>very</em> late). Unfortunately, I was only able to stay an evening and a morning, flanked by two 7 hour train rides. In spite of my short stay, the exceptionally friendly Kaiserslautern peeps managed to put together an enjoyable and especially very efficient program with dinner, a morning of research discussion  and of course my talk, which was only 45 minutes over time, and a delectable lunch outside. It was interspersed with questions and discussions, which I do like, and most of the audience managed to stay awake (!), but I still do have to take a more serious look into accurately timing interactive talks like this. Thank you very much IRTG, it was a perfect visit!</li>
<li>The Delft – Kaiserslautern trip is just so that taking the train seems to make more sense than flying. The total trip time is greater, but the difference is small enough to be justified by the great deal of work one can do on these long train rides.</li>
<li>I tried out T-Mobile’s new pre-paid Internet “abroad” option, called <a href="http://www.t-mobile.nl/service-en-contact/buitenland/internet-in-het-buitenland" title="travel&amp;surf website">Travel &amp; Surf</a>. One pays EUR 4.95 for 50 MB over 24 hours, or EUR 14.95 for 100 MB (which they call “unlimited”, HAHA) over 7 days. Without this active, my mobile internet works abroad, but in the zone 1 countries (Germany, Norway, etc.) costs me EUR 2 / MB up to a maximum of EUR 60 per month, so it’s definitely nice being able to pre-pay and control the possibly nasty surprises. However, an Android telephone sucks down 50 MB of data without even thinking, unless you remember to deactivate syncing and background data, which does help to quite an extent. This is certainly a good development, but T-Mobile and all other mobile providers are probably still making an absolute killing by acting like it’s really complicated providing internet just over the Dutch border.</li>
<li>On the really good news front, Francois Malan’s paper on measuring femoral lesions despite CT metal artifacts has been accepted for publication in Skeletal Radiology! The full citation (so far, it’s online first) is:  Malan DF, Botha CP, Kraaij G, Joemai RM, van der Heide HJ, Nelissen RG, Valstar ER., <em><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21732221" title="pubmed link to Malan 2011">Measuring femoral lesions despite CT metal artefacts: a cadaveric study</a>,</em> <strong>Skeletal Radiology</strong>, 2011. Cite it sesame!</li>
</ul>
<p>Here’s my final thing, a youtube clip that, to my surprise, I don’t think I’ve shown on this blog before. Pay attention, it’s full of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Braai" title="wikipedia page on braai">braai</a>-related culture and wisdom:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vq2SOmwzjUU?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>May your week be full of awesome!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Godzilla. [Weekly head voices #21]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/04/25/godzilla-weekly-head-voices-21/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2010 13:39:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/04/25/godzilla-weekly-head-voices-21/</guid><description>Part of this post, looking back on week 16 of 2010, was produced in a (I wish I could say speeding) train with my aging Nokia E71 tethered (by bluetooth) to my netbook. The T-Mobile unlimited mobile internet package is unfortunately still limited to 384 Kbit/s (see my speedtest.net results), but I’m attached to it for its reasonable policy on internet use outside of NL.
In any case, during the past week I enjoyed 14 hours of meetings and completed 22 GTD tasks spread over 11 projects. I also tasted fresh lamp-post for the first time, and it was delicious: Just when you thought your town square was safe! (Photo credits go to the remarkable and mysterious fpixel.wordpress.com.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Part of this post, looking back on week 16 of 2010, was produced in a (I wish I could say speeding) train with my aging Nokia E71 tethered (by bluetooth) to my netbook. The T-Mobile unlimited mobile internet package is unfortunately still limited to 384 Kbit/s (see my <a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://www.speedtest.net/result/793759978.png" title="">speedtest.net results</a>), but I’m attached to it for its reasonable policy on internet use outside of NL.</p>
<p>In any case, during the past week I enjoyed 14 hours of meetings and completed 22 GTD tasks spread over 11 projects. I also tasted fresh lamp-post for the first time, and it was delicious:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/charl_eats_lamp_post_800.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/charl_eats_lamp_post_800.jpg"
        
            alt="Just when you thought your town square was safe! (Photo credits go to the remarkable and mysterious fpixel.wordpress.com.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Just when you thought your town square was safe! (Photo credits go to the remarkable and mysterious fpixel.wordpress.com.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The occasion for my Lilliputian culinary adventure was Peter Krekel’s participation in the Baby Tycoon entrepreneurship competition semi-finals with his start-up, Clinical Graphics. After an absolutely killer presentation, Clinical Graphics and one other of the top-notch contestants were selected to go through to the finals.  Read all about it in the <a href="http://www.clinicalgraphics.com/2010/04/22/clinical-graphics-finalist-in-baby-tycoon-award-contest/" title="Clinical Graphics post about reaching finals in Baby Tycoon.">CG press release</a>.</p>
<p>In a move completely surprising even myself, I have nothing more to say.  There’s currently some hectic pre-storm quiet which I have to appreciate…</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>