<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Mizo No Kokoro on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/mizo-no-kokoro/</link><description>Recent content in Mizo No Kokoro on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 20:21:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/mizo-no-kokoro/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #81: Middle-aged zen.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 20:21:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/</guid><description>(Warning: This post has an extremely high backyard philosophy content. Will probably greatly offend any real philosophers, and a bunch of other people I probably have not even thought about.)
I recently became middle-aged. As part of the thank you I wrote for the many kind words people posted to my facebook wall, I made a short summary of the things I had learned over the past N years. I hope you don’t mind that I post them here as well:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(Warning: This post has an extremely high backyard philosophy content. Will probably greatly offend any real philosophers, and a bunch of other people I probably have not even thought about.)</em></p>
<p>I recently became middle-aged. As part of the thank you I wrote for the many kind words people posted to my facebook wall, I made a short summary of the things I had learned over the past N years. I hope you don’t mind that I post them here as well:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>… here’s what I’ve picked up over the past decades (only two things, I’m a slow learner):</p>
<ol>
<li>Relationships – the most important thing (and maybe even the only thing) in the world.</li>
<li>Kindness – it really looks like we have unlimited quantities of this to give, but somehow there’s not as much of it going around as there could be. Let’s fix this!</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Since that note (I’ve skipped a number of weekly posts here as you might have noticed; really really busy) I have also been thinking about the relationship between one’s happiness, one’s circumstances, and the plasticity of one’s self.</p>
<p>I’ll start this little story with me during a coffee-induced zen moment:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/wpid-cpbotha_at_coffee_roasting_co.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/wpid-cpbotha_at_coffee_roasting_co.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Zen is a real thing that you can read about on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen">wikipedia</a>, in a billion blogs and also in <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://youtu.be/MOXQo7nURs0">BookBooks</a>. I don’t think that I’m deviating <strong>too</strong> far from the real deal when I use zen to describe any form of personal enlightenment, or that elevated state of self I should be striving for every moment of every day, but mostly forget to do because I get caught up in life as, ironically, I am not yet zen enough.</p>
<p>Sometimes, I find myself in a perfect little moment of warmth and humanity with close friends or family (and/or with a perfect coffee) and I am somehow able to observe and appreciate the moment in real-time from a spot somewhere outside of the conversation, for example while I’m walking to school with my daughter on a spring morning and realise that life in these simple moments is even greater than I thought. Sometimes I am briefly able to distance myself from some perceived life complexity, a distance from which everything actually looks pretty fine and then turns out to be exactly that. Was it that way to start with, did it change, or did I change?</p>
<p>I think being able to take a few (or a thousand) steps back in order to better see yourself and your situation is related to one of the few fundamental zen principles: Enlightenment through growing self-knowledge. I also somehow had in my mind that there was some connection between zen and the principle of mind like water, or <em>mizo no kokoro</em> if you prefer its prettier ring. In searching for this link, I stumbled onto <a href="http://www.goodreads.com/quotes/163198-you-must-be-shapeless-formless-like-water-when-you-pour">this Bruce Lee quote</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You must be shapeless, formless, like water. When you pour water in a cup, it becomes the cup. When you pour water in a bottle, it becomes the bottle. When you pour water in a teapot, it becomes the teapot. Water can drip and it can crash. Become like water my friend.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>During those occasional and coincidental flashes of increased perception I mentioned above the quote, when I was both in the experience and outside, at a good distance, I was able to look inwards and see how I could best change <em>me</em> to suit the situation better. The better I suit the situation, the more it agrees with me. Harmony.</p>
<p>Let me restate that: Most often I am not able to change my environment. However, I am apparently able to train my ability to change <em>me</em>, which in many cases can lead to the same desired harmonious outcome.</p>
<p>So, sort of in addition to the things I’ve learned over the past years, here are the things I strive to have cultivated when I grow up:</p>
<ul>
<li>Mindfulness, of me, the human beings I am fortunate to be surrounded with and all of the interactions between us. This includes the ability to take a thousand steps back, and to see clearly.</li>
<li>A mind like water, not to do kung fu fighting, but to be able to change and flow continuously to contribute more to harmony and happiness.</li>
</ul>
<p>Because I’m not sure how else to do this, I’m ending this story with a photo of a beer that I took during a really sunny zen moment:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-radison_jack_black.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-radison_jack_black.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Have a beautiful and harmonious week fellow humans!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>