<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>avi on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/avi/</link><description>Recent content in avi on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2009 13:27:13 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/avi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Two PowerPoint 2007 tricks that could save your life</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/10/31/two-powerpoint-2007-tricks-that-could-save-your-life/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2009 13:27:13 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/10/31/two-powerpoint-2007-tricks-that-could-save-your-life/</guid><description> On Wednesday evening I was putting the finishing touches on probably the most important presentation I’ve given in the past few years. As I was testing everything on my trusty little netbook just before bed-time, two scary problems reared their ugly heads: 1) An embedded MS-MPEG4 encoded AVI simply showed a black box when played and, perhaps even more disheartening, 2) the last and most important slide took between 4 and 6 seconds to appear.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>On Wednesday evening I was putting the finishing touches on probably the most important presentation I’ve given in the past few years.  As I was testing everything on my trusty little netbook just before bed-time, two scary problems reared their ugly heads: 1) An embedded MS-MPEG4 encoded AVI simply showed a black box when played and, perhaps even more disheartening, 2) the last and most important slide took between 4 and 6 seconds to appear.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/ms.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/ms.jpg"
        
            alt="The people that brought you PowerPoint."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The people that brought you PowerPoint.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Some of you might remember that I posted about a <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2005/03/06/hyperlinked-avis-and-powerpoint-2003/" title="Link to previous PowerPoint 2003 bug">strange PowerPoint 2003 bug and its work-around</a> back in 2005.  In short, hyperlinking to an MS-MPEG4 encoded AVI would result in a completely unnecessary warning dialogue.  Renaming the AVI to MPG made this problem go away.</p>
<p>Guess how I worked around the <strong>movie clip black box problem in PowerPoint 2007</strong>?  Yes, children, <strong>changing the file extension from AVI to MPG and re-embedding</strong> the movie-clip resulted in a perfectly-playing embedded AVI.  You can thank the clever guys and girls at Microsoft for keeping life interesting with these pleasant little surprises.</p>
<p>Problem #2 took slightly longer to solve, but Uncle Google soon had me on the <a href="http://www.tech-recipes.com/rx/1423/powerpoint_compress_and_optimize_presentations_ppt_to_decrease_size/" title="tech-recipes site with more information concerning compression of ppts">right track</a>.  The last slide in my presentation, the one that took 4 to 6 seconds to appear, was quite image-heavy.  It turns out that PowerPoint saves embedded images in a relatively inefficient non-compressed form.  This does, contrary to what we expect from MS, make sense, as one would like to retain all image information.  However, when one is doing a slide-show, the processing that has to take place scaling and displaying all images takes an inordinate amount of time.  Having an upwards of 4 second delay before the next slide appears is simply not acceptable.</p>
<p>The solution is <strong>saving a copy of your presentation, but with image compression activated</strong>.  Do “Save As” and on the bottom-left of the dialogue that appears, select the “Tools” menu button, then “Compress Pictures”, then “Options” and finally “Screen (150ppi)”.  Now “Ok” twice, then finally select a new filename and click on “Save”.  In my case, the presentation file was reduced from 10MB to 2MB, and the load time for that crucial last slide from 4 seconds (minimum) to slightly less than 1.</p>
<p>That concludes the second installment in my exciting life as a PowerPoint flunky!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>