<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Deadmau5 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/deadmau5/</link><description>Recent content in Deadmau5 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 20:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/deadmau5/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #86: Beardy.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/11/27/weekly-head-voices-86-beardy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/11/27/weekly-head-voices-86-beardy/</guid><description>You could have set your watch by the appearance of this weekly blog post! Enjoy it while you can.
Here&amp;rsquo;s a random photo from my week:
I finally figured out what planking is.
Note-taking and todo system chaos (NERD WARNING). My email-note-taking-todo-system is again slowly morphing into something strange and unknown. I once called using Trello for task management “the time management connoisseur equivalent of lying in the gutter with a cheap bottle of wine in a brown paper bag”.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>You could have set your watch by the appearance of this weekly blog post! Enjoy it while you can.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a random photo from my week:</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/wpid-millhouse_kitchen_plank.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/11/wpid-millhouse_kitchen_plank.jpg"
        
            alt="I finally figured out what planking is."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>I finally figured out what planking is.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="note-taking-and-todo-system-chaos-nerd-warning">Note-taking and todo system chaos (NERD WARNING).</h2>
<p>My email-note-taking-todo-system is again slowly morphing into something strange and unknown. I <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/comparison-of-task-managers-rtm-astrid-wunderlist-todoist/#comment-71">once called</a> using <a href="https://trello.com/">Trello</a> for task management “the time management connoisseur equivalent of lying in the gutter with a cheap bottle of wine in a brown paper bag”.</p>
<p>Well either I was just plain wrong, or I&rsquo;m lying in that gutter again and I just don&rsquo;t realize it.</p>
<p>Because I became very frustrated with all the task systems that I tried (and committed to) because all of them (including the one I designed together with big G) insist on presenting all of my tasks in neat little project-grouped or deadline-ordered lists, whilst my brain is a chaotic spread-out network that wishes to see <i>everything</i> at the same time, preferably spread out and very visual, I&rsquo;m back to using a giant Trello board (that <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2014/08/08/driving-the-dell-u2713hm-at-2650x1440-from-the-hdmi-output-of-the-acer-v3-571g/">2560×1440 monitor</a> is very slowly earning its keep).</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s perhaps better than it sounds: When I process mail on my phone or in my Emacs, I forward the ones that need action to a secret Trello address which turns said mail into a Trello card in the “incoming” list of my tasks board, including all email attachments and images. Sometimes I&rsquo;m naughty, and I reply to the sender summarising the list of actions I will attempt to undertake, and then Bcc that reply to Trello.</p>
<p>On that Trello board I have lists for reminding me of the important projects I have to remember to work on, and then lists for <code>ASAP</code>, <code>This week</code>, <code>Later (scheduled)</code> and <code>Someday / ideas</code>. I also have lists called <code>Done (week WEEKNUM)</code> into which I can move cards once I&rsquo;ve taken care of them. After a few weeks, I archive the whole <code>done</code> list of a particular week for posterity. It also doesn&rsquo;t hurt that <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.trello">the Trello Android app</a> is quite beautiful.</p>
<p>On the notes front, I&rsquo;m currently very much in love with <a href="http://orgmode.org/">Emacs org-mode</a>, as you might have guessed from <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2014/11/20/weekly-head-voices-85-gone-south/">last week&rsquo;s WHV</a>. What I did not mention then, is that I now also have a date-stamped .org jourrnal for each project that I&rsquo;m working on. From each general daily .org journal I link to the various project journal .org files for that day. Based on these daily / project-based log files, I can generate high-quality LaTeX reports, <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2014/06/16/level-sets-the-practical-10-minute-introduction/">technical blog posts</a> and even presentations, if only I can remember the exact sequence of 17 emacs keyboard shortcuts to do so. As mentioned previously, I use <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/deft-turbo">deft-turbo</a> to navigate my notes database.</p>
<p>I still dream of an even more graphical and non-linear way of doing all of this.</p>
<h2 id="musings-on-beards-real-men-warning">Musings on beards (REAL MEN WARNING).</h2>
<p>Besides being the sign of a true man, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beard#The_.22Philosopher.27s_beard.22">the internet says</a> that the beard was “seen as the defining characteristic of the philosopher; philosophers had to have beards, and anyone with a beard was assumed to be a philosopher”. Based on extensive research, I can assure you that this is still the case.</p>
<p>On a slightly more serious note, I might be getting slightly beard-rospective, because my hairy face-friend might really have to disappear soon. I&rsquo;m going to have to do my part in an academic committee or two, and I&rsquo;m going to have to cross borders into the EU. The former might not be such an issue, but my current slightly middle-eastern look might not be the best option in terms of the latter.</p>
<p>In any case, before I reluctantly join the shaven masses, I would like to share with you two realizations from the perspective of a weirdly bearded man.</p>
<p>In my town, there are no hipsters. There probably will never be. That, plus the fact that I deviate significantly from the text-book hipster look, means I get recognized everywhere I go. I think this is partly due to appearing different from most other people I would normally be pigeon-holed with. Subtly complementary to this is the fact that my face has become a kind of a graphical icon of itself: If you were to take a photo of it, and you were to scale it down to 32×32 pixels, you&rsquo;d probably still be able to recognize it. The upshot of this is that even when I&rsquo;ve visited a restaurant or café only once, the next time, weeks afterwards, I am treated like a long-time regular. That&rsquo;s pretty cool.</p>
<p>More important than this, is the fact that people now experience difficulty applying their pigeon-holing mechanism. Around these parts, there is far too much assumed piece-wise homogeneity. In other words, people are used to believing that they are able to stereotype you after one look. I have now experienced that when I have contact with locals, their little stereotyping sensors start smoking a little bit and then fizzle out. There is usually a short moment of panic, but then we start afresh, which is nice.</p>
<h2 id="while-12">While (1&lt;2).</h2>
<p>I would like to leave you with this track from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/While(1_Is_Less_Than_2)">deadmau5&rsquo;s latest album</a>. I&rsquo;m doing this, because it&rsquo;s an extremely surprising album. You should definitely listen to the whole work, but this track should serve as an example of the <i>while (1&lt;2)</i> surprise.</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<div class="embed-vimeo" style="text-align: center;">
<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="473" mozallowfullscreen="" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/101257125" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="840"></iframe>
</div>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>