<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>phd on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/phd/</link><description>Recent content in phd on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2014 19:10:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/phd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #87: Good Reads.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/12/04/weekly-head-voices-87-good-reads/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2014 19:10:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/12/04/weekly-head-voices-87-good-reads/</guid><description> Two days ago, I received this in the mail: For various reasons I was temporarily ever-so-slightly misty-eyed. Well-done boys, I’m SUPER proud of you!
Other books you might also like. I’ve recently finished reading two other mind-expanding books:
The Three Body Problem by Liu Cixin: Liu Cixin is a wildly popular Chinese science fiction author. I found this recently translated first edition of a trilogy to be an awesome first peek into modern Chinese science fiction.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Two days ago, I received this in the mail:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/wpid-proefschriften_peter_kok_stef_busking.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/12/wpid-proefschriften_peter_kok_stef_busking.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>
</p>
<p>For various reasons I was temporarily ever-so-slightly misty-eyed. Well-done boys, I’m <strong>SUPER</strong> proud of you!</p>
<h2 id="other-books-you-might-also-like">Other books you might also like.</h2>
<p>I’ve recently finished reading two other mind-expanding books:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20518872-the-three-body-problem">The Three Body Problem by Liu Cixin</a>: Liu Cixin is a wildly popular Chinese science fiction author. I found this recently translated first edition of a trilogy to be an awesome first peek into modern Chinese science fiction. The translator, Ken Liu, managed to produce an English version of this story that still managed to bring across themes of Chinese history and culture. On top of that, you also get a computer consisting of 30 million soldiers arranged into inter-connected logic gates (think that’s far-fetched?), artificially intelligent quantum entangled photons (told you), and much more. I’ll be lining up as soon as the translations of part 2 and 3 appear.</p>
<p>I read <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuromancer">William Gibson’s Neuromancer</a> probably shortly after it was published in 1984. At that stage, I compensated for lack of internet by working my way through the local library, book by book. Through the succeeding years, as the internet came onto the scene, and cyberspace became more of a reality, I’ve re-read Neuromancer a number of times. Each time, it caused more goose-bumps than the previous.</p>
<p>In my eyes, Gibson already deserved his status as <i>literary</i> author many times over. With <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Peripheral">The Peripheral</a>, he has shown, in an exceptionally suave and absolutely in-control way, that he is the <i>final boss</i> of modern writing. The number of mind-bending ideas that he develops, whilst fleshing out characters that feel more real than some real people, all the while masterfully having the reader ride along with the two protagonists and having us figure out the story along with them, is nothing short of amazing. (Yes people, I am positively gushing. It’s that good.)</p>
<h2 id="other-news">Other news.</h2>
<ul>
<li>The OSSSA core team has recently doubled in size. There are two of us
now. Thanks to the <a href="https://twitter.com/lgmarincowitz">extremely
welcome addition</a>, we are now <a href="http://osssa.org.za/2014/12/02/call-for-information-do-you-or-does-your-organization-work-with-open-source-software-please-send-us-your-info/">actively
busy gathering information</a> on all open source software entities in South
Africa, so that we can create the go-to resource for this. If you’re in
SA, and you’re into OSS, please respond!</li>
<li>Due to a whole team of intrepid Dutch adventurers with fairly concrete plans,
please look for the Dutch Bicycle Repair and Pimping Shop at <a href="http://afrikaburn.com/the-event/afrikaburn-2014">AfrikaBurn 2015</a>,
because you might just find <i>us</i>!</li>
</ul>
<p>Have a great week people, wherever you are!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>On the importance of taking notes. [Weekly Head Voices #38]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2011 22:39:52 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/</guid><description> Post summary: Part one is about friends graduating from Evil School, part two is rather short mentioning vague bits of good news and part three is 100% time management and productivity boosting goodness! Feel free to skip, skim or reorder!
One On Thursday, February 10, 2011, my dear friend Mister Krekel graduated from Evil School after years of hard work and evil-doing, and will henceforth go through life as the formidable Doctor Krekel.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Part one is about friends graduating from Evil School, part two is rather short mentioning vague bits of good news and part three is 100% time management and productivity boosting goodness! Feel free to skip, skim or reorder!</em></p>
<h2 id="one">One</h2>
<p>On Thursday, February 10, 2011, my dear friend Mister Krekel graduated from Evil School after years of hard work and evil-doing, and will henceforth go through life as the formidable Doctor Krekel. Please do watch out.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_school_by_fmalan.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_school_by_fmalan.jpg"
        
            alt="Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The joyous transition took place in the Evil School’s Academiegebouw in Leiden, and this time yours truly (I’m referring to me in a round-about fashion) even had the great honour of playing a part in the formal proceedings. If you’re curious as to what exactly this ritual constitutes, see <a href="/2010/05/29/augmentation-weekly-head-voices-23/" title="previous edition of the WHV also on PhD defences in Leiden">this previous edition of the WHV</a> on the graduation of another terribly evil colleague. I believe that the bunch of us now constitute a bona fide Axis of Evil. No, the evil jokes can unfortunately not stop yet.</p>
<p>The Party was held in a secret cafe nearby. You will notice that I’ve capitalised Party, as it was not your average run of the mill Evil School graduation affair, but a social event of note. Here in Holland, the PhD defence and graduation are a combined affair, and so the whole day is dedicated to just one person. It is actually very special: People take time off from work, sometimes even temporarily put aside their differences, and travel from all over to attend the festivities. It’s like a wedding, except that there’s only one of you. I can only recommend it very highly. At the Party, everyone had clearly read the memo, and they were there with that singular goal in mind: Celebrate the freshly minted Evil Doctor. Presents were given, speeches were held, photos were shown, beer was imbibed and, flying in the face of all advice concerning the mixing of alcohol, cameras and social networking, the <a href="http://fpixel.wordpress.com/" title="link to the evil photographer">best evil photographer in town</a>, who’s coincidentally also in Evil School, took the most amazing photos that you should be able to see on Facebook if you’re one of the privileged few to belong to The Network, also known as <em>The Friends of the Axis of Evil</em>.</p>
<h2 id="two">Two</h2>
<p>On the good news front, you&rsquo;ll see (or not) on the <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/program.php" title="list of eurovis 2011 conditional accepts">list of EuroVis 2011 conditional accepts</a>, that a paper by cool colleagues from far away, to which I contributed a small part, has been conditionally accepted, and hence has a significant chance of being presented at said event in Bergen, Norway (May 31 to June 3). We also have plans to submit a poster (or two), so there&rsquo;s an even more significant chance that I will make an appearance at this fantastic conference! We&rsquo;re also cooking up various odds and ends that will hopefully crystallise sufficiently by the end of March to be submissible for VisWeek 2011. Cross yer fingers.</p>
<h2 id="three">Three</h2>
<p>Today&rsquo;s backyard time management section is in fact more about planning than it is about notes. However, my Pro-Tips involve combining them in an easy to implement productivity booster. When people start out in research, one of the first bits of advice they get is keeping some kind of lab journal. I think this advice applies to more than just research: If you do any kind of independent or project work, jotting down your activities, thoughts and results during the day is useful in helping to structure your thought processes, and also very helpful when you have to backtrack a complex multi-day procedure. During my Ph.D., I filled a number of real cardboard-and-paper books with notes. More recently, I&rsquo;ve started using Google Documents for the same purpose. Besides all the other advantages, having to document explicitly your work output keeps you productive and on your toes.</p>
<h3 id="pro-tip-1">Pro Tip #1</h3>
<p><em>Keep a lab journal, even if you don&rsquo;t work in a lab.</em></p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="/2011/01/09/2011-a-cyber-suburban-odyssey-weekly-head-voices-35/" title="2011 start post">mentioned before</a> that my resolutions for 2011 included more concrete planning. This has manifested in a work-in-progress planning for the whole year, including milestones, awards won, and so forth, but much more practically, it has manifested in a little lab-journal-compatible trick. Every morning when I sit down to begin the day, I spend a few minutes thinking and then start the day&rsquo;s journal entry by writing down, as concretely as possible, the tasks that I plan to complete by the end of the day. This also ensures that I spend effort on the <em>important</em> things, and not only on the urgent things. So, that brings us to:</p>
<h3 id="pro-tip-2">Pro Tip #2</h3>
<p><em>At the start of each day, write down in your lab journal exactly and
concretely what you plan to accomplish by the end of that day.</em></p>
<p>These pro tips appear to be quite straight-forward, but together they help one
to focus, and to keep tabs on one&rsquo;s <em>effective</em> productivity. In other words,
just being terribly busy the whole day gets you nothing; the trick is being
terribly busy in all the right directions.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Somebody is clearly pushing the boundaries of awesomeness… cowboys AND aliens!</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/In-m2RJw3hE?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Sometimes, being in academia rules. [Weekly Head Voices #25]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/28/sometimes-being-in-academia-rules-weekly-head-voices-25/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2010 20:41:50 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/06/28/sometimes-being-in-academia-rules-weekly-head-voices-25/</guid><description> Kids! It’s now truly summer over here, which means as much as possible time outside, which means less time available for writing blog posts. However, weeks 24 and 25 of 2010 contained such newsworthy items, that I’m simply forced to trade some sun-light for a bit of TFT exposure. In this post, we talk flowers, PhD defences, scientific talks, funny Js and finally stick figures, so please stick around! I took this photo of the Oude Kerk in Delft as we were taking a walk with one of our esteemed guests.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Kids!  It’s now truly summer over here, which means as much as possible time outside, which means less time available for writing blog posts. However, weeks 24 and 25 of 2010 contained such newsworthy items, that I’m simply forced to trade some sun-light for a bit of TFT exposure. In this post, we talk flowers, PhD defences, scientific talks, funny Js and finally stick figures, so please stick around!








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/delft_oude_kerk_1280x960.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/delft_oude_kerk_1280x960-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="I took this photo of the Oude Kerk in Delft as we were taking a walk with one of our esteemed guests. So it&#39;s really relevant to this post, ok?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>I took this photo of the Oude Kerk in Delft as we were taking a walk with one of our esteemed guests. So it's really relevant to this post, ok?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Last week we had our department’s yearly BBQ at the Blue Lagoon at Scheveningen.  In a not altogether surprising turn of events, I’ve been working at the TU for 10 years, and I now have the bunch of orange flowers to show for it! Time is really fun when you’re having flies.</p>
<p>Five of my MedVis (that’s <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/in4307" title="MedVis IN4307 website">IN4307</a>; if you’re at the TU, make sure you take this life-changing course! :P ) students presented their final project work. Between the visualisations of coronary stents from optical coherence tomography data, the 3D lung volume reduction surgery (LVRS) planning tool and the real-time X-Ray simulator, I was hugely and pleasantly impressed.  Expect to see a large part of this functionality in a future release of <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Projects/DeVIDE" title="compulsory link to DeVIDE">DeVIDE</a>. This was energy-producing event #1 of the past two weeks. Energy-producing event #2 was a M.Sc. defence that I opposed just this past Friday, where the candidate presented and defended, in a highly-entertaining and convincing fashion, his thesis on investigating 3D synthetic aperture radar construction on multi-core architectures.</p>
<p>Energy-producing event #3 was when the now freshly minted <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/~eric/" title="Eric Griffith's homepage">Dr Eric Griffith</a> defended his PhD thesis on <em><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Griffith2010" title="Link to Eric's PhD page">Visualizing Cumulus Clouds in Virtual Reality</a></em> in stellar fashion.  Dr Griffith did a superb job of maintaining an eloquent discussion with all 7 of his opponents. The offence of <a href="http://www.cs.rug.nl/~roe/" title="homepage Prof. Jos Roerdink">Prof Jos Roerdink</a> (Visualisation, Groningen) also deserves mention: The multi-level questions and typically professorial delivery were most entertaining.</p>
<p>The final energy-producing event that I’m going to mention has been named #4 for mysterious reasons, and, for other reasons that will soon become clear, was for me the most significant. <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/~jorik/" title="Jorik's homepage">Jorik Blaas</a>, close collaborator and friend for the past seven (7!) years, defended his PhD on the <em><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Blaas2010" title="Link to Jorik's PhD page">Visual Analysis of Multi-Field Data</a></em>, on Thursday June 24. To take part in the offence, we were extremely honoured to welcome three <em>luminaries</em> of my research field (that’s Visualisation, for those of you who’ve just joined!): <a href="http://www.win.tue.nl/~vanwijk/" title="homepage Prof. Jack van Wijk">Prof.dr. Jack van Wijk</a>, <a href="http://www.itn.liu.se/~andyn/" title="homepage Prof.dr. Anders Ynnerman">Prof.dr. Anders Ynnerman</a> and the Viennese-Bergenesque <a href="http://www.ii.uib.no/vis/team/hauser/" title="homepage Prof.dr. Helwig Hauser">Prof.dr. Helwig Hauser</a>. Having all three of them in Delft was just <strong>WOW</strong>, you just have to trust me on this. In any case, for the first time at the TU, I was also allowed to take my place in the PhD committee. :)</p>
<p>Of course, Dr Blaas sailed through the defence, his usual understated yet verbally effective hyper-intelligent self. Invited lectures by our guests, much late night discussion on the nature of (visualisation) science and of life in general and finally a PhD party that stress-tested all glandular resilience helped to turn this into one seriously wonderful and life-affirming week. I am thankful to all involved.</p>
<p>In completely unrelated news:</p>
<ul>
<li>Have you ever wondered what that funnily isolated ‘J’ character is doing at the end of sentences in emails?  Well, <a href="http://chris.pirillo.com/j-smiley-outlook-email-problem-and-fix/" title="funny J in emails">wonder no more</a>! (5-second-version: it’s supposed to be a smiley, but Outlook on the sending side substitutes it with a character from the Wingdings font that is rendered at the receiving side, if that font is not available, as a ‘J’)</li>
<li>My 4-year old daughter recently made a drawing with two stick figures standing next to each other. Not significant as such, but the one stick figure was wearing a bow tie, while the other stick figure had a thought bubble above its head with a bow tie in it.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thank you for joining me again for this edition of the Weekly Head Voices, and please feel free to kick-off completely unrelated discussions in the comments.  Next week (actually this week, I’m late), four of us will be going to Leipzig for the bi-annual Eurographics workshop on <a href="http://vcbm.org/2010" title="EG VCBM 2010 website">Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine (VCBM)</a>, which I’ll probably be reporting on in a future blog post (and hopefully on twitter with hashtag <a href="http://twitter.com/search?q=%23vcbm2010" title="link to twitter hashtag #vcbm2010">#vcbm2010</a>). Stay tuned for much fun and excitement!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Augmentation [Weekly Head Voices #23]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/05/29/augmentation-weekly-head-voices-23/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2010 18:37:03 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/05/29/augmentation-weekly-head-voices-23/</guid><description> (This edition is about babies, textbook Ph.D. defences and mind-viruses in Snow Crash, all of which can mostly be filed under backyard-philosophy(ish).)
On the theme of striving for The Next Level, my not-quite-1-month-old bundle of joy laughed out loud today for the first time! I&amp;rsquo;m sure that it was not a false alarm, as I was being my usual comedic genius self (I target the 1 to 3 month-old crowd), and the pattern of stimulus and reaction was just too well-coordinated and sustained to be coincidental.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(This edition is about babies, textbook Ph.D. defences and mind-viruses in Snow Crash, all of which can mostly be filed under backyard-philosophy(ish).)</em></p>
<p><strong>On the theme of striving for</strong> <strong><a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/05/13/the-next-level-weekly-head-voices-22/" title="next level blog post">The Next Level</a></strong>, my
not-quite-1-month-old bundle of joy laughed out loud today for the first time!
I&rsquo;m sure that it was not a false alarm, as I was being my usual <em>comedic
genius self</em> (I target the 1 to 3 month-old crowd), and the pattern of stimulus
and reaction was just too well-coordinated and sustained to be coincidental.</p>
<p><strong>On the theme of really cool events</strong>, on Thursday I had the privilege of being part of the <em>Best Ph.D. Defence EVAR</em>. Seriously people, the day that my good friend Frans Steenbrink became my good friend Dr. Frans Steenbrink will pleasantly resonate in my mind for a long time to come.</p>
<figure>
<a href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2010/05/matrix_fight.jpg">
<img alt="" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2010/05/matrix_fight.jpg"/>
</a>
<figcaption>
A typical scene during an average Ph.D. defence. The candidate is in the
middle, surrounded by committee members on both sides. At this very moment, he
is investigating two possible lines of argument.
</figcaption>
</figure> 
<p>Here in NL, a Ph.D. defence is a fantastic affair: The candidate has to defend his work against the highly-experienced offensive mental manoeuvres of a committee consisting of around 7 wise men, most of them grizzled veteran professors who have eaten many a hapless candidate FOR BREAKFAST! As if that weren’t awe-inspiring enough, the defence usually takes place in some imposing building, preferably more than a few hundred years old (in this case, it was the <a href="http://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Academiegebouw_(Leiden)" title="Wikipedia page for Academiegebouw">Academiegebouw in Leiden</a>, almost 500 hundred years old), the committee are in full academic (read: battle) garb, and the whole affair is public, so the candidate is joined by a potentially sizeable audience. Believe me, this can be a nauseatingly stressful experience.</p>
<p>Of course Dr. Steenbrink handled the whole affair with elegance and, extremely unusually, a healthy dose of humour. It might be the first time that I’ve ever seen a candidate disarm his opponents not only by artfully responding to their questions, but with an ever-so-slightly irreverent injection of humour. It was beautiful.</p>
<p>After the successful defence, we were all picked up by a boat and taken via the Leiden canals to <a href="http://www.poort.nl/content/view/12/26/" title="De Poort website">De Poort</a> for the after-party, and what an after-party it was… Besides the live performance of <a href="http://www.frederiksteenbrink.com/" title="Frédérik Steenbrink website">Frédérik Steenbrink</a>, the <a href="http://www.myspace.com/sonocracymain" title="Link to Sonocracy">two electro DJs</a>, the superb saxophonist who was able to accompany them musically (!!!), the Louis Theroux-style documentary put together by <a href="http://www.clinicalgraphics.com/" title="Website of Mr Cricket's business">Mr Cricket</a>, and copious amounts of free beer, it was positively life-affirming to see the Master of Good Karma (the freshly minted doctor goes by many names) being surrounded by his Karma-children, all emanating. You need to know him in order to understand this completely, but you have to trust me that it was beautiful.</p>
<p><strong>On the theme of understated super-heroes</strong>, I finally got around to reading Neal Stephenson’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snow_Crash" title="Wikipedia page explaining Snow Crash">Snow Crash</a>, triggered by a <a href="http://boingboing.net/2010/05/09/snow-crash-cosanostr.html" title="Cosa Nostra t-shirt on boingboing">Cosa Nostra t-shirt shown on boingboing</a>. I know I know, I could have lost my Cyberpunk Nerd membership card for only reading it this late in my life…</p>
<p>In any case, I really enjoyed the book, especially for the characters (the protagonist, called Hiro Protagonist, is naturally a half-African American half-Korean hacker / sword-fighter / pizza delivery guy), the far-out society (the world is run by private franchises, amongst others the Mafia, owner of the extremely influential Cosa Nostra pizza chain and run by the charismatic Uncle Enzo), the crazy technological artefacts (the Rat Things!) and for all the changes in society brought about by the crazy technology, not least of which the Metaverse. The Metaverse is the name Stephenson gave to his extrapolation of various phenomena present or considered in 1992: The internet, virtual reality, Gibsonian cyberspace. The protagonists spend a portion of their time not quite jacked in, but with augmented reality goggles and high-fidelity ear-phones, walking around as avatars in an artificial world with a total population of slightly less than what facebook has now, if I remember correctly.</p>
<p>Personally, I didn’t find Snowcrash quite as good as Gibson’s Neuromancer (see <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2002/08/15/william-gibson-knew-it-then/" title="Link to my Neuromancer blurb.">my 2003 ode here</a>. it still gives me goose-flesh…), but somehow, very sneakily, it has still managed to manoeuvre itself into my list of all-time favourite books.</p>
<p>The story is built around the interesting idea of a neuro-linguistic virus, that is a certain sequence of sounds that is somehow able to get into the human deep brain, screw things up royally and spread through verbal contact with other humans. It has a cyberspace equivalent called Snow Crash: If programmers in the Metaverse see this specially coded binary image (through their AR interfaces), their brains essentially crash and they’re turned into vegetables. It’s all very complex (see <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snow_Crash" title="Snow Crash wikipedia page">this wikipedia page</a>) and quite far fetched, but the idea of considering certain large-scale social phenomena as a kind of mind-virus, that is a potentially damaging entity that integrates at very low level with its host, is self-replicating and is able to spread to other humans, is intriguing to say the least.</p>
<p>Recall that Dawkins partly coined the by now well-known English term <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meme" title="Wikipedia page on memes">“meme”</a> in his 1976 book, The Selfish Gene, as it turns out that the concept was more or less first written about by Semon in 1904. A meme, analogous to a gene, is an element of social information, for example the mistaken idea that going outside in cold weather increases the chances of getting a cold (in this case, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/09/27/weekly-head-voices-5-google-docs-netbook-karma-common-cold/" title="my blog post on cold not causing colds">not true</a>, but still a meme). Analogous to a biological virus, a mind-virus would then be built up from various memes. Each meme would take care of a different function of the mind-virus, helping to guarantee its survival and proliferation throughout humankind, for example: Don’t question me (meme1), believe in me (meme2), spread me (meme3), be exclusively faithful to me (meme4), do this or you will be severely punished (meme5), do this and you will be greatly rewarded (meme6).</p>
<p>If you’re wondering what I mean by all of this, rest assured in the fact that <a href="http://zombo.com/" title="Zombo Com website">Zombo Com</a> has all the answers.</p>
<p>Kids, now go and have yourselves a fantastic week!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>