<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Commentary on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/categories/commentary/</link><description>Recent content in Commentary on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 10:05:10 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/categories/commentary/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Let’s replace Twitter with something much better.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 10:05:10 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/19/lets-replace-twitter-with-something-much-better/</guid><description> (There is also a Russian language version of this post available, translated and published by SoftDroid on 2017-04-12.)
I love Twitter. I love that by following certain people, my timeline has become a stream of interesting and entertaining information. I love that sometimes I am able to fit my little publication just so into the 140 characters given to me. I found The Trumpocalypse truly depressing, but the joke tweets were golden:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(There is also a <a href="http://softdroid.net/chem-zamenit-twitter-alternativa">Russian language version of this post available</a>, translated and published by <a href="http://softdroid.net/">SoftDroid</a> on 2017-04-12.)</em></p>
<h1 id="i-love-twitter">I love Twitter.</h1>
<p>I love that by following certain people, my timeline has become a stream of interesting and entertaining information. I love that sometimes I am able to fit my little publication just <em>so</em> into the 140 characters given to me. I found The Trumpocalypse truly depressing, but the joke tweets were golden:</p>








<figure><a href="https://twitter.com/AFLNow/status/796210777241710592">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/2016-11-19-112633_665x359_scrot.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I love that Twitter is so widely accessible and utilised. For example here in South Africa, if you make a small effort, you can get great, grassroots-level inputs from all corners of our political spectrum. This has helped me tremendously to try and understand our complicated environment a little better.</p>
<h1 id="however">However…</h1>
<p>I really don’t like that we are all putting our content, including those golden joke tweets, into someone else’s silo. You’re giving Twitter full control over all of your content. That’s a huge price to pay for the exposure, especially in the light of the fact that there are user-controlled alternatives.</p>
<p>Also, with Twitter’s commercial survival <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/david-giannetto/the-future-of-twitter-sta_b_9232280.html">often being debated</a>, can we really trust this budding public service (it has become that central) with our public history?</p>
<p>Far more importantly, Twitter is doing a really <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2016/10/19/13328380/twitter-abuse-disney-salesforce-bids-pulled">bad job at keeping abusive users and abuse out of the system</a>. Users have very little power against abusive groups. There have been a great number of cases when users were forced to leave Twitter, in effect being muzzled, due to direct and concerted abuse.</p>
<p>This can’t be right.</p>
<h1 id="couldwe-replace-twitter-with-something-better">Could we replace Twitter with something better?</h1>
<p>Yes, I think we can.</p>
<p>Blogs and RSS, the latter a system for subscribing to a collection of blogs, and being able to read their posts in a single chronological stream, almost exactly like Twitter, have been around forever.</p>
<p>Setting up a blog at for example <a href="https://wordpress.com/">WordPress.com</a> is not much more complicated than creating a new Twitter account. Readers can subscribe to your blog using any number of apps, for example the <a href="https://en.blog.wordpress.com/2013/05/29/wordpress-reader/">WordPress.com Reader</a> or any other so-called aggregator, such as <a href="http://www.inoreader.com/">Inoreader</a> or <a href="https://feedly.com/i/welcome">Feedly</a>. Your list of subscriptions can be freely exported from one aggregator and imported into another.</p>
<p>Instead of posting your 140 character masterpiece via the Twitter app, you would do so via the <a href="https://apps.wordpress.com/mobile/">WordPress app</a>. You can write short tweets, or long essays, with as much embedded media and with as much typesetting as you like.</p>
<p>By default, you have to moderate (approve or deny) comments on any of your posts. Bye-bye abusive users. In fact, you’re able to muzzle <em>them</em>, which is how it should be. This is <em>your</em> content and <em>your</em> voice after all. However, they are also free to start their own blogs of course. Everyone else is free never to go there.</p>
<p>Furthermore, your content can be easily exported into a self-hosted blog (using the open source wordpress.org software), such as this one, where you truly control the whole system. In all cases, the content is yours to do with as you please.</p>
<h1 id="what-needs-to-happen">What needs to happen?</h1>
<p>It looks like all the components of the solution have been right here all along.</p>
<p>However, to become as accessible as Twitter, they definitely require some polish (this used to be “a little polish”, but commenter AJ made valid points) .</p>
<p>If for example the WordPress app became as straight-forward as the Twitter app, for setting up a new blog, for posting and for reading all of your followed blogs, that would be great.</p>
<p>If the WordPress app, or any alternative, could come up with a streamlined user story for the posting of short (approximately 140 characters maybe?! :) snippets, that would be even better. (If you did not know about post formats yet, <a href="https://en.support.wordpress.com/posts/post-formats/">check them out</a>. For exmample, the “aside” post format is a way to post a short title-less snippet to your blog.)</p>
<p>Furthermore, we definitely need a good discovery platform. This is the thing where Twitter will recommend new accounts to follow based on your existing subscriptions. WordPress does something similar, but it has to be much more discoverable.</p>
<p>In the coming weeks, I will be running a little experiment by trying to post even my short, previously twitter-only blurbs to this blog. I will have to cross-tweet these, but at least the primary source will be right here in my own database.</p>
<p>What do you think? Is this possible? Is it something you would like?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>South Africa, why are you not running Linux?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/05/31/south-africa-why-are-you-not-running-linux/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 May 2014 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/05/31/south-africa-why-are-you-not-running-linux/</guid><description> Ubuntu, my personal favourite Linux distribution, has recently released version 14.04 LTS. LTS stands for Long Term Support: LTS releases are supported for 5 years, meaning that with 14.04 you are covered until 2019.
Trusty Tahr, as 14.04 is known, is beautiful, functional and still free. Ubuntu means “humanity to others”. It also means pretty desktop!
This seemed like an opportune moment to get something off my chest. I’m trying to understand why South Africa, my current home, is not running more Linux.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Ubuntu, my personal favourite Linux distribution, has recently released version 14.04 LTS. LTS stands for Long Term Support: LTS releases are supported for 5 years, meaning that with 14.04 you are covered until 2019.</p>
<p>Trusty Tahr, as 14.04 is known, is beautiful, functional and still free.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-screenie-ubuntu-1404.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/wpid-screenie-ubuntu-1404-1024x576.jpg"
        
            alt="Ubuntu means “humanity to others”. It also means pretty desktop!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Ubuntu means “humanity to others”. It also means pretty desktop!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>This seemed like an opportune moment to get something off my chest. I’m trying to understand why South Africa, my current home, is not running more Linux. In this post, I’m going to summarise the reasons why I think that, especially in SA, we should move away from proprietary solutions such as those offered by Microsoft and Apple, to solutions that are technically at least as good, are completely open and free, and, perhaps most importantly, better empower us to stimulate our local technology ecosystem and the national economy.</p>
<h2 id="cost-to-the-national-economy">Cost to the national economy</h2>
<p>Every year, I and a few million other South Africans pay a boat load of income and other taxes. Because in SA not everyone is able to pay tax, it is <i>especially</i> important that this money is used for the common good, for issues such as health-care, education and job creation.</p>
<p>However, instead of using my hard-earned tax to stimulate local industry, the South African government is sending millions of rands, each and every year, to Microsoft, a fantastically rich company in the USA, a fantastically rich country in comparison to South Africa.</p>
<p>The majority of government workstations absolutely don’t need MS Windows, MS Office or Outlook. The majority of government employees would be able to do their job (email, reports, spreadsheets, forms, use of web-apps) better and more securely using Linux.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the use of Linux and open source software encourages the use of open standards for public documentation. In 2007, the SA government <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenDocument_adoption#South_Africa">officially standardised on the OpenDocument format</a>. However, MS Office use is still rife, and encourages people to use Microsoft’s own XML formats. Although MS standardised these in a bid to stay in the global government game, OpenDocument should be preferred, as it’s better supported by more free and open packages that are available to all citizens, not just those with money for MS Windows and MS Office.</p>
<p>As an added but very important advantage, some of the considerable funds that would have been sent to the USA for MS licensing and support would then be injected into the local Linux support economy, stimulating local skills and creating more high-tech jobs.</p>
<p>Don’t you find it strange that South Africa, a developing country, is sending that much money to the USA when better solutions exist? Don’t you too think that it would be great to have a thriving and more independent Linux-based operating system and application industry right here in SA?</p>
<h2 id="personal-cost">Personal cost</h2>
<p>I <a href="http://mygaming.co.za/news/news/46487-windows-8-versions-sa-pricing-detailed.html">just</a> checked, it looks like the cost for an OEM license of Windows 8 in SA is R1000. We want as many as possible South Africans to have access to computers and to have access to internet. You can get a cheap PC for R3000 to R4000. It really makes absolutely no sense to spend R1000 on Windows, when Linux would work perfectly well on that same PC hardware.</p>
<p>It gets even more silly when you add in the price of MS Office. For 95% of personal users, packages like OpenOffice or LibreOffice, completely free and even open source, or Google Docs, not open but free, are more than sufficient.</p>
<p>A part of the problem here is simply momentum. Because everyone is still using Microsoft products, everyone thinks that that’s what you need to have. Imagine that the government standardised on Linux, it would not take long before people would then evaluate this as a serious choice when acquiring a new PC.</p>
<h2 id="security">Security</h2>
<p>For the largest part due to Edward Snowden’s actions, and great journalism by The Guardian, it is now widely known (and much has been corroborated), that the NSA and other intelligence agencies around the world have been eavesdropping on everyone and everything.</p>
<p>An important part of this practice, is the working relationships that these intelligence agencies have built up with software vendors around the world. When you run MS Windows or Mac OSX, or any other prioprietary software, you have absolutely no way of knowing, or checking, what your computer is doing with your information. It sounds like something from a spy movie, but <a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2013/06/nsa-gets-early-access-to-zero-day-data-from-microsoft-others/">the NSA works closely with Microsoft to be able to hack into computers running Windows</a>.</p>
<p>In the case of personal use, this may not be such a problem, but in the case of the South African government and the whole corporate world, it’s slightly crazy that everyone is willing to take the risk that all of their information is being snooped on by cooperating intelligence agencies.</p>
<p>With open source systems one can’t be 100% sure either, but one is able to check and modify and part of the system, at the source code level, that one is working on. Based on this openness, I have personally in the past programmed kernel drivers to support new hardware, and fixed low-level driver bugs. This was possible only because I have access to the source code of everything on my system.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>There you have at least three reasons why we here in SA should be running more Linux. Not doing so is costing our national economy money, and it’s costing our people money. More importantly, we’re missing a huge opportunity of technologically and economically empowering South Africans.</p>
<p>A more general point I would like to make, is the following. It turns out that the whole world is <a href="file:///2013/06/16/dont-dream-big/">actually running Linux already</a>: android telephones, tablets, TVs, zillions of servers, and so on. When you teach people how to use this open and free Linux system instead of the proprietary alternatives, you are in fact teaching them how to control the world.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>You must vaccinate</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/05/21/you-must-vaccinate/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2009 09:02:02 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/05/21/you-must-vaccinate/</guid><description> Image courtesy of dbtechno.com. I was mistakenly under the impression that, at least in my social circles, the whole vaccination issue had been put completely to rest, but based on the number of serious questions that I’ve been asked recently, this unfortunately does not seem to be the case.
For those of you who don’t have time, I’ll cut to the chase immediately:
Yes, you simply must vaccinate your children.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<img alt="" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/05/vaccine_autism_vaccinations.jpg" style="margin-left: 0px;"/>
<figcaption>Image courtesy of dbtechno.com.</figcaption>
</figure> 
<p>I was mistakenly under the impression that, at least in my social circles, the
whole vaccination issue had been put completely to rest, but based on the
number of serious questions that I’ve been asked recently, this
unfortunately does not seem to be the case.</p>
<p>For those of you who don’t have time, I’ll cut to the chase immediately:</p>
<p><strong>Yes, you simply <em>must</em> vaccinate your children.  This is the <em>best and
safest</em> choice, for both your child and your fellow humans.</strong></p>
<p><strong>No, there is no link between vaccination and autism. No, spreading out the
(MMR) vaccinations is not safer, it is in fact more dangerous.  Also, the
“vaccine overload” hypothesis is flawed.</strong></p>
<p>For those of you with a bit more time or those of you who are not willing to take me on my word, I’ll go into some more detail on each of the points mentioned above.  Most of what I write here is based on articles in the Wikipedia.  I’ve deliberately done this, because these articles are accessible and readable to everyone, and they do link to the original scientific articles that they are based on.  Feel free to jump to any section.  Also, each section ends with a short summary of its contents to make it easier for you to skip.</p>
<h1 id="recent-history">Recent history</h1>
<p><em>This section is based on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MMR_vaccine_controversy" title="Wikipedia article on MMR vaccine controversy">Wikipedia article on the MMR vaccine
controversy</a>.</em></p>
<p>In 1998, Andre Wakefield and co-authors published a paper in the Lancet where,
based on 12 case reports, they speculated on a possible link between the MMR
vaccination and autism, and also speculated that it might be better to space
out the vaccinations.  Of course the press and media picked this up and went
completely wild, causing a health scare in the UK.  It is important to note
that both of these claims were highly speculative.</p>
<p>It later turned out that Wakefield had received 55000 (fifty-five thousand) UK
pounds from Legal Aid Board solicitors who were gathering evidence to use in a
case against vaccine manufacturers, and that a number of parents of the
children taking part in Wakefield’s study were directly involved in the
law-suit.  Wakefield did not mention any of this at the time of publication. 
Ten of his 12 co-authors have since completely retracted their interpretation
of the paper.</p>
<p>In short, the author of the paper that started most of the modern vaccination-autism scare was completely corrupt, and his corruption directly affected this specific research.</p>
<p>He did manage to cause such a scare in the UK, that measles (one of the diseases that MMR vaccinates against) is for the first time in decades at almost epidemic levels.   Since then, there have been cases of measles killing children, something which would most probably not have happened had the vaccination compliance not been at an all-time low.  Isn’t that absolutely crazy when one considers that measles was all but eradicated?</p>
<p>In the years between 1998 and the present, there have been numerous extremely well-designed and large studies, none of which have been able to find <em>any</em> kind of link between vaccination and autism.</p>
<p><em>To summarise this section: The research that the vaccination scare is based
on, was deeply flawed and based on corruption, not science.</em></p>
<h1 id="spreading-out-of-vaccines">Spreading out of vaccines</h1>
<p><em>This section is based on the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaccine_controversy#Vaccine_overload" title="Wikipedia article on Vaccine controversy.">Wikipedia article on the general Vaccine
Controversy</a>.</em></p>
<p>In some cases, parents opt for spreading out the vaccinations, because they
mistakenly think that this is safer than not doing so.  The flawed idea that
administering all these vaccines together could be dangerous is called the
“vaccine overload hypothesis”.  It is flawed for the reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Common childhood ilnesses represent a much heavier load on the infant immune system.</li>
<li>The vaccination cocktail given currently represents less than 10% of the immunological load of the vaccinations given to children in the 80s.</li>
<li>Numerous studies have shown that the combination of vaccinations does NOT damage the infant immune system.</li>
</ul>
<p>Importantly, if you spread out vaccines, you increase the time during which your child is susceptible to the diseases that are being vaccinated again, thus greatly increasing the health risk to your child and all other children it comes into contact with.  You are a bad parent if you do this.</p>
<p><em>To summarise this section:</em> <em>Administering the vaccinations together does not damage your child’s immune system.</em> <em>Spreading out vaccines is dangerous for both your child and all children it comes into contact with.</em></p>
<h1 id="celebrities-campaigning-against-vaccination">Celebrities campaigning against vaccination</h1>
<p>Recently, a number of celebrities, most prominent of which Jenny McCarthy and
her partner Jim Carrey, supported by Oprah, have been campaigning against
vaccination.  You have to remember that these are actors and entertainers,
with almost ZERO medical or scientific background or training.   McCarthy
dropped out of nursing school to become a Playboy Bunny: There’s nothing
wrong with that, but you really cannot base important medical decisions,
concerning the health and survival of your child (!!), on the opinions of an
erstwhile nude model!</p>
<p>_To summarise: Think carefully about the scientific and medical backgrounds of
actors telling you how to care for the health and well-being of your child,
even more so when it concerns life and death issues such as vaccination.</p>
<h1 id="the-logical-conclusion">The logical conclusion</h1>
<p>To the best of our scientific knowledge, vaccinations as they are administered today are safe and do not cause autism.  In spite of this, research continues day and night to make sure of this observation.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you don’t vaccinate, the risk of your child
getting ill and dying is <em>significantly</em> higher.  If a large enough number of
you don’t vaccinate, we lose our herd immunity and then there is a very
real risk that <em>many</em> more of our children will get ill and die due to your
inaction.  Do you seriously want to take this very real risk with your <em>and</em>
my children’s lives?</p>
<h1 id="post-scriptum">Post scriptum</h1>
<p>I hope that this has helped.  If there are any issues that are not clear, or
missing, or you are not convinced, please let me know so that we can discuss
and so that I can improve this article.</p>
<h1 id="extra-resources">Extra resources</h1>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://tallguywrites.livejournal.com/148012.html" title="Andrew Wakefield comic">Brilliant comic</a> explaining how the corrupt Andrew Wakefield managed to cause this whole debacle.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.slate.com/id/2217798/" title="aritcle in slate criticising oprah for supporting mccarthy">Article in Slate</a> criticising Oprah’s support of Jenny McCarthy.</li>
<li>Popular <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2006/feb/12/health.medicineandhealth" title="Observer article about medical backlash over vaccine scare">article in the Guardian’s Observer</a> about spreading out vaccines.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nhs.uk/chq/Pages/1034.aspx?CategoryID=68&amp;SubCategoryID=154" title="statement on the NHS on why separate vaccinations are not necessary.">Clear statement by the NHS</a> on why there is no reason to offer MMR vaccine in a spaced / spread out fashion, and that spreading out is in fact dangerous.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="updates">Updates</h1>
<ul>
<li>July 25, 2012: <a href="http://io9.com/5928722/this-graph-of-whooping-cough-cases-in-washington-state-should-scare-the-crap-out-of-you" title="io9 article with increasing incidence of whooping cough in Washington State in 2012">Whooping Cough incidence in Washington State is up by 1300% in 2012</a> relative to 2011, most probably due to the anti-vaccination movement.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Outraged</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2008/05/12/outraged/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2008 16:56:06 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2008/05/12/outraged/</guid><description> The year is 2008.
A young Iraqi woman falls in love with a British soldier. Her father hears of this and subsequently, assisted by his two sons, stamps on, suffocates and stabs to death his own daughter. He is outraged that she has shamed his family in this way. Furthermore, he claims that she deserved this, as what she did was unacceptable to any Muslim that honours his religion. The father is not prosecuted for his barbaric behaviour.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The year is 2008.</p>
<ol>
<li>A young Iraqi woman falls in love with a British soldier.</li>
<li>Her father hears of this and subsequently, assisted by his two sons, stamps on, suffocates and stabs to death his own daughter.  He is outraged that she has shamed his family in this way.  Furthermore, he claims that she deserved this, as what she did was <strong><em>unacceptable to any Muslim that honours his religion</em></strong>.</li>
<li>The father is not prosecuted for his barbaric behaviour.  It is apparently on honour killing, and therefore tolerated.  In this case, the police apparently congratulated him.</li>
</ol>
<p>Read the full story <a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/may/11/iraq.humanrights" title="The Guardian article: My daughter deserved to die">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Dr Werner, you are a singularity of stupid</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2008/03/22/dr-werner-you-are-a-singularity-of-stupid/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2008 08:18:14 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2008/03/22/dr-werner-you-are-a-singularity-of-stupid/</guid><description> We all know that homeopathy is really stupid, just like most alternative medicine. However, when I saw this “lecture” by Dr Charlene Werner, I was astounded by the depths of stupidity that she is able to attain. It’s almost like she’s a kind of Superheroine of Stupidity, with the special power of creating a singularity of stupid. This is of course stupidity that’s so extreme that it tends towards infinity and temporarily makes all reason disappear into a black-hole of scientific incompetence.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>We all know that homeopathy is really stupid, just like most alternative medicine. However, when I saw <a href="http://www.badscience.net/?p=642" title="Singularity of Stupid lecture">this “lecture”</a> by Dr Charlene Werner, I was astounded by the depths of stupidity that she is able to attain. It’s almost like she’s a kind of Superheroine of Stupidity, with the special power of creating a singularity of stupid. This is of course stupidity that’s so extreme that it tends towards infinity and temporarily makes all reason disappear into a black-hole of scientific incompetence. Wow.</p>
<p>Bottom-line: if you have a brain-cell or two and you care about it, <em>stay very far away from homeopathy</em>. It will make you stupid too.</p>
<p><strong>Update</strong></p>
<p>They pulled that specific video from youtube, probably because they were concerned about Dr. Werner’s reputation going even more to the dogs than it already has (but not as much as it deserves). Fortunately, the video has been mirrored:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/C0c5yClip4o?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Alternative medicine, you suck</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2008/01/03/alternative-medicine-you-suck/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2008 22:04:19 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2008/01/03/alternative-medicine-you-suck/</guid><description> My blood has cooled down enough for me to write this now, it was positively boiling an hour or two ago. Tonight Netwerk, a documentary on one of the Dutch national channels, reported on the AIDS vs sangoma situation back in South Africa.
Those of you who understand Dutch can read this compact summary.
In short, sangomas (witch doctors) have a huge amount of sway with the local population. So when someone is infected with HIV and it manifests as AIDS, they go to the sangoma, who then coolly explains that they’re sick due to the interference of the spirits of their forefathers and claims that they know exactly how to remedy the problem (usually with some typically ineffective mystical ritual, also involving giving the patient lots of laxatives, thereby exacerbating the symptoms).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>My blood has cooled down enough for me to write this now, it was positively boiling an hour or two ago. Tonight Netwerk, a documentary on one of the Dutch national channels, reported on the AIDS vs sangoma situation back in South Africa.</p>
<p>Those of you who understand Dutch can read <a href="http://www.netwerk.tv/archief/6147784/2040/De_geest_van_AIDS.html" title="Summary of Netwerk episode ">this compact summary</a>.</p>
<p>In short, sangomas (witch doctors) have a huge amount of sway with the local population. So when someone is infected with HIV and it manifests as AIDS, they go to the sangoma, who then coolly explains that they’re sick due to the interference of the spirits of their forefathers and claims that they know exactly how to remedy the problem (usually with some typically ineffective mystical ritual, also involving giving the patient lots of laxatives, thereby exacerbating the symptoms). The sangomas often actively discourage AIDS sufferers from going to the clinics where they would be treated with <a href="http://www.niaid.nih.gov/publications/hivaids/23.htm" title="Link to AZT study">proven</a> AIDS retardant drugs such as AZT.</p>
<p>The clinics do their best to educate sufferers, but the sangomas have a great amount of status in the local communities and are very afraid of admitting that they really cannot successfully treat AIDS, as this will put their position in danger. Let me rephrase that: they’re selfish idiots and they’re killing people. They should be prosecuted for obstructing conventional medicine.</p>
<p>To put this in context: a quarter of the South African population is HIV positive. Our minister of health, Dr. Manto Tshabalala-Msimang, believes that AIDS can be cured by <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/5319680.stm" title="Manto says, ">eating garlic and beetroot</a>. To add insult to injury, she has pulled strings to jump to the start of the liver transplant queue because she screwed up her own with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manto_Tshabalala-Msimang" title="Wikipedia article on Manto">alcohol abuse</a>.</p>
<p>Remember kids, if a treatment is not backed by evidence-based research, it’s probably bad for you, either directly, or due to effective inaction. The sangomas might be an extreme case, but in general, alternative medicine is to be handled with the greatest of suspicion.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Bush knew that Saddam had no WMDs</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2007/09/06/bush-knew-that-saddam-had-no-wmds/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2007 07:08:09 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2007/09/06/bush-knew-that-saddam-had-no-wmds/</guid><description> With this I’m doing my bit to spread this news in my part of the blogosphere (*cough* I’m not supposed to use that word, EVAR).
It turns out that Bush knew all along that Saddam had absolutely no WMDs, but that the decision had already been made to invade Iraq, and that the intelligence was simply twisted to fit this policy. Read all the nasty details in this Salon article. Here’s a choice excerpt:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>With this I’m doing my bit to spread this news in my part of the blogosphere (*cough* I’m not supposed to use that word, EVAR).</p>
<p>It turns out that Bush knew all along that Saddam had absolutely no WMDs, but that the decision had already been made to invade Iraq, and that the intelligence was simply twisted to fit this policy. Read all the nasty details in <a href="http://www.salon.com/opinion/blumenthal/2007/09/06/bush_wmd/?source=whitelist" title="Salon article ">this Salon article</a>. Here’s a choice excerpt:</p>
<p><em>On April 23, 2006, CBS’s “60 Minutes” interviewed Tyler Drumheller, the former CIA chief of clandestine operations for Europe, who disclosed that the agency had received documentary intelligence from Naji Sabri, Saddam’s foreign minister, that Saddam did not have WMD. “We continued to validate him the whole way through,” said Drumheller. “The policy was set. The war in Iraq was coming, and they were looking for intelligence to fit into the policy, to justify the policy.”</em></p>
<p><em>Now two former senior CIA officers have confirmed Drumheller’s account to me and provided the background to the story of how the information that might have stopped the invasion of Iraq was twisted in order to justify it. They described what Tenet said to Bush about the lack of WMD, and how Bush responded, and noted that Tenet never shared Sabri’s intelligence with then Secretary of State Colin Powell. According to the former officers, the intelligence was also never shared with the senior military planning the invasion, which required U.S. soldiers to receive medical shots against the ill effects of WMD and to wear protective uniforms in the desert.</em></p>
<p>This was brought under my attention by <a href="http://scienceblogs.com/pharyngula/" title="Pharyngula blog.">Pharyngula</a>, a brilliant science-blog that you should definitely add to your aggregator. Oh by the way, it has an ever-so-slight militantly atheistic tone, but that only makes it better.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Egyptian blogger jailed for “inciting hatred of Islam”</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2007/02/25/egyptian-blogger-jailed-for-inciting-hatred-of-islam/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2007 10:29:55 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2007/02/25/egyptian-blogger-jailed-for-inciting-hatred-of-islam/</guid><description> See this Boing Boing post.
This is too primitive for words. Get a grip people. Religion is passÃ©, getting all up in arms about your particular backwater religious flavour or icon is just barbaric.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>See <a href="http://www.boingboing.net/2007/02/24/egypt_blogger_kareem.html" title="Boing Boing post Kareem Amer">this Boing Boing post</a>.</p>
<p>This is too primitive for words. Get a grip people. Religion is passÃ©, getting all up in arms about your particular backwater religious flavour or icon is just barbaric.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The idiotic South African AIDS policy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2006/08/20/the-idiotic-south-african-aids-policy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2006 18:07:51 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2006/08/20/the-idiotic-south-african-aids-policy/</guid><description> Reading the NRC Handelsblad of yesterday, I come across this article. For those of you who don’t read Dutch, here is the BBC’s version of more or less the same issues.
In short, the South African government, and specifically the intellectually (greatly) challenged minister of health, Manto Tshabalala-Msimang, believe that AIDS and HIV should be treated with cutting-edge medication such as garlic, lemons and beetroots. To add insult to injury, at the South African stall at the international AIDS conference in Toronto, representatives were demonstrating said garlic, lemons and beetroots.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Reading the NRC Handelsblad of yesterday, I come across <a href="http://cpbotha.net/thingies/nrc_20060819_aidsbeleid_za.pdf">this article</a>. For those of you who don’t read Dutch, here is the <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/5265432.stm">BBC’s version</a> of more or less the same issues.</p>
<p>In short, the South African government, and specifically the intellectually (greatly) challenged minister of health, Manto Tshabalala-Msimang, believe that AIDS and HIV should be treated with cutting-edge medication such as garlic, lemons and beetroots. To add insult to injury, at the South African stall at the international AIDS conference in Toronto, representatives were demonstrating said garlic, lemons and beetroots.</p>
<p>I agree heartily with the strong criticism of Stephen Lewis (UN special envoy for AIDS in Africa) and of the protesters demanding that Tshabala-Msimang be arrested for her crimes against the South African people. It’s bad enough that Mbeki (the president) denied the link between HIV and AIDS for years, and that Zuma (yet another idiot member of the SA government) <a href="http://msnbc.msn.com/id/12647411/">recently claimed</a> that showering after unprotected sex decreases the chance of infection.</p>
<p>Remember: Every day, 800 South Africans die of AIDS.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>