<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>M1 on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/m1/</link><description>Recent content in M1 on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 07:14:29 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/m1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #222: Scotty, we need more power!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 14:07:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/</guid><description>Welcome back everyone!
It&amp;rsquo;s now early(ish) Friday morning of the weekend after, but I would like to get the 222d edition of the WHV out, namely the one covering the two weeks from Monday, April 19 to Sunday, May 2, 2021.
My excuse for skipping a week is that the second week was spent on vacation. Exhibit A is shown below:
Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s now early(ish) Friday morning of the weekend after, but I would like to
get the 222d edition of the WHV out, namely the one covering the two weeks from
Monday, April 19 to Sunday, May 2, 2021.</p>
<p>My excuse for skipping a week is that the second week was spent on
vacation. Exhibit A is shown below:</p>










<figure><a href="st_francis_beach_run_202104.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_bbb76e39724cc3f7.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_bfb1ba72e5ab2b58.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_ec9238ff28cf4ddf.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_681f14d95b121950.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_bfb1ba72e5ab2b58.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The rest of this post has (imagine the following in Bill Hader&rsquo;s Stefon voice):</p>
<ul>
<li>migraines and science</li>
<li>scifi ipads</li>
<li>VR</li>
<li>a life tip</li>
</ul>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="brain-glitch">Brain glitch</h2>
<p>I lost almost half a work day to a <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/conditions/ocular-migraine.htm">visual migraine</a>.</p>
<p>Looking at my notes, it seems that these only started during the past few
years, although it could be that I just didn&rsquo;t record the previous ones.</p>
<p>It starts out with bright spots in the middle of your field of vision, which
slowly grow until they form jiggly circles. This is not ideal, but at least you
can now look through their centres. Haha.</p>
<p>It looks eerily identical to the illustration on the linked website.</p>
<p>After half an hour to about an hour, sometimes a headache will hit, and
sometimes not. This time it was unusually intense, and I had no choice but to
detach from work for a while.</p>
<p>Looking back at my notes now, I really appreciate the time-stamped entries as
the migraine developed all the way to its end.</p>
<p>Lesson reaffirmed: Take good notes, no matter what.</p>
<h3 id="fascinating-scientific-review-of-migraine-and-metabolism">Fascinating scientific review of migraine and metabolism</h3>
<p>After a related chat with a friend who reported that in his case blood sugar
played a role (he can&rsquo;t skip breakfast, and can&rsquo;t eat too sweet), my
permanently foraging internet tentacles entirely coincidentally dredged up this
publication in Nature Reviews Neurology titled &ldquo;The metabolic face of
migraine - from pathophysiology to treatment&rdquo; (<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31586135/">pubmed</a>, <a href="https://orbi.uliege.be/bitstream/2268/247255/1/Gross%20et%20al%20Metabolic%20face%20of%20migraine-Nat%20Rev%20Neurol%202019.pdf">PDF fulltext</a>).</p>
<p>The article is pretty dense, but here are some interesting observations:</p>
<p>The first is from box 1: In some humans, when brain energy demands outstrip
metabolic reserves, rendering them vulnerable to disruption of cortical
homeostatis (energy balance), there is a whole cascade of events that,
according to the article&rsquo;s authors, might be started by the pannexin channels
in neurons. (These channels act as sensors of cortical homeostasis.)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s quite straight-forward then that (haha):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The final result of this cascade is trigeminovascular activation and calcitonin
gene-related peptide release in the extradural space, which leads to headache.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Following from there, they postulate two alternate pathways that cause
respectively migraine with and without aura (visual effects).</p>
<p>In other words, when your brain requires more energy than you have available,
and you are one of the many genetic variants who suffer from this mechanism,
you could be in for some migraine when your body reacts to the imbalance.</p>
<p>On top of that, the authors present one more good reason <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#skip-you-some-breakfast-for-great-good">to become fat-adapted</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>These increases in lipolysis and ketogenesis can also be interpreted as
counter-​regulatory responses to a cerebral energy deficit. Given that ketone
bodies are an efficient alternative fuel for the brain when glucose
availability is low, their elevation would be expected to restore brain energy
homeostasis. However, the Western carbohydrate-​laden diet means that in most
people in Western countries the brain is not keto-​adapted so does not have the
enzymatic composition and transporters to make use of ketone bodies produced
during an energy crisis.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Box 2 in the article provides the following quite intriguing &ldquo;Suggested
approach to improving mitochondrial function and energy metabolism in
migraine&rdquo; (emphasis mine, so that you can skim over if you want):</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>Individualize supplementation of micronutrients. To ensure that all
micronutrients needed for mitochondrial function are available, laboratory
tests can be used to individualize supplementation with minerals,
hydrophobic and lipophilic vitamins and trace mineralsthat are deficient.</li>
<li>Reduce oxidative stress and increase antioxidants. Measurement of oxidative
and/or nitrosative stress levels and antioxidant status in individuals could
detect a potential mismatch between oxidative stress levels and antioxidant
capacity and enable therapeutic adjustments to be made, although studies are
needed to prove that such an approach improves migraine
management. Strategies to reduce oxidative stress could include <strong><strong>elimination
or reduction of processed food, food with a high glycaemic index and</strong></strong>
<strong><strong>alcohol, use of green or blue light filtering glasses, interruption of
hormone-based contraception, lifestyle changes</strong></strong> and addition of
antioxidants,such as polyphenols, coenzyme Q10, α-lipoic acid or
β-hydroxybutyrate mineral salts, to the diet.</li>
<li><strong><strong>Stabilize blood glucose levels</strong></strong>. An oral glucose tolerance testshould be
undertaken in patients with migraine and clinical features that suggest
glucose intolerance or a family history of glucose intolerance. Patients
with reactive hyperinsulinaemia and reactive hypoglycaemia are likely to
benefit from stabilization of blood glucose levels, which can often be
achieved with dietary adjustments.</li>
<li>Provide an <strong><strong>alternative energy substrate for the brain</strong></strong>. For patients with
compromised energy metabolism, an alternative source of fuel for the brain,
in addition to glucose and lactate, might be beneficial. This source can be
generated with a ketogenic diet and/or use of exogenous ketogenic
substances, such asmedium-chain triglycerides or exogenous ketone body
salts. Further placebo-controlled trials are needed to validate ketogenic
therapies in migraine.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="4-20-ipad-pro-supercomputers-straight-outta-scifi">4/20 iPad Pro supercomputers straight outta SciFi</h2>
<p>On 4/20 I tuned into a liveblog (I think it was <a href="https://live.arstechnica.com/apples-april-20-2021-spring-loaded-event/">the one by Ars Technica</a>) of
Apple&rsquo;s release event.</p>
<p>Apple is currently evolving the computing landscape quite substantially, so I
find it immensely interesting to see what they are bringing next.</p>
<p>They did a whole bunch this time, but what struck me as the most significant,
is that they introduced two new iPad Pro tablets with M1 chips.</p>
<p>You know, that same M1 chip powering <a href="/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/">the super fast and energy-efficient laptop
on which I&rsquo;m typing up this post</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to sticking a desktop-class processor (err, desktop-class
performance, but mobile-level battery efficiency) back into a mobile device
that you can also buy with 2 terabytes of built-in storage (I find this a bit
surreal), the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2021/4/21/22395449/apple-ipad-pro-2021-liquid-retina-xdr-mini-led-explainer">new Liquid Retina XDR display on the top-end iPad Pro</a> has 10000
of a new kind of micro-led just for the back-lighting and thus is able to offer
1000 nits of full-screen brightness and adaptively up to 1600 nits on portions
of the screen, all of that with a contrast ratio of 1 to&hellip;. ONE MILLION.</p>
<p>As I was reading this, and later listening as the excitement led (&hellip;) me to
tune in to the video stream, one of my inner voices marvelled at the sheer
technological innovation on display (sorry can&rsquo;t stop) here.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m curious to see how this new class of supercomputer-level tablet device is
going to change how we humans interact with the digital world.</p>
<h2 id="oculus-quest-2">Oculus Quest 2</h2>
<p>On that topic&hellip;</p>
<p>On the weekend that we returned from vacation, we welcomed an <a href="https://www.theverge.com/21437674/oculus-quest-2-review-features-photos">Oculus Quest 2 VR
headset</a> into the family.</p>
<p>In the early 2000s, <a href="https://graphics.tudelft.nl/">the TU Delft Graphics research lab</a> that I was part of had
an AR / VR research line, so I got some exposure to state-of-the-art equipment
then.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 15 years, and the self-contained Oculus Quest 2 at $299 is
mind-blowingly good.</p>
<p>Specifically the head tracking is phenomenal.</p>
<p>Graphics elements in VR are rock-solid in virtual space as you move your head
(and yourself) around. The resolution is high enough that you could even work
on a document if you would like. With the most recent firmware update, Quest 2
now does 120 Hz.</p>
<p>In short, when you put on the headset, immersion is total.</p>
<p>No more outside world.</p>
<p>You can double tap on the side of the helmet to switch on reality (viewing your
surroundings through the 4 cameras mounted on the outside), and double tap to
switch reality off and go back into VR.</p>
<p>Facebook (they own Oculus) has some interesting work-focused ideas with this:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/5_bVkbG1ZCo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>When I saw that video for the first time, before having tried out the Quest 2,
I thought &ldquo;haha look at fb faking VR&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s pretty much spot-on.</p>
<p>(We&rsquo;re not playing office-office with the kids though, beat saber is much more
fun in 3D!)</p>
<h2 id="flip-it">Flip it</h2>
<p>During a recent chat with a busy friend, seeing if we could have coffee
somewhere, I reminded us both (you have to imagine this in Afrikaans, but
failing that in English with a thick Afrikaans accent):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Remember that the moments of relaxation and humanity are the anchors. All of
the rest should flow around that.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is so easy to forget.</p>
<p>We (and I also mean I) postpone the chat, or the run, or time with the family,
because of work.</p>
<p>It should be the other way round!</p>










<figure><a href="st_francis_sunset_watch_202104.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_b36de7acfc1e6653.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_4ba8d8a922c30068.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_d77a49f3e110f83.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_876d61fb3f2dd092.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_4ba8d8a922c30068.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Awesome ritual in St Francis where people make a whole celebration of the sunset. We were there thanks to GOU#1&rsquo;s tip."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Awesome ritual in St Francis where people make a whole celebration of the sunset. We were there thanks to GOU#1&rsquo;s tip.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>New Emacs-capable hardware: M1 MacBook Air</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 21:49:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</guid><description>You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&amp;rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I usually write a little something about it.
These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&amp;rsquo;ve back-tagged most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient &amp;ldquo;new computer&amp;rdquo; tag list!
Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of the new Apple M1 chip and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I
usually write a little something about it.</p>
<p>These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&rsquo;ve back-tagged
most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient <a href="/tags/new-computer/">&ldquo;new computer&rdquo; tag
list</a>!</p>
<h2 id="fast-cheap-and-energy-efficient-choose-three">Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three</h2>
<p>This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of
the new <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple%5FM1">Apple M1 chip</a> and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great
performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.</p>










<figure><a href="m1-macbook-air-about.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_de2f1e5efc3aadf2.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_6c2a206fdadbba4.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_2a184c7768aa3ee0.png 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_6c2a206fdadbba4.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;m still <em>quite</em> happy with the <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1 Extreme Gen1</a> as my main
workstation, but although classed as thin-and-light it <em>is</em> still a
workstation.</p>
<p>Specifically, due to the fact that it takes at least a minute or two to resume
from sleep, and the fact that its performance on battery is substantially
slower than on AC, it&rsquo;s not the sort of machine that you can flip open to work
on when inspiration strikes.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, it&rsquo;s a really effective lap warmer, and so gets
uncomfortable <em>quite</em> quickly.</p>
<p>In sharp contrast, the performance of this MacBook Air is the same, namely
&ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;, whether it&rsquo;s on AC or on battery, the laptop resumes from
standby faster that I&rsquo;m able to open the lid, and it hardly ever gets warm.</p>
<p>In short, I can bust this out of my bag and be typing on my lap in under 3
seconds, and this is something that has already started paying off in terms of
my writing.</p>
<h2 id="this-might-be-the-best-emacs-host-i-ve-ever-used">This might be the best Emacs-host I&rsquo;ve ever used</h2>
<p>This very post is currently being typed on <code>GNU Emacs 27.1.91 (build 1, arm-apple-darwin20.3.0, Carbon Version 164 AppKit 2022.3) of 2021-03-15</code> on the
device in question.</p>
<p>Have I mentioned &ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;?</p>
<p>By the way, if you build Emacs like this on the M1:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew tap railwaycat/emacsmacport
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew install --formula emacs-mac --HEAD
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; you should be good to go.</p>
<h3 id="update-on-2021-04-15">Update on 2021-04-15</h3>
<p>A few days ago, I started seeing the following error during homebrew Emacs update:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-text" data-lang="text"><span style="display:flex;"><span>./temacs --batch  -l loadup --temacs=pbootstrap
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>make[1]: *** [bootstrap-emacs.pdmp] Killed: 9
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>make: *** [src] Error 2
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This looks similar to <a href="https://github.com/d12frosted/homebrew-emacs-plus/issues/292">this github issue on emacs-plus</a>, which was fixed on emacs
master.</p>
<p>It was easiest for me to switch to emacs-plus, which went like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew uninstall emacs-mac
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew tap d12frosted/emacs-plus
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew install emacs-plus@28 --with-no-titlebar
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="quo-vadis-one-device-to-rule-them-all">Quo vadis, one device to rule them all?</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s a pity that the ThinkPad, although powerful enough to satisfy <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#the-story-behind-this-story-one-context-to-rule-them-all">my single
computing device / single context requirement</a>, and with <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 becoming
increasingly useful</a> and hence addressing the dual-boot issue, does not satisfy
the <em>instantly available</em> requirement.</p>
<p>Fortunately the two devices cater for complementary contexts.</p>
<p>The Air is for instant-on writing, communication, admin and maybe a tiny bit of
development, whilst the ThinkPad is for all of the heavy lifting, but who knows
how these lines are going to be blurred in the coming months?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>