<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>planning on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/planning/</link><description>Recent content in planning on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 13:39:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/planning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #126: Fleur-de-lis.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 13:39:32 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/</guid><description> Betty’s Bay’s Crepuscular Rays. An apostrophe in time saves rhyme.
Happy new year everyone, and welcome to the first Weekly (truly?! will this be the year?) Head Voices of 2018! I ended 2017 with a longish (by my standards) run in the morning, followed by a laid-back mini-party and finally by struggling really hard to stay awake until midnight. In contrast, returning to the office on January 2 was a pretty good way to ease gradually into work in 2018.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/bettys_crepuscular_rays-2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/bettys_crepuscular_rays-2-1024x462.jpg"
        
            alt="Betty’s Bay’s Crepuscular Rays. An apostrophe in time saves rhyme."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Betty’s Bay’s Crepuscular Rays. An apostrophe in time saves rhyme.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<ul>
<li>Happy new year everyone, and welcome to the first <em>Weekly</em> (truly?! will this be the year?) Head Voices of 2018!</li>
<li>I ended 2017 with a longish (by my standards) run in the morning, followed by a laid-back mini-party and finally by struggling really hard to stay awake until midnight.</li>
<li>In contrast, returning to the office on January 2 was a pretty good way to ease gradually into work in 2018. Many colleagues were still on vacation, so the week felt a bit like work with training wheels.</li>
<li>Pro-tip #1 for the new year: In the last few weeks of 2017 I started (again…) explicitly making quiet time at the start of the day to think about what I want to take care of. These take the form of a small number of <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Org mode</a> “<code>- [ ] Do this thing</code>” checklist items that are usually related to but separate from my main tasks. I find it amazing to which extent these few minutes are able to shape my day. (In my org mode monthly journal, I also usually start by listing out manually the tasks I want to complete during that month, as well as the ideas / thoughts / principles I want to keep in my sights.)</li>
<li>Pro-tip #2 for the new year: After years of resisting these types of software tools due to my belief that I should simply apply more grit and will power to squeeze out more focus hours, I finally broke down and purchased the <a href="https://heyfocus.com/">macOS app called Focus</a>. You click its pretty icon, and then your computer goes into focus mode: The Mail application and a bunch of other non-focus-related apps all get killed, and a bunch of websites (reddit, youtube, work chat, etc) are blocked for a user-configurable block of time. I rationalised this purchase with the following reasoning: <em>It usually takes a single moment of weakness for a distraction to terminate a valuable block of focus. It takes a single moment of strength for this tool to start a valuable block of focus.</em></li>
<li>Although I’m having fun, I really don’t think I’m supposed to use bullets like this.</li>
<li>Thank you very much for spending time here with me. I wish you a week of value and focus, followed by a visit to the next WHV!








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/huguenot_monument_franschhoek.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/huguenot_monument_franschhoek-1024x653.jpg"
        
            alt="The Huguenot Monument in Franschhoek, where we found ourselves an hour or two ago. Immediacy FTW."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Huguenot Monument in Franschhoek, where we found ourselves an hour or two ago. Immediacy FTW.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</li>
</ul>
<p>P.S. This post was finished during a 30 minute FocusApp block. Background music: <a href="https://www.residentadvisor.net/reviews/5988">Balance 014</a> by Joris Voorn, one of my favourite music creations ever.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>On the importance of taking notes. [Weekly Head Voices #38]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Feb 2011 22:39:52 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/</guid><description> Post summary: Part one is about friends graduating from Evil School, part two is rather short mentioning vague bits of good news and part three is 100% time management and productivity boosting goodness! Feel free to skip, skim or reorder!
One On Thursday, February 10, 2011, my dear friend Mister Krekel graduated from Evil School after years of hard work and evil-doing, and will henceforth go through life as the formidable Doctor Krekel.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Part one is about friends graduating from Evil School, part two is rather short mentioning vague bits of good news and part three is 100% time management and productivity boosting goodness! Feel free to skip, skim or reorder!</em></p>
<h2 id="one">One</h2>
<p>On Thursday, February 10, 2011, my dear friend Mister Krekel graduated from Evil School after years of hard work and evil-doing, and will henceforth go through life as the formidable Doctor Krekel. Please do watch out.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_school_by_fmalan.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/evil_school_by_fmalan.jpg"
        
            alt="Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Evil School. (Photo by the talented fpixel.wordpress.com.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The joyous transition took place in the Evil School’s Academiegebouw in Leiden, and this time yours truly (I’m referring to me in a round-about fashion) even had the great honour of playing a part in the formal proceedings. If you’re curious as to what exactly this ritual constitutes, see <a href="/2010/05/29/augmentation-weekly-head-voices-23/" title="previous edition of the WHV also on PhD defences in Leiden">this previous edition of the WHV</a> on the graduation of another terribly evil colleague. I believe that the bunch of us now constitute a bona fide Axis of Evil. No, the evil jokes can unfortunately not stop yet.</p>
<p>The Party was held in a secret cafe nearby. You will notice that I’ve capitalised Party, as it was not your average run of the mill Evil School graduation affair, but a social event of note. Here in Holland, the PhD defence and graduation are a combined affair, and so the whole day is dedicated to just one person. It is actually very special: People take time off from work, sometimes even temporarily put aside their differences, and travel from all over to attend the festivities. It’s like a wedding, except that there’s only one of you. I can only recommend it very highly. At the Party, everyone had clearly read the memo, and they were there with that singular goal in mind: Celebrate the freshly minted Evil Doctor. Presents were given, speeches were held, photos were shown, beer was imbibed and, flying in the face of all advice concerning the mixing of alcohol, cameras and social networking, the <a href="http://fpixel.wordpress.com/" title="link to the evil photographer">best evil photographer in town</a>, who’s coincidentally also in Evil School, took the most amazing photos that you should be able to see on Facebook if you’re one of the privileged few to belong to The Network, also known as <em>The Friends of the Axis of Evil</em>.</p>
<h2 id="two">Two</h2>
<p>On the good news front, you&rsquo;ll see (or not) on the <a href="http://www.uib.no/eurovis2011/program.php" title="list of eurovis 2011 conditional accepts">list of EuroVis 2011 conditional accepts</a>, that a paper by cool colleagues from far away, to which I contributed a small part, has been conditionally accepted, and hence has a significant chance of being presented at said event in Bergen, Norway (May 31 to June 3). We also have plans to submit a poster (or two), so there&rsquo;s an even more significant chance that I will make an appearance at this fantastic conference! We&rsquo;re also cooking up various odds and ends that will hopefully crystallise sufficiently by the end of March to be submissible for VisWeek 2011. Cross yer fingers.</p>
<h2 id="three">Three</h2>
<p>Today&rsquo;s backyard time management section is in fact more about planning than it is about notes. However, my Pro-Tips involve combining them in an easy to implement productivity booster. When people start out in research, one of the first bits of advice they get is keeping some kind of lab journal. I think this advice applies to more than just research: If you do any kind of independent or project work, jotting down your activities, thoughts and results during the day is useful in helping to structure your thought processes, and also very helpful when you have to backtrack a complex multi-day procedure. During my Ph.D., I filled a number of real cardboard-and-paper books with notes. More recently, I&rsquo;ve started using Google Documents for the same purpose. Besides all the other advantages, having to document explicitly your work output keeps you productive and on your toes.</p>
<h3 id="pro-tip-1">Pro Tip #1</h3>
<p><em>Keep a lab journal, even if you don&rsquo;t work in a lab.</em></p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve <a href="/2011/01/09/2011-a-cyber-suburban-odyssey-weekly-head-voices-35/" title="2011 start post">mentioned before</a> that my resolutions for 2011 included more concrete planning. This has manifested in a work-in-progress planning for the whole year, including milestones, awards won, and so forth, but much more practically, it has manifested in a little lab-journal-compatible trick. Every morning when I sit down to begin the day, I spend a few minutes thinking and then start the day&rsquo;s journal entry by writing down, as concretely as possible, the tasks that I plan to complete by the end of the day. This also ensures that I spend effort on the <em>important</em> things, and not only on the urgent things. So, that brings us to:</p>
<h3 id="pro-tip-2">Pro Tip #2</h3>
<p><em>At the start of each day, write down in your lab journal exactly and
concretely what you plan to accomplish by the end of that day.</em></p>
<p>These pro tips appear to be quite straight-forward, but together they help one
to focus, and to keep tabs on one&rsquo;s <em>effective</em> productivity. In other words,
just being terribly busy the whole day gets you nothing; the trick is being
terribly busy in all the right directions.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Somebody is clearly pushing the boundaries of awesomeness… cowboys AND aliens!</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/In-m2RJw3hE?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>