<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>plastic on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/plastic/</link><description>Recent content in plastic on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2019 17:04:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/plastic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #183: Wave functions wearing lycra.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2019 17:04:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/</guid><description> This, the 183d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the week from Monday November 4 to Sunday November 10, 2019.
In this post we have a BLoM, a story about the conflict between a man and a toy and finally some great quantum mechanics visualizations for your meat-based neural network.
On the way home from a compact but enjoyable Sunday party with built-in family gathering at Skilpadvlei near Stellenbosch.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 183d edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looks back at the week from
Monday November 4 to Sunday November 10, 2019.</p>
<p>In this post we have a BLoM, a story about the conflict between a man and a toy
and finally some great quantum mechanics visualizations for your meat-based
neural network.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu889d67f11708c8e57fb81c04eabccc67_1909149_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu889d67f11708c8e57fb81c04eabccc67_1909149_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu889d67f11708c8e57fb81c04eabccc67_1909149_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu889d67f11708c8e57fb81c04eabccc67_1909149_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/11/12/weekly-head-voices-183-wave-functions-wearing-lycra/skilpadvlei_exit_hu889d67f11708c8e57fb81c04eabccc67_1909149_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
On the way home from a compact but enjoyable Sunday party with
built-in family gathering at Skilpadvlei near Stellenbosch. 
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="blom-bullet-list-of-miscellany">BLoM (Bullet List of Miscellany).</h2>
<ul>
<li>Thanks to the gentle urging of my friend <a href="https://twitter.com/vogonpoet">the Vogon
Poet</a>, I finally got around to fixing my
custom Hugo shortcode for image inclusion so that it would use full path
names. This will hopefully result in RSS feeds and the subscription email
correctly displaying images.</li>
<li>I forgot to mention in the previous WHV that I wrote a post explaining how
you can <a href="/2019/11/02/forming-and-maintaining-habits-using-orgmode/">use Emacs and Orgmode to form and maintain good
habits</a>. This has
really been working quite well for me.</li>
<li>It is hard to explain how happy I am that the comments on this blog are now
also <a href="/2019/11/10/we-now-have-self-hosted-isso-comments/">self-hosted using the open-source software
isso</a>. Of all of the
advantages, I think I appreciate the lower barrier to entry the most. With
full markdown support, you should be able to post whole blog posts down below
in the comment section! (HINT HINT)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="i-should-really-look-where-im-walking">I should really look where I&rsquo;m walking.</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>On Wednesday evening, as I was walking onto the carpet in our room, feet nicely
marinated and super soft thanks to the shower I had just taken, senses and
planning wetware focused on three different non-floor points in the room (I was
carrying two items that needed to be deposited in two different locations, and
I spotted genetic relation units on the bed), I managed to step right onto the
single pink plastic toy my youngest GOU had left on the floor.</p>
<p>Naturally I did this with the softest part of my soft foot.</p>
<p>The plastic shattered, and somehow my reflexive foot action only served to
result in a partial retract followed by an apparently inevitable rejoining of
the vertical foot-toy-mashup, which on its part served to bring more bits of
shattered plastic into membrane piercing force levels of contact with the soft
underside of my foot.</p>
<p>Are you still picturing?</p>
<p>Relatively-speaking large floor, unoccupied with one small exception.</p>
<p>Single highly shatter-friendly toy, made of <em>pink</em> plastic.</p>
<p>Man manages to angle foot <em>just so</em>, applies copious force, and impales said
foot on lone toy, not once, but multiple times.</p>
<p>Anyways people, measuring by the amount of blood and other KPIs, I can in all
honesty say that this is somewhat worse than stepping on a lego.</p>
<p>Three days later, we extracted what was hopefully the last bit of plastic from
the underside of my foot.</p>
<p>On the bright side, the tweezer from <a href="/2018/02/11/weekly-head-voices-131-function-over-form/#what-a-tool">my Gerber every day carry (EDC)
micro-tool</a>
has now shown itself excellent for the purpose of light home surgery.</p>
<p>Also on the bright side, this will hopefully serve as powerful reminder that I
should really focus better on where I put my feet down at home, at least until
the volume of toys starts to diminish in a few years time.</p>
<p>(On Sunday, I couldn&rsquo;t not, so I did squeeze in a short and careful run. I was
quite happy that everything did still seem to work, albeit with some extra
feeling.)</p>
<h2 id="gravitational-waves-on-the-high-seas-of-curved-spacetime">Gravitational waves on the high seas of curved spacetime.</h2>
<p>My favourite video showing the idea of how gravity warps (curves; bends)
spacetime is the one below.</p>
<p>For those of you who prefer not viewing YouTube videos, let me do another
&ldquo;picture this&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Sooooo&hellip; PICTURE THIS:</p>
<ul>
<li>The gentleman explaining the idea has a sheet of lycra stretched taut over a
circular frame. He makes a funny joke about it being an old swimming costume.</li>
<li>Placing heavy bearings on the sheet stretches the lycra down into a
funnel-shape, as you would expect. (that reminds me of this tangential thing
I wanted to tell you at some other point: it turns out your neural network
had to learn explicitly that model of material stretching as you were growing
up)</li>
<li>Throwing more bearings onto the lycra, one can see how the curved surface
causes them to orbit around the larger bearings!</li>
</ul>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/MTY1Kje0yLg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>Well, isn&rsquo;t that just a fabulous image to have in your mind&rsquo;s eye right now?!</p>
<p>This is exactly how you can visualize the warping of the gravity field in which
you and I and all of our friends and the Earth and all the planets and
everything in the whole universe are snugly embedded!</p>
<p>This more than explains the old <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Action_at_a_distance">&ldquo;action at a
distance&rdquo;</a> mystery.</p>
<p>In other words, how is it possible that the Sun is able to exert a force on the
planet-formerly-knows-as-Pluto?</p>
<p>Well, as you can visualize now, the Sun, being the baddest mofo in this valley,
warps the gravitational field (enveloping us all) the most, and this is what
keeps Pluto in orbit.</p>
<p>Anyways, as beautiful as this is, it is probably old news to many of you.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go on to my NEW story!</p>
<p>During a recent <a href="https://lexfridman.com/sean-carroll/">Lex Fridman podcast</a>
with the CalTech theoretical physicist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sean_M._Carroll">Sean
Carroll</a>, Carroll non-chalantly
mentioned that general relativity was simply the extension to the idea of
warped spacetime of a change at one point of the gravitational field not being
able to propagate faster than the speed of light to another point!</p>
<p>BRAIN ASPLODE.</p>
<p>I had never thought of it this way before.</p>
<p>When an object accelerates, it emanates a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravitational_wave">gravitational
wave</a> which travels through
the gravitational field at the speed of light. (Yes, these <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First_observation_of_gravitational_waves">gravitational waves
have been
measured</a>.)</p>
<p>Going back to our lycra visualization, it made intuitive sense to me that a
change in the warping of the lycra, for example due to the heaviest bearing
being moved by a giant hand, would have to travel at finite speed through the
lycra material for the new warped configuration to have reached all of its
corners!</p>
<p>At that point in the podcast, as if my brain was not reeling sufficiently from
these brilliant new mental images of gravitational waves rippling through
curved spacetime, just like the patterns formed by small rocks skipping over
water, Carroll started explaining how we are all just quantum wave functions
continuously getting entangled with each other the whole time.</p>
<p>I think I have just convinced myself <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Something-Deeply-Hidden-Emergence-Spacetime-ebook/dp/B07LCP3YRY/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=1573570733&amp;sr=8-1">what I will have to
read</a>
right after I finish with <em>Why we sleep</em>&hellip;</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>