<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>New Computer on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/new-computer/</link><description>Recent content in New Computer on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 08:54:08 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/new-computer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #246: Call up your friends</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2022 17:08:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/</guid><description>This, the 246th edition of the WHV, looks back at the longer-than-expected stretch of time between Monday August 8 and Sunday September 25 of the year 2022.
Figure 1: A slightly alternative view from somewhere up along Platties.
Disclaimer The later I get, the more difficult it becomes to put these things out.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This, the 246th edition of the WHV, looks back at the longer-than-expected
stretch of time between Monday August 8 and Sunday September 25 of the
year 2022.</p>










<figure><a href="2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu_cf19a3873ebb9580.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu_d7d1d0b93074b6ef.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu_741ac136db711393.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu_3a8db43130b978a0.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-09-table-mountain-platties-whv_hu_d7d1d0b93074b6ef.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A slightly alternative view from somewhere up along Platties."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>A slightly alternative view from somewhere up along Platties.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2>
<p>The later I get, the more difficult it becomes to put these things out.</p>
<p>Although not that many people read them, it feels like expectations increase
over time, and thus the barrier continues getting higher and higher.</p>
<p>Contrary to what it might sound like, I love doing what I&rsquo;m doing right now.</p>
<p>However, sometimes I wish to return to less complicated times, when writing a
post was a relaxed Sunday morning affair.</p>
<p>Changing space and time is not going to happen, and so, as is often the case, <em>I</em>
am the one who will have to change.</p>
<p>On the immediate term, it means that this post is even more all over the place
than normal. I would tell you to skip it, but then you might miss the bits at
the end.</p>
<p>On the slightly longer term, I would like to try to write a few WHV sentences
every day, apart from my normal daily notes, to see if that could mitigate the
writing gradient build-up.</p>
<p><em>On y va!</em></p>
<h2 id="birthday-messages">Birthday messages</h2>
<p>During the past weeks, I completed another orbit around the sun, of course only
as a (hopefully sufficiently erudite) planetary hitchhiker.</p>
<p>On the day, many friends sent me so many lovely messages over various
communication channels.</p>
<p>In some cases, people had clearly made use of the opportunity to include
additional and quite specific warm wishes.</p>
<p>Every year, I am again surprised by how <em>much</em> I appreciate these gifts.</p>
<p>This is my reminder to me, and to anyone else who might need to hear it: Write
sweet birthday wishes. In fact, make use of any such excuse to connect with
people.</p>
<p>P.S. Back in 2015, <a href="/2015/06/28/weekly-head-voices-93-a-thank-you-note/">I mentioned the sage advice of David Sedaris</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Write thank you notes.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="coffee-machine-reincarnation">Coffee machine reincarnation</h2>
<p>Some of you might remember when it arrived, and some of you have even tasted of
its dark and delicious produce over the years.</p>
<p>I am of course referring the beautiful mechanical beast that is our Saeco
Incanto Cappuccino, the Italian bean-to-cup machine <a href="/2007/04/08/infinite-espressos/">that came into our lives
fifteen years ago</a> and since then has only brought us pleasure, and structure,
and so much focus.</p>
<p>Sadly, it recently started tripping the RCD, aka residual current device, aka
the ECB, aka the earth leakage breaker, aka the GFCI if you&rsquo;re in the US.</p>
<p>This generally happens after the first cup, at the second solenoid tap (of
three), between the grinding and the pouring of the coffee.</p>
<p>This means that somewhere in the machine a live wire  has come into contact with
the chassis. The RCD measures this as a (small) current difference (the earth
leakage) between live and neutral and isolates that circuit to prevent any
humans from being electrocuted.</p>
<p>I took it in for repairs, and although it came back all nice and shiny with new
o-rings everywhere, the earth leakage was not remedied.</p>
<p>We took this as a sign that it was finally time to invest in a new bean-to-cup
machine, and so we did&hellip;</p>
<p>&hellip; into a brand new Saeco, this time the <a href="https://www.philips.co.za/c-p/HD8927_01/picobaristo-super-automatic-espresso-machine">Saeco PicoBaristo</a>.</p>
<p>While the old machine was the epitome of purpose-built simplicity, the new one
does have <em>significantly</em> more buttons and lights.</p>
<p>One improvement that I can really appreciate, is the fact that the new machine
is able to complete a coffee that is interrupted by the water reservoir
empyting mid-process.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, it is <em>quite</em> capable of converting beans into tasty
coffee at sufficient speed with just the right amount of ritual, and that was
the point.</p>
<h2 id="the-world-in-their-eyes">The world in their eyes</h2>
<p>Thanks to friends visiting us from NL (for the first time), we had the
privilege of spending some time with them (re-)exploring our surroundings.</p>
<p>Thanks to their abundance of vacation energy (keeping up even for the while
that we did was challenging) we squeezed in a number of activities (themes:
hikes, restaurants and fine wine), two of which I would like to mention here:</p>
<p>We had an absolutely fabulous Sunday lunch adventure at <a href="https://www.creationwines.com/">Creation Wines</a> on the
Hemel-en-Aarde ridge.</p>
<p>This lunch adventure consisted of various small and large dishes combined with
the tasting of various Creation wines, all of this coordinated by Jack, our amazing
sommelier and story-teller for the afternoon.</p>
<p>Combined with the frankly brilliant view of the vineyard-covered mountain, this
was definitely one of those <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">perfect present moment <em>things</em> deserving all of
one&rsquo;s attention</a>.</p>
<p>In order to compensate for our sins on the Sunday, on Monday we hiked up to the
top of Table Mountain via Platteklip Gorge. It was quite a bit slower than <a href="/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/#getting-high">my
previous Platties adventure in 2017</a>, but it was good fun nonetheless.</p>
<p>However, now I do feel obliged to go up again in the not too distant future,
but this time in speed mode in order to calibrate my memory of my 2017
performance.</p>
<p>More generally speaking, spending time with friends in tourist mode is a great
way to maintain one&rsquo;s gratitude for this amazing place.</p>
<h2 id="blom-bullet-list-of-miscellany">BLoM: Bullet List of Miscellany</h2>
<h3 id="never-ending-search-for-mobile-notes-is-never-ending">Never-ending search for mobile notes is never-ending</h3>
<p>From the niche-within-a-niche-within-a-niche department: If you&rsquo;re using
Org-roam in Emacs, and you&rsquo;d like to have random markdown files act like
they&rsquo;re org-roam nodes, you too could <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/2022/09/24/modify-md-roam-for-frontmatter-less-operation/">modify md-roam for frontmatter-less
operation</a>!</p>
<h3 id="beautiful-alder-lake-aka-meep12700">Beautiful Alder Lake aka meep12700</h3>
<p>I have a new work machine and it&rsquo;s an old-fashioned desktop PC!</p>
<p>Due to various constraints, some of them budgetary, I ended up with an:</p>
<ul>
<li>Intel 12700 (12th gen baby!)</li>
<li>Corsair H100x AiO water cooling (so the 12700 power limits can be lifted if
needed)</li>
<li>64GB of DDR4-3200 RAM</li>
<li>2 TB of PCIe 4.0 SSD: The Mushkin Vortex with Innogrit IG5236 controller</li>
<li>Asus TUF GAMING B660M-PLUS WIFI D4 motherboard</li>
<li>Super Flower Leadex III Gold 850W PSU</li>
<li>all of the above contained in the roomy and airflowy Phanteks Eclipse P400A
case.</li>
</ul>
<p>See <a href="https://pcpartpicker.com/list/tCfRwc">this PCPartPicker</a> for the full details.</p>
<p>Laptops definitely have their perks, but there&rsquo;s something magical about the
raw performance of a new PC, and especially about its longevity.</p>
<p>Completely subjectively, <a href="/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/#new-machine-zen">meepzen3, home PC acquired slightly more than a year
ago</a>, feels ever so slightly quicker.</p>
<h3 id="meet-your-heroes">Meet your heroes</h3>
<p>Lex Fridman made a 5 hour+ long <a href="https://lexfridman.com/john-carmack/">podcast with John Carmack</a>.</p>
<p>As is the case for many programming nerds, Carmack has been a hero of mine
since the day I learned of his existence. Also like many nerds of my era, I
spent many hours first with Commander , and later with Wolfenstein, Doom and
Quake.</p>
<p>Although John Romero certainly deserves much of the credit for these culture
changing projects, Carmack was and probably still is one of the best
programmers on the planet.</p>
<p>Anyways, it was great to hear that he sounds like a very decent human as well.</p>
<p>You should probably listen to the podcast (haha), but I would like to single
out here how Carmack explained that they were uniquely positioned when starting
on Commander Keen, in terms of the hundreds (thousands?) of hours of practice
they had had building multiple games per year for Softdisk.</p>
<p>In other words, while they were brilliant, Carmack attributes a great deal of
their break-through success to plain old hard work.</p>
<p>(See <a href="/2018/03/11/weekly-head-voices-135-its-all-rainbows-and-unicorns-no-really/#the-carmack-productivity-method-cpm">WHV #135</a> for a previous bit about Carmack&rsquo;s productivity.)</p>
<h3 id="call-up-your-friends">Call up your friends</h3>
<p>In an interview between Sam Harris and Oscar Burkeman (he of <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#reading">the 4000 weeks
book, winner of the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em></a> , and of <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">the power of
being able to put down your work</a>), Sam remarks so astutely that we have become
so caught up in the importance of the illusion of control of one&rsquo;s time, that
we have stopped calling up our friends.</p>
<p>Instead, you send a message with something like &ldquo;hey, let me know when you have
a few minutes for a phone call&rdquo;&hellip;</p>
<p>Now your friend either sees this much later, or sees it when you send it, and
then has to cogitate about if and when they could maybe fit you in somewhere
later in the day.</p>
<p>Not so long ago, you could just call up your friend, all serendipitous, and all
present-momenty, because what could be truly more important than spending a few
minutes connecting with your friend and/or loved one, and maybe having the
opportunity to just let them know that you&rsquo;re there for them?</p>
<p>If they are really unable to take your call, they won&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>However, the subtle improvement here is that everyone sometimes needs a tiny
bit of a nudge to do the right thing and connect with a brother or sister.</p>
<p>Be the nudge. Accept the nudge. Call up your friends!</p>










<figure><a href="2022-08-28-west-coast-whv.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hu_6091b9f99dc9f0cb.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hu_4904029b3140d862.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hu_f2773349e6773303.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hu_dac14bbc3fa1b800.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/2022-08-28-west-coast-whv_hu_4904029b3140d862.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Impression from a sneaky slightly early trip to the West Coast to see the flowers."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Impression from a sneaky slightly early trip to the West Coast to see the flowers.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #224: Zen machine</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 08:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/</guid><description>Dear friends,
You are reading the 224th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the week from Monday May 17 to Sunday May 23 of the year 2021.
Figure 1: Scene from a truly fabulous autumn Sunday lunch with the family. As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, Autumn weekends down here can be rough.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>You are reading the 224th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covering the week
from Monday May 17 to Sunday May 23 of the year 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="vergelegen_camphors_20210523.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu_cdd20b62c96e81d7.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu_85e03b41eb3d2f2.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu_37378ab6b1f95c7.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu_e7d463cbdd2eaa1f.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/29/weekly-head-voices-224-zen-machine/vergelegen_camphors_20210523_hu_85e03b41eb3d2f2.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a truly fabulous autumn Sunday lunch with the family. As I&rsquo;ve mentioned before, Autumn weekends down here can be rough."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from a truly fabulous autumn Sunday lunch with the family. As I&rsquo;ve mentioned before, Autumn weekends down here can be rough.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="fasted-runs-are-not-as-scary-as-i-thought">Fasted runs are not as scary as I thought</h2>
<p>At the time of drawing my <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#skip-you-some-breakfast-for-great-good">anti-breakfast line in the sand in WHV #221</a>, I did
still make the exception of eating a banana or three before a morning run, with
the reasoning that I would burn through much of the resultant glucose during
the run, and that runs without all those sweet sweet carbs were probably
quite difficult.</p>
<p>However, shortly after publishing that post, I decided that I would like to put
even more money where my mouth is, and started doing morning runs in the fasted
state.</p>
<p>I am happy to report that not only are fasted runs not scary at all, they are
actually quite enjoyable.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s no recently ingested food jostling around in your insides, which means
one less distraction from focusing on the running.</p>
<p>Perhaps most importantly, perceived energy did not seem to be a problem at all,
at least for the runs of up to an hour and a half that I have tried, some of
them over lunch time.</p>
<p>(It&rsquo;s possible that glycogen stores from the previous day were still
sufficient. I&rsquo;m hoping that at least some of those highly energy-dense fat
cells were involved. <a href="https://www.dietdoctor.com/fasting-and-exercise">This blog post about fasting and exercise</a> is a good read
and clearly explains the relevant concepts.)</p>
<p>I do need to caveat all of this with the remark that all of these runs have
been in the relative cool of autumn. I don&rsquo;t know (yet) how a longer, much more
sweaty run will go in the fasted state.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for the next few months to find out!</p>
<p>NB: Please see <a href="./#isso-2776">Pieter&rsquo;s comments below</a>. The text above is me talking about how
I experience my training (non-race) runs in the fasted state. If you decide to
exert yourself in the fasted state, please be careful, read what you can, and
measure carefully how your body responds to smaller doses initially.</p>
<h2 id="yarn-pnp-will-rescue-you-from-node-modules-hell">Yarn PnP will rescue you from <code>node_modules</code> hell</h2>
<p><em>NERD WARNING: <code>if not(nerd) skip_section();</code></em></p>
<p>The other day as I opened a laptop after having worked on the new zen machine
(see below) setting up some of our frontend development environments, its tiny
little metal frame almost creaked as dropbox started syncing, on all cores, the
many thousands of files from one of the cursed <code>node_modules</code> directories that
I had forgotten to exclude from syncing on the new machine.</p>
<p>My thoughts at that moment: &ldquo;YARGH! THAT DOES IT! we&rsquo;re going to try that shiny
new thing that we have been avoiding because the current solution was OK until
it absolutely wasn&rsquo;t.&rdquo;</p>
<p>That new thing is <a href="https://yarnpkg.com/features/pnp">Yarn 2&rsquo;s PnP</a>.</p>
<p>(That page describes the various other issues with <code>node_modules</code>, besides your
laptop creaking.)</p>
<p>Instead of downloading a thousand dependencies and then unpacking those
thousand dependencies to easily one hundred thousand tiny little files, right
in your source directory (and that&rsquo;s <code>node_modules</code> folks!), PnP creates a
single <code>.pnp.js</code> file along with a local cache of the one thousand packages
which it keeps neatly zipped up.</p>
<p>In terms of numbers of tiny files, this is an improvement of one to two orders
of magnitude, which is significant. With <code>enableGlobalCache</code>, you can even move
these out of your source dir, keeping just the <code>.pnp.js</code>.</p>
<p>In addition to this, because of this new structure, the PnP can be much more
strict in resolving dependencies, resulting in builds that are <strong>actually</strong>
reproducible.</p>
<p>I followed <a href="https://yarnpkg.com/getting-started/migration">the step-by-step instructions for migrating the project in question
to Yarn PnP</a>, and before you could say dependency-resolution 58 times, the
project in question was cured of the hundred thousand file problem, and IDEs
like Visual Studio Code or any of the JetBrains family were perfectly capable
of navigating through the new dependency structure, right down to lines of code
inside the package zips.</p>
<p>Based on this experience, and the momentum and support that PnP has, my advice
is to convert at your soonest convenience.</p>
<p>The feeling of relief and increased build speed are worth it!</p>
<h2 id="new-machine-zen">New machine zen</h2>
<p>The tradition around here is to write something about any new computers in the
family.</p>
<p>However, as this new one was not entirely planned, I almost wanted to keep it a
secret.</p>
<p>Weird instinct that.</p>
<p>As a compromise, I&rsquo;ll hide it in this section down here.</p>
<p>So, as I said, I was not yet planning to get a new workstation to complement
the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/">the new M1-powered mobile device</a>, because <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">the ThinkPad</a> is still a very
capable machine.</p>
<p>However, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen%5F3">the new AMD Zen3 architecture</a> was proving far too hard for me to
resist, and so I started <em>fantasy</em> shopping for my next Zen3-powered workstation.</p>
<p>This continued for quite a while in the evenings, with me swapping in and out
different components in my local retailer&rsquo;s online shop, reading reviews, and
generally enjoying the process of putting together my <em>imaginary</em> workstation,
with real parts, from a real store, and with the fairly specific rule (for some
or other reason) that I could only use parts that were in stock at the retailer
in question&hellip;</p>
<p>What could possibly go wrong, right?!</p>
<p>Well, what could go wrong, is that I&rsquo;m typing these words on a new Zen3
workstation with 12 cores (24 threads, I think you can guess the chip now?), a
really fast PCIe 4.0 SSD (around 7Gbytes/s read and write) and the &ldquo;old&rdquo;
RTX2070 GPU salvaged from the upgraded <a href="/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/">meepz97, the desktop that joined this
club back in 2015</a>.</p>
<p>(Back then the Samsung 850 Pro was indeed &ldquo;STUPID FAST&rdquo; at about 500MB/s. The
new drive, Sabrent&rsquo;s Rocket 4 Plus, is 7 times that speed, and 4 times as
large.)</p>
<p>Just a few years back, this sort of raw computing power could only be found in
well-guarded and relatively secret government facilities.</p>
<p>Now all of that is standing on my desk, running Emacs, a 40 year old text
editor.</p>
<p>Although getting my old friend Emacs running smoothly on <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/wslg">the bleeding edge WSLg</a>
has been causing a great deal of teeth gnashing, and although clearly many
other things have changed since then, I would like to conclude this post in the
same way as <a href="/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/#are-you-happy-now">the one for meepz97</a>:</p>
<h2 id="are-you-happy-now">Are you happy now?</h2>
<p>Yes.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>New Emacs-capable hardware: M1 MacBook Air</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 21:49:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</guid><description>You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&amp;rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I usually write a little something about it.
These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&amp;rsquo;ve back-tagged most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient &amp;ldquo;new computer&amp;rdquo; tag list!
Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of the new Apple M1 chip and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I
usually write a little something about it.</p>
<p>These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&rsquo;ve back-tagged
most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient <a href="/tags/new-computer/">&ldquo;new computer&rdquo; tag
list</a>!</p>
<h2 id="fast-cheap-and-energy-efficient-choose-three">Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three</h2>
<p>This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of
the new <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple%5FM1">Apple M1 chip</a> and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great
performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.</p>










<figure><a href="m1-macbook-air-about.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_de2f1e5efc3aadf2.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_6c2a206fdadbba4.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_2a184c7768aa3ee0.png 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_6c2a206fdadbba4.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;m still <em>quite</em> happy with the <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1 Extreme Gen1</a> as my main
workstation, but although classed as thin-and-light it <em>is</em> still a
workstation.</p>
<p>Specifically, due to the fact that it takes at least a minute or two to resume
from sleep, and the fact that its performance on battery is substantially
slower than on AC, it&rsquo;s not the sort of machine that you can flip open to work
on when inspiration strikes.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, it&rsquo;s a really effective lap warmer, and so gets
uncomfortable <em>quite</em> quickly.</p>
<p>In sharp contrast, the performance of this MacBook Air is the same, namely
&ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;, whether it&rsquo;s on AC or on battery, the laptop resumes from
standby faster that I&rsquo;m able to open the lid, and it hardly ever gets warm.</p>
<p>In short, I can bust this out of my bag and be typing on my lap in under 3
seconds, and this is something that has already started paying off in terms of
my writing.</p>
<h2 id="this-might-be-the-best-emacs-host-i-ve-ever-used">This might be the best Emacs-host I&rsquo;ve ever used</h2>
<p>This very post is currently being typed on <code>GNU Emacs 27.1.91 (build 1, arm-apple-darwin20.3.0, Carbon Version 164 AppKit 2022.3) of 2021-03-15</code> on the
device in question.</p>
<p>Have I mentioned &ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;?</p>
<p>By the way, if you build Emacs like this on the M1:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew tap railwaycat/emacsmacport
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew install --formula emacs-mac --HEAD
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; you should be good to go.</p>
<h3 id="update-on-2021-04-15">Update on 2021-04-15</h3>
<p>A few days ago, I started seeing the following error during homebrew Emacs update:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-text" data-lang="text"><span style="display:flex;"><span>./temacs --batch  -l loadup --temacs=pbootstrap
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>make[1]: *** [bootstrap-emacs.pdmp] Killed: 9
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>make: *** [src] Error 2
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This looks similar to <a href="https://github.com/d12frosted/homebrew-emacs-plus/issues/292">this github issue on emacs-plus</a>, which was fixed on emacs
master.</p>
<p>It was easiest for me to switch to emacs-plus, which went like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew uninstall emacs-mac
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew tap d12frosted/emacs-plus
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew install emacs-plus@28 --with-no-titlebar
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="quo-vadis-one-device-to-rule-them-all">Quo vadis, one device to rule them all?</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s a pity that the ThinkPad, although powerful enough to satisfy <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#the-story-behind-this-story-one-context-to-rule-them-all">my single
computing device / single context requirement</a>, and with <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 becoming
increasingly useful</a> and hence addressing the dual-boot issue, does not satisfy
the <em>instantly available</em> requirement.</p>
<p>Fortunately the two devices cater for complementary contexts.</p>
<p>The Air is for instant-on writing, communication, admin and maybe a tiny bit of
development, whilst the ThinkPad is for all of the heavy lifting, but who knows
how these lines are going to be blurred in the coming months?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>meepx1e: I haz new laptop!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 14:02:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/</guid><description>WARNING: EXTREME PC hardware-related nerdiness ahead. Read at your own risk.
Just the new laptop, skulking in the bush. It is tradition around these parts that the welcoming of new computer machines is celebrated by, amongst many other rituals, a sometimes incomprehensible amount of customisation-related labour and a mention (or two) in these pages.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>WARNING: <strong>EXTREME</strong> PC hardware-related nerdiness ahead. Read at your own risk.</em></p>
<figure>
<a href="x1_skulking_in_bush.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hu_dfb8210ffe3d3c9d.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hu_1c301f9c1d303da5.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hu_55e451adb5cfb1bb.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hu_2fd34a2e53339f9c.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1_skulking_in_bush_hu_1c301f9c1d303da5.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>Just the new laptop, skulking in the bush.
</figure>
<p>It is tradition around these parts that the welcoming of new computer machines
is celebrated by, amongst many other rituals, a sometimes incomprehensible
amount of customisation-related labour and a mention (or two) in these pages.</p>
<p>Some examples from the past include:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2002/07/26/whoohooo-xfree86-dri-hacked-to-suspendresume/">Hacking Radeon suspend / resume support into the Linux kernel and the
X-Server in 2002</a>,
so that my cheap clone laptop could too.</li>
<li><a href="/2004/05/26/laptop-no-2/">Acquiring my first name-brand laptop (HP NC6000) in
2004</a>, with a whole gigabyte of RAM.</li>
<li><a href="/2006/07/22/new-new-laptop-laptop/">My first dual-core laptop in 2006</a>.</li>
<li><a href="/2007/04/10/a-critical-look-at-ubuntu-feisty-beta-on-an-hp-nc8430-laptop/">Reviewing Ubuntu Feisty on above-mentioned
laptop</a>
led to, as far as I can remember, my first really popular post, with about
50k visitors in a few days.</li>
<li>Relatively low-key announcements during my macOS phase, starting with the <a href="/2015/06/14/weekly-head-voices-91-theyre-back/">2015
MacBook Pro</a> and then later
the <a href="/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/">2017 MacBook Pro</a> on my birthday in
2017.</li>
</ul>
<p>Well folks, this post exists because on Tuesday, April 17, 2019 I became the
new owner of a Lenovo ThinkPad X1 Extreme.</p>
<p>This new device, just like all the previous ones, took up a considerable amount
of mental cycles before, during and after its acquisition.</p>
<p>This does make sense: It&rsquo;s the technical artefact I use for a large part of the
day to interface with and shape the universe around me. This shaping is how I
try to create value, so the main physical tool I used for this should be as
sharp as possible.</p>
<h1 id="so-tell-me-why-did-your-somewhat-stylish-macbook-phase-have-to-come-to-an-end">So, tell me, why did your somewhat stylish MacBook phase have to come to an end?</h1>
<p>It seems like <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/#new-laptop">just the other day when my mysterous employer bought me that
shiny 2017 top-of-the-line(ish) MacBook
Pro</a>.</p>
<p>They grow up so fast!</p>
<p>&hellip; at which point they summarily have to be replaced by a slightly different
and hopefully more effective new thing.</p>
<p>The virtual machines I have to use for some of my projects caused the <a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/SP756?locale=en_US">16GB
2.9GHz 2017 MacBook Pro</a> to
grind to a halt once too often.</p>
<p>I evaluated upgrading to the <a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/SP776?locale=en_US">2018 model with 32GB RAM and the 8th generation
i7</a>, but the disappointing
keyboards on the current MacBook Pro range made it even trickier than usual to
justify the substantial price of the upgrade.</p>
<p>The MacBooks are stellar machines, but only if you can look past the keyboard.</p>
<p>To add to that, after five years of macOS, it was time to check that I was
still able to work just as efficiently with The Other desktop operating
systems.</p>
<h1 id="why-did-you-decide-to-get-the-thinkpad-x1-extreme">Why did you decide to get the ThinkPad X1 Extreme?</h1>
<p>When you go searching for laptop workstations that are in the same class as the
15&quot; MacBook Pros, one of the main candidates is the <a href="https://www.lenovo.com/za/en/laptops/thinkpad/x-series/ThinkPad-X1-Extreme/p/22TP2TXX1E1">ThinkPad X1
Extreme</a>,
which, to my delight, was straight-forward to obtain from my favourite local
supplier!</p>
<figure>
<a href="x1e_180.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hu_3bbbd16ef3b780a1.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hu_a9b9d86ef187aabe.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hu_d5a5091712d37555.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hu_5f009f74df0b80cf.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/x1e_180_hu_a9b9d86ef187aabe.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>Can your workstation do this? (The keyboard is definitely an
improvement. I'm reserving judgement until a few months in. I'm still getting
used to that red mouse nub. In theory, this should be ideal for mostly keyboard
use with Emacs for example.) </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>(Interestingly, the price down here in ZAR is better than the dollar price on
Amazon directly converted to ZAR. This is usually the other way round.)</p>
<p>I made a deliberate choice for the version with the FullHD screen, and <em>not</em>
the 4k multi-touch panel.</p>
<p>&ldquo;WHAT? ARE WE BACK IN THE 1990s?!!&rdquo; you might ask, tapping away on your
high-resolution touch device with its beautiful screen and superb battery life.</p>
<p>During the 1.5+ years of using the 15&quot; MacBook Pro, with one of the most
beautiful screens in the business, I very rarely used that screen. Furthermore,
when mobile, the significantly longer battery life of the FHD version, along
with the slightly reduced weight, are more important.</p>
<p>Along with the 6-core 8750H i7 CPU, 16GB of RAM and 512GB of SSD ThinkPad, I
ordered an additional 1TB Samsung EVO Plus 970 NVMe SSD and an additional 16GB
RAM module.</p>
<p>One simply unscrews the bottom panel to reveal two accessible DIMM slots, and
two accessible M.2 SSD slots. I added the extra drive and extra RAM, put the
panel back, and booted up to a pretty sweet upgrade.</p>
<p>(Both drives are in the gigabytes per second read and write class. The built-in
WDC PC SN720 SDAQNTW-512G-1001 is only slightly slower than the Samsung 970.)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s good to know that I will be able to upgrade the RAM to 64GB, and the
storage to multiple terabytes of SSD, should that become necessary, or should I
be able to fabricate some or other good reason for this in the future.</p>
<h2 id="pro-tip-beware-duplicate-volume-ids-when-you-clone-a-drive">Pro-tip: Beware duplicate volume IDs when you clone a drive.</h2>
<p>I used the free <a href="https://www.samsung.com/semiconductor/minisite/ssd/download/tools/">Samsung Drive Migration Software for Consumer SSD
tool</a> to
image the factory-install of Windows to the new 1TB Samsung SSD.</p>
<p>After this, I simply changed the boot order in the BIOS (which also swaps C:
and D:, oh Windows!, and Bob was my uncle.</p>
<p>OR WAS HE?!</p>
<p>Only later when diagnosing why the Windows indexer was not picking up any new
files from my drive, did I figure out that the duplicate volume IDs on the
drives was confusing it.</p>
<p>Even later, after I had almost forgotten about the volume IDs, I had huge fun
fighting with the Windows boot loader simply giving up after an Ubuntu install.</p>
<p>You won&rsquo;t guess what the issue was, or will you?</p>
<h1 id="what-are-your-first-impressions">What are your first impressions?</h1>
<p>Although it feels lighter than the MBP, the laptop is thicker and slightly
bigger than the MBP. Due to the shape of the chassis, and especially the
ventilation rib on the bottom, it feels good in the hand.</p>
<p>The fans do come on quite easily in Windows, which can be disturbing. There are
fortunately a number of configuration options to ameliorate this issue.</p>
<p>The Linux support for this laptop is quite good. After a few hours of Manjaro
(I&rsquo;ve always wanted to see what an Arch-derivative was like), I installed
Ubuntu 19.04.</p>
<p>With minimal tuning, I can get the idle power consumption (with Emacs running
of course) down to about 7W.</p>
<p>This would in theory give me 10 hours of staring at Emacs, which is epic.</p>
<p>(Shortly after getting the laptop, I had to invest a not inconsiderable number
of hours into fine-tuning my Emacs configuration for Windows. Although Emacs on
Linux is still the ultimate experience, Emacs on Windows comes close
enough. For now.)</p>
<p>Probably due to the reduced weight and due to the laptop being able to keep
itself cool much more easily, the laptop fares significantly better than the
15&quot; MacBook Pro in the official Working in Bed and also Flipping Out Your
Laptop To Do Something Real Quick tests.</p>
<p>Other than that, features like the way the BIOS unlocks both hardware-encrypted
SSDs at boot using my fingerprint, are really quite neat.</p>
<h1 id="do-you-have-anything-else-to-say">Do you have anything else to say?</h1>
<p>No.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #125: Buddy.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2017 20:45:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/</guid><description>Monday, July 30 to Sunday, September 3, 2017.
(This post has turned into a huge ramble. It starts with parking, makes a quick visit to Yurp, buys a new laptop, compulsively measures time to try and increase quality of life, and then bounces like a hyperactive pinball between a book, a video and a blog post, all three about either not being special, not being happy or both. ENJOY!)
Parking Because I would prefer that you perceive the time that you invest in reading these posts as time also usefully spent, allow me to start with a visual exposition of the pleasantly straight-forward geometry of parallel parking.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Monday, July 30 to Sunday, September 3, 2017.</p>
<p>(This post has turned into a huge ramble. It starts with parking, makes a quick visit to Yurp, buys a new laptop, compulsively measures time to try and increase quality of life, and then bounces like a hyperactive pinball between a book, a video and a blog post, all three about either not being special, not being happy or both. ENJOY!)</p>
<h2 id="parking">Parking</h2>
<p>Because I would prefer that you perceive the time that you invest in reading these posts as time also usefully spent, allow me to start with a visual exposition of the pleasantly straight-forward <strong>geometry of parallel parking</strong>.</p>
<p>In other words, if you&rsquo;re like me and your parallel parking performance could do with some improvement (mine oscillates between “I am the best parallel parker in the world, wheels perfectly aligned 5mm from the pavement” and “ABORT ABORT!! Oh well, we will find parking another day.”), the following animation might be of assistance:</p>
<blockquote class="imgur-embed-pub" data-id="2g5Bzi9" lang="en"><a href="//imgur.com/2g5Bzi9">Parallel Parking</a></blockquote><script async="" charset="utf-8" src="//s.imgur.com/min/embed.js"></script>
<h2 id="yurp">Yurp</h2>
<p>In an astonishingly fortunate confluence of events, I ended up again in <strong>my other home country</strong>. Although time was short, business was executed, and a great deal of highly concentrated joy was artfully squeezed from every minute.</p>
<p>Thank you Dutch family. I hope to see you again soon!</p>
<h2 id="new-laptop">New laptop</h2>
<p>Back home, it was time for me to add another life year to my steadily growing collection.</p>
<p>My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">gracious employer</a> thought that the big day was an as good moment as any to equip me with a <strong>brand new work machine</strong>.</p>
<p>Up to then, I had been working on all of three different machines: <a href="/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/">Linux-running i7 desktop</a> (acquired in Feb of 2015), <a href="/2015/06/14/weekly-head-voices-91-theyre-back/">early 2015 13″ retina MacBook Pro</a> (acquired in June of 2015) and my <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2013/03/24/acer-v3-571g-fullhd-ips-superb-priceperformance-linux-development-laptop/">trusty old klunky i7 Acer Linux-running laptop</a> (acquired around March 2013).</p>
<p>Data is kept in sync, but context switching between different projects with different development environments on different machines at home and at work does seem to take up more time than I would care to admit.</p>
<p>Having everything on a single <em>powerful</em>-enough laptop would indeed make the most sense from a time-efficiency perspective.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m typing on the thing now. The keyboard&rsquo;s second-generation butterfly switches do take a little getting used to, but I believe I may have been converted.</p>
<p>Importantly, I&rsquo;ve already started seeing the advantages of always having all my work (and all my computer-based hobby-related toys) with me. No more context-switching means more time available for what happens between the switches.</p>
<p>(My more nerdily inclined readers, you can probably guess exactly which laptop this is. Ask me in the comments why this and not the alternatives!)</p>
<h2 id="measure-all-the-things">Measure all the things</h2>
<p>On the topic of <strong>time efficiency</strong>, in an attempt to better understand what I was doing with my free time, and how exactly I was spending time at work, I put in some extra effort <strong>to record more accurately every minute of my time awake</strong>. I dream about being able to squeeze out more value from each day by being able to measure and review.</p>
<p>This is an extension to establishing a <a href="/2017/06/28/weekly-head-voices-123-a-semblance-of-a-cadence/">cadence of accountability for deep work</a>, where one looks not only at deep work performed, but general value contributed and derived.</p>
<p>Watching SNL or College Humor clips on YouTube is fun, but can&rsquo;t really be considered high value. In terms of R&amp;R, reading a book, writing a blog post, learning something new and spending time with your family are all of high value.</p>
<p>Recording time like this does seem ever so slightly OCDish, but it was really for science, and mostly for evolution (see <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">rule #3 of <em>WHV’s Two Rules for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em></a>).</p>
<p>I did only manage to keep it up for slightly over two weeks.</p>
<p>What was interesting, was that the act of having to specify and record each block of time forced me to be much more <em>deliberate</em> about everything I did.</p>
<p>All of a sudden, even goofing off could only happen if I explicitly spent time deciding that goofing off was really justified. Furthermore, the fact that I knew exactly how many minutes I was goofing off, tended to keep these distractions short.</p>
<p>The problem with this experiment quite unsurprisingly turned out to be the overhead of mechanically having to record every minute. That being said, I think the availability of a practical, highly private and practical mechanism (unlike the one I tried) for the real-time and aggregated measurement and reporting of “time value” could be a substantial help in the continuous optimisation of one&rsquo;s days.</p>
<h2 id="happy-not-happy">Happy not happy</h2>
<p>On the topic of quality of life, I recently read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Subtle-Art-Not-Giving-Counterintuitive/dp/0062457713"><em>The Subtle Art of Not Giving a F*ck: A Counterintuitive Approach to Living a Good Life</em> by Mark Manson</a>. I was involuntarily eye-rolling quite regularly through the first 3/4 of the book, but by that time either Manson had just worn me down, or his writing had in fact greatly improved.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I think the message is an important one, especially for young(er) people: You&rsquo;re not special, so make peace with that as soon as you can. Accept that life is really just a series of problems that you have to solve, so at least pick the interesting ones. <strong>You probably won&rsquo;t ever be happy or content for more than a few moments</strong> (<a href="/2011/04/07/happinessexception-weekly-head-voices-44/">sounds familiar, doesn&rsquo;t it?</a>) because that&rsquo;s quite logically been evolved out of us. Pick the few things that you really care about, and commit to them.</p>
<p><a href="https://sivers.org">Derek Sivers</a>, himself no slouch when it comes to modern survival, summarises the book with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The opposite of every other book. Don’t try. Give up. Be wrong. Lower your standards. Stop believing in yourself. Follow the pain. Each point is profoundly true, useful, and more powerful than the usual positivity. Succinct but surprisingly deep, I read it in one night.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(Interestingly, the first of the four noble truths of <strong>Buddhism</strong> is that <strong>life is suffering</strong>. “Human beings are subject to desires and cravings, but even when we are able to satisfy these desires, the satisfaction is only temporary. Pleasure does not last; or if it does, it becomes monotonous.” see <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/buddhism/beliefs/fournobletruths_1.shtml">this BBC entry</a> for more happy thoughts about Buddhism. In fact-checking my summary up above, I just saw in Manson&rsquo;s book that he does in fact explicitly tell the story of Buddha, in chapter 2 already. Doh.)</p>
<p>On the topic of not being special, I recently stumbled upon this interview with Simon Sinek. It&rsquo;s all about the phenomenon of millenials in the workplace. Many of us around here (hey, we read long form blogs, this means we&rsquo;re probably old-school) don&rsquo;t classify as millenials, but the points Sinek makes about the role of old-school patience and focus in the work-place as opposed to the millenial-era instant gratification attention economy resonated with me.</p>
<p>Also, we&rsquo;re still not special. :)</p>
<p>Try and make time for the first 3 to 4 minutes of the video. That&rsquo;s what
I did, because I&rsquo;m not a millenial and I don&rsquo;t like watching
YouTube videos of what could have been blog posts, but then I just had to
finish the whole 18 minutes (dangit youtube! video was pulled so I had to
replace with 15 minute version on 2019-04-16:</p>
<iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hER0Qp6QJNU" width="560"></iframe>
<p>It would be remiss of me not to mention Wait but Why&rsquo;s brilliant and complementary exposition of <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/2013/09/why-generation-y-yuppies-are-unhappy.html">Why Generation Y Yuppies Are Unhappy</a>.</p>
<p>Whatever shall we do with this information?</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re not special (phew, that&rsquo;s a weight off one&rsquo;s shoulders!), and we can&rsquo;t ever attain more than fleeting happiness or contentment.</p>
<p>What we <em>can</em> do is to make peace, and to savour with wide open senses the fractal infinity hidden in the moments that we are blessed with.</p>
<p>P.S. Buddha also had a <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/buddhism/beliefs/fournobletruths_1.shtml">number of great tips</a>.</p>
<p>P.P.S. During the night I started worrying that readers, especially my mom (hi mom!), might think that I&rsquo;m unhappy, and that this post is a cry for help. I would like to assure you all that I&rsquo;m currently enjoying life more than ever before, at least as far as my failing old memory is concerned. I can personally vouch for the making-peace-and-savouring-moments approach.</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. Statistically, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/08/24/under-50-you-still-havent-hit-rock-bottom-happiness-wise/">humans hit happiness rock bottom</a> at around about 50, see the u-shaped graph below (thanks <a href="http://francoismalan.com">FM</a> for sending). A number of us are hiding here in the we&rsquo;ve-made-our-peace-thanks-for-all-the-fish long tails of the distribution, where we plan to ride this one out. Join us!</p>










<figure><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2017/08/24/under-50-you-still-havent-hit-rock-bottom-happiness-wise/">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/wapo-happy-graph.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #91: They’re back.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/06/14/weekly-head-voices-91-theyre-back/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2015 14:59:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/06/14/weekly-head-voices-91-theyre-back/</guid><description>So after exactly no-one asked me when the Weekly Head Voices would be back, or why they stopped, I decided to reverse my almost-decision of quitting. This hiatus made me realise that the WHV are one of the few tenuous connecting lines between me and a tiny group of readers, people I am quite fond of, dotted around the world.
Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2015.
Again inspired by the information-and-entertainment-dense way that Swimgeek manages to do it, I’m going to try this in bullet form.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>So after exactly no-one asked me when the Weekly Head Voices would be back, or why they stopped, I decided to reverse my almost-decision of quitting. This hiatus made me realise that the WHV are one of the few tenuous connecting lines between me and a tiny group of readers, people I am quite fond of, dotted around the world.</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/wpid-afrikaburn-2015-sunset-cpbotha.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/wpid-afrikaburn-2015-sunset-cpbotha.jpg"
        
            alt="Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2015."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Sunset at AfrikaBurn 2015.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Again inspired by the information-and-entertainment-dense way that <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/">Swimgeek</a> manages to do it, I’m going to try this in bullet form.</p>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
    We, that’s me with friends <a href="http://dewijnrecensent.nl/">DWR</a>, PK, TvD, CvdB, MJ and a Very Flat Cat, spent the whole week (Monday April 25 to Sunday May 1) at <a href="http://afrikaburn.com/">AfrikaBurn</a> 2015. We built (the desert truly is rock hard – try ramming a metre of rebar down into it, then repeat) and ran <i>Pompen en Pimpen</i>, bicycle repair and pimping theme camp extraordinaire, on the corner of 9ish and Binnekring. The experience unfortunately is exactly one of those things that is more or less impossible to explain in words. I’ll try a few keywords nonetheless: Hard labour at the Best Party Ever; music never stops (sleep never really comes); engineered herd humanity; so many people, so much space; gifting really is great. We’re going to have to go again.
  </li>
<li>
    Damnit. I’m not very good at bullets.
  </li>
<li>
    As if fate were a thing that could taunt me, a super interesting project at work has resulted in me: <ul class="org-ul">
<li>
        Buying an early 2015 13″ Retina MacBook Pro. It’s super portable and the battery lasts more than 6 hours, but I still like working on my <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2013/03/24/acer-v3-571g-fullhd-ips-superb-priceperformance-linux-development-laptop/">klunky Linux-running Acer laptop</a> more.
      </li>
<li>
        Learning Objective C and X Code (AppCode is miles better).
      </li>
<li>
        Working on an experimental iOS app.
      </li>
<li>
        Learning to program Apple Metal on iOS and on the OSX desktop (way before most other people).
      </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
    In another project I got my hands dirty with <a href="http://threejs.org/">three.js</a>. What a lovely library for doing WebGL! We’ll soon be shipping a product feature based on this.
  </li>
<li>
    Shortly afer having resigned myself to never ever finding a new house that we all liked, we found a house we all liked! If all goes according to plan, and the various mafia bosses we’re borrowing money from cooperate, we will soon be moving in to a place of our own. I guess this means we are sort of settling down again.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>Have a beautiful week tiny group of readers!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>meepz97: I haz a new computar machine!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2015 07:36:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/02/15/meepz97-i-haz-a-new-computar-machine/</guid><description>WARNING: EXTREME PC hardware-related nerdiness ahead. Read at your own risk.
My most awesome employer to date (that’s the vxlabs of course!) decided to treat me with a brand new workstation. On Tuesday, February 10 of the year 2015 the new desktop PC arrived. (Around these parts, we have a long tradition of writing about new computer acquisitions, see for example 2002, 2004, 2006, 2008, 2009, 2010, 2011 or 2013.)
Because this event has sparked quite some interest amongst the various groups reading this blog, management has decided to present workstation-related information in a Q and A format.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>WARNING: <strong>EXTREME</strong> PC hardware-related nerdiness ahead. Read at your own risk.</em></p>
<p>My most awesome employer to date (that’s <a href="http://www.vxlabs.com/">the vxlabs</a> of course!) decided to treat me with a brand new workstation. On Tuesday, February 10 of the year 2015 the new desktop PC arrived. (Around these parts, we have a long tradition of writing about new computer acquisitions, see for example <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2002/07/17/toe-matj-toe-sei-not-enaf-taim/">2002</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2004/05/26/laptop-no-2/">2004</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2006/07/22/new-new-laptop-laptop/">2006</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/07/15/pleasure-apparatus-2008/">2008</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/">2009</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/">2010</a>, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/">2011</a> or <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2013/03/24/acer-v3-571g-fullhd-ips-superb-priceperformance-linux-development-laptop/">2013</a>.)</p>
<p>Because this event has sparked quite some interest amongst the various groups reading this blog, management has decided to present workstation-related information in a Q and A format.</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/wpid-meepz97_exposed.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/wpid-meepz97_exposed.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="say-what-a-desktop-pc-and-not-a-laptop">Say what?! A desktop PC and not a laptop??!</h2>
<p>Yes people, it’s an actual desktop PC, not a laptop. They’re big boxy things that eat laptops for breakfast and they really appeal to old-school nerds like me. Plus, when I go to work at the coffee shop around the corner with a ginormous black midtower PC under my arm instead of some far-too-easy-to-carry mac laptop, the other hipsters have no choice but to concede that <i>I</i> am their new king.</p>
<p>(Beautiful and thin laptops have become completely mainstream. Even that erstwhile PC-toting bro with his suit supply suit and his excel spreadsheets and his outlook email now has one. Hehe.)</p>
<h2 id="what-exactly-do-you-have-in-that-big-black-box">What exactly do you have in that big black box?</h2>
<p>I’m so happy you asked. Sensitive readers might want to look away, because this is going to get fairly graphical. I hand-picked all components from the limited set available to us this far south on the African continent. This is what I came up with:</p>
<ul>
<li>One hundred and twenty rainbows.</li>
<li>Fifty growth-hormone boosted angry unicorns, with twenty spares.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.technologyx.com/featured/gigabyte-ga-z97-d3h-motherboard-review/">Gigabyte Z97-D3H motherboard</a> (Intel LAN, Realtek ALC1150 audio)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.guru3d.com/articles-pages/core-i7-4790-processor-review,1.html">Intel Core i7 4790</a></li>
<li>16 JIJABYTES of Corsair DDR3 RAM</li>
<li><a href="http://www.guru3d.com/articles-pages/gigabyte-geforce-gtx-750-ti-windforce-review,1.html">Gigabyte GeForce GTX750Ti Windforce</a> graphics</li>
<li><a href="http://www.techradar.com/reviews/pc-mac/pc-components/storage/disk-drives-hdd-ssd/samsung-850-pro-512gb-1255900/review">Samsung 850 PRO 512GB SSD</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.guru3d.com/articles-pages/cooler-master-cm-690-iii-review,1.html">Cooler Master 690 iii chassis</a> with 550W Cooler Master Vanguard power supply</li>
<li>More rainbows.</li>
</ul>
<p>As nerdiness-fuelled retail fixes go, this rated 23 on a scale of 1 to 10, with 10 being multiple head asplosions. Even now, multiple days later, when I look sideways at the beautiful black box, my knees turn into jelly and I blush a little bit.</p>
<h2 id="what-operating-system-have-you-installed-on-this-machine">What operating system have you installed on this machine?</h2>
<p>Emacs and Linux, software of the gods.</p>
<p>(By the way, if you run into kernel GPFs in <code>__slab_alloc</code> with this hardware, remember to add <code>intremap=no_x2apic_optout</code> to the kernel boot parameters. It seems the BIOS is being naughty and reporting that it does not have x2apic when it in fact does.)</p>
<h2 id="how-fast-is-the-samsung-850-pro-ssd">How fast is the Samsung 850 PRO SSD?</h2>
<p>This SSD is STUPID FAST, there is just no other way to describe it.</p>
<p>Anandtech <a href="http://www.anandtech.com/show/8216/samsung-ssd-850-pro-128gb-256gb-1tb-review-enter-the-3d-era/13">has this to say about the drive</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To be honest, there is not a single thing missing in the 850 Pro because
regardless of the angle you look at the drive from, it will still top the
charts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(My employer is still smarting a little bit from the cost angle however. I’ll work extra hard to compensate.)</p>
<h2 id="are-you-disappointed-that-having-to-encrypt-the-ssd-will-slow-it-down">Are you disappointed that having to encrypt the SSD will slow it down?</h2>
<p>Fortunately, this drive also has hardware-based full disc encryption built right in. A further major improvement over my previously favourite drives which also have hardware support for encryption, the Intel 520 SSDs, is that the Samsung 850 PRO supports the TCG Opal 2.0 standard for the configuration and unlocking of the drive encryption.</p>
<p>In short, all data that touches the drive is transparently encrypted, at over 500 megabytes / second (!!). When the PC boots up, it asks me for my decryption password. If I get it right, the drive unlocks itself; if I don’t it does not. If anyone (I’m not paranoid, they really ARE out to get me!) gets access to my PC by whichever means, they will most probably not be able see one bit of my or my client’s data.</p>
<p>If you’re interested, you can find much more detail about how this works, and I how I configured it using open source tools, in <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2015/02/11/use-the-hardware-based-full-disk-encryption-your-tcg-opal-ssd-with-msed/">this other post I wrote over at vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<h2 id="are-you-happy-now">Are you happy now?</h2>
<p>Yes.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>New Samsung NP300V3A laptop is welcomed into the family!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2011 11:03:53 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/08/16/new-samsung-np300v3a-laptop-is-welcomed-into-the-family/</guid><description>It’s traditional around these parts that I write a post whenever I get to welcome a new computer into the family. In July of 2002 it was Dr. Evil, more a brick than a laptop, in May of 2004 it was my beloved 14″ HP NC6000 laptop, in July of 2006 I met my 15.4″ HP NC8430 (employer-supplied, thank you employer!), which in turn led to this Ubuntu-critical blog post of mine that attracted 50000 (yes, fifty thousand) readers over 2 days, in July of 2008 I splurged on a lovely quad core desktop machine, in September of 2009 I acquired an Asus 1005HA-H netbook, and in November of 2010 my employer got me a super-strong Dell Latitude E6410 laptop.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>It’s traditional around these parts that I write a post whenever I get to welcome a new computer into the family. In <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2002/07/17/toe-matj-toe-sei-not-enaf-taim/" title="dr evil laptop">July of 2002 it was Dr. Evil</a>, more a brick than a laptop, in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2004/05/26/laptop-no-2/" title="NC6000 post">May of 2004 it was my beloved 14″ HP NC6000 laptop</a>, in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2006/07/22/new-new-laptop-laptop/" title="nc8430 post">July of 2006 I met my 15.4″ HP NC8430</a> (employer-supplied, thank you employer!), which in turn led to <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2007/04/10/a-critical-look-at-ubuntu-feisty-beta-on-an-hp-nc8430-laptop/" title="15 seconds of blog fame">this Ubuntu-critical blog post of mine</a> that attracted 50000 (yes, fifty thousand) readers over 2 days, <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/07/15/pleasure-apparatus-2008/" title="bees blog post">in July of 2008 I splurged on a lovely quad core desktop machine</a>, in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/" title="asus 1005HA-H netbook">September of 2009 I acquired an Asus 1005HA-H netbook</a>, and in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/" title="dell e6410 post">November of 2010 my employer got me a super-strong Dell Latitude E6410 laptop</a>.</p>
<p>Today I welcomed the latest and probably prettiest laptop so far into the family:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/samsung_np300v3a.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/08/samsung_np300v3a.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty Samsung NP300V3A-S01NL laptop!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty Samsung NP300V3A-S01NL laptop!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Behold the <a href="http://tweakers.net/pricewatch/286118/samsung-np300v3a-s01nl.html" title="tweakers pricewatch page for the Samsung NP300V3A-S01NL">Samsung NP300V3A-S01NL (Series 3)</a>. It has an absolutely gorgeous-to-type-on chiclet keyboard, a 13.3″ matte (!) display, NVIDIA GT520m graphics with Optimus, second-gen Core i5 2410m, 4G RAM and 500G disc, all for a terribly reasonable price, which is important, as this one is not employer-bought. A man needs a laptop like this for his top-secret personal biznizz, yes?</p>
<p>It’s running Windows Home Premium, so I have to use Truecrypt instead of EFS for encrypting my biznizz, which is stored mostly in my Dropbox pro account. The battery life is quite impressive probably due in part to Optimus switching. The drawback of this is that I probably won’t be putting Linux on here anytime soon. These days you can use both the graphics adapters in Linux, but both of them stay active all the time, so it kills the battery really quickly.</p>
<p>We learn at least two more things from this post:</p>
<ol>
<li>I do seem to exhibit a certain obsessive compulsive behaviour when it comes to keeping track of the arrival dates of the various computers in my life.</li>
<li>When spring comes around, hide my credit card.</li>
</ol>
<p><em>Update on May 2, 2012:</em> I have just eaten my hat. Ubuntu Linux 12.04 with Bumblebee runs just wonderfully on this laptop. Read all about it in <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2012/05/01/review-of-ubuntu-linux-12-04-on-the-samsung-np300v3a-core-i5-nvidia-optimus-laptop/" title="vxlabs blog post reviewing ubuntu 12.04 on the samsung np300v3a">my VXLabs blog post</a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>An Inside Job. [Weekly Head Voices #33]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 14:10:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</guid><description>Hiatus: temporarily over.
My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to that, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am. :)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hiatus: temporarily over.</p>
<p>My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to <em>that</em>, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am. :)</p>
<p>In this post, I’m going to touch upon the highlights of the past seven weeks (40 to 46) and I’m going to do so with bullets, seeing as I’m in a bullety-kind of mood.</p>
<ul>
<li>I spent a week in Stellenbosch teaching Information Visualisation! Read all about it in <a href="/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/" title="stbvis2010 blog post">this special blog post</a>.</li>
<li>The week after that my mom came to visit us. She really has the best genes.</li>
<li>I met my new work laptop: A Dell Latitude E6410 with Core i5 M540 2.53GHz CPU, 4G ram, 500G HDD, NVidia NVS 3100m GPU with 512 MB video mem. It’s a 14″ latop (15.4″ is a completely useless format, flame me in the comments), but due to the materials used quite heavy. I like it!</li>
<li>Another one of our STW NIG research proposals has been granted. I conceived and developed this one together with colleagues from the LUMC Departments of Anatomy, of Surgery and of Orthopaedics. The title is <em>High-definition Atlas-based surgical planning for Pelvic Surgery</em> and we get to combine high-resolution human histology, mega-volume rendering, , biomechanical modelling and surgical simulation. With this grant we can appoint two more Ph.D. students (one in my group, one at the LUMC) for four years to work on this!!</li>
<li>The week after that I went to Salt Lake City (Utah, US and A) to attend the conference previously known as <a href="http://vis.computer.org/VisWeek2010/" title="IEEE VisWeek 2010 website">IEEE Visualization</a>. It was AWESOME! (blog post half-written, will soon publish).</li>
<li>The week after that I had a really cool dream: I was playing high-speed catch with a bunch of people outside. The ball was randomly changing shape between rock, papers and scissors. If you wanted to catch it, you didn’t only have to be at the right place at the right time, but your hand also had to be in the right complementary configuration to catch the shape-shifting ball.</li>
<li>Now that we’re talking about dreams: <em>I finally saw <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1375666/" title="IMDB page for Inception">Inception</a> and was completely blown away.</em> It’s not about being complicated, it’s about being a well-told story and a fantastically filmed movie. What I positively adored, is the fact that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan" title="Wikipedia page about Christopher Nolan">Nolan</a> doesn’t require much: He only needs you to believe that dreams can be shared, without giving away too many of the details of the mechanism, and then builds a marvellous story on that canvas. My absolute favourite scene was the waking up on the plane, just before the landing, almost at the end of the film. I loved the way in which the characters looked at each other, and the possible interpretations of their expressions.</li>
<li>On the topic of the Underworld gig in the Heineken Music Hall: I hope I have my voice back before my morning lecture tomorrow morning. Thank you Fantastic Friends!</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it kids. If you’ve come this far, you’re now mostly up to date. Please leave me a comment, it’s good for my serotonin! I hope you have a great week. To get you off to a  good start, here’s a music video showing what an infectious idea could look like…</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<div class="embed-vimeo" style="text-align: center;">
<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="473" mozallowfullscreen="" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/15391189" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="840"></iframe>
</div>
</div>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices for Week 36</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2009 08:35:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/</guid><description>Dear readers,
The time has come for the second installment of the exciting new Weekly Head Voices feature! My PR people tell me that this is a roaring success and that I am rapidly on my way to becoming an A-List blogger. My therapist tells me that I should find a good psychiatrist.
Before starting, I’d like to show the following photo (will get back to it later):</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear readers,</p>
<p>The time has come for the second installment of the exciting new Weekly Head Voices feature!  My PR people tell me that this is a roaring success and that I am rapidly on my way to becoming an A-List blogger. My therapist tells me that I should find a good psychiatrist.</p>
<p>Before starting, I’d like to show the following photo (will get back to it later):</p>
<p><a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:The_Tropicana.JPG" title=""><img alt="The_Tropicana_400" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-581" data-attachment-id="581" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"5.34","credit":"","camera":"FinePix A345","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1147716095","copyright":"","focal_length":"7.8","iso":"64","shutter_speed":"0.0024003840614498","title":""}' data-image-title="The_Tropicana_400" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400-300x225.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400.jpg" data-orig-size="400,300" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2009/09/05/weekly-head-voices-for-week-36/the_tropicana_400/" height="300" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 85vw, 400px" src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400.jpg 400w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/09/The_Tropicana_400-300x225.jpg 300w" title="The_Tropicana_400" width="400"/></a></p>
<p>In order to facilitate your reading experience, I have bolded in each paragraph some words that represent, with differing levels of effectiveness, the theme of that paragraph.  This way, you can easily skip ahead, keeping in mind that you’re probably skipping over some truly inspiring writing.</p>
<p>During the past week, I had 11 face-to-face <strong>meetings</strong> with students, colleagues and collaborators.  Apart from these meetings, I presented the MedVis group’s research to a group of new postgrads on Tuesday and hosted, together with colleagues from the LUMC, a visit by <a href="http://www.tornier.com/site" title="Tornier website">Tornier</a> on Friday.  It turns out that this job does in fact require a seemingly paradoxical mix of computer nerd and social butterfly.</p>
<p>On Monday, I acted as external member in the M.Sc. opposition of a thesis titled “In vivo identification of short range stiffness in the human wrist” – the student managed to figure out internal wrist muscle characteristics by applying external angular displacement and measuring effective torque.  Reviewing the work was an interesting experience, as biomechanical modelling is not one of my research foci.  All in all, very good work, although it did remind me again of why <strong>one should not typeset longer documents with a sans serif font</strong>.</p>
<p>The highlight of the week is surely <a href="http://gerwindehaan.nl/" title="Gerwin's website"><strong>Gerwin de Haan</strong></a><strong>‘s</strong> <a href="http://visualization.tudelft.nl/People/GerwinDeHaan/thesis" title="Gerwin's PhD page"><strong>PhD defense</strong></a>.  An exemplary opposition, with solid attacks by the committee (6 full professors and 1 associate professor) and great defensive moves by the intrepid candidate, made for an entertaining morning.  The day was concluded with a celebratory party during which the candidate, besides consuming amounts of beer fit for a fresh doctor, received congratulatory loot fit for a PS3 and Rockband-addicted pirate!</p>
<p>In other nerd-worthy news: I am now the proud owner of an <a href="http://www.cnet.com.au/asus-eee-pc-1005ha-h-339297780.htm" title="asus eeepc 1005ha-h cnet review"><strong>Asus 1005HA-H Netbook</strong></a>, rated with 10.5 hours of battery life.  I can confirm that the battery life is indeed awe-inspiring, also in practice.   The little beast easily lasts a whole day, and then some.  The only issue so far has been choosing a <strong>good encryption solution</strong>.  The little Atom N280 doesn’t manage much more than 30MB/s in the Truecrypt encryption benchmark, and about 38MB/s even with the optimised Diskcryptor implementation.  The Windows XP Home that this netbook ships with of course does not support EFS.  In the end, I went for Truecrypt (I use it everywhere else) and just copied over the 25G encrypted container from my Big Laptop.</p>
<p>Getting back to the photo above:  Boys and girls, thanks to my generous leader and the TU Delft, I get to join said generous leader and <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/~jorik/" title="Jorik's homepage">Jorik</a> on a trip to <a href="http://vis.computer.org/VisWeek2009/" title="VisWeek 2009"><strong>IEEE Visualization 2009</strong></a> in Atlantic City!  For the socially more well-adjusted readers, this is like Visualisation Nerd Heaven: A whole week of mingling with technically creative colleagues, discussing the latest visualisation tidbits, following paper presentations and Sleeping Much Less(tm).  Brilliant!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>