<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Lazar-Focus on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/lazar-focus/</link><description>Recent content in Lazar-Focus on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 21:26:26 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/lazar-focus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #229: Staycation PERMA-Station</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 21:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/</guid><description> Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&amp;rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="bettys_jocks.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_cd0e487bf3a491b3.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_fe1fd4e1918cf601.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_da4cbb1337c453aa.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_a75b8a71c1ebf5a5.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/07/27/weekly-head-voices-229-staycation-perma-station/bettys_jocks_hu_fe1fd4e1918cf601.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a short but surprisingly balmy weekend in Betty&rsquo;s Bay (In Winter, a large part of Betty&rsquo;s remains permanently in the shadow of the mountain.)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This edition of the WHV looks back at the week from Monday July 19 to Sunday
July 25, 2021, a week of untold wonders and intense enjoyment, a week deserving
of the hallowed title of&hellip; <em>STAYCATION!</em></p>
<p>Jokes aside, it was a perfectly enjoyable week of time off, most of it spent at
home or close to it.</p>
<p>We spent time together, took care of hobby- and side-projects, and even had
time to daydream and come up with some wacky ideas which should probably never
see the light of day, but which one day just might.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-1-dot-3-released">Lazar Focus 1.3 released</h2>
<p>On the evening of Tuesday, July 20, after a flurry of programming and testing,
<a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2021/07/21/lazar-focus-1.3.0-released-real-time-focus-feedback/">Lazar Focus 1.3 was released</a>.</p>
<p>Noteworthy is its new ability to measure and give real-time feedback on your
current focus, as an easy to interpret percentage.</p>
<p>The more you resist distractions, the higher the focus percentage.</p>
<p>When developing this feature, I ended up selecting a 5 minute rolling window,
after I was initially planning a pomodoro length. Five minutes seem to be a
sort of sweet spot in terms of seeing one&rsquo;s distractions affect one&rsquo;s score,
but not having it immediately distroyed, so that there&rsquo;s still time to recover.</p>
<p>I wanted to mention here the interesting disconnect between the programming I
do for this completely disconnected hobby project in a language (Pascal-ish)
that I don&rsquo;t particularly prefer but don&rsquo;t mind on the one hand, and my day
job, for which I sometimes still get to program, on the other.</p>
<h2 id="perma-the-five-building-blocks-of-well-being">PERMA: The five building blocks of well-being</h2>
<p>So yeah, there&rsquo;s a pretty interesting disconnect&hellip;</p>
<p>Writing code for LF, in this case perhaps perhaps noteworthy the real-time
focus tracking data-structure, namely a run-length encoded series of (no)focus
time durations that automatically get truncated, lengthened and pruned as time
progresses, was 100% fun and relaxation.</p>
<p>This is not the most tricky thing to implement, but the process of first
cooking it up in my brain, and then later sitting down to implement it, and
seeing it work, was just challenging enough to result in several periods of
complete immersion in, or engagement with, the task.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Flourish-Visionary-Understanding-Happiness-Well-being/dp/1439190763/ref=sr%5F1%5F6?dchild=1&amp;qid=1627409990&amp;refinements=p%5F27%3AMartin+Seligman&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-6">Martin Seligman&rsquo;s book titled <em>Flourish</em></a>, which I&rsquo;m slowly working through
at the moment (he is a great and impactful psychologist, but perhaps not the
world&rsquo;s greatest story teller, sorry Prof Seligman), he explains that human
<a href="https://ppc.sas.upenn.edu/learn-more/perma-theory-well-being-and-perma-workshops">well-being, or flourishing, consists of five building blocks, namely</a>:</p>
<ol>
<li>Positive Emotion: gratitude, savouring the present, hope and optimism,</li>
<li>Engagement: Lose oneself in a challenging (err) task,</li>
<li>Relationships: Love and be loved by friends and family,</li>
<li>Meaning: belonging to and serving some cause greater than oneself and</li>
<li>Accomplishment: Pursuing achievement and mastery for its own sake.</li>
</ol>
<p>My little LF programming exercise was <em>exactly</em> right for triggering a bit of
item number 2, namely engagement.</p>
<p>I am happy that I could slip a little PERMA in here on the back of Lazar Focus,
a little tool that is also proving useful in ways that I did not expect. ;)
Although the book is not the easiest going, it makes some valuable points if
you too are a fan of well-being.</p>
<h2 id="pfizer-jab-1-in-da-pocket">Pfizer jab #1 IN DA POCKET</h2>
<p>I really loves me some cutting edge science.</p>
<p>I know that the mRNA vaccines have been in development for decades now, but
they still represent such an amazing technological flex.</p>
<p>How fantastic is it that some of our cleverest humans have designed and tested
<a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/different-vaccines/mrna.html">this vaccine that consists of usually unstable mRNA</a>, to be injected into human
cells where our the cellular machinery in our bodies will dutifully follow the
mRNA instructions to frikking synthesise and display a piece of spike protein
that looks enough like the COVID-19 spike protein so that our immune system
will notice and immediately start creating antibodies, all without us actually
getting infected.</p>
<p>As if that&rsquo;s not enough, the introduced mRNA is broken down ASAP after
synthesis.</p>
<p>HOT DAMN we live in the future and it&rsquo;s pretty awesome up here!</p>
<p>I AM EXCITE</p>
<p>I am also really happy with the super efficient walk-in vaccination procedure at the Town Hall here in Somerset West.</p>
<p>I would have been in and out in 30 minutes with Pfizer jab #1 had I not run
into and started chatting with friends in the side-effect waiting area.</p>
<p>Kudos to the Western Cape for running this like the Star Trek medical bay.</p>
<p>Still friends, how strange are the days that we find ourselves in?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #208: Stilbaai</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 10:59:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</guid><description>Welcome back folks!
Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.
It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.
Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks!</p>
<p>Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.</p>
<p>It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period
Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.</p>










<figure><a href="skulpiesbaai_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu_46acf3c3f678d550.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu_f7f6cdf435a7c4d9.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu_1614c582d184de22.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu_f29fa82170a547c1.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu_f7f6cdf435a7c4d9.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="running-and-reading">Running and reading</h2>
<p>I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> (14) completed her
first (virtual) 10km race.</p>
<p>Her journey started when a friend from school invited her to join the race, at
which point GOU #1 suddenly became much more enthusiastic about running
regularly with her old dad. (that&rsquo;s me)</p>
<p>There is something pretty primal about running with your offspring, an
observation that I might have mentioned before on these pages.</p>
<p>Anyways, after her race she was visibly happy, and also relieved that, in her
words, &ldquo;she didn&rsquo;t die&rdquo;.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m perhaps even more happy about than the preparatory runs together, and
her completing the race, is that since the race we&rsquo;ve been out together for a
run or three.</p>
<p>(Running and reading are two of the most important low-level habits I would
like to try and get my offspring hooked on.)</p>
<h2 id="ieee-vis2020">IEEE VIS2020</h2>
<p>At the start of October, I had a great experience <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#vcbm-2020-virtually">virtually attending the VCBM
2020 conference</a>.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough grade A1 10/10 conferencing for one year, my other
favourite conference, IEEE VIS (for visualization) was also fully virtual this
year in the week of October 26, so again I dove into YouTube streams and
well-organised discord rooms, and again this experience was highly edifying and
enjoyable.</p>
<p>Somehow, it was even <em>more</em> fun than my already optimistic expectations to run
into friends at the conference.</p>
<p>I would like to transfer this one piece of sage advice given by the amazing
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%5Fvan%5FWijk">Prof. Jarke van Wijk</a> during the panel on &ldquo;Why should I stay in academia&rdquo; when
the discussion treated the issue of dealing with rejection, something that is
unfortunately a regular part of most academic careers.</p>
<p>At this point, he was referring specifically to accepted papers and proposals,
but the advice should really be applied to any victory, large or small, in all
walks of life:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Celebrate your victories.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="cycles">Cycles</h2>
<p>You will of course remember that we were fortunate enough to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">spend our last few
days of freedom in Stilbaai,</a> as autumn was arriving, and more acutely right
before the first lockdown started on March 26,</p>
<p>It was really great going back to the exact same house (thanks kind host!),
after months of various levels of lockdown, this time just as spring was really
getting off the ground.</p>










<figure><a href="stilbaai_0181.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_hu_307c06ace4a2e073.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_hu_6d9a3153824ea304.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_hu_a412f99424343cec.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_hu_9b81c80d3a5894ee.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_hu_6d9a3153824ea304.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I did take work with me for the long weekend, but this time, and quite
unexpectedly, the important <a href="/tags/disconnecting">disconnect</a> happened quite quickly without too much
conscious effort from my side.</p>
<p>If I had to put my finger on it, I would say that getting everyone to go
outside as often as possible on little adventures of various sizes was the
catalyst.</p>
<h2 id="back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">Back to reality: An 18-minute plan for managing your day</h2>
<p>I could not imagine a more sudden transition from the long weekend zen above
than this jump to Peter Bregman&rsquo;s 18 minute plan for planning your work day.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Sometimes, fortunately mostly later in the afternoon, I wonder why my systems
have failed in helping me to keep my eye on that ball for longer. (See <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">my
slippery eel</a> for more struggles.)</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s when I procrastinate quasi-productively by searching online for any new
self-optimisation tricks that I might have missed, and which might constitute
that Last Piece of The Puzzle that will fix this once and for all.</p>
<p>This time, to my great surprise, I did actually run into something 1. that was
written aaaaaall the way back in 2009 and 2. that contained something new that
I had not run into before, namely the &ldquo;refocus&rdquo; reminder.</p>
<p>The refocus reminder is literally an alarm that goes off every hour on the
hour, at which point you explicitly take a step back for a whole minute to
review the past hour, and, if required (most probably the case the later it is
in the day), to re-commit to the following hour.</p>
<p>This reminded me specifically about mindfulness&rsquo;s <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#therunning-and-the-mindful">&ldquo;Each breath a new beginning;
each out-breath a letting go&rdquo;</a>, and more generally about <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">life as eternal
practice</a>.</p>
<p>You can use any sort of timer to do this, but this seemed like a great feature
for the little Lazar Focus app, so I implemented it along with a nice
mindfulness bell sound to add some gravitas to the moment.</p>
<p>If you like, you can read the short summary I wrote about the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/10/24/peter-bregmans-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day-and-the-surprising-power-of-refocus-reminders/">18-minute plan
and refocus reminders over on the LazarFocused blog</a>. There are some other more
widely known but great tips for running your work days more efficiently.</p>
<h2 id="kind-regards">Kind regards</h2>
<p>Folks, thank you very much for joining me here.</p>
<p>The comments section below is ready for your thoughts, if you would like to
externalise them.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #200: We are extremely pleased to be here</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 17:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/</guid><description> Figure 1: A rainbow over Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay, captured by GOU#1.
Well hello there everyone, and welcome to this, the 200th edition of the Weekly Head Voices.
While I am super happy that we&amp;rsquo;ve reached this number of episodes, I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything special planned, besides being festively two weeks late.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="bb_rainbow.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu_c3336be346de21de.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu_3d1e61d5698c1df8.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu_748cbaeb57ebf6ba.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu_55fc6d15be58919c.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/bb_rainbow_hu_3d1e61d5698c1df8.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A rainbow over Betty&rsquo;s Bay, captured by GOU#1."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A rainbow over Betty&rsquo;s Bay, captured by GOU#1.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there everyone, and welcome to this, the 200th edition of the Weekly
Head Voices.</p>
<p>While I am super happy that we&rsquo;ve reached this number of episodes, I don&rsquo;t have
anything special planned, besides being festively two weeks late.</p>
<p>Being that late also means that this post looks back at the three weeks from
Monday June 29 to Sunday July 19 of the year 2020, also known as Cray-cray 20.</p>
<h2 id="my-attempt-at-dipping-my-toes-carefully-into-the-world-of-mechanical-keyboards">My attempt at dipping my toes carefully into the world of mechanical keyboards</h2>
<p>You might remember that <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#ergonomic-keyboard-one-way-street">back in May I wrote the following</a> after having tried
out a cheap non-ergonomic (i.e. straight) keyboard:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One could perhaps get used to the mushiness, or preferably just invest in a
more expensive (mechanical) keyboard, but that ulnar deviation is a total deal
breaker.</p>
<p>My dreams of joining the clickety-clackety cliques of the mechanical keyboard
digerati had been shattered, fortunately quite cheaply.</p>
<p>Instead, I shall be redoubling my Sculpt stockpiling efforts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Well about that&hellip;</p>
<p>The clickety-clackety cliques continued calling, and so I decided to apply an
additional but small amount of money on a very much entry-level mechanical
keyboard in order to determine if my mechanical keyboard dreams were to remain
just that.</p>
<p>The cheap but still quite respectable (well, if you&rsquo;re ok with rainbow
lighting) <a href="https://youtu.be/IYN3aHjbxmU">T-Dagger Corvette</a> arrived this past Wednesday around lunch time,
along with its extremely clicky and hotswappable (!!) <a href="https://mechanicalkeyboards.com/switches/index.php?switch=Outemu-Blue">Outemu blue switches</a>.</p>
<p>(Each and every key has its own removable, mechanical switch, in this case
Outemu blues, which are tactile and clicky. Each colour of each brand has its
own characteristics, so you can fine-tune how you would like to type, and how
you would like it to sound while you type.)</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve only spent a few days working with it, but my word, what a bunch of fun
typing has become!</p>
<p>The extreme tactility of the keys, together with the calmly confident click that
each press causes (this dream can of course only really take place during the
current WFH phase we are going through), has really put the titillation back
into typing.</p>
<p>This is so much fun that I&rsquo;ll probably keep at it for a while.</p>
<p>Also, compared to <a href="/2020/05/03/weekly-head-voices-193-covid-19-part-3/#microsoft-sculpt-ergonomic-desktop-at-4-years-rip">one of my previous Sculpt keyboards where the failure of a
single key meant that I had to replace the whole keyboard</a>, it&rsquo;s great that with
this far cheaper mechanical keyboard I am able to pull and replace, quite
trivially, the mechanical switch in question.</p>
<p>The only problem now is that I have this strange new craving to acquire more
mechanical keyboards and keyboard paraphernalia&hellip;</p>
<h3 id="keyboard-addendum">Keyboard addendum</h3>
<p>The keyboard officially supports &ldquo;full key non-conflict&rdquo;, which sounds like
some sort of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rollover%5F(key)#Keyboard%5Fusage">key roll-over</a>.</p>
<p>As a non-gamer, this will probably never affect me, although I have
experimented with it by mashing down on as many keys simultaneously as
possible, and then seeing them all still appear on the screen.</p>
<p>I do fantasise that sometimes I type that fast, and that then this rollover
will really help!</p>
<p>(I just did a quick experiment: 8 fingers mashing down at the same time on the
dvorak home row gave me &ldquo;ansoeuht&rdquo;. Keys in order from left to right are
&ldquo;aoeuhtns&rdquo;. Neat.)</p>
<p>Not unimportantly, my GOUs are fascinated by the pretty water droplet mode of
the RGB backlighting, which I can fortunately disable when working.</p>
<p>To my surprise, the backlighting in one of its static not-too-bright modes is
really quite useful when the sun starts setting at the end of a work day.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-update">Lazar Focus update</h2>
<p>Since <a href="/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/#on-slipping-and-shipping-a-side-project">I last mentioned</a> my shipping little side-project <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a>, the windows
distraction blocker that helps you focus like a boss (I&rsquo;m still working on the
marketing over here, sorry), another big feature update shipped, namely fully
automatic time-tracking.</p>
<p>The number of sales is currently somewhat more than one, but still fewer than
ten.</p>
<p>Although I use LF almost every day, it&rsquo;s brilliant when someone else who
generally does not even know me, decides to <strong>buy</strong> a copy for themselves.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re into relaxing (some might say sleep-inducing) screencasts, I have two
new ones on offer.</p>
<p>The first is 4 minutes, and shows how to get started with Lazar Focus and its
automatic activity logging:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G8z7ZACPtrc" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>The second got a bit out of hand.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s 12 minutes of me, in my evening voice, taking you through the minute
details of a work day as tracked by Lazar Focus:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ccMp1yYBOd0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>If you&rsquo;re on twitter, and you&rsquo;d like to keep an eye on Lazar Focus, you could
consider following <a href="https://twitter.com/LazarFocused">@LazarFocused</a>! (tweet frequency is currently about once to
twice per week)</p>
<h2 id="camper-philosohpy">Camper philosohpy</h2>
<p>Picture this:</p>
<p>Driving along <a href="/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/#the-beach">Clarence drive</a> three weeks ago, with the usual awe-inspiring
views over the bay, we saw a couple sitting beside the road next to their
camper, bathed in the golden, nay <em>divine</em>, late-afternoon sun.</p>
<p>They were clearly having a ridiculously good time.</p>
<p>On the back of their camper, the following important message stood lettered:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We are extremely pleased to be here.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Folks, I really wish each and every one of you moments like that, moments so
good that you can be extremely pleased to be exactly where you are.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #197: How to ship side-projects</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 22:28:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/</guid><description>Hello friends!
Weekly Head Voices #197 looks back at the week from Monday June 1 to Sunday June 7.
Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect.
Work-work is quite high intensity at the moment.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello friends!</p>
<p>Weekly Head Voices #197 looks back at the week from Monday June 1 to Sunday June 7.</p>










<figure><a href="morgenster.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu_b2f67d936de59fab.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu_277217977545b8e5.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu_5993673659342359.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu_b3e40117b180dcd3.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu_277217977545b8e5.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Work-work is quite high intensity at the moment.</p>
<p>I really would not mind a bit of respite any time soon now.</p>
<p>In the meantime, let me look back, and by the crazy laws of metaphysics
also inwards, at the previous week:</p>
<h2 id="on-slipping-and-shipping-a-side-project">On slipping and shipping a side-project</h2>
<p>I have <a href="/2018/05/13/weekly-head-voices-142-theory-of-mind/#the-side-project-dilemma">written</a> <a href="/2018/09/03/weekly-head-voices-152-a-small-but-highly-trained-team-of-11-year-olds/#au-revoir">before</a> about nerds and their side-projects.</p>
<p>You might recall that I said that they mostly don&rsquo;t ever see the light of day,
although they still have indirect benefits.</p>
<p>In any case, the two I linked to above both failed, so at least that&rsquo;s nice for
consistency.</p>
<p>However, on Friday I went and bucked the trend ever so slightly by
soft-launching the Lazar Focus app and website distraction blocker for Windows.</p>
<p>I <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">mentioned LF last week</a>, but it now has a website, called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">lazarfocused.com</a>,
and it has a <a href="https://gumroad.com/l/yExQgr">product page on gumroad</a>.</p>
<p>It has a <em>substantially</em> smaller number of bugs thanks to brilliant beta
testing by multi-modal medical visualization expert and productivity app
<em>connoisseuse</em> <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/">Noeska</a>.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re on Windows, this is exactly the little app you need to block
distractions, only when you say so of course, so that you can focus on all of
The Important Stuff™ you undoubtedly would rather get done, so that you
can get back to goofing off.</p>
<p>AMIRITE?!</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re one of those people who don&rsquo;t need any help to help focusing and to
stay in the zone, but you work with people who might, the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/06/06/the-philosophy-behind-lazar-focus/">philosophy behind
Lazar Focus</a> blog post is a good introduction to share with them. (Also, could I
interview you? :)</p>
<h2 id="dry-january-finally-ends--or-maybe-not--with-rochefort">Dry January finally ends (or maybe not) with Rochefort</h2>
<p>This year, I <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">started Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) on January 6</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m happy to report that this was interrupted only once for a superb glass of
my favourite Chardonnay (that&rsquo;s the Haskell Anvil, see <a href="/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/#what-i-did-in-week-41">WHV #181</a> for the first
encounter) with besties, right at the source.</p>
<p>Other than that, I remained in EAZ until Saturday, June 6, when the St
Bernhardus Abt 12 and the Trappistes Rochefort #8 and #10 that a friend had
brought for me all the way from The Netherlands and that had been waiting
patiently for me in the cupboard, had just been sitting there waiting for long
enough.</p>
<p>(By the way, the St Bernhardus Abt 12 is a taste clone of the Westvleteren, the
pretty expensive king of the Trappist beers, as a drunk gentleman once
explained to me in the Doerak in Delft late one evening. He was right, as my
companion and I subsequently confirmed when we acquired both beers for a
comparative tasting on the spot.)</p>
<p>The time, but far more pertinently the opportunity, had come to end (or was it
merely to interrupt&hellip;) EAZ 2020.</p>
<p>Friends, that Rochefort is simply packed with a multitude of sweet, warm
memories of days and evenings in my other home, with my other family.</p>










<figure><a href="rochefort_8_action_shot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu_1d90a1400dfe275c.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu_91516c73332cbfa7.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu_8d1fb821fe1b31cd.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu_b4717790e3145ab7.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu_91516c73332cbfa7.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Just in case you needed reminding, the Rochefort 8 looks like this. Memories of a lifetime not pictured."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Just in case you needed reminding, the Rochefort 8 looks like this. Memories of a lifetime not pictured.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>(Going even further back, I have <a href="/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/">mentioned before</a> that this blog contains <a href="/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/">a
written record of my very first encounter with Rochefort</a>, all the way back in
2003, right in the town of La Roche-en-Ardenna, about 30 minutes away from
Rochefort itself. Reading that post now, it really was a sort of WHV avant la
lettre!)</p>
<h2 id="the-last-bit">The last bit</h2>
<p>Ok folks, it is now 22:17 on Thursday evening, and I&rsquo;m at that super difficult
&ldquo;HOW IN THOR&rsquo;S NAME DO I CONCLUDE THIS THING?!&quot;-stage, a problem which I seem
to be solving with the &ldquo;I KNOW LET&rsquo;S BREAK THE FOURTH WALL / SIMPLY TALK
ABOUT HOW WE DON&rsquo;T KNOW HOW TO END THIS THING&rdquo;-manoeuvre.</p>
<p>On the bright side, I think we did <em>just</em> make the deadline with this edition
of the WHV, narrowly avoiding postponement and a larger-than-normal next post.</p>
<p>Have a brilliant rest of the week and weekend. I look forward to seeing you
again, here and anywhere!</p>
<p>P.S. I still don&rsquo;t know how to ship side-projects.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #196: Get focused</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 22:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/</guid><description> Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&amp;rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&amp;rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&amp;rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="sylvia_draws_family_20200531.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_a45ab388b85c4527.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_9e67ca7a19e8a10b.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_9bdc60a70b4a330a.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_e95086249cbd6c5.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/sylvia_draws_family_20200531_hu_9e67ca7a19e8a10b.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Our house clan, as drawn by GOU #2. I&rsquo;ve blurred out the names of everyone else, but those of you who know us should be able to figure out who&rsquo;s who. Readers might also notice that I&rsquo;m slightly outnumbered here.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there folks, please make yourself at home!</p>
<p>This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday May 18 to Sunday May 31 of the
extremely strange year of 2020.</p>
<p>That effort of looking back has resulted in the following three items.</p>
<h2 id="when-building-automatic-analysis-pipelines-get-your-batch-accuracy-testing-up-as-soon-as-you-can">When building automatic analysis pipelines, get your batch accuracy testing up as soon as you can</h2>
<p>A substantial part of my work hours these past two weeks went into working on a
automatic medical image analysis pipeline, with machine learning
inside™. (I mean &ldquo;AI&rdquo;, of course. And drones.)</p>
<p>I really do love this stuff, but sometimes it ends up coming down to putting
your head down and keeping it down, in order to grind out every percent or two
in improved accuracy.</p>
<p>The tip I wanted to offer here is the following: Even when you think your
pipeline is way too far from &ldquo;done&rdquo;™, get your batch accuracy testing up
and running.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a double whammy:</p>
<ol>
<li>You and your team get early and regular feedback on how your performance is
going.</li>
<li>You are forced to have the whole concept working from end-to-end. It can be
surprising how many little issues you still need to solve, and running into
them sooner rather than later is only good.</li>
</ol>
<p>By the way, the practical machine learning icon <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew%5FNg">Professor Andrew Ng&rsquo;s</a> free book
<a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai/machine-learning-yearning/">Machine Learning Yearning</a> is filled to the brim with practical tips for
implementing ML in practice.</p>
<h2 id="lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">Lazar Focus: The super tiny Windows app and website distraction blocker that you&rsquo;ve always wanted</h2>
<p>Back at the <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">start of 2018 I wrote the following about the macOS app and website
distraction blocker called Focus</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>After years of resisting these types of software tools due to my belief that I
should simply apply more grit and will power to squeeze out more focus hours,
I finally broke down and purchased the macOS app called Focus. You click its
pretty icon, and then your computer goes into focus mode: The Mail application
and a bunch of other non-focus-related apps all get killed, and a bunch of
websites (reddit, youtube, work chat, etc) are blocked for a user-configurable
block of time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Even if you skipped that extract, please read the following one about the
<em>idea</em> behind such a focus app:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It usually takes a single moment of weakness for a distraction to terminate a
valuable block of focus. It takes a single moment of strength for this tool to
start a valuable block of focus.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Anyways, I was really missing this functionality on Windows, and so I busted
out my trusty <a href="https://www.lazarus-ide.org/">Lazarus IDE</a> (who <em>didn&rsquo;t</em> make apps back in the day with the old
win32 Delphi?!) and figured out the various required Windows APIs to create
this brand new super tiny but super effective app and website blocker:</p>










<figure><a href="lazar_focused_screenshot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hu_3ea9d753f10fd2a4.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hu_71d14bfb18afecb6.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hu_cc5f57817664d11a.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/lazar_focused_screenshot_hu_71d14bfb18afecb6.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Screenshot of Lazar Focus 1.0.0.beta1, main window on the left, settings dialog on the right.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As shown in the screenshot, it&rsquo;s sitting at 5 MB of memory use. In the age of
Electron apps, that&rsquo;s really small.</p>
<p>When you activate focus mode, it&rsquo;ll prevent your browser (Chrome, Brave,
Firefox or Edge) from viewing any distracting website (you get to configure the
list) by redirecting to a local web page with an inspiring quote, e.g.:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Concentration can be cultivated. One can learn to exercise willpower,
discipline one&rsquo;s body and train one&rsquo;s mind. &ndash; Anil Ambani</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It will also terminate any distracting apps, and helpfully prevent you from
starting them up during your focus session.</p>
<p>The convenient progress bar shows how far you are on your way to a 25 minute
pomodoro, but that is purely for motivation, and not enforced.</p>
<p>The total focus blocks and hours at the top should also help to keep us
motivated and&hellip; <strong>LAZAR FOCUSED!</strong></p>
<p>So, because there are probably (hopefully?) at least two other people who&rsquo;ll
find this as useful as I do, and because shipping and selling software that you
made yourself is awesome especially when it&rsquo;s a hobby project, I have decided
to try and sell Lazar Focus using something like <a href="https://gumroad.com/">gumroad</a>.</p>
<p>Hopefully soon with a hobby hour or three I can finish the installer and the
website, and then make the beta available at a reduced rate.</p>
<p>Because I prefer it for apps like this when I am the buyer, I have decided to
make it available as a one-time purchase, no eval but money-back, with
time-limited upgrades (probably a year?), but with your last licensed version
obviously remaining fully functional until the end of The Windows API.</p>
<h2 id="art-fun-with-portrait-ai">Art fun with Portrait AI</h2>
<p>Ever since I spent a bit of time better curating my twitter subscriptions,
getting rid of the vitriol and adding much more STEM (shout out to <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Eric Topol</a>
&ndash; you could install twitter <em>just</em> for him and you would be great), they often
bring me shiny treasures.</p>
<p>Recently, it was <a href="https://portraitai.com/">portraitai.com</a> which brought a great deal of mirth to my home
as we made authentic looking portraits of each other. (We&rsquo;re just a bunch of
silly primates with amazing gadgets.)</p>
<p>It didn&rsquo;t seem to work all that well on me however, until I started pulling
funny faces:</p>










<figure><a href="charl_portraitai.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_60b307dd03ff58c.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_4ac89d1f2179bf4f.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_298bd39ecfd5cd80.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_b291b94c239595d1.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/charl_portraitai_hu_4ac89d1f2179bf4f.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>With that, dear friends, I bid you kindness, happiness and health.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>