<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Bullet Lists on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/bullet-lists/</link><description>Recent content in Bullet Lists on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 20:48:30 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/bullet-lists/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #253: Weekend Warrior</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 16:38:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/</guid><description>Welcome back everyone!
It&amp;rsquo;s clear to me that I have to get back in the WHV saddle, but preaching sure is easier than practising, and so I thought it might be a good idea to try and bullet-list myself back into it.
(When I say &amp;ldquo;bullet-list&amp;rdquo; I mean &amp;ldquo;helpfully named hierarchical sections&amp;rdquo;, because Emacs tends to frown quite disapprovingly at mere bullet lists. Here I am after the intention of the bullet-list, namely to just get on with it.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s clear to me that I have to get back in the WHV saddle, but preaching sure
is easier than practising, and so I thought it might be a good idea to try and
<a href="/tags/bullet-lists/">bullet-list</a> myself back into it.</p>
<p>(When I say &ldquo;bullet-list&rdquo; I mean &ldquo;helpfully named hierarchical sections&rdquo;,
because <a href="/tags/emacs/">Emacs</a> tends to frown quite disapprovingly at mere bullet lists. Here I
am after the <em>intention</em> of the bullet-list, namely to <em>just get on with it</em>.)</p>










<figure><a href="bilthoven_manege.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_2e0173759a9b3934.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_1740715dbd8e6fe0.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_3893d5e642d52f69.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_31349c7dd6e8518e.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/bilthoven_manege_hu_1740715dbd8e6fe0.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Manege from a late summer stroll in NL. Smells, sounds, weather took me back so hard."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Manege from a late summer stroll in NL. Smells, sounds, weather took me back so hard.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It is important to mention that this post attempts to cover time up to
Wednesday, August 23, 2023.</p>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>My running habit has been steadily returning to its pre-op state, both in terms of
fitness but, more importantly, in terms of joy.</p>
<p>Also, my sixth pair of Altra Escalantes (version 3.0) recently arrived. I
wanted black ones, as I usually recycle old Altras after their recommended
700km or so into super comfortable office shoes, but my supplier was out of
stock and so I ended up with these surprisingly attractive blue and red ones:</p>










<figure><a href="altra_escalante_v3_no6.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/altra_escalante_v3_no6_hu_c8d1293b0b36ab.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/altra_escalante_v3_no6_hu_a5aea862418ea2ec.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/altra_escalante_v3_no6_hu_230eb4b8efe70307.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/altra_escalante_v3_no6_hu_a5aea862418ea2ec.jpg"
            

         width="50%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>In more good news, it turns out that it&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.webmd.com/fitness-exercise/news/20230719/your-heart-benefits-even-if-you-exercise-as-a-weekend-warrior">entirely OK if you spend all of your
minimum of 2.5 weekly hours of exercise during the weekend</a>.</p>
<p>Personally, I usually manage to fit in two shorter runs during the week, and a
longer run during the weekend, for a desired total of 25km per week, but I have
always wondered if it was in fact required to exercise on every day of the week
for maximal health benefit.</p>
<p>P.S. My main motivation is the unqualified joy of the run and not so much the
health benefits, although the benefits sure are nice!</p>
<p>P.P.S. <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#running">25km per week was my resolution for 2023</a>, but that plan was quite rudely
torpedoed by my <a href="/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/">prostate cancer adventure a few months ago</a>, so now I just try
to make it week by week.</p>
<h2 id="genai">GenAI</h2>
<p>For the past months, I&rsquo;ve been going deeper and deeper into generative AI, and
more specifically large language models (LLMs), down to the nuts and bolts and
let&rsquo;s-get-Llama-2-70-billion-quantized-and-running-on-my-PC levels.</p>
<p>Here are a few things that I really liked learning about:</p>
<ul>
<li>Although it has indeed been a longer journey, the current GenAI explosion /
hype seems to have been ignited in the third quarter of 2022, with the open
source release of Stable Diffusion in August, and the birth of ChatGPT in
November.</li>
<li>For the largest part, the most powerful LLMs have been trained, on hundreds
of billions to trillions of words, how to predict the next / missing word of
an incomplete document. After enough of this, they appear to gain some sort
of reasoning capability, including being able to answer theory of mind
questions.
<ul>
<li>There are striking similarities to how humans interpret speech.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Almost all of the currently famous models (Stable Diffusion, Whisper, all
current LLMs) are based on a specific type of neural network called a
Transformer, introduced in the paper <em>Attention Is All You Need</em>, published by
Ashish Vaswani and fellow Google researchers in 2017.</li>
</ul>
<p>For many more details about these, and other hopefully interesting
observations, please come to one of my GenAI talks!</p>
<p>GenAI developments are continuing at a truly impressive pace, and now I hope
that we (personally) can also start showing some practical and useful
applications!</p>
<p>P.S. Read the brilliant Lyn Alden&rsquo;s latest newsletter <a href="https://www.lynalden.com/august-2023-newsletter/">Six AI Themes to Consider</a>
in which she discusses how AIs (actually LLMs) are already starting to use
bitcoin (lightning) to pay for services (soon other AIs and also humans) in
order to complete their tasks.</p>
<h2 id="lowlands-2023">Lowlands 2023</h2>
<p>One could say that the WHV series owes its life to a certain 3-day festival in
the Netherlands as <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">it was born in the sweet afterglow of the 2009 edition</a>.</p>
<p>However, due to the strict WHALLSALL privacy policy, you will find only
<a href="/tags/lowlands/">pleasant echoes of the experience</a> in a number of posts on this blog.</p>
<p>This time it felt even more special, because it&rsquo;s the first time that I was
able to go since <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/">all the way back in 2019</a>.</p>
<p>I was pleasantly shocked by the warm <em>familiarity</em> of my other home, starting all
the way from the airport in Cape Town, joining hundreds of Dutchies returning
home after their vacations in SA, to arriving in NL and letting that lovely
language permeate my neural network, all through the festival chaos and
sometimes extremely close proximity to tens of thousands of locals, to walking
and cycling under the late summer sun, to spending the highest possible quality
time with my friends there.</p>
<p>Again I am left overflowing with gratitude.</p>
<p>Thank you other home, and eternal thank you friends!</p>
<h2 id="i-am-a-function">I am a function</h2>
<p>Back in <a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">WHV #70 from 2014</a>, based on some reading about the turnover of matter
in humans, I came to the following conclusion:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Now I see us all as nothing more than the continuously changing patterns that
form briefly in the grains of sand of the universe. Winds blow grains of sand
around, now taking part in one pattern and then in another. At some point, your
body has contained parts of your best friend, and of your worst enemy. The
patterns change continually; sometimes they fade away, and sometimes new
patterns emerge.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the intervening years, reader KvG first introduced me to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Watts">Alan Watts</a>, noting
that they saw similar themes in our writing.</p>
<p>I am wording it carefully here, as I obviously can&rsquo;t really compare my backyard
philosophical attempts to the work of Alan Watts, which I have now come to know
better.</p>
<p>That story was required to bring us to this, the concluding quote of this post:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You are a function of what the whole universe is doing in the same way that a
wave is a function of what the whole ocean is doing. &ndash; Alan Watts</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I really love that.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #68: Harsh Autumn Weekends.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/04/21/weekly-head-voices-68-harsh-autumn-weekends/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2014 20:32:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/04/21/weekly-head-voices-68-harsh-autumn-weekends/</guid><description>Noeska’s new weekly status update blog posts inspired me to get mine back on the road again. To be more precise, the observation that I really enjoyed being updated in this fashion with a far-away friend’s exploits hints at the possibility that, somewhere out there, there might be someone who finds it similarly enjoyable to read mine! (Long ago I learnt the trick from Swimgeek, who is still going strong with his weekly updates.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><a href="http://noeskasmit.com/weekly-status-update-1/" title="Noeska's weekly status updates">Noeska’s new weekly status update blog posts</a> inspired me to get mine back on the road again. To be more precise, the observation that I really enjoyed being updated in this fashion with a far-away friend’s exploits hints at the possibility that, somewhere out there, there might be someone who finds it similarly enjoyable to read mine! (Long ago I learnt the trick from <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/" title="Swimgeek's blog">Swimgeek</a>, who is still going strong with his weekly updates.)</p>
<p>You know the rules: We write short summaries of our week’s activities, often in the form of bullet lists. I’m going to break both rules this time by rambling on about the past three weeks, and by showing you a bunch of photos I took on the weekends.</p>
<p>I’d like to show you how the autumn weekends here in SA can be quite harsh, but first I need to geek out for a bit (do not fear non-nerds, there are pictures after this brief interlude!):</p>
<ul>
<li>I’m back with Emacs. &lt;3 &lt;3 &lt;3 On my continuous search for the ultimate information organizing system I have now arrived editing the Markdown files contained in a git-backed <a href="https://github.com/gollum/gollum" title="Gollum github page">Gollum wiki</a> with my Emacs 24.3. I even wrote a (nerdy) <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2014/04/08/syntax-highlighting-markdown-fenced-code-blocks-in-emacs/" title="vxlabs blog post on emacs fenced code block highlighting">blog post explaining how you to can configure your Emacs to do language-specific fenced code-block syntax highlighting</a>. Somehow Emacs and I are just getting along much better than we did before my Vim period (dark dark days). I think it’s because I’ve decided to embrace the Lisp, which brings me to:</li>
<li>In my copious amounts of free time, I was searching for a functional language to learn. The <a href="http://www.erlang.org/doc/getting_started/users_guide.html" title="Erlang tutorial">Erlang tutorial</a> was enjoyable, but I was not too crazy about what I read about the details of deploying Erlang systems. I bought <a href="http://learnyouahaskell.com/" title="Learn you a Haskell, man!">Learn you a Haskell for Great Good</a> and started reading it, but somehow Haskell didn’t tickle me enough. Then, probably infected by having to look at Emacs Lisp again, I picked up the <a href="http://www.clojurebook.com/" title="Clojure Programming">Clojure Programming book</a>. Now that pushed all of the right buttons! I haven’t this much fun with a new language since I picked up Python, and my mind has been expanded at a few points as well (what do you mean the code that I write <strong>IS</strong> the AST?! (Picture my Neo face saying: “Whoa.”)). <a href="http://clojure.org/" title="clojure website">Clojure</a> is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisp_(programming_language)">Lisp</a> dialect that does a pretty good job of walking the line between beauty and pragmatism. Built on the JVM (and having full interop with the rest of Java) it also has STM (software transactional memory), agents, and async channels all built-in. As if that wasn’t enough, I get to use Emacs with the CIDER package to play with it. (<code>M-x cider-jack-in</code> starts up the Clojure REPL and then… JACKS ME IN.)</li>
</ul>
<p>Err, I might have exhausted my nerd quota for the week. Let’s do the rest of the Weekly Head Voices in pictures!</p>
<p>Three weekends ago I went to visit the Spice Route farm in the Paarl with family and friends. Besides the coffee roastery, the chocolatier, the winery and the two restaurants, this farm also houses the Cape Brewing Company, a magical place that produces delicious craft beers, which you can taste, and take home with you. The view is not too shabby either:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/spice_route_panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/spice_route_panorama-1024x318.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from the Spice Route farm is Not Too Shabby(tm)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from the Spice Route farm is Not Too Shabby(tm)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>On the topic of delicious craft beers, THIS, my dear readers, is The Darling Bone Crusher, another super tasty white beer constructed with much love in the town called Darling:









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/darling_bone_crusher.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/darling_bone_crusher-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The Darling Bone Crusher white craft beer"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The Darling Bone Crusher white craft beer</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>… and this is the sun setting on some Milk and Honey, crafted in Knysna (this one is quite good, but their other ale called the Old Wobbly is even nicer):










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/sunset_and_milk_and_honey.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/sunset_and_milk_and_honey-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Craft beer from the land of milk and honey"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Craft beer from the land of milk and honey</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Lest you think all we do is drink craft beers around here, here’s a photo of the vicious river delta I had to cross during my afternoon fitness activity (this was before we started drinking craft beers again):










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/jogging_delta.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/jogging_delta-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Vicious river delta"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Vicious river delta</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>… and here’s a pretty <del>butterfly</del> moth (thanks <a href="http://mentat.za.net/">Stéfan</a>) I just had to take a photo of:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/pretty_butterfly.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/pretty_butterfly-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Pretty butterfly in Betty’s Bay"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pretty butterfly in Betty’s Bay</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>On the way back home after another harsh weekend, we were stuck in some sort of traffic jam. After a few minutes inching ahead, we ran into the culprits causing our delay:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/baboons_on_cars.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/baboons_on_cars-1024x504.jpg"
        
            alt="Baboons on cars!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Baboons on cars!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>(Yes, those are baboons sitting on people’s cars. “Oh, were you planning to drive that sir? You’re going to have to wait until the baboon decides it’s time to go home.”)</p>
<p>The road we were on (the R44 between Gordon’s Bay and Betty’s Bay) is one of the prettiest I know. On another of these autumn weekends, it looked like this:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/r44_to_bettys.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/r44_to_bettys-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="R44 between Gordon’s Bay and Betty’s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>R44 between Gordon’s Bay and Betty’s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The End.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>