<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Cancer on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/cancer/</link><description>Recent content in Cancer on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 12:58:51 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/cancer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 6 of 2024: Head Like a Hole</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</guid><description>Why do I lifelog? One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&amp;rsquo;s not form their own mind.
Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="why-do-i-lifelog">Why do  I lifelog?</h2>
<p>One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&rsquo;s not form their own mind.</p>
<p>Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</p>
<h3 id="journalling-vs-lifelogging">Journalling vs lifelogging</h3>
<p>In my view, <em>journalling</em> is a more developed form of <em>lifelogging</em>. While the latter is just the direct jotting down of happenings and noteworthy items, the former, at least to me, entails more thinking and more processing, i.e. there is more retro- and introspection going on. I would prefer to be <em>journalling</em>, because that has even more benefits, but I&rsquo;ll take <em>lifelogging</em> when I can&rsquo;t make the prerequisite time to think, and really craft my words.</p>
<p>On to the lifelog:</p>
<h2 id="monday-2024-02-05">Monday 2024-02-05</h2>
<ul>
<li>Friend LM told me about wikitree.org, which is a collaborative online family tree thingy. I tried to import the myheritage.com exported GEDCOM, but wikitree.org wants me to reject or accept each and everyone of the hundreds of people in my database. This is understandable, but it&rsquo;s also a  blocker, exacerbated by the fact that wikitree&rsquo;s matching algorithm is quite bad.</li>
<li>Casey Neistat&rsquo;s Apple Vision Pro review is insightful. See the bit from 7:20 onwards: <a href="https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440">https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440</a> &ndash; &ldquo;&hellip; This is it. This is the future of computing&hellip;&rdquo;
<ul>
<li>also see my tweet embedded below</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>NVIDIA&rsquo;s GenAI competition <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/">https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/</a>
<ul>
<li>Use TensorRT or TensorRT-LLM on Windows to build something cool, submit by Feb 23, win RTX 4090 and GTC conf attendance. EZ PZ!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Remember that life is <em>supposed</em> to be just a long sequence of problems that you need to solve.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is such a fun &quot;review&quot; of the Apple Vision Pro by Casey Neistat, but his discussion at 7:20 on the significance of the product is so spot on.<br><br>I had similar ideas about ubiquitous face-computing back in 2009: <a href="https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc">https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc</a> <a href="https://t.co/au9RBh7as0">https://t.co/au9RBh7as0</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1754421449719193753?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 5, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>










<figure><a href="avp-angry-gf.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b5f62d2dc15edfd3.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b31467e1ec255b77.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_c35fee7f6f8120f9.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-06">Tuesday 2024-01-06</h2>
<ul>
<li>Using inkscape to draw SVG glyphs which can be converted with <a href="https://react-svgr.com/">svgr</a> into React components, for my visualization project. This works so well!</li>
<li>Definitely a bit stressed about tomorrow&rsquo;s surgery. Also little throat niggle, and as if that was not enough, stomach issues due to droëwors I ate in the afternoon to preload a bit for tomorrow&rsquo;s required fasting.
<ul>
<li>Narrator: This would be followed by one of <em>the</em> worst nights in a long time, including fever chills, nausea, and so on.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>My brain keeps on jumping on ideas for 3D / VR / AR / AI friendly / native ideas for managing personal knowledge / notes
<ul>
<li>on the one hand, it feels like the atomic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten">Zettelkasten</a> approach could work well here</li>
<li>on the other, we have chunking techniques to break up documents, so that we can extract the nuggets we want in order to embed them
<ul>
<li>this chunking can be dynamic and adaptive, perhaps even going down to sentences and individual diagrams, or dynamically constructed chunks consisting of sub-chunks merged from different sources</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>in the end, will it help  or even just be interesting to be able to walk / move through / manipulate different projections of your (or someone else&rsquo;s) thoughts, possibly even connected in different ways?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-07">Wednesday 2024-01-07</h2>
<ul>
<li>Microsoft Lens makes me login every single time, and is quite temperamental
<ul>
<li>alternatives are OneDrive app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo; or Files app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At Summerhill day clinic for the excision of the morpheaform basal cell carcinoma (BCC) on my forehead
<ul>
<li>Fortunately, the doctor decided the excision on my back (with clean borders pronounced by pathology lab) does not need to be re-excised.</li>
<li>Excision of 2cm x 1.5cm patch from my forehead via <a href="https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/conditions-and-diseases/mohs-surgery">Mohs surgery</a> is successful after first attempt, happiness!</li>
<li>Reconstructive surgeon however now has a challenge: How to close up hole with no loose skin in sight? (I am a tightly wrapped person)
<ul>
<li>problem is solved with step-wise incision from the top middle of my forehead all the way down to my right temple, about 20cm in total.</li>
<li>I look like I could be the son of Frankenstein and Harry Potter</li>
<li>The care at Summerhill is beyond excellent. Now I just have to follow instructions, drink many pills, and my new friend-for-life Scar should heal up nicely.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-08">Thursday 2024-01-08</h2>
<ul>
<li>Working from home because reasons</li>
<li>I have to work hard to focus, the medication seems to affect my concentration. I will grit my teeth harder.</li>
<li>In break time, tried out <a href="https://www.modular.com/blog/mojo-sdk-v0-7-now-available-for-download">Mojo v0.7.0 (released 2024-01-25)</a> through its REPL and also just a simple <code>hello.mojo</code>, which compiled into a nice 300kB binary on this MacBook! Cautiously excited for the future of this. (also&hellip;. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Lattner">Chris Lattner</a>! 😍)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-09">Friday 2024-01-09</h2>
<ul>
<li>In the morning, got mu4e setup and working on the new MacBook, although I thought I was not going to need this mail client
<ul>
<li>What is your favourite mail client?</li>
<li>I use the Fastmail web client, mu4e for Emacs and macOS Mail, but none of them is perfect. mu4e comes close. ;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Really struggled during the day with drowsiness, although I&rsquo;m sleeping extra well every night.</li>
<li>By the end, at least was able to make demo video of my in-progress visualization project.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-10">Saturday 2024-01-10</h2>
<ul>
<li>head still feeling quite woozy</li>
<li>happy to have kids at home, and have a pretty relaxed morning</li>
<li>I would really like to write / create something today. What?</li>
<li>family tree updates
<ul>
<li>tried out ancestris, which is unusably slow on my m1pro. just getting a context menu on a person in the tree, or scrolling around, has too much lag. Tried on my Windows desktop where it&rsquo;s better but still really slow.</li>
<li>Went back to wikitree (recommended by LM) where I updated some more records (extremely laboriously).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.familysearch.org/en/">https://www.familysearch.org/en/</a> has been really useful for scans of church registers and so on, confirming more of my earlier findings.
<ul>
<li>See for example <a href="https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910">https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910</a> which just came in as I was typing this. That&rsquo;s the death notice of my paternal great grandmother in 1919, very shortly after the birth of my grandfather.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I think I might have spent too much time on this today. There&rsquo;s a bit of a dopamine rush every time you solve a mini riddle. Here also I would like to have something shareable and reusable for other members of my family. For that, wikitree, although painful, seems like a good bet.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>mind wandered at 13:30ish, of course it ended up in infinite canvases and pkm
<ul>
<li>wanted to keep on letting it wander, but also wanted to use laptop to read about freeform
<ul>
<li>Apple Freeform looks like the pretty-ok-like-notes canvas solution: <a href="https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue">https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Instead of going to bed early, experimented with round-tripping markdown to docx and back with pandoc. See tomorrow for results.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-11">Sunday 2024-01-11</h2>
<ul>
<li>Briefly tried out the new(ish) built-in <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-za/guide/iphone/iph0e5ca7dd3/ios">iOS Journal app</a>
<ul>
<li>Super nice that it taps into your activities (photos, music, workouts, etc.) and makes recommendations for packets of media you could add to a journal, all of this entirely on-device.</li>
<li>Private, encourages folks to lock the app and so on.</li>
<li>No export capability, so your journals remain utterly locked in for now.</li>
<li>Makes it easy to configure reminders that will prompt you to write  a journal at specific moments during the week.</li>
<li>Minimalistic and well-executed app, will probably get quite a few iPhone users to start journalling, but not for me. I already have too many Apple apps in my personal system that I need to use (e.g. Apple Notes) but that don&rsquo;t interoperate particularly well with other systems.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent some more time on familysearch.org creating and attaching person records (from my family) to scans of old archive documents. Also uploaded a PDF of hand-written notes made by one of my family members from the headstones on a farm on which a number of my ancestors were buried.
<ul>
<li>Two-world problem. Bringing the physical into the digital.</li>
<li><strong>familysearch really does work better than wikitree&hellip;</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>About that Two World Problem. Had some thoughts about it in the context of my personal knowledge management, but it was slightly too much for the bullets I had allocated to it, and so it become a short post titled <a href="/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/">On the two world problem and personal knowledge management</a>.
<ul>
<li>In an ideal world, I am able to publish mini posts like that on a weekly basis.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Oh wait, I also made a short post on vxlabs with the results of last night&rsquo;s pandoc experiments, titled <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/02/11/pandoc-roundtrip-from-markdown-to-docx-and-back/">Pandoc roundtrip from markdown to docx and back</a>
<ul>
<li>In this case, I went direct to Hugo markdown instead of starting in Emacs Orgmode first, in order to further reduce activation energy. This makes sense for posts I want to get published where I don&rsquo;t necessarily need the benefit of having the content integrated with my main notes database.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 2 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/15/daily-head-voices-2024-01-08_14/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 22:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/15/daily-head-voices-2024-01-08_14/</guid><description>Inspired by the impressive power (and philosophy) of One Punch Man&amp;rsquo;s Consecutive Normal Punches, I present: A Series of Consecutive Normal Daily Head Voices!
Monday 2024-01-08 First day back at work 😱 &amp;hellip; but the most lovely lunch run (not literally) and chat with colleague E. Single cable life at work is there, but it&amp;rsquo;s complicated: Thunderbolt3 cable from macbook to Thinkpad dock, dock thunderbolt3 to displayport-mini (adapter), displayport-mini to displayport to monitor. Had blood drawn for my quarterly PSA test. (prostate-specific antigen; regular test to check that prostate cancer stays gone) Double Commander (currently at 1.1.8) on macOS is even better than I remember it, and is only a brew install --cask double-commander away. Tuesday 2024-01-09 marimo looks really good! From the github: a reactive notebook for Python. It allows you to rapidly experiment with data and models, code with confidence in your notebook&amp;rsquo;s correctness, and productionize notebooks as pipelines or interactive web apps. I still have to play with it, but it sounds like an Observable for Python. Wednesday 2024-01-10 Shorter weekday run because hip and because sun. Hip only started complaining by the end, a little later than my last short run. 🎉 Tried to find reclining high-back office chairs with footrest in South Africa, starting from: https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/ Spectacular failure! Google Bard, Bing Chat, Perplexity come up with plausible looking links that go to different sites, but nowhere any chairs to be found perplexity is probably the least bad because it more often admits to just not finding any links in SA See e.g. https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c and https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5 Because of work, started to spend some quality time with d3.js again. I hope to be doing some nice interactive visualization soon! Thursday 2024-01-11 PSA is 0.006! 🥳 if you&amp;rsquo;ve ever worked with d3.js, you will have used bl.ocks.org quite often. To my surprise, none of these links work anymore, and instead redirect you to the source gist, where they used to show you the live visualization. I could not find much official news about this sunsetting, but was consoled by the discovery of the open source bl.ocks.org clone at https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/ via https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513 Tune of the evening: RÜFÜS DU SOL - On My Knees (Adriatique Remix) Friday 2024-01-12 Short week-day run, no hip issues! Very nice focused day at home: First half wrapping up a code review. Second half diving back into d3.js. So much old memories I have to unearth. In between hacked in an idle mode for org-roam-similarity, in the process discovered that on this M1 Pro, CPU is much faster (2x) and uses much less RAM than the hardware accelerated PyTorch MPS version Lovely weekend-starter braai with family. Ran into the final sections (and private comments the source org file) of WHV #208 &amp;ndash; besides the nostalgic music bits, really enjoyed reading some of the older journals. Publish or not, strong motivation to keep on writing journals. (now-you is often a very different person than then-you. interesting to keep in touch!) Saturday 2024-01-13 one of the highlights of the day was phone-call by and substantial conversation with bestie PK rest of day quite laid-back with the whole family, which was great thinking a lot about stefanv&amp;rsquo;s week planner instead of day planner, and the implications of this seemingly reduced planning effort (my daily planning is mostly only theoretical) greater family braai (GFB) Sunday 2024-01-14 Overslept a bit, woke up at 9 AM. This has not happened in ages. Slightly longer weekend run at 10 with new running hat and SPF50 on me face and neck. Hip issue did not manifest, am touching wood! Because I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about more visual ways to plan my week, worked on org-roam-canvas, making it a whole lot faster.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Inspired by the impressive power (and philosophy) of One Punch Man&rsquo;s <em>Consecutive Normal Punches</em>, I present: A Series of Consecutive Normal Daily Head Voices!</p>
<h2 id="monday-2024-01-08">Monday 2024-01-08</h2>
<ul>
<li>First day back at work 😱</li>
<li>&hellip; but the most lovely lunch run (not literally) and chat with colleague E.</li>
<li>Single cable life at work is there, but it&rsquo;s complicated: Thunderbolt3 cable from macbook to Thinkpad dock, dock thunderbolt3 to displayport-mini (adapter), displayport-mini to displayport to monitor.</li>
<li>Had blood drawn for my quarterly PSA test. (prostate-specific antigen; regular test to check that prostate cancer stays gone)</li>
<li>Double Commander (currently at 1.1.8) on macOS is even better than I remember it, and is only a <code>brew install --cask double-commander</code> away.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-09">Tuesday 2024-01-09</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/marimo-team/marimo">marimo</a> looks really good! From the github: <em>a reactive notebook for Python. It allows you to rapidly experiment with data and models, code with confidence in your notebook&rsquo;s correctness, and productionize notebooks as pipelines or interactive web apps</em>. I still have to play with it, but it sounds like an <a href="https://observablehq.com/">Observable</a> for Python.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-10">Wednesday 2024-01-10</h2>
<ul>
<li>Shorter weekday run because hip and because sun. Hip only started complaining by the end, a little later than my last short run. 🎉</li>
<li>Tried to find reclining high-back office chairs with footrest in South Africa, starting from: <a href="https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/">https://www.wellnessgrit.com/best-reclining-office-chair-with-footrest/</a>
<ul>
<li>Spectacular failure! Google Bard, Bing Chat, Perplexity come up with plausible looking links that go to different sites, but nowhere any chairs to be found</li>
<li>perplexity is probably the least bad because it more often admits to just not finding any links in SA</li>
<li>See e.g. <a href="https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c">https://g.co/bard/share/39071699296c</a> and <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5">https://www.perplexity.ai/search/Following-is-a-aMds8_E1SkSAwsHGKNF_tQ?s=c#68c76cf3-f135-4a44-80c2-c1c628d17fb5</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Because of work, started to spend some quality time with <a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js</a> again. I hope to be doing some nice interactive visualization soon!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-11">Thursday 2024-01-11</h2>
<ul>
<li>PSA is 0.006! 🥳</li>
<li>if you&rsquo;ve ever worked with d3.js, you will have used bl.ocks.org quite often. To my surprise, none of these links work anymore, and instead redirect you to the source gist, where they used to show you the live visualization. I could not find much official news about this sunsetting, but was consoled by the discovery of the open source bl.ocks.org clone at <a href="https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/">https://blocks.roadtolarissa.com/</a> via <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513">https://stackoverflow.com/a/75351168/532513</a></li>
<li>Tune of the evening: <a href="https://youtu.be/IAmmkJZ55vM?si=WjEjD8MLge7sCo0E">RÜFÜS DU SOL - On My Knees (Adriatique Remix)</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-12">Friday 2024-01-12</h2>
<ul>
<li>Short week-day run, no hip issues!</li>
<li>Very nice focused day at home: First half wrapping up a code review. Second half diving back into d3.js. So much old memories I have to unearth.</li>
<li>In between hacked in an idle mode for <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity">org-roam-similarity</a>, in the process discovered that on this M1 Pro, CPU is much faster (2x) and uses much less RAM than the hardware accelerated PyTorch MPS version</li>
<li>Lovely weekend-starter braai with family.</li>
<li>Ran into the final sections (and private comments the source org file) of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/#thank-you-joris">WHV #208</a> &ndash; besides the nostalgic music bits, really enjoyed reading some of the older journals. Publish or not, strong motivation to keep on writing journals. (now-you is often a very different person than then-you. interesting to keep in touch!)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-13">Saturday 2024-01-13</h2>
<ul>
<li>one of the highlights of the day was phone-call by and substantial conversation with bestie PK</li>
<li>rest of day quite laid-back with the whole family, which was great</li>
<li>thinking a lot about stefanv&rsquo;s week planner instead of day planner, and the implications of this <em>seemingly</em> reduced planning effort (my daily planning is mostly only theoretical)</li>
<li>greater family braai (GFB)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-14">Sunday 2024-01-14</h2>
<ul>
<li>Overslept a bit, woke up at 9 AM. This has not happened in ages.</li>
<li>Slightly longer weekend run at 10 with new running hat and SPF50 on me face and neck. Hip issue did not manifest, am touching wood!</li>
<li>Because I&rsquo;ve been thinking about more visual ways to plan my week, worked on <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">org-roam-canvas</a>, making it a <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas/commit/a67ad1ee59c93a2998a0c2975ed7d567e7f02c8d">whole lot faster</a>.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2023 to 2024 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 15:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2024 everyone, and especially to this traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: View from first morning of the Cape of Good Hope hiking trail with family and friends. The 3-in-1 hill climb in the summer sun at the end of day 2 almost took me out.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2024 everyone, and especially to this <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition post</a>!</p>










<figure><a href="2023-12-16-cape-point-hike.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_e736f7a9c5849337.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_5d2baa1368199c5d.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_92dc0cc764247a73.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_878bfcc0c607f876.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/2023-12-16-cape-point-hike_hu_5d2baa1368199c5d.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from first morning of the Cape of Good Hope hiking trail with family and friends. The 3-in-1 hill climb in the summer sun at the end of day 2 almost took me out."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>View from first morning of the Cape of Good Hope hiking trail with family and friends. The 3-in-1 hill climb in the summer sun at the end of day 2 almost took me out.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="overview-and-a-warning">Overview, and a warning</h2>
<p>While the year transition posts down here are usually an optimistic and upbeat affair, I have to warn you that this year&rsquo;s edition is a bit different.</p>
<p>Most of the possibly depressing stuff is in the first section, all about aging and cancer and mortality, which you probably could have guessed based on the title, and if not, now on the summary here. Consider strongly skipping the section if you prefer a more optimistic reading of this post.</p>
<p>After the aforementioned <em>harshing of the vibe</em>, I give an extremely spotty review of the physical (running and exercise), the cerebral (writing) and the virtual (systems and tools) aspects of the past year.</p>
<p>I conclude the post with some backyard philosophical ramblings on my continuing efforts at being a good human, and my wishes for you and your loved ones.</p>
<h2 id="aging-is-rough">Aging is rough</h2>
<p>For me, 2023 was the year of really getting in touch with my mortality.</p>
<p>In August of 2023, I <em>started</em> my 50th revolution around the sun.</p>
<p>My birthday might have been enough of a reminder, but the message was made unquestionably clear with <a href="/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/">my prostate cancer</a> diagnosis in February. No thanks to mother nature, and all thanks to science and modern healthcare, the surgical treatment was swift and as effective as we are able to measure.</p>
<p>Love, by all of my friends and family supporting me throughout all of this, and science, see modern healthcare above, got me through this whole adventure with only a small number of scars to show for it. Besides the physical scars, my previously strong trust in my physical robustness took a really big knock.</p>
<p>Much more recently, as in a day or two ago, the pathology results for two recently excised suspicious skin growths came back from the pathology lab.</p>
<p>Both are basal cell carcinoma (BCC), but while the one was completely excised, the other was not, and was also classified as morpheaform BCC, the rarest and more aggressive form of the three.</p>
<p>To the best of my current knowledge, we just need to remove the rest and I should be mostly derisked, but dangit, I had really hoped not to have to think about any form of cancer again for a little while longer.</p>
<p>So, people, please take the following advice as seriously as you possibly can:</p>
<ul>
<li>The sun, especially down here, is amazing but also quite dangerous. Lotion up as often as possible, wear that stupid hat, spend more time in the shade.</li>
<li>All of you, especially younger readers: Use hearing protection at music events. Last year before Lowlands I acquired <a href="https://eargasm.com/products/eargasm-high-fidelity-earplugs">Eargast High Fidelity Earplugs</a>, only about 20 years too late! (like skin canccer, tinnitus is another one of those things you have to start actively preventing decades before it possibly starts)</li>
<li>Over 40? Get your PSA tested.</li>
</ul>
<p>On a more philosophical and hopefully not too depressing note: It has become viscerally clear to me that once one is past reproductive age, one has irrevocably entered the domain of borrowed time.</p>
<p>If you think about evolution and more specifically selection, you can see that survival traits, by the power of math, could only really be encouraged in the young. After the reproductive phase, with <em>genes already passed on</em>, there could be no <em>effective</em> reward or punishment for respectively beneficial and detrimental traits.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, the antagonistic pleiotropic (AP) hypothesis posits that there are genes which control more than one trait &ldquo;where at least one of these traits is beneficial to the organism&rsquo;s fitness early on in life and at least one is detrimental to the organism&rsquo;s fitness later on due to a decline in the force of natural selection&rdquo; (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antagonistic_pleiotropy_hypothesis">AP - wikipedia</a>, <a href="https://www.nature.com/scitable/knowledge/library/the-evolution-of-aging-23651151/">The Evolution of Aging - Nature</a>)</p>
<p>An interesting recent example is <a href="https://alzres.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13195-020-00740-0">this 2021 study of apolipoprotein E (APOE ε4)</a>, which is the strongest genetic risk factor for late onset Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease, but at the same time is also associated with cognitive benefits earlier in life.</p>
<p>From the discussion in the linked paper:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>These results taken together provide support for the antagonistic pleiotropic hypothesis as cognitive performance was better at younger ages in APOE ε4 heterozygotes and both heterozygous and homozygous APOE ε4 carriers also had higher risk of dementia at older ages.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So&hellip; about &ldquo;mother&rdquo; nature.</p>
<p>Nature is beautiful, but absolutely ruthless.</p>
<p>The mental model of &ldquo;natural&rdquo; being beneficial for us humans is at best only coincidentally and very partially useful. For the most part, it&rsquo;s wrong and quite dangerous.</p>
<p>In the end, we can only rely on science, and on each other, to survive and flourish.</p>
<h2 id="running-and-exercise">Running and exercise</h2>
<p>In last year&rsquo;s transition post, I was <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#running">hoping for an average of 25km per week in 2023</a> which would have meant about 1200km for the year.</p>
<p>However, I did not plan on being taken out of the&hellip; running for 6 weeks by my prostate before being allowed to start slowing picking it up again.</p>
<p>In spite of that, I was super happy to see a bit later in the year that 1000km was still in reach, and so I went for that.</p>
<p>Something that looks like it could be my gluteus medius attempted to sabotage my efforts during the final weeks, but on December 30 I pushed through with a last run of the year. 1000km in the pocket!</p>










<figure><a href="strava-fitness-2023.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_fda5ac701be2142f.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_c8669b3c69d1229.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_e07f5d05f7cfd8af.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_9f954c3d4f0bafc3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/strava-fitness-2023_hu_c8669b3c69d1229.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: The smooth part of the curve from the start of April until mid-May was for surgery and recovery. I&rsquo;m happy with the gradual build-up after that and the big push at the end of the year!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>The smooth part of the curve from the start of April until mid-May was for surgery and recovery. I&rsquo;m happy with the gradual build-up after that and the big push at the end of the year!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Regular running is the mechanical backbone of my life.</p>
<p>Even when the stress is great and it feels like stuff is falling apart, those clockwork runs bring peace and perspective. When it&rsquo;s going really great, they bring exhilaration and they feel like a celebration of life!</p>
<p>Although I am hopeful that the current injury resolves itself, which it should if it is in fact my gluteus medius, I might start looking into cross-training this year. It would be great to have an alternative exercise modality to tide me over when injuries happen and to keep me out of the sun a part of the time.</p>
<p>My only running-specific desire is to be able to continue running.</p>
<p>For you numbers-people, that&rsquo;s probably not the most interesting goal.</p>
<p>As a hopefully more satisfying alternative, I would like to offer my super-secret exercise goal for 2024:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be able to do 50 consecutive push-ups,</li>
<li>have a VO₂ Max of at least 50 and</li>
<li>a resting state heart rate of 50 or under.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>For reasons that I&rsquo;ve now mentioned often enough, I produced only a small number of longer blog posts in 2023, namely the <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/">transition post</a>, three (3) weekly head voices posts (including the cancer one), and the <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/">2023 note-taking strategy post</a> which I&rsquo;m really happy with.</p>
<p>Besides that, there were a few short technical postlets over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>On November 14, faced by this barren landscape of almost no blogging, I thought it was worth trying to break through the concomitant writer&rsquo;s block by putting out a <em>daily</em> bullet list of life minutiae: Experiences, learnings and observations that might be interesting to Someone on the Internet.</p>
<p>By reducing the expectation to a straight-forward list of daily miscellanea it would in theory be substantially easier and faster to produce said list.</p>
<p>Further, I deliberately did so on my favourite mastodon server, namely <a href="https://emacs.ch/">emacs.ch</a>, because I trusted that the obscurity of mastodon would mean that not many people would actually see my daily lifelogs, which would further reduce posting friction.</p>
<p>In a surprising turn of events, all of this seemed to work!</p>
<p>As I <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/issues/26868">can&rsquo;t directly link to a mastodon search yet</a>, you will have to go to <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha">my profile</a> or to <a href="https://emacs.ch/tags/lifelog">the #lifelog tag</a> and browse back if you are interested in the first 30 (thirty!) posts, starting on November 14.</p>
<p>On <a href="/2023/12/18/daily-head-voices-on-monday-2023-12-18/">December 18 I decided to move the Daily Head Voices back here</a> because reasons (which you can read about in that post). Since then I have really been enjoying keeping them going during the Christmas break, and I&rsquo;ve also made some tweaks to the technical setup in order to be able to publish them more efficiently.</p>
<p>Although I would really like to work on more substantial posts in the future, recent experience has shown that it might be a while before I can make the space that that requires. The <a href="/categories/lifelog/">lifelog posts</a> are an enjoyable way for me to keep the writing pipes open in the meantime!</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools">Systems and tools</h2>
<p>A core part of my functioning is <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human">the system of software tools and other tricks</a> that I use to work and live better. Other names that people use to describe this thing include second brain, <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">exocortex</a>, or just a really big pile of lists.</p>
<p>Shortly after my pretty detailed <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/">Note-taking strategy 2023</a> blog post, I underwent what I can only describe as some form of Emacs crisis of faith.</p>
<p>During this period, I experienced deep doubt in my current system, and came pretty close to jumping ship.</p>
<p>My crisis was largely due to three things:</p>
<ol>
<li>The shiny webkit-based rendering engines in many of the competitors, enabling useful-looking visualizations and interesting new visual interaction approaches.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://obsidian.md/plugins">vibrant extension community of the local-first Obsidian note-taking tool</a> where many enthusiasts were tapping into the enormous javascript / typescript library ecosystem, and shiny webkit-rendering mentioned above.</li>
<li>Emacs and org-mode&rsquo;s comparatively weak mobile support. (yes, I&rsquo;ve tried, and purchased were relevant, <a href="#d41d8c">beorg</a>, plain.org, organice, orgro and probably many more.)</li>
</ol>
<p>After months of cogitation, I fortunately convinced myself to first test the waters before jumping, where my usual style is just to throw <strong>everything</strong> out and start over, and extremely quickly ran into the glaring weakness that is Obsidian&rsquo;s lack of first class support for the humble timestamp&hellip;</p>
<p>This is something that we Orgmode users take for granted, but man, the Orgmode timestamp is actually pretty amazing.</p>
<p>This textual analogue of an inverted ice bucket seemed to shock me out of my daze, and suddenly I was again able to make peace with Old Reliable BFG9000, aka Emacs and Org.</p>
<p>As part of my atonement, and also to mitigate some of their perceived deficiencies, I coded up and published the following software upgrades to Emacs, Org-mode and Org-roam:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/braindump4000">braindump4000</a>: Convert any Org-mode database into a hyperlinked website, and also an Obsidian vault, so that you can browse it on your phone using the Obsidian app.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-canvas">org-roam-canvas</a>: Expose your whole org-roam database in such a way that you can embed org-roam notes as part of an Obsidian canvas. (see screenshots on the github)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity">org-roam-similarity</a>: Use AI-based similarity (i.e. learned document embeddings / vectors) to interactively list similar org-roam notes to the one that you are working on. This is something that I&rsquo;ve been dreaming about for years, and this is also something that I&rsquo;ve been using quite regularly and successfully to surface relevant information from the depths of my notes!</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-to-apple-notes">org-roam-to-apple-notes</a>: This was quite painful thanks to Apple&rsquo;s super bad AppleScript support of Apple Notes, but it has turned out to be quite useful. On macOS, you can export your whole org-roam database, or just the note that you&rsquo;re currently working on, straight into Apple Notes. Although I implemented base64 embedding of images as this was <em>rumoured</em> to work, images don&rsquo;t work because Apple.</li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_c599996d6ef5a83.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_bc73da04581f6dbb.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_e15f6dbc1a62ed46.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_910a12b14db41a96.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/screenshot-org-roam-similarity-klunky_hu_bc73da04581f6dbb.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: A screenshot of org-roam-similarity showing similar notes in org-roam-buffer."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>A screenshot of <code>org-roam-similarity</code> showing similar notes in <code>org-roam-buffer</code>.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As I write this, it really feels like my faith has been fully restored.</p>
<h3 id="ai">AI</h3>
<p>2023 was the year when, through the astounding success and utility of large language models like ChatGPT and friends, as well as latent diffusion models like StableDiffusion, Dall-E and Midjourney, and many more examples of generative AI, we could finally start using the term &ldquo;AI&rdquo; almost completely unironically!</p>
<p>Thanks to Day Job, <a href="/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/#genai">I had the opportunity to go quite deep</a>, giving a number of pretty detailed talks on the nuts and bolts of transformer-based language models.</p>
<p>The reason I&rsquo;m mentioning it here though, is just to make a public note of the fact that I have been exploring and integrating these new tools into all of my workflows as much as makes sense, attempting to push the barriers here and there.</p>
<p>Like the preternaturally productive <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2023/Mar/27/ai-enhanced-development/">Simon Willison writes</a>, the current generation of AI coding assistance tools are enabling me to take on personal projects I previously would not have due to the time required, and to get those projects to a usable state far more quickly.</p>
<p>My own programming ability is still the driving force (this is the part in my brain that models and simulates software systems in wetware so that I can implement and debug them), but the AI takes care of so much boiler plate, and also helps quickly exploring multiple high probability solutions to the little problems that one invariably runs into.</p>
<p>Besides <a href="https://github.com/features/copilot">Github Copilot</a> which I use in VS Code and also in Emacs via <a href="https://github.com/copilot-emacs/copilot.el">copilot.el</a> to write, sort of ironically, better Emacs Lisp code more quickly, I am trying to integrate at least one AI assistant into my general daily workflow.</p>
<p>My current flavour is <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/">perplexity</a>, an LLM-based system that focuses on answering questions, using background web searches coupled with a current generation LLM.</p>
<p>Although perplexity works really well as a question answering tool, I am waiting for something that combines its talents with a more refined version of the already impressive but sometimes a bit wild <a href="https://github.com/KillianLucas/open-interpreter">Open Interpreter</a> (which I have obviously played with), and for that true AI assistant Jarvis-like tool to be always within reach&hellip;</p>
<p><a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2023/09/new-ray-ban-meta-smart-glasses/">Meta&rsquo;s new Ray Ban AI-powered smart glasses</a> look like a very interesting hardware step in this direction, and might even mean that while I lost <a href="/2009/10/18/futuristic-betting-at-visweek-2009/#bet-1-huds">that 2009 bet about HUDs</a> with regard to its timing, I was at least thinking in the right direction!</p>
<p>Please excuse the rambling; I am really quite excited about the now near future role of AI assistants in human culture!</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2024">Life systems 2024</h2>
<p>As <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/#even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">January 2022 Charl remarked</a>, <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">our January 2021 self really seemed to have everything figured out and organized</a>, at least in terms of life directions. Furthermore, if we&rsquo;re being honest with ourselves, <a href="/2023/01/01/the-2022-to-2023-transition-post/#things-i-would-like-to-work-on-in-2023">January 2023</a> was also quite fuzzy&hellip;</p>
<p>Surprisingly to me however, this year, after spending some thinking time during the vacation, I have compiled a pretty organized-looking and hopefully practical list of personal values, which I will hereby add to the famous <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">WHV approach to life, the universe and everything (WALUE)</a>.</p>
<p>You might recall that our guiding principles were two-fold: 1. Love. 2. Science. (in that order)</p>
<p>.. while the <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">The WHV’s Two no Three Rules for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</a> were 1. Be useful, 2. be likable and 3. evolve.</p>
<p>Over the years I added six personal directions on top of all that, and then later, in a seemingly well-motivated but eventually unsuccessful attempt to apply those directions more successfully, I grouped them into two clusters, namely 1. Grow, learn, build, enjoy. (motion) and 2. Be useful. Be likeable. Be kind. (self-checks).</p>
<p>Well, <strong>this</strong> year I&rsquo;m replacing those two clusters with the following re-expanded list of my more concrete personal values and priorities.  In all cases, it should be possible to use these to check the desirability of any choice or activity.</p>
<ol>
<li>Be kind.</li>
<li>Be grateful.</li>
<li>Attend fully to the now.</li>
<li>Enjoy life with family and with my friends.</li>
<li>Help my children on their journey to becoming useful, likeable and evolving life enjoyers.</li>
<li>Be there for my family.</li>
<li>Add value through work.</li>
<li>Be healthy: Sleep, diet, exercise.</li>
<li>Build or/or fix something.</li>
<li>Learn new things.</li>
<li>Commit to lifelong practice of the good things.</li>
</ol>
<p>In summary, the shiny new 2024 life systems edition consists of the same old a) two guiding principles and the same old b) two no three rules, but now we&rsquo;ve added these c) 11 shiny new personal values all for the same low, low price.</p>
<p>There are no real surprises in this list, but hopefully keeping it close will help to bias daily action in the right directions.</p>
<p>P.S. Please don&rsquo;t forget the <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#learning-at-the-burning">PERMA</a> when thinking about your personal well-being.</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2024">Wishes for 2024</h2>
<p>Dear fellow human,</p>
<p>This is the end of this blog post.</p>
<p>Thank you for being here.</p>
<p>I wish you and your loved ones a year of learning, kindness, gratitude, health and happiness.</p>










<figure><a href="stilbaai-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_f4c4eedfe584fe5a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_8c04e2966d04c4f1.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_1a92a7bd1be2fa3d.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_2021f04e9c9f0447.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/stilbaai-sunset_hu_8c04e2966d04c4f1.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #252: My prostate cancer post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 14:01:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/</guid><description> Figure 1: A dazzle of zebras
Welcome back everyone!
My excuse this time for the multi-month WHV blogging hiatus is that I was dealing with prostate cancer.
I was diagnosed in February, but I wanted to wait for calmer waters before writing anything.
Extremely fortunately, those calmer waters have arrived, and now I can talk openly.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="dazzle-of-zebra.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_553474bf4e68c1b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_1d0de5a264e5fb60.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_d2d6dbd49b798c55.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_fa1286d2e3011625.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/dazzle-of-zebra_hu_1d0de5a264e5fb60.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A dazzle of zebras"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>A dazzle of zebras</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome  back everyone!</p>
<p>My excuse this time for the multi-month WHV blogging hiatus is that I was
dealing with prostate cancer.</p>
<p>I was diagnosed in February, but I wanted to wait for calmer waters before
writing anything.</p>
<p>Extremely fortunately, those calmer waters have arrived, and now I can talk
openly.</p>
<p>I wanted to write up this whole story firstly because this blog has a long
history of stories about significant life events, but also just in case it
could help anyone else who might find themselves in a similar boat and would
like to talk. If you are such a person, please <a href="https://cpbotha.net/about/">email me</a> or leave a comment down
below.</p>
<p>On to the story:</p>
<h2 id="discovery">Discovery</h2>
<p>In January my GP randomly tacked on a PSA (Prostate Specific Antigen) test to
the <a href="https://apob.app/about">Apolipoprotein B (ApoB) blood test</a>, which at that point still was the main
topic of our interest.</p>
<p>The tacked-on PSA came back at 6.5ug/L, which is <em>convincingly</em> above the range
for my age, and hence was suddenly promoted to The Main Topic of Interest.</p>
<p>Three weeks later a repeat test at the urologist came back even a tad higher,
and so I was scheduled for a prostate biopsy two weeks after that.</p>
<p>This procedure, fortunately under general anaesthesia, is where the urologist
sticks a number of needles into one&rsquo;s prostate in order to gather actual tissue
samples that can be studied by the pathology lab.</p>
<p>Those biopsy results came back with&hellip;</p>
<p>Prostate cancer.</p>
<p>ULP&hellip; although my science brain had deduced that this was probably going to
be the outcome (low <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/c-reactive-protein-test/about/pac-20385228">CRP</a> = probably no prostatitis, few other indications of
<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/benign-prostatic-hyperplasia/symptoms-causes/syc-20370087">BPH)</a>, my human brain was in panic.</p>
<p>To be more specific about the diagnosis, it was <a href="https://www.cancer.org/cancer/diagnosis-staging/tests/understanding-your-pathology-report/prostate-pathology/prostate-cancer-pathology.html">Gleason score 3+4 aka grade
group 2 (on the favourable side of &ldquo;intermediate risk&rdquo;)</a> prostate cancer. 9
out of the 13 biopsy cores (samples) were cancerous, with both lobes of the
prostate involved.</p>
<p>Cue some more shock here&hellip;</p>
<p>After that initial shock came the more cognitive realisation (thanks science
brain!) that as cancers and cancer gradings go, this was quite&hellip; <em>reasonable</em>.</p>
<p>That being said, the <em>existential dread</em> caused by this disease, which was
entirely willing and able to kill me, was quite visceral.</p>
<p>By the way, you know that thing about the atheists and the foxholes?</p>
<p>Contrary to the wisdom of the foxhole, I found <em>immense</em> peace in my science, and
endless strength in my family and my friends.</p>
<h2 id="surgery">Surgery</h2>
<p>My urologist explained that for someone at my age, with this diagnosis, he
would recommend in no uncertain terms to have the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prostatectomy">prostate removed</a>, preferably
via <em>robot-assisted laparoscopic prostatectomy</em>, aka my new friend Wreck-it RALP
(silent H).</p>
<p>In my <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">previous career as academic in The Netherlands</a>, a significant part of my
research was computer-assisted surgery. Although I did most of my work in
orthopaedics with the academic hospital in Leiden, the Da Vinci surgical robot
(previous generation!) was very much on our radar.</p>
<p>Little did I know that a decade or so later I would experience its successor,
the Da Vinci X, very much first hand.</p>
<p>(It&rsquo;s hard for me to put in words how grateful I am now for all of the
thousands of hours of research and development that have gone into
robot-assisted surgery&hellip; thank you colleagues!)</p>
<p>On March 30, my partner and I left home at 4 AM to report at the hospital
at 5.</p>
<p>First that horrible open-at-the-back hospital wear, and then the warm enema
they brought in shortly after admission, were pretty clear signs that things
were getting <em>uncomfortably</em> real.</p>
<p>My experience of the surgery itself was of course sublime &ndash; oblivion is indeed
bliss!  &ndash; thanks to the anaesthetist&rsquo;s magic.</p>
<p>The main procedure was performed by <a href="https://caperoboticsurgery.co.za/">Dr Conray Moolman</a>, a urological surgeon who
specialises in RALP, with hundreds of prostatectomies under the belt.</p>
<p>(Why yes, I am in fact now <em>expected</em> to brandish this level of punnery, thanks
for asking.)</p>
<p>Having the operation done by someone with his level of experience is a best
case scenario for me personally, but the role of that experience in the
surgical outcome is underlined by much of the literature on robotic
prostatectomy.</p>
<p>As you can see in the handy Wikipedia illustration below, the surgeon has to
cut out the prostate and some of the surrounding tissue, and then attach the
remaining urethra to the bladder neck.</p>
<p>The poor urethra is just expected to stretch to the occasion.</p>










<figure><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prostatectomy#/media/File:Prostate_Removal.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/fb/Prostate_Removal.png"
         width="50%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>All of this happens via the Da Vinci X&rsquo;s many robotic arms, a number of them
inserted into my abdominal cavity through the five incisions (four small and
one larger) in my abdomen.</p>










<figure><a href="davinci-table.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_9d81c6c80d2fd942.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_3657f00e43b134d5.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_acd23c8750a659c7.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2023/07/01/weekly-head-voices-252-prostate-cancer/davinci-table_hu_3657f00e43b134d5.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>One of the main challenges for the surgeon here is that, along with the whole
prostate, they need to remove as little as possible of the surrounding nerves,
which would result in certain post-operative functional deficits, but enough of
the surrounding tissue to include cancer cells that may have progressed to
there.</p>
<h2 id="post-op">Post-op</h2>
<p>I was able to walk a little bit on the same afternoon, with the expert help of
the physiotherapist, and in spite of the interference of my new and fortunately
temporary augmentation the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foley_catheter">Foley catheter</a>, which had to remain in place for at
least a week to give the new bladder-urethra hook-up time to heal.</p>
<p>A few days later, the first fantastic bit of news was that the post-op
pathology report, completed a few days later, showed that <a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/positive-surgical-margins-following-radical-prostatectomy-20090617171">&ldquo;all margins were
clear&rdquo;</a>, meaning that it was highly probable that all prostate cancer cells
had been taken care of.</p>
<p>I was able to return to work just over two weeks after surgery.</p>
<p>The first post-op PSA test 6 weeks afterwards showed a new PSA level of 0.01.</p>
<p>I have not been able to find out if that amount is just what the test shows at
its lower end, or if there is somehow some residual PSA left in my system.</p>
<p>My urologist seems happy with this result, which is important.</p>
<p>For the first year, I&rsquo;ll have to repeat this blood test every three months to
ensure that there&rsquo;s really nothing there. I am keeping my fingers crossed.</p>
<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts</h2>
<p>As I write this, exactly three months after the prostatectomy, I am looking out
over the Crocodile river, at the end of <a href="/tags/knp/">our traditional winter KNP break-away</a>.</p>
<p>Shortly after the 6-week PSA test, I had to have another small surgical
procedure due to a urethral stricture which developed most probably due to the
catheter. Fortunately the stricture was very distal (ahem), far away from the
critical new urethra-bladder-neck junction.</p>
<p>I am almost back up to pre-surgical strength, although I do have to go to the
bathroom substantially more regularly (also at night) due to the remaining
nerves (most of them, fortunately!) still having to learn new tricks, but
probably more due to the urethral sphincter being exactly the part that is
newly sutured to the bladder neck. Other than that, my running fitness took
quite a hit, and is now in the slow process of building up again.</p>
<p>On the mental side, my confidence in my own health and physical resilience has
taken a bit of a knock. This is something I really need to work on.</p>
<p><strong><strong>Through all of this, support from work, friends and family has been absolutely
phenomenal.</strong></strong></p>
<p>Amongst many other lessons, this has shown me how much even that random
WhatsApp from a friend who I haven&rsquo;t seen in ages can mean, and so I have
resolved to send that random supportive message through whichever medium,
whenever there&rsquo;s an opportunity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>