<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>triggerfish on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/triggerfish/</link><description>Recent content in triggerfish on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 19:22:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/triggerfish/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #82: Tiles and platitudes.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/09/23/weekly-head-voices-82-tiles-and-platitutes/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 19:22:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/09/23/weekly-head-voices-82-tiles-and-platitutes/</guid><description> The reason I’m behind with blogging, is because I’m currently working on three products. One of these is already being used by real live people (!!!), and another will shortly be quite intensively interacted with by quite a large number of people, if it doesn’t melt under the load that is. The third will hopefully soon also go live in some form or another.
I might currently be at peak Django people.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>The reason I’m behind with blogging, is because I’m currently working on three products. One of these is already being used by real live people (!!!), and another will shortly be quite intensively interacted with by quite a large number of people, if it doesn’t melt under the load that is. The third will hopefully soon also go live in some form or another.</p>
<p>I might currently be at peak Django people. Peak Django!</p>
<p>(It also seems that my lust for programming is unnaffected by all the deadlines. Estimation on the other hand… just eeuw.)</p>
<p>With the time I save by not blogging <em>that</em> regularly, I still get to hang out with friends, drink local craft beer, and scorch meat. Here’s a photo to prove it:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-arty_bone_crusher.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-arty_bone_crusher.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>During a different pleasant encounter with a different old friend at Triggerfish Brewing, enjoying some super strong locally-brewed IPAs, abovementioned old friend somehow managed to convince me to try <a href="http://i3wm.org/">i3</a>. i3 is a tiling window manager. This means that it forces you to think (mostly) in a single layer on the desktop, meaning no overlapping windows. After a false start (Unity does so many things <em>right</em> out of the box) I’m now the happy but conflicted owner of a finely hand-tuned i3 configuration. Here’s a screenshot:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-i3_cpbotha_screenie.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/wpid-i3_cpbotha_screenie.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>This also means that my neckbeard is probably invading my brain.</p>
<p>On the more wholesome front, after reading <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/walking-helps-us-think">this article</a> on the creative benefits of walking, I’ve been taking more walks at work (often with a really great old friend I have the privilege of sharing an office with these days). I can report, entirely unscientifically, that this activity has made a huge difference, especially when performed in the middle of those painfully long afternoons when one’s brain starts to feel like slowly sloshing chunky peanut butter sauce in a skull-shaped dip bowl. (oh come on, you know the feeling)</p>
<p>So recently a picture of the Dalai Lama with the following quote was circulating on Facebook:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Dalai Lama, when asked what surprised him most about humanity, answered, ‘Man. Because he sacrifices his health in order to make money. Then he sacrifices money to recuperate his health. And then he is so anxious about the future that he does not enjoy the present; the result being that he does not live in the the present or the future; he lives as if he is never going to die, and then dies having never really lived.’</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now we all know the rule for pictures with famous people and quotes on them, and especially those circulating on facebook: <em>It’s probably BS.</em></p>
<p>In this case I was conflicted, because I secretly liked what this platitude-in-sheep’s-clothing was trying to tell us: Remember to focus on the important stuff, remember to focus on the now.</p>
<p>However, that rule felt nothing for my conflict. It looks like the quote is not by the Dalai Lama, but by a fellow named Jim Brown, see <a href="http://cascadianwanderer.wordpress.com/2014/07/29/the-dalai-lama-is-jim-brown/">here</a> and <a href="http://centerforgloballeadership.wordpress.com/2012/06/30/an-interview-with-god-i-stand-corrected/">here</a>. Take that, you quotes on pictures of important people!</p>
<p>Fake quotes or not, focusing on the now fortunately is still real. Have a great week kids!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #74: Truth.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/06/15/weekly-head-voices-74/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2014 21:18:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/06/15/weekly-head-voices-74/</guid><description> I think I might have forgotten to tell you that one of the many perks of working at the Stone Three offices is that there’s a micro-brewery within walking distance. Triggerfish Brewing, as brewery in question is called, was the location of a midweek mini-get-together that ended up looking like this:
Triggerfish’s Roman Red Ale on a Winter’s day.
On the topic of not-too-shabby settings for meetings, I finally got around to visiting Truth Coffee in Cape Town, described by some as The best coffee shop in the world.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I think I might have forgotten to tell you that one of the many perks of working at the Stone Three offices is that there’s a micro-brewery within walking distance. <a href="http://www.triggerfishbrewing.co.za/">Triggerfish Brewing</a>, as brewery in question is called, was the location of a midweek mini-get-together that ended up looking like this:</p>
<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-0" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-triggerfish_amber_ale.jpg" title="">
<p><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-triggerfish_amber_ale-300x225.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">Triggerfish’s Roman Red Ale on a Winter’s day.</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>On the topic of not-too-shabby settings for meetings, I finally got around to visiting <a href="http://www.truthcoffee.com/">Truth Coffee</a> in Cape Town, <a href="http://travel.uk.msn.com/photos/the-best-coffee-shop-in-the-world">described by some</a> as <em>The best coffee shop in the world</em>. I was too busy having a good meeting, enjoying the superb coffee, and generally gawking at the fantastic interior and the pretty people (guests and staff) to take any photos, so you’re going to have to take me on my word and check <a href="http://www.thisiscolossal.com/2013/09/truth-steampunk-coffee-shop/">some of the photos floating around on the web</a>.</p>
<p>In between coffee, beer and meetings, I wrote two short nerdy posts at the vxlabs:</p>
<ul class="org-ul">
<li>
<a href="http://vxlabs.com/2014/06/09/fixing-roundcube-error-in-ddl-upgrade/">Fixing Roundcube 1.0 schema upgrade error</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href="http://vxlabs.com/2014/06/15/huawei-e3331-3g-usb-dongle-works-on-ubuntu-14-04-linux/">Confirming that the Huawei E3331 3G modem works with Linux</a>
</li>
</ul>
<p>It was pretty awesome to hear that <a href="http://io9.com/5963263/how-nasa-will-build-its-very-first-warp-drive">NASA is thinking pretty seriously about developing a warp drive</a>, with which a ship would we able to traverse space at effectively faster than light speeds. It would do this without <em>locally</em> exceeding the speed of light by warping space around the travelling ship, contracting spacetime before the moving ship and expanding it behind it. The ideas are based on a paper by Miguel Alcubierre from 1994 titled <a href="http://iopscience.iop.org/0264-9381/11/5/001"><em>The warp drive: hyper-fast travel within general relativity</em></a>, and so this gets to be called the Alcubierre Drive!</p>
<p>Well now they’ve gone and <a href="http://io9.com/heres-nasas-new-design-for-a-warp-drive-ship-1588948192">published artist’s impressions</a> of what such an Alcubierre Drive-equipped ship could look like, and it’s gorgeous!</p>
<figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 300px"><a data-rel="lightbox-image-1" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-alcubierre_ship.jpg" title="">
<p><img src="http://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/wpid-alcubierre_ship-300x168.jpg" alt=""></a><figcaption class="wp-caption-text">My favourite view of the ship. The rings on the outside are there to create the warp bubble which will BEND SPACETIME!</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>These are pretty exciting times.</p>
<p>I’m going to end this post with an acronym I embarrasingly only learnt the meaning of yesterday: LLAP!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>