<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>rochefort on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/rochefort/</link><description>Recent content in rochefort on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 22:28:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/rochefort/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #197: How to ship side-projects</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 22:28:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/</guid><description> Hello friends!
Weekly Head Voices #197 looks back at the week from Monday June 1 to Sunday June 7.
Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect.
Work-work is quite high intensity at the moment.
I really would not mind a bit of respite any time soon now.
In the meantime, let me look back, and by the crazy laws of metaphysics also inwards, at the previous week:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello friends!</p>
<p>Weekly Head Voices #197 looks back at the week from Monday June 1 to Sunday June 7.</p>








<figure><a href="morgenster.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/morgenster_hu00493877939b967d40d1829263b80ca0_1079342_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Weekend morning runs are generally great, but this Saturday morning run was particularly perfect.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Work-work is quite high intensity at the moment.</p>
<p>I really would not mind a bit of respite any time soon now.</p>
<p>In the meantime, let me look back, and by the crazy laws of metaphysics
also inwards, at the previous week:</p>
<h2 id="on-slipping-and-shipping-a-side-project">On slipping and shipping a side-project</h2>
<p>I have <a href="/2018/05/13/weekly-head-voices-142-theory-of-mind/#the-side-project-dilemma">written</a> <a href="/2018/09/03/weekly-head-voices-152-a-small-but-highly-trained-team-of-11-year-olds/#au-revoir">before</a> about nerds and their side-projects.</p>
<p>You might recall that I said that they mostly don&rsquo;t ever see the light of day,
although they still have indirect benefits.</p>
<p>In any case, the two I linked to above both failed, so at least that&rsquo;s nice for
consistency.</p>
<p>However, on Friday I went and bucked the trend ever so slightly by
soft-launching the Lazar Focus app and website distraction blocker for Windows.</p>
<p>I <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">mentioned LF last week</a>, but it now has a website, called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">lazarfocused.com</a>,
and it has a <a href="https://gumroad.com/l/yExQgr">product page on gumroad</a>.</p>
<p>It has a <em>substantially</em> smaller number of bugs thanks to brilliant beta
testing by multi-modal medical visualization expert and productivity app
<em>connoisseuse</em> <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/">Noeska</a>.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re on Windows, this is exactly the little app you need to block
distractions, only when you say so of course, so that you can focus on all of
The Important Stuff™ you undoubtedly would rather get done, so that you
can get back to goofing off.</p>
<p>AMIRITE?!</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re one of those people who don&rsquo;t need any help to help focusing and to
stay in the zone, but you work with people who might, the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/06/06/the-philosophy-behind-lazar-focus/">philosophy behind
Lazar Focus</a> blog post is a good introduction to share with them. (Also, could I
interview you? :)</p>
<h2 id="dry-january-finally-ends--or-maybe-not--with-rochefort">Dry January finally ends (or maybe not) with Rochefort</h2>
<p>This year, I <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">started Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) on January 6</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m happy to report that this was interrupted only once for a superb glass of
my favourite Chardonnay (that&rsquo;s the Haskell Anvil, see <a href="/2019/10/17/weekly-head-voices-181-the-slow-ones/#what-i-did-in-week-41">WHV #181</a> for the first
encounter) with besties, right at the source.</p>
<p>Other than that, I remained in EAZ until Saturday, June 6, when the St
Bernhardus Abt 12 and the Trappistes Rochefort #8 and #10 that a friend had
brought for me all the way from The Netherlands and that had been waiting
patiently for me in the cupboard, had just been sitting there waiting for long
enough.</p>
<p>(By the way, the St Bernhardus Abt 12 is a taste clone of the Westvleteren, the
pretty expensive king of the Trappist beers, as a drunk gentleman once
explained to me in the Doerak in Delft late one evening. He was right, as my
companion and I subsequently confirmed when we acquired both beers for a
comparative tasting on the spot.)</p>
<p>The time, but far more pertinently the opportunity, had come to end (or was it
merely to interrupt&hellip;) EAZ 2020.</p>
<p>Friends, that Rochefort is simply packed with a multitude of sweet, warm
memories of days and evenings in my other home, with my other family.</p>








<figure><a href="rochefort_8_action_shot.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/06/11/weekly-head-voices-197-shipping-a-side-project/rochefort_8_action_shot_hu09101c82e03d9743f9adfcf38f7fad1a_1303533_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Just in case you needed reminding, the Rochefort 8 looks like this. Memories of a lifetime not pictured."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Just in case you needed reminding, the Rochefort 8 looks like this. Memories of a lifetime not pictured.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>(Going even further back, I have <a href="/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/">mentioned before</a> that this blog contains <a href="/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/">a
written record of my very first encounter with Rochefort</a>, all the way back in
2003, right in the town of La Roche-en-Ardenna, about 30 minutes away from
Rochefort itself. Reading that post now, it really was a sort of WHV avant la
lettre!)</p>
<h2 id="the-last-bit">The last bit</h2>
<p>Ok folks, it is now 22:17 on Thursday evening, and I&rsquo;m at that super difficult
&ldquo;HOW IN THOR&rsquo;S NAME DO I CONCLUDE THIS THING?!&quot;-stage, a problem which I seem
to be solving with the &ldquo;I KNOW LET&rsquo;S BREAK THE FOURTH WALL / SIMPLY TALK
ABOUT HOW WE DON&rsquo;T KNOW HOW TO END THIS THING&rdquo;-manoeuvre.</p>
<p>On the bright side, I think we did <em>just</em> make the deadline with this edition
of the WHV, narrowly avoiding postponement and a larger-than-normal next post.</p>
<p>Have a brilliant rest of the week and weekend. I look forward to seeing you
again, here and anywhere!</p>
<p>P.S. I still don&rsquo;t know how to ship side-projects.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #109: GABA</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 11:17:09 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/07/19/weekly-head-voices-109-gaba/</guid><description> From now on, I would like to limit WHVs to bullets (really) or to named sections, to ease reading. DOWN WITH WALLS OF TEXT! After a multi-year, completely coincidental, break from medical imaging, I am back to The Real Business since the start of July. I am super excited about the plans we’re cooking up and executing. I can obviously not say too much, unless beer is involved, or you hang around here for muuuuuch longer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>From now on, I would like to limit WHVs to bullets (really) or to named sections, to ease reading. DOWN WITH WALLS OF TEXT!</li>
<li>After a multi-year, completely coincidental, break from <strong>medical imaging</strong>, I am back to <em>The Real Business</em> since the start of July. I am super excited about the plans we’re cooking up and executing. I can obviously not say too much, unless beer is involved, or you hang around here for muuuuuch longer. I think I am allowed to mention <strong>digital pathology</strong> and <strong>machine learning</strong> and beer.</li>
<li>Last week we <strong>road-tripped up the East Coast to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Francis_Bay">St Francis Bay</a></strong>, via Oudtshoorn and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cango_Caves">Cango Caves</a>.
<ul>
<li>Pro tip: When road tripping with more than 0 (zero) children (babies count double; sick babies +5 hit points), and you have to stay overnight somewhere, invest extra in the biggest suite you (or your children’s college fund) can afford.</li>
<li>On the beach in St Francis Bay (right in the middle of winter, you still seem to get these lovely balmy beach days), it seemed that <em>everybody</em> was surfing. Whole families, with the mom, the dad, all the kids, and grandma and grandpa, were all on various sizes of surfboards in the sea catching some waves.</li>
<li>Here’s a photo from the furthest point on what I call “Not The Ugliest Jogging Route in The World” (in St Francis Bay):</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/20160714_170901.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/20160714_170901-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<ul>
<li>Last night I accidentally discovered that I can pinpoint the exact weekend and location when and where I first tasted my <strong>favourite <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trappist_beer">trappist beer</a> (EVER)</strong>, namely Rochefort #8. It’s all written up in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/">this 2003 post</a>.</li>
<li>When Google send me an email this weekend asking me exactly <em>how</em> I would like them to use my email (yes, a few months ago I migrated my mail empire back to Google because <a href="/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">my self-hosting experiment</a> had started to cost me time and money) to show me custom advertisements, I was reminded that I do actually find the machine learning models they’re building about me quite creepy, and that perhaps I would prefer not also handing them 12 years of emails to make their models more accurate. There and then <strong>I migrated said 12 years of emails from GMail to <a href="https://www.fastmail.com/">FastMail</a></strong>. So far I’m really impressed by the product, mostly due to the speed and the user experience of the web-app. There might be a more detailed post in the near future, let me know if you’re interested.</li>
<li><em>Most surprising and interesting (to me) new scientific discovery of the week:</em> A team of scientists at Northeastern University in Boston <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/2095769-gut-bacteria-spotted-eating-brain-chemicals-for-the-first-time/">have shown</a> that <strong>one of the many kinds of bacteria living in your stomach eats exclusively <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-Aminobutyric_acid">GABA</a></strong>, a really important brain chemical (neurotransmitter) that plays a role in keeping you calm. Based on this and other work, it looks like the bacteria in your tummy, also known as your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gut_flora">gastrointestinal microbiota</a>, besides being crucially important to your digestive system and your general survival, probably also play quite an important role in your psyche. I find this slightly mind-blowing.</li>
</ul>
<p>Have a great week kids, I hope to see you on the other side.</p>
<p>P.S. Those bullets made for quite an impressive wall of text, didn’t they?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>An eventful weekend</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2003 22:33:34 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2003/04/21/an-eventful-weekend/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Much happened this weekend. Because many readers have fantastically short attention spans, I&rsquo;ll break my report up into clearly marked sections.
Is my laptop hard drive defective? My laptop has done this once before: after the laptop is switched on, the hard drive refuses to start. It&rsquo;s usually very quiet, but definitely audible at startup. This weekend before we left for Belgium (more on this later) the laptop decided it was time for the &ldquo;the hard drive can&rsquo;t be bothered to start up&rdquo; trick again.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Much happened this weekend. Because many readers have fantastically short
attention spans, I&rsquo;ll break my report up into clearly marked sections.</p>
<h2 id="is-my-laptop-hard-drive-defective">Is my laptop hard drive defective?</h2>
<p>My laptop has done this once before: after the laptop is switched on, the hard
drive refuses to start. It&rsquo;s usually very quiet, but definitely audible at
startup. This weekend before we left for Belgium (more on this later) the
laptop decided it was time for the &ldquo;the hard drive can&rsquo;t be bothered to start
up&rdquo; trick again. No amount of restarts, reboots, hard drive reseats (yes, I
<em>do</em> mean &ldquo;reseat&rdquo;) and cursing seems to remedy this. When I returned today
(i.e. after almost 4 days of rest and relaxation for both me and the hard
drive) it started up without a hitch.</p>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t been able to find very much information on the Toshiba MK3018GAS hard
drive and its issues. Maybe I&rsquo;m just lucky to have that one <em>special</em> hard
drive.</p>
<h2 id="a-toothbrush-i-am">A toothbrush. I am.</h2>
<p>We spent this weekend in the south of Belgium, in a <a href="http://www.tenneville.be/">little town</a> almost in
the middle of nowhere. Yes, it has its own frikking website.</p>
<p>In anycase, Tenneville is in a French-speaking province. My French is atrocious
on the best of days, so I had the pleasure of some extremely entertaining
conversations with some of the native francophones. I am glad to say that
during the weekend, simply because no-one speaks a word of English and one or
two exceptions can manage a few phrases of Flemish (i.e. Dutch), my French
glands got so much exercise that I experienced a significant improvement.</p>
<p>I will definitely take more time to watch TV5 and one day I shall do my
erstwhile French teacher proud!</p>
<h2 id="ardenne-ham-and-abbey-beer">Ardenne ham and abbey beer</h2>
<p>Everybody knows and accepts that Belgian beers rule the earth. Those who don&rsquo;t
are profoundly stupid. It&rsquo;s also widely accepted that the better Belgian beers
are made by monks in their abbeys. Bless their souls. This weekend my beer
glands transcended to the next level of consciousness as I imbibed the
<a href="http://www.belgianstyle.com/mmguide/example/label.php3?img=rochfort.gif&amp;beer=Rochefort+8">Trappistes Rochefort Numero 8</a>.</p>
<p>Just to demonstrate that some people are endowed with unfair amounts of kharma,
I was having some of the finest hams in the world whilst sipping this divine
beer. You can do the same: just mosy on down to <a href="http://www.laroche.be/">La Roche-en-Ardenne</a> (close
by Tenneville) and walk into a suitable charcuterie. Work with the waitress on
the rest.</p>
<h2 id="water-is-wet">Water is wet</h2>
<p>To conclude an already perfect weekend, we kayaked down l&rsquo;Ourthe (the river
running through La Roche). The bastards at the kayak place conveniently forgot
to warn us about that last rapid. We succeeded in shooting over the thing
without overturning the kayak, but took so much water that not capsizing
actually became an academic distinction.</p>
<h2 id="the-belgian-ardenne">The Belgian Ardenne</h2>
<p>&hellip; is highly recommended. Go there. :)</p>
<h2 id="post-scriptum">Post Scriptum</h2>
<p>It struck me this weekend to what an extent 21st century technology has
permeated our lives. I telephoned my mother whilst lying on a grassy hill in
front of the house that we rented in Tenneville. When my mother answered, she
explained that they were on a mountain top on the southern-most tip of the
African continent. The fact that I could hear a crystal-clear reproduction of
her voice more than 10000km away and communicate with her in real-time on a
cheap consumer device is quite astounding, don&rsquo;t you think?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>