<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Plans on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/plans/</link><description>Recent content in Plans on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 11:03:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/plans/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2019 to 2020 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2020 11:03:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/</guid><description>Welcome to 2020 folks!
In retrospect, I really should have written this post during the vacation, when it is substantially easier to wax all optimistic about the year to come.
As it stands, we&amp;rsquo;re slightly more than a week of work into the new year, and most of that vacation naiveté has been brought summarily crashing down to earth as part of a sort of planetary body check.
Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s better this way after all. Let&amp;rsquo;s keep it real.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2020 folks!</p>
<p>In retrospect, I really should have written this post during the vacation, when
it is substantially easier to wax all optimistic about the year to come.</p>
<p>As it stands, we&rsquo;re slightly more than a week of work into the new year, and
most of that vacation naiveté has been brought summarily crashing down to earth
as part of a sort of planetary body check.</p>
<p>Perhaps it&rsquo;s better this way after all. Let&rsquo;s keep it real.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_7ae0711e1ec24e44.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_9fec7f25ff8c1eda.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_b51b8f872c372a04.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_c9178771c548d66e.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/bettys_walk_pano_hu_9fec7f25ff8c1eda.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
A sample of the view as I was walking to the main beach in Betty's Bay,
listening to a super entertaining <a
href="https://www.wnycstudios.org/podcasts/radiolab/articles/man-against-horse">radiolab
podcast about a recent 50 mile race between humans and horses</a>. (Hint: A human won!)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>During the vacation, I did manage to find all (most?) of <a href="/tags/transition/">the previous (year)
transition posts</a> all the way back to 2010 and retro-tag
them, for your and my reading pleasure, but mostly because I like to keep
things orderly around here.</p>
<p>The rest of this post is a very brief and spotty review of 2019, followed by my
far-more-grounded-than-usual (see above) hopes and dreams for 2020.</p>
<h2 id="learnings-and-events-that-i-found-important-through-the-lens-of-this-blog">Learnings and events that I found important, through the lens of this blog.</h2>
<p>I now find <a href="/tags/sleep/">sleep</a> <em>at least</em> as important as healthy eating (and
<a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">not
eating</a>)
and exercise for human wellness. I started writing about sleep in the <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 to
2018 transition post</a> after
reading about Matthew Walker for the first time in a Guardian interview.</p>
<p>In 2019 I got around to reading his book as well, and I now I&rsquo;m even more
scared of losing sleep over anything.</p>
<p>(For a giggle, contrast this with <a href="/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/#earlyish-morning-sessions">my early morning work sessions in WHV
#161</a>. On
second thought, in Summer time one could probably get this working again.)</p>
<p>Our home is <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">now solar
powered</a>. In fact,
this post is for the largest part made using power directly from the sun!</p>
<p><a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">Stone Three
Healthcare</a>,
a new med-tech company I am officially part of, was officially launched after
a great incubation period.</p>
<p>Exciting times lie ahead.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/07/25/weekly-head-voices-174-i-row-row-row-your-boat/#life-is-but-a-dream">Reality is just a different type of
dreaming</a>,
and other implications of brain-based reality simulation.</p>
<p>We are still feeling <a href="/2019/09/01/weekly-head-voices-176-cycle-of-life/#loss">the loss of a clan mother</a>.</p>
<p><a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">ABC stands for Always Be
Compounding</a>.</p>
<p>Maybe <em>that</em> will be my main theme for 2020.</p>
<h2 id="blogging-stats">Blogging Stats.</h2>
<p>In 2019 I published 35 posts on this blog, slightly down from 2019&rsquo;s 36 posts.</p>
<p>(I also published 12 more nerdy posts over on vxlabs, slightly up from 2019&rsquo;s 11 posts.)</p>
<p>The static log analyzer tool I installed in March of 2019 (awstats, if you have
to know) reports 37403 unique visitors reading just under 160000 pages between
them.</p>
<p>It could be that all of that is due to my small group of friends voraciously
re-reading everything on here, each time with a new dynamically assigned IP
address.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be (voracious) readers, thank you for reading the things
I write!</p>
<h2 id="technical-changes-to-the-site-with-implications-for-the-writing-process">Technical changes to the site, with implications for the writing process.</h2>
<p>In March of this year, I <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">ported this whole site from wordpress to the Hugo
static site generator</a>.</p>
<p>Although this has resulted in a significantly faster and more secure site, the
real benefits only dawned on me a few weeks in.</p>
<p>With Hugo, my main input modality is the humble text editor, where I write the
<a href="https://commonmark.org/help/">markdown</a>, that is semi-structured plaintext
with a few tricks, of each post before converting it to its final published
form.</p>
<p>In contrast to the WYSIWYG of Wordpress and especially of its new-fangled
Gutenberg visual editor, the latter which was probably the biggest reason for
me to make the jump, I see only text and the markdown heading structure when I
write posts, with very few other distractions.</p>
<p>This has magically resulted in me applying significantly more focus and
discipline to how I write these posts, which has further resulted in an
unexpected increase in writing satisfaction.</p>
<p>(I am carefully optimistic that it might even contribute ever so slightly to
post quality.)</p>
<p>In November of 2019, I also moved all 20 years of super valuable (to me) reader
comments <a href="/2019/11/10/we-now-have-self-hosted-isso-comments/">away from the Disqus silo and into a self-hosted open-source
commenting system called
isso</a>.</p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>In 2019, Strava says I ran 1086km, down from over 1200km in 2018.</p>
<p>I am happy with this.</p>
<p>At the start of 2019, <a href="/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/#running-inspiration">I slowed down a bit
(again)</a>
to help save my ankles.</p>
<p>That seemed to have worked, because I had no mentionable injuries for the rest
of the year, and <em>that</em> makes me happier than more distance would have.</p>
<p>For the sake of this retrospective, I do have to note that I did attain my
secret-until-unlock extra 2019 running goal, namely <a href="/2019/11/22/weekly-head-voices-184-the-tai-chi-of-you/#running">the casual 20km
jog</a> on one
not-too-hot Saturday morning in November.</p>
<p>For 2020, my main goal is simply to continue running throughout the year (see
ABC above) without injury.</p>
<p>The secret additional milestone has not yet been formulated.</p>
<p>(I still enjoy running the most on barefoot or sandals, but for the longer
runs, I am really happy to have made the <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/#escalante">Altra connection in
September</a>.)</p>
<h2 id="plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">Plans and life directions for 2020.</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#other-plans-for-2019">January 6, 2019 transition WHV were definitely more
ambitious</a>
than I currently feel.</p>
<p>Traditionally, Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) starts around this time and then
continues for a month or more.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s a great tradition, so Monday, January 6, 2020 marks the date this time
around.</p>
<p>Other than EAZ and my humble running goals, it is probably relevant to mention
my recently started experimental daily list of life directions.</p>
<p>At the start of 2012, <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">I wrote the following about life
goals</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Don&rsquo;t set life goals, but rather set life directions. Instead of defining the
point that you want to go towards, define your preferred direction. If you do
it right, you&rsquo;ll pass those points as you go along in any case, except you
won&rsquo;t land in the depressing goal vacuum right after reaching the point that
you&rsquo;ve been moving towards for so long, because you&rsquo;re motoring along in a
direction, and that&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s important.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(I should have added then that life goals, especially the new year&rsquo;s resolution
variety, are also incredibly easy to fail at.)</p>
<p>Finally applying this advice concretely to my <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019">note-taking / PKM
system</a>, I have recently added an
&ldquo;Experiment: Articulate your directions / systems&rdquo; heading to <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">the daily
planning template</a>.</p>
<p>In other words, every(ish) morning during day planning, I <em>attempt</em> to write
down (again&hellip;) my current life directions.</p>
<p>This is a neat trick to force me to be reminded multiple times per week of
these guidelines.</p>
<p>It also gives me the opportunity to adapt the wording, or even the list
itself. Your surroundings change continuously, and so do you.</p>
<p>The most recent version is as follows:</p>
<ol start="0">
<li>nurture your clan.</li>
<li>grow the business.</li>
<li>keep on writing, also for publication.</li>
<li>keep on programming, also for publication.</li>
<li>keep on learning, and sharpen tools.</li>
<li>optimise physiology.</li>
</ol>
<p>All of these are
<a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding"><em>compounding</em></a>.</p>
<p>None of them are concrete goals which I can quantitatively attain.</p>
<p>They are all <em>directions of movement</em>, along which any decision or action can
be measured.</p>
<p>If that action furthers one or more of the six directions above, we are good to
go.</p>
<p>If not, it&rsquo;s probably time to go to bed.</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2020">Wishes for 2020.</h2>
<p>Dear readers, <strong>thank you for being here</strong>.</p>
<p>I wish you a brilliant 2020.</p>
<p>I look forward to all of our meetings, both here on these pages, and everywhere
else where they may happen.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>