<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>healthfit on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/healthfit/</link><description>Recent content in healthfit on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 20:17:27 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/healthfit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #153: pH &lt; 7 dreams.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/09/11/weekly-head-voices-153/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2018 20:17:27 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/09/11/weekly-head-voices-153/</guid><description> Looking back at the week from Monday September 3 to Sunday September 9, I present to you the following memories and after-effects.
Aphex Twin never left us I serendipitously ran into T69 Collapse, the brand new track and video by Aphex Twin.
In the grand tradition of WHV intro art, I have embedded the video above.
Whether you’re a fan or not, I think it’s worth sitting through this one, preferably with the headphones and the video in full screen.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SqayDnQ2wmw?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Looking back at the week from Monday September 3 to Sunday September 9, I present to you the following memories and after-effects.</p>
<h1 id="aphex-twin-never-left-us">Aphex Twin never left us</h1>
<p>I serendipitously ran into T69 Collapse, the brand new track and video by Aphex Twin.</p>
<p>In the grand tradition of WHV intro art, I have embedded the video above.</p>
<p>Whether you’re a fan or not, I think it’s worth sitting through this one, preferably with the headphones and the video in full screen.</p>
<p>Pro-tip: This is not one of those tracks where the whole thing can be more or less predicted by viewing the first minute. There’s a thing at 1:55 and a second thing at 3:14.</p>
<p>I had to wonder whether the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_3:14">3:14</a> was intentional. We’re not much into our biblical references over here as you might know, but you have to recall that Aphex Twin is the guy who, already back in 1999, hid his face in the spectrogram of a music track called:</p>
<p>\[\Delta M_i^{-1} = -\alpha \sum\limits_{n=1}^N D_i [n] \left[\sum\limits_{j \in C[i]} F_{ji} [n-1] + Fext_i [n^{-1}]\right]\]</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s the actual name of the track (#2 on the famous <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windowlicker">Windowlicker EP</a>), although most people (plebs!) refer  to it as just <em>Function</em> or <em>Equation</em>. I got sucked down that rabbit hole last night, but no-one on the internet seems to know the true meaning of the equation. Please ask RDJ if you ever run into him.</p>
<p>Anyways, I have embedded \(\Delta M_i^{-1} = -\alpha \sum\limits_{n=1}^N D_i [n] \left[\sum\limits_{j \in C[i]} F_{ji} [n-1] + Fext_i [n^{-1}]\right]\) below for your listening and viewing pleasure. Aphex Twin’s face appears at 5:30.</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M9xMuPWAZW8?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<h1 id="apfs-encryption-vs-samsung-hardware-encryption-effective-ssd-speed">APFS encryption vs Samsung hardware encryption effective SSD speed</h1>
<p>I ran benchmarks on my external Samsung T3 SSD comparing the speed of encrypted APFS to unencrypted APFS with Samsung’s hardware-based full disk encryption.</p>
<p>I used <a href="http://www.katsurashareware.com/pgs/adm.html">AmorphousDiskMark</a>, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/blackmagic-disk-speed-test/id425264550?mt=12">BlackMagic Disk Speed Test</a> and plain old iostat whilst copying 30GB of files to and from the disk.</p>
<p>There will probably soon be a detailed blog post over on vxlabs.com about this, but I’ll give you the skinny here:</p>
<ul>
<li>It’s hard to get benchmarks right. BlackMagic gave wildly varying results depending on how many times I let it run its benchmark for example.</li>
<li>APFS’s software encryption looks like it causes a performance hit ranging from 5 to about 10%, with outliers in both directions.</li>
<li>Emacs can calculate over columns of data, for example from iostat’s standard out, using a simple <code>M-x calc-grab-from-rectangle</code> and <code>M-x calc-vector-mean</code>.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="brave-browser-and-the-basic-attention-token-bat-this-could-be-big-or-not-its-at-least-interesting">Brave browser and the Basic Attention Token (BAT): This could be big. Or not. It’s at least interesting.</h1>
<p><a href="https://brave.com">Brave</a> is a new(ish) browser also based on the Chrome engine.</p>
<p>I knew they were doing something with cryptocurrency, and paying or getting paid for the consumption of content and/or advertising, but I was, as you can see, quite vague on the details.</p>
<p>What I learned last week taking it for a quick spin is the following:</p>
<p>Brave out of the box is massively privacy-focused. Without installing any plugins, it blocks every single advertisement and tracking cookie known to humankind. It also automatically switches to secure SSL wherever that’s possible.</p>
<p>More interestingly, in Brave you can opt in to “<a href="https://brave.com/publishers/">Brave Payments</a>“, which looks like it might soon be renamed to Brave Rewards, but don’t quote me on that.</p>
<p>One part of this system, is that you as a user contribute a set amount of BAT tokens (these are tokens on the ethereum chain) per month. At the end of each month, Brave will pay out your tokens to the websites that you visited, based on the amount of time you spend on each site.</p>
<p>In this way, publishers can get recompensed for their content in hard cash, without having to resort to advertising. (It does look like Brave also supports the model where advertisers can pay, in BAT tokens of course, for your eyeball time.)</p>
<p>Brave already has 4 million monthly active users (MAU).</p>
<p>If they’re able to grow this user base, and get a significant portion to participate in the payment system, this could be a game changer. Imagine being able to pay your favourite content creators in this seamless way, and being able to switch off ads in  the process!</p>
<h1 id="runalyze-where-have-you-been-all-my-life">RunAlyze where have you been all my life?</h1>
<p>I publish my runs to Strava, as I have a bunch of friends there, and I like the idea of a social network where you have pay with a bucket of sweat before you’re allowed to say <em>anything</em>.</p>
<p>However, I was also relying on Strava to keep track of my shoe mileage. Recently, it started losing the miles I put on my Xero Genesis sandals (the most unforgiving shoes in the universe), and I was not able to coax the system into correctly tracking those terrible, terrible kilometres.</p>
<p>Because I use HealthFit to push my data to Strava, I took a look at some of its other endpoints and then, again extremely serendipitously, ran into:</p>
<p><a href="https://blog.runalyze.com">RUNALYZE</a></p>
<p>It’s a site made by two running nerds (and it <strong>really</strong> shows) from Germany.</p>
<p>It keeps track of my shoes (the goal of this… <em>exercise</em>, bad pun, sorry) but the authors have also implemented a bunch of metrics from academic papers, some metrics of their own, and they show tables of your data sliced and diced in many different ways ON ALL FOUR WALLS of their website.</p>
<p>&lt;Dr Evil voice&gt;It’s breathtaking.&lt;/Dr Evil voice&gt;</p>
<p>Anyways, if you’re a running nerd too, you should probably take a peek.</p>
<h1 id="fin">Fin</h1>
<p>See you soon brothers and sisters. I am grateful for our time together.</p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #149: I forgot to proof-read this.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/24/weekly-head-voices-149/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 20:49:20 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/07/24/weekly-head-voices-149/</guid><description> Part of the Sunday morning trail. Although I really enjoy these, I’m at my happiest running down antelope on the savannah. Antelope strictly-speaking not required, but those wide open plains on the other hand…
This, the one hundred and forty ninth edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covers the week from Monday July 16 to Sunday July 22 of the year 2018.
This week, we have apple watch running adventures, deep learning in production (finally), yet another focus tip and finally a youtube poetry reading.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_0420-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/07/IMG_0420-PANO-1024x318.jpg"
        
            alt="Part of the Sunday morning trail. Although I really enjoy these, I’m at my happiest running down antelope on the savannah.  Antelope strictly-speaking not required, but those wide open plains on the other hand…"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Part of the Sunday morning trail. Although I really enjoy these, I’m at my happiest running down antelope on the savannah.  Antelope strictly-speaking not required, but those wide open plains on the other hand…</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This, the one hundred and forty ninth edition of the Weekly Head Voices, covers the week from Monday July 16 to Sunday July 22 of the year 2018.</p>
<p>This week, we have apple watch running adventures, deep learning in production (finally), yet another focus tip and finally a youtube poetry reading.</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h1 id="the-apple-watch-vitality-and-you">The Apple Watch, Vitality and You</h1>
<p>On Monday, I became the owner of a brand new Apple Watch 3, FOR FREE(ish).</p>
<p>I feel that two points are worth mentioning:</p>
<ol>
<li>Having one’s work macbook unlock <em>automatically</em> as one prepares to put one’s hands on the keyboard, with a sweet little unlock sound emitting from one’s watch, is much more fun than I had expected.
<ul>
<li>Said watch has a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_S3">dual-core processor with 768MB of RAM and 16GB of flash, and a GPU</a>. That’s just crazy.
<ul>
<li>In 2003, <a href="/2003/10/05/first-thoughts-on-the-tungsten-e/">I had similar thoughts about the processing power of my Tungsten E PDA</a>, and all the way back in <a href="/2016/12/06/weekly-head-voices-113-science-and-creation/#devil-on-my-arm">2016 I was already laughing at 2003 me</a>. I should know better by now.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>One was looking forward to using third party running apps on the watch, such as iSmoothRun which does real-time reporting of cadence, which can be shown together with a number of other stats on a number of configurable screens a la Garmin . One has had to cancel these plans, because Vitality, the shadowy organisation responsible for the FOR FREE(ish) nature of the watch, only recognises runs submitted by the built-in Workouts app.
<ul>
<li>The September watchOS update will include runtime (haha) cadence, which is great. However, some technical system for the support of third party apps would have been even better. I’ll live.</li>
<li>Runs logged with the built-in Workouts app can be easily and automatically submitted to other platforms, such as Strava, where many of my running peeps hang out, and even to one’s own Dropbox in FIT format, with <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/za/app/healthfit/id1202650514?mt=8">the HealthFit iOS app</a>, a very reasonable once-off purchase.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="deeplearning-insidetm">DeepLearning Inside(tm)</h1>
<p>On Friday, we shipped a new version of the most important work project I am currently involved in.</p>
<p>Again I feel that two points are worth mentioning:</p>
<ol>
<li>We now also have deep learning, albeit a humble example, out in actual production. I was starting to feel a little left out. Anonymous shout-out (because top secret) to the team members who made this happen!</li>
<li>They say one should never deploy or ship on Friday. Because I come from the I-won’t-do-what-you-tell-me generation, I cut the final release on Friday evening <em>after</em> the traditional weekend-starter braai.
<ul>
<li>To be honest, this was only <em>necessary</em> because I had promised our client that we would release, and it was only <em>possible</em> because we have a fairly good test-suite, with end-to-end being most crucial in this specific scenario, and a checklist-style release procedure.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="sobsodsit-cipwob-fba">SoBSoDSiT-CIPWOB-FBA</h1>
<p>As part of my chaotic but ever-evolving constellation of systems for maintaining work focus, I have renamed the <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/#shorter-focus-blocks-work-better">shorter focus blocks approach</a> to the <em>short-but-specially-defined-so-that-completion-is-possible-within-one-block focus blocks approach</em> (SBSDSTCIPWOB-FBA).</p>
<p>This adds the incentive of a small but probable shot of dopamine at the end of the focus block, and sometimes even leads to its unwitting extension by the woefully undersized (not to mention super lazy) rider sometimes sitting atop my mental elephant.</p>
<p>It sometimes feels like I’m slowly reinventing GTD.</p>
<p>(This blog post is an emotional roller coaster ride for me. This is the first time I’m feeling something.)</p>
<p><a href="/2007/10/07/my-palmos-based-gtd-setup/">I used to be a fan of GTD</a> when I still believed that my function in life was to answer emails really quickly, and master multi-tasking.</p>
<p>Since then however, I’ve slowly had to come to the realisation that, at least in my case, the amount of email processed is more or less exactly inversely correlated to the actual value that I produce.</p>
<h1 id="the-impotence-of-proof-reading">The impotence of proof-reading</h1>
<p>The following poetry reading made various subsets of my neurons fire in extremely pleasant ways.</p>
<p>I hope that you experience similar effects. See you next time!</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OonDPGwAyfQ?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>