<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>email on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/email/</link><description>Recent content in email on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 10:06:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/email/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #203: Spiritual</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 10:06:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/</guid><description> Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&amp;rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&amp;rsquo;s magic.
Dear friends,
It brings me joy to meet you here again.
Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10 to Sunday September 6, 2020.
If I were in your shoes, I would hop skip and jump selectively over the hopefully not too unhelpfully titled headings.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="jonkershoek_magic_20200901.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/jonkershoek_magic_20200901_hu635092065b93855ef7cf383a4ee01019_1994691_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&amp;rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&amp;rsquo;s magic."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A tiny bit of Jonkershoek&rsquo;s beauty, thanks to Wim&rsquo;s magic.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>It brings me joy to meet you here again.</p>
<p>Due to an unintentionally longer than normal blog hiatus, this edition will
attempt to cover a substantial amount of temporal ground from Monday August 10
to Sunday September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>If I were in your shoes, I would hop skip and jump selectively over the
hopefully not too unhelpfully titled headings.</p>
<p>In order to reduce this wall of text somewhat, I have pre-emptively moved a
sub-section or two to the next edition of the WHV.</p>
<p><em>Dear Charl of the Future,</em></p>
<p><em>You have no choice. (also no free will haha) I am writing this for you, so you
better read every last bit.</em></p>
<p><em>I am watching you.</em> 👀</p>
<h2 id="i-m-sorry-but-it-really-is-just-quite-complicated">I&rsquo;m sorry, but it really is just quite complicated</h2>
<p>I would like to kick this off with the following cartoon by Wiley Miller, which
entered my information field of view via dr topol&rsquo;s tweet stream. (don&rsquo;t worry,
this came in via my rss reader. i have not returned to twitter.)</p>








<figure><a href="science_vs_everything_else.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/science_vs_everything_else_hu3aebbd24d40b7ab7614020c56d748aba_197920_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: science vs. everything else by wiley miller</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It is ironic that the people who get it, already got it, but that the people who
really should get it, won&rsquo;t get it.</p>
<p>As is the case with many of these efforts, i guess that the best we can hope
for is that some of those on the borders between the aforementioned two groups
might be gently encouraged to gravitate towards the light.</p>
<h3 id="the-giant-band-aid-phenomenon">the giant band-aid phenomenon</h3>
<p>Related to the cartoon above, it is quite interesting to me how often
well-meaning people desire to come up with a giant band-aid for any current
problem.</p>
<p>Climate change? Inequality? Surely if we just find a band-aid big
enough we can make the problem go away!</p>
<p>There really is no band-aid.</p>
<h2 id="on-the-minimum-unit-of-focus">On the minimum unit of focus</h2>
<p>Somewhere in week 34 i was struggling to wrap up a piece of programming work
that i had been struggling with for a few days, in-between meetings and a whole
smorgasbord of other modern interruptions.</p>
<p>Finally i decided to bust out the little focus tool that i shall not name here,
because that&rsquo;s not the point.</p>
<p>The point is rather that i created an interruption-free block of time and then
wrapped up the stupid programming problem decisively, there and then.</p>
<p>Relieved that it was finally done, I did feel stupid that it had taken me that
long to just shut off those damn interruptions.</p>
<p>The experience did remind me of the following cartoon by <a href="https://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/">the slightly
disgruntled scientist</a>. It describes <strong>extremely</strong> well how a single little
interruption can derail a whole constellation of mental models in an instant.</p>
<p>Click or tap to zoom in, or skip past if you know this:</p>








<figure><a href="ProgrammerInterrupted.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted_hu3267a53534c5d7f823d13c1b76e71025_414884_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/ProgrammerInterrupted.png"
            

         width="30%"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>I have found that the absolute minimum block of distraction-free time i need to
do reliably something worthwhile is about an hour.</p>
<p>A large part of my job is indeed handling the information that arrives via all
of the those pesky interruptions, but sometimes i wonder if there&rsquo;s not a
better way to reconcile these two facets.</p>
<p>Very much related to this phenomenon, is falling into the morning distraction
trap, something which is probably familiar to a number of you. (future charl,
you don&rsquo;t count.)</p>
<p>It goes like this: i arrive at work (or these days, i walk a few metres on from
the kitchen into the guest bedroom / home office), and then i start the day
with meetings, microsoft teams chats, and emails.</p>
<p>If I&rsquo;m not careful, I get stuck in this reactive mode, forgetting until far too
late in the day to eject from the reactive-jet for some of them juicy focus
hours.</p>
<p>#feelsbadman</p>
<p>Just this past week, I decided on Thursday and Friday to start work directly on
my main project, ignoring emails and chats and any other distractions until the
first stand-up meeting at 9:00.</p>
<p>Just priming my mind like this for slightly more than an hour was enough to
give the whole day a flavour of focus and intentionality.</p>
<p>It feels like I forget this lesson every other day.</p>
<p>How do you manage this?</p>
<h2 id="on-the-opposite-of-focus">On the opposite of focus</h2>
<p>Sort of inspired by <a href="https://youtu.be/0m3hGZvD-0s">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s deliberate scheduling of a shallow work
session</a> after the day&rsquo;s deep work, I was pleasantly surprised during a past few
evening sessions where I combined an entertaining DJ Set on the second screen
with some actual programming work on the main.</p>
<p>Somehow the fully intentional addition of distracting entertainment, and
importantly the <em>acceptance</em> that the work would necessarily be approached with
a leisurely attitude, I got a surprising amount of extra work done, and
experienced the whole session as relaxing.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to file this under &ldquo;101 stupid but effective tricks to fool your mind
into being more useful&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Let me know if you try this, or if you knew this all along and <em>that&rsquo;s</em> how you
manage everything so well!</p>
<p>P.S. <a href="https://lexfridman.com/podcast/">Lex Fridman&rsquo;s podcasts</a> are edifying and humanity-affirming. Try them if
you haven&rsquo;t yet.</p>
<h2 id="on-divide-and-conquer-for-the-email">On divide and conquer for the email</h2>
<p>Spontaneously in the night somewhere during the past weeks, I had the idea that
it was time to split my <a href="https://www.stonethree.com/">Stone Three</a> work email account from the rest of my
email empire (which is partially also work, because vxlabs, but not my main
job).</p>
<p>I did this because the account I use to manage everything, the <a href="/tags/fastmail/">fastmail one</a>,
was becoming far too chaotic.</p>
<p>(Back in the TU Delft days, an adventure that ended now almost 7 years ago, I
also used to sport an e-mail split.)</p>
<p>My perception now is that I&rsquo;m working against the idea of the whole being
greater than the sum of the parts, i.e. the whole chaos is perhaps worse than
the two smaller chaos explosions by themselves.</p>
<p>(That&rsquo;s a pretty convoluted way to think about &ldquo;divide and conquer&rdquo;, isn&rsquo;t it?)</p>
<p>Also, the dream of being able to search through all of my email and actually
finding stuff is not being realised.</p>
<p>Email searching these days is usually a last resort, because I have a pretty
good <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">personal knowledge management system</a>. It could also be that fastmail
search is not as clever as gmail search.</p>
<p>In the weeks since I did this split (my notes tell me this happened on Friday,
August 21, 2020 at around 8:30 in the morning), I have noticed that my Stone
Three email is now under control, while my personal email is slightly out of
control, which is an improvement.</p>
<p>I have noticed that I do in fact apply a whole different mode of cognition and
context to the handling of work email than I do to personal/work-ish email.</p>
<p>A further advantage is that I can now focus on mastering the way of life that
is called Outlook. The first artifact I have to show for this is a pretty
complicated blog post in the drafts folder that shows how you can link to
arbitrary outlook items (in the latest outlook) from anywhere, in my case of
course Emacs.</p>
<h2 id="life-progress-update">Life progress update</h2>
<p>During the past several weeks, I passed a birthday.</p>
<p>As one bestie remarked, I am now just past the halfway mark, at least by one
pretty optimistic estimate of the total duration of me.</p>
<p>Anyways, moving on&hellip;</p>
<p>I took the largest part of the day off to go run the in the mountains here in my
backyard.</p>
<p>The route that I took for the first time, and which caused a considerable
amount of enjoyment, could be described by Watsonia, Baboon traverse, Leopard
Loop, Caracal, Protea, Sugarbird.</p>
<p>Making time for outdoorsy activities on your birthday: Two WHV thumbs up, would
do again.</p>
<p>Thanks to the <a href="http://www.workoutdoors.net/">WorkOutDoors Apple Watch app</a>, which I bought two years ago but
have never used, I did not get lost like I usually do when attempting trail
runs.</p>
<p>The app displays brilliant vector maps on your watch, optionally overlaid with
GPX routes supplied by generous friends.</p>
<p>After the birthday run, I use it again on more trails (see photo at start of
post) to run almost like someone who actually possesses a sense of
direction.</p>
<p>Technological augmentation FTW!</p>
<h2 id="here-s-to-a-more-regular-return">Here&rsquo;s to a more regular return</h2>
<p>Thank you for working through this mishmash with me!</p>
<p>We are now caught up until Sunday, September 6, 2020.</p>
<p>At this stage, I would have preferred to post more coherent little posts more
often, but I seem to find myself in a loop of slightly too much busyness (and
other issues), which ironically is contributing to my need to write more, but
which is taking up so much time and so many mental cycles that blog-writing
opportunities are hard to create and make use of.</p>
<p>Anyways&hellip; at least the overfull post-pipeline fence has now been cleared.</p>
<p>Folks, I wish you equanimity, kindness and health.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next connection.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #175: Plaintext me.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 09:11:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/</guid><description> Good evening fellow humans.
This is Head Voice #37 reporting for duty. I have been instructed to perform retrospection on the period of time from Monday July 22 to Sunday July 28.
Due to the ongoing hibernation and consequent lack of interesting events to talk about, this should be short.
This delectable Fred &amp; Max Flat White was one of a quite few more enjoyed during life-affirming breakfast with a Very Flat Cat.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Good evening fellow humans.</p>
<p>This is Head Voice #37 reporting for duty. I have been instructed to perform
retrospection on the period of time from Monday July 22 to Sunday July 28.</p>
<p>Due to the ongoing hibernation and consequent lack of interesting events to
talk about, this should be short.</p>
<figure>
<a href="fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hub43ba565be6a358f8793e882864d5d02_2490114_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hub43ba565be6a358f8793e882864d5d02_2490114_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hub43ba565be6a358f8793e882864d5d02_2490114_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hub43ba565be6a358f8793e882864d5d02_2490114_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/30/weekly-head-voices-175-plaintext-me/fred_max_flatwhite_veryflatcat_hub43ba565be6a358f8793e882864d5d02_2490114_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
This delectable Fred & Max Flat White was one of a quite few more enjoyed
during life-affirming breakfast with a Very Flat Cat. (By the way, why didn't
any of you tell me that fried egg yolk slowly drenching the quinoa bed it lies
on is so amazing?!)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="im-stubbornly-doubling-down-on-plaintext-email">I&rsquo;m stubbornly doubling down on plaintext email.</h2>
<p>I spent a precious hour or two (or perhaps three, in which case I am ashamed)
performing experiments to try and understand how GMail, fastmail web,
thunderbird and the iOS mail.app encode quoting in HTML email replies.</p>
<p>The answer is that they all do it in subtly different ways&hellip;</p>
<p>The even more shocking answer is that since HTML email took over, people have
really just been winging it, and quite badly so.</p>
<p>To give you an idea, gmail adds explicit inline CSS <em>styling</em> to display the
vertical reply bar on the left, like some kind of <em>barbarian</em>.</p>
<p>WAT?!</p>
<p>Back when plaintext email was the only game in town, there were <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Posting_style">fairly strict
but effective guidelines</a> that
determined exactly how one could quote previous emails, up to any depth, when
crafting that thoughtful reply.</p>
<p>However, it seems that, thanks to Outlook and perhaps far more insidiously
Google&rsquo;s GMail, <em>many</em> people currently have no idea that a thing such as email
quoting with inline replies used to be a solved problem.</p>
<p>That is, until users mistakenly thought that badly chosen fonts with even more
badly chosen colours were more important than, you know, effective and
efficient written communication.</p>
<p>Although this battle is lost, this has only encouraged me to stick it to the
(HTML email) man, and double-down on my old-school plaintext emails.</p>
<p>If you receive a simple-looking email from me which sometimes wraps strangely,
you&rsquo;ll know why.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;d like join me, the new
<a href="https://useplaintext.email/">useplaintext.email</a> site is a good start!</p>
<h2 id="linux-on-the-thinkpad">Linux on the ThinkPad.</h2>
<p>I <em>thought</em> that the NVIDIA GPU being hard-wired to the external display
outputs on this <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad</a> meant that I would
never be able to run Linux with <em>dynamic</em> display connection.</p>
<p>Well it turns out I was wrong.</p>
<p>I slipped this weekend, and now the Linux partition is configured with Manjaro
Linux (a surprise to me too).</p>
<p>In short, ThinkPad consumes just over 5W at idle, because NVIDIA is only
switched on when necessary. I can switch it on for CUDA (for example to work
with neural networks that fit into the 4GB of VRAM), and I can switch it on
when I need to connect an external display.</p>
<p>All of this without having to reboot or even logout and back in again.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested, see the <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/28/manjaro-bumblebee-thinkpad-x1-extreme-2019/">vxlabs blog
post</a>
for all of the details.</p>
<h2 id="we-live-in-the-future">We live in the future.</h2>
<p>At the UMC Utrecht, two patients have received entirely patient-specific
3D-printed titanium spinal implants.</p>
<p>Thanks to this, the patients, one of whose spine had previously collapsed, are
still able to walk.</p>
<p>Read more in <a href="https://www.dutchnews.nl/news/2019/07/teenager-can-walk-again-thanks-to-dutch-3d-printed-spinal-implant/">this DutchNews
summary</a>,
or preferably <a href="https://www.volkskrant.nl/wetenschap/implantaten-uit-de-3d-printer-laten-utrechtse-patient-weer-lopen~bab3372e/">this Volkskrant
article</a>
if you can follow Dutch.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve embedded the Lancet video abstract for your convenience:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315"
src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/3gxiDo3ac0k" frameborder="0"
allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>This used to be the stuff of science fiction folks!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #173: I know.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 21:53:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/</guid><description> Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm still quite bad. Let&amp;rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:
Well hello there folks!
A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not have much to report on.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="helderberg_protea.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/helderberg_protea_hu74588f15139e031d0111d34ce33071f6_1906769_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
Taken on a run in the mountain, on a trail quite aptly called the protea. By
the way, although I have become slightly less terrible at running up hills, I'm
still quite bad.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go for a slightly less anxious start than the previous edition did:</p>
<p>Well hello there folks!</p>
<p>A week ago, I made a deliberate decision not to post a WHV, as I really did not
have much to report on.</p>
<p>However, it&rsquo;s funny how these things go. One week nothing&hellip; Then it&rsquo;s just a
single week later and there&rsquo;s almost a bit too much that I would like to talk
about.</p>
<p>It seems to have been a mix of more writing, but also just more doing.</p>
<p>So, looking back at the two weeks from Monday July 1 to Sunday July 14, 2019, I
would like to present the following notes.</p>
<h2 id="bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">Bullet List of Miscellany (BLoM).</h2>
<ul>
<li>GOU#1, age 13, is on a week-long school trip in a different time zone
(GMT+8). I am super happy that she can have this experience, but durnit, one
misses one&rsquo;s genetic offspring units dearly!</li>
<li>Remember that I told you about our <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#solar-powerrrrrrrr">solar inverter not talking to the
battery&rsquo;s BMS</a>?
Well, one small recommended firmware upgrade later, from 151507 to 151508,
and the whole system is completely down. Please cross your fingers, because
we&rsquo;ve tried <strong>everything</strong> else.</li>
<li>I regularly get accosted by off-leash dogs whilst running. There are
incredibly clear by-laws down here which absolutely forbid any dog ever being
off-leash in any public space which is not a designated off-leash zone. I
recently made the mistake (twice) of trying to explain this to the relevant
dog-owners. Well, dog-owners seem to be quite sadly under-endowed in the area
of introspective capability, but at least I&rsquo;m getting a lot better at
unprepared debates in public spaces. (Psychologists in the audience, help me
out here with any tips please!)</li>
<li>I really enjoyed <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/162-medical-intelligence/">this Sam Harris podcast with Eric
Topol</a>. <a href="https://www.scripps.edu/faculty/topol/">Eric
Topol</a> is a cardiologist and the
founder and director of the Scripps Research Translational Institute in the
US. Apart from the main topic of the discussion, namely Topol&rsquo;s
well-developed and articulated view of AI in medicine (well, his books on
this topic are quite influential, so there&rsquo;s that), I was struck and inspired
by the humble gentleness of this impressive intellect. Furthermore, although
we are not supposed to use twitter anymore (in some circles, it has been
dubbed &ldquo;road rage of the internet&rdquo;), <a href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol">Prof Topol&rsquo;s tweet
stream</a> is a shining example of how twitter
could be used more constructively.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="would-you-like-some-more-emacs-with-that-email">Would you like some more Emacs with that Email?</h2>
<p>During the past two weeks I published two blog posts on my nerd blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/03/send-queued-mails-in-background-with-mu4e/">Sending queued mails in the background with
mu4e.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/07/05/mbsync-vs-offlineimap-speed/">Is mbsync really faster than offlineimap? A
measurement.</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Based on these, you might come to the conclusion that I&rsquo;m processing email
inside of Emacs
<a href="/2014/05/24/weekly-head-voices-71-vote-for-the-future/">again</a>.</p>
<p>I can confirm that this is indeed the case.</p>
<p>Probably for a large part due to the popularity of google&rsquo;s gmail, the growth
of the rest of the email ecosystem seems to have been stunted to a significant
degree.</p>
<p>In this specific case, I am referring to the dearth of really good email
clients for Windows.</p>
<p>(By the way, Thunderbird, still my fallback, usually makes the top of any
Windows email client lists. However, if it weren&rsquo;t for GMail, Thunderbird
would probably also be miles better than it is today.)</p>
<p>After losing more hours than I could afford trying to find that perfect email
client (I would have settled for &ldquo;still has all of its own teeth&rdquo;), I realised
that I would just have to buckle down and get <a href="/tags/mu4e/">mu4e</a>, my favourite
Emacs email client, working well enough on Windows, which I currently <em>prefer</em>
(DID I JUST SAY THAT?!) due to my <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1E
baby</a>.</p>
<p>That was of course a whole different wormhole to get sucked into.</p>
<p>Well, more of those precious hours later, I have a Frankensteined concoction
consisting of Emacs running on the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL),
displaying to the Windows desktop via <a href="https://token2shell.com/x410/">X410</a>,
and opening email and orgmode attachments, and dired files, using the native
Windows handlers via an
<a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Xdg-utils#xdg-open">xdg-open</a> work-alike
I coded up in Python.</p>
<p>(I am planning to release my xdg-open clone along with a more detailed howto
blog post. Let me know if you would like advanced access.)</p>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. after all of that effort I am now back more or less to where I
started in 2014.</p>
<p>(To be honest, Emacs is near the top of my list of compounding activities. The
fact that it&rsquo;s back in my email workflow, combined with five years of
compounded Emacs skills, has resulted in further increased efficiency.)</p>
<h3 id="sticking-it-to-the-man-gmail-with-fastmail">Sticking it to the Man (GMail) with FastMail.</h3>
<p>Wrapping up that email workflow reconfiguration frenzy, I did spend some
minutes doing a quick survey of fastmail alternatives which might have email
servers somewhat closer to the Southern tip of Africa and hence shave off a few
seconds of latency.</p>
<p>I found nothing that came close in terms of features and price. Except for one
outage, <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">I&rsquo;ve been a really happy fastmail camper for the last three
years</a>.</p>
<p>All of that, together with the fact that gmail&rsquo;s continued dominance is
unhealthy for the world of email, convinced me to stick with fastmail for the
conceivable future.</p>
<h2 id="stone-three-healthcare-is-now-a-thing">Stone Three Healthcare is now a thing.</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.stonethree.com/healthcare/">Stone Three Healthcare</a>, until recently
a business unit within Stone Three Venture Technology, has now been officially
spun out.</p>
<p>In other words, S3HC is now a more-or-less independent company that will
henceforth have to create its own success.</p>
<p>As some of you know, this project has been cooking for a few years now.</p>
<p>We have a really great team, products with customers and a market, and a
respectable patch of runway.</p>
<p>There are worse ways for a startup to start up.</p>
<p>P.S. if you have any golden tips for startup dummies, I (and probably others)
would be super grateful if you could let &rsquo;em loose in the comments!</p>
<h2 id="always-be-compounding-the-side-project-edition">Always Be Compounding: The side-project edition.</h2>
<p>In the previous WHV, I <a href="/2019/06/30/weekly-head-voices-172-abc/#always-be-compounding">started going on about the principle of ABC, or Always Be
Compounding</a>.</p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been spending a great deal of mental cycles on finding more
ways to ABC.</p>
<p>Besides the more general examples I mentioned there, another method is to
design some long-running project that can function as a container for all of
the work that you&rsquo;ll have to do in any case.</p>
<p>A perhaps slightly flawed personal example is DeVIDE, an open source
visualization and image processing tool that started life somewhere in 2001,
<a href="/2003/12/19/the-visualisation-and-image-processing-platform-formerly-known-as-dscas3/">was renamed to DeVIDE at the end of
2003</a>,
open-sourced in 2007 and had its last release in 2012.</p>
<p>Although it did see some use after that, the project went into hibernation
(weeeelll&hellip;.) when I left academia.</p>
<p>My point is that, for about 10 years, I had a single technical <em>artifact</em> with
a name that became slowly better known (even if it was often by its alias &ldquo;Not
Responding&rdquo;), into which I could integrate all the other new work I was doing.</p>
<p>This enabled me to enjoy some of the advantages of compounding effort, in the
shape of DeVIDE, even although the work I was doing over the years necessarily
had to change.</p>
<p>(A really nice additional benefit was that some students sometimes found the
software useful! I do wish that that part could have continued for a little
longer.)</p>
<p>Setting aside my
<a href="/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/#a-strange-thing-happened-this-weekend">DeVIDE-nostalgia</a>
(and a bit of sadness) for a moment, I would like to apply some of this
learning to my current (and perhaps your) situation.</p>
<p>My idea would be to define a new side-project that can act as the slightly
longer-lived container for some of the smaller side-projects and learnings I
sometimes manage to spend time on.</p>
<p>It would have to be a technology / thematic fit for many of my other
side-projects. It would of course constitute a double-whammy if this
side-project had commercial potential.</p>
<p>Well, SURPRISE!</p>
<p>I do have at least one side-project that ticks a number of these boxes, and
could <em>potentially</em> serve as such a vehicle.</p>
<h3 id="aikno">AIKNO</h3>
<p>The side-project in question is called AIKNO, which is pronounced &ldquo;I know&rdquo;, but
which somehow expands to <em>AI organizational knowledge base</em>. Magic!</p>
<p>It eats all of your organization&rsquo;s emails for breakfast, and then uses
different methods, both algorithmic and crowd/team-sourced, to sort and
organize those emails and all of their attachments, and then makes those easily
and attractively (hey, data visualization!) accessible by that organization.</p>
<p>Think of it as an almost zero-effort always-up-to-date organizational knowledge
base.</p>
<p>Besides having slots for various machine learning and visualization techniques,
it fits nicely into my overgrown knowledge management hobby.</p>
<p>The first commit in the AIKNO repo was in November of 2017. Oof. The prototype
is able to import emails and attachments into its structured database, and
already does funky stuff with similarity searches and whatnot.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, it has also suffered from my regular technology stack
changes, and it&rsquo;s currently languishing while I write blog posts.</p>
<p>My previous failed side-project was called <em>TableTops</em>, or <em>Paradigm Desktop</em> by
the same people who dubbed DeVIDE &ldquo;Not Responding&rdquo;.</p>
<p>It was a free-form canvas / whiteboard tool for the free-form storage and
linking of <em>anything</em>. For example, it had relational data structures for
linking specific coordinates or regions in photos to centralised concepts, and
other interesting things that will probably never see the light of day.</p>
<p>It went through seven tech-stack-change-induced rewrites before being obsoleted
by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">my growing Emacs Orgmode powers</a>. (first
commit October 2013, last commit August 2017, now on the backest back
burner. the one that&rsquo;s not burning.)</p>
<p>I did learn a <em>tremendous</em> amount.</p>
<p>Maybe <em>that</em> is the real reason for doing these things?</p>
<h2 id="always-be-learning">Always Be Learning.</h2>
<p>Thanks for joining me on that trip folks.</p>
<p>I hope to see you soon. Until then, make an amazing time!</p>
<figure>
<a href="coffee_company_belgian_brownie.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/coffee_company_belgian_brownie_hu94fbd03beb887ab9d982d192632c7e69_2796738_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
100% amazing Belgian brownie and delectable flat white at the
Coffee Company on Lourensford this past weekend.
</figcaption>
</figure>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Deep Work: A welcome kick in the butt.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 08:31:25 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Based on this tweet by Enrico Bertini:
Little project I developed during the break looking back at 2016: &quot;Quantifying and Visualizing “Deep Work”&quot; https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q
&mdash; Enrico Bertini (@FILWD) January 3, 2017 &hellip; after having been successfully primed by this one some weeks ago (because locals!):
I also recommend https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf. I was skeptical, but it’s surprisingly good.
&mdash; Rian van der Merwe (@RianVDM) December 22, 2016 ]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Based on this tweet by <a href="http://enrico.bertini.io/">Enrico Bertini</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Little project I developed during the break looking back at 2016: &quot;Quantifying and Visualizing “Deep Work”&quot; <a href="https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q">https://t.co/s3d9Zn685Q</a></p>&mdash; Enrico Bertini (@FILWD) <a href="https://twitter.com/FILWD/status/816374094212067328?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 3, 2017</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; after having been successfully primed by this one some weeks ago (because locals!):</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I also recommend <a href="https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf">https://t.co/pILlM1OZpf</a>. I was skeptical, but it’s surprisingly good.</p>&mdash; Rian van der Merwe (@RianVDM) <a href="https://twitter.com/RianVDM/status/811955081201319936?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 22, 2016</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script
<p>&hellip; I bought and then devoured <a href="http://calnewport.com/books/deep-work/">Deep Work by Cal Newport</a> in two to three sessions.</p>
<p>As I munched through the book, I could almost physically sense the impact it was making on my thought patterns. I have since spent another Deep Work Pomodoro scanning through its pages again to make sure I did not miss anything.</p>
<p>Deep Work is at its heart Cal Newport&rsquo;s passionate argument for Deep Work in this extremely fragmented and highly connected information age. He defines Deep Work as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Professional activities performed in a state of distraction-free concentration that push your cognitive capabilities to their limit. These efforts create new value, improve your skill, and are hard to replicate.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Armed with a whole book full of stories and examples, he makes the case for eschewing <em>network tools</em> such as email, twitter, facebook, reddit, slack, whatsapp and so forth, instead dedicating as much of your time as possible to specific valuable outcomes. Yes, even after work, he makes the case for structuring your leisure activities in a similar fashion.</p>
<p>Although the book cites a number of studies, storytelling is its main persuasive tool. Whatever the case may be, I am utterly convinced.</p>
<p>I have resolved to put in a massive effort to get my Deep Work muscles back in top form.</p>
<p>I <em>knew</em> all of this stuff before. Heck, I&rsquo;ve even written on this blog about <a href="/2010/09/28/slow-e-mail-weekly-head-voices-32/">deprioritising communication to make room for important things</a>, <a href="/2010/08/08/workin-9-to-5-weekly-head-voices-28/">minimising interruptions and maximising concentration</a> and more (use the search Luke).</p>
<p>Somehow, maybe because of my transition to business, I&rsquo;ve slipped back into the illusion that you have to be connected all the time. On an average workday, I have email, two instances of slack, one instance of mattermost and whatsapp all open on my desktop, just in case I need to be reached. (To be clear, there&rsquo;s a great deal of messages that go through them every day, so it&rsquo;s not just me sitting there waiting in vain for someone, anyone, to please send me a message.)</p>
<p>Contrary to what I&rsquo;ve convinced myself of, these tools all detract significantly from my value production, both in terms of quality and throughput.</p>
<h2 id="structure-and-summary-of-the-book">Structure and summary of the book</h2>
<p>In Part 1, Newport tries to convince you of the value and necessity of Deep Work. The take-home message is that in order to excel at learning and at doing especially in the current interruption and distraction filled information age, we need unfragmented periods of distraction-free concentration, during which we push our cognition to the limit.</p>
<p>When I say it like that, it seems pretty obvious, doesn&rsquo;t it?</p>
<p>Phrased differently, the great fallacy of current times is that one can perform at one&rsquo;s best whilst being hyper-connected.</p>
<p>One can&rsquo;t.</p>
<p>Even worse, if we continue doing it this way, we&rsquo;ll start losing our ability to focus.</p>
<p>In Part 2, Newport gives high-level advice towards implementing Deep Work, packaged as the four rules of Deep Work:</p>
<ol>
<li>Work deeply: More about this further down.</li>
<li>Embrace boredom: Avoid busywork. That is, when you have a few minutes waiting in line somewhere, use the time to think instead of reaching for your smartphone.</li>
<li>Quit social media: EEEKE! Don&rsquo;t worry, it&rsquo;s slightly more complicated, but “manage social media” would not have had the same impact.)</li>
<li>Drain the shallows: Squeeze out as much as possible shallow work from your schedule. Focus work should be the default, distractions (shallow work) the exception.</li>
</ol>
<p>In terms of scheduling, rule #1 can be implemented in at least four different ways: monastic (isolate yourself almost permanently), bimodal (isolate yourself some of the time, but for significant periods, e.g. a month sabbatical), rhythmic (integrate into your schedule at set times during the day every day), journalistic (cultivate the ability to work deeply whenever you get a moment).</p>
<p>Of these, the rhythmic philosophy is probably the most practical for me and for most of the readers of this blog.</p>
<p>More practically, rule #1 (“Work Deeply”, remember?!) can be implemented using the following four disciplines:</p>
<ol>
<li>Focus on the wildly important: Make sure that you always know what the absolute most valuable thing is to work on.</li>
<li>Act on lead measures: Track your deep work by metrics that can be calculated <em>before</em> the output realises and not after, for example track your daily number of hours during which you were able to work deeply.</li>
<li>Keep a compelling scoreboard: Create some modality with which you can see clearly your daily deep work performance.</li>
<li>Create a cadence of accountability: Your daily or weekly routine should ensure that you review your work, and your deep work performance via the scoreboard for example.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="how-im-planning-to-apply-deep-work">How I&rsquo;m planning to apply Deep Work</h2>
<p>In the book Newport reiterates an important observation: We humans have limited stores of will power. These can and will get depleted through the day if we&rsquo;re not careful.</p>
<p>If it takes too much conscious effort to avoid distractions and to stay focused on the mentally taxing task at hand, our will power is depleted at some point and then our defences crumble.</p>
<p>Before you know it, you&rsquo;re stuck in that super satisfying (not) email, twitter, facebook, reddit, email, twitter, whatsapp, slack loop again.</p>
<p>An effective remedy for this is ritualization.</p>
<p>This does not mean that you have to get out the old Ouija board. Rather, it means that you should develop “routines and rituals to your working life designed to minimize the amount of your limited willpower necessary to transition into and maintain a state of unbroken concentration”.</p>
<p>Fortunately, because of a choice I made in 2013, my work already involves spending longer periods reading, thinking and programming. Now I only need to ensure that these periods are as deep as possible, which means eliminating distractions and practising as intensively as possible focusing on that One Really Important Thing.</p>
<p>I will eliminate distractions by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Using the pomodoro method (as I&rsquo;ve been doing all this time, just badly).</li>
<li>Extending the length of the 25 minute pomodoro. If I&rsquo;m in the deep work flow, I&rsquo;ll continue past the 25 minute alarm. A longer break can be taken later.</li>
<li>Activating my phone&rsquo;s no distraction mode during pomodori. Only phone calls get through, nothing else.</li>
<li>Killing my email app and all browser tabs that have to do with real-time communication (slack, mattermost, whatsapp, and so on).</li>
<li>Just in case, pasting a list of time-wasting site hostnames into my uBlock Origin&rsquo;s “My Filters” list.</li>
</ul>
<p>Besides that, I am recording deep work by prepending one of D0, D1, … D5 to the mytomatoes.com pomodoro description, corresponding to the spectrum from shallow to most deep work.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="http://www.veronikach.com/">veronikach.com</a>, I am using <a href="https://www.focusatwill.com/">focus@will</a> which helps tremendously with my concentration in the sometimes busy office.</p>
<p>Newport explains that most people can manage a maximum of four hours per day of truly deep work. Furthermore, for many people, it is most effective to schedule creative and deep work for the morning, and shallow work (email, admin, meetings etc.) for the afternoon. For a longer time I have been following the guideline of scheduling meetings for the afternoon, so now I&rsquo;ll strengthen that by trying to get my deep work done in the morning, leaving shallow work for the afternoon as far as possible.</p>
<p>Finally, I think that probably the most important advice here is to practise, practise and then practise some more.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This could very well be due to my own bias, but if I had to describe Deep Work as compactly as possible, I would have to say that it comes down to “mindful action”.</p>
<p>It might sound like a contradiction in terms (mindfulness is the practice of being, amongst other things), but I am referring to the practice of being fully connected to and focused on the current moment.</p>
<p>With Deep Work, one practises connecting fully to and focusing on the current endeavour, thus greatly enriching that experience and the output that it generates.</p>
<p>Thank you, Cal Newport, for this very welcome kick in the butt.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #71: Vote for the future.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/05/24/weekly-head-voices-71-vote-for-the-future/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2014 20:27:40 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/05/24/weekly-head-voices-71-vote-for-the-future/</guid><description> On Wednesday May 7, together with just over 18 million other South Africans, I voted. Afterwards, my thumb looked like this: POWER THUMB!
… and the rest of me felt like a million bucks!
Some complained about the outcome. I think we’re moving, albeit slowly, in the direction of a healthy democracy. Here are this year’s results, and here are 2009’s results. The opposition has been growing (slowly) at a national level.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>On Wednesday May 7, together with just over 18 million other South Africans, I voted. Afterwards, my thumb looked like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/voting_thumb.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/voting_thumb.jpg"
        
            alt="POWER THUMB!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>POWER THUMB!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>… and the rest of me felt <strong>like a million bucks</strong>!</p>
<p>Some complained about the outcome. I think we’re moving, albeit slowly, in the direction of a healthy democracy. Here are <a href="http://www.news24.com/Elections/results">this year’s results</a>, and here are <a href="http://www.news24.com/Elections/results#year=2009">2009’s results</a>. The opposition has been growing (slowly) at a national level. Interestingly, in Gauteng, smallest province with all of the money and power, the opposition is making similar progress.</p>
<p>Late to the party as per usual, I discovered <a href="http://vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a>, a fantastic command-line tool to create, use and destroy virtual machines AT A WHIM. I was so happy with this that I created <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://youtu.be/sY0wNgTpEOg" title="vagrant screencast">this screencast</a>, which has the added advantage of being an effective component of insomnia treatment. (Yes, I do know about and have even played with Docker. For what I’m doing now (deploying multiple self-contained servers on on-premises servers without direct access), vagrant+virtualbox fits better.)</p>
<p>On the topic of nerdy software, let’s turn the dial to 11. I’ve started using emacs 24 with <a href="http://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/mu4e.html">mu4e</a> as my main email client now. It looks like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/cpbotha-mu4e-screenie.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/cpbotha-mu4e-screenie.png"
        
            alt="mu4e screenshot with nvpy search active"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>mu4e screenshot with nvpy search active</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>After leaving GMail, I made do for a while with Thunderbird, but wasn’t really happy with it. (It’s really an awesome email client, but my inner nerd wanted more.) I can honestly say that I’m in email heaven at the moment. My 68 thousand email archive is locally mirrored with <a href="http://offlineimap.org/">offlineimap 0.6.5</a>. mu4e in Emacs is able to perform search requests through the whole archive in milliseconds. It makes GMail seem positively snail-like in comparison. In addition, I can use my crappy elisp-fu to make it do the most silly things with the user interface and my email. Oh yes, and <a href="http://slinky.imukuppi.org/zenburnpage/">zenburn</a>. Gaaaaaaaaaaah…</p>
<p>Completely accidentally, I saw Star Trek Into Darkness on Netflix the other night (no, we don’t have Netflix over here, really) and was completely BLOWN AWAY. Benedict Cumberbatch as Khan was an awe-inspiring movie villain. According to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khan_Noonien_Singh">the Wikipedia page on Khan Noonien Singh</a> (recurring villain in the Star Trek universe), Jonathan Romney of The Independent had the following to say about Cumberbatch’s voice:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>[It was] so sepulchrally resonant that it could have been synthesised from the combined timbres of Ian McKellen, Patrick Stewart and Alan Rickman holding an elocution contest down a well.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Dang. If you’ve seen the movie, you’ll know what he’s talking about.</p>
<p>Just in case you thought that we didn’t live in the future, have a look at this live video stream of the Earth, taken by the cameras of the International Space Station, which is only floating 422km above the Earth’s surface:</p>
<iframe frameborder="0" height="302" scrolling="no" src="http://www.ustream.tv/embed/17074538?v=3&amp;wmode=direct" style="border: 0px none transparent;" width="480"></iframe>
<p>(read more <a href="http://www.ustream.tv/channel/iss-hdev-payload">here</a>)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Please update your email and RSS subscriptions (cpbotha.net)</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2012/12/24/please-update-your-email-and-rss-subscriptions-cpbotha-net/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 13:56:49 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2012/12/24/please-update-your-email-and-rss-subscriptions-cpbotha-net/</guid><description> Dear readers,
I will soon be starting a new life adventure. In fact, maybe even two of them. Hence, there is a significant probability that this weblog will again be updated more frequently in 2013.
Also, I have just changed the email and RSS subscription system:
If you were subscribed via email, please subscribe anew via the subscribe button to the right. If you still receive emails from feedburner concerning this blog, please unsubscribe using the instructions in those emails.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Dear readers,</p>
<p>I will soon be starting a new life adventure. In fact, maybe even two of
them. Hence, there is a significant probability that this weblog will again be
updated more frequently in 2013.</p>
<p>Also, I have just changed the email and RSS subscription system:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you were subscribed via email, please subscribe anew via the subscribe
button to the right. If you still receive emails from feedburner concerning
this blog, please unsubscribe using the instructions in those emails. The
idea is to stop using the feedburner email subscription (which was active
for the past few years) and to start using wordpress.com for this (the new
system).</li>
<li>If you were subscribed via RSS reader, double check that your feed address
is <a href="http://cpbotha.net/feed">http://cpbotha.net/feed</a> and NOT anything to do with feedburner
anymore. The feedburner feed should redirect to my own feed in any case.</li>
</ul>
<p>I hope that you have a fabulous vacation, and a happy and healthy 2013! I look
forward to seeing you then.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>