<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>table mountain on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/table-mountain/</link><description>Recent content in table mountain on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 15:04:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/table-mountain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #211: Table Mountain Run(ish)</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 15:04:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/</guid><description> Welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices friends!
These ones, the two hundred and eleventh (haha, remember at school you always wondered if anyone would ever really need to be able to write out numbers&amp;hellip; IT WAS ALL FOR ME) edition, will hopefully be talking more or less coherently about events that took place during the two weeks from Monday November 23 to Sunday December 6 of the year 2020.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back to the Weekly Head Voices friends!</p>
<p>These ones, the two hundred and eleventh (haha, remember at school you always
wondered if anyone would ever really need to be able to write out numbers&hellip; IT
WAS ALL FOR ME) edition, will hopefully be talking more or less coherently
about events that took place during the two weeks from Monday November 23 to
Sunday December 6 of the year 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="table-mountain-20201204-pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/table-mountain-20201204-pano_huce60cc94a24f6cf5ce5bfc6ff21aad43_2042658_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Not the worst spot to eat one&amp;rsquo;s peanut butter sandwiches"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Not the worst spot to eat one&rsquo;s peanut butter sandwiches</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">Wetware checklist to bootstrap your software checklist</h2>
<p>My <a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/#daily-review">daily review</a> routine has been taking quite a beating.</p>
<p>The busier it gets, the more easily I somehow skip my whole daily review in the
morning thinking that I can better invest that time into just jumping on the
most urgent things first.</p>
<p>This is of course one of the stupidest things I can do at that point.</p>
<p>It doesn&rsquo;t help that the daily review contains quite a number of points I have
to take care of every morning.</p>
<p>So, what does one do to help sticking to your morning daily review habit?</p>
<p>Logically, one creates yet another, but this time smaller and hopefully more
robust, habit that triggers the larger habit!</p>
<p>(In the end, it&rsquo;s turtles all the way down in any case.)</p>
<p>The one redeeming factor in my morning routine has been the increasing
regularity of meditation exercise. (Thanks PK for putting me back on that
horse, or should I say <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/#shorter-focus-blocks-work-better">elephant</a>, and thanks to Sam Harris and his Waking Up
app.)</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;ve now added to my system is a smaller checklist with three items on it:</p>
<ol>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> meditation</li>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> deep reading</li>
<li><input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> planning: review + task setting</li>
</ol>
<p>The difference is that this checkpoint now lives in my brain, and is much
harder to side-step. Also, because of the firmly embedded meditation kernel,
there&rsquo;s a bit of momentum to help me move on to items 2 and 3.</p>
<p>I sneaked in item 2, because reading is basically cheap but really powerful
cybernetic upgrades for normal humans, and I found that it nicely completes
this 30 minutes (or so) of quite time in the morning before I start with work.</p>
<p>So far, this small addition to my firmware has made quite a positive impact,
although I have to admit that AoC (see further down) is temporarily interfering
with items 2 and/or 3.</p>
<p>Oh well, one just has to keep on keeping on.</p>
<h2 id="someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet-part-972387">Someone is wrong on the internet, part 972387</h2>
<p>Some of you (does 2 out of my total of 5 readers qualify as &ldquo;some of you&rdquo;,
relatively speaking?) will remember that I sometimes have a fraught
relationship with people being wrong on the internet, or you could just look up
<a href="/2014/07/01/weekly-head-voices-76-someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet/">WHV #76 to read about a previous episode</a>.</p>
<p>Most recently, I was again trying spectacularly unsuccessfully to avoid
twitter, when I ran into a thread where people were arguing about wearing
facemasks or not in these times.</p>
<p>My plan was to pull myself away from my phone, then throw the phone into the
fire, and then start the BBQ, but unfortunately one of the persons who was
arguing on the wrong side carries the same name as I do.</p>
<p>Although I am the <strong>one true Charl Botha</strong>, as is confirmed by the world&rsquo;s
premier reference on everything Charl Botha, namely the website <a href="https://charlbotha.com/">charlbotha.com</a>,
I was still worried that someone somewhere might confuse me with the third-rate
Charl Botha who was putting his lack of humanity on display.</p>
<p>My initial reaction was to go in there with all of my verbal guns blazing in
order to correct the poor sod, and to ensure that people would see there were
more Charls, some of which were not <em>as</em> bad, but fortunately some of the
psychology I have been absorbing from the literature kicked in on time and I
managed to limit my reply tweet to the fact that 1) I was in fact the real
Charl Botha (the one with a brain), and 2) that I thought one should wear a
mask because it&rsquo;s kind to other humans.</p>
<p>This made me think about the observation that mask deniers would always believe
that there were holes in the science of mask-wearing, when the most important
consideration comes down to the fact that even if mask-wearing helped your
fellow humans possibly only a little bit, it&rsquo;s already the kind thing to do.</p>
<p>After that, I made the following tweet to summarise my thinking on this topic:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Folks, remember that
of the 14 mask types tested in <a
href="https://t.co/BrQ6cpCnkk">https://t.co/BrQ6cpCnkk</a> (sensitive to
droplet size all the way down to 0.5um), 13 of them reduced droplet
transmission relative to no mask. SO: Be kind. Wear a multi-layer mask, reduce
droplets, help your fellow humans. <a
href="https://t.co/COyrdksV9K">pic.twitter.com/COyrdksV9K</a></p>&mdash; Charl
Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a
href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1332014932481732608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November
26, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>What I learned from this would-be altercation, is that it&rsquo;s better for me to
focus my someone-is-wrong-on-the-internet rage into something that&rsquo;s more
constructive:</p>
<p>Strip the issue down as far as you can. Inject information. Combine that with
the desire that many humans share for a society where we can all just get
along.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s probably still not going to work, but just maybe, it&rsquo;ll cause less trouble
and result in a little bit more goodwill, and who knows where that may lead?</p>
<p>P.S. On the topic of mask-wearing: Even if there were no COVID-19, don&rsquo;t you
think we&rsquo;d all be a little better of if the wearing of good masks became the
norm?</p>
<p>There are indications that <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/flu-season-never-came-to-the-southern-hemisphere1/">mask-wearing and physical distancing basically
stopped flu season in the Southern Hemisphere</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Never in my 40-year career have we ever seen rates &hellip; so low</p>
<p>&ndash; Greg Poland, influenza expert at the Mayo Clinic</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="advent-of-code-2020">Advent of Code 2020</h2>
<p>Thanks to this tweet by <a href="https://twitter.com/RameezKhanSA">@RameezKhanSA</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My pledge this year is
to do the <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/AdventOfCode?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#AdventOfCode</a>
in <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Clojure?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Clojure</a>. Looking
forward to it. Already started doing some of last years challenges. Want to
keep it simple. No Leiningen just a plain deps.edn.</p>&mdash; Rameez
(@RameezKhanSA) <a
href="https://twitter.com/RameezKhanSA/status/1332692669190074370?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">November
28, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>&hellip; I am taking part, for the first time, in <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">the Advent of Code</a>!</p>
<p>Nerds from the world over get a new two-part programming puzzle every day at 5
AM UTC, from December 1 to December 25, for a total of 50 puzzles.</p>
<p>The idea is that said nerds use any programming language, or combination of
programming languages, to solve the puzzles and enter the answers on the AoC
website.</p>
<p>The quickest nerds, the ones who manage to solve these puzzles in an amazing
minute or three, earn a highly-coveted place on the <a href="https://adventofcode.com/2020/leaderboard">leaderboard</a>.</p>
<p>Just like Rameez, I wanted to use the AoC to get to know a programming language
better, although in my case that language is Nim.</p>
<p>So far, this has been a great deal of fun!</p>
<p>To my non-programmer friends: Solving puzzles is like concentrated cat nip to
programmers. In the case of AoC, you get unadulterated puzzle solving, and none
of the other complications of writing production software.</p>
<p>Besides the fun, Nim <em>really</em> shines at this. As I mentioned in <a href="/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/#save-image-from-clipboard">the previous
WHV</a>, Nim somehow manages to combine the expressivity and development velocity
of Python, with a great dollop of Python&rsquo;s famed batteries-included, with close
to the metal performance.</p>
<p>(My brain is currently spending background cycles figuring out if I could
somehow use this in a product.)</p>
<p>I am sort of expecting to drop out eventually, because, based on past years,
it&rsquo;s going to take up an increasing amount of time.</p>
<p>However, although I&rsquo;m already happy with what I have (day 6&rsquo;s puzzles completed
on Sunday December 6, ostensibly the end of this WHV&rsquo;s window of reality), I
would be really chuffed reaching the double digits!</p>
<p><em>Narrator: He ended up reaching the double digits.</em></p>
<h2 id="table-mountain-run--ish--2020">Table Mountain Run(ish) 2020</h2>
<p>We thought we were going to do a trail run up Skeleton Gorge.</p>
<p>Well, if one is us, one does not simply run up Skeleton Gorge. Instead, one
huffs and one puffs, for about a kilometre of ascent. It is a substantial
amount of huffing and puffing.</p>
<p>We did get to run on top of the mountain, from the beach at the top of Skeleton
Gorge (yes, there&rsquo;s a beach), to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maclear%27s%5FBeacon">Maclear&rsquo;s Beacon</a>, which I&rsquo;ve now learned was
used in the calculation of the curvature of he Earth, to the old cable station,
past the reservoirs to end up walking really slowly back down Nursery Gorge.</p>
<p>It was an interesting observation that although I found parts of the route hard
and sometimes maybe even a little unpleasant (coming down Nursery Gorge&hellip;)
whilst in the thick of things, the whole memory of the experience started
transmogrifying into <em>wonderful</em> verging on <em>magical</em> extremely soon after we
had reached the finish.</p>
<p>12/10 would do again, but next time a more gradual descent please!</p>
<h2 id="hi-mom">Hi mom</h2>
<p>My mom has now seen three quarters of a century.</p>
<p>I am happy to report that she is as fit as a fiddle. Genetics and some really
great habits are a really solid combination.</p>
<p>Importantly, we are truly fortunate to count her as an integral part of our
household.</p>
<p>(Them is some big words for: We have so much fun together! Our GOUs, who are
also her GOUs, will probably never forget these stories with their Oma.)</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s to the next quarter century!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve convinced her of the great business opportunity of publishing a book at
100 with tips and tricks for other (aspirant) centenarians, so she really needs
to remain as sharp and as fit as she is today!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #114: So you know what I did last summer.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 07:17:10 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/</guid><description> WELL HELLO THERE FRIENDS FROM THE BLOGOSPHERE!
It’s definitely time to get out a Weekly Head Voices, so that we can all feel nicely up to date. This post covers the period from Monday December 5, 2016 to Sunday January 15, 2017, which is ever so slightly *cough* later than average.
My excuse is: SUMMER HOLIDAY.
If you have not yet read my 2016 to 2017 transition post, this is a gentle reminder to make some time to do so.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>WELL HELLO THERE FRIENDS FROM THE BLOGOSPHERE!</p>
<p>It’s definitely time to get out a Weekly Head Voices, so that we can all feel nicely up to date. This post covers the period from Monday December 5, 2016 to Sunday January 15, 2017, which is ever so slightly *cough* later than average.</p>
<p>My excuse is: SUMMER HOLIDAY.</p>
<p>If you have not yet read <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">my 2016 to 2017 transition post</a>, this is a gentle reminder to make some time to do so. There’s some backyard philosophy in that post that you might find useful.</p>
<p><em>(The main reason for writing this post is to satisfy my NO-GAPS-BETWEEN-WEEKLY-HEAD-VOICES-DAMNIT OCD. I’ve added pretty pictures to help us get through it.</em></p>
<p><em>Godspeed fellow traveller!__)</em></p>
<h1 id="the-holiday-starts">The holiday starts</h1>
<p>Below is a photo I have quite surprisingly titled “A scene with a beach, the sea and some fluffy clouds in the brilliant blue sky”. The photo was taken on the beach at Boggomsbaai, a really small sea-side village on the East coast where we spent the first few days of our holiday.</p>
<p>Up ahead you can see the bustling metropole (well, it has one really expensive minimarket and an impressive gate) of Vleesbaai.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161210_1712298.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161210_1712298-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Boggomsbaai beach. Vleesbaai in the distance. This is a really lovely run."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Boggomsbaai beach. Vleesbaai in the distance. This is a really lovely run.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<h1 id="head-voices-review-surprise">Head Voices Review. SURPRISE!</h1>
<p>After the truly disappointing <a href="/2016/12/20/review-awei-a990-bl-wireless-sport-bluetooth-earphones-avoid/">final death of my Awei bluetooth headphones</a> whilst running on that very beach, I acquired the Samsung Level Link, a tiny bluetooth transceiver which can turn any old set of cheap wired earphones into bluetooth earphones! It looks like this:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/samsung_level_link_1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/samsung_level_link_1-1024x852.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>After five or six runs with this device of trouble-free music listening whilst running (Flume’s Skin was the business until recently, but I’ve just switched to the Tron Legacy soundtrack by Daft Punk which I’m enjoying, although I’m missing some of the Underworld-esque dancing in the summer afternoon sunset feels; THEM FEELS), the <strong>Head Voices Review</strong> (we’re baaaa-aaaaack!) is currently considering the following <em>initial review</em>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Samsung Level Link: AWESOME.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="surfing">Surfing</h1>
<p>Shortly before Christmas, some of our Dutch besties arrived for a good old fashioned swap-the-Dutch-winter-for-some-guilt-free-South-African-summer shenanigans.</p>
<p>It’s a treat being able to show visitors from our other home around our old and now new again home. This often makes me do things which I should have done a long time ago but kept on postponing due to less important matters getting in the way.</p>
<p>One such thing is taking surfing lessons.</p>
<p>Funny thing is, there’s a brilliant surfing school (<a href="http://www.surfschools.co.za/">Son in Strand</a>, in case you were wondering) which is just a 15 minute drive away.</p>
<p>Our instructor was fabulous, and we are now all surfers as you can see:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/windowlicker_takes_surfing_lessons.jpeg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/windowlicker_takes_surfing_lessons-1024x768.jpeg"
        
            alt="You can see by my hands doing a strange mix of sign of the horns and the shaka sign that I still have too much metal in me. Faces of the innocent have been evil-ised. Windowlicker. Respect it."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>You can see by my hands doing a strange mix of sign of the horns and the shaka sign that I still have too much metal in me. Faces of the innocent have been evil-ised. Windowlicker. Respect it.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<h1 id="getting-high">Getting high</h1>
<p>Another favourite local pastime is getting high with friends. Below is a picture of one such occasion. We were only moderately high, in preparation for another planned expedition described further down, but the views were beautiful nonetheless.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/gordon_rock_from_bretagne_rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/gordon_rock_from_bretagne_rock-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Gordon Rock as seen from the middle part of Bretagne Rock in Paarl. The black blob in the middle is GOU#1 practising her weird stealth mutation."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Gordon Rock as seen from the middle part of Bretagne Rock in Paarl. The black blob in the middle is GOU#1 practising her weird stealth mutation.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>At this point I feel it is mention-worthy that a lion ate my hat later that day. Literally.</p>
<div class="gallery galleryid-2727 gallery-columns-2 gallery-size-medium" data-carousel-extra='{"blog_id":1,"permalink":"https:\/\/cpbotha.net\/2017\/01\/20\/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer\/"}' id="gallery-5">
<figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon landscape">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-5" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/my_hat_in_danger.jpg" title=""><img alt="" aria-describedby="gallery-5-2757" class="attachment-medium size-medium" data-attachment-id="2757" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"2.2","credit":"","camera":"PRIV","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1482938300","copyright":"","focal_length":"4.75","iso":"50","shutter_speed":"0.00060606060606061","title":"","orientation":"0"}' data-image-title="my_hat_in_danger" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/my_hat_in_danger-1024x790.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/my_hat_in_danger-300x232.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/my_hat_in_danger.jpg" data-orig-size="2296,1772" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/my_hat_in_danger/" height="232" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/my_hat_in_danger-300x232.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/my_hat_in_danger-300x232.jpg 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/my_hat_in_danger-768x593.jpg 768w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/my_hat_in_danger-1024x790.jpg 1024w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/my_hat_in_danger-1200x926.jpg 1200w" width="300"/></a>
</div><figcaption class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-5-2757"> My hat thought it was safe there in the corner. </figcaption></figure><figure class="gallery-item">
<div class="gallery-icon landscape">
<a class="rl-gallery-link" data-rel="lightbox-gallery-5" data-rl_caption="" data-rl_title="" href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/the_lion_ate_my_hat.jpg" title=""><img alt="" aria-describedby="gallery-5-2758" class="attachment-medium size-medium" data-attachment-id="2758" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-description="" data-image-meta='{"aperture":"2.2","credit":"","camera":"PRIV","caption":"","created_timestamp":"1482940221","copyright":"","focal_length":"4.75","iso":"50","shutter_speed":"0.00026136957658129","title":"","orientation":"0"}' data-image-title="the_lion_ate_my_hat" data-large-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/the_lion_ate_my_hat-1024x746.jpg" data-medium-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/the_lion_ate_my_hat-300x219.jpg" data-orig-file="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/the_lion_ate_my_hat.jpg" data-orig-size="1932,1408" data-permalink="https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/20/weekly-head-voices-114-so-you-know-what-i-did-last-summer/the_lion_ate_my_hat/" height="219" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 85vw, 300px" src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/the_lion_ate_my_hat-300x219.jpg" srcset="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/the_lion_ate_my_hat-300x219.jpg 300w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/the_lion_ate_my_hat-768x560.jpg 768w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/the_lion_ate_my_hat-1024x746.jpg 1024w, https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/the_lion_ate_my_hat-1200x875.jpg 1200w" width="300"/></a>
</div><figcaption class="wp-caption-text gallery-caption" id="gallery-5-2758"> I’m not sure what the lion thought at this point. </figcaption></figure>
</div>
<p>That other planned expedition I mentioned was an absolutely brilliant hike to the top of Table Mountain via <a href="http://www.southafrica.net/za/en/articles/entry/article-platteklip-gorge-hike">Platteklip Gorge</a>, also known as Platties around these parts.</p>
<p>Platties is the steepest (and probably quickest, if you’re fit enough) walking route up Table Mountain. We were at the starting point before 8 AM in the morning to avoid the morning heat, but it was already quite hot (probably about 25+, it was 30+ later).</p>
<p>The walk was exhilarating (I could almost hear my mitochondria gnashing their teeth), and the views from the top textbook-spectacular:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama-1024x325.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Shortly after having arrived at the top, I saw a man wearing only shorts who had sort of just ran up the mountain barefoot.</p>
<p>He did not rest, instead choosing to circle around a bush at the top and going straight down again.</p>
<p>Still barefoot.</p>
<p>Slap-slap-slap, I could hear his feet hit the rocks.</p>
<h1 id="the-beach">The Beach</h1>
<p>Taking a trip along the photogenic coast-hugging <a href="http://www.mountainpassessouthafrica.co.za/find-a-pass/western-cape/item/95-clarence-drive,-gordons-bay.html">Clarence Drive</a>, we stopped to pay a visit to Dappat se Gat, a sort-of-secret beach.</p>
<p>Once you wade through all the trash from the side of the road :( and cross over a bunch of rocks back in the direction of Gordon’s bay, you find yourself on a beautiful secluded beach with a cave or two.</p>
<p>One of the photos I took came out with suitably interesting shading:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_1857389.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_1857389-1024x768.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>It was hard to ignore the extreme hipness of the young people lounging and playing on the beach as we tried but failed to blend in.</p>
<p>After a short hike (with the little ‘uns) up Leopard’s Kloof in Betty’s Bay a few days later, we were rewarded by scenes of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disa_uniflora">Disa Uniflora</a>, an orchid which is exceptionally exclusive to our little corner of the planet.</p>
<p>By the power of the internets, I present you with new, more grainy photos of this pretty flower growing peacefully right next to a waterfall:</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161231_1227116-1-e1484856373330.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161231_1227116-1-e1484856373330-768x1024.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>In sharp contrast to last year when I welcomed the new year from the comfort of my bed and a book (hey man, some of us were gestating!), this year a significant number of us entered 2017 in Light Party Mode.</p>
<p>In fact, as the clock struck 00:00, we found ourselves on a rock formation in the sea, in the dark, with waves crashing around us. Pretty neat now that I think about it.</p>
<p>That reminds me, I did see for the first time fully <strong>bioluminescent waves</strong>! As each wave broke, the foam had a distinct green light. The fact that we were not able to film this (not enough photons) only served to make it more magical.</p>
<p>During the day we <em>were</em> able to try out them new-fangled smartphone high speed video functions, yielding pretty slow motion captures of crashing waves, such as this one:</p>
<div class="wp-video" style="width: 840px;">
<video class="wp-video-shortcode" controls="controls" height="473" id="video-2727-2" preload="metadata" width="840"><source src="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/slow_wave.mp4?_=2" type="video/mp4"/><a href="https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/slow_wave.mp4">https://cpbotha.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/slow_wave.mp4</a></video>
</div>
<h1 id="the-holiday-ends">The holiday ends</h1>
<p>For the last few work weeks of 2016, I could not help but notice that it was time for a vacation. I had to apply substantial amounts of raw will power (that is, buckling down, hard) every day to maintain my usual levels of production.</p>
<p>This vacation has been wonderful in the sense of causing total brain switch-off from day one. The surroundings definitely played a role in this, but for a large part I think it was due to the active holiday programme we pursued with our friends.</p>
<p>This, and previous experiences, further strengthen the observation that <strong>true rest and mental refreshment can be better accomplished by running up and down mountains, swimming in the sea and being generally really busy taking part in new experiences</strong>, rather than, you know, actually resting.</p>
<p>However, even after this holiday’s mental rejuvenation and renewed energy, I was still not completely happy with the (admittedly less than before the vacation) amount of will power that was required during the first days of work.</p>
<p>I remembered this to have been much easier in the old days.</p>
<p>Serendipitously, I read and more or less immediately <a href="/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">absorbed Cal Newport’s Deep Work into my atoms</a> after my first week at work.</p>
<p>After two weeks of weaving more deepness into my work, it seems that this was indeed the missing piece of the will power puzzle.</p>
<p>Have fun friends! I hope to see you sooner rather than later.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #100: Happy 2016!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/03/weekly-head-voices-100-happy-2016/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 09:20:26 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/03/weekly-head-voices-100-happy-2016/</guid><description> Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res.
I wish you a truly happy 2016, filled with learning and helping other people! Neil deGrasse Tyson, exemplary human, said it best:
For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And along the way, lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/table_mountain_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/table_mountain_view.jpg"
        
            alt="Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Cape Town photographed from the top of Table Mountain. Click for high-res.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I wish you a truly happy 2016, filled with learning and helping other people! Neil deGrasse Tyson, exemplary human, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/IAmA/comments/qccer/i_am_neil_degrasse_tyson_ask_me_anything/c3wgffy">said it best</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For me, I am driven by two main philosophies, know more today about the world than I knew yesterday. And along the way, lessen the suffering of others. You’d be surprised how far that gets you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Time is fun when you&rsquo;re having flies! I can&rsquo;t believe that four months have flown by since <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2015/08/23/weekly-head-voices-99-no-lands/">the previous WHV</a>. Since then, quite a bunch has happened. Some highlights for me:</p>
<ul>
<li>I spent a week in The Netherlands, my other home, taking part in a second hackathon with the Evalueserve peeps (the previous one was in Gurgaon in India). This was again loads of fun, and we managed to build a significant new shippable feature (measurable value!) almost from scratch.</li>
<li>In October, I went back to The Netherlands (it&rsquo;s my other home, remember) for 2.5 days to take part in the Doctorification of <a href="http://francoismalan.com/">a friend</a>. Besides the doctorification process (I&rsquo;ve been out of academia for a while, so my terminology might not be 100%) which went swimmingly, I had so many high-intensity interactions with some of my favourite people that I literally almost missed my flight back. Just picture me waking up in Delft at 8:30 with a flight leaving from Amsterdam at 10:00…</li>
<li>For a work project,  I started programming in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swift_(programming_language)">Apple&rsquo;s Swift</a>. As compiled high-performance languages go, this one has a number of modern language features which make it a truly interesting addition to one&rsquo;s programming toolbox.</li>
<li>Further on the nerd-front, I&rsquo;m trying to get more of us to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">use Signal instead of WhatsApp</a> whenever possible.</li>
<li>We spent so many weekends and the Christmas vacation doing fun outdoorsy stuff (living at the southern tip of Africa has serious perks), not least of which was a trip up Table Mountain for the first time in 15 years. See the photo up top for an impression.</li>
</ul>
<p>I have some fun changes in mind for this blog in 2016, but you&rsquo;re going to have to stick around to find out what they are, so… see you later peeps!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>