<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>meaningful on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/meaningful/</link><description>Recent content in meaningful on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2013 11:22:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/meaningful/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>5 months as an independent engineer: lessons learnt.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2013/08/03/5-months-as-an-independent-engineer-lessons-learnt/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2013 11:22:00 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2013/08/03/5-months-as-an-independent-engineer-lessons-learnt/</guid><description> In February of this year, I left academia (read more about my reasons in the accompanying blog post) to start a new life as an independent engineer, or simply freelancer, if you will. In this post, I would like to summarise the lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt so far. Also, because of my strong nerdtastic tendencies, I will write a separate post talking about the various tools of the trade, software and hardware, that I&amp;rsquo;ve found useful.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In February of this year, I left academia (read more about my reasons in <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/" title="Dear Academia, I hope we can still be friends.">the
accompanying blog post</a>) to start a new life as an independent engineer, or
simply freelancer, if you will. In this post, I would like to summarise the
lessons I&rsquo;ve learnt so far. Also, because of my strong nerdtastic
tendencies, I will write a separate post talking about the various tools of the
trade, software and hardware, that I&rsquo;ve found useful.</p>
<h2 id="the-perception-of-independence">The perception of independence</h2>
<p>First of all: <strong>Having the illusion of being independent is exhilarating.</strong> I
still get up early in the mornings, sometimes even before the rest of the
family to put some extra time into side-projects, and I start the rest of my
work program, fully dressed, at a more or less normal time. I still work the
whole day, and I still spend some evenings and weekends tinkering. Sometimes I
even experience deadline stress. However, the perception that I&rsquo;m doing all of
this directly for the people that find my work useful enough to pay for it, and
that in theory I can choose for whom I do this and how I do it, is awesome.</p>
<p>The little things also make a difference. When there&rsquo;s someone interesting in
town, or slightly out of town, a breakfast or lunch is absolutely justified. If
I feel like going to work in a cafe somewhere, I do so. I&rsquo;m making good
progress on getting rid of those deeply-ingrained employer-directed guilt
pangs. Knowing that I always end up doing the time (or rather generating the
value) helps much.</p>
<p>Oh yes, I also get to buy toys. For my business.</p>
<h2 id="pricing">Pricing</h2>
<p><strong>One of the most challenging exercises when starting out as an independent
contractor / consultant is setting your price.</strong> I think I must have scanned
the whole internet when doing research on this. Talking to other similarly
skilled engineers helped the most. (ping me privately if you need advice with
hard figures) Part of the problem is that each freelancer has different
value-generating capabilities, and has a different estimation of their value
generating potential. My short time in industry working with some kick-ass
engineers, followed by more than a decade in an application-oriented scientific
setting (and one that&rsquo;s all about dealing with data!) working with some really
clever people (and a bit of industry), together with genetically advanced
verbal circuits, means I can build theoretically advanced software systems that
solve practical problems in a robust fashion, and, importantly, that I can
explain how and why they&rsquo;re valuable. (See what I did there? :)</p>
<p>There are two practical tips that I would like to give here:</p>
<ol>
<li>Quote and charge per day. For any worth-while project, you&rsquo;re going to be
putting full-time days into it, not hours.</li>
<li>More importantly: You can easily give special discount on your rates, but
clients don&rsquo;t like it if you become more expensive all of a sudden.</li>
</ol>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently running two longer term projects that fill up all of my time. In
both cases I have arranged with my clients that I do my best to spend N days
per week. If I spend fewer than that (for example due to vacation), I charge
them <em>pro rata</em> less. If I manage to spend more, that&rsquo;s their free bonus.</p>
<h2 id="underpromise-overdeliver">Underpromise. Overdeliver.</h2>
<p>This leads me to my next tip, which is something that I learnt from <a href="https://twitter.com/veryflatcat" title="veryflatcat's twitter profile">A Very
Flat Cat</a>, a very special mentor and friend of mine.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Underpromise. Overdeliver.</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It&rsquo;s one of those guidelines that one has to strive for. The first one helps to
compensate for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planning_fallacy" title="wikipedia page on the planning fallacy">the planning fallacy</a>, the cognitive bias that makes us all
underestimate the time we need to complete a task. Importantly, it helps with
the second part: Deliver your project either slightly ahead of time or over
specification. In other words, try to surprise your client with even more value
than they thought they were going to get.</p>
<h2 id="long-term-vision-as-an-independent-contractor">Long-term vision as an independent contractor</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s only been 5 months, but one has to start thinking about <strong>one&rsquo;s long term
vision</strong> as an independent. Working on client projects is huge fun, and it even
pays the bills, but these same techniques could be used to work on one&rsquo;s own
product or service. <strong>Ideally, one is able to come up with a product or service
that is found useful by a large enough group of people so that a sustainable
business can be built around that product or service.</strong> Fortunately, the
internet / software engineering / data universe is exploding with
possibilities, and is set to continue doing so for the coming decades.</p>
<h2 id="create-the-meaning-in-your-work">Create the meaning in your work</h2>
<p><a href="http://cpbotha.net/2012/07/24/startups-vs-academic-research-groups-fight/" title="Startups vs. Academic Research Groups: FIGHT!">I&rsquo;ve mentioned before</a> the importance of <strong>doing something meaningful</strong>. If
your goal is to be sustainably happy, this is still just as important. When
wrapping up your work for the day, or the night, it&rsquo;s important to have the
feeling that what you&rsquo;ve done has the potential to make a positive impact on
the world around you. My advice here also is not to be too ambitious. (Oh wait,
I <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2013/06/16/dont-dream-big/" title="Don’t dream big.">have a post about that too</a>!) Even if your work, or your open source side
project, has a positive effect on only one other person, you&rsquo;ve done a good
job. Besides selecting one&rsquo;s projects based on this, the meaningfulness of
one&rsquo;s activities can be further increased by putting effort into open source,
or into educational activities.</p>
<h2 id="fin">Fin</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s it for this chapter of <em>Freelancing for Dummies</em>! Let me know in the
comments if there&rsquo;s anything else you&rsquo;d like to discuss.</p>
<p>(I seem to have forgotten everything I read in <em>Writing Blog Post Conclusions
for Dummies</em>.)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>