<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>sleep on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/sleep/</link><description>Recent content in sleep on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 22:29:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/sleep/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #237: Don't step over the thing</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2022 22:29:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/</guid><description> Well hello there and welcome to the first Weekly Head Voices of the year 2022!
Figure 1: So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay.
Where we usually pretend that a WHV covers a certain period of time since the previous one, this one will simply engage in some excessive but pretty skillful hand-waving and say that if you read it and the 2021 to 2022 year transition post, you should be more or less up to date with the state of this nation up to Sunday, January 30, 2022.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well hello there and welcome to the first Weekly Head Voices of the year 2022!</p>








<figure><a href="stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/stony_point_penguins_2022-01-07_hu52ea6b72fcd7443fb0538e6c2d985b60_2006719_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>So many penguins at Stone Point in Betty&rsquo;s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Where we usually pretend that a WHV covers a certain period of time since the
previous one, this one will simply engage in some excessive but pretty skillful
hand-waving and say that if you read it and the <a href="/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/">2021 to 2022 year transition
post</a>, you should be more or less up to date with the state of this nation up to
Sunday, January 30, 2022.</p>
<h2 id="eaz-and-sleep">EAZ and sleep</h2>
<p><a href="/tags/eaz/">EAZ (Experiment Alcohol Zero - no alcohol for at least a month but usually
more)</a> is still going strong, and it&rsquo;s getting harder for me to ignore the fact
that it&rsquo;s (again) having a drastic impact on my sleep quality.</p>
<p>Where I normally am quite chuffed to wake up feeling that I&rsquo;ve had a solid
night of sleep, these days it feels like I&rsquo;m almost guaranteed a great night of
shut-eye as long as I can get to bed on time.</p>
<h2 id="gou-updates">GOU updates</h2>
<p>In other much more important news, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> has left the nest.</p>
<p>Ok fortunately only sort of&hellip; She now spends her weeks in the school&rsquo;s
dormitory.</p>
<p>They are extremely well looked-after, and she gets to participate even more
fully in school activities where previously this was a bit constrained by the 1
to 1.5 hour travel time (school bus in traffic) involved.</p>
<p>We do miss her quite a lot in the weeks.</p>
<p>In her absence, GOU #2 (2IC, IOW) has quickly taken on a new role, which is
interesting to see.</p>
<p>GOU #3 has just started with Grade R (first year of &ldquo;big school&rdquo;), and it looks
like she&rsquo;s taken to it like a fish to water.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a lot more fun now with both #2 and #3 in the car in the mornings,
although we could probably do without all the karma loss I suffer in traffic
every morning. The 4km from my house to school can easily take up to 25
minutes, during which I&rsquo;m obviously surrounded by people who clearly can&rsquo;t
drive.</p>
<h2 id="the-apple-doesn-t-fall-far-from-the-tree">The apple doesn&rsquo;t fall far from the tree</h2>
<p>At the start of 2019 I decided for some or other reason that I really wanted to
know how my branch of the Botha family connected to the rest of the tree.</p>
<p>Botha is a pretty common surname down here.</p>
<p>Many Botha&rsquo;s probably know that we are the descendants of <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Both-15">Friedrich Both</a>, a
soldier who came to the Cape from Wagenheim (from the Thuringen region of
Germany) in 1678 to assist the Dutch colonists.</p>
<p>OR ARE WE?</p>
<p><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23948326/">A 2013 study by Greeff and Erasmus, titled <em>Appel Botha: The abc of a three
hundred year old divorce case</em></a>, showed that Theunis Botha, the first of four
sons of Friedrich Both and his Dutch wife, Maria Kickers (divorced from Jan
Cornelisz because they could not have children), was in fact the extra-marital
product of Maria&rsquo;s relationship with Ferdinandus Appel!</p>
<p>DUN DUN DUUUUUUUN!</p>
<p>According to the study, Theunis Appel is responsible for roughly half (38000) of all
of the Botha&rsquo;s (78000) living in 2013.</p>
<p>Returning to my branch all the way down here: My uncle E was so kind to send me
notes he made of the gravestones on one of the farms my ancestors lived on,
including full names and dates of birth and death of a number of said
ancestors. As you might realise, full names and birth / death dates are genealogy gold.</p>
<p>My aunt M&rsquo;s many stories helped to fill in any further gaps, especially by
confirming identities through matching full names with nick names.</p>
<p>Although initially I was unable to make the connection to the greater Botha
tree using this information, the <a href="https://www.myheritage.com/">MyHeritage</a> databases, and various bits of
information I could get from older clan members, I recently picked up my notes
again (after a two year hiatus!) and was suddenly able to make a single
high-impact connection (my great-great-grandfather) that I previously missed.</p>
<p>Long story short, the moment I did this all of the fragments came together, and
I&rsquo;m now able to say with reasonable confidence that <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Appel-29">Ferdinandus Appel</a> and <a href="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Kickers-1">Maria
Kickers</a> are my great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-grandparents.</p>
<p>DUN DUN DUUUUUUUUUN!</p>
<h2 id="i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">I don&rsquo;t want to step over the thing</h2>
<p>At the end of their <a href="https://lexfridman.com/sam-harris/">3 hour long podcast interview from May</a>, Lex Fridman asks
Sam Harris one of his standard questions (you can listen to the bit in question
<a href="https://youtu.be/4dC_nRYIDZU?t=11241">precisely here</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is the meaning of life?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In almost typical Sam Harris fashion, he replies that it&rsquo;s the wrong question.</p>
<p>Less cryptically, Sam explains that if you&rsquo;re searching for that mythical
<em>meaning of life</em> that&rsquo;s going to make everything better, you might be doing it
wrong.</p>
<p>In his words (which I have transcribed and cleaned up a little bit especially
for you):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You don&rsquo;t have to live with the illusion anymore that you need a good enough
reason and that things are going to get better when you do get those reasons.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a mirage-like quality to every future attainment and every future
breakthrough and every future peak experience that eventually you get the
lesson that you never quite arrive.</p>
<p><strong>You don&rsquo;t arrive until you cease to step over the present moment in search of
the next thing.</strong></p>
<p><strong>We&rsquo;re constantly stepping over the thing that we think we&rsquo;re seeking in the
act of seeking it.</strong> [ed: my emphasis. I loved this bit]</p>
<p>&hellip;</p>
<p>You can&rsquo;t actually become happy. You can only be happy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>His words hit home for me.</p>
<p>Dear readers, I truly wish you an abundance of recognizing the thing, and of
<em>being</em> happy.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #204: What is your purpose?</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 22:22:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/</guid><description> Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September 13, 2020.
Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.
Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.
Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back here folks, to the 204th edition of the Weekly Head Voices,
examining a sample of life from Monday September 7 to Sunday September
13, 2020.</p>
<p>Summer is starting to make an appearance down here, albeit with a bit more
subtlety, some would say difficulty, than usual.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the week in question offered plenty of opportunities for being
outside, opportunities that some of us made grateful use of.</p>








<figure><a href="guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/guardian_peak_20200910_cpb_cfs_hu30c79b06d7d62c3aee261061cff7e609_5760431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with Microsoft Research&amp;rsquo;s Image Composite Editor, and the power of math."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Random scene from a lunch at Guardian Peak with one of my most long-time friends who as a bonus is also brilliant company. What you see is the result of three iPhone photos stitched together with <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/product/computational-photography-applications/image-composite-editor/">Microsoft Research&rsquo;s Image Composite Editor</a>, and the power of math.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="sleep-update">Sleep update</h2>
<p>With our teenager back in school, we have to get up at 5:45, mercifully only
for two days of the week with the school in COVID-19-mode.</p>
<p>On other days we get to sleep in until 6:45. LUXURY!</p>
<p>(The lock-down also saved us from a few months of 5:45 wake-ups 5 time per
week during the darkest part of the winter, so there&rsquo;s that.)</p>
<p>This, together with increased pressure at work, has again brought into sharp
focus my sleep hygiene.</p>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t been doing too badly during the past months, but the current period
seemed to require a tad more attention to good sleep.</p>
<p>After reading the disappointing news that the promised first-party (Apple, in
other words) sleep-tracking in the new WatchOS 6 release was not going to be
much more than tracking time in bed, I searched around for the best third-party
sleep tracking app.</p>
<p>Well folks, after a few weeks of testing, I think that <a href="http://autosleep.tantsissa.com/">AutoSleep</a> is it!</p>
<p>(Beware, there&rsquo;s a straight rip-off app in the Google Play store. It&rsquo;s not even
in the same reality as the real thing, although the scammers have stolen a
bunch of visual elements and even copy from the real autosleep website. Oh
Android&hellip;)</p>
<p>The app appears to be almost too full of complicated-looking visual gizmos, so
much so that initially I was not as positive about it. See below for an example
of my sleep history overview:</p>








<figure><a href="autosleep_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot_huce0efa54e288cea4a99599142a3b63a7_817330_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/autosleep_screenshot.png"
            

         width="240px"/> </a>
</figure>

<p>However, after using it for a while, and coming to grips with the various
pieces of feedback, this app has turned out to be a great tool in my quest for
sleep hygiene nirvana.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I did have to change my watch charging habits by charging my watch
in the evening hours, so that I can sleep with it on my wrist, and I also have
to remember to tap the &ldquo;lights out&rdquo; button when I attempt to start my sleep
(you don&rsquo;t have to do this, but it gives more accurate tracking that way).</p>
<p>Now I have measurements to show how important the wind-down routine is (if I
can fit in some book-reading in bed, I can fall asleep after that in almost no
time); how some nights when it feels like I&rsquo;m quite restless, I actually do get
quite an amount of sleep; and finally how a drink or two on a weekend night can
affect my average heart rate through the night (+5 beats, oof), and more.</p>
<h2 id="wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 and nativecomp Emacs workflow update</h2>
<p>The following is for my more nerdy readers.</p>
<p>After running into <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/WSL/issues/4619#issuecomment-678652118">this comment</a> on a github issue I am subscribed to, I learned
that you can use the versatile <a href="http://www.dest-unreach.org/socat/">socat</a> tool to forward connections from a unix
socket on WSL2, via the WSL bridge and a WSL1 instance, to a TCP port on
localhost.</p>
<p>The upshot of this is that I now have a robust X11 connection from WSL2 to X410
running on my Windows laptop.</p>
<p>This is possible without socat, but you either need to forward ports using SSH
(which I&rsquo;ve done), or punch holes in the firewall, and then, as if that&rsquo;s not
bad enough, deal with a connection that breaks every time the laptop goes into
suspend.</p>
<p>With the socat X11 connection in place, I decided that it was time to go
further around the WSL2 bend and replace my complicated rsync-based scripts for
copying source code from the Windows host to the WSL2-native filesystem with a
second instance of dropbox running directly on WSL2, with a severe selective
sync configuration.</p>
<p>By the way, after <a href="https://dropbox.tech/infrastructure/rewriting-the-heart-of-our-sync-engine">Dropbox rewrote their sync engine (in Rust)</a>, nothing else
even comes close in terms of performance.</p>
<p>Thanks to this perfect storm of socat-X11-boosted WSL2 and MULTI-dropbox, I
decided that it was finally time to commit to <a href="https://akrl.sdf.org/gccemacs.html">the new nativecomp Emacs &ldquo;capable
of compiling and running Emacs Lisp as native code&rdquo;</a>, so I busted out my
slightly modified version of <a href="https://masteringemacs.org/article/speed-up-emacs-libjansson-native-elisp-compilation">Mickey Petersen&rsquo;s</a> Dockerfile and compiled me one.</p>
<p>This very post is being written on native-compiled Emacs Lisp, running on WSL2,
displaying via socat to X410.</p>
<p><code>#feelsgoodman</code></p>
<p>(P.S. I&rsquo;ve been running like this for about three weeks, with nary an
issue. The future is now.)</p>
<h2 id="keyboard-update-unicorns-with-rgb">Keyboard update: Unicorns-with-RGB</h2>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/07/19/weekly-head-voices-200-we-are-extremely-pleased-to-be-here/#my-attempt-at-dipping-my-toes-carefully-into-the-world-of-mechanical-keyboards">WHV #200 how I carefully started dipping my toes in the
clickity-clackety waters of mechanical keyboards</a> by acquiring a cheap keyboard
with hot-swappable <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile-clicky/outemu-blue/">Outemu blue switches</a>.</p>
<p>What I did not tell you then, was that shortly after acquiring that keyboard, I
had already ordered the <a href="https://youtu.be/e9gRESbY-e8">Womier K87 all-acrylic RGB-overload keyboard</a> from
Banggood.</p>
<p>My reason for ordering that specific board was not so much the lighting (WHICH
IS FREAKING SPECTACULAR BUT BACK THEN I DID NOT KNOW THIS), but rather because
it was the most affordable mechanical keyboard with universal(-ish)
hotswappable switches.</p>
<p>You see, the Outemu board can only take Outemu switches, while with a board
with universal sockets, you have access to a whole smorgas(key)bord of
different switches!</p>
<p>The Womier finally arrived after slightly more than a month, with <a href="https://input.club/the-comparative-guide-to-mechanical-switches/tactile/gateron-brown/">Gateron brown
switches</a> installed as I had requested.</p>
<p>Probably due to both the brown switches (rated 45g actuation force but probably
less, tactile but not clicky) and due to the board&rsquo;s far more solid
composition, my typing comfort and speed on this thing are close to what I
usually have on my Microsoft Sculpt ergonomic.</p>
<p>Because of this, I don&rsquo;t swap back to the Sculpt nearly as often.</p>
<p>Together with the fact that the keyboard has an impressive and varied
collection of intricate animated lighting patterns thanks to the RGB LED behind
each and every single key, and a whole bunch of extra LEDs in the acrylic body,
this leads to a great deal of typing fun.</p>
<p><code>#feelsbrightman</code></p>
<h2 id="running-update">Running update</h2>
<p>Back in <a href="/2019/09/09/weekly-head-voices-177-streakers/">WHV #177</a> I embraced the space and acquired my first pair of Altras, a
pair of road shoes named Escalante 1.0, for a good price, because the 1.5 had
already been released.</p>
<p>Recently I was again in the fortunate position to buy a pair of 1.5s for a good
price, as, you guessed it, the 2.0 had already been released.</p>
<p>The new babies look like this:</p>








<figure><a href="altra_escalante_1.5.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/altra_escalante_1.5_hubf87e8a77a5ca4fb8ed62f60a5e7acbc_1920181_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Running in them has been super enjoyable.</p>
<p>(The 1.0s are at about 700km, which is usually a good time to retire them from
running. Now they are just for cocktail parties and business meetings.)</p>
<p>On a more philosophical note, with the aforementioned improving weather, the
aforementioned increased pressure at work, and the non-aforementioned abundance
of mountains all around me, I have taken to randomly taking a few hours off
from aforementioned work to go run in the now aforementioned mountains.</p>
<p><code>#feelslifeaffirmingman</code></p>
<h2 id="what-is-your-purpose">What is your purpose?</h2>
<p>We have a great tradition here at the WHV of revising our official and utterly
complete life philosophy based on discussions with wise friends.</p>
<p>See for example <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">WHV #124</a> where I had to add a third rule to <em>WHV&rsquo;s Two Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</em>.</p>
<p>Quite poetically, the additional rule was &ldquo;Evolve&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(FYI, the current official WHV approach to life, the universe and everyhing is
summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.)</p>
<p>During the beautifully-surrounded lunch discussion with longest-time friend
(LTF, henceforth), as depicted in the panoramic photo at the start of this
post, we also spent some time talking about life directions vs. goals.</p>
<p>As you know, I am <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">not a fan of life goals, instead opting for life directions</a>.</p>
<p>LTF agreed with some of my reasoning, but made the valid point that goals were
required to measure and maintain velocity along one&rsquo;s chosen directions, or
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">systems</a>.</p>
<p>In principle we agree on this point also, but I believe that the conversation
will have to continue, as we still need to define and then articulate a
closed-form solution to the directions vs goals issue, or rather a guideline
that can be used to determine the correct relative dosage.</p>
<p>Probably more important was LTF&rsquo;s contribution of the concept of &ldquo;purpose&rdquo;.</p>
<p>One could argue that life directions form one&rsquo;s purpose, but that would be
missing an opportunity I think.</p>
<p>As LTF later quipped:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Purpose = the reason you get up in the morning. Goals = help you go to sleep at
night.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At least in my case, I have a number of life directions, but I think a purpose
is a higher-level, mostly singular, desired outcome of your life&rsquo;s work.</p>
<p>Ideally, <em>life directions</em> should be set in order to orient one towards
fulfilling one&rsquo;s <em>purpose</em>, with continuously evolving <em>goals</em> punctuating the way
there.</p>
<p>What is <em>your</em> purpose?</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #171: ICEMiRB.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 22:38:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/</guid><description> Down here, you never know what sort of fantastic beasts you could run into. I met this particular fullmetal creature right about here.
Dear friends,
In this post, I do a particularly lossy review of my trip through time, from Monday May 6 to Sunday May 19, 2019.
First we talk about sleep, then a long part on technical tricks, then a slightly more backyard philosophical piece on human tool sharpening, and finally the announcement of a new academic event somewhere in the far or near or medium term future.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="fullmetal_baboon.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu11350bd797bb1be412e08418b0ebf08a_3967777_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
<p>Down here, you never know what sort of fantastic beasts you could run into. I
met this particular fullmetal creature <a
href="https://goo.gl/maps/KpcQGa6hEcbd87mF7">right about here</a>.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>In this post, I do a particularly lossy review of my trip through time, from
Monday May 6 to Sunday May 19, 2019.</p>
<p>First we talk about sleep, then a long part on technical tricks, then a
slightly more backyard philosophical piece on human tool sharpening, and
finally the announcement of a new academic event somewhere in the far or near
or medium term future.</p>
<h1 id="sleep">Sleep.</h1>
<p>If you were one of the people who found themselves in my company for more than
about 10 nanoseconds during the past weeks, I probably tried to get you to
listen to <a href="/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/#the-easiest-but-most-high-impact-measure-you-can-take-to-not-die-too-soon-go-to-bed-on-time">the 6-hour long podcast between Peter Attia and Matthew Walker on
the topic of
sleep</a>.</p>
<p>Usually I&rsquo;m able to get something sufficiently out of my system by writing
about here. I do this quite deliberately to try and spare my innocent
bystanders.</p>
<p>This time, either it didn&rsquo;t really help, or I underestimate how much I would
have blabbed about it had I not let off some of the sleep steam here.</p>
<p>IN ANY CASE&hellip;</p>
<p>During the past weeks I have been paying more attention than usual to sleep, in
terms of quality, quantity and consistency.</p>
<p>Because I also decided to take more notes than usual during the day, I could
see quite acutely the effects of good sleep vs bad sleep on my performance and
energy levels the next day.</p>
<p>If sleep was good the night before, my exercise the next day seemed to take
much less effort, I still seemed to have more than enough energy at the end of
the afternoon, and, most importantly, I had almost no trouble with that
ever-important f-word:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>FOCUS.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Conversely, if I let sleep-onset slip by as little as half an hour, my brain
would be in three thousand pieces by three &lsquo;o clock the next afternoon.</p>
<p>It is starting to dawn on me that all of those evenings where I tried to borrow
an hour or even two from my sleep had a far greater cost the day after than I
ever realised.</p>
<p><strong>I can only conclude, that to experience the highest quality and intensity
waking hours, one simply has no choice but to pay the full 33% sleep tax.</strong></p>
<h2 id="damnit-coffee">Damnit coffee.</h2>
<p>Caffeine has a quarter life of 12 hours.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re positively buzzing at 1PM, 25% of that caffeine is still active in
your system at 1AM and absolutely will interfere with your sleep quality.</p>
<p>I have compromised by having my last shot before lunch, or in extreme cases
right after.</p>
<h1 id="til-things-i-learned">TIL: Things I learned.</h1>
<p>This WHV is one week late, because it seemed like nothing happened in the first week.</p>
<p>However, it seems I did learn quite few new technical tricks. In the
subsections below, I share a selection of these with you.</p>
<h2 id="remarkjs-is-great-for-quickly-building-technical-presentations">remarkjs is great for quickly building technical presentations.</h2>
<p>At <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Helderberg-Software-Developers-and-Entrepreneurs/">my favourite local
meetup</a>,
I was planning to give a talk on <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a>, the static website
generator which is powering this site, and which I&rsquo;m increasingly using instead
of wordpress.</p>
<p>Because every new project is an opportunity to check and perhaps upgrade one&rsquo;s
tools (see below for how this can also sometimes backfire), I set aside the
trusty <a href="https://revealjs.com/">reveal.js</a> and <a href="https://github.com/yjwen/org-reveal">ox-reveal Emacs orgmode
interface</a> I usually bust out, and paddled
out onto rough internet seas, on the lookout for an alternative solution.</p>
<p>(Now that I think back, I had no good reason to search for an alternative,
except that my pre-configured reveal.js style and formatting never made me
really happy.)</p>
<p>Fortunately, after not too long I ran into <a href="https://remarkjs.com">remark</a>, an
HTML- and markdown-based presentation tool that seems simpler than reveal, but
still quite attractive, as you&rsquo;ll be able to see on the demo site above.</p>
<p>At this point, I was pleasantly surprised that this distraction had not cost
more than about 30 minutes.</p>
<p>At least, that <em>was</em> the case until I ran into <a href="https://github.com/torgeir/remark-mode.el">remark-mode for
Emacs</a>!</p>
<p>As you can see from the screenshot, this enables a pretty smooth
generate-as-you-type workflow.</p>
<p>Also noteworthy, is the great built-in presenter mode. Press <code>C</code> to clone the
window into a new linked presentation which you can move off to the external
display, and then press <code>P</code> to switch to presenter mode where you can see all
of the comments you have left in the markdown.</p>
<p>I made two small fixes in <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/remark-mode.el">my own
fork</a> to enable seeding with your
own HTML template, and to enable the generate-as-you-type to work also on
straight <code>.md</code> files. I prefer keeping my presentations as <code>.md</code> (vs <code>.remark</code>)
as most of the search logic I have built in Emacs assumes <code>.org</code> and <code>.md</code>
files for my notes.</p>
<p>By choosing remarkjs instead of my existing revealjs workflow I did manage to
exhaust the short block of time I had allocated to prepare for the talk, and so
the talk morphed into a more spontaneous affair, dealing with orgmode, remarkjs
and in the end, also a bit of hugo.</p>
<h2 id="pybtex-is-a-pure-python-bibtex-parser-and-renderer">pybtex is a pure-Python bibtex parser and renderer.</h2>
<p>One of the sites getting the wordpress-to-hugo upgrade treatment was my
internet persona placeholder, the almost completely unknown
<a href="https://charlbotha.com/">charlbotha.com</a>.</p>
<p>The upgrade of this tiny site would have gone quite easily, were it not for the
fact that I was using the wordpress papercite plugin to publish a list of all
of the publications, including fulltexts in most cases, that I&rsquo;ve had the
pleasure to be involved in over the years.</p>
<p>I could not find any tool which could give me exactly the sort of publication
lists that papercite was able to.</p>
<p>To me it was clear that yet another tool was required. (&ldquo;my god, it&rsquo;s full of biases!&rdquo;)</p>
<p>Fortunately, <a href="https://mentat.za.net">@stefanvdwalt</a> very quickly pointed me at
the Python package <a href="https://pybtex.org">pybtex</a> when he saw that I was
careening off into the dark side with <a href="https://citation.js.org">citation.js</a>.</p>
<p>A few hours later I had built a script which was able to eat my
Zotero-generated bibtex file and spit out different lists of publications with
linked PDFs straight into a Hugo-edible markdown file.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://charlbotha.com/publications/">charlbotha.com/publications</a> for the
result.</p>
<p>P.S. Making it available to a broader audience is on my todo-list.</p>
<h2 id="asciidoc-is-one-of-your-best-choices-to-write-software-manuals">asciidoc is one of your best choices to write software manuals.</h2>
<p>We are currently working hard towards the release of version 2.0 of our
flagship FDA-certified cardiology product,
<a href="https://www.telesensi.com">TeleSensi</a>.</p>
<p>Because updating the user manual with every release is not as fun as it could
be, I had the idea to convert the doc-format source file to some text-based
document authoring system.</p>
<p>Again, in spite of past positive experience writing manuals with
<a href="http://docutils.sourceforge.net">reStructuredText</a> and LaTeX, I made use of
the opportunity to try out
<a href="https://asciidoctor.org/docs/what-is-asciidoc/">asciidoc</a>.</p>
<p>In <em>this</em> case, I am happy to report that the choice of asciidoc ended up
beating all of the alternatives by a mile.</p>
<p>I started by <a href="https://pandoc.org">pandoc</a>-ing the docx to asciidoc, and then
manually (ha ha, it&rsquo;s a joke we writers tell) fine-tuned the document until, in
a few hours, the new manual looked significantly better than the original.</p>
<p>Long story short, our manual is now part of the software source repository and
hence version-locked, it can be automatically built for new releases, and parts
of the manual can be linked programmatically to form parts of our compliance
documentation.</p>
<p>With the manual now essentially being a software construct, there are many more
tricks we can do (and already do, but I&rsquo;m not allowed to say much more).</p>
<h2 id="you-can-build-self-contained-installers-with-legacy-non-modular-apps-and-recent-modular-java">You can build self-contained installers with legacy non-modular apps and recent modular Java.</h2>
<p>In a rather surprising (to me) turn of events, I had to convert some legacy
(read: non-modular) Java code from a product component to a self-contained
installer on Windows and macOS so that our users never even have to <em>think</em>
about JREs.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s possible that the following magical recipe could help you, should you ever
find yourself in a similar predicament:</p>
<ul>
<li>Install <a href="https://adoptopenjdk.net">AdoptOpenJDK</a> 11 (LTS)</li>
<li>Retrieve and extract this <a href="https://mail.openjdk.java.net/pipermail/openjfx-dev/2018-September/022500.html">backport of the new
javapackager</a>
from the yet to be released Java 13 into your OpenJDK 11.</li>
<li>Build your legacy <a href="https://imagej.net/Uber-JAR">uber-JAR</a> with the freshly
installed OpenJDK11.</li>
<li>Use <code>jdeps</code> to determine the list of modular dependencies of your uber-JAR.</li>
<li>Armed with this knowledge, build a mini java-runtime using <code>jlink</code>.</li>
<li>Now feed your uber-jar and the freshly created java-runtime to <code>jpackager</code> in
order to construct a fully self-contained executable or platform-specific
installation package.</li>
</ul>
<p>Much, but not all, of that comes from <a href="https://medium.com/@adam_carroll/java-packager-with-jdk11-31b3d620f4a8">this blog
post</a>.</p>
<h2 id="you-can-easily-dired-jump-to-the-currently-ivy-readd-file-in-emacs">You can easily dired-jump to the currently ivy-read&rsquo;d file in Emacs.</h2>
<p>I mix and match <a href="https://github.com/abo-abo/swiper">ivy</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm">helm</a> in my Emacs.</p>
<p>When you&rsquo;re helming for a file, you can usually press <code>F5</code> to open dired
(Emacs&rsquo;s built-in filemanager) on that file&rsquo;s directory.</p>
<p>This is quite convenient, and something I was missing in ivy, which I use for
example as part of <code>find-file-in-project</code>.</p>
<p>Weeeeell, by adding the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; for any ivy-read, press M-o to get action menu,</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; then &#39;d&#39; to start dired with that file selected</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#268bd2">ivy-add-actions</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#268bd2">t</span> <span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; add for all types</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; (cdr x) gets the full filename, not just relative</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> `((<span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;d&#34;</span> ,(<span style="color:#cb4b16">lambda</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">x</span>) (<span style="color:#268bd2">dired-jump</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">nil</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">cdr</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">x</span>))) <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;dired&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   ))
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; you get to select <code>d</code> from the <code>M-o</code> action menu to <code>dired-jump</code> (a
wonderful command by itself, usually bound to <code>C-x C-j</code>) to the currently
focused file.</p>
<h1 id="sharpening-these-rocks">Sharpening these rocks.</h1>
<p>All of that brings us to this.</p>
<p>I spent quite a few hours last week performing meta-work: That is, not doing
the work itself, but rather sharpening the tools required to do that work.</p>
<p>As with all important matters, there&rsquo;s an XKCD comic about this topic too:</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://xkcd.com/1205/">
<img src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/is_it_worth_the_time.png" alt="xkcd on
tool sharpening">
</a>
<figcaption>
Incredibly useful visualization by XKCD: How much time will your tool
sharpening save per event, and how frequently does that event occur? The
cross-indexed block is how much time this could save you over 5 years.
</figure>
<p>Besides the mostly defensible tricks mentioned in the previous section, I did
also invest hours in attempting to update the mobile and email-based parts of
my personal knowledge management strategy (because
<a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">Windows</a>), but these hours led to a less than
satisfactory solution.</p>
<p>If I have to be honest, it feels like those hours were wasted, although it was
impossible to say beforehand that the effort to outcome ratio was going to be
that bad.</p>
<p>(To make it all a bit more interesting, a few days later some of the dead-ends
explored during those wasted hours led to coincidental improvements of other
frequently occurring (on the order of 5 times per day) components of my
workflow.)</p>
<p>Some folks double down on their workflows, rather taking the small hits and
spending the time doing their actual work.</p>
<p>I find it difficult to resist an opportunity for streamlining.</p>
<p>Sometimes this pays off, not in the least because of the compounding effects of
frequently applicable optimisations, and other times I fall down the rabbit
hole.</p>
<p>In my dreams, I am able to reach a sort of workflow optimisation pinnacle,
where all inefficiencies have been excised from the system. In reality, goal
posts like to move it move it, and so the scramble never ends.</p>
<p>How do you approach this?</p>
<h1 id="icemirb">ICEMiRB</h1>
<p><em>The International Conference on Emacs, Minimal Running and Blogging</em>, or
ICEMiRB, is a new meeting of minds and legs that the aforementioned and
indomitable <a href="https://mentat.za.net">@stefanvdwalt</a> and I are currently bouncing
around.</p>
<p>I actually just want the t-shirt, but the more I think about this, the more I
think it&rsquo;s something that one day really has to happen.</p>
<p>Please let me know in the comments if you would be interested in taking part.</p>
<p>I imagine we will go all out in terms of the various forms of attendance and
participation that we accommodate.</p>
<p>Have a beautiful week folks, I hope to see you again soon!</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>@stefanvdwalt just reminded me that Mindfulness is to be the fourth main topic
of the ICEMiRB.</p>
<p>Because the acronym is already of substantial girth (yes, we know that
Mindfulness and Minimal could co-habit the same part of the
acronym. coincidence?!), we will try to settle for one of two conference
taglines:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ICEMiRB - A Mindful(TM) Conference.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>or</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ICEMiRB - The Mindfulness is silent.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>or not.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #170: Yeet.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2019 22:02:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/</guid><description> Hello there friends!
This edition of the WHV, number 170, is how I choose look back at the three weeks from Monday April 15 to Sunday May 5, 2019.
This period was host to whooshing-by-deadline-induced stress, one amazing and thought-provoking wedding, the birthdays of two of my GOUs, and, a bit strangely part of this list, the acquisition of a new computing device.
At least we were able to pause everything for a sublime afternoon at a favourite vineyard close to my backyard:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello there friends!</p>
<p>This edition of the WHV, number 170, is how I choose look back at the three
weeks from Monday April 15 to Sunday May 5, 2019.</p>
<p>This period was host to whooshing-by-deadline-induced stress, one amazing and
thought-provoking wedding, the birthdays of two of my GOUs, and, a bit
strangely part of this list, the acquisition of a new computing device.</p>
<p>At least we were able to pause everything for a sublime afternoon at a
favourite vineyard close to my backyard:</p>
<figure>
<a href="lourensford_cellar_skies.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/lourensford_cellar_skies_huffcdbbb9c64acf5548d0ca5276abe491_2769760_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
I ended the three week WHV-hiatus in this place, together with my
fam jam<sup>*</sup>. It was lit.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h1 id="a-brief-but-educational-interlude-how-to-speak-gen-z">A brief but educational interlude: HOW TO SPEAK GEN Z.</h1>
<p>I too did not know what &ldquo;fam jam&rdquo; meant until I viewed the educational video
below.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YtrxVWf91Jo" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>I feel like I understand my budding teenager (GOU#1) a little better now.</p>
<p>On a related note: GOU#1 and I went to watch End Game together, on her 13th
birthday.</p>
<p>This is the first time I&rsquo;ve been in a cinema since forever, as I usually find
it hard to justify the time expense.</p>
<p>In this case however, the film, but far more importantly my company and the
special occasion, made it doubly worth it.</p>
<p>P.S. Dumbledore doesn&rsquo;t make it. ðŸ˜¢</p>
<p>P.P.S. That emoji comes straight from my Emacs! (It comes as a bit of a
surprise to me that I am quite excited by how our systems of written
communication are evolving.)</p>
<p>P.P.P.S. If you too want your Emacs to do this, add the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#93a1a1;font-style:italic">;; ðŸ’ªðŸ’ªðŸ’ª</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#cb4b16">use-package</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">emojify</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cb4b16">:ensure</span> <span style="color:#268bd2">t</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cb4b16">:config</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  (<span style="color:#268bd2">emojify-set-emoji-styles</span> &#39;(<span style="color:#268bd2">unicode</span>))
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  (<span style="color:#268bd2">global-emojify-mode</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  (<span style="color:#268bd2">global-set-key</span> (<span style="color:#268bd2">kbd</span> <span style="color:#2aa198">&#34;C-x 8 e&#34;</span>) <span style="color:#2aa198">&#39;emojify-insert-emoji</span>))
</span></span></code></pre></div><h1 id="the-other-blog-posts-i-did-get-around-to-writing">The other blog posts I did get around to writing.</h1>
<p>Perhaps unbeknownst to you, I was not completely quiet on the blogging front.</p>
<p>I produced the following four posts, the latter three of which will have to
live on the nerdy sister blog:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">meepx1e: I haz new laptop!</a> - The traditional
welcome-new-computer-to-my-household post on this blog.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/16/dotnet-fsi-in-vscode/">Using the new dotnet fsi from .NET Core 3 Preview 3 in Visual Studio
Code</a> - A modest trick
for an improved F# repl.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/19/django-typescript-docker-compose-windows/">PyCharm and Docker Compose for Django and TypeScript development on Windows
10</a> -
You can run your Linux inside of Microsoft-supported Docker containers on
your Windows laptop. How times have changed&hellip;</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2019/04/20/link-thunderbird-emails-from-emacs-orgmode/">Link directly to emails from Emacs Orgmode using Thunderbird and
Thunderlink</a> -
This is a core part of my task management workflows. On macOS it worked more
or less out of the box, on Windows and Linux you have to get your hands
dirty.</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="the-easiest-but-most-high-impact-measure-you-can-take-to-not-die-too-soon-go-to-bed-on-time">The easiest but most high impact measure you can take to not die too soon: Go to bed on time.</h1>
<p><a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">I&rsquo;ve mentioned Matthew Walker, the increasingly world-renowned Professor of
Sleep Science, on this blog
before</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m currently working through a three-part podcast between <a href="https://peterattiamd.com">Dr Peter Attia
MD</a>, life optimisation expert with the
hyper-analytical accent(tm), and Prof. Walker, and it is absolutely
<em>fascinating</em>.</p>
<p>Several times now, points discussed by the two gentleman have made me go
&ldquo;OH. MY. GOODNESS.&rdquo; in the car between home, the daily school-run and work.</p>
<p>The long and the short of it is that although we so easily trade away sleep for
an extra hour of work, or even worse to assuage pangs of guilt at not working
enough during the day, that sleep is one of the most crucial components of
one&rsquo;s health.</p>
<p>Looking at it from a different angle, and one which Walker is not scared to
take, probably because it is so critical, lack of sleep has terrifyingly
deleterious effects on human health.</p>
<p>Anyways, if you&rsquo;re looking for a thought-provoking conversation, you could
easily do worse than this.</p>
<ul>
<li>Part 1: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker1/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker1/</a></li>
<li>Part 2: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker2/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker2/</a></li>
<li>Part 3: <a href="https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker3/">https://peterattiamd.com/matthewwalker3/</a></li>
</ul>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have the opportunity to listen to the podcast, perhaps because you
need to catch up on your sleep, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/sep/24/why-lack-of-sleep-health-worst-enemy-matthew-walker-why-we-sleep">this 2017 article in The
Guardian</a>
is a great summary.</p>
<h1 id="the-edge-of-humanity">The Edge of Humanity.</h1>
<p>(Not interested in hearing about sleep? How about existential risks that
threaten the continued existence of our species? Here at the WHV we like to
keep the issues light and light-hearted!)</p>
<p><em>Homo Deus</em> by Yuval Harari is one of those books I really think <em>everyone</em>
should read. This is such a fantastic and broad treatise on where we came from,
and where we might be going.</p>
<p>I am happy that we have the privilege of Harari as the superbly articulate
thinker that he is.</p>
<p>This discussion between Yuval Harari and Sam Harris, available as <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/138-edge-humanity/">podcast #138
on Sam Harris&rsquo;s website</a>, is
both valuable and highly entertaining.</p>
<p>Besides the moment at about 32 minutes in when Harari made the case that all of
the large scale media manipulation and user data mining demonstrate that the
human mind is now indeed hackable (!!), I wanted to mention the
thought-provoking topic of how comically out of their depth our political
leaders are.</p>
<p>They don&rsquo;t seem to be able to do much more than <em>react</em> to short-term fears and
impulses (which they also play to), and as if that was not bad enough, they do
so with an horizon of not much more than about four years.</p>
<p>How many of our leaders would be able to field convincingly the question of
what their plans were, what their <em>vision</em> is for humanity, for the coming 40
years?</p>
<p>What <em>is</em> our 40 year grand plan for energy, for the environment, for poverty,
and for preventing another world war?</p>
<p>Please give your answers in the comments.</p>
<h1 id="a-strange-thing-happened-this-weekend">A strange thing happened this weekend.</h1>
<p>During my time at the TU Delft, I made and maintained a software tool called
DeVIDE, or the <em>Delft Visualisation and Image Processing Development
Environment</em>, or <em>Not Responding</em> as it was called by <em>some</em> of its users.</p>
<p>Development started in 2002, the first open source release was in 2007 and the
last release was in 2012.</p>
<p>(You can still download working binaries of the 2012 release from the
<a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/devide/wiki/Downloads">downloads page</a>. It was
pretty strong on loading chaotic collections of DICOM images, and it was pretty
strong on enabling users to talk to almost any part of it in Python, at
runtime. Frits Post and I published a <a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Hybrid-Scheduling-in-the-DeVIDE-Dataflow-Botha-Post/a96cc2530609d46d9a39f5884d8a9f8192991114">paper in 2008 which nicely summarised
the interesting parts of the
software</a>.)</p>
<p>When <a href="/2013/03/09/dear-academia-i-hope-we-can-still-be-friends/">I left the TU and
academia</a>, my work
positively careened off in a different direction and it became more or less
impossible for me to justify continuing to maintain DeVIDE.</p>
<p>Fast forward a few years, and due to Project Z I&rsquo;m again all up in the
<a href="https://www.dicomlibrary.com/dicom/">DICOMs</a>.</p>
<p>More acutely however, I feel the need for creatively implemented projective
geometry.</p>
<p>Well, my weekend brain got behind the steering wheel, and before I knew it I
was staring at the DeVIDE UI, all prettied up with Python 3 and VTK 8.2:</p>
<figure>
<a href="devide2019-screenshot-20190505.png">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hude98aed5ec064e93d609fc8a6d5e9b53_378650_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hude98aed5ec064e93d609fc8a6d5e9b53_378650_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hude98aed5ec064e93d609fc8a6d5e9b53_378650_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/devide2019-screenshot-20190505_hude98aed5ec064e93d609fc8a6d5e9b53_378650_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
  

   />



</a>
</figure>
<p>At this moment it&rsquo;s only a limping shadow of its previous self, but it still
managed to bring back so many warm memories.</p>
<p>With a few hours more of work, it could start becoming useful again.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not entirely sure where weekend-brain wanted to go with this. We&rsquo;ll have to
wait until he gets back to see.</p>
<h1 id="heading">ðŸ™ðŸ™ðŸ™</h1>
<p>Friends, thank you for connecting with me here in these words and symbols.</p>
<p>I am already looking forward to the next time that we meet!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #156: Karma Chameleon.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 20:56:19 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/</guid><description> Scene from a recent lunch with a very flat cat. Whilst appreciating these moments with direct experience mode set to 11, one does have to realise that itâ€™s all much more complicated than it looks.
Welcome to this, the 156th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, voices who are planning to sing about the two weeks from Monday October 8 to Sunday October 21.
Summer has arrived, and itâ€™s really very hot down here.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/cavalli_view.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/cavalli_view-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Scene from a recent lunch with a very flat cat. Whilst appreciating these moments with direct experience mode set to 11, one does have to realise that itâ€™s all much more complicated than it looks."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Scene from a recent lunch with a very flat cat. Whilst appreciating these moments with direct experience mode set to 11, one does have to realise that itâ€™s all much more complicated than it looks.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to this, the 156th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, voices who are planning to sing about the two weeks from Monday October 8 to Sunday October 21.</p>
<p>Summer has arrived, and itâ€™s really very hot down here.</p>
<p>As Iâ€™m writing this at 21:41, I am doing my best to limit my motion to the absolute minimum in a bid to keep my temperature within healthy limits.</p>
<p>You have to imagine me sitting utterly still, almost like a chameleon on a twig, with only my fingers making small darting movements over the keyboard.</p>
<p>Time is fun when youâ€™re having flies.</p>
<h1 id="karma-running">Karma Running.</h1>
<p>This morning, after losing all my karma in traffic (there was an accident on one of the main roads in my town, resulting in the normally already impressive level of stupidity of the driving mob, which I am part of, reaching hitherto unseen levels; WHEN IS THE AI GOING TO TAKE OVER PLEASE?!), I started my long road to forgiveness, and zen, by taking a barefoot run on the beach near my place of work.</p>
<p>It looked like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/strand_run.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/strand_run-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Goldilocks sand: Not too hard, not too soft, just right."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Goldilocks sand: Not too hard, not too soft, just right.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I wish I could better communicate how it felt.</p>
<p>Imagine the 30 Celsius morning sun on your back, a slight breeze from the sea and your bare feet rhythmically brushing the wet sand as you glide softly along the coast.</p>
<p>Simply keep on doing this until your body creates the stillness that your mind needs.</p>
<p>This is my new favourite run.</p>
<h1 id="mafish">MAF(ish).</h1>
<p>A friend from work told me about this idea of exercising at 80% of your maximum heart rate.</p>
<p>The idea behind this is to <a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/beginner/a20812270/should-i-do-heart-rate-training/">train your aerobic system without injuring anything, and also to be able to do so with much more volume</a> (read: more kilometres).</p>
<p>Four weeks ago I tried to squeeze in too much running in the half hour I had at my disposal. Due to me being doubly stupid, I also did this in my Xero Tolerance 5mm sole sandals, and so I was rewarded with a brand new kind of pain in my posterior tibial tendon.</p>
<p>This is the same tendon <a href="/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/#weekend-running-update">previously mentioned on this blog</a>, also in the context of running injuries.</p>
<p>However, this time I must have injured the tendon more effectively than the previous time (practice makes perfect!), because the pain seemed to be a more permanent new inhabitant of my foot.</p>
<p>Long story short, the suggestion of lower heart rate training came at the perfect time, with my ankle serving as a continuous and visceral (literally) reminder to keep an eye on my heart rate.</p>
<p>This has been going swimmingly.</p>
<p>I am slowly increasing my distance, but, more importantly, runs are again characterised by a whole lot of grinning.</p>
<p>It has not escaped me that a man running on sandals (or barefoot) with a probably fairly unpredictable-looking grin on his big hairy face could give fellow humans pause for thought.</p>
<h1 id="grab-bag-of-thought--andor-debate-provoking-pieces">Grab bag of thought- and/or debate-provoking pieces.</h1>
<h2 id="not-exercising-worse-for-your-health-than-smoking-diabetes-and-heart-disease-study-reveals3"><a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2018/10/19/health/study-not-exercising-worse-than-smoking/index.html">Not exercising worse for your health than smoking, diabetes and heart disease, study reveals</a></h2>
<p>Over a period of more than 20 years, 122000 people were put on a treadmill at Cleveland clinic. It turns out that exercise plays a crucial role in not dying.</p>
<p>Core quote: â€œBeing unfit on a treadmill or in an exercise stress test has a worse prognosis, as far as death, than being hypertensive, being diabetic or being a current smokerâ€.</p>
<h2 id="avoiding-meat-and-dairy-is-single-biggest-way-to-reduce-your-impact-on-earth4"><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2018/may/31/avoiding-meat-and-dairy-is-single-biggest-way-to-reduce-your-impact-on-earth">Avoiding meat and dairy is â€˜single biggest wayâ€™ to reduce your impact on Earth</a></h2>
<p>Iâ€™m really sorry about this one, fellow meat lovers.</p>
<p>This also looks like a pretty solid study. Core quote: â€œThe new research shows that without meat and dairy consumption, global farmland use could be reduced by more than 75% â€“ an area equivalent to the US, China, European Union and Australia combined â€“ and still feed the world.â€</p>
<p>(I have slowly started to work on the vegetarian recipe section of my notes.)</p>
<h2 id="worlds-largest-sleep-study-shows-too-much-shut-eye-can-be-bad-for-your-brain5"><a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2018-10/uowo-wls100918.php">Worldâ€™s largest sleep study shows too much shut-eye can be bad for your brain</a></h2>
<p>It is <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">well known</a> that we here at The Voices are huge fans of sleep.</p>
<p>However, now it turns out that lots of sleep is not going to cut it. You have to sleep just the right amount: Not too much and not too little.</p>
<p>You probably knew this, but this large study confirms it: Between 7 and 8 hours of sleep, no more and no less, is best for optimal mental performance.</p>
<p>Hard hitting quote: â€œOne startling revelation was that most participants who slept four hours or less performed as if they were almost nine years older.â€</p>
<h1 id="the-end">The End</h1>
<p>Thank you for connecting with me by reading this post. I am already looking forward to our next encounter, whichever form that may take!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2017 to 2018 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 11:46:06 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/</guid><description> My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis.
Does anything still work around here?
So much dustâ€¦
Is this thing on?
Testingâ€¦ 123â€¦ tessstingâ€¦ sound check sound check.
OH HI MARK.
(HELLO ALL MY OTHER FRIENDS WHO ARE NOT MARK!)
Itâ€™s been 4 months since the previous post (a Weekly Head Voices), due to reasons involving work (fortunately challenging and fun), genetic offspring units but especially the youngest one who is currently developing at a frightening speed, the South African climate, and my brain suddenly starting to refuse work any later than about 19:00 every day.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2827-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2827-PANO-1024x404.jpg"
        
            alt="My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Does anything still work around here?</p>
<p>So much dustâ€¦</p>
<p>Is this thing on?</p>
<p>Testingâ€¦ 123â€¦ tessstingâ€¦ sound check sound check.</p>
<p>OH HI MARK.</p>
<p>(HELLO ALL MY OTHER FRIENDS WHO ARE NOT MARK!)</p>
<p>Itâ€™s been 4 months since the previous post (a Weekly Head Voices), due to reasons involving work (fortunately challenging and fun), genetic offspring units but especially the youngest one who is currently developing at a frightening speed, the South African climate, and my brain suddenly starting to refuse work any later than about 19:00 every day.</p>
<p>My brain has good reasons I have to admit, having absorbed <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/sep/24/why-lack-of-sleep-health-worst-enemy-matthew-walker-why-we-sleep">this Guardian interview with Matthew Walker</a>,Â director of the Center for Human Sleep Science at the University of California, Berkeley. In short, the possible effects of sleeping anything less than 7 hours per night are simply terrifying. It made me, I mean my brain, really rethink its approach to grabbing-one-more-hour-from-sleep-because-this-stuff-is-really-super-interesting.</p>
<p>Anyhow, following the probably better and more beefy example set by my previous transition post, <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">2016-to-2017 that is</a>, I thought that a new edition would be the best way to get back into slightly more regular posting.</p>
<h1 id="2017-the-100-partial-and-spotty-review">2017: The 100% partial and spotty review</h1>
<p>I wrote 21 posts on this blog in 2017, 12 of which were Weekly Head Voices, which means I was about 23% (12 / 52) successful in terms of posting frequency with the WHV.</p>
<p>The most popular post over here wasÂ <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">Deep Work: A welcome kick in the butt</a>, published on January 9, which garnered just over 20 thousand views. From there my stats went all downhill. :)</p>
<p>More importantly than reader stats, each post, especially <a href="https://cpbotha.net/category/weekly-head-voices/">the Weekly Head Voices ones</a>,Â brought so much connection and satisfaction, which raises the question: Why am I not doing this more? (See my reasons above for not having posted for 4 months, I would have to guess.)</p>
<p>In 2017, I ran just over 800km, which, in contrast to my blogging frequency, is a nice improvement over the 440km I did in 2016. Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) of February last year contributed significantly to my average distance and speed. Those gains were maintained and slightly extended in spite of EAZ concluding in March of last year.</p>
<p>To get an idea of what I was up to work-wise in 2017, you could consider browsing <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/">the posts I wrote on my nerd-blog during 2017</a>.Â  This will give you a bad idea, but itâ€™s probably better than no idea, if you really needed to know.</p>
<p>Life-wise, I might have mentioned <a href="/category/weekly-head-voices/">The Weekly Head voices posts</a> before. There arenâ€™t that many of them for 2017, but the ones that there are, are not too bad.</p>
<h1 id="2018-again-not-much-planned-at-least-not-in-public">2018: Again not much planned, at least not in public.</h1>
<p>Following the shining example ofÂ <a href="http://www.veronikach.com/progress-reports/year-of-blogging/">DrÂ Cheplygina</a>, I would love to become a fully paid-up member of the <em>True</em> Weekly Bloggers Club.</p>
<p>For the past 6 months I sort of went Facebook cold turkey (because reasons, mostly to do with attention-abuse and above-mentioned time scarcity). That, in addition to my unplanned blogging hiatus, feels (yes, I have those, albeit in extremely limited quantities) like itâ€™s caused a bit of a disconnect between me and friends around the world.</p>
<p>I have very recently returned to facebook via the mobile website, and only after extremely liberal application of the â€œunfollowâ€ button to whittle my feed down to just the people I have a healthy connection with. This will help me te maintain connections with the friends who use that as platform.</p>
<p><strong>My reciprocation will have to take the form of weekly updates on this blog.</strong></p>
<p>I look forward to it, and I look forward even more to welcoming you here!








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2669.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2669-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from our cabin at Storms River Mouth Rest Camp. 12/10 will go again."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from our cabin at Storms River Mouth Rest Camp. 12/10 will go again.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>