<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>productivity on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/productivity/</link><description>Recent content in productivity on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 22:05:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #239: Embarrassing finitude</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 22:05:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</guid><description> This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.
Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay.
House gets more energy reserves In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three
weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.</p>








<figure><a href="bettys-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu09cdcb13fca0746a0c7253c481364b31_205979_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Fiery sunset in Betty&rsquo;s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="house-gets-more-energy-reserves">House gets more energy reserves</h2>
<p>In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium
ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of
the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</p>
<p>The complete stack looks as follows, with the new UP5000 on top, and the two
&ldquo;old&rdquo; US3000 units (3.5kWh each) under it:</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu7cc20069a69e34008c2b7387f0195fd5_4931586_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A cluster of lithium ion house batteries." width="400px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A cluster of lithium ion house batteries.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I can already see the positive effect of this on the daily line chart of solar
energy stored: Where previously there were gaps, because the battery was full,
the hot water geysers were either already hot or had not come on yet (in our
house, these act as water batteries on fixed charge times) and we were not
drawing much load, the gaps are smoothed out and the area under the curve is
consistently higher.</p>
<h2 id="dot-dot-dot-while-human-has-to-make-peace-with-limited-energy-reserves">&hellip; while human has to make peace with limited energy reserves</h2>
<p>As a human, you have to deal with a limited amount of energy every day, as if
the fact that your total time on earth was embarrassingly finite was not
challenging enough.</p>
<p>In other words, during one&rsquo;s waking hours, of which one gets a limited number,
one can&rsquo;t rely on operating at the highest energy output all of the time.</p>
<p>As far as I can surmise, one can increase one&rsquo;s daily energy through the
consistent and continuous application of positive lifestyle choices.</p>
<p>This can be hard work, and due to the infernal complexity of organics (have you
looked at a <a href="http://biochemical-pathways.com/">map of metabolic pathways recently</a>? &ndash; you should really go take a
look, it&rsquo;s complicated but also really interesting) and the effects of aging
maybe even an intractable problem, and as if that&rsquo;s not enough, the right
lifestyle can be extremely boring (to those around you).</p>
<p>My mornings usually start pretty nicely, but by the middle of the afternoon my
brain starts disassembling itself anywhere from just after lunch to later in
the afternoon.</p>
<p>What I have recently started noticing, is that when I enjoy one of those highly
productive days with focus straying sharp until late in the afternoon, I pretty
much have to tone it down a bit the next day.</p>
<p>I can still do good work, but I do need to approach the day in a slightly more
relaxed fashion in order to make it through the whole thing in one piece, and
to increase the chances of having a highly productive day after the toned down
one.</p>
<h2 id="the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">The rickety raft of life directions and priorities</h2>
<p>Staying on the theme of limited energy, but taking many steps back from the
cyclical alternate day grinding effect, I&rsquo;ve had to make peace with another
phenomenon:</p>
<p>Again thanks to embarrassingly limited energy, one can only focus on a subset
of one&rsquo;s life directions and priorities at any one time.</p>
<p>For example, when your children are younger, it&rsquo;s normal to dedicate a
substantial chunk of your time to them.</p>
<p>Between that and the necessary parts of work, not much time is left for one&rsquo;s
own hobbies, like Trying To Be a Better Human, or for other worthy goals, like
writing that novel(la) (short story, err or maybe just a nice haiku).</p>
<p>Conversely, when you&rsquo;re training for an important cycle race (not me, a
friend), some of those other dimensions by definition spend time on the
dimensional back burner.</p>
<p>So while you probably have a longer list of priorities which are all very
important to you, you have no choice but to make peace with the fact that at
any one point in time, you can only deal with a fairly narrow subset.</p>
<p>To me it looks the most important to make peace with this fact, and to treat it
as a deliberate and honest choice.</p>
<p>Oh and don&rsquo;t flip flop too much. (that&rsquo;s meant for me)</p>
<h2 id="young-human-wise-beyond-her-years">Young human wise beyond her years</h2>
<p><a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU#1</a> and I were chatting in the car, on way back from one of her social
commitments.</p>
<p>We talked about sleep. (Had she gotten enough?)</p>
<p>She mentioned people that get by on six hours per night and seem to get more
done&hellip;</p>
<p>As I was preparing to attempt commenting Socratically about this, she
pre-empted me by volunteering that when she sleeps well, and for much longer
than six hours, she experiences that she is better with other humans, and that
she feels emotions more intensely.</p>
<p>Goodness!</p>
<h2 id="two-pages-per-week">Two pages per week</h2>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. on the topic of GOU #1 and how best to spend my puny energy:</p>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/#gou-1-reveals-her-plans-and-makes-us-think--more">WHV #194</a> when GOU #1 revealed her cunning plan for
completing a PhD, part of which was writing only 136 words a day for a year,
leaving the two sandwich years for respectively planning and proofreading,
leading to a perfect thesis.</p>
<p>In the recent <a href="https://lexfridman.com/tim-urban/">Lex Fridman podcast #264 with Tim Urban</a>, he of <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/">Wait but why</a> fame,
they start <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Jd7fJgFkPU&amp;t=7166s">talking in-depth about procrastination at the 2 hour mark</a>. (relax,
you can listen to it later. <strong>&lt;ba dum tiss!&gt;</strong>)</p>
<p>(Urban considers himself a procrastinator, but he is a deep thinker, and so this
is a pretty interesting bit of conversation.)</p>
<p>He starts off with the example of a writer who is able to commit to producing
only two pages <em>per week</em>, and by consistently hitting this pretty modest
sounding goal, is able to prepare a book per year.</p>
<p>Glossing over the fact that 200 pages is perhaps not a very <em>impressive</em> book, at
least in terms of girth, publishing one every two years would be frankly
amazing.</p>
<p>He then talks about this idea of being able to attain something substantial and
worthwile by consistently chipping away.</p>
<p>He is clearly searching for the right word,
<a href="https://youtu.be/0Jd7fJgFkPU?t=7203">but then comes up with <em>compiling</em></a>.</p>
<p>I would really like to think that he was in fact searching for our old friend
<a href="/tags/compounding"><em>compounding</em></a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #236: The surprising power of consistent chipping</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/</guid><description> This 236th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the three (sorry!) weeks from Monday October 25 to Sunday November 14, 2021.
What will the beholder think? First things first: Do you notice something different about me I mean my blog?
I don&amp;rsquo;t know how most readers respond to this sort of a thing, but I can really appreciate, in a non-professional way of course, good typography on a personal blog.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This 236th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the three (sorry!)
weeks from Monday October 25 to Sunday November 14, 2021.</p>








<figure><a href="facing-strand.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hue5ad910e14412370c56758d9e1b42688_3284795_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="what-will-the-beholder-think">What will the beholder think?</h2>
<p>First things first: Do you notice something different about me I mean my blog?</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know how most readers respond to this sort of a thing, but I can really
appreciate, in a non-professional way of course, good typography on a personal
blog.</p>
<p>Over the past few years I&rsquo;ve been tweaking the CSS here and there to make small
improvements to the WHV typography, but I&rsquo;ve never been really happy with the
font.</p>
<p>That is, until I ran into <a href="https://alexanderobenauer.com/">Alexander Obenauer&rsquo;s blog</a> and just new that I had to
have the same serif on mine.</p>
<p>The font is called <a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Newsreader">Newsreader</a>. I&rsquo;m currently enjoying the subtly new look, I
hope you do too.</p>
<h2 id="new-diagramming-tool-of-the-insert-suitable-period-here">New diagramming tool of the [insert suitable period here]</h2>
<p>Via Hacker News (henceforth just &ldquo;HN&rdquo;) I ran into this <a href="https://offbyone.us/posts/why-is-excalidraw-so-good/">entertaining and
charming review of a drawing tool called &ldquo;excalidraw&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>Searching a little further, I could see that it had become in a relatively
short timespan a darling of the otherwise hyper-critical HN community.</p>
<p>Personally, I&rsquo;m always on the lookout for any tools which I think could help me
visualize some of my ideas or plans better.</p>
<p>Excalidraw is great at boxes and arrows, which is fortunate, since about 95% of
my ideas and plans are based on different ways of connecting boxes and arrows.</p>
<p>As an aside: So far, I&rsquo;ve gotten by far the most use out of Notability on the
iPad (with 1st gen Apple Pencil), but I never produce as many diagrams as I
keep on imagining that I should be doing.</p>
<p>Upon first use, Excalidraw indeed struck me with how little friction it offers
to the act of sketching out <em>stuff</em>.</p>
<p>I especially like how the authors have somehow managed to merge super-easy
drawing on the computer with the production of diagrams that look like they&rsquo;ve
been made on a paper notebook, whilst still remaining fully vectorized.</p>
<p>Let me know if you&rsquo;ve used this for anything interesting, or if you have any
other diagramming tricks you&rsquo;d like to share.</p>
<h2 id="ok-rust-i-give-up">Ok Rust, I give up</h2>
<p>Back in July of 2018, in <a href="/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/#programming-language-addiction-update">WHV #148</a>, I wrote that after noting the fact that Rust
was an expression-oriented language (I love those) and subsequently reading the
O&rsquo;Reilly <em>Programming Rust</em> book, I had filed away the language under
&ldquo;re-evaluate whenever you reach for your trusty C++&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As a programming language enthusiast, I should have know that that &ldquo;filing
away&rdquo; was merely a postponement of the inevitable.</p>
<p>Recently, in hobby time, probably because I had not yet selected a new book to
read, and because I&rsquo;m going through a bit of a programming phase (err&hellip;), I
unfiled Rust and started going through some more of the materials.</p>
<p>My current feeling is: Hot durnit! Rust may just be the fastest functional
language I have access to!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing a number of the <a href="https://exercism.org/tracks/rust">exercism exercises</a>, and after often pulling out
a pattern match for compact yet readable solutions, I&rsquo;ve been getting a strong
wolf-in-sheep&rsquo;s-clothing feeling.</p>
<p>Rust brings a number of core functional programming principles to an
exceptionally performant programming platform.</p>
<p>Sometimes there are still more nuts and bolts than I would like to see (to be
expected from a systems language that wants to give you full control), but this
mix of low-level and subjectively high-level functional programming is still a
remarkable achievement in my book.</p>
<p><em>Of course</em> I have no real-world applications in mind, unless <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">Advent of Code</a>
counts, but Rust currently makes for great programming practice.</p>
<h2 id="keep-on-keeping-on">Keep on keeping on</h2>
<p>In WHV #214 I wrote about <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">writing down that One Main Thing that you&rsquo;d like to
get done every day</a>.</p>
<p>Day job is currently not entirely conducive to this mode of work, and that&rsquo;s
putting it lightly.</p>
<p>Still, on most days I do remember to select and then write that thing down.</p>
<p>Most recently, I was dragging such an item along with me for what felt like
weeks.</p>
<p>Every morning I did the Alt-W Ctrl-Y finger dance (that&rsquo;s Emacs for copy
paste), and I experienced the concomitant pang of internally facing
embarrassment.</p>
<p>Often there would be no progress (because meetings and other non-maker work),
but on some days I would excavate the equivalent of a generously filled
teaspoon of dirt. (<a href="https://youtu.be/4_C86o5dE_c">Doctor Flammond&rsquo;s tunnel</a> anybody?)</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, the Thing neared completion, until one day (weirdly still to
my pleasant surprise) it was done, never to be copy-pasted again.</p>
<p>My happy little mental note was: Just keep on dragging One Main Thing with
you. It&rsquo;s not on the list because it&rsquo;s going to get completed, but rather
because it&rsquo;s the thing that you just have to keep on chipping away at,
<em>especially</em> when progress seems almost invisible.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #214: One Main Thing</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/</guid><description> WELCOME BACK EVERYONE TO THIS WARM AND WELCOMING CIRCLE OF WEEKLY HEAD VOICES!
Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded.
You are reading the 214th edition of the WHV, the first of 2021 (hurrah), and spottily covering the intersections of my consciousness with the period of time from Monday, January 11 to Sunday, January 24 of the year 2021.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>WELCOME BACK EVERYONE TO THIS WARM AND WELCOMING CIRCLE OF WEEKLY HEAD VOICES!</p>








<figure><a href="hermanus_coastal_walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu75071808a57a489883adc169fbf8f063_2173875_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You are reading the 214th edition of the WHV, the first of 2021 (hurrah), and
spottily covering the intersections of my consciousness with the period of time
from Monday, January 11 to Sunday, January 24 of the year 2021.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not entirely happy with the water-tightness of this coverage, but <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/">the
2020-2021 year transition post</a>, which I hope you&rsquo;ve read or at least heard
about, is probably worth this bit of start-point haziness.</p>
<h2 id="first-rule-of-blogging-we-don-t-blog-about-blogging">First rule of blogging: We don&rsquo;t blog about blogging</h2>
<p>As you know, <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">I <strong>really</strong> love Hugo</a>, the software tool with which I can write
these posts in Emacs (text editor, you heathens) and then convert them to the
fast static pages that you are now reading.</p>
<p>The one thing I <em>was</em> a bit disappointed with, was the lack of some form of
built-in yearly post archives.</p>
<p>Well, while writing the year transition post, this disappointment spiked into
action, and so I applied just enough internet and elbow grease to scratch my
yearly archive itch on this blog.</p>
<p><a href="/2021/01/10/super-simple-yearly-post-archives-hugo/">This post shows you how to do it</a>, and <a href="/archive/">here you can see the result, yearly
archives for all of the posts on this blog</a>!</p>
<p>As a first step on <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#comms-upgrade">my path to become better at asynchronous communication</a>, I
wrote <a href="/2021/01/16/intro-asynchronous-communication/">an introductory blog post on the topic</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not as happy with it as I would have liked to be, but it&rsquo;s the line in the
sand that I really wanted to draw.</p>
<p>More importantly, I&rsquo;ve been able to get a few people to read it.</p>
<h2 id="signal-i-told-you-so">Signal: I told you so</h2>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2021/01/whatsapp-users-must-share-their-data-with-facebook-or-stop-using-the-app/">WhatsApp recently making clear that they will be sharing increasing
amounts of the massive amounts of your data at their disposal with all other
companies in the Facebook family</a>, many folks have been looking for
alternatives.</p>
<p>Even more fortunately, many of those folks have been choosing the most
pragmatically private alternative, namely Signal.</p>
<p>You might recall that <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">I started recommending that we use Signal back in January
of 2016</a>, which is infinity years ago in internet time.</p>
<p>Telegram does indeed count as an alternative to WhatsApp, but its chats are by
default not end-to-end encrypted, and it&rsquo;s still backed by a for-profit
company. There&rsquo;s nothing wrong with this, but if your concern is privacy now
and in the future, Signal is by far the better choice.</p>
<p>Anyways, I am happy to see more of my contacts appear in the Signal list.</p>
<h2 id="one-main-thing">One Main Thing</h2>
<p>In 2011, <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#pro-tip-2">I wrote about starting the day by writing down concretely the tasks
one would like to complete by the end of the day</a>.</p>
<p>A few years later, <a href="/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/#thinking-of-future-you">I picked up a tip from a podcast with Sam Harris and Derren
Brown that one should explicitly ask the question which tasks would satisfy you
the most at the end of the day</a>.</p>
<p>(Interestingly, in the 2018 post above I misquoted my 2011 post as suggesting
that one writes down &ldquo;the two to three really important tasks for the
day&rdquo;. That &ldquo;two to three&rdquo; came from some other memory which I can&rsquo;t track down
right now.)</p>
<p>Last year <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#its-what-future-you-would-want-quote-edition">I ran into Lubbock&rsquo;s far more eloquent formulation</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If we are ever in doubt about what to do, it is a good rule to ask ourselves
what we shall wish on the morrow that we had done. &ndash; John Lubbock</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the comments to that post, friend AJ added the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Another iteration of what to do next that I recently heard was Gary Kellers
version: The One Thing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have not yet gotten around to reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%5FOne%5FThing%5F(book)">The One Thing</a>, but I think AJ&rsquo;s comment
did plant a seed&hellip;</p>
<p>Fast forward a few months, and I have started to realise that my most
productive and satisfying days often coincide with the days when I have the
guts in the morning to commit to one main thing for the day.</p>
<p>Conversely, when I don&rsquo;t select and commit to One Main Thing, but due to
deadlines and other expectations put more than two or more bigger items on my
list, that day has a high probability of leaving me quite frazzled by its end.</p>
<p>One Main Thing days are scary, because I feel like there is always a long list
of things I&rsquo;m not going to get to, and people I&rsquo;m going to have to disappoint.</p>
<p>However, selecting that One Main Thing wisely, explicitly committing to it, and
then knocking it off after a few hours of focus is undeniably satisfying, and
will probably help a bunch of people.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it turns out that even with this commitment, one does still manage
to get some of the little things done in the scraps of left-over time.</p>
<p>You know, just after lunch, just before dinner and so on.</p>
<p>Pay some bills, answer a few emails, and then dive back into your One Main
Thing.</p>
<h3 id="interstitial-projects">Interstitial projects</h3>
<p>In addition to this, it turns out some of my projects can be specifically
treated as <em>interstitial</em>.</p>
<p>This is the label I&rsquo;ve chosen for those projects that 1. are supported by
low-friction tools that are instantly available and 2. benefit from slivers of
thought.</p>
<p>For example, I&rsquo;m working on a few blog posts dealing with issues I come across
during my work.</p>
<p>During the day, I see something that warrants a section in one of the blog
posts&hellip;</p>
<p>Switch to Emacs, hotkey search the relevant notes file, hotkey search the
relevant section in that file, type the sentence or two in your head, switch
back to work.</p>
<p>That took all of a minute or two, but now there are two new sentences, and we
all know what sentences do, right? They <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a> into blog posts!</p>
<h2 id="do-you-want-to-produce-or-consume">Do you want to produce or consume?</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m technically not allowed to write about something that appeared after the
published timespan of a WHV, but I would be remiss if I did not mention the
nudge that got WHV #214 off the ground.</p>
<p>That nudge is <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/recommendations/">this post by Noeska</a>, and specifically these words:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Do I want to produce or consume?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You should really go read the post for context, but if you need to hear that
sentence, you&rsquo;ll probably understand exactly what it means.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #208: Stilbaai</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 10:59:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/</guid><description> Welcome back folks!
Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.
It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.
Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.
Running and reading I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, GOU #1 (14) completed her first (virtual) 10km race.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back folks!</p>
<p>Although my weeks have been quite full, this post is short.</p>
<p>It covers a few noteworthy (to me) events and observations from the period
Monday October 12 to Sunday November 1, 2020.</p>








<figure><a href="skulpiesbaai_pano.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/skulpiesbaai_pano_hu691bf885d730239611b633c8d1dd37a3_1806431_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Skulpiesbaai, taken from the halfway-point of a coastal run in Stilbaai.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="running-and-reading">Running and reading</h2>
<p>I am super chuffed that on Sunday October 18, 2020, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #1</a> (14) completed her
first (virtual) 10km race.</p>
<p>Her journey started when a friend from school invited her to join the race, at
which point GOU #1 suddenly became much more enthusiastic about running
regularly with her old dad. (that&rsquo;s me)</p>
<p>There is something pretty primal about running with your offspring, an
observation that I might have mentioned before on these pages.</p>
<p>Anyways, after her race she was visibly happy, and also relieved that, in her
words, &ldquo;she didn&rsquo;t die&rdquo;.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m perhaps even more happy about than the preparatory runs together, and
her completing the race, is that since the race we&rsquo;ve been out together for a
run or three.</p>
<p>(Running and reading are two of the most important low-level habits I would
like to try and get my offspring hooked on.)</p>
<h2 id="ieee-vis2020">IEEE VIS2020</h2>
<p>At the start of October, I had a great experience <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#vcbm-2020-virtually">virtually attending the VCBM
2020 conference</a>.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough grade A1 10/10 conferencing for one year, my other
favourite conference, IEEE VIS (for visualization) was also fully virtual this
year in the week of October 26, so again I dove into YouTube streams and
well-organised discord rooms, and again this experience was highly edifying and
enjoyable.</p>
<p>Somehow, it was even <em>more</em> fun than my already optimistic expectations to run
into friends at the conference.</p>
<p>I would like to transfer this one piece of sage advice given by the amazing
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack%5Fvan%5FWijk">Prof. Jarke van Wijk</a> during the panel on &ldquo;Why should I stay in academia&rdquo; when
the discussion treated the issue of dealing with rejection, something that is
unfortunately a regular part of most academic careers.</p>
<p>At this point, he was referring specifically to accepted papers and proposals,
but the advice should really be applied to any victory, large or small, in all
walks of life:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Celebrate your victories.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="cycles">Cycles</h2>
<p>You will of course remember that we were fortunate enough to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/">spend our last few
days of freedom in Stilbaai,</a> as autumn was arriving, and more acutely right
before the first lockdown started on March 26,</p>
<p>It was really great going back to the exact same house (thanks kind host!),
after months of various levels of lockdown, this time just as spring was really
getting off the ground.</p>








<figure><a href="stilbaai_0181.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/stilbaai_0181_huc9c81152ace165d41ebdfc6e1f30e49b_533893_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I did take work with me for the long weekend, but this time, and quite
unexpectedly, the important <a href="/tags/disconnecting">disconnect</a> happened quite quickly without too much
conscious effort from my side.</p>
<p>If I had to put my finger on it, I would say that getting everyone to go
outside as often as possible on little adventures of various sizes was the
catalyst.</p>
<h2 id="back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">Back to reality: An 18-minute plan for managing your day</h2>
<p>I could not imagine a more sudden transition from the long weekend zen above
than this jump to Peter Bregman&rsquo;s 18 minute plan for planning your work day.</p>
<p>Anyways.</p>
<p>Sometimes, fortunately mostly later in the afternoon, I wonder why my systems
have failed in helping me to keep my eye on that ball for longer. (See <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">my
slippery eel</a> for more struggles.)</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s when I procrastinate quasi-productively by searching online for any new
self-optimisation tricks that I might have missed, and which might constitute
that Last Piece of The Puzzle that will fix this once and for all.</p>
<p>This time, to my great surprise, I did actually run into something 1. that was
written aaaaaall the way back in 2009 and 2. that contained something new that
I had not run into before, namely the &ldquo;refocus&rdquo; reminder.</p>
<p>The refocus reminder is literally an alarm that goes off every hour on the
hour, at which point you explicitly take a step back for a whole minute to
review the past hour, and, if required (most probably the case the later it is
in the day), to re-commit to the following hour.</p>
<p>This reminded me specifically about mindfulness&rsquo;s <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#therunning-and-the-mindful">&ldquo;Each breath a new beginning;
each out-breath a letting go&rdquo;</a>, and more generally about <a href="/2018/02/25/weekly-head-voices-133-onder-in-my-whiskeyglas/#life-is-continuous-practice">life as eternal
practice</a>.</p>
<p>You can use any sort of timer to do this, but this seemed like a great feature
for the little Lazar Focus app, so I implemented it along with a nice
mindfulness bell sound to add some gravitas to the moment.</p>
<p>If you like, you can read the short summary I wrote about the <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/2020/10/24/peter-bregmans-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day-and-the-surprising-power-of-refocus-reminders/">18-minute plan
and refocus reminders over on the LazarFocused blog</a>. There are some other more
widely known but great tips for running your work days more efficiently.</p>
<h2 id="kind-regards">Kind regards</h2>
<p>Folks, thank you very much for joining me here.</p>
<p>The comments section below is ready for your thoughts, if you would like to
externalise them.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #167: Yes, and...</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/</guid><description> (I initially posted this blog with an incorrect slug, so I had no choice but to re-publish with the correct slug and URL. It is possible that you receive the email notification twice. I am really sorry about this! P.S. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s a dirtly little secret of the blogging industry that slugs are involved.)
I have posted similar photos before, but this one is special, because it was a crystal clear and almost wind-free Friday afternoon, hosting an almost perfect barefoot run.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(I initially posted this blog with an incorrect slug, so I had no choice but
to re-publish with the correct slug and URL. It is possible that you receive
the email notification twice. I am really sorry about this! P.S. Yes, it&rsquo;s a
dirtly little secret of the blogging industry that slugs are involved.)</em></p>
<figure>
<a href="strand_crystal_clear.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/01/weekly-head-voices-167-yes-and/strand_crystal_clear_hu426c4e9906be466fca9c3c215ba0523f_2830253_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='photo of strand beach at macassar rheinmetal fence' />



</a>
<figcaption>I have posted similar photos before, but this one is special,
because it was a crystal clear and almost wind-free Friday afternoon, hosting
an almost perfect barefoot run.  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Oh hi there friends, from this <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">brand new and quite shiny Hugo blogging
setup</a>!</p>
<p>When the novelty wears off, as it invariably does, I expect that I will be
<em>quite</em> content with this graduation to a more minimalist blogging experience:
It&rsquo;s just me, and you, and this old text editor.</p>
<p>I am looking forward.</p>
<p>At this very moment however, I am also looking back, at the week from Monday
March 25 to Sunday, March 31, 2019.</p>
<h2 id="fire-and-motion">Fire and Motion.</h2>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know how else to describe it, but the thought that came up most often
last week was: What a silly day.</p>
<p>It felt like I had to put in three times the energy to get out just a little
bit of focus. Every morning I returned to the grind, just to continue with
this Sisyphean struggle.</p>
<p>On Thursday, co-worker adt (not the security company) sent me <a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2002/01/06/fire-and-motion/">Joel Spolsky&rsquo;s
&ldquo;Fire and Motion&rdquo;
essay</a>. (I
previously thought that I had read all the best of Spolsky, but apparently
not!)</p>
<p>Spolsky starts with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sometimes I just can’t get anything done.</p>
<p>Sure, I come into the office, putter around, check my email every ten seconds,
read the web, even do a few brainless tasks like paying the American Express
bill. But getting back into the flow of writing code just doesn’t happen.</p>
<p>These bouts of unproductiveness usually last for a day or two. But there have
been times in my career as a developer when I went for weeks at a time without
being able to get anything done. As they say, I’m not in flow. I’m not in the
zone. I’m not anywhere.</p>
<p>Everybody has mood swings; for some people they are mild, for others, they can
be more pronounced or even dysfunctional. And the unproductive periods do seem
to correlate somewhat with gloomier moods.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Suddenly I felt far less bad, and super grateful that Spolsky had the guts to
publish this admission.</p>
<p>If someone as amazing as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joel_Spolsky">Joel
Spolsky</a> can experience these
bouts of non-productivity, there is hope for me too.</p>
<p>What really struck a chord is what he writes about the unproductive periods
seeming to correlate somewhat with gloomier moods.</p>
<p>I did have a lot on my mind last week.</p>
<p>Local politics are heating up before the May elections, and so various people,
including acquaintances and friends, are fighting it out on social (and
sometimes mainstream) media.</p>
<p>These fights, apart from their intrinsic violence (ad hominem seems to be in
vogue), often involve race-directed utterances that can catch one quite badly,
making one literally question one&rsquo;s place in society.</p>
<p>Added to this are the regular reminders, including the previously mentioned
load-shedding and numerous corruption scandals, that the current ANC
government is an utterly failed mechanism.</p>
<p>Added to <em>that</em> is at least one other very much related bureaucracy-fueled
personal existential issue that was both burning up mental cycles <em>and</em> stealing
sleep cycles.</p>
<p>Taking stock like this, I can&rsquo;t say anymore that I&rsquo;m surprised that last week
was not my best focus-wise.</p>
<p>You should really go read Spolsky&rsquo;s story, but I&rsquo;ll paraphrase his advice
here.</p>
<p>Everyone has these difficult days, and that&rsquo;s ok.</p>
<p>The important thing is to keep on moving forward a little bit, every day.</p>
<h2 id="yes-and">Yes, and&hellip;</h2>
<p>The extra mental cycles were fortunately not all in vain.</p>
<p>Many of them were dedicated to the question of how exactly I should best act
and react in the current situation.</p>
<p>One of the conclusions I came to is that we have to make peace with the fact
that we&rsquo;re all stuck with each other: You, the person you disagree with most
vehemently, and everyone in between.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re probably not going to be able to change each other that much in the
short term, and especially not if the narrative remains this aggressive.</p>
<p>At best, people at the fringes of the various groupings might come to new
conclusions, and gravitate towards friendlier and more humanist pastures.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, attack / defend mode is the worst mode for causing
positive change.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s also extremely tiring.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know if this is better at the political level, but I do know what my
personal approach is going to be from here on out.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s always some similarity to be found between me and my &ldquo;enemy&rdquo;, for
varying degrees of &ldquo;enemy&rdquo;. (Remember, &ldquo;enemy&rdquo; is just an extreme point on the
friendship spectrum. :)</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re all human. We really do have similar needs. Safety of our families, time
with our friends, a place in the sun for all our fellow humans.</p>
<p>We might differ on how we get there, but it can make a huge difference to
start with all of the needs that we share.</p>
<p>I have resolved to start every every discussion and every related
thought-process with the things that we have in common.</p>
<p>By starting conversations like this, one builds on a platform of similarity,
instead of trying to break down whatever you see before the conversation has
even started.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yes, and&hellip;&rdquo; is a trick used in improv theater. When it&rsquo;s your turn to take
the dialogue, you start with &ldquo;Yes, and &hellip;&rdquo; and then build on the creativity
of the previous actor. The next actor in line also starts with &ldquo;Yes, and&hellip;&rdquo;,
only further enriching the world of imagination that the previous actors are
constructing on stage.</p>
<p>I think we should &ldquo;Yes, and&hellip;&rdquo; much more in real life.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll start.</p>
<h2 id="what-stands-in-the-way-becomes-the-way">What stands in the way becomes the way.</h2>
<p>The following was recently used <em>in anger</em> (not actual anger, just in actual
application) somewhere in my network:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Our actions may be impeded by [obstacles], but there can be no impeding our
intentions or our dispositions because we can accommodate and adapt. The mind
adapts and converts to its own purposes the obstacle to our acting.</p>
<p>The impediment to action advances action.</p>
<p>What stands in the way becomes the way.</p>
<p>&ndash; Marcus Aurelius</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This could be applied to the story in this post, but one could also go a
little more meta: Initial embarrassment at not even knowing about Marcus
Aurelius&rsquo;s Meditations softly transformed into a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Meditations-New-Translation-Modern-Library-ebook/dp/B000FC1JAI/ref=as_li_ss_tl?s=digital-text&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1452403537&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=meditations+marcus+aurelius&amp;linkCode=sl1&amp;tag=camdezcom-20&amp;linkId=5a0d37b29a42b5e13ed9bc805aff9456">humble button
click</a>, and hopefully soon into a studied book.</p>
<p>Friends, I hope you have a brilliant week. Please remember &ldquo;yes, and&hellip;&rdquo;!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #164: It’s what future you would want.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 14:53:44 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/</guid><description> Pre-work not-too-shabby running route.
Welcome back friends! This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday February 18 to Sunday March 3, 2019. I was planning to release the edition of the WHV on time, but my need for a break was greater.
Because I’ve given up on ever mastering the art of the bullet-list form of the weekly(ish) status update, I am going to double-down on the old-fashioned sectioned prose form that you see before you.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/strand_running_route_2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/strand_running_route_2-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Pre-work not-too-shabby running route."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Pre-work not-too-shabby running route.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome back friends! This WHV looks back at the two weeks from Monday February 18 to Sunday March 3, 2019. I was planning to release the edition of the WHV on time, but my need for a break was greater.</p>
<p>Because I’ve given up on ever mastering the art of the bullet-list form of the weekly(ish) status update, I am going to double-down on the old-fashioned sectioned prose form that you see before you.</p>
<p>Also, this post has again evolved into a long ramble. (It’s now Saturday March 9, time to start working on the next edition. I’m curious what form it will take.)</p>
<h2 id="gou1-is-2">GOU#1 is #2</h2>
<p>It feels like through these posts you’ve pretty much seen <a href="/2010/07/26/island-style-weekly-head-voices-27/">GOU#1 grow up before your eyes</a>, so I’ve given myself permission to mention this moment of parental pride, hopefully quite briefly though (I write this blog not only for you, but also for me in 20 years time!):</p>
<p>GOU #1 has been elected as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Head_girl_and_head_boy">deputy head girl</a> of her 1600+ pupil primary school!</p>
<p>She was really mature, also before the time, about this possible outcome of taking the #2 position. She seems to have made up her mind before the time that this would in fact be, for her, the best configuration.</p>
<p>This thoughtfulness of hers might have made me even more proud than the achievement itself.</p>
<h2 id="dreams-of-clean-solar-electricity-wafting-ineffectually-against-the-greasy-gears-of-government">Dreams of clean solar electricity wafting ineffectually against the greasy gears of government.</h2>
<p>Way back in December of last year <a href="/2018/12/19/weekly-head-voices-159-extreme/#extreme-solar">I mentioned</a> that we were working on getting the house upgraded with a photovoltaic solar power system.</p>
<p>Some of you have asked me via various communication pathways how it was going.</p>
<p>Thanks to legislation, or rather the lack of communication around this legislation, the amount of physical progress we have made so far is close to zero. Oh, just make that zero.</p>
<p>My shopping list now looks as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>Unchanged: 3.6kW GoodWe EM hybrid inverter: Although a larger inverter would have been preferable, uncertainty caused by above-mentioned lack of communication motivates me to play it safe with this unit which is in the 2017 column of the approved list.</li>
<li>Unchanged: 2 x PylonTech US3000b lithium ion batteries.</li>
<li>CHANGED: 16 x Canadian Solar CS3U 350Wp or 355Wp solar panels.</li>
</ul>
<p>It used to be common knowledge that monocrystalline panel power output suffered less due to high temperature than that of the cheaper polycrystalline panels. This is quite relevant, because just sitting there on your roof the whole day, these things can get really hot!</p>
<p>Well, I finally went and looked up the temperature coefficient of these current generation Canadian Solar panels, namely the CS3U range, <a href="https://www.canadiansolar.com/upload/521adedf1d5fecb9/e5ba81805bf70380.pdf">which is -0.37% Pmax / ℃</a>. This is in fact slightly better than the -0.39% of the monocrystalline panels I had on my list.</p>
<p>I am currently on the lookout for what is going to be my fourth candidate solar installer, although at this stage I would be quite happy with a talented electrician who is not afraid of heights.</p>
<p>(My second installer had difficulty keeping up with all of their work (probably thanks to load-shedding and also to the substantial price increases expected from our embattled electricity monopoly) and my third installer has decided to focus on commercial installations.)</p>
<h2 id="my-big-and-stupid-misstep-into-google-drive">My big and stupid misstep into Google Drive.</h2>
<p>Somewhere during the past two weeks, I lost, forever and ever, at least three evenings.</p>
<p>Tipped off by a colleague at work, encouraged by my family’s mobile photos investment in Google Photos, and further tempted by the significant price difference and the family storage sharing option, I convinced myself that it was time to migrate my little empire of useless files (dropbox reports that I currently have just over 500000 (five hundred thousand) of them) out of Dropbox and into Google Drive.</p>
<p>This is how it looked on paper, i.e. in my head and in my Emacs notes:</p>
<ul>
<li>I have about 70GB of photos taken with various family cameras of kids growing up, vacations everywhere and so on. These photos are currently not easily accessible by said family. If they were on Google Drive, they could be automatically exposed to Google Photos, which my family is already using!</li>
<li>My 237G of Google Drive space, sufficient for everything, costs R39 / month (that’s about $2.75), whereas my Dropbox subscription costs $10 / month.</li>
<li>The cheap subscription of Drive already enables one to do content searches. E.g. I could find scans of documents instantly by typing OCR’d words that occur in the documents. If you want the same with Dropbox, you have to go Pro (not Plus), and pay double, that is $19.99 per month.</li>
<li>Drive has a built-in facility to backup folders outside of the main sync folder.</li>
<li>There’s a great tool called <a href="https://rclone.org/">rclone</a> with which nerds can sync files to Google Drive from the command-line!</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="four-lessons-learned-uploading-500k-files-to-google-drive">Four lessons learned uploading 500k files to Google Drive</h3>
<ol>
<li>Google has servers down here in South Africa: With larger files, the upload could easily max out my 50Mbit/s upload.</li>
<li>However, in spite of allocating and configuring my own <a href="https://rclone.org/drive/#making-your-own-client-id"><code>client_id</code></a>, I could not upload faster than about 3 files per second. Based on various threads on the rclone forums, this is a known issue.</li>
<li>Google Drive’s selective sync functionality does NOT (easily) allow you to maintain a local version of an excluded directory in the same way that Dropbox does. This is <em>especially</em> annoying for those already quite annoying <code>node_modules</code> folders.</li>
<li>Google Drive and its API support identically named files and directories, located in the same parent directory.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="how-did-the-wheels-fall-off-then">How did the wheels fall off then?</h3>
<p>I was alternating between the official Google Backup &amp; Sync client and <code>rclone sync</code>. I did this to check if rclone with a private <code>client_id</code> would be able to upload faster (it couldn’t) and because rclone showed sync progress more clearly with an estimated time of completion (all of this turned out to be wildly incorrect and variable due to all of those small files).</p>
<p>My logic was that as long as the two tools were not running in parallel, sync logic and checksums should prevail right?!</p>
<p>Well, that turned out to be a very sad assumption…</p>
<p>rclone, which I still believe is a great tool for bulk uploads and downloads, should probably not be used for syncing in situations like this.</p>
<p>Unbeknownst to me, it had created hundreds of identically-named directories everywhere. (See lesson #4 above.)</p>
<p>At about halfway through this multi-day upload project, I switched back to the official Google tool, which finally, FINALLY managed to sync everything after about 5 days I would guess.</p>
<p>I was briefly <em>quite</em> happy with Google’s arrow-in-cloud you-are-fully-synced icon in the menubar.</p>
<p>However, because happiness is so inherently fleeting anyways, I decided that it was time for the next phase of the project: Add the first Linux workstation to the little sync family.</p>
<p>Google Drive does NOT have a native client for Linux, although they’ve promised this since the start, and so I decided to try <a href="https://www.insynchq.com">Insync</a>, which seems to be one of the best of the third party clients.</p>
<p>I pre-seeded the sync directory on said Linux machine using rsync and then started the insync client. This is a use case which was often enough mentioned on the forums as being supported.</p>
<p>Initially, everything seemed to be going swimmingly!</p>
<p>However, soon I saw whole directory hierarchies with thousands of files disappearing simultaneously from both my local disc and google drive.</p>
<p>STAAAAAAAAHP!!! JUST STAHP.</p>
<p>A second, stubborn attempt, after having recovered files and synced everything up with Google’s tool, yielded similarly frustrating results.</p>
<p>Granted, the duplicate folders on Google Drive are a far from ideal test case, but deleting directories like that on both client and server is not defensible.</p>
<p>Defeated, I retreated to the expensive, but safe, embrace of Dropbox.</p>
<h3 id="more-lessons-learned">More lessons learned:</h3>
<ul>
<li>The lack of an official Google Drive client on Linux is debilitating to my workflow.</li>
<li>Handle the third-party Insync client with extreme caution.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://www.behavioraleconomics.com/resources/mini-encyclopedia-of-be/sunk-cost-fallacy/">sunk cost fallacy</a> is a real danger in cases like these.</li>
<li>The hours I lost are probably worth at least a year or two of Dropbox.</li>
<li>Having reliable incremental backups outside of your cloud syncing service remains important.</li>
</ul>
<p>On that last point: Juggling my 500k files between Dropbox, Google Drive, then going live on Google Drive with real work before jumping into the shady world of badly implemented sync clients made me realise (again) the importance of a separate set of incremental backups.</p>
<p>Before my macOS phase (which started on May 6, 2015 when my employer bought me my first MacBook Pro and I wrote in my diary: “Bought 13.3 retina MacBook Pro early 2015, 128 GB SSD. I am doomed.”) I used to maintain a <a href="http://dirvish.org">dirvish</a> backup.</p>
<p>(Dirvish is an amazing tool by the way.)</p>
<p>The truly stupid and frustrating adventure I write about here, did at least lead to some learning, and to me hooking up a <a href="https://www.storagereview.com/seagate_4tb_backup_plus_portable_drive_review">Seagate 4TB external drive</a> to my desk at work. Now when I connect my MacBook, Time Machine performs incremental backups the whole day long.</p>
<p>The next time I have one of these moments of irrationality again, I will at least have the possibility of returning my files to sanity as soon as I do.</p>
<h2 id="thinking-of-future-you">Thinking of future you.</h2>
<p>There was one more learning I wanted to share.</p>
<p>I have mentioned before <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#three">on this blog</a> the well-known productivity trick of writing down, during your morning planning, the two to three really important tasks for the day.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/143-keys-mind/">the Sam Harris podcast where he interviews Derren Brown</a>, they briefly mention a really interesting take or perspective on the tip above.</p>
<p><em>When writing those tasks down, try to predict the two to three tasks the completion of which will satisfy future you the most at the end of the day.</em></p>
<p>It sounds like a small tweak, but this is a great way to encourage deeper (almost meta-)consideration of tasks that will really matter.</p>
<p>Additionally and more straight-forward than that, with this exercise you increase the chances that you end the day with that great feeling of closure that comes with getting important stuff done.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #161: Email Equilibrium.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 07:01:08 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/02/06/weekly-head-voices-161-email-equilibrium/</guid><description> Welcome to the one hundred and sixty first edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looking back at the week from Sunday January 27 to Sunday February 3, 2018.
I am writing this draft in a markdown file, using good old Emacs, during an early morning session (more about that later), because I am still not really loving the Gutenberg block-based editor experience in WordPress 5.0.
Today, I have three stories:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/screenshot_2019-01-31_06-16-47.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/screenshot_2019-01-31_06-16-47.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to the one hundred and sixty first edition of the Weekly Head Voices, looking back at the week from Sunday January 27 to Sunday February 3, 2018.</p>
<p>I am writing this draft in a markdown file, using good old Emacs, during an early morning session (more about that later), because I am still <a href="/2019/01/26/weekly-head-voices-160-write-stuff-down/#btw-1-why-i-dont-yet-like-the-new-wordpress-editor">not really loving the Gutenberg block-based editor experience in WordPress 5.0</a>.</p>
<p>Today, I have three stories:</p>
<h2 id="running-inspiration">Running inspiration</h2>
<p>After a <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#running">month-long normal-shoe-person hiatus</a> at the end of last year which again led to tender ankles, I realised (I’m a slow realiser, ok?) that it’s not the shoes but the person in the shoes.</p>
<p>Because it seemed that the shoes initially offered some relief, I reflexively started increasing distance and speed until my ankles started complaining again.</p>
<p>Durnit!</p>
<p>I then chatted with an erstwhile collaborator who is now, besides still being a successful tech entrepreneur, a successful sandal-wearing ultra runner and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leadville_Trail_100">Leadville Trail 100 mile finisher</a>.</p>
<p>He gave great advice, especially with regard to continuously training complementary muscle groups so that they can better contribute to the whole running mechanism.</p>
<p>Perhaps more importantly (to me) than that, was simply knowing that someone with a history, mechanism and control system not too dissimilar from mine, including the flat feet, runs so far with much joy.</p>
<p>Shortly after the chat, friend LM sent me <a href="https://runrepeat.com/arch-support-study">this highly interesting Run Repeat survey of 150+ studies about arch support</a>.</p>
<p>Amongst other things, it again confirmed what we know about barefoot and minimalist runners running with less impact and more efficiency, two ideas that I really like.</p>
<p>All of this led to me getting back on my Lunas, and my Xeros, and my bare feet.</p>
<p>I have been keeping the distances shorter, and my pace lower.</p>
<p>Initial results are encouraging.</p>
<p>P.S. Of course that survey does not come with a simple answer. However, the quote at the end by itself is worth the price of admission:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>
    If you don’t need an arch support, you probably shouldn’t use one. It is the equivalent of wearing a cast when you don’t have a stress fracture or broken bone. Why would you do that? The best forms of injury prevention are make sure your body is balanced in strength, mobility and flexibility, you are training smart and getting good sleep and nutrition. An arch support affects only one aspect of the body. Don’t forget the big picture.
  </p>
<p>
    A FAR cheaper and more long term solution? Work on you arch, foot and hip strength!!! That is where you are supposed to get “arch support” from. Not some shoe insert. Work on your posterior tibialis, fibularis longus, single leg balance, proprioception, gluteal strength, core strength, body alignment, etc.
  </p>
<p>
<cite>﻿<a href="http://www.doctorsofrunning.com/">Dr Mathew Klein</a></cite>
</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="earlyish-morning-sessions">Early(ish) morning sessions</h2>
<p>It usually takes us until about 20:30 and often up to about 21:00 when all of our GOUs are finally in their beds. There’s a spread of 10 years between the oldest and the youngest, so there’s a wide range of themes and activities keeping us busy until that hour.</p>
<p>In my younger days (ack!) I used to be able to switch my work brain back on at that time, and work quite productively for a few hours.</p>
<p>(It is of course also possible that I just don’t remember this too well. Who knows what’s real anymore?!)</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, it seems that I wrote blog posts, did some more reading and learning, and was generally productive.</p>
<p>More recently however, I’ve noticed that my work brain simply refuses to come back online at nine.</p>
<p>In order to work around this issue, my awake brain devised a plan, during the daylight hours of course.</p>
<p>Instead of trying to force poor work-brain to continue working, I go to bed at 22:00 and set my alarm for 5:30 (the optimal amount of sleep these days is 7.5 hours <em>exactly</em>). It does not seem like much, but I have an extra 50 minutes to an hour of <em>crystal clear</em> time in the mornings before the rest of the family wakes up to start the day.</p>
<p>(I also used to do this in 2012 when we were finishing The Visual Computing in Medicine Book. In Dutchie-land, the kids go to school much later, so I had even more time in the mornings.)</p>
<p>I usually start the morning with a little mindfulness exercise from the Waking Up course (extremely high-stress double-project-lead duties in 2013 were the catalyst that got me into mindfulness and early morning practices in the first place!), then I do <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">the day planner</a>, and <em>then</em> I take care of one or two important activities, the selection of which is usually clear after the day planning.</p>
<p>(It has not escaped me that this whole exercise is quite reminiscent of HN’s <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4166183">startup founder daily routine parody</a>. :).</p>
<p>This morning, I get to write the words you are currently reading, with a clear(ish) mind to boot.</p>
<p>Whether this is just novelty, I don’t know yet, but it currently does seem as if starting the day with a bit of quiet and focus increases the probability the rest of my day at the office also starts more productively.</p>
<h2 id="inbox-under-control-what-is-happening">Inbox under control. WHAT IS HAPPENING?!</h2>
<p>In the old days, I used to be a fan of <a href="/tag/inbox-zero/">inbox zero</a>.</p>
<p>However, due to life stubbornly not adhering to <a href="https://lifehacker.com/merlin-mann-presents-inbox-zero-282544">Merlin Mann’s view of email</a> (quite poetically, it seems that the <a href="http://inboxzero.com">inboxzero.com website</a> is currently down), I eventually ended up with 1000+ unread emails in my inbox. (I know people with multiples of that…)</p>
<p>The term <em>email bankruptcy</em> (shudder) had even come up once or twice in conversations with friends.</p>
<p>Whoops.</p>
<p>I wrote <a href="/2014/04/29/weekly-head-voices-69-no-sugar-added/">back in WHV #69</a> that there seemed to be an inverse correlation between my creativity and inbox-zero.</p>
<p>I still think there is something to be said for that observation.</p>
<p>One can definitely get sucked into busy-work, a prime example of which is the grooming of one’s email, wasting time and energy that could far better be invested in creative pursuits.</p>
<p>However, could it be possible in some situations that one’s email landscape has changed in such a way that it has suddenly become tractable to maintain inbox-zero with a creativity-friendly and entirely affordable amount of energy?</p>
<p>Could it be that because one has let email slip so long, people don’t send as much email anymore, and now one paradoxically has the opportunity to reclaim inbox zero?</p>
<p>It seems it can be.</p>
<p>On January 31, at the tail end of that day’s early morning session, I was staring incredulously at the words:</p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-style-default">
<p>
    This Folder is Empty.
  </p>
<p>
<cite>my inbox</cite>
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t want to call this inbox zero, because it’s not 2007 anymore Dorothy.</p>
<p>Let’s go for Email Equilibrium Startup Founder Parody instead.</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>Friends, thank you for reading this.</p>
<p>I am looking forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #157: Melodramatic.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/11/06/weekly-head-voices-157-melodramatic/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 20:45:10 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/11/06/weekly-head-voices-157-melodramatic/</guid><description> Vergelegen, an important node on my Rome Glen – Vergelegen – Lourensford – Land en Zeezicht route.
It&amp;rsquo;s Monday evening around 22:31.
The track “Still on Fire” by Trentemøller is making my neurons fire in highly pleasant patterns while I try to gaze back through time at the days from Monday October 22 to Sunday November 4, and to gather my thoughts.
I have come to a decision:
The rest of this blog will be less melodramatic.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/vergelegen_entrance.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/11/vergelegen_entrance-1024x542.jpg"
        
            alt="Vergelegen, an important node on my Rome Glen – Vergelegen – Lourensford – Land en Zeezicht route."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Vergelegen, an important node on my Rome Glen – Vergelegen – Lourensford – Land en Zeezicht route.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It&rsquo;s Monday evening around 22:31.</p>
<p>The track <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="https://youtu.be/liHjofQBAeM">“Still on Fire” by Trentemøller</a> is making my neurons fire in highly pleasant patterns while I try to gaze back through time at the days from Monday October 22 to Sunday November 4, and to gather my thoughts.</p>
<p>I have come to a decision:</p>
<p>The rest of this blog will be less melodramatic. Instead, I shall focus my efforts on puns.</p>
<p>(You should still listen to the track.)</p>
<h2 id="productivity-and-focus">Productivity and Focus</h2>
<h3 id="vitamin-r--tomatoes-for-apples">Vitamin-R – tomatoes for apples!</h3>
<p>As a <a href="https://cpbotha.net/?s=mytomatoes">quick search will tell you</a>, we here at the WHV headquarters are big fans of <a href="http://mytomatoes.com/">mytomatoes.com</a>, an online pomodoro timer that keeps track of your pomodori in a truly low friction fashion.</p>
<p>Bonus factoid: mytomatoes was built and is maintained by <a href="https://twitter.com/magnars?lang=en">Magnar Sveen</a>, who is revered, at least in my circles, as a young Emacs god. Take a gander at his <a href="http://emacsrocks.com/">jaw-dropping dexterity and raw nerd power</a>. The <a data-rel="lightbox-video-1" href="https://youtu.be/jNa3axo40qM">one where he uses Emacs to calculate the number of hours his videos have wasted</a> around the world is especially good.</p>
<p>I digress.</p>
<p>Some of us need a constant reminder that we&rsquo;re trapped inside a tomato with absolutely no way to get out.</p>
<p>mytomatoes lives in a browser window, and can easily disappear under the thousands of distractions trying to snatch victory from your ambitious little hands.</p>
<p>No friends. Nothing less than a permanent reminder on the main OSX menubar will do!</p>
<p>I initially made a small misstep with Be Focused Pro. This does satisfy the requirement of displaying a timer in the menubar, but also tries, unfortunately quite badly, to be a task manager, and to connect each pomodoro to a task that you have to create. (As an <a href="https://orgmode.org/">orgmode</a> user, I have infinitely high expectations of any task manager.)</p>
<p>I digress. Again.</p>
<p>After 30 minutes of searching, I fortunately landed on <a href="http://www.publicspace.net/Vitamin-R/">Vitamin-R</a> (the new version 3) on October 29. Since then, it has helped me to churn successfully through an impressive number of pomodori.</p>
<p>Why I&rsquo;m probably going to buy this after the evaluation period:</p>
<ul>
<li>Vitamin-R is exactly configurable enough. I could get it to work exactly like I wanted, without having to wade through an overly complex UI.</li>
<li>I get to log what work I plan to do during each pomodoro, and I get to edit this afterwards, but it&rsquo;s incredibly low friction, i.e. no task creation and so on.</li>
<li>It has a number of simple but useful charts that help me to do better each day.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="multiple-desktops-seem-to-have-been-detrimental-to-my-focus">Multiple-desktops seem to have been detrimental to my focus.</h3>
<p>Back in the early 90s, I started using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_desktop">multiple virtual desktops</a> on my humble Linux 0.99pl13 computer. Because the year of the Linux Desktop was never really to be, we had to console (nerd pun, sorry) ourselves with obscure features like this.</p>
<p>Fast forward a few years, and Ctrl-Alt-SOMENUMBER is deeply ingrained into my muscle memory. 1 is work, 2 is more work, 3 is Emacs (all hail her greatness) and related admin tools, 4 is email and other communication, 5 is browsing and 6 is utility browsing.</p>
<p>This means that a single neuron misfiring leads to my number 5 finger (index) lashing upwards, like some sort of digital (Latin pun intended, work with me here people) cobra, with thumb and pinkie deftly dance-dance-revolutioning over to respectively alt and control, which switches me away from my work (usually 1 or 3) to browsing, all of this in about 3 milliseconds.</p>
<p>This visual shock routinely causes <a href="/2018/05/20/weekly-head-voices-143-the-rider-and-the-elephant/">the rider on my mental elephant</a> to keel over backwards and fall from the large pachyderm.</p>
<p>Hours of web-browsing ensue, during which my already extensive knowledge of useless trivia is expanded, but no to absolutely no work is done.</p>
<p>This stage is usually followed by the guilt, and the crying to sleep, and the renewed chasing of deadlines the next day.</p>
<p>In my feeble but eternal endeavour to increase my focus, I recently tried to mitigate the effects of these misfiring neurons by disabling multiple desktops.</p>
<p>Yes readers, like many of you have wisely been doing all along, I am now limited to a single desktop.</p>
<p>Desktop One: I can&rsquo;t switch there, because I am already here, right now.</p>
<p>Before I started this experiment, I searched for any relevant scientific literature, but came up quite empty. It could be because it&rsquo;s a complicated thing to measure. People are very different, and the computing they do is very different.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, my experience the past two weeks has been positive.</p>
<p>In spite of neurons misfiring and muscle memory invoking key combinations, I have been staring quite dutifully at Desktop One all this time.</p>
<h2 id="two-other-blog-posts-that-you-might-find-interesting-i-dont-know-let-me-know-in-the-comments-or-dont">Two other blog posts that you might find interesting I don&rsquo;t know let me know in the comments or don&rsquo;t.</h2>
<p>Between this and the previous WHV, I wrote two other blog posts that I know of:</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/">Importing all of your orgmode notes into Apple Notes for mobile access</a> – This used to be a huge weakness of my otherwise amazing orgmode-based note-taking: I could not access any of my Orgmode notes from my phone. In the end, all I needed to do was to use Orgmode&rsquo;s built-in HTML site publishing function to get hundreds of org files, including images, math, source code and other wisdom, into my Apple Notes, ready to search and access on the phone.</li>
<li><a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/11/04/pytorch-1-0-preview-nov-4-2018-packages-with-full-cuda-10-support-for-your-ubuntu-18-04-x86_64-systems/">PyTorch 1.0 preview (Nov 4, 2018) packages with full CUDA 10 support for your Ubuntu 18.04 x86_64 systems</a> – The title says it all. The backstory (not in that post) is that I now have a private RTX 2070 With TensorCores(tm) !!!1!! at my disposal, with which I plan to do my part in bringing about the AI-pocalypse. (Actually, I just want the AIs to take away all of our driving licenses. Humans are truly crappy drivers.)</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="gou2-discovers-parts-of-buddhism-in-the-car-on-the-way-to-school">GOU#2 discovers parts of Buddhism in the car on the way to school.</h2>
<p>On Monday, October 23, as we were on our way to school, GOU#2, age 8, explained something she had come to realise.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s about really wanting that certain brilliant and <em>clearly</em> amazing toy.</p>
<p>You want it so much, but you have to wait so long for it.</p>
<p>When you finally do get it, you play with it for a while, but you soon realise that it&rsquo;s really not making you as happy as you thought it would.</p>
<p>I listened carefully to her story.</p>
<p>As far as I could establish, it did sound like a general lesson she had extracted, that is, not just about that one specific dud toy.</p>
<p>I explained to her and GOU#1 that that was a core learning from Buddhism.</p>
<p>We humans desire things, and we go to great lengths to acquire them, and once we have them, we usually realise that the happiness they bring is fleeting at best.</p>
<p>If we are clever, we see this pattern, and so we stop desiring things, instead finding happiness wherever we are right now.</p>
<p>Me?</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m on <em>Desktop One</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #155: Lush.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 07:10:33 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/</guid><description> Happy place: Running on a gravel road somewhere, this time in Wilderness.
HELLO FRIENDS!
Due to being outside so often, I have not been able to make the time to sit down and write to you more regularly over the past weeks.
I did miss you!
Fortunately, I am here now (that was Tuesday, it’s now Friday…) to babble a little bit about my subjective experience of the period of time from Monday September 17 to Sunday October 7.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0814.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0814-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Happy place: Running on a gravel road somewhere, this time in Wilderness."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Happy place: Running on a gravel road somewhere, this time in Wilderness.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>HELLO FRIENDS!</p>
<p>Due to being outside so often, I have not been able to make the time to sit down and write to you more regularly over the past weeks.</p>
<p>I did miss you!</p>
<p>Fortunately, I am here now (that was Tuesday, it’s now Friday…) to babble a little bit about my subjective experience of the period of time from Monday September 17 to Sunday October 7. I did bring pictures!</p>
<h1 id="gous-go-camping-for-their-first-time-ever">GOUs go camping for their first time ever.</h1>
<p>BFS decided to have his birthday party at a camp site called Beaverlac, close to Porterville. Beaverlac is beautiful and offers the additional amazing perk of No Cellular Reception.</p>
<p>The environment looks something like this:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0727.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0727-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="One of the many Beaverlac pools. That water is COLD."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>One of the many Beaverlac pools. That water is COLD.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>To my pleasant surprise, all three GOUs had a roaring time just being outside. Disconnection from the outside world was simply accepted as a given, which contributed significantly to their experience.</p>
<p>Before we move on to the next bit, a word to the wise: Your front wheel drive car will probably not be able to pull a trailer of any significant mass up the mountain when you leave Beaverlac. (There is only that one torturous way out, filled with thousands upon thousands of loose little stones…)</p>
<p>We learned this the hard way. Fortunately, the vehicle BFS had arranged for the weekend was an all-wheel drive, and so, after half an hour of hitching-unhitching-and-hitching again various trailers, we all managed to get back up to the top of the mountain.</p>
<h1 id="spring-break-in-wilderness">Spring break in Wilderness.</h1>
<p>The week after that, we left to spend a few days of the school spring break in Wilderness.</p>
<p>Having grown up in the Winelands, Wilderness is a whole different kind of pretty.</p>
<p>Wilderness has it all (say in <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="https://youtu.be/NkdlM_vO3I8">Stefon voice</a> for maximum effect):</p>
<p>Verdant, all enveloping forests, rivers snaking everywhere, mountains and a beautiful coastline.</p>
<p>If they had called the place “LUSH” instead of “WILDERNESS”, that would also have been quite apt.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0867.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0867-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The top of Big Tree of the Knysna Forests. Also known as the Outeniqua Yellowood, this specific one is about 800 years old."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The top of Big Tree of the Knysna Forests. Also known as the Outeniqua Yellowood, this specific one is about 800 years old.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<h1 id="productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">Productivity pro-tip: Fool yourself into doing a good daily review.</h1>
<p>Many productivity systems, including GTD, recommend or sometimes even require that one performs a regular review of one’s task system. This always looks quite good on paper, but this activity somehow falls often and easily to the wayside.</p>
<p>In the latest evolution of my orgmode task management evolution, the checklist I mentioned in a <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">WHV #126</a> has become much more useful.</p>
<p>I now have a standard day planner template which I activate in the mornings by pressing a specific Emacs keyboard shortcut (C-c c p if you must know, it’s just an orgmode capture template).</p>
<p>This is a long(ish) checklist that ensures I review all of the important elements of my planning:</p>
<ul>
<li>Longer term goals and reminders which I update every month. This includes which books I want to finish reading, which longer term projects I need to think about, and so on.</li>
<li>My calendar for the day. Yes, I need to be reminded to double-check my calendar for any unexpected meetings.</li>
<li>The “00 ToDo” folder in my email. I sometimes move emails in there from my telephone. These need to be processed and turned into real todos.</li>
<li>The main list of orgmode tasks. These are extracted on-demand from my monthly journal and the various project files I maintain in orgmode.</li>
<li>macOS / iOS reminders. Don’t judge me. Sometimes I voice-command one of my iDevices that I should do this or that on this or that day, at which point they get added to the synchronised list of reminders. This review step ensures that I take care of those.</li>
</ul>
<p>The check list has an additional section with a list of habits that I try to build and maintain. This includes check list items for my sleep hours the previous night, the number of pomodori I complete (and whether I’m happy with that specific number) and whether I’ve read and thought enough for the day.</p>
<p>As with all of these systems, this one is far from perfect, but there are two things I specifically like about it:</p>
<ol>
<li>It takes a single keypress in the morning to create and configure the checklist.</li>
<li>Checklists are amazing. In this case, the checklist is helping me to pull reminders of various kinds from a range of different sources, which enables me to exert a just a little more control over my daily evolution.</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="slippery-slippery-focus">Slippery slippery focus.</h1>
<p>Sometimes it feels like I have to spend the majority of my time just ensuring that I focus on the important stuff.</p>
<p>For an example, see the previous section.</p>
<p>A normal part of mindfulness meditation, is recognising when your attention wanders, and then just bringing your attention back to the breath.</p>
<p>In spite of the fact that this is an extremely well-known aspect of mindfulness, it has taken me until fairly recently to make peace with the fact that my normal daily focus (although sometimes it somehow finds itself in flow, which is amazing when it happens) will in many cases follow the same pattern.</p>
<p>Like many of you, I have the feeling that there’s an extremely complicated equation describing the relationship between sleep, diet, mood, time of day, environment, and so on, on the one hand and sustained focus on the other. I have an extremely rough idea how many of these affect focus, but on many days, experience breaks all of the rules.</p>
<p>Long story short, until we figure out how exactly to manipulate focus, I accept that the best way to handle the slippery focus problem, is, just like in mindfulness, to accept that it will never really stop wavering, and rather to work on recognising this wavering, and then simply bringing that focus back.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0911.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/10/IMG_0911-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="Flat white at La Belle Alliance in Swellendam."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Flat white at La Belle Alliance in Swellendam.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #135: It’s all rainbows and unicorns, no really!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2018/03/11/weekly-head-voices-135-its-all-rainbows-and-unicorns-no-really/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Mar 2018 20:04:08 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2018/03/11/weekly-head-voices-135-its-all-rainbows-and-unicorns-no-really/</guid><description> This rainbow unicorn, floating serenely on a cloudy background, is winking right at you. Down below, we are celebrating GOU #3’s second birthday. Photo taken with the expert assistance of GOU#1, age 11 going on 32.
Hi there friends, welcome back to the weekly (!!!) head voices! I missed you.
Software Release Frazzle Releasing desktop software, even for a small group of people, can get tricky quickly yo!
Yes, people still write desktop software, and we do love doing it.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/rainbow_unicorn_2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/rainbow_unicorn_2.jpg"
        
            alt="This rainbow unicorn, floating serenely on a cloudy background, is winking right at you. Down below, we are celebrating GOU #3’s second birthday. Photo taken with the expert assistance of GOU#1, age 11 going on 32."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>This rainbow unicorn, floating serenely on a cloudy background, is winking right at you. Down below, we are celebrating GOU #3’s second birthday. Photo taken with the expert assistance of GOU#1, age 11 going on 32.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Hi there friends, welcome back to the weekly (!!!) head voices! I missed you.</p>
<h1 id="software-release-frazzle">Software Release Frazzle</h1>
<p>Releasing desktop software, even for a small group of people, can get tricky quickly yo!</p>
<p>Yes, people still write desktop software, and we do love doing it. However, compared to web-apps, there are some additional challenges.</p>
<p>One can’t easily roll-out an incremental fix while no-one is watching, because every release is a significant event where users have to go to the effort of downloading and installing your baby.</p>
<p>It’s a fairly new product, so our release process is still being refined. Long story short, we caught a bug on the release platform (we develop cross-platform, but deploy for a single platform) shortly before release and so we really had to scramble to fix. This, together with the fact that the preparations for the release were already generally intense, left me quite frazzled by Wednesday evening after dinner.</p>
<p>Lesson learned: In a cross-platform development, don’t allow <em>any</em> dependency version discrepancies between platforms, no matter if it causes developer inconvenience.</p>
<h1 id="unicorns-and-rainbows">Unicorns and rainbows</h1>
<p>GOU #3 turned 2 on Thursday.</p>
<p>The littlest genetic offspring unit seems to be verbally well developed. She’s already using words like “eintlik” (“eigenlijk” in Dutch, “actually” in English) in fairly well-structured sentences. I have taught her to say phrases like “universiteit” and “lekker internet”, which she does with a smile.</p>
<p>She is able to express her wants and needs at a level which exceeds that of some 30 year olds.</p>
<p>Anyways, yesterday we held a birthday party for her.</p>
<p>It was a fabulously enjoyable affair with far too many delectable delicacies, and more than sufficient amounts of craft beer and good wine (expensive local Chardonnay is my current preference, if you must know).</p>
<p>It was beautiful to see so much of the family together in one place, all connecting like we humans should be doing as often as we can, but often don’t.</p>
<p>Thank you little GOU #3, for everything.</p>
<h1 id="your-complimentary-grab-bag-of-interesting-cocktail-party-conversational-tidbits">Your complimentary grab-bag of interesting cocktail party conversational tidbits</h1>
<h2 id="trump--brexit-voters-were-scared">Trump / Brexit voters were scared.</h2>
<p>In my <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#the-bad-with-a-hopefully-slightly-positive-outlook-at-the-end">2016 to 2017 transition post</a>, I lamented the observation that for both Brexit and the Trumpocalypse, a lower level of education was the strongest indicator for a vote for leave and for Trump respectively.</p>
<p>A new study by the Queensland University of Technology has now shown that in both cases <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2018-03/quot-2be030818.php">the vote for Brexit / Trump was also driven by fear</a>. It also makes the scary point that the respective campaigns deliberately targeted this fear, which is more than worrisome.</p>
<p>Use this tidbit with care, or right before you were planning to leave the party anyways.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-defend-your-exercise-addiction">How to defend your exercise addiction</h2>
<p><a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/acel.12750/full">A recent study published in Aging Cell</a>, showed that older people who exercised regularly (in this case cycling), had the same levels of T-cells as 20 year olds. In other words, their immune systems are as effective as people a fraction of their age.</p>
<p>One of the co-authors of the study, 82-year old Prof Norman Lazarus (who himself cycles 100km at a time), <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/health-43308729">summarised it neatly in the media as follows</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>If exercise was a pill, everyone would be taking it.</strong> It has wide-ranging benefits for the body, the mind, for our muscles and our immune system.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(I like how he casually takes aim at our pill-obsession.)</p>
<h2 id="the-carmack-productivity-method-cpm">The Carmack Productivity Method (CPM)</h2>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Carmack">John Carmack</a> is the modern-day genius who was the lead programmer of genre- and era-defining games like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wolfenstein_3D">Wolfenstein 3D</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(1993_video_game)">DOOM</a> (“one of the most significant and influential titles in video game history”) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quake_(video_game)">Quake</a>. During working on these projects, he invented a number of important computer graphics techniques.</p>
<p>It turns out that Carmack is not only a genius, but a productivity and focus <em>monster</em>.</p>
<p>In <a href="http://bookofhook.blogspot.co.za/2013/03/smart-guy-productivity-pitfalls.html">this 2013 blog post</a>, a colleague of Carmack at id Software describes how Carmack would apparently play CDs while he was working. If he was checking his email, or if he was interrupted by a colleague, or he needed to go to the bathroom, in other words, if he was not focusing on the core of his work, he would pause the CD player.</p>
<p>By the end of the day, he knew exactly how much focused work he had done by how far he had gotten through his playlist.</p>
<p>Compared to the interrupt-driven way programmers work today (thanks internet!) this sounds like an amazingly visceral way to recognise and signal interruptions in your flow: THE MUSIC SIMPLY STOPS.</p>
<p>Would you be able to implement something like this for your work?</p>
<h1 id="à-bientôt">À bientôt</h1>
<p>Thank you very much for stopping by! Have a productive week, and don’t forget to exercise.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>