<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Productivity on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/productivity/</link><description>Recent content in Productivity on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #261: Father's day</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 13:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/</guid><description>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.
Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive
The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.
&amp;ndash; Marcel Proust
Bliss It&amp;rsquo;s father&amp;rsquo;s day today.
When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period from Tuesday, April 22 to Sunday, June 15, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250428_clarence_pano.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_9407df7811cef8cf.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_4f5b997776ce1c56.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_72fa3b251facc47.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/20250428_clarence_pano_hu_bdfc48c092e2df2.webp"
            

        
            alt="Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Another beautiful view from Clarence Drive</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<blockquote>
<p>The real voyage of discovery consists not in seeking new landscapes, but in having new eyes.</p>
<p>&ndash; Marcel Proust</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="bliss">Bliss</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s father&rsquo;s day today.</p>
<p>When I woke up and went to say good morning to Genetic Offspring Unit (GOU) #3, she gave me the card she made, with a rainbow and a red heart and a sweet hand-written message in 9-year-old Afrikaans.</p>
<p>Hearing that we were up, GOU #2 came out of her room, with a beautiful illustration she had made for (and of!) me. (GOU #2 has found her passion in drawing. She practises on most days, and her skill and talent are very obvious.)</p>
<p>Soon after, GOU #1 arrived home with flat whites (my favourite), fresh ciabatta and croissants from the bakery, and hugs.</p>
<p>What I&rsquo;m trying to say here is that when your offspring units all tell you in their different ways that they appreciate you being their dad, when you&rsquo;re fundamentally dedicated to and deeply grateful for being just that, and those very offspring units constitute the whole focus of this important life endeavour, you better hope that you are able to keep those eyes dry.</p>
<h2 id="vo-max-redux">VO₂ Max redux</h2>
<p>One of my <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">exercise goals for 2024</a> was to reach a VO₂ Max of at least (HAHAHA) 50.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t make it in 2024, but I also didn&rsquo;t do anything other than just my normal running during the year. I know that I should probably engage in some high intensity interval training of some sort if I really want to move the needle, but I run because I like running and not because I want to be fit, although I do want to be fit. (It&rsquo;s complicated being a teenager.)</p>
<p>At the start of 2025, I stated, much more softly this time, that I would maybe <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#running-and-exercise">still like to hit that 50 VO₂ Max</a>.</p>
<p>Again I realized I would have probably have to <em>do</em> something interval-ly about it, but again I kept on postponing.</p>
<p>WELL KIDS it turns out that postponing can also be a winning strategy! On Monday, May 19, my Garmin reported that I had indeed hit a VO₂ Max of 50, which, <a href="https://www8.garmin.com/manuals/webhelp/GUID-C001C335-A8EC-4A41-AB0E-BAC434259F92/EN-US/GUID-1FBCCD9E-19E1-4E4C-BD60-1793B5B97EB3.html">according to its tables</a>, places me at the bottom of the coveted top-most category for my age and gender, namely <em>Superior</em>.</p>
<p>I always knew it, but thanks anyways Garmin!</p>
<p>P.S. I do have to deflate my <em>superiority</em> a bit by reminding us all that, in addition to finding myself at the bottom of the superior range, I have also only recently entered my current age section, giving me an extra advantage. Jokes aside, 50 at 50 is not bad, so allow me to bask for a while.</p>
<h2 id="org-mode-timestamps-in-obsidian">org-mode timestamps in obsidian</h2>
<p>One feature I have really been missing in Obsidian since <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my recent break-up with Org-mode</a> is the amazing org timestamps.</p>
<p>There is no real convention in Obsidian, whilst in Org-mode timestamps <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Timestamps.html">are well-defined and quite functional</a>. My &ldquo;old&rdquo; notes are scattered with them: time ranges, scheduled times, deadlines, random timestamps inside random text notes.</p>
<p>The time logging script <a href="/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/#loggin-time">I mentioned previously</a> made use of the dataview-convention of adding timestamps to work items for example:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 (start:: 2025-05-20T07:55) - (end:: 2025-05-20T08:10)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; which did work but was no fun to work with.</p>
<p>Long story short, I could not resist for much longer, and so I hacked together a new Obsidian plugin called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian-org-timestamps">Org timestamps</a>.</p>
<p>As you can see in the comparative screenshots below, I&rsquo;ve copied the org-mode timestamp and time range format verbatim, with the additional bonus of rendering these timestamps nicely in preview mode, inspired by <a href="https://github.com/minad/org-modern">the Emacs package org-modern</a>.</p>
<p>Deviating from org-mode proper, my plugin also renders date-less timestamps &ndash; I often use these when adding entries to daily file. Speaking of which, full org timestamps can have <code>[[...]]</code> links around the date parts so that they link back to the relevant daily file.</p>








    


<figure><a href="obsidian-org-timestamps.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_e1ef46eb4edabd57.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_2719acebe5e07bc9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_f52dbf2785777e5.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/06/16/weekly-head-voices-261-fathers-day/obsidian-org-timestamps_hu_85c7a76b567140b9.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>In addition to the rendering, the plugin also offers commands to move any timestamps to the nearest 5 minutes forward or backward, similar to what org-mode does with <code>shift-up/down</code>, and a feature I have always used multiple times per day.</p>
<p>Putting all of this together, my monthly time logging files now has entries that look like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>## theme 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> project 1
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#cf222e">-</span> task 1 &lt;2025-05-20 07:55-08:10&gt;
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; and I can tweak those timestamps with the adjustment commands.</p>
<p>I have adapted the logging script to support both the old dataview-style and org-timestamp-style timestamps, and now the barely usable UX has become a tad less barely.</p>
<p><em>(10 minutes later&hellip;)</em></p>
<p>Because I keep on mentioning the script, I guess it&rsquo;s time to <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/obsidian_dataview_timelogging">put it online</a>, albeit extremely barely. Let me know in the comments below if you are the one other user on the planet who would like to try this.</p>
<h2 id="my-friend-this-is-the-end-again">My friend this is the end again</h2>
<p>This was one of the most stubborn WHVs I have pushed out in a very long time.</p>
<p>Before it became this hard, it used to be easier: Somehow there was always something to talk about, either interesting or entertaining, or both.</p>
<p>Although this could also just be another symptom of  me getting older, it does feel like the whole online landscape has changed quite substantially.</p>
<p>Up until recently, it was only dopamine-targeting social media which affected the way people read (or don&rsquo;t) blog posts, but these days I imagine that I&rsquo;m also detecting a whiff of AI-nihilism. Although I still feel strongly about writing each of these words by myself, the experience of the resultant output happens on the background of machines that can now generate hundreds of perfectly-written versions of this post in an instant.</p>
<p>Anyways, I plan to continue with this labour of love, even as it becomes increasingly difficult.</p>
<p>P.S. My recent reading / book-listening has taken me on fascinating journeys through neuroscience and consciousness. Before reaching this point right here, I mistakenly thought that I would share more about them in this post. Instead I&rsquo;m going to leave you with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I am not a thing in the world; I am the space in which the world is happening.</p>
<p>&ndash; Richard Lang</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #260: I'm not your guy, buddy</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/</guid><description>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.
The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay. GOU #3 (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining. It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This wildly-non-weekly 260th edition of the Weekly Head Voices covers the period of my life, exceptionally patchily, from Wednesday, March 12 to Monday, April 21, 2025.</p>








    


<figure><a href="20250322_palmiet_hike.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_94326a752c7d0837.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_3039937a478d9ff0.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_95661b4813429562.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/20250322_palmiet_hike_hu_43ba0c8877284452.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>The photo above is from a little family hike down to the Palmiet river mouth, next to Betty&rsquo;s Bay. <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU #3</a> (now 9), seemed to enjoy the first bit, but then suddenly did not, which usually leads to quite a bit of complaining.  It was really great to see her perk up again when I returned with the car to pick them up more quickly than she expected. (All of that running exercise has a purpose you know.)</p>
<p>A week or two later, GOU #3 recovered by being an absolute trooper through the whole of the slightly more substantial and absolutely brilliant 6.5km family hike all around the little <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/rreQJ7uyT1SFSKfJ7">Sea Farm private reserve&rsquo;s peninsula</a>. I tell myself, and others, that this is partially due to involving her in the progress of the event, by showing her at regular intervals on Google Maps exactly where we found ourselves, and how we were making progress around the peninsula.</p>
<p>Maybe one day, we will both have better answers to the question:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why am I in such a rush to get through life when I want so much to enjoy it?</p>
<p>&ndash; Jan Chozen Bays</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(With that in mind, you might also find <a href="/2022/02/03/weekly-head-voices-237-dont-step-over-the-thing/#i-don-t-want-to-step-over-the-thing">WHV #237</a> interesting!)</p>
<h2 id="the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-migrates-again">The whole cpbotha.net-hive migrates again</h2>
<p>Slightly more than five years after <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">the previous migration of the whole so-called cpbotha.net-hive from WebFaction (RIP) to Hetzner</a>, I got an offer I could not refuse, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/mackuba.eu/post/3ll7dgrep7c25">on Bluesky (!)</a>, for a <a href="https://www.netcup.com/en/server/vps/vps-1000-g11-12m-iv">netcup VPS</a> with double the number of vCPUs, double the RAM and 5x the storage, all for about 25% cheaper every month.</p>
<p>On the weekend of March 28 I managed to port the six websites in question across (3 easy static ones, including this blog, and 3 slightly more tricky wordpress ones).</p>
<p>I am most grateful that as part of this porting effort I have now finally been able to dockerize the binaries I built years ago of the super obscure <a href="https://github.com/ma-tech/WlzIIPSrv">WlzIIPSrv fork of the C++ IIP image slice server</a> and will in future be able to migrate much more easily if I ever need to do so again. WlzIIPSrv is the software that serves the pannable and zoomable histology slices when you browse a <a href="https://visible-orbit.org/slices/dk2904l-registered/">visible-orbit.org (wordpress site also hosted on this new server) stack like this one</a>.</p>
<p>Although this migration is a significant and positive technical event for me, most of you will probably not even notice that this site responds a tad (or three) more snappily than it used to.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, I am celebrating that this is officially the first blog post coming to you from this shiny new server!</p>
<h2 id="productivity-devolution">Productivity (d)evolution</h2>
<h3 id="just-get-it-done-with-kanban">Just get it done with Kanban</h3>
<p>Someone once called using Trello for task management &ldquo;the time management connoisseur equivalent of lying in the gutter with a cheap bottle of wine in a brown paper bag&rdquo;.</p>
<p>(So, by the way, that someone was me! See <a href="/2014/11/27/weekly-head-voices-86-beardy/#note-taking-and-todo-system-chaos-nerd-warning">the previous admission on this blog, in WHV #86 from 2014</a>, original source of my statement is <a href="https://noeskasmit.com/comparison-of-task-managers-rtm-astrid-wunderlist-todoist/#comment-71">this comment on Noeska&rsquo;s blog</a>.)</p>
<p>I mention this now, because my current system, the one which has to act as replacement for <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#a-bient%C3%B4t-monsieur-org">my almighty Emacs Org-mode</a>, is a monthly Kanban board with columns for &ldquo;todo&rdquo;, &ldquo;today / next&rdquo;, &ldquo;doing&rdquo; and &ldquo;done&rdquo;, and task cards that I can move, quite satisfyingly, from column to column, which is essentially a less full-featured but fully local version of my old Trello-based system.</p>
<p>While the 2014-org-mode-me mind really cannot comprehend this, the current system, based on the plugins <a href="https://github.com/mgmeyers/obsidian-kanban">obsidian-kanban</a> and <a href="https://publish.obsidian.md/tasks/Introduction">obsidian-tasks</a>, is working just fine for the moment.</p>
<h3 id="pomodori-made-from-100-xbar">pomodori made from 100% xbar</h3>
<p>You might recall from the previous WHV that I was still <a href="/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/#productivity-hack-of-the-year">using Emacs as an over-powered pomodoro timer</a>.</p>
<p>Well, even that started itching a bit too much, and now I&rsquo;ve just re-implemented the whole thing, along with the productivity boosting auto-DnD setting, by <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/xbar-pomodoro-timer-with-DnD-for-macOS">modifying an existing self-contained macOS xbar script</a> which you can use if you too wish to work harder.</p>
<h3 id="loggin-time">Loggin&rsquo; time</h3>
<p>Together with the pomodoro timing, I was also using org-mode to maintain detailed time logs for work, using the built-in org-clock functionality.</p>
<p>Because of above-mentioned itch, I now have a semi-usable replacement which I put together as an <a href="https://blacksmithgu.github.io/obsidian-dataview/api/code-reference/#dvviewpath-input">Obsidian Dataview custom view</a>, in other words, a bunch of javascript that piggy-backs on the dataview parser and groups bullet items with start and end timestamps under their parent tasks and container headings, as projects, in order to spit out daily and monthly timelog breakdowns.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve only been testing this since the start of April. Although it&rsquo;s giving me all of the data that I need, the UX is just barely over the threshold of usable-by-me.</p>
<p>Perhaps in the coming weeks I&rsquo;ll find some time to write more about this tool to hear what others think.</p>
<h2 id="the-bozo-explosion">The Bozo explosion</h2>
<p>My great friend Dave told me about this phenomenon, of which I then had to go find the source.</p>
<p>It turns out the originator is none other than Steve Jobs, with the idea being injected into the internet hive-mind by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guy_Kawasaki">Guy Kawasaki</a>, a Guy who worked for Jobs at Apple (I see what I&rsquo;m doing here) from 1983 until about 1986.</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a short but great post by Guy Kawasaki titled <a href="https://guykawasaki.com/what-i-learned-from-steve-jobs/">What I Learned From Steve Jobs</a> which is definitely worth a few minutes of your time.</p>
<p>Here I want to focus on point 9, namely &ldquo;A players hire A+ players&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve personally seen this a number of times with the smartest and best leaders I&rsquo;ve ever had the privilege of interacting with. They, the A players, actively seek and appoint colleagues who are smarter or better than they are, the A+ players. They absolutely revel in the opportunity of being challenged by the best people they can find. This turns into a positive feedback loop, with more and more similarly capable people seeking out their peers.</p>
<p>The opposite of this happens when you start with B players. B players easily feel threatened by more capable folks, and so they tend to recruit C players so that they can maintain the pecking order. Those C players will accordingly recruit D players and so on. This process of course leads to what Jobs coined as &ldquo;the Bozo explosion&rdquo;, which sounds frighteningly similar to what is currently happening in some parts of the world today.</p>
<p>Next time when you&rsquo;re evaluating a new opportunity, do make some time to ensure that the folks involved have the A player mentality.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>For future me, here&rsquo;s a list of other notable events from the period under review:</p>
<ul>
<li>Two 50th celebrations.</li>
<li>Various very special eating and drinking occasions with treasured friends, some from afar, and family.</li>
<li>Three family hikes.</li>
<li>1 Sting concert (with my life partner) which exceeded all my expectations.</li>
<li>My first running race (Spookhill challenge).</li>
<li>Visits with Parisian friends and family to the breathtaking <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeitz_Museum_of_Contemporary_Art_Africa">Zeitz Museum of Contemporary Art Africa (MOCAA)</a> and the Two Oceans aquarium.</li>
<li>Far too many marshmallow eggs.</li>
</ul>
<p>&hellip; and with that, I would like to leave you with this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The trick is to learn how to want the things you already have.</p>
<p>&ndash; William B. Irvine</p>
</blockquote>








    


<figure><a href="zeitz_mocaa_ocular.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7e8591922bb9e2d9.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_426183b3ab1ebea9.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_7a603b5cd15f6d27.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/04/22/weekly-head-voices-260-not-your-guy-buddy/zeitz_mocaa_ocular_hu_cf675cf4d544cfde.webp"
            

        
            alt="Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Top floor of Zeitz MOCAA, looking at the Ocular restaurant</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<!-- "not your guy, buddy" from the South Park episode "Canada on strike" https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1211261/characters/nm0005295/ --> ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #259: Backbone</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</link><pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/</guid><description> Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!
(I just learned that the English connoisseur comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved connaisseur (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little oi.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







    


<figure><a href="bettys_sunset.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_84d7d5fb2023d1f3.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_94ef9e4fb9dd976e.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_b061658b14bcf3ec.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/bettys_sunset_hu_52ae292c79f1df4c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Well hello there you old-school blog enjoyer, you internet connoisseur you!</p>
<p>(I <em>just</em> learned that the English <a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/connoisseur"><em>connoisseur</em> comes from the now obsolete pre-1835 French spelling</a>. The originators of the term have since moved on to the new and improved <em>connaisseur</em> (like the Dutch, which is why I was briefly confused), but in English we are stuck with our quaint little <em>oi</em>.)</p>
<h2 id="how-do-you-do-fellow-humans">How do you do, fellow humans?</h2>
<p>This Sunday morning I browsed through all of my Obsidian daily entries, starting from Monday January 20, the day after <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/">The 2024 to 2025 transition post</a> appeared, because the urge to write here has become quite persistent of late, an urge that is clearly quite oblivious to my feeling that it has become increasingly more tricky to make the time to sit down and focus on just this one thing.</p>
<p>I, very briefly I should add, considered feeding all of those daily posts to one of our artificial friends to extract highlights, but for the time-being, I really like that every word you read here was produced by my laborious and messy (fluids-based, for the most part) biology-based process.</p>
<p>This means that I read every single stupid word I wrote in those daily entries, re-experienced various emotions, some of them transformed by the ever-changing self, while I read them, and let those ideas all simmer for a while in the wetware mostly enclosed by my skull, before sitting down here and producing a new set of emotions whilst typing out a bunch of new words on this (mechanical) keyword.</p>
<p>Blood, sweat and tears my friends, blood sweat and tears.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Since my last entry here, I&rsquo;ve been reading a lot more, something that I&rsquo;m really happy about.</p>
<p>Besides the deep-seated and strong instinct that reading good books makes me a better human, it also turns out to be an <em>excellent</em> doom-scrolling suppressant, by virtue of simply pushing that activity out of one&rsquo;s daily schedule.</p>
<p>Apart from that motivation, what has made a huge difference in my reading volume was adding audiobooks as well as Zotero on my laptop to the reading modality mix.</p>
<p>Where I previously would only read on my Kindle e-reader, I&rsquo;ve discovered that picking the right medium for the right book means I can comfortably use these three channels during different phases of the day.</p>
<p>In the evening right before closing my eyes, I usually read fiction on the Kindle. After 10 to 20 minutes of reading, my eyes start closing of their own accord and my brain shuts down. Current Kindle book: <a href="https://www.gregegan.net/MORPHOTROPHIC/MORPHOTROPHIC.html">Morphotrophic by Greg Egan</a>. <a href="/2022/03/21/weekly-head-voices-240-i-am-just-a-copy-of-a-copy-of-a-copy/#permutation-city">Egan has previously appeared on this blog</a> for a much older creation which I really loved.</p>
<p>During the day in the car on short commutes, I prefer to read non-fiction books like <a href="https://www.ynharari.com/book/nexus/">Nexus by Yuval Harari</a> (which I loved by the way). With Nexus at 1.5x speed, which is still very comfortable, it was around 17 hours of listening time which went by a lot faster than I expected. I&rsquo;m currently on [<em>Behave: The Biology of Humans at Our Best and Worst</em> by Robert M. Sapolsky] which is super entertaining and extremely successful at repeatedly blowing my mind.</p>
<p>Some non-fiction books deserve even closer attention, like <a href="https://www.abriefhistoryofintelligence.com/">Max Bennett&rsquo;s <em>A Brief History of Intelligence</em></a>, which I started reading on my Kindle but then completed on my laptop, using the fantastic epub reader in Zotero. With this tool I can make highlights and notes to my heart&rsquo;s content.</p>








    


<figure><a href="screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett.webp">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_fd5d3cc24c0400cb.webp 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_ded6f76846ff592d.webp 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_a10ae5587078729c.webp 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2025/03/11/weekly-head-voices-259-backbone/screenshot_zotero_bhoi_bennett_hu_1b09363d2d5128c.webp"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>On the topic of Zotero, the two features that would make it even more perfect for me are <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/pull/836">the iOS epub support</a>, so I can open annotated epubs on the go, and <a href="https://github.com/zotero/zotero-ios/issues/597">iOS webpage snapshot support</a>, so that I can save <a href="https://github.com/gildas-lormeau/SingleFile">SingleFile</a> snapshots of web pages from my phone like on desktop, and not just the link.</p>
<h3 id="thanks-for-nothing-amazon">Thanks for nothing Amazon</h3>
<p>On that topic, <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/02/psa-amazon-kills-download-transfer-via-usb-option-for-kindles-this-week/">on February 26 Amazon killed the Kindle &ldquo;download &amp; transfer via USB&rdquo; feature</a>, the exact feature that I&rsquo;ve always used to make copies of Kindle titles for my own use, most often for highlighting and further study, sometimes leading to <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/book/">book notes posts</a>.</p>
<p>Although I really appreciated the convenience of e.g. hearing about a book, and then being able to purchase and start reading that book within minutes, this user-hostile move by Amazon is the last straw for me.  All the way back in 2016, <a href="https://mentat.za.net/blog/2016/08/21/amazon-owns-your-ebooks/">friend Stéfan warned us all about the Kindle Swindle</a>, i.e. the way that Amazon restricts ebook rights far more than necessary, and is in essence able to &ldquo;switch off&rdquo; all ebooks that you have bought.</p>
<p>For me personally, this latest move just means that I will drastically reduce my spending on Kindle books, and anything else from Amazon, as far as possible.</p>
<h2 id="101-productivity-hacks-for-stubborn-people">101 productivity hacks for stubborn people</h2>
<p>Also known as The Productivity Section!</p>
<h3 id="a-bientôt-monsieur-org">A bientôt monsieur Org</h3>
<p>In the 24/25 year transition post I talked about <a href="/2025/01/19/the-2024-to-2025-transition-post/#emacs-and-obsidian">my apparently eternally brewing personal tension between Emacs and Obsidian</a>.</p>
<p>It looks like I might have found myself in the third <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_stages_of_grief">stage of grief</a>, namely <em>bargaining</em>, when I wrote that I would explore the interplay between the two poles of Emacs and Obsidian.</p>
<p>Well, as I write this, it feels like I might have reached the fifth and final stage, namely <em>acceptance</em>, acceptance of the fact that orgmode (note, not Emacs, but orgmode), although far more powerful and flexible, is probably always going to be the silo that it currently is, in contrast to markdown (note, not necessarily Obsidian) which, while functionality-wise is but a shadow of orgmode, is hugely more accessible and inter-operates with everyone and their dogs.</p>
<p>You see, since writing that transition post, I&rsquo;ve been creating more and more markdown notes, to the extent that I keep on running into the inconvenience of orgmode nexus nodes which I can in theory link to from markdown, but with links that are not as fully featured as markdown to markdown links.</p>
<p>It really does seem like &ldquo;interplay&rdquo; is turning into &ldquo;dominance&rdquo;, if you&rsquo;ll excuse my multiple layers of innuendo here.</p>
<p>And so after a really good 10 year run as orgmode-disciple, as chronicled by <a href="https://vxlabs.com/tags/orgmode/">10+ years of vxlabs posts on the topic</a>, a bunch of <a href="/tags/orgmode/">appearances on this blog</a> and even <a href="https://orgmode-exocortex.com/">the orgmode-exocortex</a>, it&rsquo;s time to read the writing on the wall, writing that upon closer inspection has turned out to be in markdown format after all.</p>
<h3 id="productivity-hack-of-the-year">Productivity hack of the year</h3>
<p>In a textbook case of <a href="https://quoteinvestigator.com/2024/06/07/report-death/">greatly exaggerated rumours of someone&rsquo;s demise</a>, my orgmode isn&rsquo;t completely dead yet&hellip;</p>
<p>By far the most effective productivity hack I&rsquo;ve implemented in many months, in terms of actual focus hours gained, has been the <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar">orgmode-based pomodoro timer I hacked together and wrote about in my other OTHER website TIL section</a>.</p>
<p>While it was already helpful to have a boring text-based pomodoro-timer display a countdown on my macOS menubar, I had wildly underestimated how much impact the addition of <a href="https://charlbotha.com/til/Show-Emacs-org-timer-countdown-in-macOS-menubar#double-bonus-macos-do-not-disturb-during-pomodoro">the automatic do-not-disturb mode</a> would have.</p>
<p>When I start the 25 minute pomodoro focus timer, my script automatically activates the so-called do-not-disturb &ldquo;focus&rdquo; across all of my (Apple) devices. For those 25 minutes, absolutely nothing pings or alerts, and only calls by my my inner-inner circle can get through. When the 25 minutes are up, DnD is disabled across all devices, and I can see to any emergencies that might have occurred.</p>
<p>(🍅 These particular paragraphs are being typed within such an interruption-proof pomodoro BTW.)</p>
<h2 id="how-are-the-children">How are the children?</h2>
<p>Why thank you for asking!</p>
<p>Here I would like to mention that Genetic Offspring Unit #1 (GOU#1) has now experienced the first few weeks of industrial engineering at university (which is the same as the first few weeks of most of the engineering disciplines) and seems to be loving it to bits.</p>
<p>It brings me great joy that, in spite of the fact that she is a wonderfully well-adjusted and socially graceful human, her engineering DNA is shining through brilliantly. This way of thinking suits her, she just seems to get it, and she&rsquo;s really <em>enjoying the work</em>.</p>
<p>P.S. It also brings me joy, but also a tiny bit of concern, that she really enjoys and also sometimes makes dad jokes <em>AT ME</em>.</p>
<h2 id="spiritual-hygiene-backbone">Spiritual hygiene backbone</h2>
<p>All of that reading I wrote about a few paragraphs back somehow happens even when my days seem to fall apart due to general life chaos, various distractions many of my own (unintentional design) and/or due to will power failure on my part.</p>
<p>So on those days, when I finally fall asleep reading, I console myself with the affirmation that the day was not <em>complete</em> chaos, at least I&rsquo;ve done some reading&hellip;</p>
<p>The same goes for my running.</p>
<p>A seemingly low-level function somewhere in my system <em>needs</em> to take me out running an average of three times a week.</p>
<p>Even when I don&rsquo;t want to, I often find myself standing outside in my shoes and ready to go.</p>
<p>It does help that I&rsquo;ve programmed myself with the mantra &ldquo;If you&rsquo;re wondering whether you should go run the answer is YES&rdquo;.</p>
<p>During my many low-power moments, that mantra often nudges me over the edge.</p>
<p>My daily writing habit also seems to be getting stronger.</p>
<p>I might be tired, or distracted, but <a href="/2022/05/23/weekly-head-voices-242-multiplicity-of-me/#multiplicity-of-you">one of the voices</a> often gets me to write with mind-tricks like &ldquo;oh just a bullet or two man, surely you can manage that?&rdquo; to which my simple mind succumbs, and before I know it, I&rsquo;ve written a few more bullets, and maybe even a paragraph or two.</p>
<p>Unbeknownst to simple mind (shhhht), retro- and introspection have now been performed, and prepared for future review.</p>
<p>I have now come to realise that these three habits, namely reading, running and writing, and their various positive feedback loops, together form a pretty decent <em>spiritual hygiene backbone</em>.</p>
<p>Especially when the rest feels like it wants to flop around or even fall apart, this backbone is a robust, reliable and, quite importantly, <em>simple</em> construct that defines my desired internal structure, enabling me to maintain focus and humanity.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #254: Ratio</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 15:02:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/</guid><description>Hello there WHV enjoyers, and welcome back! &amp;hellip;ish.
The last official WHV, by name, was WHV #253, published on September 2, 2023, although the 2023 to 2024 transition post certainly deserves its honorary WHV title.
In the meantime, I have been experimenting with the Daily Head Voices / lifelogs, which was fun, but ultimately not sufficiently meaty to fill the WHV vacuum.
We are clearly going through a pretty significant WHV-hiatus.
Although I&amp;rsquo;m still not sure what the new stable state is going to be, I have some extremely modest plans, and in addition to those I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to dust off and revive the draft of WHV #254 which was just lying there on my disc since September of last year, all languishing.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hello there WHV enjoyers, and welcome back! &hellip;ish.</p>
<p>The last official WHV, by name, was <a href="/2023/09/02/weekly-head-voices-253-weekend-warrior/">WHV #253, published on September 2, 2023</a>, although the <a href="/2024/01/04/the-2023-to-2024-transition-post/">2023 to 2024 transition post</a> certainly deserves its honorary WHV title.</p>
<p>In the meantime, I have been experimenting with the <a href="/categories/lifelog/">Daily Head Voices / lifelogs</a>, which was fun, but ultimately not sufficiently meaty to fill the WHV vacuum.</p>
<p>We are clearly going through a pretty significant WHV-hiatus.</p>
<p>Although I&rsquo;m still not sure what the new stable state is going to be, I have <em>some</em> extremely modest plans, and in addition to those I&rsquo;ve decided to dust off and revive the draft of WHV #254 which was just lying there on my disc since September of last year, all languishing.</p>










<figure><a href="wilderness-view-from-the-views.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_3a2af3333e208e2c.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_81aa06121ae775ec.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_e50b29cbe418a449.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_51f1e144bf2c94d8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/wilderness-view-from-the-views_hu_81aa06121ae775ec.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: The view from our return-journey lunch at The Views in Wilderness was awe-inspiring."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>The view from our return-journey lunch at The Views in Wilderness was awe-inspiring.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="easter-break-on-the-garden-route">Easter break on the Garden Route</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m typing these words on my laptop in the family car, moving back home along the N2 after an absolutely fabulous Easter break-away on the Garden Route.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I have not yet figured out a safe way to drive and type at the same time, so my partner is graciously helping out with the driving bits during this shift.</p>
<p>GOU#1&rsquo;s exchange family &ldquo;sister&rdquo; from Germany is currently visiting, and so we have been doing our best to show her some of the best this amazing country has to offer.</p>
<p>Although this makes for a fairly jam-packed holiday programme (almost no time to work on hobby projects), it really has been loads of fun.</p>
<p>Some highlights (ask me in the comments if you&rsquo;re curious about anything):</p>
<ul>
<li>Ebb &amp; Flow rest camp in Wilderness - one of my favourite running routes next to the Serpentine river</li>
<li>Sun-down at Salinas Beach restaurant in Wilderness</li>
<li><a href="https://knysnaelephantpark.co.za">Elephant encounters at the Knysna Elephant Park</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.sanparks.org/parks/garden-route/camps/storms-river-mouth">Storms River Mouth rest camp (Tsitsikamma)</a> - beauty all round, hikes over the hanging bridges up past the view point, also the start of the Otter trail at the other end of the camp</li>
<li>Lunch at The Views in Wilderness</li>
<li>St Francis, beautiful as always, with specific mention of Etienne&rsquo;s surfing lessons at the main beach for our teenagers, and the super entertaining St Francis Bay canal sunset cruise</li>
<li>We were absolutely blessed with balmy later summer weather, except for one rainy morning in Storms</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="two-mention-worthy-personal-knowledge-tools">Two mention-worthy personal knowledge tools</h2>
<p>As is traditional around these parts, we have this nerdy section surprise here to talk about software tools that I really like, after which there will be some backyard philosophy sections.</p>
<h3 id="miniflux">miniflux</h3>
<p>My yearly <a href="https://www.inoreader.com">inoreader</a> rss reader subscription was up for renewal.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a really fantastic product that I&rsquo;ve been using (and paying for) for years as <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#mobile">a core part of my personal knowledge management approach</a>, but the renewal email and especially the price tag was a good reminder to review my options, especially since I already have an old Linux laptop serving <a href="https://pi-hole.net">Pi-hole</a> for family-wide ad-blocking, and <a href="https://www.home-assistant.io">Home Assistant</a> to track energy production and usage stats of some of our devices at home.</p>
<p>A few minutes of searching fortunately led me to <a href="https://miniflux.app">miniflux</a>, &ldquo;a minimalist and opinionated feed reader&rdquo;. After a few more minutes, I had the docker-compose up and running (miniflux and postgres containers), and after some more minutes I had a <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/en-gb/products/tunnel/">CloudFlare tunnel</a> up so that I can easily access my miniflux&rsquo;s web UI from anywhere via an automatic Cloudflare-supplied SSL certificate. Finally, through the magic of OPML, it was straight-forward to move my 130+ feed subscriptions from inoreader to miniflux.</p>










<figure><a href="screenshot-miniflux.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_ef74d383072aa1b5.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_4c429f2130b9c515.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_34a9379b4036d398.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_6bf961f84eb46697.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-miniflux_hu_4c429f2130b9c515.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: miniflux often looks like this"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>miniflux often looks like this</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been using this setup for the past week or two and so far it looks like a strong keeper!</p>
<p>miniflux has extensive keyboard support on the desktop, but it works great on mobile, which is where I mostly use it.</p>
<p>I really like its minimalism: It shows me a paged view of all my feeds (page size configurable), via which I can easily jump to the source page, or use miniflux&rsquo;s built-in reader mode, and also easily toggle the whole page as read before moving on to the next.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re in the market for a self-hosted RSS reader, take this as a strong recommendation for miniflux. Even if you don&rsquo;t want to self-host, <a href="https://miniflux.app/hosting.html">their $15 / year hosted offering</a> is probably worth a look.</p>
<h3 id="omnivore">omnivore</h3>
<p>After years of eschewing &ldquo;read-it-later&rdquo; apps like Pocket and friends for the more straight-forward but often klunky  <a href="/2019/03/21/weekly-head-voices-165-get-in-my-pocket/#replacing-pocket-with-just-a-bunch-of-pdfs-jbop">&ldquo;just print to PDF and store&rdquo; approach</a>, I had to give <a href="https://omnivore.app/">omnivore</a> a go, as it offered native support to sync article highlights into Obsidian&rsquo;s markdown, and I thought that I would be able to use this for my Emacs setup as well.</p>
<p>I was indeed able to co-opt the Obsidian integration to get saved article highlights into my Emacs setup, but in the process fell completely for the omnivore app as a whole.</p>
<p>On mobile, which is where I use this most, I am able to import any web-page or post into omnivore with two taps.</p>
<p>On average, it does a great job of extracting the article contents and rendering it in a far more consistent and reading-friendly way.</p>
<p>One can make different coloured highlights in any article, and even add a note to each highlight.</p>
<p>Finally, it also imports PDFs with aplomb, and offers most of its functionality there. There are additional subtle delights, like the fact that you can double-tap on one column of a multi-column PDF, at which point omnivore will zoom to bring only that column into maximum width view.</p>










<figure><a href="screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom_hu_7e164320f45eb29e.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom_hu_f767113c0785ef74.jpg 800w,
            
                
                
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/03/31/weekly-head-voices-254-ratio/screenshot-omnivore-pdf-column-zoom_hu_f767113c0785ef74.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Vertically partial screenshot of Omnivore during PDF column zoom. Maps of Bounded Reality is a piece by the great Daniel Kahneman (1934-03-05 - 2024-03-27, rest in peace) which gives an overview of his and Amos Tversky&rsquo;s groundbreaking work making sense of human behaviour." width="320px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Vertically partial screenshot of Omnivore during PDF column zoom. Maps of Bounded Reality is a piece by the great Daniel Kahneman (1934-03-05 - 2024-03-27, rest in peace) which gives an overview of his and Amos Tversky&rsquo;s groundbreaking work making sense of human behaviour.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For me the only downside of omnivore is that it violates <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#high-level-overview">both my single search interface and plain old files on local drives characteristics</a>. However, both of these violations are partially mitigated by the aforementioned note-syncing feature. I don&rsquo;t really want to have <strong>all</strong> of my saved articles to be part of my database, so here I should make syncable highlights when something is important enough to go into the primary notes database.</p>
<p>After some months of use, I strongly recommend omnivore as your web-resource-ingestion-and-assimilation tool!</p>
<h2 id="the-three-or-four-hours-rule-for-getting-creative-work-done">The three-or-four hours rule for getting creative work done</h2>
<p>Last year, I listened to a short piece by Oliver Burkeman, who has <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">featured on this blog a number of times</a>, which made an impression on me. I made a note of it in the pre-hiatus draft of this post, and then promptly forgot about it.</p>
<p>The core of Burkeman&rsquo;s three-or-four hours rule, which you can <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/fourhours">read more about on his website</a>, is summarised in the following quote:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&hellip; use whatever freedom you do have over your schedule not to &ldquo;maximise your
time&rdquo; or &ldquo;optimise your day&rdquo;, in some vague way, but specifically to ringfence
three or four hours of undisturbed focus (ideally when your energy levels are
highest).</p>
<p>Stop assuming that the way to make progress on your most important projects is
to work for longer. And drop the perfectionistic notion that emails, meetings,
digital distractions and other interruptions ought ideally to be whittled away
to practically nothing.</p>
<p>Just focus on protecting four hours – and don&rsquo;t worry if the rest of the day is
characterised by the usual scattered chaos.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have definitely suffered from the &ldquo;maximise your time&rdquo; bug and can attest to its negative effects.</p>
<p>Burkeman suggests to worry only about a core few high-focus hours (he says 3 or 4, I think sometimes depending on your context, even 1 could work) and let the rest be what it wants to be.</p>
<p>I think this is a far better approach which strongly complements <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">the one main thing philosophy</a>.</p>
<p>P.S. There&rsquo;s another important tenet of Burkeman&rsquo;s approach, which he talks about in his post linked above, and which also <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">featured in WHV #230, namely: Know how to put down your work</a> (although I just noticed that back then I did not mention the chaos part&hellip;). In summary: Guard your focus hours, let &ldquo;the chaos&rdquo; fill the rest, but become really good at detaching and walking away at the end of the work day. Thank you <a href="http://noeskasmit.com">Noeska</a> for the reminder!</p>
<h2 id="the-magic-relationship-ratio-is-5-to-1">The Magic Relationship Ratio is 5 to 1</h2>
<p>I really enjoyed the <a href="https://lexfridman.com/shannon-curry/">fascinating podcast between Lex Fridman and Dr Shannon Curry</a>, a clinical and forensic psychologist, titled &ldquo;Johnny Depp &amp; Amber Heard Trial, Marriage, Dating &amp; Love&rdquo;, much of it in fact about human relationships (<a href="https://www.podcastworld.io/episodes/366-shannon-curry-johnny-depp-amber-heard-trial-marriage-dat-sz9ltosy">textual summary here</a>).</p>
<p>Among the many practical and science-based topics that Dr Curry talked about, she mentioned the <a href="https://www.gottman.com/blog/the-magic-relationship-ratio-according-science/">&ldquo;5 to 1magic relationship ratio&rdquo;</a>, which refers to the observation that the interactions between happy couples tend to consist of at least 5 positive interactions for each negative interaction.</p>
<p>It should come as no surprise that being able to spend decades together in a permanent state of happiness, by definition continuously facing various internal and external stressors in an often resource-constrained environment, is probably not realistic.</p>
<p>Thus I really like that this observation runs with the knowledge that almost no-one is going to get this right, and that the smart approach is instead to accept that and focus on what you can attain, namely, that more practical but still ambitious 5 to 1 ratio.</p>
<h2 id="ratio">Ratio</h2>
<p>This is the part of the post where I try to tie up some of the threads, or at least justify the title.</p>
<p>Burkeman&rsquo;s three-or-four hours rule is all about working towards a practical and healthy <em>ratio</em> between focus time and the rest of the daily chaos, instead of being continuously disappointed because it&rsquo;s not really possible to fill all of your days with pure focus hours.</p>
<p>The 5 to 1 ratio is the same: We make peace with reality, and work towards a healthy ratio between positive and negative interactions.</p>
<p>The third <em>ratio</em> I want to mention here refers to the Dutch word &ldquo;ratio&rdquo; (<a href="https://nl.bab.la/uitspraak/nederlands/ratio">pronunciation)</a>, one of whose definitions is &ldquo;reason&rdquo; or &ldquo;logic&rdquo;, or more idiomatically, the noun corresponding to adjective &ldquo;rationeel&rdquo;, which is the same as the English &ldquo;rational&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As with all things language, the use of this word implies subtle little differences. Whatever the case may be, I was delighted when I discovered that the Dutch had adopted the original Latin for this. To me it felt like that meant there was a special place for and focus on <em>ratio</em> in their world.</p>
<p>With that trifecta (a neologism, I just learned, for contrast!) of <em>ratio</em> examples, I think that I can now conclude this post with the earnest wish, for you and for me, that we are able to instantiate, maintain and propagate superb levels of <em>ratio</em>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 7 of 2024: Rest For Success</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/18/daily-head-voices-week-7-2024/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 17:42:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/18/daily-head-voices-week-7-2024/</guid><description> Most people in high-stress, decision-making industries are always operating at this kind of simmering six, as opposed to the undulation between just deep relaxation and being at a 10. Being at a 10 is millions of times better than being at a 6. It’s just in a different universe. &amp;ndash; Josh Waitzkin (see Sunday below)
Monday 2024-02-12 I really enjoyed this Rolling Stone article about Nine Inch Nails&amp;rsquo; Head Like a Hole Yes, that&amp;rsquo;s also a subtle jab at those of you who read last week&amp;rsquo;s title and did not get the reference. :P Extreme almost asymptotic anger moment at Outlook PWA: Spent time crafting a detailed meeting description. Unrelated meeting notification came in, meeting edit dialog disappears, all of those beautiful words gone. Forever. Accidentally upgraded Emacs to 29.2 (brew upgrade if you must now, and there it went building emacs along with installing all the other smaller dependencies, the ones I actually had in mind) Added ad-hoc similar node search for org-roam-similarity (that links to the new function&amp;rsquo;s documentation) This means you can also select any text, or just use the whole current buffer as your input, and then get a completing read list of similar nodes to open The area of my forehead around the scar feels like it has substantial nerve drop-out. I can&amp;rsquo;t feel much there, and I also can&amp;rsquo;t actuate much. The reconstructive surgeon warned before the time that this might be the case. Thanks again cancer. I&amp;rsquo;m crossing my fingers that there&amp;rsquo;s still some recovery that needs to happen and this is not my forehead&amp;rsquo;s final form. bitbar is now xbar. It looks like xbar can eat RAM https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725 I looked this up, because during my previous macOS phase I contributed code to bitbar to support Lua plugins. That work is now gone. Oh well. What a craptastically unproductive day. I had all of the time, and in that time I utterly failed at my selected task. I did some other interesting and possibly valuable stuff, but the majority of the time was wasted. Old lesson on this blog: some days gonna be crap However, responded to this by reviving my old FocusApp licence (see pro-tip #2 in WHV #126) and installed on my machine Tuesday 2024-02-13 First day back at the office. Lots of conversations due to the giant scar criss-crossing over half my forehead. Implemented the new (but very very old) &amp;ldquo;avoid all social media during work hours except a little bit on your phone during real breaks&amp;rdquo; rule. Using terminal Emacs for some remote work, because reasons Bothersome delay when pressing escape to get out of insert mode into normal mode. IT WAS TMUX. https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868 Noticed how much I rely on the cursor shape to know in what mode (insert, normal, emacs) I am. Fortunately found https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer and it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;hellip; game changer. Today was much fun at the office. Also much higher productivity due to above-mentioned no-social-media-goofing-off-rule. Wednesday 2024-02-14 Happy Valentine&amp;rsquo;s day everyone! Utterly crazy this morning because load-shedding, but due to GOU#3 being so very on time we left at 7:05 and could avoid most of that chaos. 6.5km short run just to get back into it, after 1.5 weeks out thanks to surgery and recovery. Garmin not happy with my fitness, but man it felt good. Went to doctor&amp;rsquo;s rooms to have stitches removed. Kind and professional nurse left the stitches in the middle, because skin there still needed some time to relax into the new situation. Feels really good to have the others out. Will go back on Friday for the rest. Pro-tip: it was a bit of a change management challenge, but I&amp;rsquo;ve converted my household to the new shopping list support in Apple Reminders. If you&amp;rsquo;re an Apple family, this woks much better than a WhatsApp group named &amp;ldquo;Shopping&amp;rdquo;. True story. Thanks to said app, remembered to get flowers. FocusApp really did its work today. I&amp;rsquo;m a tiny little bit bummed that no-one picked up on the Head like a Hole reference from last week&amp;rsquo;s Daily Head Voices. Or maybe someone did, but they just have not contacted me about it. Hopefully this week&amp;rsquo;s title does better. SUCH A GOOD DAY today thank you! Thursday 2024-02-15 Pretty busy day with meetings (Thursday is secondary meeting day at work after all), good conversations with colleagues, and an internal product playbook workshop. Friday 2024-02-16 Sublime run in Land &amp;amp; Zeezicht (school district) right after dropping off GOU#3, which also helped to avoid most of the traffic back home, again utterly crazy due to the 6 - 8:30 AM load-shedding slot disabling some critical (for us) traffic lights. Best afternoon ever: Father and daughter picnic with GOU#1 (school event, so many other fathers and daughters) at Zorgvliet Wine Estate In the evening, got my work inbox unread email count to just under 4000. Thank you for coming to my TED talk. Spent a bit more time reading about the new and open source Observable Framework I&amp;rsquo;ve always liked the ObservableJS notebooks, but this new development which supports working locally and self-hosting is really exciting! marimo is very nice for experimentation, but big advantage of OF is that it builds a static site as output. marimo needs Python to be running on the server. Again that idea: How automatically could I push a completely new OF built dashboard to a newly allocated CloudFlare pages site? Tried it out on Sunday evening (IN THE FUTURE): Was really quick to get the intro dashboard going in my case with pnpm, but a big challenge at this moment is the developer experience: There is very little coding assistance of any kind as you work on the javascript code blocks in the markdown pages. Hopefully they will be able to improve this with a vscode extension and/or a web-based editing experience, like marimo. Tried out Thunderbird 115.7 on the macbook. Much better than the TB 115 experience I had just after its release on Windows, where its currently selected mail logic handled it very badly when I archived a mail. I am trying out TB, because I miss the today, yesterday, last week date grouping. Saturday 2024-02-17 Woke up with low body battery (Garmin). Somewhat surprised, because only two beers last night. Perhaps the stress of the arguments, and probably still the alcohol because I&amp;rsquo;m old now. Wrote some Mojo to see if I could create a Pandas DataFrame and write to disc as Parquet. I love parquet. Although Mojo is still missing some data structures, it was not too involved to use the imported numpy and pandas libraries to do this job. Smoked snoek braai (so good! 🤤) at friend LM&amp;rsquo;s place with more friends. Sunday 2024-02-18 Super enjoyable 13km run. Not too hot, just a little bit of wind, and enough energy to finish strong. George Mack makes the statement: &amp;ldquo;There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.&amp;rdquo; This might indeed be a controversial statement, but I really like that his advice is to focus on the quality and purity of one&amp;rsquo;s rest (a very mindful idea), leading to much more energy for intensity 10 work. See his tweet (also embedded below, but please do click on &amp;ldquo;show more&amp;rdquo;) for a bunch of interesting examples. Figured out that it&amp;rsquo;s pretty easy to setup &amp;ldquo;Smart Mailboxes&amp;rdquo; on Apple Mail for today, yesterday, last week and so on. Truly sublime lunch with family at Stables on Vergelegen wine estate. Semi-controversial opinion: There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.
1. Winston Churchill used to work 16 hours per day in his old age during the war — but he also worked in bed every day until 11am. He had a nap after lunch, and a 2 hour nap… pic.twitter.com/kyiAuTEwjA</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
<p>Most people in high-stress, decision-making industries are always operating at this kind of simmering six, as opposed to the undulation between just deep relaxation and being at a 10. Being at a 10 is millions of times better than being at a 6. It’s just in a different universe. &ndash; Josh Waitzkin (see Sunday below)</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="monday-2024-02-12">Monday 2024-02-12</h2>
<ul>
<li>I really enjoyed this <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-features/nine-inch-nails-head-like-a-hole-anthem-900750/">Rolling Stone article about Nine Inch Nails&rsquo; Head Like a Hole</a>
<ul>
<li>Yes, that&rsquo;s also a subtle jab at those of you who read last week&rsquo;s title and did not get the reference. :P</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Extreme almost asymptotic anger moment at Outlook PWA: Spent time crafting a detailed meeting description. Unrelated meeting notification came in, meeting edit dialog disappears, all of those beautiful words gone. Forever.</li>
<li>Accidentally upgraded Emacs to 29.2 (<code>brew upgrade</code> if you must now, and there it went building emacs along with installing all the other smaller dependencies, the ones I actually had in mind)</li>
<li>Added ad-hoc similar node search for <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-similarity?tab=readme-ov-file#key-bind-the-ad-hoc-similarity-search">org-roam-similarity</a> (that links to the new function&rsquo;s documentation)
<ul>
<li>This means you can also select any text, or just use the whole current buffer as your input, and then get a completing read list of similar nodes to open</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The area of my forehead around the scar feels like it has substantial nerve drop-out. I can&rsquo;t feel much there, and I also can&rsquo;t actuate much. The reconstructive surgeon warned before the time that this might be the case. Thanks again cancer. I&rsquo;m crossing my fingers that there&rsquo;s still some recovery that needs to happen and this is not my forehead&rsquo;s final form.</li>
<li>bitbar is now xbar. It looks like xbar can eat RAM <a href="https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725">https://github.com/matryer/xbar/issues/725</a>
<ul>
<li>I looked this up, because during <a href="/2017/09/05/weekly-head-voices-125/#new-laptop">my previous macOS phase</a> I contributed code to bitbar to support Lua plugins. That work is now gone. Oh well.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What a craptastically unproductive day. I had all of the time, and in that time I utterly failed at my selected task. I did some other interesting and possibly valuable stuff, but the majority of the time was wasted.
<ul>
<li>Old lesson on this blog: <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#pragmatic-thinking-and-learning">some days gonna be crap</a></li>
<li>However, responded to this by reviving my old FocusApp licence (see pro-tip #2 in <a href="/2018/01/07/weekly-head-voices-126-fleur-de-lis/">WHV #126</a>) and installed on my machine</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-02-13">Tuesday 2024-02-13</h2>
<ul>
<li>First day back at the office. Lots of conversations due to the giant scar criss-crossing over half my forehead.</li>
<li>Implemented the new (but very very old) &ldquo;avoid all social media during work hours except a little bit on your phone during real breaks&rdquo; rule.</li>
<li>Using terminal Emacs for some remote work, because reasons
<ul>
<li>Bothersome delay when pressing escape to get out of insert mode into normal mode. IT WAS TMUX. <a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868">https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/25638/32868</a></li>
<li>Noticed how much I rely on the cursor shape to know in what mode (insert, normal, emacs) I am. Fortunately found <a href="https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer">https://github.com/7696122/evil-terminal-cursor-changer</a> and it&rsquo;s a &hellip; game changer.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Today was much fun at the office. Also much higher productivity due to above-mentioned no-social-media-goofing-off-rule.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-02-14">Wednesday 2024-02-14</h2>
<ul>
<li>Happy Valentine&rsquo;s day everyone!</li>
<li>Utterly crazy this morning because load-shedding, but due to GOU#3 being so very on time we left at 7:05 and could avoid most of that chaos.</li>
<li>6.5km short run just to get back into it, after 1.5 weeks out thanks to surgery and recovery. Garmin not happy with my fitness, but man it felt good.</li>
<li>Went to doctor&rsquo;s rooms to have stitches removed. Kind and professional nurse left the stitches in the middle, because skin there still needed some time to relax into the new situation. Feels really good to have the others out. Will go back on Friday for the rest.</li>
<li>Pro-tip: it was a bit of a change management challenge, but I&rsquo;ve converted my household to the new shopping list support in Apple Reminders. If you&rsquo;re an Apple family, this woks much better than a WhatsApp group named &ldquo;Shopping&rdquo;. True story.
<ul>
<li>Thanks to said app, remembered to get flowers.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>FocusApp really did its work today.</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m a tiny little bit bummed that no-one picked up on the Head like a Hole reference from last week&rsquo;s Daily Head Voices. Or maybe someone did, but they just have not contacted me about it.
<ul>
<li>Hopefully this week&rsquo;s title does better.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>SUCH A GOOD DAY today thank you!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-02-15">Thursday 2024-02-15</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pretty busy day with meetings (Thursday is secondary meeting day at work after all), good conversations with colleagues, and an internal product playbook workshop.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-02-16">Friday 2024-02-16</h2>
<ul>
<li>Sublime run in Land &amp; Zeezicht (school district) right after dropping off GOU#3, which also helped to avoid most of the traffic back home, again utterly crazy due to the 6 - 8:30 AM load-shedding slot disabling some critical (for us) traffic lights.</li>
<li>Best afternoon ever: Father and daughter picnic with GOU#1 (school event, so many other fathers and daughters) at Zorgvliet Wine Estate</li>
<li>In the evening, got my work inbox unread email count to just under 4000. Thank you for coming to my TED talk.</li>
<li>Spent a bit more time reading about the new and open source <a href="https://observablehq.com/framework/">Observable Framework</a>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve always liked the ObservableJS notebooks, but this new development which supports working locally and self-hosting is really exciting!</li>
<li>marimo is very nice for experimentation, but big advantage of OF is that it builds a static site as output. marimo needs Python to be running on the server.</li>
<li>Again that idea: How automatically could I push a completely new OF built dashboard to a newly allocated CloudFlare pages site?</li>
<li>Tried it out on Sunday evening (IN THE FUTURE): Was really quick to get the intro dashboard going in my case with <code>pnpm</code>, but a big challenge at this moment is the developer experience: There is very little coding assistance of any kind as you work on the javascript code blocks in the markdown pages. Hopefully they will be able to improve this with a vscode extension and/or a web-based editing experience, like marimo.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Tried out Thunderbird 115.7 on the macbook.
<ul>
<li>Much better than the TB 115 experience I had just after its release on Windows, where its currently selected mail logic handled it very badly when I archived a mail.</li>
<li>I am trying out TB, because I miss the today, yesterday, last week date grouping.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-02-17">Saturday 2024-02-17</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up with low body battery (Garmin). Somewhat surprised, because only two beers last night. Perhaps the stress of the arguments, and probably still the alcohol because I&rsquo;m old now.</li>
<li>Wrote some Mojo to see if I could create a Pandas DataFrame and write to disc as Parquet.
<ul>
<li>I love parquet.</li>
<li>Although Mojo is still missing some data structures, it was not too involved to use the imported numpy and pandas libraries to do this job.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Smoked snoek braai (so good! 🤤) at friend LM&rsquo;s place with more friends.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-02-18">Sunday 2024-02-18</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super enjoyable 13km run. Not too hot, just a little bit of wind, and enough energy to finish strong.</li>
<li>George Mack makes the statement: &ldquo;There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.&rdquo;
<ul>
<li>This might indeed be a controversial statement, but  I really like that his advice is to focus on the quality and purity of one&rsquo;s rest (a very mindful idea), leading to much more energy for intensity 10 work.</li>
<li>See <a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1759122352036577546">his tweet</a> (also embedded below, but please do click on &ldquo;show more&rdquo;) for a bunch of interesting examples.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Figured out that it&rsquo;s pretty easy to setup &ldquo;Smart Mailboxes&rdquo; on Apple Mail for today, yesterday, last week and so on.</li>
<li>Truly sublime lunch with family at <a href="https://vergelegen.co.za/restaurants/stables-at-vergelegen/">Stables on Vergelegen wine estate</a>.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-dnt="true"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Semi-controversial opinion: There’s no such thing as working too hard. There’s just being under rested.<br><br>1. Winston Churchill used to work 16 hours per day in his old age during the war — but he also worked in bed every day until 11am. He had a nap after lunch, and a 2 hour nap… <a href="https://t.co/kyiAuTEwjA">pic.twitter.com/kyiAuTEwjA</a></p>&mdash; George Mack (@george__mack) <a href="https://twitter.com/george__mack/status/1759122352036577546?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 18, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 4 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/28/daily-head-voices-2024-01-22_28/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-22 As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&amp;rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS! At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&amp;hellip; Short but really nice streamlit demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually played with it. Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3. In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&amp;hellip; &amp;hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola. Tuesday 2024-01-23 At the office nice and early (7:30). Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at react-flow and comfyui react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY! streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &amp;ldquo;things I learned&amp;rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document. Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&amp;rsquo;s a zero day vulnerability in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites. Wednesday 2024-01-24 8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW! Remember kids: Our spine&amp;rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally. This is also the reason why I&amp;rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair. Lovely working lunch with friend S at No Way José Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work: idea: make github so that people can pipx install marimo-turbo to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on. idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS &amp;hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844 (post is also embedded below) idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&amp;gt; nginx -&amp;gt; supervisord -&amp;gt; tornado systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation I would prefer to use supervisord for this This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick? ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &amp;ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&amp;rdquo; googling blog post: https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/ the kubernetes thing: https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&amp;rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via iframe.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-22">Monday 2024-01-22</h2>
<ul>
<li>As GOU#1 and GOU#2 were busy leaving for school, #3 came in to #2 for a hug but #2 was a bit too focused on getting all of her things ready to go in the car. Good Charl, in his only appearance of the day, spontaneously interjected with: &ldquo;When you&rsquo;re in a hug, for that moment, you put your full attention into that hug. For that moment, nothing else exists but the hug.&rdquo;. I could really see the message hitting home with #2, and she vocalised as much. Monday: BIG SUCCESS!</li>
<li>At work, managed to spill black coffee all over meself as I was just doing step 1 of living the one cable dream (read: attaching usb-c cable to my macbook). Clumsy Charl clearly at the wheel&hellip;</li>
<li>Short but really nice <a href="https://streamlit.io/">streamlit</a> demo during a work meeting. I knew about streamlit, but I&rsquo;ve never actually played with it.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day fighting trying, without success, to update the webcola d3 adapter to the latest version of d3.
<ul>
<li>In bed that night, had light-bulb that React was probably a better solution for this visualization in any case&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip; and then realised that few years back I built something similar for work, and had a similar evolution of ideas which ended up with react + webcola.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-23">Tuesday 2024-01-23</h2>
<ul>
<li>At the office nice and early (7:30).</li>
<li>Chatted with colleague about the abovementioned React + webcola thing we worked on together, at which point he pointed me at <a href="https://reactflow.dev/">react-flow</a> and comfyui
<ul>
<li>react-flow looks like it could work pretty well for this new project. Also: SO SHINY!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>streamlit app life cycle: script re-runs every time user interacts, see <a href="https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary">https://docs.streamlit.io/get-started/fundamentals/summary</a>
<ul>
<li>it does have caching mechanisms to make this go faster</li>
<li>marimo, although much newer, approaches this issue with its reactive cell pattern</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Idea: We should write focused technical memos at work. This is now howto, but rather &ldquo;things I learned&rdquo; formulated to teach not just to document.</li>
<li>Upgaded phone to iOS 17.3 and MacBook to macOS 14.3. Apparently there&rsquo;s a <a href="https://www.tomsguide.com/news/apple-issues-urgent-security-updates-to-fix-zero-day-flaw-update-your-iphone-and-mac-right-now">zero day vulnerability</a> in previous versions that can be exploited via malicious websites.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-24">Wednesday 2024-01-24</h2>
<ul>
<li>8km run at just after 7 AM before it really got hot</li>
<li>dip in the pool (friend LM says we must but pool is probably not cold enough due to +30℃ temps), then started to work</li>
<li>right after dip in pool, partially pulled back muscle. Partial, because two warning spasms, but not complete lock like many previous times. PHEW!
<ul>
<li>Remember kids: Our spine&rsquo;s vertical operation is a major evolutionary hack job and a mechanical disaster just waiting to happen. My advice: Spend more time horizontally.</li>
<li>This is also the reason why I&rsquo;m still searching for a long enough reclining chair.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Lovely working lunch with friend S at <a href="https://www.facebook.com/NoWayJoseSomerset">No Way José</a></li>
<li>Some random ideas that popped into my head as I was trying to work:
<ul>
<li>idea: make github so that people can <code>pipx install marimo-turbo</code> to get install with pandas, altair, matplotlib, and so on.</li>
<li>idea: figure out way to publish marimo dashboard to HTTPS url somewhere, for really really cheap
<ul>
<li>sounds like AWS API gateway + lambdas can do something complicated to host streamlit, which also uses websockets</li>
<li>in the end, probably better to do this on my own VPS
<ul>
<li>&hellip; or even better, on my own machine behind tailscale funnel! This was straight-forward and seems to work well. See <a href="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844">https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844</a> (post is also embedded below)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>idea: (which has been active for a bit longer) A reliable pattern to lazy start upstream processes only when the first request comes in, and to stop them when no-one is connected. Client -&gt; nginx -&gt; supervisord -&gt; tornado
<ul>
<li>systemd can partially do something like this using socket activation: <a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation">https://serverfault.com/questions/1121584/start-apache-on-demand-using-systemd-socket-activation</a></li>
<li>I would prefer to use supervisord for this</li>
<li>This will remain on the todo list for now, unless one of you knows a trick?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>ran into dude who built kubernetes thing for Hetzner using Crystal, a programming language of which I remembered that it just had a release, so quickly lost some more time on &ldquo;crystal vs nim-lang&rdquo; googling
<ul>
<li>blog post: <a href="https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/">https://vitobotta.com/2023/01/07/kubernetes-on-hetzner-cloud-the-easiest-way/</a></li>
<li>the kubernetes thing: <a href="https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s">https://github.com/vitobotta/hetzner-k3s</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<iframe src="https://emacs.ch/@cpbotha/111811547009420844/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0" width="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><script src="https://emacs.ch/embed.js" async="async"></script>
<h3 id="til-mastodon-embeds-are-not-as-durable-as-twitter-embeds">TIL: mastodon embeds are not as durable as twitter embeds</h3>
<p>As I pasted the above embed, I saw to my disappointment that it&rsquo;s just pulling in the mastodon post URL via <code>iframe</code>.</p>
<p>With twitter, you get more self-contained HTML which will render even when twitter or just the original tweet don&rsquo;t exist anymore.</p>
<p>This is probably just another reason to figure out how I can get more low-friction microblogging going on my own websites so that the embedding implementations of other microblogging sites become irrelevant.</p>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-25">Thursday 2024-01-25</h2>
<ul>
<li>Took a look at <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/connections/connect-networks/get-started/">cloudflare tunnels</a> to expose marimo and other dashboards to the internet
<ul>
<li>great that I can use my existing domains for this, and I can route between multiple domains to multiple locally running services</li>
<li>some more steps to setup, but it did not take more than about 5 minutes, and gives me even more options than tailscale funnels. OPTIONS MAN!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At work, quickly got react-flow&hellip; flowing. SHINY!</li>
<li>In the evening, found <a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/">https://www.macstories.net/stories/generating-markdown-links-to-mail-messages-with-shortcuts-and-applescript/</a> which is the new Shortcuts based way, based on the old AppleScript way, of getting a <code>message://</code> link onto the clipboard.
<ul>
<li>You <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/#email-linking">might recall from this blog</a> that <code>message://</code> are the most durable and cross-platform way to link to emails from your notes (or anywhere else)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-26">Friday 2024-01-26</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up to cool, overcast weather, a big change from a series of 30℃ + days. Really had to resist going out for a run (normal run day + that amazing coolness), because of Wednesday&rsquo;s partially pulled back muscle not being 100% yet.</li>
<li>Worked on mystery visualization project (react-flow)</li>
<li>Lovely and energising lunch with previous colleague and friend. Happy that I reached out on Thursday although they have a packed schedule because only in country for limited time. I guess this is quite related to <a href="/2022/09/25/weekly-head-voices-246-call-up-your-friends/#call-up-your-friends">calling up your friends</a>, with a ping of serendipity salt.</li>
<li>I was shocked by how well and fast <a href="https://ollama.ai/">ollama</a> worked on my MacBook. See embedded tweet below.</li>
<li>Almost at the end of the afternoon, friend S and I went to some more friends for the first Weiss-off, that is, a Weiss beer tasting contest. It was huge fun blind-tasting 10 different Weiss beers, ranking them, trying to identify them (so much harder than I thought!), and then having them revealed at the end.
<ul>
<li>Between the experts there (read: us), Stangen Weiss Bier came out on top, followed by Weisbier No5 and Jack Black Atlantic Weiss. The fourth place was shared by Erdinger and CBC Amber Weiss.</li>
<li>My favourite, Stellenbrau Jonkersweiss, is glaringly absent from the top. I&rsquo;ll live, probably consoled by just such a Jonkersweiss. Super happy that Amber Weiss and Atlantic are both present!</li>
<li>There was a trophy (for the taster who could blind-identify the most beers in the Weiss-off), which we have christened the <em>David Weisselhoff wisseltrofee</em>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">With <a href="https://twitter.com/MistralAI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@MistralAI</a>&#39;s Mistral 7B at Q4_0 on this MacBook M1 Pro 10C / 16C, <a href="https://twitter.com/ollama?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ollama</a> looks like it&#39;s easily 3 times faster than the new MLX 0.0.11 (with GGUF support).<br><br>It&#39;s subjectively (visually) faster, and the tokens/s measurements confirm this. <a href="https://t.co/9vyluimLKK">pic.twitter.com/9vyluimLKK</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1750824125419942036?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 26, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-27">Saturday 2024-01-27</h2>
<ul>
<li>Yesterday&rsquo;s Wonderful Weiss-off also had some, thankfully quite minor, effect the next morning, but I went out for a careful weekday distance run, which fortunately went without a hitch. Just very hot thanks.</li>
<li>Went to Buco and then to <a href="https://appletoolandgas.com/">Apple Tool and Gas</a> to find the rest of the screws I needed to repair the shower door. Friendly gentleman at Apple even sawed some of my screws to size! Shower door back in operation.</li>
<li>Updated my &ldquo;old&rdquo; M1 MBA to macOS 14.3 and then reset to transfer to GOU#1&rsquo;s iCloud. Say what you want about Apple, but that part of their stuff works <em>really</em> well.</li>
<li>Left for Betty&rsquo;s Bay at about 16:00 with GOUs #1 and #2. The rest of the family already there.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-28">Sunday 2024-01-28</h2>
<ul>
<li>Woke up in Betty&rsquo;s Bay after a longer than normal night of sleep, but Garmin body battery was still not completely happy.</li>
<li>In spite of having run yesterday and still feeling a bit tired (see body battery above), I had the best run of the month so far in Betty&rsquo;s. Go figure.</li>
<li>Spent some time with Canva &ndash; what a great resource for doing nice designs, even flow charts &ndash; but not sure where I could use this.</li>
<li>Background thought through the past weeks, and mentioned on Tuesday: I would really like to do (and promite) more TIL-style writing at work and at home. See <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/">Simon Willison&rsquo;s amazing TIL collection</a> for inspiration.</li>
<li>Ran into <a href="https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines">https://github.com/outlines-dev/outlines</a> a Python library that can guarantee structured text generation from many LLMs, e.g. 100% valid JSON according to a specified schema. What makes it different from similar libraries? &ldquo;Unlike other libraries, regex-guided generation in Outlines is almost as fast as non-guided generation.&rdquo;</li>
<li>I already had <a href="https://github.com/microsoft/autogen">AutoGen</a> on my list for experimenting with multi-agent LLM applications, but now it has been joined by <a href="https://github.com/joaomdmoura/crewAI">crewAI</a> which I have also just ran into (thanks reddit!) and which seems to have significant support online.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 3 of 2024</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 20:21:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/</guid><description>Monday 2024-01-15 Discovered that we (at work) now have access to GPT-4 Turbo via Azure OpenAI: 128K context and much cheaper than the old GPT-4. Will have to upgrade our private internal assistant, code name StoneGPT. Inspired by stefanv, carefully trying out weekly planning, but in a slight deviation I&amp;rsquo;m doing this in addition to my daily planning, which I only get around to a fraction of the time in any case. I think that this sort of multi-scalar examination and planning will help. Went to Bloemhof for the welcoming of the new grade 8 learners. Was really great to see GOU#1 and GOU#2 there, on two very opposite ends of the spectrum. Tuesday 2024-01-16 MS Copilot Pro ($20) has been announced, and also Copilot 365 is now available for businesses of all sizes (not just enterprises who can commit to 300 seats): https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/ Copilot Pro not yet available in South Africa 😥 $20 per month for integration with some Office apps (which could be useful, will have to see), priority access to latest models such as GPT-4 Turbo, and custom Copilots. I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced, will stick to my perplexity.ai for now. Copilot for 365 can be purchased per seat, but minimum 1 year commitment which is $360 per person per year. Ouch. In addition to many meetings (Tuesday = meetings day), did manage to spend some quality time with a new visualization project. Slowly starting to use webcola again, but this time with d3@latest &amp;ndash; sorta works, but no dragging. Have found work-around, still need to test. Went to bed really early, because must be up at 5:30 to help GOU#2 get ready for school and get to the bus stop on time. (Slept super badly thanks.) Wednesday 2024-01-17 Up at 5:30 after a pretty restless night. GOU#2 on the bus at 6 after some serious morning prep multi-tasking, GOU#3 (age 7) so organized and independent, ready to leave for school at 7! Nice and early(ish) slightly longer weekday run before work. My hip sent me a Teams message &amp;ldquo;Hi&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; at about 80% of the route somewhere, but fortunately no follow-up. Colleagues on chat, haha. Got caught up in GEKKO Optimization Suite due to meetings with colleagues about various simulations. My initial enthusiasm was somewhat dampened upon learning that behind the Python API lies an admittedly useful but quite black-box compiled binary called apm.exe. TIL: John Lasseter drew the BSD daemon! See https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html &amp;ndash; I remember that daemon from the time when I had FreeBSD on my machine at home instead of Linux (somewhere in the 90s). You might remember that name from the Creativity Inc. book (the one about Pixar!) notes post on this blog Thursday 2024-01-18 AlphaGeometry from Google DeepMind is great work combining a symbolic math engine with a language model to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. See below for my breathless tweet. (twitter is still the uncontested ML firehose) News on our in-house GPT-wrapper front: Discovered that I now have to upgrade to the new tool_call api as the old functions one has been deprecated. Made use of the opportunity to improve our implementation of the supplied OpenAI type annotations Note to self, and to you: The *Params types are TypedDict declarations which you can use to work directly with JSON requests and responses, while the non-*Params types are pydantic models which you can use to (de)serialize JSON. Went to see a really good Mohs surgery dermatologist who will soon be removing my basal cell carcinomas. As always, AMA in the comments or via email. This is such fantastic work! Symbolic engine + language model working together to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. Also, beautiful illustrations in the paper and posts. https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="monday-2024-01-15">Monday 2024-01-15</h2>
<ul>
<li>Discovered that we (at work) now have access to GPT-4 Turbo via Azure OpenAI: 128K context and much cheaper than the old GPT-4. Will have to upgrade our private internal assistant, code name StoneGPT.</li>
<li>Inspired by stefanv, carefully trying out weekly planning, but in a slight deviation I&rsquo;m doing this <em>in addition</em> to my daily planning, which I only get around to a fraction of the time in any case. I think that this sort of multi-scalar examination and planning will help.</li>
<li>Went to Bloemhof for the welcoming of the new grade 8 learners. Was really great to see GOU#1 <em>and</em> GOU#2 there, on two very opposite ends of the spectrum.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-16">Tuesday 2024-01-16</h2>
<ul>
<li>MS Copilot Pro ($20) has been announced, and also Copilot 365 is now available for businesses of all sizes (not just enterprises who can commit to 300 seats): <a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/">https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2024/01/15/bringing-the-full-power-of-copilot-to-more-people-and-businesses/</a>
<ul>
<li>Copilot Pro not yet available in South Africa 😥
<ul>
<li>$20 per month for integration with some Office apps (which could be useful, will have to see), priority access to latest models such as GPT-4 Turbo, and custom Copilots. I&rsquo;m not convinced, will stick to my <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/">perplexity.ai</a> for now.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Copilot for 365 can be purchased per seat, but minimum 1 year commitment which is $360 per person per year. Ouch.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In addition to many meetings (Tuesday = meetings day), did manage to spend some quality time with a new visualization project. Slowly starting to use <a href="https://ialab.it.monash.edu/webcola/">webcola</a> again, but this time with d3@latest &ndash; sorta works, but no dragging. Have found work-around, still need to test.</li>
<li>Went to bed really early, because must be up at 5:30 to help GOU#2 get ready for school and get to the bus stop on time. (Slept super badly thanks.)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-17">Wednesday 2024-01-17</h2>
<ul>
<li>Up at 5:30 after a pretty restless night. GOU#2 on the bus at 6 after some serious morning prep multi-tasking, GOU#3 (age 7) so organized and independent, ready to leave for school at 7!</li>
<li>Nice and early(ish) slightly longer weekday run before work. My hip sent me a Teams message &ldquo;Hi&hellip;&rdquo; at about 80% of the route somewhere, but fortunately no follow-up. Colleagues on chat, haha.</li>
<li>Got caught up in <a href="#d41d8c">GEKKO Optimization Suite</a> due to meetings with colleagues about various simulations. My initial enthusiasm was somewhat dampened upon learning that behind the Python API lies an admittedly useful but quite black-box compiled binary called apm.exe.</li>
<li>TIL: John Lasseter drew the BSD daemon! See <a href="https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html">https://www.jacobelder.com/2024/01/17/director-of-toy-story-also-drew-bsd-daemon.html</a> &ndash; I remember that daemon from the time when I had FreeBSD on my machine at home instead of Linux (somewhere in the 90s). You might remember that name from the <a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/#the-story-is-more-important-than-the-technology">Creativity Inc.</a> book (the one about Pixar!) notes post on this blog</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-18">Thursday 2024-01-18</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>AlphaGeometry from Google DeepMind is great work</strong> combining a symbolic math engine with a language model to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. See below for my breathless tweet. (twitter is still the uncontested ML firehose)</li>
<li>News on our in-house GPT-wrapper front:
<ul>
<li>Discovered that I now have to upgrade to the new <code>tool_call</code> api as the old <code>functions</code> one has been deprecated. Made use of the opportunity to improve our implementation of the supplied OpenAI type annotations</li>
<li>Note to self, and to you: The <code>*Params</code> types are <code>TypedDict</code> declarations which you can use to work directly with JSON requests and responses, while the non-<code>*Params</code> types are pydantic models which you can use to (de)serialize JSON.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Went to see a really good <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/tests-procedures/mohs-surgery/about/pac-20385222">Mohs surgery</a> dermatologist who will soon be removing my basal cell carcinomas. As always, AMA in the comments or via email.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is such fantastic work! Symbolic engine + language model working together to solve Olympiad geometry math problems at just under gold-medalist level. Also, beautiful illustrations in the paper and posts. <a href="https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7">https://t.co/DtREuQK5k7</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1747857845356298739?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 18, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-19">Friday 2024-01-19</h2>
<ul>
<li>Spent most of my working hours wrappng up and deploying the brand new version of our internal GPT. I read somewhere that you should <em>always</em> deploy on a Friday, as late as possible.</li>
<li>I was stressing quite a bit, as I had a great task before me:</li>
<li>Braaiing 200 boeries in the 39 degrees Celsius heat at the school in Stellenbosch, in order to feed the new grade 8 learners on the evening of their initiation.
<ul>
<li>All thanks to the fellow dad who joined me, the stress transformed completely into an enjoyable few hours taking care of this important duty, and I made a new friend!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The kids, including our very own GOU#2, were facing the challenging night before them&hellip;</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-20">Saturday 2024-01-20</h2>
<ul>
<li>woke up at 5:40 because was planning to fetch GOU#1 and GOU#2 after their eventful and successful night, but thankfully partner was willing to go!</li>
<li>me very tired the whole day, just hanging (literally) around with family, and spending too much time on twitter / threads / reddit / inoreader! (brain was not willing to do much else, at least learned new things, some of which are mentioned below)</li>
<li>Based on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39055139">this HN discussion</a> about <a href="https://delta.io/blog/delta-lake-vs-parquet-comparison/">this blog post comparing Delta Lake and Parquet</a>, learned that Delta Parquet aka Delta Tables (which I&rsquo;ve read about in the context of Azure) is just a bunch of parquet files with some json metadata!
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;ve been enjoying <a href="https://parquet.apache.org/">parquet</a> for years now, in the context of scipy and specifically pandas.</li>
<li>Indeed, OneLake, also part of Microsoft Fabric, has Delta Parquet at its core.</li>
<li>Apache Iceberg is a similar but more open source implemenation: <a href="https://iceberg.apache.org/">https://iceberg.apache.org/</a></li>
<li>Based on <a href="https://www.dremio.com/blog/exploring-the-architecture-of-apache-iceberg-delta-lake-and-apache-hudi/">this comparison between Iceberg, Delta Lake and Hudi</a> it looks like all of these data lake storage layers are just parquet files with metadata, and then some logic, to give database like semantics over distributed object stores. Neat!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In bed last night, falling asleep, I had the following idea:
<ul>
<li><em>My Current Life Canvas</em> is a 3D bubble (off to my right for some reason&hellip; and moving with me as I walk) the interior of which I can view using my phone via AR (have to move phone in space to view inside of bubble, with current topics arranged in familiar spots; I thought having a world map would help, because well-known and memorable locations for your topics / priorities / ideas) or any of these amazing new VR headsets, BUT you can also interact with it via computer because inside of bubble can just be projected to surface using any of the well-known <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Map_projection">map projection techniques</a>.</li>
<li>CLC does not have a regular cadence like the daily or weekly plan, but is revised or redone a few times per year. It focuses on your major life priorities at any one point in time.</li>
<li>Although this was just a dreamy idea, I do like that it offers multi-modal interaction on the spectrum from AR/VR to more conventional desktop paradigms</li>
<li>&hellip; of course there should be some kind of friendly AI floating in the bubble with you :P (Microsoft Bob?)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-21">Sunday 2024-01-21</h2>
<ul>
<li>Super enjoyable weekend long(ish) run.</li>
<li>Tried out Omnivore&rsquo;s PDF annotation support, see screenshot below. Pretty impressive, and very cool that the highlights sync into my Emacs-based notes setup via markdown. Have slightly mixed feelings, because now will have to come up with new rule for when a paper goes into Zotero (fully local, full citations, but no automatic highlights sync) and when it goes into Omnivore (good sort of cloud but not local, no full citations, automatic sync into my notes)</li>
<li>Extended family Sunday lunch at our place was great, but me not at normal energy levels yet.</li>
<li>One of my goals for this week was &ldquo;Get through the week, especially Friday braai&rdquo;. Mission successful!</li>
</ul>










<figure><a href="20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_8552fa2e79f0c31.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_d562277b8133fec1.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_70c21750f4c22771.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_3fd7290a1dd605.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/01/21/daily-head-voices-2024-01-15_21/20240121-screenshot-omnivore-pdf-emacs_hu_d562277b8133fec1.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #239: Embarrassing finitude</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 22:05:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/</guid><description>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.
Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&amp;rsquo;s Bay.
House gets more energy reserves In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices, number 239, looks back on the three
weeks from Monday February 7 to Sunday February 27, 2022.</p>










<figure><a href="bettys-sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_74eb8d485118227a.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_82bbe2abd04f454.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_d618afba10beff8e.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_ad4c99d4cb012cd8.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/bettys-sunset_hu_82bbe2abd04f454.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Fiery sunset in Betty&rsquo;s Bay."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Fiery sunset in Betty&rsquo;s Bay.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="house-gets-more-energy-reserves">House gets more energy reserves</h2>
<p>In the first week of February, my house gained an additional 4.8kWh of lithium
ion battery storage for a total of 11.8, so that we are able to harvest more of
the copious amounts of sun in the summer.</p>
<p>The complete stack looks as follows, with the new UP5000 on top, and the two
&ldquo;old&rdquo; US3000 units (3.5kWh each) under it:</p>










<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_c456be51232ea52.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_907b8abe3409612e.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_cf07fa7f64eb5e01.png 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_22ea2d044cfbe8ef.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/03/01/weekly-head-voices-239-embarrassing-finitude/images/2022/2022-02-21_22-08-53_screenshot_hu_907b8abe3409612e.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: A cluster of lithium ion house batteries." width="400px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>A cluster of lithium ion house batteries.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I can already see the positive effect of this on the daily line chart of solar
energy stored: Where previously there were gaps, because the battery was full,
the hot water geysers were either already hot or had not come on yet (in our
house, these act as water batteries on fixed charge times) and we were not
drawing much load, the gaps are smoothed out and the area under the curve is
consistently higher.</p>
<h2 id="dot-dot-dot-while-human-has-to-make-peace-with-limited-energy-reserves">&hellip; while human has to make peace with limited energy reserves</h2>
<p>As a human, you have to deal with a limited amount of energy every day, as if
the fact that your total time on earth was embarrassingly finite was not
challenging enough.</p>
<p>In other words, during one&rsquo;s waking hours, of which one gets a limited number,
one can&rsquo;t rely on operating at the highest energy output all of the time.</p>
<p>As far as I can surmise, one can increase one&rsquo;s daily energy through the
consistent and continuous application of positive lifestyle choices.</p>
<p>This can be hard work, and due to the infernal complexity of organics (have you
looked at a <a href="http://biochemical-pathways.com/">map of metabolic pathways recently</a>? &ndash; you should really go take a
look, it&rsquo;s complicated but also really interesting) and the effects of aging
maybe even an intractable problem, and as if that&rsquo;s not enough, the right
lifestyle can be extremely boring (to those around you).</p>
<p>My mornings usually start pretty nicely, but by the middle of the afternoon my
brain starts disassembling itself anywhere from just after lunch to later in
the afternoon.</p>
<p>What I have recently started noticing, is that when I enjoy one of those highly
productive days with focus straying sharp until late in the afternoon, I pretty
much have to tone it down a bit the next day.</p>
<p>I can still do good work, but I do need to approach the day in a slightly more
relaxed fashion in order to make it through the whole thing in one piece, and
to increase the chances of having a highly productive day after the toned down
one.</p>
<h2 id="the-rickety-raft-of-life-directions-and-priorities">The rickety raft of life directions and priorities</h2>
<p>Staying on the theme of limited energy, but taking many steps back from the
cyclical alternate day grinding effect, I&rsquo;ve had to make peace with another
phenomenon:</p>
<p>Again thanks to embarrassingly limited energy, one can only focus on a subset
of one&rsquo;s life directions and priorities at any one time.</p>
<p>For example, when your children are younger, it&rsquo;s normal to dedicate a
substantial chunk of your time to them.</p>
<p>Between that and the necessary parts of work, not much time is left for one&rsquo;s
own hobbies, like Trying To Be a Better Human, or for other worthy goals, like
writing that novel(la) (short story, err or maybe just a nice haiku).</p>
<p>Conversely, when you&rsquo;re training for an important cycle race (not me, a
friend), some of those other dimensions by definition spend time on the
dimensional back burner.</p>
<p>So while you probably have a longer list of priorities which are all very
important to you, you have no choice but to make peace with the fact that at
any one point in time, you can only deal with a fairly narrow subset.</p>
<p>To me it looks the most important to make peace with this fact, and to treat it
as a deliberate and honest choice.</p>
<p>Oh and don&rsquo;t flip flop too much. (that&rsquo;s meant for me)</p>
<h2 id="young-human-wise-beyond-her-years">Young human wise beyond her years</h2>
<p><a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/">GOU#1</a> and I were chatting in the car, on way back from one of her social
commitments.</p>
<p>We talked about sleep. (Had she gotten enough?)</p>
<p>She mentioned people that get by on six hours per night and seem to get more
done&hellip;</p>
<p>As I was preparing to attempt commenting Socratically about this, she
pre-empted me by volunteering that when she sleeps well, and for much longer
than six hours, she experiences that she is better with other humans, and that
she feels emotions more intensely.</p>
<p>Goodness!</p>
<h2 id="two-pages-per-week">Two pages per week</h2>
<p>Soooo&hellip;. on the topic of GOU #1 and how best to spend my puny energy:</p>
<p>You might remember from <a href="/2020/05/10/weekly-head-voices-194-136-words-a-day/#gou-1-reveals-her-plans-and-makes-us-think--more">WHV #194</a> when GOU #1 revealed her cunning plan for
completing a PhD, part of which was writing only 136 words a day for a year,
leaving the two sandwich years for respectively planning and proofreading,
leading to a perfect thesis.</p>
<p>In the recent <a href="https://lexfridman.com/tim-urban/">Lex Fridman podcast #264 with Tim Urban</a>, he of <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/">Wait but why</a> fame,
they start <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Jd7fJgFkPU&amp;t=7166s">talking in-depth about procrastination at the 2 hour mark</a>. (relax,
you can listen to it later. <strong>&lt;ba dum tiss!&gt;</strong>)</p>
<p>(Urban considers himself a procrastinator, but he is a deep thinker, and so this
is a pretty interesting bit of conversation.)</p>
<p>He starts off with the example of a writer who is able to commit to producing
only two pages <em>per week</em>, and by consistently hitting this pretty modest
sounding goal, is able to prepare a book per year.</p>
<p>Glossing over the fact that 200 pages is perhaps not a very <em>impressive</em> book, at
least in terms of girth, publishing one every two years would be frankly
amazing.</p>
<p>He then talks about this idea of being able to attain something substantial and
worthwile by consistently chipping away.</p>
<p>He is clearly searching for the right word,
<a href="https://youtu.be/0Jd7fJgFkPU?t=7203">but then comes up with <em>compiling</em></a>.</p>
<p>I would really like to think that he was in fact searching for our old friend
<a href="/tags/compounding"><em>compounding</em></a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #236: The surprising power of consistent chipping</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/</guid><description>This 236th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the three (sorry!) weeks from Monday October 25 to Sunday November 14, 2021.
What will the beholder think? First things first: Do you notice something different about me I mean my blog?
I don&amp;rsquo;t know how most readers respond to this sort of a thing, but I can really appreciate, in a non-professional way of course, good typography on a personal blog.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This 236th edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back at the three (sorry!)
weeks from Monday October 25 to Sunday November 14, 2021.</p>










<figure><a href="facing-strand.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_c50724b8184b629d.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_b0b8092f9b20be8a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_da4f1a8a09255adf.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_c738209363b258d5.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/11/15/weekly-head-voices-236-surprising-power-of-consistent-chipping/facing-strand_hu_b0b8092f9b20be8a.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<h2 id="what-will-the-beholder-think">What will the beholder think?</h2>
<p>First things first: Do you notice something different about me I mean my blog?</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know how most readers respond to this sort of a thing, but I can really
appreciate, in a non-professional way of course, good typography on a personal
blog.</p>
<p>Over the past few years I&rsquo;ve been tweaking the CSS here and there to make small
improvements to the WHV typography, but I&rsquo;ve never been really happy with the
font.</p>
<p>That is, until I ran into <a href="https://alexanderobenauer.com/">Alexander Obenauer&rsquo;s blog</a> and just new that I had to
have the same serif on mine.</p>
<p>The font is called <a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Newsreader">Newsreader</a>. I&rsquo;m currently enjoying the subtly new look, I
hope you do too.</p>
<h2 id="new-diagramming-tool-of-the-insert-suitable-period-here">New diagramming tool of the [insert suitable period here]</h2>
<p>Via Hacker News (henceforth just &ldquo;HN&rdquo;) I ran into this <a href="https://offbyone.us/posts/why-is-excalidraw-so-good/">entertaining and
charming review of a drawing tool called &ldquo;excalidraw&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>Searching a little further, I could see that it had become in a relatively
short timespan a darling of the otherwise hyper-critical HN community.</p>
<p>Personally, I&rsquo;m always on the lookout for any tools which I think could help me
visualize some of my ideas or plans better.</p>
<p>Excalidraw is great at boxes and arrows, which is fortunate, since about 95% of
my ideas and plans are based on different ways of connecting boxes and arrows.</p>
<p>As an aside: So far, I&rsquo;ve gotten by far the most use out of Notability on the
iPad (with 1st gen Apple Pencil), but I never produce as many diagrams as I
keep on imagining that I should be doing.</p>
<p>Upon first use, Excalidraw indeed struck me with how little friction it offers
to the act of sketching out <em>stuff</em>.</p>
<p>I especially like how the authors have somehow managed to merge super-easy
drawing on the computer with the production of diagrams that look like they&rsquo;ve
been made on a paper notebook, whilst still remaining fully vectorized.</p>
<p>Let me know if you&rsquo;ve used this for anything interesting, or if you have any
other diagramming tricks you&rsquo;d like to share.</p>
<h2 id="ok-rust-i-give-up">Ok Rust, I give up</h2>
<p>Back in July of 2018, in <a href="/2018/07/17/weekly-head-voices-148-data-stylist/#programming-language-addiction-update">WHV #148</a>, I wrote that after noting the fact that Rust
was an expression-oriented language (I love those) and subsequently reading the
O&rsquo;Reilly <em>Programming Rust</em> book, I had filed away the language under
&ldquo;re-evaluate whenever you reach for your trusty C++&rdquo;.</p>
<p>As a programming language enthusiast, I should have know that that &ldquo;filing
away&rdquo; was merely a postponement of the inevitable.</p>
<p>Recently, in hobby time, probably because I had not yet selected a new book to
read, and because I&rsquo;m going through a bit of a programming phase (err&hellip;), I
unfiled Rust and started going through some more of the materials.</p>
<p>My current feeling is: Hot durnit! Rust may just be the fastest functional
language I have access to!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing a number of the <a href="https://exercism.org/tracks/rust">exercism exercises</a>, and after often pulling out
a pattern match for compact yet readable solutions, I&rsquo;ve been getting a strong
wolf-in-sheep&rsquo;s-clothing feeling.</p>
<p>Rust brings a number of core functional programming principles to an
exceptionally performant programming platform.</p>
<p>Sometimes there are still more nuts and bolts than I would like to see (to be
expected from a systems language that wants to give you full control), but this
mix of low-level and subjectively high-level functional programming is still a
remarkable achievement in my book.</p>
<p><em>Of course</em> I have no real-world applications in mind, unless <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">Advent of Code</a>
counts, but Rust currently makes for great programming practice.</p>
<h2 id="keep-on-keeping-on">Keep on keeping on</h2>
<p>In WHV #214 I wrote about <a href="/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/#one-main-thing">writing down that One Main Thing that you&rsquo;d like to
get done every day</a>.</p>
<p>Day job is currently not entirely conducive to this mode of work, and that&rsquo;s
putting it lightly.</p>
<p>Still, on most days I do remember to select and then write that thing down.</p>
<p>Most recently, I was dragging such an item along with me for what felt like
weeks.</p>
<p>Every morning I did the Alt-W Ctrl-Y finger dance (that&rsquo;s Emacs for copy
paste), and I experienced the concomitant pang of internally facing
embarrassment.</p>
<p>Often there would be no progress (because meetings and other non-maker work),
but on some days I would excavate the equivalent of a generously filled
teaspoon of dirt. (<a href="https://youtu.be/4_C86o5dE_c">Doctor Flammond&rsquo;s tunnel</a> anybody?)</p>
<p>Slowly but surely, the Thing neared completion, until one day (weirdly still to
my pleasant surprise) it was done, never to be copy-pasted again.</p>
<p>My happy little mental note was: Just keep on dragging One Main Thing with
you. It&rsquo;s not on the list because it&rsquo;s going to get completed, but rather
because it&rsquo;s the thing that you just have to keep on chipping away at,
<em>especially</em> when progress seems almost invisible.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #214: One Main Thing</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 21:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/</guid><description>WELCOME BACK EVERYONE TO THIS WARM AND WELCOMING CIRCLE OF WEEKLY HEAD VOICES!
Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>WELCOME BACK EVERYONE TO THIS WARM AND WELCOMING CIRCLE OF WEEKLY HEAD VOICES!</p>










<figure><a href="hermanus_coastal_walk.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu_536d804904491d41.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu_19b8cc6641c35fad.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu_b115b17cbda04156.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu_643879c0e4a6f9ea.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/26/weekly-head-voices-214-one-main-thing/hermanus_coastal_walk_hu_19b8cc6641c35fad.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: View from a family walk in Hermanus. I was surprised by the beauty here, memories of years ago apparently faded.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>You are reading the 214th edition of the WHV, the first of 2021 (hurrah), and
spottily covering the intersections of my consciousness with the period of time
from Monday, January 11 to Sunday, January 24 of the year 2021.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not entirely happy with the water-tightness of this coverage, but <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/">the
2020-2021 year transition post</a>, which I hope you&rsquo;ve read or at least heard
about, is probably worth this bit of start-point haziness.</p>
<h2 id="first-rule-of-blogging-we-don-t-blog-about-blogging">First rule of blogging: We don&rsquo;t blog about blogging</h2>
<p>As you know, <a href="/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">I <strong>really</strong> love Hugo</a>, the software tool with which I can write
these posts in Emacs (text editor, you heathens) and then convert them to the
fast static pages that you are now reading.</p>
<p>The one thing I <em>was</em> a bit disappointed with, was the lack of some form of
built-in yearly post archives.</p>
<p>Well, while writing the year transition post, this disappointment spiked into
action, and so I applied just enough internet and elbow grease to scratch my
yearly archive itch on this blog.</p>
<p><a href="/2021/01/10/super-simple-yearly-post-archives-hugo/">This post shows you how to do it</a>, and <a href="/archive/">here you can see the result, yearly
archives for all of the posts on this blog</a>!</p>
<p>As a first step on <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#comms-upgrade">my path to become better at asynchronous communication</a>, I
wrote <a href="/2021/01/16/intro-asynchronous-communication/">an introductory blog post on the topic</a>.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m not as happy with it as I would have liked to be, but it&rsquo;s the line in the
sand that I really wanted to draw.</p>
<p>More importantly, I&rsquo;ve been able to get a few people to read it.</p>
<h2 id="signal-i-told-you-so">Signal: I told you so</h2>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2021/01/whatsapp-users-must-share-their-data-with-facebook-or-stop-using-the-app/">WhatsApp recently making clear that they will be sharing increasing
amounts of the massive amounts of your data at their disposal with all other
companies in the Facebook family</a>, many folks have been looking for
alternatives.</p>
<p>Even more fortunately, many of those folks have been choosing the most
pragmatically private alternative, namely Signal.</p>
<p>You might recall that <a href="/2016/01/02/when-we-can-lets-use-signal-instead-of-whatsapp/">I started recommending that we use Signal back in January
of 2016</a>, which is infinity years ago in internet time.</p>
<p>Telegram does indeed count as an alternative to WhatsApp, but its chats are by
default not end-to-end encrypted, and it&rsquo;s still backed by a for-profit
company. There&rsquo;s nothing wrong with this, but if your concern is privacy now
and in the future, Signal is by far the better choice.</p>
<p>Anyways, I am happy to see more of my contacts appear in the Signal list.</p>
<h2 id="one-main-thing">One Main Thing</h2>
<p>In 2011, <a href="/2011/02/19/on-the-importance-of-taking-notes-weekly-head-voices-38/#pro-tip-2">I wrote about starting the day by writing down concretely the tasks
one would like to complete by the end of the day</a>.</p>
<p>A few years later, <a href="/2019/03/09/weekly-head-voices-164-its-what-future-you-would-want/#thinking-of-future-you">I picked up a tip from a podcast with Sam Harris and Derren
Brown that one should explicitly ask the question which tasks would satisfy you
the most at the end of the day</a>.</p>
<p>(Interestingly, in the 2018 post above I misquoted my 2011 post as suggesting
that one writes down &ldquo;the two to three really important tasks for the
day&rdquo;. That &ldquo;two to three&rdquo; came from some other memory which I can&rsquo;t track down
right now.)</p>
<p>Last year <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#its-what-future-you-would-want-quote-edition">I ran into Lubbock&rsquo;s far more eloquent formulation</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If we are ever in doubt about what to do, it is a good rule to ask ourselves
what we shall wish on the morrow that we had done. &ndash; John Lubbock</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the comments to that post, friend AJ added the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Another iteration of what to do next that I recently heard was Gary Kellers
version: The One Thing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have not yet gotten around to reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The%5FOne%5FThing%5F(book)">The One Thing</a>, but I think AJ&rsquo;s comment
did plant a seed&hellip;</p>
<p>Fast forward a few months, and I have started to realise that my most
productive and satisfying days often coincide with the days when I have the
guts in the morning to commit to one main thing for the day.</p>
<p>Conversely, when I don&rsquo;t select and commit to One Main Thing, but due to
deadlines and other expectations put more than two or more bigger items on my
list, that day has a high probability of leaving me quite frazzled by its end.</p>
<p>One Main Thing days are scary, because I feel like there is always a long list
of things I&rsquo;m not going to get to, and people I&rsquo;m going to have to disappoint.</p>
<p>However, selecting that One Main Thing wisely, explicitly committing to it, and
then knocking it off after a few hours of focus is undeniably satisfying, and
will probably help a bunch of people.</p>
<p>Furthermore, it turns out that even with this commitment, one does still manage
to get some of the little things done in the scraps of left-over time.</p>
<p>You know, just after lunch, just before dinner and so on.</p>
<p>Pay some bills, answer a few emails, and then dive back into your One Main
Thing.</p>
<h3 id="interstitial-projects">Interstitial projects</h3>
<p>In addition to this, it turns out some of my projects can be specifically
treated as <em>interstitial</em>.</p>
<p>This is the label I&rsquo;ve chosen for those projects that 1. are supported by
low-friction tools that are instantly available and 2. benefit from slivers of
thought.</p>
<p>For example, I&rsquo;m working on a few blog posts dealing with issues I come across
during my work.</p>
<p>During the day, I see something that warrants a section in one of the blog
posts&hellip;</p>
<p>Switch to Emacs, hotkey search the relevant notes file, hotkey search the
relevant section in that file, type the sentence or two in your head, switch
back to work.</p>
<p>That took all of a minute or two, but now there are two new sentences, and we
all know what sentences do, right? They <a href="/tags/compounding/">compound</a> into blog posts!</p>
<h2 id="do-you-want-to-produce-or-consume">Do you want to produce or consume?</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;m technically not allowed to write about something that appeared after the
published timespan of a WHV, but I would be remiss if I did not mention the
nudge that got WHV #214 off the ground.</p>
<p>That nudge is <a href="http://noeskasmit.com/recommendations/">this post by Noeska</a>, and specifically these words:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Do I want to produce or consume?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You should really go read the post for context, but if you need to hear that
sentence, you&rsquo;ll probably understand exactly what it means.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>