<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Ivy on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/ivy/</link><description>Recent content in Ivy on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Dec 2020 15:55:51 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/ivy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #210: MiniBurn 2020</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 09:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/</guid><description> Welcome back to the WHV blogging clubhouse, gang!
Somewhat inspired by Descartes, I can say with a fair amount of confidence that you are now reading these words, and for that I am grateful.
This post covers the weeks from Monday, November 9 to Sunday, November 22 of the year 2020.
papercite_static: put some bibtex into your Hugo After languishing for almost a year on my todo list, I finally got around to cleaning up and making available my Python script for embedding your BiBTeX bibliographies in your markdown files.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="dirt_road_to_stanford.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu_df55c8c205226d65.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu_a5dd115f6b641bf5.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu_f1f04ca55337507f.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu_c61b320f51f08f68.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/11/29/weekly-head-voices-210-miniburn-2020/dirt_road_to_stanford_hu_a5dd115f6b641bf5.jpg"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Welcome back to the WHV blogging clubhouse, gang!</p>
<p>Somewhat inspired by Descartes, I can say with a fair amount of confidence that
you are now reading these words, and for that I am grateful.</p>
<p>This post covers the weeks from Monday, November 9 to Sunday, November 22 of
the year 2020.</p>
<h2 id="papercite-static-put-some-bibtex-into-your-hugo">papercite_static: put some bibtex into your Hugo</h2>
<p>After languishing for almost a year on my todo list, I finally got around to
cleaning up and making available my Python script for embedding your BiBTeX
bibliographies in your markdown files.</p>
<p>The script is called <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/papercite%5Fstatic">papercite_static</a>, because it was inspired by <a href="https://wordpress.org/plugins/papercite/">the papercite
Wordpress plugin</a> that I previously used, but it was built for use in static
websites.</p>
<p>Catchy right?</p>
<p>This is pretty useful when you are academically inclined, or just really like
managing BiBTeX files.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re one of those people, you can go check it out at <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/papercite%5Fstatic">the papercite_static
github page</a>.</p>
<h2 id="save-image-from-clipboard">save_image_from_clipboard</h2>
<p>From the Department of Catchy Names, the same one that brought you the script
above, comes <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/save%5Fimage%5Ffrom%5Fclipboard">save_image_from_clipboard</a>!</p>
<p>I wrote this to scratch my own extremely niche itch (scranitch-ware!), but it
could be useful in other slightly less niche contexts.</p>
<p>My Emacs is configured with the org-download package so that I can use any
system tool to screenshot an arbitrary region of my screen to the clipboard,
and then tell Emacs to attach whatever is in the clipboard to the current
Orgmode heading.</p>
<p>This is something I use really often during daily note-taking and task
management.</p>
<p>The org-download package expects a PNG image to be available on the
clipboard. When this is not the case, because the screenshotting or other image
copying workflow instead copied a JPG or a BMP (long story, starts with a W,
ends with SL&hellip;), I get a blank attachment which makes me sad, and costs me
more time.</p>
<p>On macOS, I used <a href="https://github.com/jcsalterego/pngpaste">pngpaste</a> for this, a tool that ensures that whatever image
format is in the clipboard gets converted to PNG.</p>
<p>Well, <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/save%5Fimage%5Ffrom%5Fclipboard">save_image_from_clipboard</a> does exactly this, and a little more by simply
converting whatever&rsquo;s on the clipboard to the format that you specify.</p>
<p>This has already saved me countless SECONDS of time, and a substantial amount
of frustration.</p>
<p>P.S. I&rsquo;ve again been spending more hobby time with <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a>, which would have
resulted in a much smaller and faster binary in this case, but the Python
version wrote itself fairly quickly, with both of my hands behind my back.</p>
<p>P.P.S. nim is <em>so</em> hard to resist, in spite of what <a href="/2019/04/15/weekly-head-voices-169-a-cunning-plan/#nimfatuation-is-now-over">I wrote about nimfatuation
being over, back in WHV #169</a>. It combines much of the expressiveness and some
of the batteries-included of Python, paired with the generation of tiny
self-contained binaries.</p>
<h2 id="my-emacs-is-now-all-in-on-ivy">My Emacs is now all-in on Ivy</h2>
<p>As you will <em>most probably</em> remember from <a href="/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/#you-can-easily-dired-jump-to-the-currently-ivy-readd-file-in-emacs">WHV #171</a>, my Emacs configuration used
a mishmash of <a href="https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm">Helm</a> and <a href="https://github.com/abo-abo/swiper">Ivy</a>.</p>
<p>Helm and Ivy are two great, but different, examples of Emacs completion /
selection frameworks, something that is really important to any disciple of
this amazing religion.</p>
<p>In something that is probably some sort of reflection of my character, I was
happily using both of them simultaneously for quite a while.</p>
<p>However, waking up one morning with the realisation that this was yet another
small context switch that was costing me time and focus, in one of my highest
ROI tool workflows to boot, I decided that it was time to excise Helm from my
configuration.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a few hours of Lisp-driven terraforming, and I was all-in on my
Ivy.</p>
<p>During this terraforming I ran into some undesired behaviour in ivy-rich, which
resulted first in me writing <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2020/11/15/fix-ivy-rich-switch-buffer-directories-display-in-emacs/">a blog post documenting the work-around</a>, then
noticing that ivy-rich&rsquo;s astute author had subsequently integrated part of my
fix, and finally authoring a <a href="https://github.com/Yevgnen/ivy-rich/pull/92">github pull request (PR)</a>, merged shortly after to
fix the remaining issues.</p>
<p>P.S. I sometimes wonder whether people outside of the open source world
understand how much github contributed to the software world by streamlining
the process whereby random developers are able to contribute lines of source
code into open source projects like this.</p>
<p>WELL DO YA?!</p>
<h2 id="mynoise-dot-net-is-an-amazing-soundscape-generator">mynoise.net is an amazing soundscape generator</h2>
<p>In the past few weeks, Lazar Focus has rescued my days so often.</p>
<p>What usually happens is that I get distracted&hellip; no wait, I fall down a
rabbit-hole&hellip; no wait, I actually get violently pulled into a rabbit
<strong>singularity</strong> from whence no productivity can escape.</p>
<p>The best I can do at that point, is to pour all will power into my puny arm and
click on that FOCUS button in Lazar Focus, at which point it instantly kills
everything that&rsquo;s sapping my attention, and then I again have a chance to save
the day.</p>
<p>Thanks to a recommendation by Noeska which ended up languishing in my
sub-conscious but then fortunately managed to bubble to the top, I found myself
on a wonderful site called <a href="https://mynoise.net/">myNoise</a>.</p>
<p>This is the creation of <a href="https://stephanepigeon.com/">Dr. Ir. Stéphane Pigeon</a>, a research engineer &amp; sound
designer from Belgium, who has combined noise generation as well as a library
of the highest quality recording of samples from the world over with a system
for composing these into the most amazing sound-scapes.</p>
<p>Why is this interesting, you might ask?</p>
<p>Well, in one&rsquo;s quest to block distractions of all kinds, finding the perfect
aural stimulus that is pleasant, but does not soak up attention itself, and is
also able to mask both external and internal (tinnitus, e.g.) sounds, myNoise
is exactly what the doctor ordered!</p>
<p>To give you a taste of Dr Pigeon&rsquo;s attention to detail, see for example the
<a href="https://mynoise.net/NoiseMachines/singingBowlsDroneGenerator.php">singing bowls generator</a>, and then the <a href="https://mynoise.net/NoiseMachines/enliaVocalSoundscape.php">Free-falling with vocalist Enlia
soundscape</a>.</p>
<p>Notice that in both cases you are able to customise different elements of each
soundscape with the sliders, or even press <code>A</code> to have them animate randomly
over time, morphing the landscape as you work.</p>
<p>What I only recently learned, is that Dr Pigeon designed the soundscapes to
work also simultaneously. In other words, keep the two soundscapes above open
in two browser tabs, and note how wonderfully they mesh.</p>
<p>It really feels like my brain is starting to associate high attention mode with
the mynoise soundscapes.</p>
<p>Between that and LF, we might be going places!</p>
<p>P.S. Narrator: <em>Yes, he did make a small donation to mynoise, and based on the
value he has derived since, will probably make another.</em></p>
<h2 id="what-does-it-mean-for-humanity-when-the-ai-can-derive-your-talking-face-from-your-voice-alone">What does it mean for humanity when the AI can derive your talking face from your voice alone?</h2>
<p>You might have read about <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/5/21502003/nvidia-ai-videoconferencing-maxine-platform-face-gaze-alignment-gans-compression-resolution">NVIDIA&rsquo;s new AI-based video conferencing bag of
tricks, called Maxine</a>.</p>
<p>An interesting part of this is that they use a technique, similar to deepfakes,
to send only the pose of your face over the internet, and then reconstruct a
high quality version of it on the other side.</p>
<p>From the article:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Instead of streaming the entire screen of pixels, the AI software analyzes the
key facial points of each person on a call and then intelligently re-animates
the face in the video on the other side,&rdquo; said the company in a blog
post. &ldquo;This makes it possible to stream video with far less data flowing back
and forth across the internet.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This made me think:</p>
<p>Soon the AI will be good enough that it can reconstruct your face from just the
audio, or maybe even text that you type.</p>
<p>This idea started as a half-serious joke, but it does raise really interesting
questions around the implications of this technology. (BTW, it is technically
entirely possible.)</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re having a conversation with someone, and both of your faces are
indistinguishable <em>simulations</em> of the real thing, and hence help the quality
of the conversation, what does that mean for the conversation that&rsquo;s happening?</p>
<p>In other words, imagine for a second that you&rsquo;re having an intense (emotional)
conversation with someone, but the faces that both of you are seeing, are 100%
synthesised.</p>
<p>They reflect almost exactly how your faces would have looked had you had a
video link, but they are estimated by the AI.</p>
<p>Did you really have that intense conversation?</p>
<h2 id="miniburn-2020">MiniBurn 2020</h2>
<p>As you might remember from <a href="/2020/03/24/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-1/#sht-gets-real-in-mzansi">WHV #191</a>, AfrikaBurn 2020 was one of the first group
events down here that was cancelled by the pandemic.</p>
<p>Months after that, and with stats looking almost reasonable, the local subset
of our camp (THE BURNIVERSITY) decided to celebrate life together, as
responsibly as possible (which mostly comes down to: stay outside, keep your
distance), by gathering at some secret but beautiful location for the weekend.</p>
<p>(You might have deduced by now that this is one of those Burny situations where
I have no choice but to keep things as vague as they are. I still wanted to
write <strong>something</strong> as a beacon for future me. Future me, when you read this:
Read our private notes man. I left you something there.)</p>
<p>We sort of modeled the weekend like a whole Burn: Friday is arrival, setup, and
first small celebrations. Saturday represents the body of the week: Running,
workshops, celebration. Sunday is, just like it is for the full Burn, the
slightly depressing but already nostalgic clean-up, pack-up and leave the
desert stage. It&rsquo;s surprising how well this whole sequencing worked.</p>
<p>Thanks to the awe-inspiring talents of specific camp members, the cuisine was
divine and the music beautiful. Combined with the personalities and shared
memories of our small ensemble, the resultant experience was nothing short of
magic.</p>
<p>P.S. Ironically, <a href="/2020/11/12/weekly-head-voices-208-blogging-like-its-2009/#thank-you-joris">GU43 <strong>is</strong> turning into the 2020 soundtrack that I wanted</a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #171: ICEMiRB.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 22:38:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/</guid><description> Down here, you never know what sort of fantastic beasts you could run into. I met this particular fullmetal creature right about here.
Dear friends,
In this post, I do a particularly lossy review of my trip through time, from Monday May 6 to Sunday May 19, 2019.
First we talk about sleep, then a long part on technical tricks, then a slightly more backyard philosophical piece on human tool sharpening, and finally the announcement of a new academic event somewhere in the far or near or medium term future.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="fullmetal_baboon.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu_bcd57a5072bf9e1b.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu_69a49565a53a1413.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu_fb9cdec0b4146e63.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu_14aacecae2fd7902.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/05/22/weekly-head-voices-171-icemirb/fullmetal_baboon_hu_69a49565a53a1413.jpg"
  

   />



</a>
<figcaption>
<p>Down here, you never know what sort of fantastic beasts you could run into. I
met this particular fullmetal creature <a
href="https://goo.gl/maps/KpcQGa6hEcbd87mF7">right about here</a>.</p>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Dear friends,</p>
<p>In this post, I do a particularly lossy review of my trip through time, from
Monday May 6 to Sunday May 19, 2019.</p>
<p>First we talk about sleep, then a long part on technical tricks, then a
slightly more backyard philosophical piece on human tool sharpening, and
finally the announcement of a new academic event somewhere in the far or near
or medium term future.</p>
<h1 id="sleep">Sleep.</h1>
<p>If you were one of the people who found themselves in my company for more than
about 10 nanoseconds during the past weeks, I probably tried to get you to
listen to <a href="/2019/05/07/weekly-head-voices-170-yeet/#the-easiest-but-most-high-impact-measure-you-can-take-to-not-die-too-soon-go-to-bed-on-time">the 6-hour long podcast between Peter Attia and Matthew Walker on
the topic of
sleep</a>.</p>
<p>Usually I&rsquo;m able to get something sufficiently out of my system by writing
about here. I do this quite deliberately to try and spare my innocent
bystanders.</p>
<p>This time, either it didn&rsquo;t really help, or I underestimate how much I would
have blabbed about it had I not let off some of the sleep steam here.</p>
<p>IN ANY CASE&hellip;</p>
<p>During the past weeks I have been paying more attention than usual to sleep, in
terms of quality, quantity and consistency.</p>
<p>Because I also decided to take more notes than usual during the day, I could
see quite acutely the effects of good sleep vs bad sleep on my performance and
energy levels the next day.</p>
<p>If sleep was good the night before, my exercise the next day seemed to take
much less effort, I still seemed to have more than enough energy at the end of
the afternoon, and, most importantly, I had almost no trouble with that
ever-important f-word:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>FOCUS.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Conversely, if I let sleep-onset slip by as little as half an hour, my brain
would be in three thousand pieces by three &lsquo;o clock the next afternoon.</p>
<p>It is starting to dawn on me that all of those evenings where I tried to borrow
an hour or even two from my sleep had a far greater cost the day after than I
ever realised.</p>
<p><strong>I can only conclude, that to experience the highest quality and intensity
waking hours, one simply has no choice but to pay the full 33% sleep tax.</strong></p>
<h2 id="damnit-coffee">Damnit coffee.</h2>
<p>Caffeine has a quarter life of 12 hours.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re positively buzzing at 1PM, 25% of that caffeine is still active in
your system at 1AM and absolutely will interfere with your sleep quality.</p>
<p>I have compromised by having my last shot before lunch, or in extreme cases
right after.</p>
<h1 id="til-things-i-learned">TIL: Things I learned.</h1>
<p>This WHV is one week late, because it seemed like nothing happened in the first week.</p>
<p>However, it seems I did learn quite few new technical tricks. In the
subsections below, I share a selection of these with you.</p>
<h2 id="remarkjs-is-great-for-quickly-building-technical-presentations">remarkjs is great for quickly building technical presentations.</h2>
<p>At <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Helderberg-Software-Developers-and-Entrepreneurs/">my favourite local
meetup</a>,
I was planning to give a talk on <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a>, the static website
generator which is powering this site, and which I&rsquo;m increasingly using instead
of wordpress.</p>
<p>Because every new project is an opportunity to check and perhaps upgrade one&rsquo;s
tools (see below for how this can also sometimes backfire), I set aside the
trusty <a href="https://revealjs.com/">reveal.js</a> and <a href="https://github.com/yjwen/org-reveal">ox-reveal Emacs orgmode
interface</a> I usually bust out, and paddled
out onto rough internet seas, on the lookout for an alternative solution.</p>
<p>(Now that I think back, I had no good reason to search for an alternative,
except that my pre-configured reveal.js style and formatting never made me
really happy.)</p>
<p>Fortunately, after not too long I ran into <a href="https://remarkjs.com">remark</a>, an
HTML- and markdown-based presentation tool that seems simpler than reveal, but
still quite attractive, as you&rsquo;ll be able to see on the demo site above.</p>
<p>At this point, I was pleasantly surprised that this distraction had not cost
more than about 30 minutes.</p>
<p>At least, that <em>was</em> the case until I ran into <a href="https://github.com/torgeir/remark-mode.el">remark-mode for
Emacs</a>!</p>
<p>As you can see from the screenshot, this enables a pretty smooth
generate-as-you-type workflow.</p>
<p>Also noteworthy, is the great built-in presenter mode. Press <code>C</code> to clone the
window into a new linked presentation which you can move off to the external
display, and then press <code>P</code> to switch to presenter mode where you can see all
of the comments you have left in the markdown.</p>
<p>I made two small fixes in <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/remark-mode.el">my own
fork</a> to enable seeding with your
own HTML template, and to enable the generate-as-you-type to work also on
straight <code>.md</code> files. I prefer keeping my presentations as <code>.md</code> (vs <code>.remark</code>)
as most of the search logic I have built in Emacs assumes <code>.org</code> and <code>.md</code>
files for my notes.</p>
<p>By choosing remarkjs instead of my existing revealjs workflow I did manage to
exhaust the short block of time I had allocated to prepare for the talk, and so
the talk morphed into a more spontaneous affair, dealing with orgmode, remarkjs
and in the end, also a bit of hugo.</p>
<h2 id="pybtex-is-a-pure-python-bibtex-parser-and-renderer">pybtex is a pure-Python bibtex parser and renderer.</h2>
<p>One of the sites getting the wordpress-to-hugo upgrade treatment was my
internet persona placeholder, the almost completely unknown
<a href="https://charlbotha.com/">charlbotha.com</a>.</p>
<p>The upgrade of this tiny site would have gone quite easily, were it not for the
fact that I was using the wordpress papercite plugin to publish a list of all
of the publications, including fulltexts in most cases, that I&rsquo;ve had the
pleasure to be involved in over the years.</p>
<p>I could not find any tool which could give me exactly the sort of publication
lists that papercite was able to.</p>
<p>To me it was clear that yet another tool was required. (&ldquo;my god, it&rsquo;s full of biases!&rdquo;)</p>
<p>Fortunately, <a href="https://mentat.za.net">@stefanvdwalt</a> very quickly pointed me at
the Python package <a href="https://pybtex.org">pybtex</a> when he saw that I was
careening off into the dark side with <a href="https://citation.js.org">citation.js</a>.</p>
<p>A few hours later I had built a script which was able to eat my
Zotero-generated bibtex file and spit out different lists of publications with
linked PDFs straight into a Hugo-edible markdown file.</p>
<p>See <a href="https://charlbotha.com/publications/">charlbotha.com/publications</a> for the
result.</p>
<p>P.S. Making it available to a broader audience is on my todo-list.</p>
<h2 id="asciidoc-is-one-of-your-best-choices-to-write-software-manuals">asciidoc is one of your best choices to write software manuals.</h2>
<p>We are currently working hard towards the release of version 2.0 of our
flagship FDA-certified cardiology product,
<a href="https://www.telesensi.com">TeleSensi</a>.</p>
<p>Because updating the user manual with every release is not as fun as it could
be, I had the idea to convert the doc-format source file to some text-based
document authoring system.</p>
<p>Again, in spite of past positive experience writing manuals with
<a href="http://docutils.sourceforge.net">reStructuredText</a> and LaTeX, I made use of
the opportunity to try out
<a href="https://asciidoctor.org/docs/what-is-asciidoc/">asciidoc</a>.</p>
<p>In <em>this</em> case, I am happy to report that the choice of asciidoc ended up
beating all of the alternatives by a mile.</p>
<p>I started by <a href="https://pandoc.org">pandoc</a>-ing the docx to asciidoc, and then
manually (ha ha, it&rsquo;s a joke we writers tell) fine-tuned the document until, in
a few hours, the new manual looked significantly better than the original.</p>
<p>Long story short, our manual is now part of the software source repository and
hence version-locked, it can be automatically built for new releases, and parts
of the manual can be linked programmatically to form parts of our compliance
documentation.</p>
<p>With the manual now essentially being a software construct, there are many more
tricks we can do (and already do, but I&rsquo;m not allowed to say much more).</p>
<h2 id="you-can-build-self-contained-installers-with-legacy-non-modular-apps-and-recent-modular-java">You can build self-contained installers with legacy non-modular apps and recent modular Java.</h2>
<p>In a rather surprising (to me) turn of events, I had to convert some legacy
(read: non-modular) Java code from a product component to a self-contained
installer on Windows and macOS so that our users never even have to <em>think</em>
about JREs.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s possible that the following magical recipe could help you, should you ever
find yourself in a similar predicament:</p>
<ul>
<li>Install <a href="https://adoptopenjdk.net">AdoptOpenJDK</a> 11 (LTS)</li>
<li>Retrieve and extract this <a href="https://mail.openjdk.java.net/pipermail/openjfx-dev/2018-September/022500.html">backport of the new
javapackager</a>
from the yet to be released Java 13 into your OpenJDK 11.</li>
<li>Build your legacy <a href="https://imagej.net/Uber-JAR">uber-JAR</a> with the freshly
installed OpenJDK11.</li>
<li>Use <code>jdeps</code> to determine the list of modular dependencies of your uber-JAR.</li>
<li>Armed with this knowledge, build a mini java-runtime using <code>jlink</code>.</li>
<li>Now feed your uber-jar and the freshly created java-runtime to <code>jpackager</code> in
order to construct a fully self-contained executable or platform-specific
installation package.</li>
</ul>
<p>Much, but not all, of that comes from <a href="https://medium.com/@adam_carroll/java-packager-with-jdk11-31b3d620f4a8">this blog
post</a>.</p>
<h2 id="you-can-easily-dired-jump-to-the-currently-ivy-readd-file-in-emacs">You can easily dired-jump to the currently ivy-read&rsquo;d file in Emacs.</h2>
<p>I mix and match <a href="https://github.com/abo-abo/swiper">ivy</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm">helm</a> in my Emacs.</p>
<p>When you&rsquo;re helming for a file, you can usually press <code>F5</code> to open dired
(Emacs&rsquo;s built-in filemanager) on that file&rsquo;s directory.</p>
<p>This is quite convenient, and something I was missing in ivy, which I use for
example as part of <code>find-file-in-project</code>.</p>
<p>Weeeeell, by adding the following to your <code>init.el</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; for any ivy-read, press M-o to get action menu,</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#57606a">;; then &#39;d&#39; to start dired with that file selected</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">ivy-add-actions</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#0550ae">t</span> <span style="color:#57606a">;; add for all types</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#57606a">;; (cdr x) gets the full filename, not just relative</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span> <span style="color:#0550ae">`</span><span style="color:#1f2328">((</span><span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;d&#34;</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">,</span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">lambda</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">x</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">dired-jump</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">nil</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">cdr</span> <span style="color:#953800">x</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)))</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;dired&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>   <span style="color:#1f2328">))</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; you get to select <code>d</code> from the <code>M-o</code> action menu to <code>dired-jump</code> (a
wonderful command by itself, usually bound to <code>C-x C-j</code>) to the currently
focused file.</p>
<h1 id="sharpening-these-rocks">Sharpening these rocks.</h1>
<p>All of that brings us to this.</p>
<p>I spent quite a few hours last week performing meta-work: That is, not doing
the work itself, but rather sharpening the tools required to do that work.</p>
<p>As with all important matters, there&rsquo;s an XKCD comic about this topic too:</p>
<figure>
<a href="https://xkcd.com/1205/">
<img src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/is_it_worth_the_time.png" alt="xkcd on
tool sharpening">
</a>
<figcaption>
Incredibly useful visualization by XKCD: How much time will your tool
sharpening save per event, and how frequently does that event occur? The
cross-indexed block is how much time this could save you over 5 years.
</figure>
<p>Besides the mostly defensible tricks mentioned in the previous section, I did
also invest hours in attempting to update the mobile and email-based parts of
my personal knowledge management strategy (because
<a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">Windows</a>), but these hours led to a less than
satisfactory solution.</p>
<p>If I have to be honest, it feels like those hours were wasted, although it was
impossible to say beforehand that the effort to outcome ratio was going to be
that bad.</p>
<p>(To make it all a bit more interesting, a few days later some of the dead-ends
explored during those wasted hours led to coincidental improvements of other
frequently occurring (on the order of 5 times per day) components of my
workflow.)</p>
<p>Some folks double down on their workflows, rather taking the small hits and
spending the time doing their actual work.</p>
<p>I find it difficult to resist an opportunity for streamlining.</p>
<p>Sometimes this pays off, not in the least because of the compounding effects of
frequently applicable optimisations, and other times I fall down the rabbit
hole.</p>
<p>In my dreams, I am able to reach a sort of workflow optimisation pinnacle,
where all inefficiencies have been excised from the system. In reality, goal
posts like to move it move it, and so the scramble never ends.</p>
<p>How do you approach this?</p>
<h1 id="icemirb">ICEMiRB</h1>
<p><em>The International Conference on Emacs, Minimal Running and Blogging</em>, or
ICEMiRB, is a new meeting of minds and legs that the aforementioned and
indomitable <a href="https://mentat.za.net">@stefanvdwalt</a> and I are currently bouncing
around.</p>
<p>I actually just want the t-shirt, but the more I think about this, the more I
think it&rsquo;s something that one day really has to happen.</p>
<p>Please let me know in the comments if you would be interested in taking part.</p>
<p>I imagine we will go all out in terms of the various forms of attendance and
participation that we accommodate.</p>
<p>Have a beautiful week folks, I hope to see you again soon!</p>
<h2 id="ps">P.S.</h2>
<p>@stefanvdwalt just reminded me that Mindfulness is to be the fourth main topic
of the ICEMiRB.</p>
<p>Because the acronym is already of substantial girth (yes, we know that
Mindfulness and Minimal could co-habit the same part of the
acronym. coincidence?!), we will try to settle for one of two conference
taglines:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ICEMiRB - A Mindful(TM) Conference.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>or</p>
<blockquote>
<p>ICEMiRB - The Mindfulness is silent.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>or not.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>