<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>mitch hedberg on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/mitch-hedberg/</link><description>Recent content in mitch hedberg on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:43:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/mitch-hedberg/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #168: Postcards from the edge.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 22:43:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek, Stellenbosch. My friend showed me a photo and said &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s a picture of me when I was younger&rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger. &ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)
In this edition of the WHV, I cast my now older eyes back on the week starting on Monday, April 1 and ending on Sunday, April 7, 2019.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <figure>
<a href="postcard_cafe_view.jpg">
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/postcard_cafe_view_hu03250394b5533205db249a2d1d0cc394_2490609_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



</a>
<figcaption> 
Sometimes it feels like the place is falling apart, and sometimes
you find yourself in a heavenly corner like this. Postcard Café, Jonkershoek,
Stellenbosch.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<blockquote>
<p>My friend showed me a photo and said &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s a picture of me when I was
younger&rdquo;. Every picture is of you when you were younger.
&ndash; Mitch Hedberg (RIP)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this edition of the WHV, I cast my now older eyes back on the week starting
on Monday, April 1 and ending on Sunday, April 7, 2019.</p>
<p>I have to apologise for the extremely high nerd content. There will be wine at
the end to make up for it!</p>
<h2 id="working-late-like-its-1998">Working late like it&rsquo;s 1998.</h2>
<p>At the start of the week, I had resolved to get more sleep.</p>
<p>It seems that when I have a good night&rsquo;s sleep, really working that
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glymphatic_system">glymphatic system</a> (I&rsquo;m
currently fascinated by the glymphatic system, I hope you like it too),
amongst other nightly repair activities, there is a greater probability that I
am able to hold my focus the next day.</p>
<p>This was going swimmingly.</p>
<p>At least that was the case until Wednesday, when I decided that the time had
come to port <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs</a>, the far more nerdy sister of this
blog, from <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/03/31/wordpress-to-hugo/">wordpress to hugo as
well</a>.</p>
<p>One thing led to another, and by 1:00AM (on a school night no less!) I was
busy wrapping up the isso commenting system configuration.</p>
<p>(We&rsquo;re able to use free and ad-free disqus over here because this is a
personal blog. vxlabs on the other hand is strictly speaking a commercial
site, even although it&rsquo;s filled with non-commercial blog posts.)</p>
<p>One of the many funny things about being a nerd, is that it&rsquo;s almost
impossible to go to bed before a technical thing like this has been
convincingly put to bed.</p>
<p>Fortunately this late night indiscretion yielded a working self-hosted
commenting system, and, far more importantly, a <a href="/2019/04/06/isso-on-webfaction/">rather attractively styled
post, thanks to the Hugo-port, detailing the whole
installation</a>.</p>
<p>In entirely predictable fashion, the next day was not the best focus-wise.</p>
<p>P.S. 1998 - first postgrad year in the DSP lab. All-nighters all the way down&hellip;</p>
<figure>
















  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu9ee58e4bdba0ae214d7d56f78a627136_96292_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu9ee58e4bdba0ae214d7d56f78a627136_96292_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w
  
  
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/04/08/weekly-head-voices-168-postcards-from-the-edge/dsp_lab_photo4_hu9ee58e4bdba0ae214d7d56f78a627136_96292_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
  

  alt='photo taken at postcard cafe' />



<figcaption>DSP lab, somewhen between 97 - 99.</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="nim-surprise">nim-surprise.</h2>
<p>I chose Isso because it&rsquo;s Python.</p>
<p>DayJob(tm) is all about Python, so this was a great choice in terms of time
savings.</p>
<p>With all of the time I had saved, I decided that I would experiment with
re-implementing parts of Isso in <a href="https://fsharp.org/">f#</a>, my current hobby
functional language.</p>
<p>Setting aside the irony here, I learned after some time that getting f#, the
impressive looking <a href="https://fsprojects.github.io/SQLProvider/">SQLProvider</a> and
sqlite (isso&rsquo;s database) all working together on Linux was <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/fsharp/comments/8ufvzz/how_can_i_add_sqlprovider_to_my_existing_project/e1idy1o/">&ldquo;probably the
single most complicated thing that you can do with a F# project, when it comes
to
tooling&rdquo;</a>.</p>
<p>In this case, I was thankfully able to switch gears and did a brief review of
possible candidates for a functional(ish), memory efficient, fast(ish)
compilation languages that could be used to implement an Isso web-service
replacement.</p>
<p>Somehow I ended up with <a href="https://nim-lang.org/">nim</a>.</p>
<p>This has been on my radar for a while now, but there were always shinier
things to try.</p>
<p>I think what might have put me off was the similarity to Python.</p>
<p>So, with the rest of the time I had saved choosing Isso, I got up to
speed(ish) with nim by starting to implement a replacement for parts of the
isso commenting system.</p>
<p>I was quite positively surprised by the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Compilation speed: The nim compiler transforms my webservice code into C and
then compiles that in about 1.2 seconds.</li>
<li>Performance and memory size of resultant binary: This is not a fair
comparison to Python, but the multi-threaded nim service consumes a few
megabytes in total.</li>
<li>Availability of packages especially for building a web service like this:
Using the nimble package manager, I could install
<a href="https://github.com/dom96/jester">jester</a> and had my first running
web-service in a few minutes.</li>
<li>Built-in sqlite support.</li>
<li>Real macros: I used the list comprehension one in the <code>sugar</code> module.</li>
</ul>
<p>This was really just an exercise (for now), but I have a new tool for whenever
I need to write a fast and compact compiled web-service again!</p>
<p>P.S. Learning new programming languages is one of my favourite things.</p>
<p>P.P.S. Thanks to the internet and open source, and especially tools like
github, we are currently going through a sort of programming language Cambrian
explosion. See this <a href="http://fll.presidentbeef.com/">Fledgling Languages List</a>
for example. Pony!</p>
<h2 id="decompression">Decompression.</h2>
<p>On Sunday, we made the drive out to Jonkershoek in Stellenbosch.</p>
<p>Even although it&rsquo;s only 40 minutes away, I haven&rsquo;t been there in far too
long. It&rsquo;s a truly beautiful corner of the planet.</p>
<p>At the Postcard Café, after some internal deliberation, I made the decision
that the moment was special enough to interrupt LAZ
(lifestyle-alcohol-zero(tm)) with an all the more special glass of the
<a href="https://winemag.co.za/stark-conde-the-field-blend-2014/">Stark-Condé Field Blend white
wine</a>.</p>
<p>This is a hyper-local blend of Chenin Blanc, Rousanne, Verdelho and Viognier,
all four varietals which grow on the mountain-side right across from the
Café&rsquo;s veranda.</p>
<p>It really was divine.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Coffee addiction potpourri. [Weekly Head Voices #57]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/09/18/coffee-addiction-potpourri-weekly-head-voices-57/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2011 12:38:43 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/09/18/coffee-addiction-potpourri-weekly-head-voices-57/</guid><description> Yes boys and girls, I was keeping back writing that Rebecca Black post, but now it’s 4 days later and I can let ‘er rip again, like I promised. This week’s post sort of reflects my week 37: Chock-full of super-dense life nuggets. Hmmm, sounds like a brilliant new high energy meta-physical chocolate bar that would probably be immediately declared illegal by the current conservative and non-thinking (excuse the tautology) batch of spineless politicians (excuse the tautology).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Yes boys and girls, I was keeping back writing <a href="/2011/09/14/rebecca-black-is-ok-weekly-head-voices-56/" title="Rebecca Black post">that Rebecca Black post</a>, but now it’s 4 days later and I can let ‘er rip again, like I promised. This week’s post sort of reflects my week 37: Chock-full of super-dense life nuggets. Hmmm, sounds like a brilliant new high energy meta-physical chocolate bar that would probably be immediately declared illegal by the current conservative and non-thinking (excuse the tautology) batch of spineless politicians (excuse the tautology).</p>
<p>Let’s get today’s life lessons started with Mitch Hedberg, Comic Genius (note the captital C, and the capital G):</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/u6xaj2fC1jI?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Hedberg’s genius unfortunately could not save him from drug addiction and his overdose-related death in 2005.</p>
<p>On the topic of addiction, <a href="http://fpixel.wordpress.com/" title="fpixel website">fpixel</a> forwarded <a href="http://www.dutchdailynews.com/drinking-coffee-genes/">these new findings that coffee drinking is genetic</a>, both in terms of capacity and perhaps also in terms of addiction. Even my atoms are addicted to coffee, so that feels about right. What’s really interesting however, is that the documented study found that the genes involved in the metabolism of coffee (CYPIA1 and NRCAM, if I understand correctly) are also related to the onset of Parkinson’s disease. You see, coffee drinkers are less prone to Parkinson’s disease (<a href="/2011/07/02/the-monthly-weekly-head-voices-50/" title="a previous WHV including some coffee health tidbits">as well as a whole list of other diseases</a> including prostate cancer, type 2 diabetes and liver cancer). However, past studies of course show correlation and not causation, i.e. coffee drinking and low risk of disease X appear together, but that does not tell us anything about what causes what. This new study has made the first steps towards understanding the mechanism that actually links Parkinson’s disease and coffee drinking.</p>
<p>On the topic of coffee <em>and</em> addiction, <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="abbreviations page">TNR</a> and I spent the Monday morning working (like animals) on our new parallel startup (there, I said it) at the <a href="http://www.coffeecompany.nl/" title="Coffee Company website">Coffee Company</a> in Delft. Two things:</p>
<ol>
<li>The Coffee Company makes a killer cappuccino. The milk is steamed to perfection, but it’s got the perfect espresso bomb exploding through all that milky goodness at just the right moment. BAM! HELLO THERE! Highly recommended. With every purchase, you get WiFi access for one hour, so no surprises or misunderstandings.</li>
<li>It’s amazing what such a change of working environment does for one’s creativity.</li>
</ol>
<p>On the topic of startups, Dr Jorik Blaas, ex PhDer, full-time genius and friend, is now the director of research and development at <a href="http://synerscope.com/" title="synerscope website">Synerscope</a> (probably no relation with sinister, but my subconscious is just not behaving today), a high-potential startup that makes visualisation-based tools for fraud detection in big data (big money, IOW). Synerscope has brought together some of the top visualisation brains in the country. Personally, I can’t help but imagine it like this:







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/Dr_Evil.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/Dr_Evil.jpg"
        
            alt="Are you in there somewhere?"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Are you in there somewhere?</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>On Tuesday and Wednesday, we made a quick train trip (*cough* 9 hours there due to delay thank you NS, 7+ hours back) to Magdeburg for the <a href="http://www.fg-medvis.de/" title="link to German MedVis group site">bi-annual German MedVis meeting</a>. You’ll recall that I spent <a href="/2009/04/25/my-first-sabbatical/" title="my magdeburg sabbatical">my first micro-sabbatical there</a>. The city almost feels like home, and it was really great seeing many of the Magdeburg peeps again. The meeting itself was of high quality, with a number of VisWeek contributions being presented. Thomas Kroes (should I start using fictitious names and acronyms again?) presented his <a href="http://exposure-render.googlecode.com/" title="exposure render website">interactive photo-realistic volume renderer</a> too! By the way, download it, use it (it makes fantastically beautiful renderings), spread it, and do cite the soon-to-appear article.</p>
<p>On Saturday, it rained (again, or still, I forget), so I decided to flip Mother Nature the bird by BBQing four juicy rib-eye steaks outside. Take that Mother Nature! The steaks were delicious, thank you. Mother Nature is not all bad though… Check this out: The Southern Lights. FROM SPACE!








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/aurora.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/aurora.jpg"
        
            alt="Aurora Australis (thanks Bart!) FROM SPACE, taken by Ron Garan. Click on the photo to go to the original."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Aurora Australis (thanks Bart!) FROM SPACE, taken by Ron Garan. Click on the photo to go to the original.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I’m going to wind down this post with two backyard philosophy-themed bits. The first is a quote by mathematician Alfred North Whitehead from this article on “The Skill that Matters Most” (found via <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/" title="joe's blog">Joe Botha</a>, serial entrepreneur, currently changing the world with <a href="https://www.trustfabric.com/">Trust Fabric</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Civilization advances by extending the number of important operations which we can perform without thinking about them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I haven’t thought about it that way before, but it does make complete sense. The more things we humans do well in a routine fashion, the better.  Otherwise, our inconsistency is prone to lead to problems. By the way, the mentioned skill is <em>self-control</em>.</p>
<p>Finally, <a href="http://www.flipangle.org/" title="AJ's site">AJ</a> forwarded this video called Disconnect to Connect. I’ll just let you watch and think about it for a while:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GnwNGNOv19A?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>I’ll be off now. Please do have an epic week, and think of me when your level of enjoyment is at a local maximum. At these points, you might also consider jumping around randomly.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>