<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Apple on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/apple/</link><description>Recent content in Apple on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 07:42:28 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/apple/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Daily Head Voices for week 6 of 2024: Head Like a Hole</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/</guid><description>Why do I lifelog? One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&amp;rsquo;s not form their own mind.
Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2 id="why-do-i-lifelog">Why do  I lifelog?</h2>
<p>One of the reasons to publish these lifelogs is to make available a peek into the minutiae of another life (mine) that could help someone else get out of a rut, or just supply some alternative input that&rsquo;s not form their own mind.</p>
<p>Put differently, I think that when I see what other people are doing and thinking day to day, it feels like a small, external disturbance (i.e. new information) that will help to nudge me in interesting and new directions.</p>
<h3 id="journalling-vs-lifelogging">Journalling vs lifelogging</h3>
<p>In my view, <em>journalling</em> is a more developed form of <em>lifelogging</em>. While the latter is just the direct jotting down of happenings and noteworthy items, the former, at least to me, entails more thinking and more processing, i.e. there is more retro- and introspection going on. I would prefer to be <em>journalling</em>, because that has even more benefits, but I&rsquo;ll take <em>lifelogging</em> when I can&rsquo;t make the prerequisite time to think, and really craft my words.</p>
<p>On to the lifelog:</p>
<h2 id="monday-2024-02-05">Monday 2024-02-05</h2>
<ul>
<li>Friend LM told me about wikitree.org, which is a collaborative online family tree thingy. I tried to import the myheritage.com exported GEDCOM, but wikitree.org wants me to reject or accept each and everyone of the hundreds of people in my database. This is understandable, but it&rsquo;s also a  blocker, exacerbated by the fact that wikitree&rsquo;s matching algorithm is quite bad.</li>
<li>Casey Neistat&rsquo;s Apple Vision Pro review is insightful. See the bit from 7:20 onwards: <a href="https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440">https://youtu.be/UvkgmyfMPks?si=LWAoKBGCsyRZKzbe&amp;t=440</a> &ndash; &ldquo;&hellip; This is it. This is the future of computing&hellip;&rdquo;
<ul>
<li>also see my tweet embedded below</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>NVIDIA&rsquo;s GenAI competition <a href="https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/">https://www.nvidia.com/en-us/ai-data-science/generative-ai/rtx-developer-contest/</a>
<ul>
<li>Use TensorRT or TensorRT-LLM on Windows to build something cool, submit by Feb 23, win RTX 4090 and GTC conf attendance. EZ PZ!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Remember that life is <em>supposed</em> to be just a long sequence of problems that you need to solve.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">This is such a fun &quot;review&quot; of the Apple Vision Pro by Casey Neistat, but his discussion at 7:20 on the significance of the product is so spot on.<br><br>I had similar ideas about ubiquitous face-computing back in 2009: <a href="https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc">https://t.co/v5KR0cBQgc</a> <a href="https://t.co/au9RBh7as0">https://t.co/au9RBh7as0</a></p>&mdash; @cpbotha@emacs.ch (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1754421449719193753?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">February 5, 2024</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>










<figure><a href="avp-angry-gf.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b5f62d2dc15edfd3.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_b31467e1ec255b77.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_c35fee7f6f8120f9.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/daily-head-voices-2024-02-05_11/avp-angry-gf_hu_59e7dd8328751436.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>My favourite AVP meme at the moment! (thanks friend Kobie!)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="tuesday-2024-01-06">Tuesday 2024-01-06</h2>
<ul>
<li>Using inkscape to draw SVG glyphs which can be converted with <a href="https://react-svgr.com/">svgr</a> into React components, for my visualization project. This works so well!</li>
<li>Definitely a bit stressed about tomorrow&rsquo;s surgery. Also little throat niggle, and as if that was not enough, stomach issues due to droëwors I ate in the afternoon to preload a bit for tomorrow&rsquo;s required fasting.
<ul>
<li>Narrator: This would be followed by one of <em>the</em> worst nights in a long time, including fever chills, nausea, and so on.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>My brain keeps on jumping on ideas for 3D / VR / AR / AI friendly / native ideas for managing personal knowledge / notes
<ul>
<li>on the one hand, it feels like the atomic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten">Zettelkasten</a> approach could work well here</li>
<li>on the other, we have chunking techniques to break up documents, so that we can extract the nuggets we want in order to embed them
<ul>
<li>this chunking can be dynamic and adaptive, perhaps even going down to sentences and individual diagrams, or dynamically constructed chunks consisting of sub-chunks merged from different sources</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>in the end, will it help  or even just be interesting to be able to walk / move through / manipulate different projections of your (or someone else&rsquo;s) thoughts, possibly even connected in different ways?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="wednesday-2024-01-07">Wednesday 2024-01-07</h2>
<ul>
<li>Microsoft Lens makes me login every single time, and is quite temperamental
<ul>
<li>alternatives are OneDrive app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo; or Files app, then select &ldquo;scan document&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>At Summerhill day clinic for the excision of the morpheaform basal cell carcinoma (BCC) on my forehead
<ul>
<li>Fortunately, the doctor decided the excision on my back (with clean borders pronounced by pathology lab) does not need to be re-excised.</li>
<li>Excision of 2cm x 1.5cm patch from my forehead via <a href="https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/conditions-and-diseases/mohs-surgery">Mohs surgery</a> is successful after first attempt, happiness!</li>
<li>Reconstructive surgeon however now has a challenge: How to close up hole with no loose skin in sight? (I am a tightly wrapped person)
<ul>
<li>problem is solved with step-wise incision from the top middle of my forehead all the way down to my right temple, about 20cm in total.</li>
<li>I look like I could be the son of Frankenstein and Harry Potter</li>
<li>The care at Summerhill is beyond excellent. Now I just have to follow instructions, drink many pills, and my new friend-for-life Scar should heal up nicely.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="thursday-2024-01-08">Thursday 2024-01-08</h2>
<ul>
<li>Working from home because reasons</li>
<li>I have to work hard to focus, the medication seems to affect my concentration. I will grit my teeth harder.</li>
<li>In break time, tried out <a href="https://www.modular.com/blog/mojo-sdk-v0-7-now-available-for-download">Mojo v0.7.0 (released 2024-01-25)</a> through its REPL and also just a simple <code>hello.mojo</code>, which compiled into a nice 300kB binary on this MacBook! Cautiously excited for the future of this. (also&hellip;. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chris_Lattner">Chris Lattner</a>! 😍)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="friday-2024-01-09">Friday 2024-01-09</h2>
<ul>
<li>In the morning, got mu4e setup and working on the new MacBook, although I thought I was not going to need this mail client
<ul>
<li>What is your favourite mail client?</li>
<li>I use the Fastmail web client, mu4e for Emacs and macOS Mail, but none of them is perfect. mu4e comes close. ;)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Really struggled during the day with drowsiness, although I&rsquo;m sleeping extra well every night.</li>
<li>By the end, at least was able to make demo video of my in-progress visualization project.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="saturday-2024-01-10">Saturday 2024-01-10</h2>
<ul>
<li>head still feeling quite woozy</li>
<li>happy to have kids at home, and have a pretty relaxed morning</li>
<li>I would really like to write / create something today. What?</li>
<li>family tree updates
<ul>
<li>tried out ancestris, which is unusably slow on my m1pro. just getting a context menu on a person in the tree, or scrolling around, has too much lag. Tried on my Windows desktop where it&rsquo;s better but still really slow.</li>
<li>Went back to wikitree (recommended by LM) where I updated some more records (extremely laboriously).</li>
<li><a href="https://www.familysearch.org/en/">https://www.familysearch.org/en/</a> has been really useful for scans of church registers and so on, confirming more of my earlier findings.
<ul>
<li>See for example <a href="https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910">https://www.familysearch.org/photos/artifacts/149882910</a> which just came in as I was typing this. That&rsquo;s the death notice of my paternal great grandmother in 1919, very shortly after the birth of my grandfather.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I think I might have spent too much time on this today. There&rsquo;s a bit of a dopamine rush every time you solve a mini riddle. Here also I would like to have something shareable and reusable for other members of my family. For that, wikitree, although painful, seems like a good bet.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>mind wandered at 13:30ish, of course it ended up in infinite canvases and pkm
<ul>
<li>wanted to keep on letting it wander, but also wanted to use laptop to read about freeform
<ul>
<li>Apple Freeform looks like the pretty-ok-like-notes canvas solution: <a href="https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue">https://youtu.be/y8zekgRCFIA?si=a4ronKU-tBslTIue</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Instead of going to bed early, experimented with round-tripping markdown to docx and back with pandoc. See tomorrow for results.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sunday-2024-01-11">Sunday 2024-01-11</h2>
<ul>
<li>Briefly tried out the new(ish) built-in <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-za/guide/iphone/iph0e5ca7dd3/ios">iOS Journal app</a>
<ul>
<li>Super nice that it taps into your activities (photos, music, workouts, etc.) and makes recommendations for packets of media you could add to a journal, all of this entirely on-device.</li>
<li>Private, encourages folks to lock the app and so on.</li>
<li>No export capability, so your journals remain utterly locked in for now.</li>
<li>Makes it easy to configure reminders that will prompt you to write  a journal at specific moments during the week.</li>
<li>Minimalistic and well-executed app, will probably get quite a few iPhone users to start journalling, but not for me. I already have too many Apple apps in my personal system that I need to use (e.g. Apple Notes) but that don&rsquo;t interoperate particularly well with other systems.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent some more time on familysearch.org creating and attaching person records (from my family) to scans of old archive documents. Also uploaded a PDF of hand-written notes made by one of my family members from the headstones on a farm on which a number of my ancestors were buried.
<ul>
<li>Two-world problem. Bringing the physical into the digital.</li>
<li><strong>familysearch really does work better than wikitree&hellip;</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>About that Two World Problem. Had some thoughts about it in the context of my personal knowledge management, but it was slightly too much for the bullets I had allocated to it, and so it become a short post titled <a href="/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/">On the two world problem and personal knowledge management</a>.
<ul>
<li>In an ideal world, I am able to publish mini posts like that on a weekly basis.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Oh wait, I also made a short post on vxlabs with the results of last night&rsquo;s pandoc experiments, titled <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2024/02/11/pandoc-roundtrip-from-markdown-to-docx-and-back/">Pandoc roundtrip from markdown to docx and back</a>
<ul>
<li>In this case, I went direct to Hugo markdown instead of starting in Emacs Orgmode first, in order to further reduce activation energy. This makes sense for posts I want to get published where I don&rsquo;t necessarily need the benefit of having the content integrated with my main notes database.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>On the two world problem and personal knowledge management</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 12:52:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/</guid><description> Figure 1: Photo by Igor Omilaev on Unsplash
In this recent Mojo community blog post, I came across the term &amp;ldquo;two-world problem&amp;rdquo;, describing the disconnect in bio-informatics between the high-performance, low-level (often C++) and the more expressive, high-level (often Python) software layers.
As someone who has experienced this first-hand in scientific visualization and image processing, also between C++ and Python (quite acutely with VTK and ITK, less so but still relevant with SciPy), I really like this term.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 









<figure><a href="igor-omilaev-p059oXBEWe4-unsplash.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/igor-omilaev-p059oXBEWe4-unsplash_hu_4816191a2dae1d67.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/igor-omilaev-p059oXBEWe4-unsplash_hu_207a5fc72d4fd5bf.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/igor-omilaev-p059oXBEWe4-unsplash_hu_aa120e91e6d1f8dd.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/igor-omilaev-p059oXBEWe4-unsplash_hu_fc88fb9c84cc0c4d.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2024/02/11/two-world-problem-and-pkm/igor-omilaev-p059oXBEWe4-unsplash_hu_207a5fc72d4fd5bf.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Photo by Igor Omilaev on Unsplash"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@omilaev">Igor Omilaev</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-pair-of-virtual-glasses-on-a-pink-and-yellow-background-p059oXBEWe4">Unsplash</a></p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In this recent <a href="https://www.modular.com/blog/outperforming-rust-benchmarks-with-mojo">Mojo community blog post</a>, I came across the term &ldquo;two-world problem&rdquo;, describing the disconnect in bio-informatics between the high-performance, low-level (often C++) and the more expressive, high-level (often Python) software layers.</p>
<p>As someone who has experienced this first-hand in scientific visualization and image processing, also between C++ and Python (quite acutely with VTK and ITK, less so but still relevant with SciPy), I really like this term.</p>
<p>I could not find any canonical sources for its use in this context. The closest was a blog post or two talking about the digital vs the physical world.</p>
<p>However, I think this is also what I&rsquo;m going to use to describe the continuous tension I experience between the Apple and non-Apple personal data ecosystems in my life. For various good reasons, I use some Apple tools like Apple Notes, which have limited or no interoperability with the rest of my slightly more open data environment. See <a href="/2023/04/11/note-taking-strategy-2023/">my 2023 note-taking mega-post</a> if you&rsquo;re interested in the details.</p>
<p>In addition to the Apple boundary, there are additional boundaries between for example the Google cloud (which my family uses) and the plain files on my filesystems.</p>
<p>For how long will there still be room for &ldquo;files on someone&rsquo;s disc&rdquo;, currently my preference?</p>
<p>In an ideal world, my data environment is fully unified. Everything I ingest or process lives in the same happy data universe and can be re-used and re-combined by me and my AIs. Interop with other folks must also be transparent and with low friction.</p>
<p>This vision is quite far from my current reality.</p>
<p>I think this problem is going to become a lot more prominent with new computing modalities like the Apple Vision Pro. Folks using the AVP will have their whole data universe inside the Apple garden in order to have access to their stuff in the AVP virtualities.</p>
<p>What is the Meta (Quest) tribe going to do? Where is their data going to live?</p>
<p>Furthermore, how are our personal AI assistants going to get unified access to our personal data in order to become more useful?</p>
<p>At this point, it looks like it&rsquo;s going to become an extremely interesting and quite treacherous question of pick-your-cloud. The coice of personal cloud, AI and XR systems becomes inextricably intertwined, with lock-in almost guaranteed. The already existing problem of silos will probably become only more challenging.</p>
<p>It feels like some (many?) folks are already there; they are happy to have selected one and one only of Apple, or Google, or Microsoft for everything that they do. Staying exclusive to that single ecosystem has many benefits, but one clearly also risks creating a reality where no other choice will be possible.</p>
<p>What does your data landscape look like at this moment? Where do you think we&rsquo;re going to end up?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Saturday 2023-12-23</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/25/daily-head-voices-on-saturday-2023-12-23/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 18:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/25/daily-head-voices-on-saturday-2023-12-23/</guid><description> First thing, could not resist taking another quick peek at ox-pandoc and figured out that it honours default-directory, so instead of trying to find the last *pandoc &amp;lt;N&amp;gt;* buffer it created, I can just write to a file in a temporary directory difficult 12km run in St Francis. Wind, heat and that durn hip niggle. Year goal is starting to slip out of reach&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;ll deal. Made use of perplexity.ai offer of two months free: https://www.threads.net/@perplexity.ai/post/C1KquV6gyWd Spent a substantial amount of time struggling with AppleScript, Notes and Emacs, and I&amp;rsquo;m not sure yet how I feel about all of this. https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-to-apple-notes is out there for other people to learn about all the ways in which this can fail.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>First thing, could not resist taking another quick peek at ox-pandoc and figured out  that it honours <code>default-directory</code>, so instead of trying to find the last <code>*pandoc &lt;N&gt;*</code> buffer it created, I can just write to a file in a temporary directory</li>
<li>difficult 12km run in St Francis. Wind, heat and that durn hip niggle. Year goal is starting to slip out of reach&hellip; I&rsquo;ll deal.</li>
<li>Made use of perplexity.ai offer of two months free: <a href="https://www.threads.net/@perplexity.ai/post/C1KquV6gyWd">https://www.threads.net/@perplexity.ai/post/C1KquV6gyWd</a></li>
<li>Spent a substantial amount of time struggling with AppleScript, Notes and Emacs, and I&rsquo;m not sure yet how I feel about all of this. <a href="https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-to-apple-notes">https://github.com/cpbotha/org-roam-to-apple-notes</a> is out there for other people to learn about all the ways in which this can fail.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Friday 2023-12-22</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/25/daily-head-voices-on-friday-2023-12-22/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 18:46:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/25/daily-head-voices-on-friday-2023-12-22/</guid><description> Throughout the day, probably spent far too much time fighting with AppleScript to figure out attachments (learned stuff, also that Apple Notes AppleScript is quite broken), and then also some time on ox-pandoc export, as it can embed image attachments as base64, which is what should in theory work for Apple notes (haha&amp;hellip;) I used a mix of perplexity (free), bing chat in gpt4 mode and even a bit of you.com to help me, but AppleScript and specifically its application in notes is pretty obscure, with ox-pandoc not very far behind. Did get https://github.com/zerolfx/copilot.el working in Emacs &amp;ndash; this has turned out really useful for my most recent emacs-lisp adventures! My config is below in case you find it useful. (use-package copilot :ensure t :vc (:fetcher &amp;#34;https://github.com/zerolfx/copilot.el.git&amp;#34;) :config ;; only copilot in insert mode ;; https://www.irfanhabib.com/2022-04-26-setting-up-github-copilot-in-emacs/ (customize-set-variable &amp;#39;copilot-enable-predicates &amp;#39;(evil-insert-state-p)) ;; binds inspired by https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/editor/github-copilot (define-key copilot-completion-map (kbd &amp;#34;&amp;lt;tab&amp;gt;&amp;#34;) &amp;#39;copilot-accept-completion) (define-key copilot-completion-map (kbd &amp;#34;TAB&amp;#34;) &amp;#39;copilot-accept-completion) (define-key copilot-completion-map (kbd &amp;#34;M-]&amp;#34;) &amp;#39;copilot-next-completion) ;; command-right on macOS, windows-right on Linux / Windows (define-key copilot-completion-map (kbd &amp;#34;s-&amp;lt;right&amp;gt;&amp;#34;) &amp;#39;copilot-accept-completion-by-word))</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Throughout the day, probably spent far too much time fighting with AppleScript to figure out attachments (learned stuff, also that Apple Notes AppleScript is quite broken), and then also some time on ox-pandoc export, as it can embed image attachments as base64, which is what should in theory work for Apple notes (haha&hellip;)</li>
<li>I used a mix of perplexity (free), bing chat in gpt4 mode and even a bit of you.com to help me, but AppleScript and specifically its application in notes is pretty obscure, with ox-pandoc not very far behind.</li>
<li>Did get <a href="https://github.com/zerolfx/copilot.el">https://github.com/zerolfx/copilot.el</a> working in Emacs &ndash; this has turned out really useful for my most recent emacs-lisp adventures! My config is below in case you find it useful.</li>
</ul>
<!--listend-->
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-emacs-lisp" data-lang="emacs-lisp"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">use-package</span> <span style="color:#953800">copilot</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#6639ba">:ensure</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">t</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#6639ba">:vc</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">:fetcher</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;https://github.com/zerolfx/copilot.el.git&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#6639ba">:config</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#57606a">;; only copilot in insert mode</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#57606a">;; https://www.irfanhabib.com/2022-04-26-setting-up-github-copilot-in-emacs/</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">customize-set-variable</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;copilot-enable-predicates</span> <span style="color:#0550ae">&#39;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">evil-insert-state-p</span><span style="color:#1f2328">))</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#57606a">;; binds inspired by https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/editor/github-copilot</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">define-key</span> <span style="color:#953800">copilot-completion-map</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">kbd</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;&lt;tab&gt;&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;copilot-accept-completion</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">define-key</span> <span style="color:#953800">copilot-completion-map</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">kbd</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;TAB&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;copilot-accept-completion</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">define-key</span> <span style="color:#953800">copilot-completion-map</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">kbd</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;M-]&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;copilot-next-completion</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#57606a">;; command-right on macOS, windows-right on Linux / Windows</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#6639ba">define-key</span> <span style="color:#953800">copilot-completion-map</span> <span style="color:#1f2328">(</span><span style="color:#953800">kbd</span> <span style="color:#0a3069">&#34;s-&lt;right&gt;&#34;</span><span style="color:#1f2328">)</span> <span style="color:#032f62">&#39;copilot-accept-completion-by-word</span><span style="color:#1f2328">))</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div> ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Daily Head Voices on Wednesday 2023-12-20</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/22/daily-head-voices-on-wednesday-2023-12-20/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2023 12:13:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2023/12/22/daily-head-voices-on-wednesday-2023-12-20/</guid><description> Morning run on the gravel road along the Serpentine river in Wilderness, probably one of my favourite routes ever. On a new wifi network with Apple TV, but forgot remote at home. Moved TV and Apple TV closer to AP to plug in via ethernet, which allowed the iPhone remote to connect, BUT Apple decided to be infuriating again: If your Apple TV has an Ethernet port, make sure your Apple TV isn&amp;rsquo;t connected to an Ethernet cable. If you&amp;rsquo;re using an Ethernet cable, you won&amp;rsquo;t see the option to connect to Wi-Fi. see https://support.apple.com/en-za/102346 &amp;ndash; this is of course a great big catch 22 for us at the moment. They do plenty of things right, but man, they make some really stupid mistakes. On a related note, it seems that before iOS 17, the Remote app on the iPhone was able to control the Apple TV even when they weren&amp;rsquo;t on the same WiFi network, see https://www.reddit.com/r/appletv/comments/16mo99d/apple_tv_remote_app_requires_a_wifi_connection_as/ On the other hand: Based on the following two recent publications, it really looks like Apple is cooking up something really interesting with large language models (LLMs): Apple announces ProTIP: Progressive Tool Retrieval Improves Planning &amp;ndash; so they are working on much improved ways of hooking up LLMs to tools, perhaps even on their devices? via https://twitter.com/_akhaliq/status/1736982938942677421 New Arxiv paper by Apple titled &amp;ldquo;LLM in a flash: Efficient Large Language Model Inference with Limited Memory&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; from the abstract: &amp;ldquo;These methods collectively enable running models up to twice the size of the available DRAM, with a 4-5x and 20-25x increase in inference speed compared to naive loading approaches in CPU and GPU, respectively. Our integration of sparsity awareness, context-adaptive loading, and a hardware-oriented design paves the way for effective inference of LLMs on devices with limited memory.&amp;rdquo; via https://www.threads.net/@sung.kim.mw/post/C1Dwx7Iypg4/ Spent some time digging into AppleScript (again) and how I could make a better orgmode to apple notes workflow Previous attempt is here: https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/#bonus-round-convert-orgmode-buffer-to-apple-note-using-applescript The new flow should merge more cleverly with an existing folder in Notes, instead of re-importing the whole database each time</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <ul>
<li>Morning run on the gravel road along the Serpentine river in Wilderness, probably one of my favourite routes ever.</li>
<li>On a new wifi network with Apple TV, but forgot remote at home. Moved TV and Apple TV closer to AP to plug in via ethernet, which allowed the iPhone remote to connect, BUT Apple decided to be infuriating again: <em>If your Apple TV has an Ethernet port, make sure your Apple TV isn&rsquo;t connected to an Ethernet cable. If you&rsquo;re using an Ethernet cable, you won&rsquo;t see the option to connect to Wi-Fi.</em> see <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-za/102346">https://support.apple.com/en-za/102346</a> &ndash; this is of course a great big catch 22 for us at the moment.
<ul>
<li>They do plenty of things right, but man, they make some really stupid mistakes.</li>
<li>On a related note, it seems that before iOS 17, the Remote app on the iPhone was able to control the Apple TV even when they weren&rsquo;t on the same WiFi network, see <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/appletv/comments/16mo99d/apple_tv_remote_app_requires_a_wifi_connection_as/">https://www.reddit.com/r/appletv/comments/16mo99d/apple_tv_remote_app_requires_a_wifi_connection_as/</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>On the other hand: Based on the following two recent publications, it really looks like Apple is cooking up something really interesting with large language models (LLMs):
<ul>
<li>Apple announces ProTIP: Progressive Tool Retrieval Improves Planning &ndash; so they are working on much improved ways of hooking up LLMs to tools, perhaps even on their devices? via <a href="https://twitter.com/_akhaliq/status/1736982938942677421">https://twitter.com/_akhaliq/status/1736982938942677421</a></li>
<li>New Arxiv paper by Apple titled &ldquo;LLM in a flash: Efficient Large Language Model Inference with Limited Memory&rdquo; &ndash; from the abstract: &ldquo;These methods collectively enable running models up to twice the size of the available DRAM, with a 4-5x and 20-25x increase in inference speed compared to naive loading approaches in CPU and GPU, respectively. Our integration of sparsity awareness, context-adaptive loading, and a hardware-oriented design paves the way for effective inference of LLMs on devices with limited memory.&rdquo; via <a href="https://www.threads.net/@sung.kim.mw/post/C1Dwx7Iypg4/">https://www.threads.net/@sung.kim.mw/post/C1Dwx7Iypg4/</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Spent some time digging into AppleScript (again) and how I could make a better orgmode to apple notes workflow
<ul>
<li>Previous attempt is here: <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/#bonus-round-convert-orgmode-buffer-to-apple-note-using-applescript">https://vxlabs.com/2018/10/29/importing-orgmode-notes-into-apple-notes/#bonus-round-convert-orgmode-buffer-to-apple-note-using-applescript</a></li>
<li>The new flow should merge more cleverly with an existing folder in Notes, instead of re-importing the whole database each time</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #222: Scotty, we need more power!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 14:07:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/</guid><description>Welcome back everyone!
It&amp;rsquo;s now early(ish) Friday morning of the weekend after, but I would like to get the 222d edition of the WHV out, namely the one covering the two weeks from Monday, April 19 to Sunday, May 2, 2021.
My excuse for skipping a week is that the second week was spent on vacation. Exhibit A is shown below:
Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome back everyone!</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s now early(ish) Friday morning of the weekend after, but I would like to
get the 222d edition of the WHV out, namely the one covering the two weeks from
Monday, April 19 to Sunday, May 2, 2021.</p>
<p>My excuse for skipping a week is that the second week was spent on
vacation. Exhibit A is shown below:</p>










<figure><a href="st_francis_beach_run_202104.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_bbb76e39724cc3f7.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_bfb1ba72e5ab2b58.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_ec9238ff28cf4ddf.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_681f14d95b121950.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_beach_run_202104_hu_bfb1ba72e5ab2b58.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from an unexpected and sublime run on the St Francis beach.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The rest of this post has (imagine the following in Bill Hader&rsquo;s Stefon voice):</p>
<ul>
<li>migraines and science</li>
<li>scifi ipads</li>
<li>VR</li>
<li>a life tip</li>
</ul>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="brain-glitch">Brain glitch</h2>
<p>I lost almost half a work day to a <a href="https://www.allaboutvision.com/conditions/ocular-migraine.htm">visual migraine</a>.</p>
<p>Looking at my notes, it seems that these only started during the past few
years, although it could be that I just didn&rsquo;t record the previous ones.</p>
<p>It starts out with bright spots in the middle of your field of vision, which
slowly grow until they form jiggly circles. This is not ideal, but at least you
can now look through their centres. Haha.</p>
<p>It looks eerily identical to the illustration on the linked website.</p>
<p>After half an hour to about an hour, sometimes a headache will hit, and
sometimes not. This time it was unusually intense, and I had no choice but to
detach from work for a while.</p>
<p>Looking back at my notes now, I really appreciate the time-stamped entries as
the migraine developed all the way to its end.</p>
<p>Lesson reaffirmed: Take good notes, no matter what.</p>
<h3 id="fascinating-scientific-review-of-migraine-and-metabolism">Fascinating scientific review of migraine and metabolism</h3>
<p>After a related chat with a friend who reported that in his case blood sugar
played a role (he can&rsquo;t skip breakfast, and can&rsquo;t eat too sweet), my
permanently foraging internet tentacles entirely coincidentally dredged up this
publication in Nature Reviews Neurology titled &ldquo;The metabolic face of
migraine - from pathophysiology to treatment&rdquo; (<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31586135/">pubmed</a>, <a href="https://orbi.uliege.be/bitstream/2268/247255/1/Gross%20et%20al%20Metabolic%20face%20of%20migraine-Nat%20Rev%20Neurol%202019.pdf">PDF fulltext</a>).</p>
<p>The article is pretty dense, but here are some interesting observations:</p>
<p>The first is from box 1: In some humans, when brain energy demands outstrip
metabolic reserves, rendering them vulnerable to disruption of cortical
homeostatis (energy balance), there is a whole cascade of events that,
according to the article&rsquo;s authors, might be started by the pannexin channels
in neurons. (These channels act as sensors of cortical homeostasis.)</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s quite straight-forward then that (haha):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The final result of this cascade is trigeminovascular activation and calcitonin
gene-related peptide release in the extradural space, which leads to headache.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Following from there, they postulate two alternate pathways that cause
respectively migraine with and without aura (visual effects).</p>
<p>In other words, when your brain requires more energy than you have available,
and you are one of the many genetic variants who suffer from this mechanism,
you could be in for some migraine when your body reacts to the imbalance.</p>
<p>On top of that, the authors present one more good reason <a href="/2021/04/20/weekly-head-voices-221-anti-breakfast-club/#skip-you-some-breakfast-for-great-good">to become fat-adapted</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>These increases in lipolysis and ketogenesis can also be interpreted as
counter-​regulatory responses to a cerebral energy deficit. Given that ketone
bodies are an efficient alternative fuel for the brain when glucose
availability is low, their elevation would be expected to restore brain energy
homeostasis. However, the Western carbohydrate-​laden diet means that in most
people in Western countries the brain is not keto-​adapted so does not have the
enzymatic composition and transporters to make use of ketone bodies produced
during an energy crisis.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Box 2 in the article provides the following quite intriguing &ldquo;Suggested
approach to improving mitochondrial function and energy metabolism in
migraine&rdquo; (emphasis mine, so that you can skim over if you want):</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>Individualize supplementation of micronutrients. To ensure that all
micronutrients needed for mitochondrial function are available, laboratory
tests can be used to individualize supplementation with minerals,
hydrophobic and lipophilic vitamins and trace mineralsthat are deficient.</li>
<li>Reduce oxidative stress and increase antioxidants. Measurement of oxidative
and/or nitrosative stress levels and antioxidant status in individuals could
detect a potential mismatch between oxidative stress levels and antioxidant
capacity and enable therapeutic adjustments to be made, although studies are
needed to prove that such an approach improves migraine
management. Strategies to reduce oxidative stress could include <strong><strong>elimination
or reduction of processed food, food with a high glycaemic index and</strong></strong>
<strong><strong>alcohol, use of green or blue light filtering glasses, interruption of
hormone-based contraception, lifestyle changes</strong></strong> and addition of
antioxidants,such as polyphenols, coenzyme Q10, α-lipoic acid or
β-hydroxybutyrate mineral salts, to the diet.</li>
<li><strong><strong>Stabilize blood glucose levels</strong></strong>. An oral glucose tolerance testshould be
undertaken in patients with migraine and clinical features that suggest
glucose intolerance or a family history of glucose intolerance. Patients
with reactive hyperinsulinaemia and reactive hypoglycaemia are likely to
benefit from stabilization of blood glucose levels, which can often be
achieved with dietary adjustments.</li>
<li>Provide an <strong><strong>alternative energy substrate for the brain</strong></strong>. For patients with
compromised energy metabolism, an alternative source of fuel for the brain,
in addition to glucose and lactate, might be beneficial. This source can be
generated with a ketogenic diet and/or use of exogenous ketogenic
substances, such asmedium-chain triglycerides or exogenous ketone body
salts. Further placebo-controlled trials are needed to validate ketogenic
therapies in migraine.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="4-20-ipad-pro-supercomputers-straight-outta-scifi">4/20 iPad Pro supercomputers straight outta SciFi</h2>
<p>On 4/20 I tuned into a liveblog (I think it was <a href="https://live.arstechnica.com/apples-april-20-2021-spring-loaded-event/">the one by Ars Technica</a>) of
Apple&rsquo;s release event.</p>
<p>Apple is currently evolving the computing landscape quite substantially, so I
find it immensely interesting to see what they are bringing next.</p>
<p>They did a whole bunch this time, but what struck me as the most significant,
is that they introduced two new iPad Pro tablets with M1 chips.</p>
<p>You know, that same M1 chip powering <a href="/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/">the super fast and energy-efficient laptop
on which I&rsquo;m typing up this post</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to sticking a desktop-class processor (err, desktop-class
performance, but mobile-level battery efficiency) back into a mobile device
that you can also buy with 2 terabytes of built-in storage (I find this a bit
surreal), the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2021/4/21/22395449/apple-ipad-pro-2021-liquid-retina-xdr-mini-led-explainer">new Liquid Retina XDR display on the top-end iPad Pro</a> has 10000
of a new kind of micro-led just for the back-lighting and thus is able to offer
1000 nits of full-screen brightness and adaptively up to 1600 nits on portions
of the screen, all of that with a contrast ratio of 1 to&hellip;. ONE MILLION.</p>
<p>As I was reading this, and later listening as the excitement led (&hellip;) me to
tune in to the video stream, one of my inner voices marvelled at the sheer
technological innovation on display (sorry can&rsquo;t stop) here.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m curious to see how this new class of supercomputer-level tablet device is
going to change how we humans interact with the digital world.</p>
<h2 id="oculus-quest-2">Oculus Quest 2</h2>
<p>On that topic&hellip;</p>
<p>On the weekend that we returned from vacation, we welcomed an <a href="https://www.theverge.com/21437674/oculus-quest-2-review-features-photos">Oculus Quest 2 VR
headset</a> into the family.</p>
<p>In the early 2000s, <a href="https://graphics.tudelft.nl/">the TU Delft Graphics research lab</a> that I was part of had
an AR / VR research line, so I got some exposure to state-of-the-art equipment
then.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 15 years, and the self-contained Oculus Quest 2 at $299 is
mind-blowingly good.</p>
<p>Specifically the head tracking is phenomenal.</p>
<p>Graphics elements in VR are rock-solid in virtual space as you move your head
(and yourself) around. The resolution is high enough that you could even work
on a document if you would like. With the most recent firmware update, Quest 2
now does 120 Hz.</p>
<p>In short, when you put on the headset, immersion is total.</p>
<p>No more outside world.</p>
<p>You can double tap on the side of the helmet to switch on reality (viewing your
surroundings through the 4 cameras mounted on the outside), and double tap to
switch reality off and go back into VR.</p>
<p>Facebook (they own Oculus) has some interesting work-focused ideas with this:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/5_bVkbG1ZCo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<p>When I saw that video for the first time, before having tried out the Quest 2,
I thought &ldquo;haha look at fb faking VR&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I was wrong.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s pretty much spot-on.</p>
<p>(We&rsquo;re not playing office-office with the kids though, beat saber is much more
fun in 3D!)</p>
<h2 id="flip-it">Flip it</h2>
<p>During a recent chat with a busy friend, seeing if we could have coffee
somewhere, I reminded us both (you have to imagine this in Afrikaans, but
failing that in English with a thick Afrikaans accent):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Remember that the moments of relaxation and humanity are the anchors. All of
the rest should flow around that.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is so easy to forget.</p>
<p>We (and I also mean I) postpone the chat, or the run, or time with the family,
because of work.</p>
<p>It should be the other way round!</p>










<figure><a href="st_francis_sunset_watch_202104.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_b36de7acfc1e6653.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_4ba8d8a922c30068.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_d77a49f3e110f83.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_876d61fb3f2dd092.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/05/08/weekly-head-voices-222-scotty-we-need-more-power/st_francis_sunset_watch_202104_hu_4ba8d8a922c30068.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Awesome ritual in St Francis where people make a whole celebration of the sunset. We were there thanks to GOU#1&rsquo;s tip."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 2: Awesome ritual in St Francis where people make a whole celebration of the sunset. We were there thanks to GOU#1&rsquo;s tip.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>New Emacs-capable hardware: M1 MacBook Air</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 21:49:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/</guid><description>You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&amp;rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I usually write a little something about it.
These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&amp;rsquo;ve back-tagged most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient &amp;ldquo;new computer&amp;rdquo; tag list!
Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of the new Apple M1 chip and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>You know the drill here at the WHV: If there&rsquo;s a new computer in the family, I
usually write a little something about it.</p>
<p>These mentions and posts go back to at least 2002, and now I&rsquo;ve back-tagged
most of them so that you can see them all in this convenient <a href="/tags/new-computer/">&ldquo;new computer&rdquo; tag
list</a>!</p>
<h2 id="fast-cheap-and-energy-efficient-choose-three">Fast, cheap and energy efficient: Choose three</h2>
<p>This time, I, or rather my employer, had difficulty resisting the siren song of
the new <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple%5FM1">Apple M1 chip</a> and especially of the entry-level M1 MacBook Air: Great
performance and power efficiency in a truly cool and quiet package.</p>










<figure><a href="m1-macbook-air-about.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_de2f1e5efc3aadf2.png 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_6c2a206fdadbba4.png 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_2a184c7768aa3ee0.png 1200w,
            
                
                
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/03/21/new-emacs-capable-hardware-m1-macbook-air/m1-macbook-air-about_hu_6c2a206fdadbba4.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>I&rsquo;m still <em>quite</em> happy with the <a href="/2019/04/27/new-laptop-2019/">ThinkPad X1 Extreme Gen1</a> as my main
workstation, but although classed as thin-and-light it <em>is</em> still a
workstation.</p>
<p>Specifically, due to the fact that it takes at least a minute or two to resume
from sleep, and the fact that its performance on battery is substantially
slower than on AC, it&rsquo;s not the sort of machine that you can flip open to work
on when inspiration strikes.</p>
<p>As if that was not enough, it&rsquo;s a really effective lap warmer, and so gets
uncomfortable <em>quite</em> quickly.</p>
<p>In sharp contrast, the performance of this MacBook Air is the same, namely
&ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;, whether it&rsquo;s on AC or on battery, the laptop resumes from
standby faster that I&rsquo;m able to open the lid, and it hardly ever gets warm.</p>
<p>In short, I can bust this out of my bag and be typing on my lap in under 3
seconds, and this is something that has already started paying off in terms of
my writing.</p>
<h2 id="this-might-be-the-best-emacs-host-i-ve-ever-used">This might be the best Emacs-host I&rsquo;ve ever used</h2>
<p>This very post is currently being typed on <code>GNU Emacs 27.1.91 (build 1, arm-apple-darwin20.3.0, Carbon Version 164 AppKit 2022.3) of 2021-03-15</code> on the
device in question.</p>
<p>Have I mentioned &ldquo;super snappy&rdquo;?</p>
<p>By the way, if you build Emacs like this on the M1:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew tap railwaycat/emacsmacport
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew install --formula emacs-mac --HEAD
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; you should be good to go.</p>
<h3 id="update-on-2021-04-15">Update on 2021-04-15</h3>
<p>A few days ago, I started seeing the following error during homebrew Emacs update:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-text" data-lang="text"><span style="display:flex;"><span>./temacs --batch  -l loadup --temacs=pbootstrap
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>make[1]: *** [bootstrap-emacs.pdmp] Killed: 9
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>make: *** [src] Error 2
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This looks similar to <a href="https://github.com/d12frosted/homebrew-emacs-plus/issues/292">this github issue on emacs-plus</a>, which was fixed on emacs
master.</p>
<p>It was easiest for me to switch to emacs-plus, which went like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#f7f7f7;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew uninstall emacs-mac
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew tap d12frosted/emacs-plus
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>brew install emacs-plus@28 --with-no-titlebar
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="quo-vadis-one-device-to-rule-them-all">Quo vadis, one device to rule them all?</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s a pity that the ThinkPad, although powerful enough to satisfy <a href="/2020/05/20/weekly-head-voices-195-pragmatic/#the-story-behind-this-story-one-context-to-rule-them-all">my single
computing device / single context requirement</a>, and with <a href="/2020/09/16/weekly-head-voices-204-what-is-your-purpose/#wsl2-and-nativecomp-emacs-workflow-update">WSL2 becoming
increasingly useful</a> and hence addressing the dual-boot issue, does not satisfy
the <em>instantly available</em> requirement.</p>
<p>Fortunately the two devices cater for complementary contexts.</p>
<p>The Air is for instant-on writing, communication, admin and maybe a tiny bit of
development, whilst the ThinkPad is for all of the heavy lifting, but who knows
how these lines are going to be blurred in the coming months?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #205: Real-time sometimes, asynchronous most of the time</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 19:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/</guid><description>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back a the week from Monday September 14 to Sunday September 20 of the year 2020.
Figure 1: Scene from a work get-together. It&amp;rsquo;s really nice when you can get into these mountains any day of the week!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>This edition of the Weekly Head Voices looks back a the week from Monday
September 14 to Sunday September 20 of the year 2020.</p>










<figure><a href="jonkershoek_pano_20200918.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/jonkershoek_pano_20200918_hu_83b4929e56d2f13b.jpg 480w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/jonkershoek_pano_20200918_hu_e6f63de4834dd81a.jpg 800w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/jonkershoek_pano_20200918_hu_944507bf69fb2650.jpg 1200w,
            
                
                https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/jonkershoek_pano_20200918_hu_9b44619bafefcd90.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/jonkershoek_pano_20200918_hu_e6f63de4834dd81a.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Scene from a work get-together. It&rsquo;s really nice when you can get into these mountains any day of the week!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: Scene from a work get-together. It&rsquo;s really nice when you can get into these mountains any day of the week!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For the first time in months, this post is exactly on time. Whatever else
happens in the rest of the post, timeousness is in the pocket!</p>
<h2 id="the-uninformed-vs-privacy-preserving-covid-tracking">The uninformed vs privacy-preserving COVID tracking</h2>
<p>(I would like to warn you that in this section, I get saltier than I&rsquo;ve been in
years.</p>
<p>People who were reading this blog more than 10 years ago will have noticed that
I used to be salty a whole lot more often back then.</p>
<p>Hopefully, this specific episode doesn&rsquo;t move this decade&rsquo;s dial by too much.)</p>
<p>During <a href="https://citizen.co.za/news/covid-19/2359102/full-speech-sa-will-move-to-lockdown-level-1-as-midnight-20-september/">his address of September 16</a>, president Ramaphosa announced the further
lifting of the national lockdown to level 1.</p>
<p>Because I had been following the <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/apple-google-bluetooth-contact-tracing-covid-19/">surprising collaboration between Apple and
Google on the anonymous disease exposure tracing</a> functionality in Android and
iOS, my ears perked up when he requested that South Africans with smart phones
install the COVID Alert mobile app:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I want to make a call this evening to everyone who has a smartphone in South
Africa to download the COVID Alert mobile app from the Apple App Store or
Google Play Store.</p>
<p>The app has been zero-rated by mobile networks, so you can download it without
any data costs.</p>
<p>Using Bluetooth technology, the app will alert any user if they have been in
close contact with any other user who has tested positive for coronavirus in
the past 14 days.</p>
<p>The app is completely anonymous, it does not gather any personal information,
nor does it track anybody’s location.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I immediately checked it out on my iPhone, and was gratified to see that the
app was well put-together, and made use of the privacy-respecting official
infrastructure designed by Apple and Google.</p>
<p>(<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/jun/18/uk-poised-to-abandon-coronavirus-app-in-favour-of-apple-and-google-models">Some countries</a> wasted millions of euros trying to build this by themselves,
and then later had to switch gears, instead of just using Google and Apple&rsquo;s
functionality from the get-go.)</p>
<p>Because effective contact-tracing requires as many people as possible to
install the app, I let a number of private chat groups know, and I even got
back on twitter quite briefly to tweet:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">SA Folks! Please install the COVID Alert South Africa app on your iPhone or Andoid. This 100% anonymous system, developed using the official Apple and Google APIs, helps enormously with contact tracing. iPhone: <a href="https://t.co/EE0J0Cd9ee">https://t.co/EE0J0Cd9ee</a> Android: <a href="https://t.co/HXkMl88oi0">https://t.co/HXkMl88oi0</a></p>&mdash; Charl Botha 😷 #Masks4All (@cvoxel) <a href="https://twitter.com/cvoxel/status/1306494451460833281?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">September 17, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>Imagine my surprise when I noticed a bit later that there was a bit of a furore
online with people being openly suspicious of the app, up to offering all kinds
of conspiracy theories as to how exactly the government was going to use this
to monitor and/or control people.</p>
<p>Interestingly, there appeared to be a pretty strong inverse correlation between
technical know-how and level of suspicion.</p>
<p>(Ironically, a large subset of the highly suspicious camp will experience difficulty
understanding the above sentence. Probably also this sentence. Not sorry.)</p>
<p>It is exasperating to me that when the SA government takes on a project like
this (the tracking app), does it by the book and does a really good job of it,
people respond this badly.</p>
<p>While it is unfortunately true that the government has been doing a terrible
job in terms of engendering confidence in its abilities and especially in its
honesty, even going so far as to disappear millions of ZAR intended for
personal protective equipment (!!), using that as an excuse to actively spread
misinformation, and thereby prevent contact tracing from getting off the
ground, is pretty hard to defend.</p>
<p>(More than one of my mom&rsquo;s acquaintances (a term that is pushing the
definition) have warned her that if she were to install the app, she was to
remove them from all other contact media. I told her that this is a great way
to cull her contacts list selectively, rendering a much more erudite address
book.)</p>
<p>Sorry folks, but when real scientific and technological progress is held back
by this level of ignorance, I can get really salty.</p>
<p>What would have been much better, would have been for said people to get the
frick informed. It can&rsquo;t be that hard to find someone with the relevant
know-how in any social circle.</p>
<p>Fortunately, some local folks have been doing their best making good information
accessible:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@gvrooyen%5F22259/the-masquerade-ball-how-covid-19-bluetooth-tracking-works-b3f5960b8ac8">The Masquerade Ball – How COVID-19 Bluetooth tracking works</a> by Prof G-J van
Rooyen is a great explanation of the finer details in an easy-to-follow
format.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.explain.co.za/2020/09/15/explainer-should-i-download-the-new-contact-tracing-app/">EXPLAINER: Should I download the new contact tracing app?</a> by Aarti Bhana at
explain.co.za makes clear that you can and should install this app, but also
discusses the fact that the government should have been doing much better in
terms of dissemination.</li>
</ul>
<p>One could blame this on lacking education, and on the government not doing
their best either, but a large part of the responsibility comes down to normal
people, with no excuse not to have educated themselves, simply letting their
primitive instincts absolve them of any critical thinking.</p>
<p>I welcome your thoughts in the comments.</p>
<h2 id="the-future-of-work-episode-23">The future of work, episode 23</h2>
<p>Just like thousands of other companies, we went from &ldquo;yeah, we&rsquo;ve read about
remote working and we should look into it more when we can make the time&rdquo; to
&ldquo;100% fully remote what is this office-thing you speak of?&rdquo; from one day to the
next when our hard lock-down started back in March.</p>
<p>A few months in, and it seems that most of the whole 70-person company would
not be surprised if we remain fully remote.</p>
<p>I think that many of us, especially the engineers, really appreciate this new
mode of operation where we have a substantially larger part of the day to work,
and where it has become theoretically (ahem) easier to cordon off blocks of
focus time.</p>
<p>Some of us are thinking about ways to further improve and streamline our remote
working process.</p>
<p>During one of my research sessions (or was it me aimlessly browsing because I
had become distracted during a particularly long afternoon&hellip;), I ran into the
following post by <a href="https://basecamp.com/">the BaseCamp company</a>, previously known as <a href="https://37signals.com/">37signals</a>:</p>
<p><a href="https://basecamp.com/guides/group-chat-problems">Group Chat: The Best Way to Totally Stress Out Your Team</a></p>
<p>As is typical for BaseCamp&rsquo;s writing, this is a really great article, in this
case looking specifically at the drawbacks of real-time company chat.</p>
<p>In our case, we migrated from Google&rsquo;s GSuite to Office365 (because much more
bang for the buck) right when COVID hit, and so we found ourselves in the
wonderful world of Microsoft Teams.</p>
<p>So far, we have had a pretty stellar experience.</p>
<p>As a company-wide real-time chat and video meeting platform, Teams does its job
well.</p>
<p>However, real-time chat has a number of fundamental problems, most of which are
super recognizably (and humorously) discussed in the linked post.</p>
<p>For example:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Group chat is like being in an all-day meeting, with random participants, and
no agenda.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Does this ring any bells for any of you?</p>
<p>I hope that you can make time to read the article, but an important part of
their answer to the real-time chat problem is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Real-time sometimes, asynchronous most of the time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At BaseCamp, they implement this idea with message boards where people post
longer form messages that can be responded to with longer-form replies. These
threads are attached to the object where they are most relevant, for example a
project, or a to-do, and so on.</p>
<p>The word &ldquo;thoughtful&rdquo; also stuck in my mind.</p>
<p>Instead of the rapid-fire, often glib, responses you see in real-time chat,
BaseCamp tries to encourage thoughtful, considered messages and replies that
are accessible to anyone who might need them (unlike email) when viewing the
project, to-do or issue in question</p>
<p>The post further talks about changes both to one&rsquo;s conventions, but also to
one&rsquo;s tools, as the latter can be effectively used to guide the former.</p>
<p>In this light, it&rsquo;s interesting to note that many of my most pleasant online
interactions have recently been taking place on github issues, whereas the
real-time chat platforms I spend time on sometimes have the tendency to cause
anxiety.</p>
<p>I have not yet read and measured enough, but I am very curious as to whether
some of these techniques could be implemented in my workplace, and how they
could contribute to a constructive and effective communication environment.</p>
<p>Please let me know in the comments if you have experience with any of this in
your environment!</p>
<h2 id="in-a-while-crocodile">In a while crocodile</h2>
<p>Friends, have a great week!</p>
<p>I wish you an abundance of calm, and of effective communication.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Why it’s healthy that Microsoft and Google are eating Apple’s lunch</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/02/why-its-healthy-that-microsoft-and-google-are-eating-apples-lunch/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 08:41:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/11/02/why-its-healthy-that-microsoft-and-google-are-eating-apples-lunch/</guid><description>Last week Apple announced their new Macbook Pro laptops.
Their great innovation (a “game-changer” in their words) was a sliver of a touch screen above the keyboard which is able to show touchable context-specific buttons. They’ve dubbed this the TouchBar. Although the OLED technology is certainly pretty, one could almost hear the enormously disappointed collective “MEH” uttered by millions of users and suddenly erstwhile Apple fans world-wide.
Was Apple, in the form of the Phil Schiller really trying to sell this? By the way, if you represent Apple, a company traditionally known for its great design sensibilities, should you not spend just a little more money to dress a little better than the couture equivalent of an old Lada? Suit up man! Phil Schiller not suiting up.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Last week Apple announced their new Macbook Pro laptops.</p>
<p>Their great innovation (a “game-changer” in their words) was a sliver of a touch screen above the keyboard which is able to show touchable context-specific buttons. They’ve dubbed this the TouchBar. Although the OLED technology is certainly pretty, one could almost hear the enormously disappointed collective “MEH” uttered by millions of users and suddenly erstwhile Apple fans world-wide.</p>
<p>Was Apple, in the form of the Phil Schiller really trying to sell this? By the way, if you represent Apple, a company traditionally known for its great design sensibilities, should you not spend just a little more money to dress a little better than the couture equivalent of an old Lada? Suit up man!










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/2016-11-02-104946_304x456_scrot.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/2016-11-02-104946_304x456_scrot.png"
        
            alt="Phil Schiller not suiting up."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Phil Schiller not suiting up.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Collectively, the internet <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/entry/new-apple-macbook-pro_us_58123abde4b064e1b4b0fd76">was disappointed</a>. Why no touch screen? Why no new iMac (last refresh a year ago) or Mac Pro (last refresh 3 years ago)? <a href="https://milen.me/writings/mac-platform-decline/">What is happening at Apple</a>?</p>
<p>The day before, on October 26, 2016, Microsoft revealed the Surface Studio. Watch this introduction:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BzMLA8YIgG0?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>… and also this video with Microsoft partners who have in secret been working with the Studio:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WMklcdzcNcU?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Even if you did not like Microsoft, you can get a good sense of the emotion around this new product.</p>
<p>They’ve managed to make something that speaks to the imagination. When I see this, as an outspoken Microsoft critic, I do get the distinct feeling that the Surface Studio is a physical artefact of the science fiction dream that my reality is gradually (and very pleasingly) turning into. My less nerdy technology-critical better half’s first reaction was: <strong><em>When can we get this?</em></strong></p>
<p>It seems that Microsoft has convincingly out-Appled Apple.</p>
<p>In other words, Microsoft has somehow become sexy whilst Apple seems to have developed strong feelings for the Lada.</p>
<p>As an interesting related tidbit, a friend, whom I was trying to convince NOT to get Google’s new Pixel XL phone because reasons, recently sent me <a href="http://www.theverge.com/circuitbreaker/2016/10/29/13466786/google-pixel-photo-better-than-iphone">this short post on The Verge</a> by Vlad Savov, a camera phone expert who until recently was of the educated opinion that the iPhone 7 was still the king of the smartphone castle. He writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>On the basis of my extended experience with Google’s Pixel, I consider it an all-around better phone than the iPhone 7. The final exhilarating straw that broke the camel’s back was the photo below, coming straight out of the Pixel XL’s camera, undoctored other than for a horizon adjustment.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>WHAT IN HEAVENS IS HAPPENING?! OUR WHOLE WORLD IS COLLAPSING!</p>
<p>Perhaps not…</p>
<p>During a Signal App conversation (you should really use Signal, it now has <a href="https://www.whispersystems.org/blog/giphy-experiment/">privacy-conscious Giphy support</a>) with <a href="http://francoismalan.com/">another friend</a>, I realised that what’s happening here, is in fact <strong>wonderfully capricious human emotion interfering with the machine that is capitalism</strong>.</p>
<p>Left to its own devices, the nature of capitalism means that successful companies tend to evolve into capitalistically optimal dead ends. In other words, large successful companies lose the will to innovate, because they realise they are able to make more money at less risk by simply not rocking that boat. Instead of investing in innovation, they invest in sales and marketing to milk their large customer-base.</p>
<p>Ironically, Steve Jobs explained this idea quite eloquently during this interview where he talked about the decline of Xerox:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_1rXqD6M614?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Fortunately, when a company like Microsoft throws an innovation curve-ball that appeals to our emotion and to our imagination, they can rock the boat for everyone.</p>
<p>Even although we’re talking about three absolute behemoths, it’s gratifying that they, as well as their smaller competitors, keep each other on their toes through the fickle wonder that is human behaviour.</p>
<p>Here’s to hoping that AI never manages to model or predict our precious caprice. :)</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #111: A swift hack.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/15/weekly-head-voices-111-a-swift-hack/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2016 20:04:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/08/15/weekly-head-voices-111-a-swift-hack/</guid><description>Well hello friends! In this here,the one hundred and eleventh edition of the Weekly Head Voices, I present a personal view of selected events that took place in the time between Monday, July 25 and Sunday, August 14 of 2016.
Post summary: HackerNews FastMail to Gmail retrospective (WARNING NERD CONTENT), Craft Beer tips, Swift Playgrounds (teach your kids to code!) and a tiny bit of backyard philosophy at the end.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well hello friends! In this here,the one hundred and eleventh edition of the Weekly Head Voices, I present a personal view of selected events that took place in the time between Monday, July 25 and Sunday, August 14 of 2016.</p>
<p>Post summary: HackerNews FastMail to Gmail retrospective (WARNING NERD CONTENT), Craft Beer tips, Swift Playgrounds (teach your kids to code!) and a tiny bit of backyard philosophy at the end.</p>
<h2 id="the-hackernews-effect">The HackerNews effect</h2>
<p>When I submitted my <a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to Fastmail blog post</a> to HackerNews last Monday, it was after some consideration, and with considerable trepidation. The previous time a similar post of mine was picked up by the HN frontpage (and reddit) in 2013, it resulted in a great number of fairly harsh insults flung my way (the harsh ones seem to hit much harder than the many more constructive ones can compensate for). The problem is not having your work criticised, it’s rather being ad hominem’ed into the ground.</p>
<p>The internet can unfortunately get quite bad that way.</p>
<p>However, this time the internet was in a good mood!</p>
<p>As a Z-list (aka hobbyist) blogger, I already get quite excited when even two people find something entertaining or educational in my blog, so you can imagine my excitement when I saw my blog stats jump into the thousands during the first hour after hitting the HN front page.</p>
<p>646 upvotes, 365 comments (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12247401">in the HN discussion</a>) and more than 50 thousand blog post views later (!!), my asbestos suit is still in storage, and the box of kleenex (for drying up my tears) is still unopened. I am very happy with the healthy and mostly happy discussion both on HN and here on the blog.</p>
<h2 id="a-taste-of-my-secret-beer-notes">A taste of my secret beer notes</h2>
<p>In my travels around the world (ok, maybe just in a few hundred kilometre radius of where I live) I taste many exotic and strange drinks (okay, maybe just the local craft beers). Here’s an excerpt from my top secret beer notes for your reading and hopefully soon tasting pleasure:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/stellies_bosch_weiss.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/stellies_bosch_weiss-648x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Stellies Bosch Weiss"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Stellies Bosch Weiss</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The <strong>Stellies Bosch Weiss</strong> is is a refreshing white beer which I can imagine enjoying much more in 35 celsius. However, I find it way too gassy for my taste and thus give it 0.4 on the Celis White scale. As everyone knows, <a href="https://www.beeradvocate.com/beer/profile/565/5222/">Celis White</a> is the best white beer in the world. I’m also not the biggest fan of CBC’s Krystal Weiss because of its gassiness. This could also be a German vs Belgian thing.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://www.darlingbrew.co.za/beers.html#/bc">Darling Brew Bone Crusher</a> is probably a 0.8 on the Celis scale, and scores mega bonus points for choosing such a heavy metal name.









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/patriot_lager.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/patriot_lager-576x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Citizen Beer’s Patriot Lager"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Citizen Beer’s Patriot Lager</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Citizen Beer has a real knack for naming beers; so this weekend I was able to do my patriotic duty (ha ha) by enjoying their <strong>Patriot lager</strong>. Fortunately, they also have a great knack for making lovely beers. This lager is more than hoppy enough to remind you that it’s a craft, but at the same time it is refreshingly light.









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_lager.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_lager-576x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Devil’s Peak Lager"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Devil’s Peak Lager</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Not completely coincidentally, I also tasted the <strong>Devil’s Peak Lager</strong> this weekend. There are subtle differences between it and the Patriot which I will only be able to describe after more tasting. For now: Same lightness, but with enough hop. Highly enjoyable.









<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_pale_ale.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/devils_peak_pale_ale-524x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Devil’s Peak Pale Ale"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Devil’s Peak Pale Ale</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>As I’ve mentioned before, it’s no coincidence that happiness and hoppiness look so similar. The <strong>Devil’s Peak Pale Ale</strong> was a superbly hoppy (about 239% more hoppy than the lager) and full flavoured conclusion to the weekend. In spite of its full body this Cape Town beer’s alcohol content is lower than I would have expected: Only 4%.</p>
<h2 id="first-impressions-of-swift-playgrounds">First impressions of Swift Playgrounds</h2>
<p>I might or might not have acquired a new iPad Air 2 with the primary motivation of being able to test the new <a href="https://www.apple.com/swift/playgrounds/">Swift Playgrounds</a> on Genetic Offspring Unit #1 (now 10 years old). This is a new and attractive iPad-only app that has been designed by Apple to teach kids how to program in Swift. Note that you’ll have to upgrade to <a href="https://beta.apple.com/sp/betaprogram/">iOS 10 Beta</a> to get the app, at least until <a href="https://www.apple.com/ios/ios10-preview/">iOS 10 is officially released</a>. One of the exercises looks like this (image taken from the website):</p>










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-14-at-6.25.43-PM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/Screen-Shot-2016-08-14-at-6.25.43-PM-1024x729.png"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Previous experiments with <a href="https://scratch.mit.edu/">scratch</a> and with <a href="https://processing.org/">processing</a> have met with limited success but no permanence. However, GOU#1 is an iPad fanatic, and the potential of getting her addicted to the programming bug is just too fantastic to let this opportunity go by.</p>
<p>On the first day, she was already writing functions and for loops in Swift in order to navigate a cute alien solving puzzles on a 3D landscape.  I was looking over her shoulder now and then: The educational content and execution of the app is impressive. Besides the built-in puzzle worlds such as the 3D one pictures above, you can create your own Swift projects from scratch. These projects can use iPad hardware such as bluetooth and the camera, but we’re not quite there yet. Apple has also promised to keep on expanding the educational content.</p>
<p>I’m really crossing my fingers that GOU#1 will keep at it. If Swift Playgrounds helps to get her programming, I might just have to go full fanboy.</p>
<h2 id="heading">∞♥</h2>
<p>This past Friday at the breakfast table, Genetic Offspring Unit #2 asked her mom how much she thought GOU#2 loved the baby GOU#3, upon which the mom asked “How much do you love GOU#3?”.</p>
<p>GOU#2 answered: Infinitely much!</p>
<p>My fragile parental unit heart almost exploded with happiness at this point. It’s what I tell GOU#1 and #2 when I put them to bed, and every morning when I drop them at school. (GOU#3 herself does not yet parse our language.)</p>
<p>Ok kids, it looks like there’s an infinite amount of the good stuff to go around. You know what to do!










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/bettys_bay_somewhere.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/08/bettys_bay_somewhere-1024x576.jpg"
        
            alt="I went jogging (or rather walking with a two-step now and then). Enjoyment of surroundings and physical activity was quite intense at this point in spacetime: 15:55 on August 7, 2016; GPS coordinates in EXIF data."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>I went jogging (or rather walking with a two-step now and then). Enjoyment of surroundings and physical activity was quite intense at this point in spacetime: 15:55 on August 7, 2016; GPS coordinates in EXIF data.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>