<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>life on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/categories/life/</link><description>Recent content in life on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/categories/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The 2021 to 2022 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/</guid><description> Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the traditional yearly year transition post!
Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.
I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to 2014 (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and 2015 (no real excuse).
Much later, on Sunday January 23: It could very well still win the Most Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&amp;rsquo;s done.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to 2022 everyone, and to this, the <a href="/tags/transition/">traditional yearly year transition
post</a>!</p>








<figure><a href="20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/20211228-st-francis-sunset-rock_hu65833b55380b189423c4687e135f9921_1379772_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 1: </span>Sunset rock in St Francis on December 28, 2021, close to the end of the main event.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought it was the latest ever, but it turns out that that honour goes to
<a href="/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/">2014</a> (which had a really good excuse to appear only in March) and <a href="/2015/01/21/weekly-head-voices-88-just-be-yourself-they-said/">2015</a> (no real
excuse).</p>
<p><em>Much later, on Sunday January 23:</em> It could very well still win the Most
Fragmented Ever, but at least now it&rsquo;s done.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging</h2>
<p>Emacs and <code>M-x count-words</code> (on a temporary buffer copied over from <a href="/archive/#2021">the 2021
blog post archive</a>) tells me that I published 28 posts on this blog, and 8
technical posts over on <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>Just like with the running below, but for different reasons, I lost a lot of
steam during the last few months of the year.</p>
<p>In a truly surprise twist, in 2022 I will again attempt to write regularly, and
to write more, and to keep it up until the end.</p>
<h3 id="stats-addendum">Stats addendum</h3>
<p>Applying the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess log analyzer</a> to this blog&rsquo;s log files with the following
invocation:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span style="display:flex;"><span>(<span style="color:#859900">for</span> i in {2..13..1}; <span style="color:#859900">do</span> <span style="color:#cb4b16">echo</span> cpbotha.net.access.log.<span style="color:#268bd2">$i</span>.gz; <span style="color:#859900">done</span>) | xargs zcat -f -- | goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>&hellip; tells me that in 2021 cpbotha.net welcomed over 115000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>The same tool reports that <a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a> clocked in at just under 165000 unique visitor IPs.</p>
<p>Even if the real number of actual human visits is a quarter of what the tool is
reporting, I am ecstatic!</p>
<p>The three most popular cpbotha.net posts based on hits during 2021 were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cpbotha.net/2013/09/15/dear-usa-my-data-has-left-your-building/">Dear USA, my data has left your building</a></li>
<li><a href="/2019/09/21/note-taking-strategy-2019/">Note-taking strategy 2019</a></li>
<li><a href="/2016/08/06/moving-12-years-of-email-from-gmail-to-fastmail/">Moving 12 years of email from GMail to FastMail</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>Thanks to Strava&rsquo;s handy training calendar shown below, we can see that I spent
125 hours last year (mostly, about 4 hours was spent on hiking just over 20km)
running a bit over 1300km.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_13-06-57_screenshot_hu72429ca752d1368a15874ecdecfff6fd_66071_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>You can also see quite clearly that I lost steam in November and especially in
December.</p>
<p>This was initially due to work getting quite busy, and then later in December a
bout with Omicron (highly probably) and also less than run-friendly weather in
St. Francis.</p>
<p>I am always happy when I manage to average 100km or more per month, and I&rsquo;ll
probably try to do that again in 2022.</p>
<h3 id="possibly-tmi-read-on-at-your-own-risk">Possibly TMI, read on at your own risk</h3>
<p>Those of you who know me, will also know about my giant <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bunion">bunion</a>, or hallux
valgus as it prefers to be called.</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            
                   
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-15_15-18-44_screenshot.png"
            

        
            alt="Figure 2: Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&amp;rsquo;s complicated." width="240px"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 2: </span>Valgus, Hallux Valgus. License to limp. Relationship status: It&rsquo;s complicated.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Anyways, Mr Valgus is unfortunately playing an increasingly frequent role in my
attempts at running, often starting to complain at N kilometres where N is
fortunately still higher than most of my attempts, but still affecting a
worrying number of them.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to push on, until Mr Valgus overstays its welcome, at which point
it will be time to explore invasive corrective procedures.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>Probably my most redeeming habit of them all, is reading books every night in
bed until I fall asleep.</p>
<p>Even if the day has been less than satisfactory, ending it with an entirely
deliberate and focused reading session tends to make up for quite a lot.</p>
<p>Although I was planning to do more book summaries in 2021, I managed to
complete only one. At least it was a good one, namely <a href="/2021/06/05/book-notes-seven-and-a-half-lessons-about-the-brain/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Seven
and a Half Lessons About the Brain&rdquo; by Lisa Feldman Barrett</a>, which I can
strongly recommend if you have not checked it out yet.</p>
<p>Thanks to strong contenders like the one above, the competition was fierce, but
in the end the <em>WHV non-fiction book of 2021 Award</em> could go to nothing other
than Oliver Burkeman&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B08FGV64B1/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;btkr=1"><em>Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals</em></a>.</p>
<p>Burkeman, he of the <a href="/2021/08/20/weekly-head-voices-230-follow-your-blisters/#know-how-to-put-down-your-work">importance of being able to put <em>down</em> your work</a> and of <a href="/tags/oliver-burkeman/">more
appearances on this blog</a>, has created a beautifully written ode to our terribly
limited lifespans (4000 weeks if you&rsquo;re lucky, you can almost hear them ticking
away&hellip;), and to our terribly limited capacity to make the most of the time
that we do get, and to really just giving up the fight to <em>get everything done</em>,
because we will never ever win the battle against the law of perpetually
filling inboxes of various kinds, and because it&rsquo;s so much better to simply
<em>disconnect</em> from the firehose (which we can&rsquo;t get rid of completely) in order to
spend time on no-excuses leisure, and especially on our loved ones.</p>
<p>My favourite fiction book by far was <em>The Anomaly</em> by Hervé le Tellier, as
translated by Adriana Hunter.</p>
<p>After having just grudgingly finished Elizabeth Bear&rsquo;s Ancestral Night (first
novel in the White Space series; some interesting ideas, but just too pulpy,
clumsy and exposition-rich for my taste, in spite of space opera being a guilty
pleasure&hellip;), the light literariness and French cynicism of The Anomaly was a
<em>delightful</em> and refreshing breeze that I was unable to put down until it was
done.</p>
<p>In 2022, I&rsquo;m planning to read more than in 2021, and publish more of those
summaries.</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>The <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#mindfulness">daily meditation streak that started in 2020</a> continued for most of 2021,
until the end-of-year school vacation started. I am not yet sure how I&rsquo;ll be
able to fit this into my new 2022 work-routine.</p>
<h2 id="worst-habit-of-2021">Worst habit of 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV Award for Worst Habit of 2021 By Far goes, without a doubt, to my old
friend TwiFRaF-Yo, although this time around the main culprits were Twitter,
Reddit and YouTube.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t know exactly when I fell out of <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#yet-another-social-media-fast-because-you-have-to-keep-on-doing-them">the previous social media fast</a>, but I
fell out with a vengeance.</p>
<p>Although I subscribe almost entirely to technical communities on reddit (Emacs,
Orgmode, Org-roam, keyboards, etc.), there are enough of them to keep a person
busy.</p>
<p>If you add to that my twitter feed, where I&rsquo;ve also taken care to remove the
noise, subscribing largerly to high-signal science-, technology- , and
engineering-related feeds, there&rsquo;s a great deal of valuable-seeming information
that one feels compelled to get through every day&hellip;</p>
<p>(It feels like I&rsquo;ve told this story before&hellip;)</p>
<p>Anyways, every time I manage to disconnect (it&rsquo;s been a few weeks now, I think
Monday January 3 was the official start date of the current fast), only then am
I able to recognise (where by &ldquo;recognise&rdquo;, I mean that friends say this to me,
and this is when I&rsquo;m able to admit that they&rsquo;re right) that the net value for
me is highly probably negative.</p>
<p>While there is certainly valuable information that enters via those streams, it
costs so much attention and emotional energy that it&rsquo;s not really worth it.</p>
<p>So.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m back on the no-social-media cart until next time.</p>
<p>Just like the previous time, I&rsquo;m limiting myself to the brilliant Inoreader RSS
subscription service (which I pay for) to keep up to date with 99% long-form
blogs, and two Twitter accounts that are worth too much to me to disconnect
from (<a href="https://twitter.com/erictopol">Eric Topol</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/alper">Alper Çuğun-Gscheidel</a>).</p>
<p>Although I sometimes think this makes me slower, because I don&rsquo;t have all of
the current happenings at my fingertips all the time, I&rsquo;m hoping this gives me
more space and time for reading, thinking and writing.</p>
<h2 id="systems-and-tools-for-running-this-human--pkm-baby">Systems and tools for running this human (PKM baby)</h2>
<p>In the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/#evolve-the-system">2018 to 2019 transition post</a> I mentioned the &ldquo;The System&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and
sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this
creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This time, for this section, I would like to limit it to tools for knowledge
management and task management (this is not my favourite term, but I&rsquo;m erring
on the side of familiarity here) .</p>
<p>All of Emacs and Orgmode and Org-roam is still going strong, although I waver
quite a bit sometimes when I see some of the shiny new things, like <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>,
which I would probably be using if it wasn&rsquo;t for Emacs.</p>
<p>However, when I sometimes dive into my notes, I can see the difference it makes
when you stick to a single tool for longer than a few years. The amount of
knowledge keeps on growing, and I am slowly getting better at linking it all
together and&hellip;  sometimes even using it.</p>
<p>The picture below shows the graph created, by the <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam-ui"><code>org-roam-ui</code></a> package, of a
sub-section of my notes network:</p>








<figure><a href="images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot.png">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1200x0_resize_box_3.png 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_1500x0_resize_box_3.png 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/images/2022/2022-01-23_10-10-50_screenshot_hu88e327303594d9cd1b697465f29419ec_1953767_800x0_resize_box_3.png"
            

        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Before I got side-tracked by the pretty picture, I was planning to dedicate
this section to a new WHV award, namely the Award for the Most Unexpectedly
Useful Software Tool of the Year 2021.</p>
<p>This year the award goes to&hellip; <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/paper/guide">Dropbox Paper</a>!</p>
<p>Back in <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/09/29/weekly-head-voices-233-atomic-party-sections/#dropbox-paper--aka-mobile-note-taking-evolving">WHV #233</a> I listed many of the reasons why. In the few months since then
it has become only more useful to me as the go-to mobile tool for checklists
(especially useful when we go on trips), lists of books, movies and music
recommended by people in person, and so on.</p>
<p>In addition to the qualifier features, such as its markdown DNA and its
usability on mobile for idea capturing, the fact that Paper documents show up
in Dropbox searches, which is how I usually search when I <span class="underline">really</span> need to find a
specific file (versus ripgrep searches in Orgmode), is the deal maker.</p>
<p>(My <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2021/09/29/convert-org-mode-files-to-docx-with-cmake-and-pandoc-for-mobile-accessibility/">strange scheme for continuously converting all org files to docx</a> for
searching and reading on the iPhone is also still going strong.)</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I had a piece written here with more details about what exactly was happening
at work, but I decided to nuke that and instead keep it more personal by
mentioning that thanks to great big dollops of serendipity and people, I find
myself, with a number of levers at my disposal, right in the middle of an
organization which, after a few months of reconfiguration and preparation, has
embarked on a genuinely exciting, and importantly more unified, course.</p>
<p>I would be remiss if I did not mention the <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2021/06/16/weekly-head-voices-226-stress-practice/#eternal-practice-vs-stress">discomfort and stress</a> I was
experiencing at the start of the current personal phase, most probably due to
trying to adapt quickly to my new circumstances and responsibilities.</p>
<p>In the time since then, my stress levels have returned to more acceptable
levels, but expectations remain high.</p>
<h2 id="friends-and-family">Friends and family</h2>
<p>One of the most positive changes I made in the past year, was to put more
effort into making regular and active (virtual) contact with friends whom I
don&rsquo;t see in person regularly enough.</p>
<p>THANKS INTERNET YOU DA BEST.</p>
<p>This year, I want to try harder to do more of that.</p>
<p>More generally, I made a note (yes, again, one has to keep doing this until the
end) to celebrate any of my peeps and our relationships whenever there&rsquo;s a
chance.</p>
<p>Secret message for my innner INNER circle: You are my energy and my joy, I am
here to be yours.</p>
<p>Whatever else happens, these precious relationships are all we have.</p>
<h2 id="even-more-plans-for-2022-continue-trying">Even more plans for 2022: Continue trying</h2>
<p>First off, I would really like to get this blog post here done and
published. (it wants to be too much, or rather I want it to be too much, and so
we sit here staring at each other instead of just getting on with it so I can
try again to write a good post for once)</p>
<p>Second, EAZ is back on, since Monday January 10. EAZ means no alcohol until at
least February 10. As has been the case previously, my sleep quality is
subjectively better, and it seems like my energy levels are more consistent
throughout the week.</p>
<p>I just looked back at last year&rsquo;s transition post, and especially at the <a href="/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/#life-systems-2021">final
sections, including the neatly documented Life Systems 2021</a>. That guy
(<a href="/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/">apparently we share only about 2% of our atoms</a>) really seemed to have his
stuff together, on paper at the very least.</p>
<p>As I write this (22:38 on Saturday, January 22), I have just realised that <em>this</em>
&ldquo;I&rdquo; definitely needs to spend some more time thinking about &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo; (The WHV
approach to life, the universe and everything, the one with the pillars (love
and science, that&rsquo;s the easy and reliable bit) and the rules) and specifically
if and how to revise the daily life direction clusters.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll have it on your desk by Monday.</p>
<p>Until then, the one thing I&rsquo;m sure about, is that I wish you and your loved
ones the best 2022 possible.</p>








<figure><a href="stormsriver-mouth.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2022/01/23/the-2021-to-2022-transition-post/stormsriver-mouth_hu5c3e6efe76845b8cafe3f5d409cdccae_3461485_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 3: Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p><span class="figure-number">Figure 3: </span>Our cottage for the night of December 20 at Storms River Mouth.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2020 to 2021 transition post</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 15:19:00 +0200</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/</guid><description><![CDATA[ Welcome to the year 2021 friends.
Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.
You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to the &ldquo;transition&rdquo; tag page.
If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition.
This transition tradition started at the end of 2009, which coincidentally is also the year that the Weekly Head Voices was born.]]></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the year 2021 friends.</p>
<p>Every year around about this time, I try to write a transition post like this one.</p>
<p>You can get a list of all of the transition posts by going to <a href="/tags/transition/">the &ldquo;transition&rdquo;
tag page</a>.</p>
<p>If you don&rsquo;t have time to read them all (haha), you could just scan through
<a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/">last year&rsquo;s 2019 to 2020 edition</a>.</p>
<p>This transition tradition <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">started at the end of 2009</a>, which coincidentally is
also the year that <a href="/2009/08/29/starting-today-head-voices-every-week/">the Weekly Head Voices was born</a>.</p>
<p>The goal of the transition post is to do a really spotty year review, and then
to gaze unsuccessfully into the future.</p>








<figure><a href="leopards_kloof.jpg">
    <img
        
            sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
              
            srcset='
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 800w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1200w,
            
                   https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_1500x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1500w,
            '

            
            
            src="https://cpbotha.net/2021/01/10/the-2020-to-2021-transition-post/leopards_kloof_hu5764d9b19d63464c70ccbed24cb90bd6_4357448_800x0_resize_q75_box.jpg"
            

        
            alt="Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&amp;rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Figure 1: A scene from a hike up Leopard&rsquo;s Kloof. I chose this one, because it deviates nicely from the usual cloudy skies images in my posts. Also, it&rsquo;s just intriguing and perhaps foreboding enough to accompany any predictions for 2021.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>More seriously, the ever-evolving network of posts on this website (there are
now literally hundreds of them), along with the ever-evolving but also fading
network of neurons in my head (probably at least a few hundred of them too!),
benefit from an occasional higher-level connecting of some of the dots.</p>
<p>In the introduction of the <a href="/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/">2018 to 2019 transition post</a>, I ramble on slightly
more about the multiscalar nature of my subjective experience, and how that is
reflected in my notes database, of which this blog is one aspect.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s get on with it!</p>
<h2 id="noteworthy-snippets-through-the-lens-of-this-blog">Noteworthy snippets through the lens of this blog</h2>
<h3 id="covid-19">COVID-19</h3>
<p>One of the biggest issues for most people last year and still at this moment is
COVID-19.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re interested, you could take a look at the Weekly Head Voices posts
that had something to say about <a href="/tags/covid19/">COVID-19</a>, but you don&rsquo;t really have to.</p>
<p>Fortunately, world-wide vaccination has commenced. However, we have to keep our
fingers crossed that:</p>
<ol>
<li>The world succeeds in getting the vaccine to a sufficient number of humans
on time.</li>
<li>A vaccine-resistant strain does not happen. It could, because math, and
because evolution (selection pressure due to the vaccine, doh),</li>
</ol>
<p>Whether the above outcomes realise or not, I do also hope that we retain as
many as possible of the lessons we have been learning thanks to the pandemic.</p>
<ul>
<li>Mask-wearing and generally improved hygeine with the major goal of protecting
our fellow humans are great habits.</li>
<li>We have made great strides towards the future of work, where many workers (by
far not all, but it&rsquo;s a good meaningful chunk) are able to commute less,
pollute less, better organize the interaction of their work and family lives
and, importantly, their work is measured by its value and not by the number
of hours it takes place in.</li>
<li>We humans are in this (today pandemic, tomorrow something else!) together.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="lazar-focus-the-side-project-that-got-released">Lazar Focus: The side-project that got released</h3>
<p>Around these parts we have a rich tradition of starting but then never
finishing side-projects, and the concomitant giant side-project graveyard to
show for it.</p>
<p>This year, I did manage to ship the little distraction blocker tool I wrote,
called <a href="https://lazarfocused.com/">Lazar Focus</a>. The <a href="/2020/05/31/weekly-head-voices-196-get-focused/#lazar-focus-the-super-tiny-windows-app-and-website-distraction-blocker-that-you-ve-always-wanted">first WHV mentioning was #196</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the fact that this little tool has ended up helping me to rescue
many aspirant unproductive days, it has sold more than 10 copies, which was my
life goal for this project.</p>
<h3 id="the-pygmalion-effect">The Pygmalion effect</h3>
<p>From Adam Grant&rsquo;s book Give and Take, I learned about the <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/#the-pygmalion-effect">Pygmalion effect</a>,
where a teacher&rsquo;s <em>belief</em> in the intrinsic capabilities of a student, whether
those were justified or not at the time, had a significant and enduring
positive, one could say potentially life-changing, effect on that student&rsquo;s
performance.</p>
<p>Besides the bit about the Pygmalion effect, <a href="/2020/08/10/weekly-head-voices-201-i-dont-have-to-miss-dr-topol/">that post (WHV #201)</a> contains a
micro-summary of the Shape Up book by Basecamp, which is also worth a look.</p>
<h3 id="take-the-day-off-to-go-run-in-the-mountain">Take the day off to go run in the mountain</h3>
<p>During the year, for example in <a href="/2020/09/12/weekly-head-voices-203-spiritual/#life-progress-update">WHV #203</a> when I took my birthday off to go
running in the mountains, I learned that taking days off on the birthdays of you
and your loved ones to go do stuff outdoors is a Great Idea(tm).</p>
<p>(I also learned that sometimes you don&rsquo;t even need an excuse. Just take the day
off and go run in the mountains.)</p>
<h3 id="use-it-or-lose-it">Use it or lose it</h3>
<p>The human system is amazingly adaptable.</p>
<p>The price that we pay for that flexibility is that each and every one of our
learned capabilities requires continuous practice in order to be maintained.</p>
<p>In short humans, <a href="/2020/12/23/weekly-head-voices-212-use-it-or-lose-it/#use-it-or-lose-it">use it, or lose it</a>.</p>
<h3 id="fool-your-mind">Fool your mind</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m making peace with the fact that I apparently need to apply, continuously,
various silly tricks to keep <a href="/2020/10/10/weekly-head-voices-206-mount-ceder/#my-mind-is-a-slippery-eel">the slippery eel that is my mind</a> on the
straight-and-narrow.</p>
<p>As a shining example, <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#back-to-reality-an-18-minute-plan-for-managing-your-day">the refocus reminder</a>, a bell that reminds you at hourly
intervals to focus, indeed sounds a bit silly but adds a great deal of value.</p>
<p>My favourite example from last year however is creating yet more (but smaller!)
habits to kickstart my bigger habits, in this case a <a href="/2020/12/12/weekly-head-voices-211-table-mountain-run-ish/#wetware-checklist-to-bootstrap-your-software-checklist">3-item morning checklist
to kickstart the more daunting full day checklist</a>.</p>
<p>The morning bootstrap checklist is, at the risk of sounding like a startup-bro:</p>
<ol>
<li>meditation,</li>
<li>deep reading and</li>
<li>planning.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="blogging-stats">Blogging stats</h2>
<p>Since February 17 of 2020 when I <a href="/2020/02/23/weekly-head-voices-189-all-systems-green/#the-whole-cpbothanet-hive-has-been-migrated-to-a-small-hetzner-server">migrated everything to a small Hetzner VPS</a>,
the server log files tell me that cpbotha.net saw just over 157000 unique
visitors, which is 492 per day on average.</p>
<p>I wrote 30 posts on cpbotha.net during 2020, of which 25 were editions of the
Weekly Head Voices.</p>
<p>Thanks to the shiny new archive page I put together today, you can now finally
<a href="/archive/#2020">see all of 2020&rsquo;s posts in one place</a>, or of any other year, should you be more
into the older stuff.</p>
<p>In addition to the cpbotha.net posts, I also published 11 posts over on
<a href="https://vxlabs.com/">vxlabs.com</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to the regular WHV posts, I&rsquo;m happy to have published what will
hopefully be only the first in a whole collection of book notes posts, namely
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Notes on the book &ldquo;Creativity, Inc.&rdquo; by Ed Catmull with Amy Wallace</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s chunky at just over 7000 words, but it will give you a pretty good idea of
the contents of the much more substantial book it is based on!</p>
<h3 id="details-for-nerds">Details for nerds</h3>
<p>This is the invocation I used to generate reports from the nginx log files
using the <a href="https://goaccess.io/">goaccess</a> tool:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#586e75;background-color:#eee8d5;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>zcat -f -- /var/log/nginx/cpbotha.net.access.log.*.gz |<span style="color:#2aa198">\
</span></span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#2aa198"></span>    goaccess --ignore-crawlers --log-format=COMBINED -
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="running">Running</h2>
<p>In 2020 I seem to have run just 100 metres shy of 1100km. (Typical&hellip;)</p>
<p>More would have been good, but I&rsquo;m happy with this.</p>
<p>Exercise did take a bit of a hit due to <a href="/2020/04/13/weekly-head-voices-191-covid-19-part-2/#exercise">lockdown</a>, although I could definitely
have squeezed more in.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, the aggregated amount of enjoyment and satisfaction
was astronomical.</p>
<p>A personal highlight was <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#random-notes-on-the-kogelberg-trail-adventure">running the 24km(ish) Kogelberg trail with a tiny
crew that included two of my Dutch family members</a>.</p>
<p>(These blog retrospectives are strange, because they are also life
retrospectives, but they shouldn&rsquo;t get too personal. I would be remiss however
if I did not mention that having these specific Dutch peeps here in 2020 was
magical. I am going to miss them terribly.)</p>
<p>Also thanks to said peeps, I did more trail running this year than ever before.</p>
<p>It turns out that I am surrounded by beautiful trails. WHO KNEW?!</p>
<p>The other highlight I want to mention was <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations">GOU#1</a> running her first race, the
distributed <a href="/2020/11/07/weekly-head-voices-208-stilbaai/#running-and-reading">CTM 10km in Jonkershoek</a>. Here&rsquo;s to many more GOU kilometres!</p>
<h2 id="mindfulness">Mindfulness</h2>
<p>Thanks to some strict words by friend PK during the year, I got solidly back on
the daily meditation train, which ended up being the start of a streak of
(workday) morning meditation longer than anything I&rsquo;ve been able to maintain up
to now.</p>
<p>(The bootstrap checklist in <a href="#fool-your-mind">Fool Your Mind</a> above might also have contributed to
this.)</p>
<p>The Waking Up course by Sam Harris has been amazing for more than two years
now, and even more so when trying to build and keep up a daily meditation
habit.</p>
<p>What I especially like about Waking Up is its focus on the explicit practice of
the experience of consciousness and the role (or non-role) of the self within
that. (for a tiny example, see <a href="/2020/10/24/weekly-head-voices-207-kogelberg/#find-a-place-in-the-universe-that-is-your-consciousness">WHV #207</a>)</p>
<p>Practising this daily has been an experience that I can only recommend in the
strongest terms.</p>
<p>(Please let me know if you&rsquo;d like to try a month for free. As a subscriber, I
get to give these out to as many peeps as I want to.)</p>
<h2 id="life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</h2>
<p>The WHV approach to life, the universe and everything (also known as &ldquo;WALUE&rdquo;,
but you have to over-emphasize the terribly soft &ldquo;W&rdquo;) has been evolving for a
few years now, but it was most recently summarised in <a href="/2020/06/16/weekly-head-voices-198-short-update-for-future-me/#post-scriptum-the-whv-approach-to-life-the-universe-and-everything">WHV #198</a>.</p>
<p>At the basis of this approach we find the two formidable pillars of</p>
<ol>
<li><em>love</em> and</li>
<li><em>science</em>,</li>
</ol>
<p>and in that order. On top of these pillars rest <a href="/2017/07/30/weekly-head-voices-124-ceci-nest-pas-dennui/">The WHV&rsquo;s Two no Three Rules
for Achieving Great Success in Life, or Just Surviving, Whichever Comes First</a>.</p>
<p>The two no three rules are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Be useful.</li>
<li>Be likable.</li>
<li>Evolve.</li>
</ol>
<p>In the previous transition post, I talked about <a href="/2020/01/12/the-2019-to-2020-transition-post/#plans-and-life-directions-for-2020">six personal daily life
directions</a>, the continuous reformulation of which I had integrated into my
morning routine.</p>
<p>It was a good start, but the life directions were a bit too specific, and six
separate things is too many to keep at the core of your thoughts.</p>
<p>Motivated by this, and also by <a href="https://lexfridman.com/chris-lattner-2/">the Lex Fridman podcast with Chris Lattner</a>
wherein Lattner, an amazing engineer, but more importantly such a kind human
being, underlined the importance to him of always continuing to grow and learn,
I mashed together everything I had to come up with two clusters of daily life
directions:</p>
<ol>
<li>Grow, learn, build, enjoy. (motion)</li>
<li>Be useful. Be likeable. Be kind. (self-checks)</li>
</ol>
<p>In the stupid-dimensional universe that is my mind, I know that these
directions are obviously in the spirit of WALUE, but I can&rsquo;t yet articulate
clearly how they relate to the pillars and the rules of WALUE.</p>
<p>Maybe they&rsquo;re just a neat little pile on top, or a little bit to the side,
leaning against the WALUE building?</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, they have been part of my daily checklist for a few
months now, and they seem to work in the sense of being practical, checkable
and tiny enough to keep in mind always.</p>
<h2 id="plans--for-tomorrow-at-least">Plans (for tomorrow, at least)</h2>
<p>This bit is quite scary.</p>
<p>I hardly know what&rsquo;s going to happen tomorrow, and here I wanted to talk about
plans for the whole year!</p>
<p>So, to be clear, what I&rsquo;ve listed below is limited to the concrete items that I
can see before me right now.</p>
<h3 id="the-absolute-basics">The absolute basics</h3>
<ul>
<li>Attempt to apply <a href="#life-systems-2021">Life Systems 2021</a> all of the time.</li>
<li>Practise mindfulness every day.</li>
<li>If I&rsquo;m wondering whether I should go run, the answer is &ldquo;yes&rdquo;.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="comms-upgrade">Comms upgrade</h3>
<p>I would like to level up my communication game.</p>
<p>Work from home is here to stay, and that&rsquo;s a good thing, but it has muffled my
face-to-face communication modality, something that has had a profound impact
on my full communication suite.</p>
<p>Most of the clever folks now agree that <a href="/2020/09/20/weekly-head-voices-205-real-time-sometimes-async-most-of-the-time/#the-future-of-work-episode-23">the correct answer is asynchronous
communication</a>. Future-facing companies like Basecamp and <a href="https://blog.doist.com/asynchronous-communication/">Doist have been
preaching this long before COVID-19</a>.</p>
<p>To be more specific, I need to figure out first how to do asynchronous
communication in my daily work, and then to become really good at it.</p>
<h3 id="write-more-about-good-books">Write more about good books</h3>
<p>I&rsquo;m planning to publish more focused book notes like the recently appeared
<a href="/2020/12/22/book-notes-creativity-inc/">Creativity, Inc. post</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s great reading these books, but I&rsquo;ve noticed that if I&rsquo;m planning to
publish book notes, I read more intently, I take better notes, and the extra
processing stage before starting to put together a blog post really helps me to
integrate the knowledge contained in the book.</p>
<p>Every good book one is able to integrate is in fact a cheap, but possibly
game-changing firmware upgrade&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="wishes-for-2021-for-you">Wishes for 2021, for you</h2>
<p>Thank you for reading this. I am grateful that you&rsquo;re here.</p>
<p>I wish you and everyone you hold dear the best 2021 possible.</p>
<p>Quite concretely, we can all help to make this happen by being as kind as we
possibly can to as many fellow humans as we possibly can.</p>
<p>In the words of a fellow traveller: SMÉAGOL OUT!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2018 to 2019 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 15:39:34 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/01/06/the-2018-to-2019-transition-post/</guid><description> The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.
Welcome to this, the most recent (as of this writing) instance of the venerable WHV year transition post tradition!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/cape_st_francis_light_house-1024x646.jpg"
        
            alt="The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The sun setting over a lighthouse with a mysterious path in the front. I might just have maxed out my quota of clichéd ending / beginning symbolism, but this situation really just presented itself a few days ago. One previous year as I arrived at this particular lighthouse, it had a rainbow as well. I think the lighthouse itself is, analogously to Mitch Hedberg’s blurry bigfoot, inherently clichéd.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Welcome to this, the most recent (as of this writing) instance of the venerable WHV year transition post tradition!</p>
<p>You can find previous editions here:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 to 2018</a> – short post, can be summarised as: “Sorry I stopped blogging for a while, I did run a bit, I’m going to blog more.”</li>
<li><a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">2016 to 2017</a> – substantial post (1800 words) with: “education will improve stupid politics; running, blogging, meditation; we made a new baby!!; kindness and gratefulness; life changes the whole time, deal with it.”</li>
<li><a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">2011 to 2012</a> – transition post disguised as WHV with: “stop doing life goals, disconnect more, list of miscellaneous life tips, because in 2011 I am not-even-40-yet Mr Wisdom”.</li>
<li><a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">2009 to 2010</a> – super short but sweet, I am clearly still new at this.</li>
</ul>
<p>Putting that list together just reminded me of an interesting observation: The more I try to take notes and document everything I see, the more I notice the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiscale_modeling">multiscalar</a> nature of my subjective experience being exposed.</p>
<p>I make detailed daily notes, all of them grouped in monthly text files.</p>
<p>At a slightly higher scale, the frequency of these WHV blog posts is somewhere between a post per week down to a post every three weeks.</p>
<p>When I write each blog post, I look back through the previous weeks, at a daily scale, and perform an extremely lossy summarisation.</p>
<p>When I write the year transitions, I perform an extremely lossy summarisation of the weekly-scale WHV posts.</p>
<p>The list above links together the various yearly transition posts, thus creating a lovely ball of multi-scalar confusion, which should not be confused with a lemur ball, shown below:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/lemur_ball-1024x682.jpg"
        
            alt="At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>At the Monkeyland Primate Sanctuary in Plettenberg Bay, I learned that lemurs huddle together in these aptly called “lemur balls” to share body heat. When it’s cold enough, they even take turns to be in the middle.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>WARNING: This post has grown into a long ramble over the past few days. I hope that you enjoy reading the ramble as much as I did thinking of you while writing it.</p>
<h2 id="focus-quantity-and-quality">Focus: Quantity and Quality.</h2>
<p>This post has been taking a while.</p>
<p>I am now back here at the start, after having been almost at the end, because I did not want you to have the idea that my 2018 did not have aspects I am not that happy with, or that I don’t use multiple negations in confusing ways often enough.</p>
<p><em>(As an aside, a friend and I have been exchanging photos of the less glamorous but entirely normal aspects of our vacations via WhatsApp: Plastic on the beach, the washing line, filthy toilets, truly terrible interior decor, and so on. What started as a joke has turned into an unintended but interesting psychological experiment in</em> <strong><em>reverse image crafting</em></strong><em>, strongly underlining the effect that this sort of communication can have.)</em></p>
<p>Back to my main story: During retrospection, I have the tendency to focus (sorry, couldn’t resist) on the good parts, because this is what I remember the best.</p>
<p>However, for the purpose of this post, I did want to spend some words on one of the (multiple!) issues that I struggled with in 2018.</p>
<p>Either I am getting worse at focusing, or I am getting better at noticing when I lose focus, or a combination of both.</p>
<p>At the very least <a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">five of the posts I wrote in 2018 dealt in some way with</a> <em><a href="https://cpbotha.net/tag/focus/">focus</a></em>.</p>
<p>The mentioned posts specifically and my thinking generally take the form of some analysis but mostly tools and tricks to try and improve the frequency, intensity and length of periods of focus.</p>
<p>(What you don’t read in the posts because of above-mentioned memory bias, is that there is usually a significant amount of inwardly-directed regret and disappointment involved.)</p>
<p>Even more subtle is the problem of selecting That One Most Suitable Thing to focus on. What’s going to have the most impact? What do I have capacity for at the moment? Can I trust my own subjective assessment of my current capacity, or is Lazy-Me being sneaky?</p>
<p>By the time I have made a decision, it’s probably wrong. <em>Sometimes</em> it’s a good decision, but by then the little block of time I had has flown away or has been blown to smithereens by the latest interruption, and so the quality of the decision is moot.</p>
<p>I would have expected that at this advanced age focus would come naturally and easily, and that I would know exactly what to do. However, I have had to accept that <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#slippery-slippery-focus">focus will probably remain this slippery</a> and require constant attention (haha I see what I did there) until the very end.</p>
<p>Besides eating well, sleeping well, exercising regularly and taking time to meditate (just in case!), our old friend <a href="https://cpbotha.net/?s=pomodoro">the pomodoro technique</a> is still the best tool in the box.</p>
<h2 id="blogging">Blogging.</h2>
<p>During 2018, 36 blog posts were published here, most of which were Weekly Head Voices. Those of you who have a math degree or two will not need much time to calculate that the “W” in “WHV” is at the moment mostly a little inside joke.</p>
<p>However, I did publish 14 more posts than I did in 2017, so there is hope for this year!</p>
<p>The wordpress.com statistics plugin reports just over 19000 visitors (unique IP numbers) who were responsible for just over 26000 page views for the whole year.</p>
<p>Because many people use some form of ad and/or tracking blocking these days, their visits won’t be counted, as the wordpress.com statistics relies on a tiny image which is hosted by wordpress.com, access to which is (rightfully) blocked by many blocker plugins.</p>
<p>In order to get a better idea of how many ad-blocker people read my stuff, I installed the <a href="https://wp-statistics.com/">wp-statistics</a> plugin, which locally tallies up all visits and hence is not blocked by blockers, at the start of March. For the period from March 2018 until the end of the year, it is reporting just over 74000 visitors and somewhere north of 390000 page hits.</p>
<p>Although to me this seems on the high side, I do think we can safely say that there were somewhere between 19000 and 74000 unique hosts, which to me is a very pleasant surprise.</p>
<p>However, I am by far the happiest due to all of the interactions I had with friends, mostly old and some new, on this blog. Most recently, the comments section of <a href="/2018/10/23/weekly-head-voices-156-karma-chameleon/">WHV #156</a> blew up in such a brilliant way!</p>
<p>More generally speaking, even when there are no comments, I know that throughout the year I am connecting with various subsets of my peeps through the posts on this blog. This acts as tremendous motivation to keep on writing. If even a single friend reads, it has been more than worth it.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, there is now a</em> <a href="https://t.me/headvoices"><em>telegram group, quite surprisingly called “headvoices”</em></a><em>, that you can join to receive a summary whenever a new post is published, and for general chitchat. Although so far only two of my most avant-garde friends have joined, this new form of blog-related communication excites me!)</em></p>
<h3 id="looking-forward">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>Surprisingly, I again will aim to write one WHV post per week.</p>
<p>I will probably fail again, but I believe that this is one of those cases of “aim for the stars, reach the moon”.</p>
<p>As mentioned above, writing these letters and writing them regularly is really important to me.</p>
<p><em>(BTW, I should probably have declared <strong>email bankruptcy</strong> years ago. I am</em> <strong><em>just</em></strong> <em>managing to keep head above water, but writing letters to friends like we used to do in the old days is becoming increasingly difficult. What is your feeling currently re email and how it has changed over the past few years?)</em></p>
<h2 id="running">Running.</h2>
<p>Strava says I ran 1286km in 2018.</p>
<p>Seeing that I had set myself a private goal of 1000km for 2018 (2016 was 440km and <a href="/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/">2017 was 880km</a>), I am quite happy with this.</p>
<p>(As an aside, I spent 119 hours running, spread out over a total of 149 runs, which means 2.86 runs every week of the year.)</p>
<p>I did 770 of those 1286 kilometres in sandals, and a further 35km on barefoot.</p>
<p>More importantly, I had to learn the humbling lesson that no amount of stubborn, brute-force exercise could work around the fact I am flat footed (arch-challenged?), resulting in easily overworked posterior tibial tendons.</p>
<p>As I pushed my weekly distance up, my feet complained more loudly, until I was forced to go back to normal-person-running-shoes.</p>
<p>After a few weeks eating humble pie in running shoes, things are going much better, and I recently did my first short and careful run in sandals.</p>
<p>(Similar to the observation confirmed by <a href="https://veronikach.com/progress-reports/my-goals-for-2018-final-progress-report/">the pattern recognition heroine veronikach in her end-of-2018 post</a>, I too ran slower this year in order to run better. I did this for the largest part due to my temporarily busted ankles, but also because more experienced athletes at work recommended heart rate training. For the past few hundreds of kilometres, I have regulated my running speed to try and keep my heart rate within the 75% to 85% of maximum range, mostly ending up closer to 85% than 80%. This has increased the occurrence of those addictive perfect runs, and it has helped to keep my ankles out of trouble.)</p>
<h3 id="looking-forward-1">Looking forward:</h3>
<p>In 2019, I would be happy to <em>maintain</em> my 2018 monthly running quota, to remain injury-free, and to maximise my running zen.</p>
<p>(“Running slow” explained above can contribute substantially to the latter two goals.)</p>
<p>I do have an additional concrete (but very humble) running-related resolution for 2019, but I have decided to keep that quiet until it’s in the pocket. :)</p>
<h2 id="other-plans-for-2019">Other plans for 2019.</h2>
<h3 id="experiment-alcohol-zero">Experiment Alcohol Zero #2.</h3>
<p>Yesterday, which at the time of writing is January 4, 2019, was the first day of EAZ #2.</p>
<p>It has been two years since <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/#experiment-alcohol-zero">the previous EAZ in 2016</a>. The previous experiment coincided with a significant jump in my running performance, the effects of which did not fade away after the end of the experiment.</p>
<p>This time around, the plan is to run EAZ for at least as long as in 2016, but hopefully a few days or weeks longer.</p>
<p>(I should probably call this EA&lt;0.5, as that is what my current favourite “alcohol-free” beer, Devil’s Peak Zero to Hero, claims.)</p>
<h3 id="ship-more-side-projects">Ship more side-projects.</h3>
<p>Most nerds I know have <em>side-projects</em>.</p>
<p>These are the technical artifacts, systems and machines one builds, because one can’t stop building stuff, even after work ends.</p>
<p>Like most nerds, I have a number of these that started with high momentum (new programming language, new tools, new problem, EXCITING! … 3 hours later … NOVELTY COMPLETELY WORN OFF doh.) and are now lying around gathering dust.</p>
<p>Inspired by a colleague who managed to ship <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/656740/Cosmonator/">a brilliant shooter game side-project on Steam</a> last year, I made myself the promise to ship more side-projects.</p>
<p>After that, I managed to ship two side-projects, one small and the other quite tiny.</p>
<p>This was a satisfying experience that I would like to continue in 2019.</p>
<p>(P.S. the problem with shipping side-projects, is that you now have more things that you actually have to look after. Next year I’ll think up a resolution for unmaintained shipped side-projects.)</p>
<h3 id="mindful-more">Mindful more.</h3>
<p>This is a simple one.</p>
<p>I used to spend a few minutes every second morning before work doing simple mindfulness breathing and focus exercises.</p>
<p>It was worth the modest time investment many times over, in terms of focus, and especially in terms of seeing life in perspective.</p>
<p>In the second half of 2018 I let this habit slip for some or other reason. I think it’s because I convinced myself that running time could also count as meditation time.</p>
<p>In 2019, I’m going to #bringbackthemeditation.</p>
<h3 id="learn-more">Learn more.</h3>
<p>During 2018, I started taking a more structured approach to the books I wanted to read, and the courses I wanted to follow, by tracking these in my <a href="/2018/10/12/weekly-head-voices-155-lush/#productivity-pro-tip-fool-yourself-into-doing-a-good-daily-review">sneaky longer term goals which form part of my daily planning routine</a>.</p>
<p>More structure meant more books read to completion, and more courses followed, resulting in an Ever So Slightly Improved Me.</p>
<p>I am planning to continue and extend this practice in 2019.</p>
<h3 id="evolve-the-system">Evolve The System.</h3>
<p>The System.</p>
<p>The System is Emacs, and orgmode, and multi-scalar note-taking everywhere, and sketching, and daily habits, and a whole bag of tricks to try and keep this creaky old frame moving in the right direction.</p>
<p>One step, and then another, and then another, until the lights finally go out.</p>
<h3 id="try-to-grow-a-tree">Try to grow a tree.</h3>
<p>I grew up with a fuerte avocado tree that gave us hundreds of the divine fruit every season.</p>
<p>Fast-forward 40 odd years, and my mom (HI MOM!) gave us a beautiful baby fuerte avocado tree for Christmas!







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/baby_avocado_tree-805x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The baby avocado tree, right after we transferred it to its new home, in a little nest of fine compost and bone meal.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>We are currently trying to nurture it through its first few weeks of life in our garden.</p>
<p>With the summer sun, and the new environment, it’s a bit touch and go at the moment, but we’re really rooting for that baby tree! (bad pun quota exhausted now?!)</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>This is it my friends.</p>
<p>You have made it to the end, an endeavour for which I am truly grateful.</p>
<p>I wish you a 2019 filled with growth, health and happiness.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2019/01/bbay_sunset-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>This reminds me of a certain sunset in the Tankwa desert with a rather funny helicopter.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2017 to 2018 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 11:46:06 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/12/29/the-2017-to-2018-transition-post/</guid><description> My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis.
Does anything still work around here?
So much dust…
Is this thing on?
Testing… 123… tesssting… sound check sound check.
OH HI MARK.
(HELLO ALL MY OTHER FRIENDS WHO ARE NOT MARK!)
It’s been 4 months since the previous post (a Weekly Head Voices), due to reasons involving work (fortunately challenging and fun), genetic offspring units but especially the youngest one who is currently developing at a frightening speed, the South African climate, and my brain suddenly starting to refuse work any later than about 19:00 every day.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2827-PANO.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2827-PANO-1024x404.jpg"
        
            alt="My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>My innermost circle of humans, on an exceptionally windy hill in St Francis.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Does anything still work around here?</p>
<p>So much dust…</p>
<p>Is this thing on?</p>
<p>Testing… 123… tesssting… sound check sound check.</p>
<p>OH HI MARK.</p>
<p>(HELLO ALL MY OTHER FRIENDS WHO ARE NOT MARK!)</p>
<p>It’s been 4 months since the previous post (a Weekly Head Voices), due to reasons involving work (fortunately challenging and fun), genetic offspring units but especially the youngest one who is currently developing at a frightening speed, the South African climate, and my brain suddenly starting to refuse work any later than about 19:00 every day.</p>
<p>My brain has good reasons I have to admit, having absorbed <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2017/sep/24/why-lack-of-sleep-health-worst-enemy-matthew-walker-why-we-sleep">this Guardian interview with Matthew Walker</a>, director of the Center for Human Sleep Science at the University of California, Berkeley. In short, the possible effects of sleeping anything less than 7 hours per night are simply terrifying. It made me, I mean my brain, really rethink its approach to grabbing-one-more-hour-from-sleep-because-this-stuff-is-really-super-interesting.</p>
<p>Anyhow, following the probably better and more beefy example set by my previous transition post, <a href="/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/">2016-to-2017 that is</a>, I thought that a new edition would be the best way to get back into slightly more regular posting.</p>
<h1 id="2017-the-100-partial-and-spotty-review">2017: The 100% partial and spotty review</h1>
<p>I wrote 21 posts on this blog in 2017, 12 of which were Weekly Head Voices, which means I was about 23% (12 / 52) successful in terms of posting frequency with the WHV.</p>
<p>The most popular post over here was <a href="https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/09/deep-work-a-welcome-kick-in-the-butt/">Deep Work: A welcome kick in the butt</a>, published on January 9, which garnered just over 20 thousand views. From there my stats went all downhill. :)</p>
<p>More importantly than reader stats, each post, especially <a href="https://cpbotha.net/category/weekly-head-voices/">the Weekly Head Voices ones</a>, brought so much connection and satisfaction, which raises the question: Why am I not doing this more? (See my reasons above for not having posted for 4 months, I would have to guess.)</p>
<p>In 2017, I ran just over 800km, which, in contrast to my blogging frequency, is a nice improvement over the 440km I did in 2016. Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) of February last year contributed significantly to my average distance and speed. Those gains were maintained and slightly extended in spite of EAZ concluding in March of last year.</p>
<p>To get an idea of what I was up to work-wise in 2017, you could consider browsing <a href="https://vxlabs.com/2017/">the posts I wrote on my nerd-blog during 2017</a>.  This will give you a bad idea, but it’s probably better than no idea, if you really needed to know.</p>
<p>Life-wise, I might have mentioned <a href="/category/weekly-head-voices/">The Weekly Head voices posts</a> before. There aren’t that many of them for 2017, but the ones that there are, are not too bad.</p>
<h1 id="2018-again-not-much-planned-at-least-not-in-public">2018: Again not much planned, at least not in public.</h1>
<p>Following the shining example of <a href="http://www.veronikach.com/progress-reports/year-of-blogging/">Dr Cheplygina</a>, I would love to become a fully paid-up member of the <em>True</em> Weekly Bloggers Club.</p>
<p>For the past 6 months I sort of went Facebook cold turkey (because reasons, mostly to do with attention-abuse and above-mentioned time scarcity). That, in addition to my unplanned blogging hiatus, feels (yes, I have those, albeit in extremely limited quantities) like it’s caused a bit of a disconnect between me and friends around the world.</p>
<p>I have very recently returned to facebook via the mobile website, and only after extremely liberal application of the “unfollow” button to whittle my feed down to just the people I have a healthy connection with. This will help me te maintain connections with the friends who use that as platform.</p>
<p><strong>My reciprocation will have to take the form of weekly updates on this blog.</strong></p>
<p>I look forward to it, and I look forward even more to welcoming you here!








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2669.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/12/IMG_2669-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from our cabin at Storms River Mouth Rest Camp. 12/10 will go again."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from our cabin at Storms River Mouth Rest Camp. 12/10 will go again.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The 2016 to 2017 transition post.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 11:05:01 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2017/01/05/the-2016-to-2017-transition-post/</guid><description> Following the rich tradition over here of year transition posts, having just rounded off a brilliant outdoorsy take-your-mind-off-of-everything vacation with friends, and also inspired by wogan.blog’s nicely personal 2016 review post, I decided that a farewell-2016 how-you-doin’-2017 post was in order.
By the way, by rich tradition I mean that I wrote the grand total of one (1) similarly titled post previously, as the year ticked from 2009 to 2010, and at least one other, disguised as a weekly head voices, as we entered 2012.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Following the rich tradition over here of year transition posts, having just rounded off a brilliant outdoorsy take-your-mind-off-of-everything vacation with friends, and also inspired by <a href="https://wogan.blog/2017/01/01/2016-in-review/">wogan.blog’s nicely personal 2016 review post</a>, I decided that a farewell-2016 how-you-doin’-2017 post was in order.</p>
<p>By the way, by <em>rich tradition</em> I mean that I wrote the grand total of one (1) similarly titled post previously, <a href="/2010/01/10/the-2009-to-2010-transition-post/">as the year ticked from 2009 to 2010</a>, and at least one other, disguised as a weekly head voices, <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">as we entered 2012</a>. <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">That last one</a> is worth another read, early 2012 cpbotha had some really good tips. There might be more such posts, <a href="/about/history/">this blog has been around for more than 15 years</a> and much of what I’ve written is not available from my short-term memory, which is nice.</p>
<p><em><strong>Warning:</strong> This post is long (1800 words+), rambly and sometimes even a bit mushy. I hope you enjoy it!</em></p>
<h1 id="2016-the-review">2016: The Review</h1>
<h2 id="the-bad-with-a-hopefully-slightlypositive-outlook-at-the-end">The bad, with a hopefully slightly positive outlook at the end</h2>
<p>Let’s get the bad stuff out of the way as soon as we can…</p>
<p>For me the biggest disappointments of 2016 were the double-whammy of the Brexit followed by the Trumpocalypse.</p>
<p>I really did not expect either of these events to go the way they did.</p>
<p>This is probably because I was, ever the optimist, over-estimating the level of human development of British and US voters.</p>
<p>The exclusionist, nationalist, xenophobic and in many cases even white supremacist thinking associated with Trump’s support in the US and the Leave vote in the UK are truly abhorrent.</p>
<p>I understand that there were many other factors at play. However, these voters were either throwing out the baby with the bath water, or, much much  worse, agreeing with the abhorrent sentiments mentioned above. Especially this second possibility depressed me greatly after the US election.</p>
<p>After such setbacks, one needs to look for solutions.</p>
<p>After Brexit, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/international/archive/2016/06/brexit-vote-statistics-united-kingdom-european-union/488780/">analysis showed that education level was the strongest indicator of a vote for leave or remain</a>. Higher education was strongly associated with remain, whilst the opposite was the case for leave.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Screen-Shot-2017-01-05-at-12.28.37-PM.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/Screen-Shot-2017-01-05-at-12.28.37-PM-709x1024.png"
        
            alt="Leave / remain voter analysis by The Atlantic. Click to go to article &#43; interactive version of this graphic."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Leave / remain voter analysis by The Atlantic. Click to go to article + interactive version of this graphic.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>For Trump voters, you probably guessed it, it was more or less the same idea. <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/education-not-income-predicted-who-would-vote-for-trump/">Less educated citizens voted for Trump, more educated citizens for Clinton</a>.</p>
<p>This is yet another strong indication that we should really be pouring every resource we have into the education of our people. (yes, correlation and causation, I know. hence the terms “strong indication”. discuss in the comments if you like.)</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrence_M._Krauss">Lawrence M. Krauss</a>, superstar theoretical physicist and author of the book A Universe from Nothing, <a href="https://twitter.com/LKrauss1/status/814947974203641857">recently tweeted</a> this <a href="http://www.quotationspage.com/quote/26977.html">1920 quote by H.G. Wells</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Human history has become, more and more, a race between education and catastrophe.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The way things are going now, that thought, and movements like #feesmustfall, are more important than ever. There can be absolutely no excuse for neglecting the highest quality and <strong>accessible</strong> education (basic up to tertiary) of future generations of humans whom we expect to further our civilization.</p>
<h2 id="therunning-and-the-mindful">The running and the mindful</h2>
<p>In 2016, I ran 440km.</p>
<p>There are a great deal of people who have run much more than that, but those are <em>my</em> 440 kilometers and somehow they brought me a great deal of deep satisfaction.</p>
<p>During the year, my per-run distance and speed have gradually increased.</p>
<p>Besides fitness gradually increasing, I discovered experimentally that shorter, quicker steps get me further and a higher pace. It took a biomechanical friend to explain to me that this was about muscles operating within the more efficient middle of their full extension/contraction ranges. I could probably just have read this somewhere, but doing it the hard way and then having a friend explain it on top of Table Mountain definitely added something to the experience.</p>
<p>For the last 200 kilometres or so, I have listened to the exact same album: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skin_(Flume_album)">Skin by Flume</a>. Every single run, I start that exact same album with the exact same sequence of tracks. As I learned from <a href="https://www.swimgeek.com/blog/2016/11/16/quick-update-445/">the SwimGeek’s blog</a>, <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/2113776/question-everything-tim-ferriss-fitness"><em>finding your soundtrack and putting it on repeat</em> whilst exercising is apparently a thing</a>.</p>
<p>With the surroundings over here being what they are, it does not take much to slip into a state of mindfulness.</p>
<p>No doing, no planning; just absorbing all of the surroundings, physical and mental, the music, and feeling how the meat-based machine that houses me propels us forward.</p>
<p>On the topic of mindfulness, for the last few months I added a repeat event to my todoist, helping me to spend five minutes every morning before work doing the breathing exercise. More recently I do this without any voice track, but previously Prof. Mark Williams at one point would say (original quote is due to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jon_Kabat-Zinn">Jon Kabat-Zinn, PhD</a>):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Each breath a new beginning; each out-breath a letting go.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There’s a whole lot in there. I have spent quite some time with it and I am far from done.</p>
<h3 id="the-blog">The blog</h3>
<p>The first rule of blogging: You don’t blog about blogging.</p>
<p>However, I hope you don’t mind me breaking that rule to mention that in 2016, this blog was viewed 133 thousand times. I already get happy when one other person reads a post. You can imagine how happy it makes me to know that there are even slightly more people who have come here to consume some of the words I have written, and even some who have taken the time to leave behind comments!</p>
<p>The lion’s share of those views were due to focused posts that got picked up by some of the more popular nerd sites. I have to admit that I derived the most enjoyment from the more personal posts that were only read by friends.</p>
<p>Whatever the case may be, this has to be my most satisfying hobby. Thank you for the crucial role that you who read play in it!</p>
<h3 id="the-new-life">The new life</h3>
<p>In early(ish) 2016, our third daughter, affectionately known as Genetic Offspring Unit #3 (GOU#3 for short) around these parts, <a href="/2016/05/05/weekly-head-voices-106-ch-ch-ch-ch-changes/">was born</a>.</p>
<p>This wonderful little cellular mega-cluster is currently making noises that have the primary purpose of being immensely cute, but are also slowly starting to make sense. Her ambulation capabilities have increased immensely, and she is on the verge of standing up by herself and so we will probably have to re-arrange our interior. Again.</p>
<p>Long ago, <a href="/2011/08/28/the-lowlands-tooth-fairy-37-weekly-head-voices-55/">I wrote here about my unexpected new role as someone else’s Tooth Fairy</a>. In the meantime, working as a part-time tooth fairy and a full-time papa to three little humans has turned out to be a more fulfilling career than I ever could have imagined.</p>
<h1 id="2017-not-much-planned-yet-you">2017: Not much planned yet, you?</h1>
<p>I prefer making resolutions in secret, then carrying them out or not, and only then reporting on them. However, that would mean that I would have to wrap up this post right now, and for that I’m not quite ready yet.</p>
<h2 id="experiment-alcohol-zero">Experiment Alcohol Zero</h2>
<p>One resolution that I am already executing on, is performing an interesting little experiment. After reading about <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/the-running-blog/2014/apr/23/how-does-alcohol-affect-athletic-performance">the effects of alcohol on one’s (running) performance and general energy levels</a>, I have decided to go for 30 days without a drop of alcohol to try and get a subjective idea of its potential impact.</p>
<p>Those of you who have spent more than 8 seconds in my or my blog’s vicinity know that I absolutely adore craft <a href="/tag/beer/">beer</a> (this includes local, but also special beers of the Belgian type) and local wines, both of which are regularly consumed by me and “business partners” during “business lunches” in the not-unattractive local surroundings.</p>
<p>This decision was not taken lightly.</p>
<p>It is mid-morning of day 2 of Experiment Alcohol Zero (EAZ) as I write this. With the air full of smoke due to <a href="/2017/01/04/massive-fires-around-here-thanks-to-firefighters-my-neighbourhood-escaped/">local vegetation fires</a>, I have not been able to go running yet, but I am imagining that my energy lasted later last night, and I got up easier this morning. I have 29 more days to investigate.</p>
<h2 id="reminders-for-a-hopefully-better-life">Reminders for a hopefully better life</h2>
<p>Every day, I remind myself <a href="/2014/09/09/weekly-head-voices-81-middle-aged-zen/">to be the kindest I can possibly be to everyone I come into contact with</a>. We have infinite amounts of kindness to spread.</p>
<p>I also remind myself to <a href="/2014/11/03/weekly-head-voices-84-on-being-grateful/">be grateful</a>. It takes continuous practice to identify the many things one can be grateful for every day, but it is definitely worth it.</p>
<p>I often remind GOU#1 (#2 and #3 are not old enough yet for this lesson) that, besides the guidelines above, we have to keep on working on two more related characteristics: being useful, and being likable.</p>
<p>Being useful means continuously developing and refining skills that enable one to contribute value to one’s surroundings. Being likable means understanding and appreciating how we humans stick together. Kindness, see above, is an important component of this.</p>
<p>In 2017, I would like to write more (on this blog probably), and read more.</p>
<h1 id="rapidly-morphing-goalpostsjumping-randomly-through-even-more-randomly-pulsating-hyperspace-with-a-slightly-positive-outlook-at-the-end">Rapidly morphing goalposts jumping randomly through even more randomly pulsating hyperspace, with a slightly positive outlook at the end</h1>
<p>Yes folks, this is going to be my parting thought.</p>
<p>When I was much younger, I used to believe that one’s life could be “cracked”. That is, if you searched, and you worked really hard at understanding yourself, your people and your surroundings, you could come up with some kind of answer with which you would be able to attain contentment.</p>
<p>In the meantime I’ve come to the realisation that that Much Younger Me, although quite dashing, was of course utterly wrong.</p>
<p>Life is utterly dynamic. You Now are a different person from You Last Year. The same goes for people around you, and the same goes for everything around you.</p>
<p>The goal posts are not just moving all the time, they are an illusion flashing in and out of an hallucinogenic and especially dynamic perception.</p>
<p>One trick to help one deal with this, is to stop thinking about goals in the first place, and instead <a href="/2012/01/28/slow-philosophy-weekly-head-voices-64/">consider the directions of your movement</a>.</p>
<p>Also keep in mind that <a href="/2016/02/02/weekly-head-voices-103-chips/">there are no answers, only choices</a>. You work to make the best ones you can with the means at your disposal at that moment.</p>
<p>Importantly, in this restless environment, some peace can be found by realising that a large part of the restlessness originates from within you. Fortunately, you have slightly more say in you than you have in your surroundings.</p>
<p>What one can do then, is nicely summarised by Prof. Mark Williams in the audio accompanying <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mindfulness-Eight-Week-Finding-Peace-Frantic/dp/1609618955">his mindfulness book</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The deep stillness we seek does not arise because the world is still or the mind is quiet. Stillness is nourished when we allow things to be just as they are for now, in this moment, moment by moment and breath by breath.</p>
</blockquote>
<h1 id="the-end-for-now">The End (for now)</h1>
<p>Alright friends, that was it from me, for now. I hope that you have the best 2017 possible. I hope especially that your kindness and that of those around you flows deeply and freely.</p>
<p>As a parting gift, here is the high-resolution panoroma I made from the top of Table Mountain, after hiking up Platteklip Gorge with friends:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2017/01/IMG_20161229_0938212-panorama-1024x325.jpg"
        
            alt="The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net. Click for high-res."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>The view from the top of Table Mountain, photo by cpbotha.net. Click for high-res.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Dolphins on the R44</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2016/04/10/dolphins-on-the-r44/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2016 15:00:18 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2016/04/10/dolphins-on-the-r44/</guid><description> On Sunday, April 10, 2016, as if the day was not already perfect enough, we were super fortunate to see a pod of dolphins speeding along in the sea right next to the R44 coastal road.
The sight was so spectacular, that we could not spare a second to get our cameras out, so you’re going to have to be satisfied with this photo of me and GOU #1 admiring the pod as they swam out of sight.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>On Sunday, April 10, 2016, as if the day was not already perfect enough, we were super fortunate to see a pod of dolphins speeding along in the sea right next to the R44 coastal road.</p>
<p>The sight was so spectacular, that we could not spare a second to get our cameras out, so you’re going to have to be satisfied with this photo of me and GOU #1 admiring the pod as they swam out of sight.</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/dolphins_on_the_r44.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/dolphins_on_the_r44-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>(The level and amount of human excitement on the sides of the road was also something to experience.)</p>
<p>The photo still includes its EXIF GPS information, but here’s a map showing the exact location of the sighting for your interest:</p>
<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="450" src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3300.994836675115!2d18.839709715218266!3d-34.172049680573494!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x0%3A0x0!2zMzTCsDEwJzE5LjQiUyAxOMKwNTAnMzAuOCJF!5e0!3m2!1sen!2s!4v1460880870012" style="border:0" width="600"></iframe>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>What a country!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/23/what-a-country/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 13:35:29 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/23/what-a-country/</guid><description> Exactly ten minutes after having made a single discreet phone call, a truck arrives at one’s house with thousands of pieces of lovingly chopped braai wood. The amount of one’s choosing is then lovingly yet efficiently stacked right by the holy altar of meat scorching, after which the truck leaves on its next mission.
(P.S. The wood is rooikrans.)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Exactly ten minutes after having made a single discreet phone call, a truck arrives at one’s house with thousands of pieces of lovingly chopped braai wood. The amount of one’s choosing is then lovingly yet efficiently stacked right by the holy altar of meat scorching, after which the truck leaves on its next mission.</p>








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/pretty_rooikrans_braai_wood.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/pretty_rooikrans_braai_wood-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>(P.S. The wood is <a href="http://www.wildcard.co.za/blog.htm?action=view-post&amp;id=2945">rooikrans</a>.)</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Surviving Autumn in the Cape: Lourensford Harvest Market</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/10/surviving-autumn-in-the-cape-lourensford-harvest-market/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 13:40:23 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2015/05/10/surviving-autumn-in-the-cape-lourensford-harvest-market/</guid><description> Six jumping castles for the little ones, beautiful food and Lourensford wine for the adults. Lourensford Harvest Market is on every Sunday at Lourensford Wine Estate.
We might just make it through this autumn in one piece!</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ 







<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/wpid-20150510_142845-e1431279158724.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/wpid-20150510_142845-1024x576.jpg"
        /> </a>
</figure>

<p>Six jumping castles for the little ones, beautiful food and Lourensford wine for the adults. Lourensford Harvest Market is on every Sunday at Lourensford Wine Estate.</p>
<p>We might just make it through this autumn in one piece!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #70: Patterns in the sand.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2014 20:15:51 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/05/07/weekly-head-voices-70-patterns-in-the-sand/</guid><description> (I just deliberately deleted the draft I was working on. It was not the best pattern.)
I want you to read this quote by Richard Dawkins, taken from the God Delusion:
Think of an experience from your childhood. Something you remember clearly, something you can see, feel, maybe even smell, as if you were really there. After all you really were there at the time, weren’t you?
How else could you remember it?</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>(I just deliberately deleted the draft I was working on. It was not the best pattern.)</p>
<p>I want you to read this quote by Richard Dawkins, taken from the God Delusion:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Think of an experience from your childhood. Something you remember clearly, something you can see, feel, maybe even smell, as if you were really there. After all you really were there at the time, weren’t you?</p>
<p>How else could you remember it? But here is the bombshell: you weren’t there. Not a single atom that is in your body today was there when that event took place …. Matter flows from place to place and momentarily comes together to be you. Whatever you are, therefore, you are not the stuff of which you are made. If that does not make the hair stand up on the back of your neck, read it again until it does, because it is important.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Do read it again. It’s a pretty mind-expanding realization.</p>
<p>However, reality is perhaps even more mind-bending than you might already think. I looked up the original work on this phenomenon by Aebersold, published in the <a href="http://www.archive.org/stream/annualreportofbo1953smit/annualreportofbo1953smit_djvu.txt" title="link to 1953 Smithsonian Institute annual report">1953 Annual Report of the Smithsonian Institution</a>. On page 232 he wrote (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But radioisotope studies have called our attention to much more  amazing facts on the day-to-day operation of our bodies. Medical men used to think of the human body as an engine that takes in food, air, and water mainly as fuel to keep running on. Only a small part  of the intake was thought to go for replacement of engine wear. Investigations with isotopes have demonstrated that the body instead is much more like a very fluid military regiment which may retain its size, form, and composition even though the individuals in it are continually changing: joining up, being transferred from post to post, promoted, or demoted; acting as reserves; and finally departing after varying lengths of service.</p>
<p>Tracer studies show that the atomic turnover in our bodies is quite rapid and quite complete. For example, in a week or two half of the sodium atoms that are now in our bodies will be replaced by other sodium atoms. The case is similar for hydrogen and phosphorus. Even half of the carbon atoms will be replaced in a month or two. And so the story goes for nearly all the elements. Indeed, <strong>it has been shown that in a year approximately 98 percent of the atoms in us now will be replaced by other atoms that we take in in our air, food, and drink</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes, you read that correctly. <em>In a single year</em>, 98% of your whole physical manifestation, your body, is completely replaced by other atoms.</p>
<p>This observation has led me to think differently about myself, and about you. I indeed used to think that we were a solid body of somehow consistent matter moving through life, constructed from millions of grains of sand somehow sticking together.</p>
<p>Now I see us all as nothing more than the continuously changing <em>patterns</em> that form briefly in the grains of sand of the universe. Winds blow grains of sand around, now taking part in one pattern and then in another. At some point, your body has contained parts of your best friend, and of your worst enemy. The patterns change continually; sometimes they fade away, and sometimes new patterns emerge. All of them are dependent on the same grains of sand.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Back in South Africa</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 10:29:50 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2014/03/21/back-in-south-africa/</guid><description> (I was supposed to publish this around the start of February, but then life happened, and I didn’t get to quite finish it.)
For the first time in the three weeks after having arrived back on South African soil, we find ourselves in something that we’re going to call home for the coming months. Until now we have been living out of our suitcases, spending time with various grandpas and grandmas somewhere in the Boerewors Gordyn (the Northern ‘burbs of Cape Town, to those of you not in the know), The Oven (I just made that up.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>(I was supposed to publish this around the start of February, but then life happened, and I didn’t get to quite finish it.)</em></p>
<p>For the first time in the three weeks after having arrived back on South African soil, we find ourselves in something that we’re going to call home for the coming months. Until now we have been living out of our suitcases, spending time with various grandpas and grandmas somewhere in the Boerewors Gordyn (the Northern ‘burbs of Cape Town, to those of you not in the know), The Oven (I just made that up. It’s Paarl, the town where I grew up thinking that 40 Celsius was a normal temperature to be wearing a blazer and a tie. 40 Celsius is now my preferred outside temperature.) and in Betty’s Bay (that’s its real name. It’s really cute that way. Look at me walking the thin line of apostrophe (ab)use.) We’ve been doing our fair share of early-to-bed-early-to-rise makes John cranky and not very wise, because Genetic Offspring Unit #1 had to be taken to school in our current town of residence, from our at that point temporary residence.








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/taking_a_walk_bbay.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/taking_a_walk_bbay-1024x768.jpg"
        
            alt="So you’re really planning to publish that blog post, but then you take a walk instead. TISA."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>So you’re really planning to publish that blog post, but then you take a walk instead. TISA.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>At the moment I’m sitting in our new home behind an extremely shaky cellular data connection (the house is like the Bermuda triangle of mobile reception. Even in this carefully chosen spot the signal dances a really silly tap dance between H, 3G and EDGE. EDGE is NOT nice, trust me. I think EDGE is actually a synonym for “no connection at all, but we just like to make you think that there has to be something”. At some vague point in the future, ADSL will hopefully be installed. Africa does not care about the timeliness of your internet connection, deal with it.).</p>
<p>So we have our suitcases, and a whole bunch of borrowed items until Our Ship Comes In. No really, we have a ship that’s coming in with all of our old stuff on it. Until that moment, we have a special place where meat can be scorched, also in a social context. This is quite grand.</p>
<p>There is also a mountain in my backyard which I can’t help gawking at whenever I return home. The mountain is majestic, and that is even more grand than the place where you can scorch your meat. I have promised myself to retain and cultivate my awe at this mountain, and at all the mind-blowing natural majesty surrounding me wherever I go in this place, for as long as I can.</p>
<p>See you later everyone!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>