<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Canary on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/canary/</link><description>Recent content in Canary on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 20:29:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/canary/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #188: Exercise Canary.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 20:29:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/</guid><description>As I mentioned in the last WHV, I am in the midst of trying to end this year on a strong and especially regular note.
So, more on time than the rest of the rest of the year, you are now reading the 188th edition of the Weekly Head Voices. This will most probably be the last WHV of the year 2019, looking back at the week from Monday December 23 to Sunday December 29.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>As <a href="/2019/12/23/weekly-head-voices-187-checklists-everywhere/">I mentioned in the last
WHV</a>, I am in the
midst of trying to end this year on a strong and especially <em>regular</em> note.</p>
<p>So, more on time than the rest of the rest of the year, you are now reading the
188th edition of the Weekly Head Voices. This will most probably be the last
WHV of the year 2019, looking back at the week from Monday December 23 to
Sunday December 29.</p>
<figure>














<a href="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path.jpg">

  <img

    sizes="(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw"
  
  srcset='
  
    https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_59397d04b7c51d36.jpg 480w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_15f2b94a18ffd728.jpg 800w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_ed5374261cfa5852.jpg 1200w
  
  
    , https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_e250dd95cfe03186.jpg 1500w 
  '



  
  src="https://cpbotha.net/2019/12/29/weekly-head-voices-188-exercise-canary/bettys_beach_path_hu_15f2b94a18ffd728.jpg"
  

   />

</a>

<figcaption>
Vacation oscillates between lazing and running.
</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="topol-tweets-for-your-vacation">Topol-Tweets™ for your vacation.</h2>
<p><a href="/2019/07/17/weekly-head-voices-173-i-know/#bullet-list-of-miscellany-blom">I may have implied before that Prof. Eric Topol&rsquo;s twitter stream is
brilliant</a>.</p>
<p>During the past few days he posted two high impact (meta-)analyses on topics
that I currently find interesting.</p>
<h3 id="time-restricted-eating">Time-restricted eating.</h3>
<p>The first is a New England Journal of Medicine systematic review of
<a href="/2019/12/18/weekly-head-voices-186-helderberg-20/#time-restricted-eating-tre-with-black-coffee-please">time-restricted
eating</a>
and intermittent fasting:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">How ironic for <a
href="https://twitter.com/NEJM?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@NEJM</a> to publish a
systematic review on time-restricting eating and fasting for <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ChristmasDay?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ChristmasDay</a>
<a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/diet?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#diet</a>
<a href="https://t.co/BLbVxUsZJt">https://t.co/BLbVxUsZJt</a> by de Cabo and
Mattson <a
href="https://twitter.com/HopkinsMedicine?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@HopkinsMedicine</a>
<a href="https://t.co/o5FHhbIISv">pic.twitter.com/o5FHhbIISv</a></p>&mdash;
Eric Topol (@EricTopol) <a
href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol/status/1209957610268397568?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December
25, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>I was able to download the full-text PDF via a free subscription to NEJM which
gives you three free articles per month.</p>
<p>However, I feel it&rsquo;s my civilly disobedient duty to inform you that the PDF is
now also available via
<a href="https://sci-hub.se/10.1056/nejmra1905136">Sci-Hub</a>. (Future readers, if that
link disappears, try <a href="https://whereisscihub.now.sh/">Where Is Sci-Hub</a>.)</p>
<p>Anyways, you can read the full article, or read the twitter discussion embedded
above.</p>
<p>The TL;DR is that fasting&rsquo;s benefits have been clinically shown &ldquo;for many
health conditions such as obesity, diabetes mellitus, CVD, cancers&rdquo; mostly for
&ldquo;overweight young and middle-age adults&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Although long term benefits in otherwise healthy humans still have to be shown,
texts like the following (and more parts of the article&rsquo;s introduction) make me
hopeful:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Periodic flipping of the metabolic switch not only provides the ketones that
are necessary to fuel cells during the fasting period but also elicits highly
orchestrated systemic and cellular responses that carry over into the fed
state to bolster mental and physical performance, as well as disease
resistance.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="amount-and-intensity-of-leisure-time-physical-activity-and-lower-cancer-risk">Amount and Intensity of Leisure-Time Physical Activity and Lower Cancer Risk.</h3>
<p>The second Topol-Tweet I wanted to single out was this gigantic study with data
pooled from 9 cohorts, totalling more than 750000 people, in which the data
showed that 2.5 to 5 hours per week of moderate-intensity [leisure-time]
activity was associated with significantly lower risk for seven different types
of cancer:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Exercise (leisure time
physical activity) and its intensity are associated with a lower incidence of
many types of <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/cancer?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#cancer</a>,
from 9 cohorts, &gt; 750,000 people <a
href="https://t.co/BBMQTCIrDm">https://t.co/BBMQTCIrDm</a> <a
href="https://twitter.com/ASCO?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ASCO</a> <a
href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/openaccess?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#openaccess</a>
by <a href="https://twitter.com/theNCI?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@theNCI</a>&#39;s
Charles Matthews and colleagues <a
href="https://t.co/u91xolRuWO">pic.twitter.com/u91xolRuWO</a></p>&mdash; Eric
Topol (@EricTopol) <a
href="https://twitter.com/EricTopol/status/1210348149849518080?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December
26, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async
src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>This <a href="https://ascopubs.org/doi/pdf/10.1200/JCO.19.02407">the full-text PDF of this Journal of Oncology article is fortunately
available thanks to open
access</a>!</p>
<p>Intriguingly, the study also found that (page 8):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There was evidence of nonlinear u-shaped associations with vigorous-intensity
activity for colon and endometrial cancer such that the protective
associations observed at intermediate activity levels were eroded at higher
levels of activity (ie, 30 v0 MET hours/week).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This either does mean that too much exercise indeed brings us right back to no
protective effect from colon and endometrial cancer relative to no exercise, or
that the data in this case (n = 309881) is still somehow misleading the
analysis.</p>
<h2 id="the-middle-aged-exercise-canary">The (middle-aged) Exercise Canary™.</h2>
<p>On Friday, during the second part of my morning run, the first part being
together with GOU #1 (running with your genetic offspring is amazing on more
than one level), I had an exercise-related realisation which I thought was
worth sharing with you peeps.</p>
<p>Another important but indirect reason to exercise (I&rsquo;m extrapolating from
running here, please correct me if you can) is the following:</p>
<p>Performing some activity at the edge of one&rsquo;s athletic capability, be it
endurance or intensity, enables one to detect with much more sensitivity than
normal, anything negatively impacting one&rsquo;s functioning and hence the status of
one&rsquo;s health.</p>
<p>For example, when I&rsquo;ve lost an hour of sleep for whatever reason, or I&rsquo;ve had
as little as a drink or two the previous day, or, as is often the case, I&rsquo;ve
sinned on both dimensions, my legs, lungs and other grit-related organs will
notify me in no uncertain terms, during my run, that they are not happy.</p>
<p>On a rest day, I <em>might</em> experience a spot of brain fog, but mental performance
is already so complicated that it could be a host of other contributing
factors.</p>
<p>A gaggle of cognitive biases (you heard it here first) means that I usually
ascribe it to everything <em>but</em> my behaviour the previous day.</p>
<p>Fortunately friends, <em>the exercise canary does not lie.</em></p>
<p>Unlike when we were still invincible, here at middle-age I prefer being
reminded early and regularly of the consequences of my daily life choices.</p>
<h2 id="friendly-wishes">Friendly wishes.</h2>
<p>Highly valued reader peeps, I wish you much wisdom and kindness as we round out
the last few days of 2019, and usher in the brave new 2020.</p>
<p>I look forward to our next meeting, either on this blog in the
soon-to-be-written traditional 2019-2020 transition post, or at whichever
other point we might become entangled.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>