<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>timberland on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/timberland/</link><description>Recent content in timberland on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</managingEditor><webMaster>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2011 19:21:34 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/timberland/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Postmodern creativity. [Weekly Head Voices #37]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/05/postmodern-creativity-weekly-head-voices-37/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2011 19:21:34 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/05/postmodern-creativity-weekly-head-voices-37/</guid><description> Post summary: Review humour, WhatsApp, SPA3102 gadget, hiking boots, happiness in the blue zones.
So there are people on the internets who have chosen as their creative outlet the writing of superbly entertaining fictitious reviews of real products on real e-commerce sites. See for example this customer review of a tub of uranium ore that was once available on Amazon: You used to be able to buy uranium ore on amazon.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Review humour, WhatsApp, SPA3102 gadget, hiking boots, happiness in the blue zones.</em></p>
<p>So there are people on the internets who have chosen as their creative outlet the writing of superbly entertaining fictitious reviews of real products on real e-commerce sites. See for example this customer review of a tub of uranium ore that was once available on Amazon:








<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/frikkin_uranium_2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/frikkin_uranium_2.jpg"
        
            alt="You used to be able to buy uranium ore on amazon. You can still read the awesome reviews: http://www.amazon.com/Images-SI-Inc-Uranium-Ore/dp/B000796XXM/"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>You used to be able to buy uranium ore on amazon. You can still read the awesome reviews: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Images-SI-Inc-Uranium-Ore/dp/B000796XXM/">http://www.amazon.com/Images-SI-Inc-Uranium-Ore/dp/B000796XXM/</a></p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I purchased this product 4.47 Billion Years ago and when I opened it today, it was half empty. — reviewer Patrick J. McGovern</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For more examples, please do see <a href="http://www.cracked.com/article_18939_8-stupid-amazon-products-with-impressively-sarcastic-reviews.html" title="cracked.com article on funny amazon reviews">this article on Cracked.com</a>. What a fantastic creative medium! One day, when I grow up, I too shall spend time honing my review writing skills.</p>
<p>Because I’ve <em>just</em> realised that this post was never going to be more than a mishmash of odd but hopefully interesting tidbits, I shall now switch to bullet-list mode:</p>
<ul>
<li>I’ve slowly started developing principles against sending texts (SMS), purely because I think the telephone companies are charging way too much for these 160 character micro-messages. Even if you do have a great big SMS bundle, usually when you text overseas, you still get whacked. <a href="http://www.whatsapp.com/" title="WhatsApp website"><strong>WhatsApp</strong></a> does a pretty good job at being a texting substitute: It runs in the background on Nokia, Android, iPhone or Blackberry smartphones, and allows one to <strong>send and receive unlimited SMS-like messages</strong> via one’s dataplan to other WhatsApp users. Just like texting, it only requires telephone numbers, so directly after installation, one sees a list of all one’s WhatsApp-running contacts (from the phone’s database). Big advantage over for example BlackBerry BBM (ping) is that WhatsApp runs on many more telephones. In short: Try it, you might like it!</li>
<li>On the theme of sticking it to the man (and when I say “man” I mean “telephone company”), I recently acquired a <a href="http://www.cisco.com/en/US/products/ps10027/index.html" title="Cisco SPA3102"><strong>Cisco SPA3102 Voice Gateway</strong></a> (used to be Sipura, then Linksys). It’s a tiny little box that sits in-between your broadband connection (ADSL or cable modem) and house telephone and, if configured correctly, routes all telephone calls via SIP (voice-over-ip) providers. In short: Seriously cheap phone calls via internet, telephone company never even sees you and hence can’t really bill you. The only problem is that this little box has the most complex configuration interface I’ve ever seen. There must be at least a few hundred configuration settings, and if you get any one of them wrong, your phone system simply stops working. I’ve written up what you need to know at my <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/02/05/sipura-linksys-cisco-spa3102-voice-gateway-in-the-netherlands/" title="SPA3102 netherlands setup guide at vxlabs.com">Even Nerdier Blog</a>.</li>
<li>What’s the deal with <strong>hiking boots and engineers</strong>? Hiking boots are great for hiking, but wearing them to work (or far worse, to a social event) must be <em>the</em> most extreme way of showing your asymptotic support of function over form. I have to admit that I myself have sinned before, but usually I have a good excuse, such as that storm outside. There are some people however (and the matching hiking boots worn by in-love engineers / nerds are the absolute worst) that don’t seem to understand that form and function do need to be in some form of balance for the world to function and for me to maintain my non-nauseous state.</li>
<li>It is important to note that Timberland boots strike this balance just perfectly, as you can see below:

  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg">
      <img
          
              
              src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg"
          
              alt="This is what form and function look like when they&#39;re in perfect balance."/> </a><figcaption>
              <p>This is what form and function look like when they're in perfect balance.</p>
          </figcaption>
  </figure>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To conclude this post, I’d like to summarise a <a href="http://lifehacker.com/5751875/five-traits-low+stress-happy-work-cultures-have-in-common" title="lifehacker summary of Buettner's book">lifehacker summary</a> of Dan Buettner’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Thrive-Finding-Happiness-Blue-Zones/dp/1426205155/" title="amazon link to buettner's book">book</a> on the factors that play a role in the happiness of people living in the world’s “blue zones” (countries / regions where people live long and contented lives): 1. work less, 2. keep your commute as short as possible, 3. have regular vacations, 4. socialise with your colleagues and finally, 5. make sure you work for a good boss.</p>
<p>No big surprises there, but sometimes it’s nice being reminded of the stuff we should never have forgotten in the first place.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Time does wait for electronic true love [Weekly Head Voices #30]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/12/time-does-wait-for-electronic-true-love-weekly-head-voices-30/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2010 15:06:55 +0000</pubDate><author>cpbotha@cpbotha.net (Charl P. Botha)</author><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/09/12/time-does-wait-for-electronic-true-love-weekly-head-voices-30/</guid><description> I probably shouldn’t be spending deadline-chasing time writing this post, but I can’t not, you know? I do have some Sunday pomodoros behind me, so the FNSF (and other involved parties) will probably not mind too much. Also, to shave off a few more seconds, I’ll temporarily switch to the Swimgeek Quick Update-style bullet list.
Before the first bullet however, you really have to see the DTV Shredder in action, the vehicle I’ve decided to equip my evil footsoldiers with, right after I manage to purchase a suitable volcanic island and install my evil lair:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I probably shouldn’t be spending deadline-chasing time writing this post, but I can’t not, you know? I do have some Sunday <a href="http://www.pomodorotechnique.com/" title="Pomodoro Technique website">pomodoros</a> behind me, so the <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviation page">FNSF</a> (and other involved parties) will probably not mind too much. Also, to shave off a few more seconds, I’ll temporarily switch to the <a href="http://www.swimgeek.com/blog/" title="SwimGeek's blog">Swimgeek Quick Update-style</a> bullet list.</p>
<p>Before the first bullet however, you really have to see the DTV Shredder in action, the vehicle I’ve decided to equip my evil footsoldiers with, right after I manage to purchase a suitable volcanic island and install my evil lair:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ws8zIHW6Ghk?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>(found via <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2010/09/12/what-happens-when-you-leave-a-skateboard-and-a-tank-alone-in-a-d/" title="engadget post on the DTV Shredder">engadget</a>.)</p>
<p>Here come the bullets:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Due to the completion of the <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Courses/TI1100A" title="TI 1100-a website">TI 1100-a project</a> by the end of the previous week, I was expecting this week to be of the more relaxed persuasion. I couldn’t have been more wrong. It turns out that a number of deadlines were simply in stealth mode, waiting for the right moment to pounce. Colour me surprised.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="Link to WHV abbreviations page">extremely resourceful  / capable individual (ERCI)</a> mentioned in <a href="/2009/09/13/weekly-head-voices-3-powerless-meat-zen-xi-leaves-nfbi-motek/" title="Weekly Head Voices #3">WHV #3</a> and <a href="/2009/11/23/weekly-head-voices-9-windows-7-geek-o-rama/" title="Weekly Head Voices #9">#9</a> completed his M.Sc. under the entertaining supervision of the <a href="/about/weekly-head-voices-abbreviations/" title="WHV abbreviations page">FSNF</a> and myself, defended his thesis (title: <em>Integrated Visual Analysis for Heterogeneous Datasets in Cohort Studies — Application to Neuropsychiatric SLE</em>) this past week, and managed to acquire his whole degree <em>Cum Laude</em>. Congratulations Ir. ERCI, we hope to see much more of you during the coming years *wink wink*!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It turns out that combining a Goretex raincoat, a <a href="http://www.senzumbrellas.com/" title="Senz Umbrellas website">Senz aerodynamic storm-proof umbrella</a> (truly awesome tech, designed by a TU Delft spinoff) and a set of <a href="http://rainlegs.com/" title="RainLegs website">RainLegs</a> (you look like the missing fifth member of the <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CS9OO0S5w2k" title="YMCA original by the Village People">Village People</a>, but your legs remain dry) results in a pretty effective counter-measure against the soul-demolishing Dutch Autumn rain, if one is able to live with wet feet. A Facebook friend with some serious tropical storm experience also recommended a pair of those big Timberland boots, a suggestion that for some or other reason resonated with me, and not only because it would solve my wet feet problem. He meant these really pretty yellow boots with the macho-looking soles:

  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg">
      <img
          
              
              src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg"
          
              alt="These are the Timberland boots you were looking for."/> </a><figcaption>
              <p>These are the Timberland boots you were looking for.</p>
          </figcaption>
  </figure>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>On Thursday, my <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Kindle-DX-Wireless-Reader-3G-Global/dp/B002GYWHSQ/" title="website Kindle DX graphite">Kindle DX Graphite</a> was delivered by the friendly UPS dude. It was love at first sight (with the Kindle and not the UPS dude), and since then my feelings have only deepened. You see, the Kindle DX embodies the fusion of two of my greatest fetishes: Reading and high-tech gadgets. Ostensibly I bought it to try paperlessify my academic review work (papers, student theses, proposals, all printed out numerous times and finally thrown out for recycling) and as soon as firmware 3.0 has been released for the KDX Graphite and I get some time I’ll write a critical blog post concerning its performance in this role, but for now I’m just euphoric with the thing as general reading platform. <a href="http://calibre-ebook.com/" title="Calibre website">Calibre</a>, once you get used to its idiosyncrasies, is fantastic as a cross-platform library manager.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Specific events of the past week, as well as interesting conversations with the FSNF and others, have again pointed out that terminal over-booking might be necessarily associated with a post-Ph.D. academic career. During your Ph.D., you have the exquisite luxury of focusing on one (perhaps three) important things for extended periods of time. Thereafter, right after the defence-afterglow has subsided, if you decide to stay in academia, your calendar and task-manager explode in a messy deluge of meetings, administration and forced work during the evenings and weekends, because this is the only way to get more than half of your stuff done. I have it from trustworthy sources that this only gets worse the further along you get in your career. As I’ve invested heavily in optimising my own time utilisation and efficiency, and now have a strategy that, although there’s significant room for improvement, doesn’t work <em>too</em> badly, I’m planning to put together <em>The Great Academic Time Management Post</em>. If you already disagree with this or with what you think the contents of the post might turn out to be, please vent in the comments!</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it for this episode. My big red pomodoro timer is looking at me in a decidedly unfriendly way… The rest of you have a great week!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>