<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Weekly Head Voices on voices in my head</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/tags/weekly-head-voices/</link><description>Recent content in Weekly Head Voices on voices in my head</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2011 19:21:34 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cpbotha.net/tags/weekly-head-voices/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Postmodern creativity. [Weekly Head Voices #37]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/05/postmodern-creativity-weekly-head-voices-37/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2011 19:21:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/02/05/postmodern-creativity-weekly-head-voices-37/</guid><description>Post summary: Review humour, WhatsApp, SPA3102 gadget, hiking boots, happiness in the blue zones.
So there are people on the internets who have chosen as their creative outlet the writing of superbly entertaining fictitious reviews of real products on real e-commerce sites. See for example this customer review of a tub of uranium ore that was once available on Amazon: You used to be able to buy uranium ore on amazon. You can still read the awesome reviews: http://www.amazon.com/Images-SI-Inc-Uranium-Ore/dp/B000796XXM/</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Review humour, WhatsApp, SPA3102 gadget, hiking boots, happiness in the blue zones.</em></p>
<p>So there are people on the internets who have chosen as their creative outlet the writing of superbly entertaining fictitious reviews of real products on real e-commerce sites. See for example this customer review of a tub of uranium ore that was once available on Amazon:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/frikkin_uranium_2.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/frikkin_uranium_2.jpg"
        
            alt="You used to be able to buy uranium ore on amazon. You can still read the awesome reviews: http://www.amazon.com/Images-SI-Inc-Uranium-Ore/dp/B000796XXM/"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>You used to be able to buy uranium ore on amazon. You can still read the awesome reviews: <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Images-SI-Inc-Uranium-Ore/dp/B000796XXM/">http://www.amazon.com/Images-SI-Inc-Uranium-Ore/dp/B000796XXM/</a></p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I purchased this product 4.47 Billion Years ago and when I opened it today, it was half empty. — reviewer Patrick J. McGovern</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For more examples, please do see <a href="http://www.cracked.com/article_18939_8-stupid-amazon-products-with-impressively-sarcastic-reviews.html" title="cracked.com article on funny amazon reviews">this article on Cracked.com</a>. What a fantastic creative medium! One day, when I grow up, I too shall spend time honing my review writing skills.</p>
<p>Because I’ve <em>just</em> realised that this post was never going to be more than a mishmash of odd but hopefully interesting tidbits, I shall now switch to bullet-list mode:</p>
<ul>
<li>I’ve slowly started developing principles against sending texts (SMS), purely because I think the telephone companies are charging way too much for these 160 character micro-messages. Even if you do have a great big SMS bundle, usually when you text overseas, you still get whacked. <a href="http://www.whatsapp.com/" title="WhatsApp website"><strong>WhatsApp</strong></a> does a pretty good job at being a texting substitute: It runs in the background on Nokia, Android, iPhone or Blackberry smartphones, and allows one to <strong>send and receive unlimited SMS-like messages</strong> via one’s dataplan to other WhatsApp users. Just like texting, it only requires telephone numbers, so directly after installation, one sees a list of all one’s WhatsApp-running contacts (from the phone’s database). Big advantage over for example BlackBerry BBM (ping) is that WhatsApp runs on many more telephones. In short: Try it, you might like it!</li>
<li>On the theme of sticking it to the man (and when I say “man” I mean “telephone company”), I recently acquired a <a href="http://www.cisco.com/en/US/products/ps10027/index.html" title="Cisco SPA3102"><strong>Cisco SPA3102 Voice Gateway</strong></a> (used to be Sipura, then Linksys). It’s a tiny little box that sits in-between your broadband connection (ADSL or cable modem) and house telephone and, if configured correctly, routes all telephone calls via SIP (voice-over-ip) providers. In short: Seriously cheap phone calls via internet, telephone company never even sees you and hence can’t really bill you. The only problem is that this little box has the most complex configuration interface I’ve ever seen. There must be at least a few hundred configuration settings, and if you get any one of them wrong, your phone system simply stops working. I’ve written up what you need to know at my <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/02/05/sipura-linksys-cisco-spa3102-voice-gateway-in-the-netherlands/" title="SPA3102 netherlands setup guide at vxlabs.com">Even Nerdier Blog</a>.</li>
<li>What’s the deal with <strong>hiking boots and engineers</strong>? Hiking boots are great for hiking, but wearing them to work (or far worse, to a social event) must be <em>the</em> most extreme way of showing your asymptotic support of function over form. I have to admit that I myself have sinned before, but usually I have a good excuse, such as that storm outside. There are some people however (and the matching hiking boots worn by in-love engineers / nerds are the absolute worst) that don’t seem to understand that form and function do need to be in some form of balance for the world to function and for me to maintain my non-nauseous state.</li>
<li>It is important to note that Timberland boots strike this balance just perfectly, as you can see below:

  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  <figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg">
      <img
          
              
              src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/timberland.jpg"
          
              alt="This is what form and function look like when they&#39;re in perfect balance."/> </a><figcaption>
              <p>This is what form and function look like when they're in perfect balance.</p>
          </figcaption>
  </figure>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To conclude this post, I’d like to summarise a <a href="http://lifehacker.com/5751875/five-traits-low+stress-happy-work-cultures-have-in-common" title="lifehacker summary of Buettner's book">lifehacker summary</a> of Dan Buettner’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Thrive-Finding-Happiness-Blue-Zones/dp/1426205155/" title="amazon link to buettner's book">book</a> on the factors that play a role in the happiness of people living in the world’s “blue zones” (countries / regions where people live long and contented lives): 1. work less, 2. keep your commute as short as possible, 3. have regular vacations, 4. socialise with your colleagues and finally, 5. make sure you work for a good boss.</p>
<p>No big surprises there, but sometimes it’s nice being reminded of the stuff we should never have forgotten in the first place.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Future is Sick [Weekly Head Voices #36]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/23/the-future-is-sick-weekly-head-voices-36/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2011 21:12:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2011/01/23/the-future-is-sick-weekly-head-voices-36/</guid><description>Post summary: Conference, VXLabs, SIP, boots, backyard philosophy on you the consumer, dramatic reading. Read on for more!
Just before the weekend I spent two days at the Dutch Bio-Medical Engineering Conference in Egmond aan Zee, in a ginormous seaside hotel. Probably because I attempted to keep up with the young ones during their nightly escapades, I’m currently dealing quite badly with a serious cold, which is why this is the first sick blog post of 2011. Besides all those germs, I also brought you this photo of said seaside right after sunset: Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>Post summary: Conference, VXLabs, SIP, boots, backyard philosophy on you the consumer, dramatic reading. Read on for more!</em></p>
<p>Just before the weekend I spent two days at the Dutch Bio-Medical Engineering Conference in Egmond aan Zee, in a ginormous seaside hotel. Probably because I attempted to keep up with the young ones during their nightly escapades, I’m currently dealing quite badly with a serious cold, which is why this is the first sick blog post of 2011.  Besides all those germs, I also brought you this photo of said seaside right after sunset:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/egmond_aan_zee_bme2011.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/egmond_aan_zee_bme2011.jpg"
        
            alt="Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Sunset on the Egmond aan Zee beach. Gorgeous, innit? There’s even a dude walking on the beach so that you can wax all pensive.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>The conference was an energetic and motivating affair, at which yours truly even got to chair a session, during which I tried, in spite of not getting to bed all that early the night before, to Keep Things Extremely Punctual As Well As Mildly Entertaining. I succeeded in the former, you’ll have to ask the audience about the latter.</p>
<p>The absolute highlight, for me at least, was the capstone on Friday by <a href="https://depts.washington.edu/biointel/" title="Prof. Satava's website">Professor Richard Satava</a>, a surgeon with an amazing vision of the future. Bordering on science fiction but for a large part backed by his own and other groups’ research, his superbly delivered presentation touched on surgical operating rooms completely staffed by robots (some elements remotely controlled by a surgeon), cell engineering, surgery robots that heal troops at the scene of the crime (hehe), genetic engineering, cloning and a healthy dash of trans-humanism. By the end the whole room was collectively straining at the leash to go and genetically upgrade anything and anyone they could find. With a room full of BME researchers, that’s more dangerous than it sounds. :)</p>
<p>Other note-worthy items of the past two weeks can be summarised in the following neat bullet list:</p>
<ul>
<li>I’ve started a new blog, called VXLabs, for matters that are too nerdy even for this blog. If you’re interested, you can start by reading the <a href="http://vxlabs.com/2011/01/22/htc-desire-z-an-in-depth-and-nerdy-review/" title="in-depth and nerdy review of the HTC Desire Z at VXLabs">HTC Desire Z (my lovely new smartphone) review</a> I’ve recently gotten around to writing. If you’re nerdy enough, you might consider subscribing VXLabs as well!</li>
<li>There are far cheaper ways than Skype to call telephones around the world. With SIP software, such as SIPDroid on Android, you can use cheap SIP servers that even offer free calls to many destinations. See <a href="http://www.backsla.sh/betamax" title="table of betamax providers">this page</a> for a list of just the betamax (German VOIP company) providers and the free countries that they support.</li>
<li>I was approached by a company producing Ugg-like boots to review their boots, get a free pair in the process, and get a good deal for my readers. This is probably because I went on about those BEAUTIFUL Timberland boots in one of my previous posts. Although I was flattered that the gentleman in question thought my widely-read (haha) opinion would be good for his brand and he called this a <em>fashion blog</em> (!!), I declined, stating that my readership probably is more into Timberlands than Uggs. That’s true, readership? Right?!</li>
<li><strong>Micro Backyard Philosophy</strong>: After one of those late nights refreshing my Twitter, Facebook, Google Reader and GMail for the Nth time, I got to thinking about how the internet sometimes turns us into 100% consumers, leaving <strong>no room for creativity</strong>. It’s insidious, because we believe that the internet will give us exactly what we crave if we just know how to search for it, and that it should do so with that next press on the refresh button, when in fact this is hardly ever the case, especially when that which you crave is in fact to create. Remember this the next time it’s getting late and you think Just One More Refresh. Don’t push that button. <strong>Sit back and think about what you really want to do</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it boys and girls, thank you very much for reading this far! You go and have yourselves a fabulous and especially creative week. If you get lonely waiting for the next edition of the Weekly Head Voices, marvel at this dramatic reading of a bad user game review, creativity at its finest:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4Z2Z23SAFVA?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>An Inside Job. [Weekly Head Voices #33]</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2010 14:10:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/11/21/an-inside-job-weekly-head-voices-33/</guid><description>Hiatus: temporarily over.
My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to that, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am. :)</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hiatus: temporarily over.</p>
<p>My sleeping patterns are not quite what they used to be, mostly due to the latest manifestation of our little gene pool over here. Added to that, I’ve been really busy. Added to <em>that</em>, work has been throwing unnecessary curve-balls that have done their part in keeping me (pre)-occupied. In the end, a dash of perspective, several extremely wise friends and a generally sunny predisposition go a really long way, so here I am. :)</p>
<p>In this post, I’m going to touch upon the highlights of the past seven weeks (40 to 46) and I’m going to do so with bullets, seeing as I’m in a bullety-kind of mood.</p>
<ul>
<li>I spent a week in Stellenbosch teaching Information Visualisation! Read all about it in <a href="/2010/11/21/teaching-infovis-in-stellenbosch/" title="stbvis2010 blog post">this special blog post</a>.</li>
<li>The week after that my mom came to visit us. She really has the best genes.</li>
<li>I met my new work laptop: A Dell Latitude E6410 with Core i5 M540 2.53GHz CPU, 4G ram, 500G HDD, NVidia NVS 3100m GPU with 512 MB video mem. It’s a 14″ latop (15.4″ is a completely useless format, flame me in the comments), but due to the materials used quite heavy. I like it!</li>
<li>Another one of our STW NIG research proposals has been granted. I conceived and developed this one together with colleagues from the LUMC Departments of Anatomy, of Surgery and of Orthopaedics. The title is <em>High-definition Atlas-based surgical planning for Pelvic Surgery</em> and we get to combine high-resolution human histology, mega-volume rendering, , biomechanical modelling and surgical simulation. With this grant we can appoint two more Ph.D. students (one in my group, one at the LUMC) for four years to work on this!!</li>
<li>The week after that I went to Salt Lake City (Utah, US and A) to attend the conference previously known as <a href="http://vis.computer.org/VisWeek2010/" title="IEEE VisWeek 2010 website">IEEE Visualization</a>. It was AWESOME! (blog post half-written, will soon publish).</li>
<li>The week after that I had a really cool dream: I was playing high-speed catch with a bunch of people outside. The ball was randomly changing shape between rock, papers and scissors. If you wanted to catch it, you didn’t only have to be at the right place at the right time, but your hand also had to be in the right complementary configuration to catch the shape-shifting ball.</li>
<li>Now that we’re talking about dreams: <em>I finally saw <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1375666/" title="IMDB page for Inception">Inception</a> and was completely blown away.</em> It’s not about being complicated, it’s about being a well-told story and a fantastically filmed movie. What I positively adored, is the fact that <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan" title="Wikipedia page about Christopher Nolan">Nolan</a> doesn’t require much: He only needs you to believe that dreams can be shared, without giving away too many of the details of the mechanism, and then builds a marvellous story on that canvas. My absolute favourite scene was the waking up on the plane, just before the landing, almost at the end of the film. I loved the way in which the characters looked at each other, and the possible interpretations of their expressions.</li>
<li>On the topic of the Underworld gig in the Heineken Music Hall: I hope I have my voice back before my morning lecture tomorrow morning. Thank you Fantastic Friends!</li>
</ul>
<p>That’s it kids. If you’ve come this far, you’re now mostly up to date. Please leave me a comment, it’s good for my serotonin! I hope you have a great week. To get you off to a  good start, here’s a music video showing what an infectious idea could look like…</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<div class="embed-vimeo" style="text-align: center;">
<iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="473" mozallowfullscreen="" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/15391189" webkitallowfullscreen="" width="840"></iframe>
</div>
</div>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #18: Refactor my dogfood.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/21/weekly-head-voices-18-refactor-my-dogfood/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2010 16:25:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/21/weekly-head-voices-18-refactor-my-dogfood/</guid><description>Welcome all, to this, the 18th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I discuss a number of issues that mostly have nothing specific to do with the 11th week of 2010, but which might or might not have crossed my mind during that time! Issues include good news on the EuroVis 2010 front, a new edition of the Head Voices Review featuring my completely unexpected stay in a 7 Tesla MRI scanner (as a test subject, of course) and finally some nerdy backyard philosophy dealing with the well-known itch to Rewrite Everything From Scratch, Because What’s There Now Sucks.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome all, to this, the 18th edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I discuss a number of issues that mostly have nothing specific to do with the 11th week of 2010, but which might or might not have crossed my mind during that time! Issues include good news on the EuroVis 2010 front, a new edition of the Head Voices Review featuring my completely unexpected stay in a 7 Tesla MRI scanner (as a test subject, of course)  and finally some nerdy backyard philosophy dealing with the well-known itch to Rewrite Everything From Scratch, Because What’s There Now Sucks.</p>
<p>First, because I have no other visual element for this week’s post, and  because I am, as you might have noticed, a method blogger, I present you with probably the best <a href="http://chatroulette.com/" title="chatroulette website">chatroulette.com</a> improv I’ve ever seen so far. For those of you who have been completely asleep the past few weeks, chatroulette is a new site that’s been taking the interwebs by storm. The site pairs up random strangers for webcam chats. One is allowed to move to the next random stranger with the click of a buttom (resulting in the new English verb <a href="http://www.kk.org/thetechnium/archives/2010/02/nexted.php" title="Kevin Kelly's blog post on nexting">“to next”</a> someone..). Random hilarity (and often perversity) ensues! Here’s that mostly SFW and brilliant piano improv:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JTwJetox_tU?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p><em>(The original video had to be pulled, after 4 million views, due to some YouTube issues. Merton, pianist, has posted this new version. Thanks to</em> <a href="http://fpixel.wordpress.com/" title="Link to Francois' photography site"><em>Francois</em></a> <em>for the heads-up!)</em></p>
<p>Back to business, we have just heard the great news that our two <a href="http://eurovis2010.labri.fr/" title="eurovis 2010 website">EuroVis 2010</a> submissions have been finally accepted for publication.  The articles are:</p>
<blockquote>
<ol>
<li>S. Busking, C.P. Botha, and F.H. Post, <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Busking2010" title="Link to Stef's EuroVis 2010 paper page (fulltext available)">“Dynamic Multi-View Exploration of Shape Spaces,”</a> <em>Computer Graphics Forum</em>, 2010.</li>
<li>P.R. Krekel, E.R. Valstar, J. de Groot, F.H. Post, R.G. Nelissen, and C.P. Botha, <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Krekel2010a" title="Link to Krekel EuroVis 2010 Visual Analysis of Human Motion paper">“Visual Analysis of Multi-Joint Kinematic Data,”</a> <em>Computer Graphics Forum</em>, 2010.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Fantastic work you first authors you! Remember people: YOU HAVE TO CITE THESE SOON, AND YOU HAVE TO CITE THEM OFTEN! This also means that a number of us will be going to Bordeaux in June (I can imagine worse places to go to in June) to mingle with other scientists and to drink really good red wine.</p>
<p>That good news brings us to the influential WHV feature, the <strong>Head Voices Review</strong>! (My TPN is still working on the new jingle.  Hopefully it’ll be on time for our joint Vodka review feature.) In this edition, I’ll be reviewing the Philips 7 Tesla MRI scanner and the JBL Duet-200 computer speakers.</p>
<p>On Friday, I unexpectedly had the pleasure of trying out a state-of-the-art 7 Tesla Philips MRI scanner, as a test subject. I can report that the bore, although small, is quite comfortable. However, test subjects with claustrophobic tendencies should probably look elsewhere.  Scanning can be quite noisy, especially when a diffusion weighted imaging protocol is applied that involves scanning in 162 different gradient directions (to study the structural connectivity in my brain). However, the music that gets piped in between scanning sessions more than makes up. After scanning, it was scientifically confirmed that there is indeed a brain housed in my skull, an observation that pleasantly surprised me. Soon I hope to be able to post visualisations, made by one of our MedVis ninjas, of the structural connections in my brain.</p>
<p>All in all, if you have a few million euros lying around, this piece of kit is highly recommended.  To summarise:</p>
<ul>
<li>Philips 7T MRI: AWESOME.</li>
</ul>
<p>In a <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/03/09/weekly-head-voices-16-go-go-gadget/" title="previous review of the Logitechh S3-30 speakes">previous review</a>, I was quite negative about the Logitech S3-30 speakers, for a large part due to the absolute mess of cables that it comes with. This past week I took delivery of the new <a href="http://www.amazon.com/JBL-DUET-200BLKV-Performance-Loudspeaker-Multimedia/dp/B0017XO2R6" title="JBL DUET-200 on amazon">JBL Duet-200</a> speakers I ordered, for the grand amount of 30 eurobucks, to replace it. The JBL is a single unit containing two speakers, something which might be seen as a drawback, but which I consider an advantage. In spite of its compact appearance, it packs quite a base and more than sufficient volume.  In addition, there are exactly two (2) cables: One for the power supply, and one for the audio. I can only hope that Logitech contracts JBL on their next PC speaker product design. My only (minor) gripe is that the JBL-supplied audio cable is only about 40cm long. All in all:</p>
<ul>
<li>JBL Duet-200 at € 30 price-point: AWESOME.</li>
</ul>
<p>MRI scanners and PC speakers: No product too big, no product too small for the Head Voices Review!</p>
<p>Finally, it’s time for some backyard philosophy.  This week, it’s a brief point of really nerdy philosophy, although I think the principles apply to some non-nerdy activities as well. Software developers, as well as many other engineering types, often reach a point during working on a project, when they have a hard-to-control urge to trash the whole thing and start from scratch.  There is usually a very strong belief that the project / software / product can be designed much better by starting from scratch.</p>
<p>It turns out that this is an insidious and mostly incorrect belief, for a large part due to all the knowledge present in the existing “ugly” product that will get thrown out. Engineers easily underestimate the importance of this knowledge. It turns out, much as we don’t like to hear this, that <strong>refactoring</strong> is, nine times out of ten, a far better answer than rewriting from scratch. Experienced developers know this, and are <em>mostly</em> able to suppress the rewrite from scratch itch.</p>
<p>Joel Spolsky wrote a <a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000069.html" title="Joel Spolsky on why you shouldn't rewrite software">really good essay</a> on this phenomenon. Go read it!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #17: The Eternal Foreigner.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/14/weekly-head-voices-17-the-eternal-foreigner/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2010 22:18:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/14/weekly-head-voices-17-the-eternal-foreigner/</guid><description>In this edition, looking back on the 10th week of 2010, I report briefly on the lack of blog-worthy events in my life, noting that my life is undoubtedly extremely exciting, just not always in that special blog-worthy way, before concluding with some backyard psycho-philosophy on my perception of the greenness of grass as a function of its distance from the observer. Skip to just after the YouTube clip if you want to get right to the backyard part of this blog.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this edition, looking back on the 10th week of 2010, I report briefly on the lack of blog-worthy events in my life, noting that my life is undoubtedly extremely exciting, just not always in that special blog-worthy way, before concluding with some backyard psycho-philosophy on my perception of the greenness of grass as a function of its distance from the observer.  Skip to just after the YouTube clip if you want to get right to the backyard part of this blog.</p>
<p>Work-wise, last week was good for 2 hours of lecture preparation, 3 hours of lecturing, 12 hours of meetings, including an inspiring visit to Real Scientists at the EMC, and finally some quality time catching a monday night paper deadline in the nick of time with one of our MedVis Ninjas, whom I’m coincidentally extremely proud of at the moment.  I completed only 16 GTD tasks, down 6 from last week.</p>
<p>Besides not having hot water for two days due to my boiler’s operating system (yes, it has a frikking operating system) refusing to switch on the heat exchanger, forcing me to take a bath in 15 litres of hot water boiled, cowboy style, on the stove, and also experiencing first-hand the surprisingly high actual efficiency of my house’s Super Environmentally Friendly heat-retention system (everything is insulated, air is mechanically circulated at about 100 cubic metres per hour, extra heat exchanger transfers warmth from expelled air to fresh injected air) which managed to keep the internal temperature at a comfortable 18 C (outside between 1 and 8 C) without any hot water in the radiators, and also managing to write one of the longest sentences in a blog post since last Tuesday, the only other blog-worthy artifact I have to offer you is this YouTube screencast I made the other day, demonstrating how to perform a rudimentary segmentation on DICOM CT data and extract STL surface meshes using DeVIDE:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_PtTpRz3aU8?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>You can add this to your growing list of natural non-ingestible sleep medicine.</p>
<p>Last week I heard that I’d passed my <a href="http://www.inburgeren.nl/inburgeraar/korte_vrijstellingstoets/korte_vrijstellingstoets.asp" title="link to KVT info">Korte Vrijstellingstoets</a>. This is a test that you, foreigner in The Netherlands, can take to demonstrate that you have sufficient knowledge of Dutch language and culture and thus don’t have to take bunches of other compulsory courses and/or exams that are far more time-consuming. This is not such a significant happening, were it not for the fact that it’s another very concrete symbol of my growing affinity with and attachment to this little patch of the planet. I can hardly avoid thinking seriously about the future of this relationship.</p>
<p>Further, this weekend I missed the wedding of one my best friends due to the niggling matter of 10000 kilometres conspiring with sundry but unavoidable work-related constraints. I would <em>really</em> have loved to be there… There will always be drawbacks, no matter where you choose to live. Especially if you choose for the excitement of a country-skipping adventure and do so for any significant length of time, you will always long for That Other Place, that special coordinate that you currently can’t occupy, and the people associated with it.  Even if you go back to where you started, irrevocably tainted with a strange culture, you don’t quite fit in and long for your acquired home. The grass is and will remain greener on the other side.</p>
<p>I had the good fortune of meeting a wise and well-spoken French man shortly after starting my European adventure. This man, who had done quite some country skipping, finally ending up in Lugano (one can end up in worse places than Lugano), introduced me to the concept of the Eternal Foreigner. This is what one becomes when one simply <em>embraces</em> the idea that, once having moved country and culture, one can never ever be at Home again. Instead of struggling to blend in, struggling to be more like one’s neighbour, or struggling to retain and manifest some warped version of one’s own culture in an environment where it’s doomed to wilt, simply accept Being From Elsewhere.</p>
<p>The Eternal Foreigner misses Home, but smiles, and is at peace.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #16: Go Go Gadget!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/09/weekly-head-voices-16-go-go-gadget/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2010 22:11:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/03/09/weekly-head-voices-16-go-go-gadget/</guid><description>This post is dedicated to my man Helmut in Vienna. Your appreciation is much appreciated!
In this edition, I report on my productivity and activities of the past week, extol the time-saving virtues of iGoogle and conclude with a new WHV feature: The Head Voices Review! Unfortunately, due to a chronic lack of sleep, there will be no backyard philosophical contribution. We hope to be back on track for the next edition.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p><em>This post is dedicated to my man Helmut in Vienna.  Your appreciation is much appreciated!</em></p>
<p>In this edition, I report on my productivity and activities of the past week,  extol the time-saving virtues of iGoogle and conclude with a new WHV feature: The Head Voices Review!  Unfortunately, due to a chronic lack of sleep, there will be no backyard philosophical contribution.  We hope to be back on track for the next edition.</p>
<p>During week 9 of 2010, the temporal context of the sixteenth edition of the Weekly Head Voices, I spent 2 hours preparing for lectures, 3 hours lecturing and 12 hours in scheduled meetings.  I spent a significant amount of time assisting five of our MedVis Ninjas shepherding papers out the door, so now you have to cross your fingers that we get 100% accept rate, else the Ninjas get <em>really</em> angry.  Counting up to the weekend, and without any cheating, I completed 22 GTD tasks, again one task more than last week.  If this continues, I will eventually attain infinite productivity, so you better watch out, ok?</p>
<p>Noteworthy happenings include two Skype Video meetings, which worked really well and saved me a significant amout of travel time. These meetings would be even better if my correspondents would invest in webcams, allowing me to look at more than just my own face during the discussion. In other news, I’ve been spending even more time futzing around with processing, resulting in a <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/03/04/processing-gsvideo-nyartoolkit-on-linux-x86_64/" title="blog post: installing processing +gsvideo + nyartoolkit on linux x86_64">first blog post detailing the installation of said library with video capture and augmented reality support on 64 bit Linux machines</a>.</p>
<p>The main topic of this post is gadgets. I’ll be talking about two kinds of gadgets, so first I’d like to start with a screenshot of my iGoogle:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/igoogle-screenshot-anon.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/igoogle-screenshot-anon-1024x660.jpg"
        
            alt="iGoogle your twitter."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>iGoogle your twitter.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>I’ve been aware of iGoogle, and used it as a poor man’s aggregator before getting addicted to Google Reader, but never really appreciated the possibilities.  In short, you can add all kinds of web applications, called <em>gadgets</em>, to any number of tabs (each tab is a page), thus mixing and matching for example the social networking websites you use on one single web page.  Because I’d recently been wasting far too much time switching between twitter, facebook (everytime someone mentions facebook, I somehow reflexively and compulsively open the site, hence wasting more precious minutes of my life, which at my advanced age is no small matter), gmail and compulsive news checking, I decided to compress my time wasting into a single page visit. So far, it seems to be saving me a number of minutes every day, minutes that I’m saving for later…</p>
<p>Finally, it pleases me greatly to be able to introduce a new feature on the WHV: <strong>The Head Voices Review!</strong> [As soon as my TPN completely masters Ableton, I’m hoping he’ll make me a nice theme song that I can insert here.] Some of you might know that this blog has a <em>rich</em> history in reviewing gadgets. See for example <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2006/02/10/news-on-the-audio-front/" title="post where I discuss two headsets">this post</a> where, after weeks of investigation, I posted an <em>in-depth</em> review of not one, but TWO cheap-skate headphones.  To summarise:</p>
<ul>
<li>Sennheiser PX20: SUCKS.</li>
<li>Philips HP-200: AWESOME.</li>
</ul>
<p>To kick off this first edition, I’m going to discuss three more computer audio gadgets.  First off, the Logitech S3-30 2.1 (that means stereo speakers with sub-woofer to my non-audiophile readers) computer speaker set with built-in amplifier.  I’ve used these extensively for five years now (purely for the purposes of reviewing them of course) and have set out my conclusions in the table below:</p>
<ul>
<li>Logitech S3-30: SUCKS BADLY.</li>
</ul>
<p>I base my conclusion on the sub-par design of these speakers, especially in terms of the cabling.  Below is an <em>artist’s</em> rendition of the cable design for these speakers:










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/logitech_s3-30_sketch-1024.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/logitech_s3-30_sketch-1024-933x1024.jpg"
        
            alt="Artist’s rendition of Logitech S3-30 speaker set cable design. Note the bird’s nests."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Artist’s rendition of Logitech S3-30 speaker set cable design. Note the bird’s nests.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>As you can see, it’s as if the engineers had been challenged to see how much cable they could waste in producing these speakers, and as a side-challenge, how they could ensure that any desk carrying these speakers would instantly turn into an unmanageable mess of cables in various states of entanglement.  Why why why didn’t they read <a href="http://www.livescience.com/strangenews/071003-knots-form.html" title="why knots form">this really important paper</a>?</p>
<p>I have recently ordered the <a href="http://www.amazon.com/JBL-DUET-200BLKV-Performance-Loudspeaker-Multimedia/dp/B0017XO2R6" title="jbl duet-200">JBL Duet 200</a> to replace the S3-30.  After at least five more years of extensive testing, I will document its performance in a future Head Voices Review.</p>
<p>On the topic of Logitech, a number of my screencasts up to now have been <em>performed</em> using a <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Logitech-Analog-Desktop-Stick-Microphone/dp/B00097HPHK" title="Link to amazon page on the logitech analog desktop microphone with 3.5mm jack plug.">Logitech Analog Desktop Microphone with 3.5mm jack plug</a>, purchased especially for that purpose.  Now that I’ve also purchased the quite affordable (6 bucks for the <em>whole</em> headset, that means headphone AND microphone!) yet very stylish <a href="http://www.sweex.com/nl/assortiment/sound-vision/headsets/HM400" title="Sweex HM400 headset">Sweex HM400 headset</a>, also for recording screencasts, I can present the following comparative review:</p>
<ul>
<li>Logitech Analog Desktop Microphone with 3.mm jack plug: SUCKS.</li>
<li>Sweex HM400 headset: AWESOME.  Wait till you hear my deep baritone narrating the next screencast.  I expect that it should sound almost exactly like this:</li>
</ul>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/x0I6mhZ5wMw?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Err, that’s it for the first edition of the Head Voices Review! I don’t think that you have to worry too much about the next edition arriving anytime soon.  Here at HVR headquarters we take our sweet time, as we pride ourselves in jumping to <em>all</em> of the wrong conclusions, <em>all</em> of the time.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #15: Auto-tune my cloud.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/28/weekly-head-voices-15-auto-tune-my-cloud/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2010 15:50:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/28/weekly-head-voices-15-auto-tune-my-cloud/</guid><description>In this 15th edition of my weekly head voices, I move yet more of my life into the cloud, discover (years after everyone else) the delightful auto-tune internet meme and finally go all backyard-psychological whilst staring into the distance, obviously defocused, and waxing on about the purpose of this weblog.
Before continuing, you might like to watch this clip explaining why you shall build a turtle fence (I’ll get back to the clip after my dropbox story):</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this 15th edition of my weekly head voices, I move yet more of my life into the cloud, discover (years after everyone else) the delightful auto-tune internet meme and finally go all backyard-psychological whilst staring into the distance, obviously defocused, and waxing on about the purpose of this weblog.</p>
<p>Before continuing, you might like to watch this clip explaining why you shall build a turtle fence (I’ll get back to the clip after my dropbox story):</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qizNQKzatXA?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Last week I completed, you guessed it, 21 GTD tasks spread over 10 projects. Once again, one more task than last week. The question is thus not <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em> I’m going to have to disappoint you. :)  Worth mentioning on the miscellany front is that I’ve started playing around with <a href="http://processing.org/" title="processing.org website">processing</a>, a fantastic little system for programming visual effects and interaction, in preparation for a new first year course. My goal is to get the students irrevocably addicted to the coolness that is media processing! I’ll keep you up to date…</p>
<p>In a <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2010/02/14/weekly-head-voices-13-so-you-want-to-sue-me/" title="previous WHV dropbox mention">previous post</a>, I was quite enthusiastic about Dropbox and its possibilities for collaboration. As some of you might now, I really like this whole living-in-the-cloud idea: I use GMail, Google Calendar and Google Documents quite extensively and I’m even paying for extra storage with the big G.  So, during the past week, I decided to bite the bullet some more and to move 12G more of my data right into the cloud, courtesy of a 50G Dropbox Pro account.  Up to now, I had a ridiculously complex synchronisation system keeping various subsets of my data up to date between a netbook, a laptop and three different servers. At the core of this system was <a href="http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/unison/" title="Link to unison file sync tool.">unison</a>, a brilliant multi-way open source synchronisation tool. In spite of this system mostly working, its complexity and the starkly contrasting It-Just-Works nature of Dropbox convinced me to give the simple solution a shot.</p>
<p>So far I can only report that I remain impressed: At one stage I manually copied a complete dropbox (12Gigs) from one already synced machine to a fresh target machine and started the Dropbox software on the target. It politely asked:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There is already a folder in your home folder called Dropbox. Do you want to merge all the existing files in that folder into your dropbox?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>After clicking on the “HELL YEAH!” button (that’s how it felt, ok), the software went on indexing for a minute or two and then correctly claimed that everything was nicely synced up. Very much understated robustness, kudos to the developers. I’m going to test-drive this whole business for one month, and then let you know whether it’s going to be  a permanent fixture in my cloud-home.</p>
<p>Still wondering why you should build a turtle fence? Well, you can blame the Auto-Tune internet meme. Very shortly, auto-tune is an audio effect that corrects one voice to be perfectly in tune with backing music. In other words, a vocalist who can’t sing is in fact no problem at all, computer will fix! Initially it was used quite sparingly and its application was even sometimes kept a secret, until artists such as Cher and especially <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=avaSdC0QOUM&amp;feature=channel" title="My favourite T-Pain clip: I'm on a boat!">T-Pain</a> turned it into an art form, in fact exaggerating the effect until it gave a decidedly unsubtle robotic voice effect. The effect has become so famous that it now gets to call itself an internet meme and is often parodied.  The turtle clip above is just one of a whole series (auto-tune the news, see them all!). In the clip below, internet scientists *ahem*, including the well-known Professor Weird Al Yankovic, take an in-depth look at this phenomenon:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fYzv-AVi78E?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>Finally, back to the purpose of this weblog… Good blogs all seem to have some central theme, such as <a href="http://francoism.wordpress.com/" title="francoism's photography blog">photography</a>, environmental issues, science or pokemon. I seem to recall that I’d also seen this in more than one “how to become an A-list blogger” guides.  I don’t find it hard to believe that this is very important.  However, this blog has never had a central theme, it’s always been me blabbing about the various things that I find blab-worthy.  I’ve never been able to come up with something better, and it was definitely not for lack of trying.  The Weekly Head Voices, by focusing my blabbing into slightly more coherent episodes, have finally helped me to come to a conclusion.  Besides acting as a creative outlet, sitting down every week and carefully externalising a specific subset of my experiences with the express purpose of having it read by a small number of people, is an important ritual during which I am forced to distance myself from the events of the week, and to self-reflect.  By formally concluding the previous period in this way, one has the mental room to manoeuvre in preparation for the next. If you by any chance find any of it entertaining, or at least you just can’t look away, it’s a win-win situation!</p>
<p>In other words: Theme-schmeme! The voices in my head will continue to be the many and various topics of this weblog, thank you very much. :)</p>
<p>Have a great week kids!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #14: My Week Was A Wormhole.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/21/weekly-head-voices-14-my-week-was-a-wormhole/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Feb 2010 18:25:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/21/weekly-head-voices-14-my-week-was-a-wormhole/</guid><description>In this week’s post, documenting the 7th week of 2010, I wonder about perceived business, mention two of our most recent open source releases and give to you, my readers, two screencasts about the DRE, in addition probably highly effective in the treatment of insomnia. Screenshot of the FoBVis system. This is just one of our many attempts to take over the world, subtly.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this week’s post, documenting the 7th week of 2010, I wonder about perceived business, mention two of our most recent open source releases and give to you, my readers, two screencasts about the DRE, in addition probably highly effective in the treatment of insomnia.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/fobvis1.jpg">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/fobvis1.jpg"
        
            alt="Screenshot of the FoBVis system. This is just one of our many attempts to take over the world, subtly."/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Screenshot of the FoBVis system. This is just one of our many attempts to take over the world, subtly.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>Just before bedtime on Monday, I had still managed to make a note in my special top-secret Weekly Head Voices journal.  I usually do this every day to make sure I don’t forget anything by the weekend, when I usually have some time to write these posts.  Thursday night’s entry simply says “WTF, where did my week go?!” — There had been no other entries since Monday. I’m still not quite sure why it felt that way, as my breakdown of activities is similar to that of the previous week: 2 hours of lecture preparation, 3 hours of lecturing, 15 hours of scheduled meetings and 20 tasks completed (one more than last week!!) across 10 projects. Perhaps those four extra hours of meetings don’t scale linearly in the amount of business they cause, due to the number of extra context switches that they bring. I have to add that a number of truly exciting projects are brewing, but I can’t say more about them until I can say more about them, if you know what I mean.</p>
<p>We (The Group, of course) recently released two new open source software projects:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://fobvis.googlecode.com/" title="FoBVis project site">FoBVis</a> is a tool for the real-time acquisition and visualisation of human motion: Currently it supports the Flock-of-Birds electromagnetic acquisition system, we are currently working to integrate Optotrak optical tracking system. We should also shortly have a version of the <a href="http://code.google.com/p/devide/wiki/HelpDRE" title="You can use the DRE to run stuff, including the FoBVis.">DRE</a> that can run the FoBVis on YOUR computer as well.</li>
<li><a href="http://histovis.googlecode.com/" title="HistoVis project site">HistoVis</a> is a client-server system for the visualisation of large collections of (registered) histological sections.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s all very exciting that more products of our research are entering the big bad outside world!  The FoBVis is already being actively used by the LUMC Laboratory for Motion Analysis (we hope that more labs will start using this soon), and HistoVis will soon go live from the <a href="http://visible-orbit.nl/" title="Visible Orbit website">visible-orbit.nl server</a>. Of course these have both been released under the new BSD license, as the GPL sucks.</p>
<p>Screencasts: Video Performance Art of the Nerdily Inclined. That’s where one makes a recording of one’s computer screen whilst demonstrating some or other procedure, optionally narrated by oneself, and then proceeds to upload said recording (called a screencast) to YouTube or similar. See <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/05/10/recording-screencasts-on-windows-with-free-software/" title="Instructions on creating screencasts in Windows.">a previous post of mine</a> for one possible (and free) way of doing this on Windows. This weekend I produced and uploaded two such pieces, both demonstrating aspects of the DeVIDE Runtime Environment, or <a href="http://code.google.com/p/devide/wiki/HelpDRE" title="DRE help page">DRE</a>, that paradoxically do NOT involve DeVIDE itself. Especially the second is really soothing, one could even say mildly sleep-inducing.  I just say: <a data-rel="lightbox-video-0" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xEbYw73y3pM" title="First sleep-inducing DRE screencast.">(1) Try</a> <a data-rel="lightbox-video-1" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7FwPw9qlsms" title="Second sleep-inducing DRE screencast.">(2) it</a>.</p>
<p>To conclude, I give you a track from the new Massive Attack album Heligoland, called Paradise Circus. It should make your brain sit and scratch its chin stubble, not unlike the usual dose of backyard philosophy:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jEgX64n3T7g?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #13: So you want to sue me?!</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/14/weekly-head-voices-13-so-you-want-to-sue-me/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2010 14:00:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/14/weekly-head-voices-13-so-you-want-to-sue-me/</guid><description>In this post, I talk about our latest EuroVis news, give a quick break-down of my activities of the past week whilst turning my productivity glut into a game, sing an ode to DropBox, get threatened with a lawsuit (again) and impart, as per usual, some applied backyard philosophy. All hail the beautiful EuroVis 2010 logo!
To kick start this blog post, allow me to get this off my chest: BOTH Stef Busking’s paper on the and Peter Krekel’s paper on the were conditionally accepted for EuroVis 2010! There’s some hard work ahead to get the papers ready for the final round, but this conditional acceptance (70% of submitted papers were rejected) is a great achievement. You may send them your webcammed applause and adoration.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In this post, I talk about our latest EuroVis news, give a quick break-down of my activities of the past week whilst turning my productivity glut into a game, sing an ode to DropBox, get threatened with a lawsuit (again) and impart, as per usual, some applied backyard philosophy.










<figure><a href="/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/EuroVisLogoM2.png">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/EuroVisLogoM2.png"
        
            alt="All hail the beautiful EuroVis 2010 logo!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>All hail the beautiful EuroVis 2010 logo!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>
<p>To kick start this blog post, allow me to get this off my chest: BOTH Stef Busking’s paper on the <censored> and Peter Krekel’s paper on the <censored> were conditionally accepted for EuroVis 2010! There’s some hard work ahead to get the papers ready for the final round, but this conditional acceptance (70% of submitted papers were rejected) is a great achievement. You may send them your webcammed applause and adoration.</p>
<p>During the past week, the 6th of 2010, I did 2 hours of lecture preparation, 3 hours of straight lecturing, 4 hours of demonstrations and 11 hours of scheduled meetings, most of them quite energising. According to my GTD system, I also completed 19 tasks spread over 11 projects. I’m mentioning this here, as I want to increase my weekly task completion count, and posting this on my blog turns it into a weird kind of game. Once again, you are allowed, no you’re encouraged, to boo and hiss at the appropriate moments.</p>
<p>I also finally got around to updating our research group’s publications listing scripts to generate per-paper pages, so that we’ll henceforth have a (hopefully) attractive webpage to go with each published paper. See <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/2009" title="listing of 2009 papers">this</a> for an example of the per-year listing, and <a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Krekel2010" title="example per-paper page">this</a> for an example of such a paper page.<figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-752" class="wp-caption aligncenter" id="attachment_752" style="width: 354px"></p>










<figure><a href="http://graphics.tudelft.nl/Publications/Krekel2010">
    <img
        
            
            src="/wp-content/uploads/2010/02/shoulderseg-ss.jpg"
        
            alt="Screenshot of example per-paper page, click to go there!"/> </a><figcaption>
            <p>Screenshot of example per-paper page, click to go there!</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>On Wednesday, three of us got together at my house to convert a complete PhD thesis (a good one, if I might add, and I’m allowed to, since it’s not my own) from Word to LaTeX, to get it ready for print production. Besides having lots of fun (besides bubbling personalities, beer was also involved), we got to stress-test DropBox by <em>concurrently</em> working on a shared folder filled with .tex files, and often doing full LaTeX builds involving latex, dvips, ps2pdf and bunches of image conversions. In spite of this dangerous concoction of a PhD thesis, concurrent editing, beer, laughter and the cloud, Murphy never arrived at the party and we ended up with 170 pages quite handsomely typeset in LaTeX. Kudos to Dropbox! (and us of course. duh.)</p>
<p>On a slightly less excited note, I’ve just been threatened with a lawsuit for the second time due to activities on my blog. This time, it’s a very angry and foul-mouthed homeopath. If you’re interested, search the latest few comments on <a href="http://cpbotha.net/2008/03/22/dr-werner-you-are-a-singularity-of-stupid/" title="Link to my post on Charlene Werner.">my Werner post</a> for the ones made by a certain DJ. Currently I’m hoping he’ll take the reasonable (for both of us) option and stay away. (DJ, if you’re reading this, no this is not THAT promised post. I’m keeping to my end of the deal: You stay away, your identity is safe.)</p>
<p>Continuing a short but promising tradition in backyard philosophy, I’d like to conclude with something I seem to remember a <a href="http://veryflatcat.com/" title="The Very Flat Cat's website">Very Flat Cat</a> telling me years ago, and something that recently came up again in yet another interesting discussion with the same extremely interesting guy from last week’s visualisation science discussion:</p>
<p>&gt; Under-promise, then over-deliver.</p>
<p>I’ve seen some pretty good mottos, but this one’s an absolute keeper. Thank you very much <a href="http://veryflatcat.com/" title="Yet another link to the Very Flat Cat!">Very Flat Cat</a>, also for this.</p>
<p></censored></censored></p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Weekly Head Voices #12: Ceci n’est pas une bibliothèque.</title><link>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/09/weekly-head-voices-12-ceci-nest-pas-une-bibliotheque/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2010 22:04:48 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cpbotha.net/2010/02/09/weekly-head-voices-12-ceci-nest-pas-une-bibliotheque/</guid><description>Welcome to the latest edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I briefly touch upon the, to my mind, mention-worthy events that took place within my field of observation during week 5 of the year 2010, and with which I too finally have an excuse to (ab)use the famous words of Magritte for my dubious ends. :)
WE INTERRUPT THIS PROGRAMME FOR THE FOLLOWING IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT:
I’m officially not supposed to talk about this until the next edition of the Weekly Head Voices, but it’s too big and too cool to keep quiet about until then. Google has just released Buzz, their location-based status / media updating system, and it’s fantastically cool. I’ve just posted my first Buzz via Google Maps 4.0 on my E71 (I think I’m the third buzz in Delft EVAR). Don’t know what Buzz is? Check this YouTube clip:</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Welcome to the latest edition of the Weekly Head Voices, in which I <em>briefly</em> touch upon the, to my mind, mention-worthy events that took place within my field of observation during week 5 of the year 2010, and with which I too finally have an excuse to (ab)use the famous words of Magritte for my dubious ends. :)</p>
<p>WE INTERRUPT THIS PROGRAMME FOR THE FOLLOWING IMPORTANT ANNOUNCEMENT:</p>
<p>I’m officially not supposed to talk about this until the next edition of the Weekly Head Voices, but it’s too big and too cool to keep quiet about until then.  Google has just released Buzz, their location-based status / media updating system, and it’s fantastically cool.  I’ve just posted my first Buzz via Google Maps 4.0 on my E71 (I think I’m the third buzz in Delft EVAR).  Don’t know what Buzz is? Check this YouTube clip:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yi50KlsCBio?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>YOU WILL NOW BE RETURNED TO YOUR NORMAL PROGRAMMING.</p>
<p>The reason for the title of this post is my Saturday visit to <a href="http://dok.info/" title="DOK website">DOK</a>, Delft’s unique library concept. It’s not really a library, but more of a fantastic place of gathering that coincidentally contains thousands of books, CDs, DVDs and, err, a coffee shop! They even have a number of <a href="http://www.sonicchair.de/" title="Sonic Chair website">sonic chairs</a> that one can make use of to listen to music via the mounted Macs. This Saturday, live music by one of the artists who exhibited at the DOK.  I made you a short snippet:</p>
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper">
<span class="embed-youtube" style="text-align:center; display: block;"><iframe allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube-player" height="473" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/R251vTFuM0s?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;fs=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;wmode=transparent" style="border:0;" type="text/html" width="840"></iframe></span>
</div>
<p>As even this short edition should end on a philosophical note, I’d like to conclude with an interesting discussion I had on whether the type of research we do in (medical) visualisation can be considered to be science. Very strictly speaking, the scientific method consists of observation, hypothesis forming and finally experimentation to prove or disprove the hypothesis. A large body of visualisation work is concerned with <em>making stuff that solves hard problems</em>, i.e. formulative research as opposed to the more traditional evaluative research. Although the question of whether <em>making stuff that solves hard problems</em> constitutes science is a complex discussion that deserves a whole year of blog posts, I am going to conclude with one possible and simple take on situation:</p>
<p>By taking this constructive approach we are, besides actually solving problems (a neat by-product, no?), discovering <em>how</em> to create effective visual representations of complex phenomena hidden in even more complex data. By doing this, we are in fact observing the supremely complex system consisting of the whole pipeline from data acquisition to insight, all the while experimenting with parameters (in the widest possible sense of the world) and thus confirming or disproving hypotheses concerning the nature of the pipeline and its various components. Together, these hypotheses make up the model that governs the effective extraction of insight from data via the human visual system.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>